<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91091</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ramsay-Hunt syndrome: What is the treatment?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ramsay-Hunt syndrome is peripheral facial palsy combined with a vesicular rash in the pinna or oral cavity. It is caused by the varicella zoster virus infection of the geniculate ganglion. Facial condition in the Zoster Oticus initially has a more severe and worse prognosis of recovery from Bell's palsy. Early treatment of this pathology usually consists of intravenous treatment or oral acyclovir, analgesics, corticosteroids and eye protection measures, in order to improve the probability of cure. We present a case of Ramsay-Hunt syndrome with a poor outcome in a 65 year-old woman (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contín-Pescacen, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillermo-Ruberte, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morea Colmenares, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana-Alonso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome Ramsay-Hunt asocia parálisis facial periférica acompañada de una erupción vesicular en pabellón auricular o cavidad oral, causada por la afectación del ganglio geniculado por el virus varicela-zóster. La afectación facial en el zóster ótico es inicialmente más severa y con peor pronóstico de recuperación que la parálisis de Bell. El tratamiento precoz de esta enfermedad suele incluir aciclovir intravenoso u oral, analgésicos, corticoides y medidas de protección ocular; encaminado todo ello a mejorar el pronóstico de curación. Presentamos un caso de síndrome de Ramsay-Hunt en una mujer de 65 años con mala evolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(8): 436-440, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Ramsay-Hunt: ¿qué tratamiento precisa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5966^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30052^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30052^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30052^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30052^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
