<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113222</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound-guided axillary block versus ultrasound-guided infraclavicular block for upper extremity surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Most upper limb regional anaesthesia techniques are successful, and differences in efficacy should dictate the choice of technique. Methods. This prospective, randomised study compares ultrasound-guided infraclavicular (IB) and ultrasound-guided axillary brachial plexus blocks (AB) for upper limb surgery. Anaesthesia time (performance time and onset time) was the primary outcome measure. The success rate (surgical anaesthesia), analgesia duration, postoperative pain scores, and the incidence of complications over the following 24 h were recorded. Results. A total of 82 patients were included in the study, and received either IB (n = 42) or AB (n = 40). No differences were observed between the 2 groups in terms of total anaesthesia-related time, performance time, success rate (90-95%), or postoperative pain scores. Compared with the infraclavicular approach, ultrasound-guided AB group required a longer onset time, 10.2 min (SD ± 1.4), than IB group, 6.35 min (SD ± 2). IB was also associated with a longer analgesia duration than that of AB; 20 h (SD ± 1.36) versus 13.70 h (SD ± 2.16), respectively. The only complications we observed were uneventful vascular punctures. Conclusions. We can conclude that compared to ultrasound-guided AB, ultrasound-guided IB provides a similar efficacy, a shorter onset time and longer lasting analgesia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal del Ojo, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Huertas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Con la incorporación de la ecografía en la práctica habitual de la anestesia regional, el bloqueo infraclavicular ha ido ganando popularidad. La mayoría de los abordajes de anestesia regional del miembro superior tienen una alta tasa de éxito, y las diferencias en la eficacia y en la calidad del bloqueo deberían favorecer la elección de una técnica frente a otra. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar si el bloqueo infraclavicular del plexo braquial presentaba ventajas respecto al axilar en relación con los tiempos de instauración y efectividad clínica. Métodos. Estudio comparativo, prospectivo, aleatorizado entre el bloqueo infraclavicular ecoguiado y el bloqueo axilar ecoguiado en la cirugía de miembro superior. Se evaluó el tiempo anestésico total (definido como la suma del tiempo de realización del bloqueo y el tiempo de instauración). Se registró la tasa de éxito (anestesia quirúrgica), la duración de la analgesia, el dolor postoperatorio mediante escala visual analógica y la incidencia de complicaciones durante y tras la técnica (hasta 24 h después). Resultados. Se incluyeron 82 pacientes, que se dividieron en 2 grupos: bloqueo infraclavicular (BI) (n = 42) y bloqueo axilar (BA) (n = 40). No se observaron diferencias entre los 2 grupos en cuanto a tiempo de realización del bloqueo, tasa de éxito (90-95%) y dolor postoperatorio. Comparado con el abordaje infraclavicular, el grupo BA requirió un mayor tiempo de instauración, 10,2 min (DE ± 1,4) frente a 6,35 min (DE ± 2), siendo esta diferencia estadísticamente significativa (p &lt; 0,05). Además, hubo una mayor duración de la analgesia en el grupo BI que en el grupo BA, 20 h (DE ± 1,36) frente a 13,70 h (DE ± 2,16), respectivamente. Las únicas complicaciones registradas fueron punciones vasculares, que no tuvieron incidencias. Conclusiones. El BI proporciona una eficacia similar, con un menor tiempo de instauración del bloqueo y una analgesia más duradera que el BA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(6): 313-319, jun.-jul. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo axilar ecoguiado frente a bloqueo infraclavicular ecoguiado para la cirugía de miembro superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1138^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1138^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28410</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
