<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040715</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Citizens&#146; rights in relation to health and healthcare in Catalonia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Concern for respect for citizens' rights in matters relating to health and healthcare has been a priority of the health administration since the beginning of the transfer of health powers to Catalonia. To update previous declarations, in July 2002 the Catalan government approved the citizens' charter of rights and responsibilities concerning health and healthcare as a programmatic declaration. Based on a global vision that goes beyond matters concerning healthcare exclusively, the charter promotes individual autonomy through joint participation in decisions affecting health and strengthens the responsibility that should be demanded in mature democratic societies. For the charter to come fully into force, it is intended to draw up a plan to increase awareness of the rights contained in it among organizations and health professionals, to disseminate knowledge of the charter among users, and to periodically evaluate the degree of respect for rights and responsibilities and their adaptation to citizens with specific characteristics</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manzanera, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralba, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arisa, Josep Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La preocupación por el respeto de los derechos de los ciudadanos, en relación con la salud y la atención sanitaria, está presente desde el inicio de las transferencias a Cataluña, como uno de los objetivos prioritarios a tener en cuenta por parte de la administración sanitaria. Con el fin de actualizar declaraciones anteriores, el gobierno de Cataluña aprobó en julio de 2002 como declaración programática la carta de derechos y deberes de los ciudadanos en relación con la salud y la atención sanitaria. A partir de una visión global que va más allá del aspecto exclusivamente asistencial, la carta fomenta el respeto a la autonomía de las personas mediante la coparticipación en las decisiones que afectan a la salud y el fomento de la responsabilidad que debe exigirse en las sociedades democráticas maduras. Para conseguir la plena vigencia de la carta se plantea: la elaboración de un plan de sensibilización que dinamice a organizaciones y profesionales en el respeto a los derechos contemplados en la carta, la difusión entre los usuarios para su conocimiento amplio, la evaluación periódica del grado de respeto de los derechos y deberes y la adaptación a colectivos de ciudadanos con características específicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(6): 306-310, sep. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040715</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los derechos de los ciudadanos en relación con la salud y la atención sanitaria en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2986^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
