<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044776</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of proteins enamel matrix derivative in infrabody periodontal defects. Presentacion de casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Periodontitis is a chronic infective disease of the gums caused by bacteria present in dental plaque. This condition induces the breakdown of the tooth supporting apparatus until teeth are lost. Surgery may be indicated to arrest disease progression and regenerate lost tissues. Several surgical techniques have been developed to regenerate periodontal tissues including guided tissue regeneration (GTR), and the use of proteins enamel matrix derivative (EMD). EMD is an extract of enamel matrix and contains amelogenins. There is evidence to show that amelogenins are involved not only in enamel formation, but also in the formation of the periodontal attachment during tooth formation. Accordly to two clinicals cases treated with Endogain, the aim of this presentation is, first to describe the clinical procedure, and second to make a literature review of the different materials to periodontal regeneration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arancil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La periodontitis es una infección crónica causada por las bacterias de la placa dental. Esta condición induce la perdida de soporte del aparato de inserción. La cirugía está indicada para detener la progresión de la enfermedad y regenerar el tejido perdido. Se han utilizado diferentes técnicas quirúrgicas para regenerar los tejidos periodontales incluyendo la regeneración tisular guiada (RTG), y el uso de proteínas derivadas de la matriz del esmalte (EMD). Las EMD contienen amelogenina. Se sabe que la amelogenina está relacionada con la formación del esmalte, y también con la formación de la inserción periodontal durante la formación dentaria. A través de esta presentación de dos casos clínicos tratados con Proteínas derivadas de matriz de esmalte EMDOGAIN®, se pretende , por un lado describir paso a paso el procedimiento clínico de su uso y a la vez hacer una revisión de la literatura de la regeneración periodontal y de la regeneración utilizando Emdogain® en particular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;18(1): 21-29, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044776</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de las proteinas derivadas de la matriz del esmalte en defectos infraóseos periodontales. Presentación de caso clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3758^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3758^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
