<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148467</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for stocking and using antidotes in hospitals of varying levels of complexity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The stocking of antidotes in various care settings is a subject of debate. A group of experts in hospital pharmacy and both adult and pediatric clinical toxicology was formed to review the Spanish and international literature on the subject with the aim of updating recommendations about which antidotes to stock and in what amounts in hospitals of different levels of complexity. The experts also considered the usual indications for the use of antidotes and dosing. The amount to have on hand was defined as enough to treat an adult weighing 70 kg for 24 hours (or 3 such adults in an A-level hospital; ie, a highly complex center or the reference hospital for an area). The group also listed 34 antidotes that B-level hospitals should stock and 22 that other types of hospital should stock. The recommendations also provide a guide for using the antidotes in the forms of presentation available in Spain in 2015, a list of their main indications and recommended doses, and specific notes on each (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogué-Xarau, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Salmerón, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sánchez, Lídia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Gamarra-Martínez, Edurne</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Broto-Sumalla, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pelaéz, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disponibilidad de antídotos en los diferentes ámbitos asistenciales es un tema objeto de controversia. Se formó un grupo de expertos en Farmacia Hospitalaria y Toxicología Clínica, tanto de adultos como de niños. Se procedió a revisar la bibliografía nacional e internacional sobre el tema, con el objetivo de poder ofrecer una recomendación actualizada sobre los antídotos (tipo y cantidad), que deberían estar presentes en los hospitales en función de su nivel de complejidad asistencial, al tiempo que se recordaban las indicaciones toxicológicas habituales y las recomendaciones más consensuadas de posología. La disponibilidad cuantitativa se definió como la cantidad máxima de antídoto necesaria para tratar durante 24 h a un adulto de 70 kg en hospitales comarcales (nivel A), o a tres en el caso de hospitales de alta tecnología y/o de referencia de provincia (nivel B). Como resultado, se propone un listado de 34 antídotos que deberían estar presentes en hospitales de nivel A y de 22 antídotos para el resto de hospitales. Se ofrece también una guía de utilización de los antídotos seleccionados, con las formas de presentación disponibles en España en el año 2015, las principales intoxicaciones en las que pueden estar indicados, la posología más recomendada y algunas observaciones para cada uno de ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(1): 45-54, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de disponibilidad y utilización de antídotos en los hospitales según su nivel de complejidad asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17209^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
