<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151561</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advance directives in intensive care: Health professional competences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify knowledge, skills and attitudes among physicians and nurses of adults&#146; intensive care units (ICUs), referred to advance directives or living wills. Design: A cross-sectional descriptive study was carried out. Setting: Nine hospitals in the Community of Madrid (Spain). Participants: Physicians and nurses of adults&#146; intensive care. Interventions: A qualitative Likert-type scale and multiple response survey was made. Variables Knowledge, skills and attitudes about the advance directives. A descriptive statistical analysis based on percentages was made, with application of the chi-squared test for comparisons, accepting P&lt;0.05 as representing statistical significance. Results: A total of 331 surveys were collected (51%). It was seen that 90.3% did not know all the measures envisaged by the advance directives. In turn, 50.2% claimed that the living wills are not respected, and 82.8% believed advance directives to be a useful tool for health professionals in the decision making process. A total of 85.3% the physicians stated that they would respect a living will, in cases of emergencies, compared to 66.2% of the nursing staff (p=.007).Lastly, only 19.1% of the physicians and 2.3% of the nursing staff knew whether their patients had advance directives (p&lt;.001). Conclusions: Although health professionals displayed poor knowledge of advance directives, they had a favorable attitude toward their usefulness. However, most did not know whether their patients had a living will, and some professionals even failed to respect such instructions despite knowledge of the existence of advance directives. Improvements in health profesional education in this field is needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rayón-Valpuesta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco-Sanz, TR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar los conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes de los médicos y enfermeras de las unidades de cuidados intensivos de adultos sobre las instrucciones previas (IP) o documento de voluntades anticipadas (DVA). Diseño: Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Ámbito: Nueve hospitales de la Comunidad de Madrid. Participantes: Médicos y enfermeras de cuidados intensivos de adultos. Intervenciones: Cuestionario anónimo, autocumplimentado con variables dicotómicas y escala tipo likert. Variables: Conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes sobre las IP. Análisis estadístico descriptivo con porcentajes y prueba de ji-cuadrado, tomando como significativos valores p&lt;0,05. Resultados: Respondieron al cuestionario 331 profesionales (tasa de respuesta del 51%). Además de los sociodemográficos, se obtuvo que el 90,3% no conoce todas las medidas que contemplan las IP. El 82,8% opina que el DVA es un instrumento útil para los profesionales en la toma de decisiones. El 50,2% opina que los DVA no se respetan. El 85,3% de los médicos respetaría el DVA de un paciente en caso de urgencia vital, frente al 66,2% de las enfermeras (p=0,007). Solo el 19,1% de los médicos y el 2,3% de las enfermeras conoce si los pacientes que llevan a su cargo poseen un DVA (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: Aunque los profesionales sanitarios muestran conocimientos escasos sobre las IP, presentan una actitud favorable hacia su utilidad. Sin embargo, la mayoría no conocen si los pacientes que están a su cargo poseen un DVA e incluso algunos profesionales a pesar de conocerlo, en caso de urgencia vital no lo respetarían. Se hace necesaria una mayor formación sobre las IP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(3): 154-162, abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Instrucciones previas en cuidados intensivos: competencias de los profesionales sanitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28849^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36379^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
