<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051469</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety in adolescents of a Madrid neighbourhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the degree of state-trait anxiety in adolescents and its possible association with several socio-demographic variables.                 Design. Descriptive cross-sectional study.                 Setting. First semester of 2004. Two state secondary schools in Area 7, Madrid, Spain.                 Participants. Five hundred fifty nine students from the first to third years of secondary education.                 Main measurements. Two anonymous multiple-choice tests were given out to fill in during class time: STAIC (State-Trait Anxiety Inventory for Children) and a questionnaire of socio-demographic variables (age, sex, immigration, toxic habits, socio-economic and family situation, relationships, view of life, and school results).                 Results. Four hundred forty five tests were valid. Mean age, 13.8 (SD, 1.2); 53.5% were girls, 18.7% immigrants, 20.7% took drugs (alcohol, tobacco, or illegal drugs), 32.8% had repeated at least 1 year, 14.3% considered their relationship with their family "bad," 15% referred to a "bad" relation with their class mates and 29.5% had a "bad" view of life. A statistically significant association was established between all these variables and anxiety.                 Conclusions. It is important to know what risk factors are associated with anxiety in order to detect it early and prevent its development to other serious mental disorders. In this study, higher levels of anxiety were found in immigrants, in girls, in drug users, in students in a worse socio-economic situation and in students who have had to repeat a year. This study corroborates the classic risk factors associated with anxiety, but shows that we should take into account a further one: immigration. It also suggests the importance of good family and personal relationships for psychological balance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de la Rasilla Cooper, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño Freire, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert Rodríguez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hijano Baonza, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Rodríguez, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Bun, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el grado de ansiedad estado/rasgo en adolescentes y su posible relación con diferentes variables sociodemográficas.                 Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, transversal.                 Emplazamiento. Dos institutos públicos del Área 7 de Madrid. Primer semestre del año 2004.                 Participantes. Un total de 559 alumnos de primero a tercero de ESO.                 Mediciones principales. Dos cuestionarios estructurados autoadministrados y cumplimentados de forma anónima en horario lectivo: escala STAIC (ansiedad estado/rasgo en niños) y cuestionario de variables (edad, sexo, inmigración, hábitos tóxicos, situación socioeconómica y familiar, relaciones personales, visión de su vida y rendimiento escolar).                 Resultados. Se obtuvieron 445 tests válidos. La edad media era de 13,8 ± 1,2 años. El 53,5% eran mujeres, el 18,7%, inmigrantes, el 20,7% consumidores de tóxicos; el 32,8%, repetidores, el 14,3% considera que su relación familiar es mala, el 15% refiere una mala relación con los compañeros y el 29,5% tiene una visión «mala» de la vida. Se observa una asociación estadísticamente significativa entre todas estas variables descritas y la ansiedad estado/rasgo.                 Conclusiones. Es importante conocer los factores de riesgo asociados con la ansiedad para poder detectarla precozmente y prevenir su progresión hacia enfermedades más graves.                 Se han encontrado valores más altos de ansiedad entre los inmigrantes, las mujeres, los consumidores de tóxicos, los alumnos que se encuentran en situación socioeconómica más precaria y los repetidores.                 Este estudio corrobora los clásicos factores de riesgo para la ansiedad, pero demuestra que deberíamos tener en cuenta uno más: la inmigración. También refleja la importancia de unas buenas relaciones personales para el equilibrio psicológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(3): 154-158, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad en adolescentes de un barrio de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
