<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121899</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary tract infection in children under two years of age in out-patient setting and detection of vesicoureteral reflux</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 20 year period (1983-2002) 252 children less tan two year of age and having their first diagnosed urinary tract infection (UTI) in primary care with orine collected by sterile bag was referred as outpatient hospital setting. Renal ultrasound (RUS) was performed in all patients. Abnormal RUS findings were found in 6 (2,3%) patients, although only in 2 patients was suggestive of vesicoureteric reflux (VUR). Voiding cystouretrography (VCIG) was performed in 140 patients. Abnormal VCUG was found in 13 (9,2%) patients. Six patients had VUR grade 1,5 patients had VUR grade II unilateral and 2 had VUR grade II bilateral. Renal scintigraphy DMSA was performed in 26 patients. None of them showed sings of pyelonephritis or renal scarring. Diagnostic imaging following UTI in children less than two years of age has been accepted practice since the original studies that showed high prevalence of abnormalities, and specifically the VUR. However the difficulty in specimen collection and interpretation of inadequately collected specimens in primary care may contribute to the over diagnosis of UTI. Sterile bag collection has limited accuracy and a false-positive diagnosis may result in imaging over investigation. A lack of confidence in the diagnosis of UTI in primary care in this age group often lead to a genuine dilemma about how far to investigate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Micó, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezuelo Huerta, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frontera Izquierdo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En un periodo de 20 años (1983-2002), 252 niños menores de 2 años de edad, diagnosticados de primera infección del trato urinario (ITU) en medio ambulatorio, con colección de orina en bolsa estéril, y que no precisaron hospitalización, fueron referidos a la consulta externa del hospital. Se realizó ecografía renovesical a todos los pacientes. Se encontraron anomalías en 6 pacientes (el 2.3%), aunque sólo en 2 de ellos los hallazgos fueron sugestivos de reflujo vesicoureteral (RVU). Se practicó cistoureterografía miccional (CUMS) a 140 pacientes. Fue anormal en 13 de ellos (el 9,2%). Seis pacientes tenían RVU grado 1, 5 pacientes tenían RVU grado II unilateral, y 2 pacientes, RVU grado II bilateral. Se realizó gammagrafía renal DMSA a 26 pacientes. Ninguno de ellos mostró signos de piel nefritis ni de cicatrices renales. Los estudios de imagen después de una primera ITU en niños menores de 2 años son una práctica aceptada desde los estudios originales que mostraron una alta prevalencia de anomalías y, específicamente, de RVU. Sin embargo, la dificultad de recogida de orina en esta edad y la interpretación de los resultados de orinas recogidas de manera inadecuada puede contribuir al sobrediagnóstico de ITU. La recogida de orina con bolsa estéril tiene una fiabilidad limitada y un diagnóstico falso positivo puede llevar a innecesarios estudios de imagen. Una falta de confianza en el diagnóstico de ITU en medio ambulatorio en este grupo de edad puede llevar a un verdadero dilema sobre la indicación de estudios de imagen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;61(2): 106-109, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección del tracto urinario en menores de dos años de edad en el medio ambulatorio y la detección de reflujo vésico ureteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54665^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29755^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
