<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81062</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psoriasis is a skin inflammatory disease of chronicand recurrent type, featured by erythemas (rednessof the skin), itch and skin desquamation, whichin general affects the external part of the elbows,knees and scalp. It occasionally effects the nails,and sometimes it cause a rheumatic arthritis, calledpsoriatic arthritis.The aim of this paper is to deepen in this pathologyin order to know better its process and behaviour.This would help making a more adequatediagnosis, differentiating it from other similarbut different entities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La psoriasis es una enfermedad inflamatoria de lapiel de carácter crónico y recurrente, caracterizadapor eritemas (enrojecimiento), prurito y descamaciónde la piel, que por lo general afecta la parteexterna de los codos, las rodillas y el cuero cabelludo.En algunos casos tiene una afectación en las uñas,y en ocasiones aparece una artritis inflamatoriadenominada artritis psoriásica.En este artículo se pretende profundizar en estapatología, para conocerla mejor, y poder hacerun buen diagnóstico, y a la vez, diferenciar estaentidad, de otras parecidas pero diferentes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;28(2): 66-69, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis psoriásica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
