<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97503</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obsessive-compulsive disorder after frontal lobe traumatic brain injuries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Traumatic brain injuries have been documented as a cause of obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD). The risk of developing OCD may be slightly higher among people who suffer a traumatic brain injury (TBI). Case report. We describe the case of a 23 year-old man who 12 months after TBI suffers from cognitive impairment, lack of impulse control, emotional psychopathology, obsessive, and specially compulsive symptoms. He meets criteria for ICD-10 diagnosis of OCD. Discussion. Compulsive symptoms in this patient are consistent with those most frequently documented after TBI in previous literature. As in the present case, the frontal cortex, temporal and occipital lobes have been described as some of the involved damaged areas. There is high likelihood that the lesions we can see in the computerized tomography are responsible for the OCD we describe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candocia Recarey, Alexia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costas González, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rivas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Iglesias, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los traumatismos craneoencefálicos (TCE) son una causa documentada de trastorno obsesivo-compulsivo (TOC). El riesgo de padecer un TOC después de un TCE parece ser un poco mayor que en la población general. Caso clínico. Valoración y tratamiento de un varón de 23 años de edad que tras un TCE grave presenta como posible secuela un deterioro cognitivo fluctuante, falta de control de impulsos, psicopatología afectiva depresiva y un cuadro obsesivo-compulsivo con predominio de actos compulsivos, cumpliendo criterios CIE-10 para el diagnóstico de trastorno obsesivo compulsivo. Discusión. Las compulsiones descritas en este paciente coinciden con las documentadas como más frecuentes tras TCE. Como en el caso que nos ocupa, el córtex frontal, temporal y occipital se han descrito como algunas de las áreas de lesión implicadas. Es muy probable que las lesiones observadas en la tomografía computarizada de este paciente sean las responsables de la aparición del cuadro de TOC que desarrolla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);18(2): 72-74, abr.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno obsesivo-compulsivo secundario a lesión frontal en traumatismo craneoencefálico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34373^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34373^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
