<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103158</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of massage on the weight gain of premature newborns</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the influence of massage on the weight gain ofpremature newborns, in order to incorporate this influence into clinicalpractice if the scientific evidence supports it.Material and method: a review study, based on a structured questionaccording to the PICO strategy. A search was conducted in the Pubmed,Cochrane, Cuiden, Cinahl, Lilacs and Tripdatabase databases. ReelvantMeSH were identified and limits were established (five years andrandomized clinical trials). 19 clinical trials were selected for criticalreading and assessment by the CASPe tool.Results: the final selection included 10 randomized clinical trials. Inseveral studies, the weight increase was not significant. The interventionsin the studies reviewed were: therapeutic touch, Schneider´s technique,acupuncture and meridian massage, different massage modalities combinedwith kinesthetic stimulation, and massage according to Vimalaprotocol. The side effects deribed from the intervention were not of muchimportance. Only in two studies the intervention was carried out by theparents after training.Conclusions: even though of note is the rectification in the review ofthe investigations of some of the biases found in a previous systematicreview (consideration of energy intake as a variable), studies continueto show methodological weaknesses (small samples, lack of blinding,etc.), and therefore it is not possible to establish whether the massage isa causal factor or a contributing factor to the weight gain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manso Melgosa, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Izquierdo, José Miguel de los</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Barriuso, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Molinero, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la influencia del masaje en el aumento de peso derecién nacidos prematuros, con la finalidad de incorporarlo a la prácticaclínica si la evidencia científica lo permite.Material y método: estudio de revisión, partiendo de una pregunta estructuradasegún la estrategia PICO. Se llevó a cabo una búsqueda en basesde datos. Pubmed, Cochrane, Cuiden, Cinahl, Lilacs y Tripdatabase.Se identificaron los MeSH pertinentes, se establecieron límites (cinco añosy ensayos clínicos aleatorios). Fueron seleccionados 19 ensayos clínicospara su lectura crítica y valoración mediante la herramienta CASPe.Resultados: la selección definitiva fue de 10 ensayos clínicos aleatorios.En varios estudios el incremento de peso no fue significativo. Lasintervenciones en los estudios revisados fueron: toques terapéuticos, técnicade Schneider, acupuntura y masajes en meridianos, diferentes modalidadesde masaje combinado con estimulación kinestésica y masajesegún el protocolo de Vimala. Los efectos secundarios derivados de laintervención fueron poco importantes. Únicamente en dos estudios laintervención fue realizada por los padres previa formación.Conclusiones: aunque cabe destacar la rectificación en las investigacionesrevisadas de alguno de los sesgos apuntados en una revisión sistemáticaanterior (consideración de la ingesta energética como variable), los estudioscontinúan presentando debilidades metodológicas (muestras pequeñas,falta de cegamiento, etc.), por lo que no es posible establecer si el masajees un factor causal o un factor colaborador en la ganancia ponderal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(8): 27-32, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia del masaje en el aumentode peso en recién nacidos prematuros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
