<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153521</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Type I Chiari Malformation as a cause of oropharyngeal dysphagia. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: This article reviews an uncommon entity that may appear in Chiari malformation Type I, dysphagia, whose omission may exclude the diagnosis or attribute it to other pathology. Patient: Young male with dyspnea and fever who reported 6 month&#146;s evolution neck pain and progressive dysphagia. Suspecting aspiration pneumonia, a complete and directed medical history on the topographical areas that govern swallowing and a series of additional tests, to rule out other causes of dysphagia, were held. Cranial MRI confirmed the diagnosis of type I Chiari malformation. The patient was surgically intervened through suboccipital decompression. 6 months after surgery there was an improvement in neck pain and dysphagia disappeared. Discussion: Dysphagia is an unusual symptom of type I Chiari malformation usually due to alteration by compression of the brainstem and/or to elongation of the lower cranial nerves. To achieve early diagnosis and proper treatment, the physical examination should be complete and directed over areas that govern swallowing, being MRI basic to establish causal diagnosis. Conclusion: Diagnosis of Chiari malformation or other causes of lower cranial nerves impairment must be kept in mind in patients with dysphagia of uncertain origin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sansano Algueró, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castro, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro Pascual, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro Serra, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Ruiz, Rosa Delia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalva Arigita, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mallol Badellino, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, Sonia María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: En este artículo se revisa un síntoma infrecuente que puede aparecer en la malformación de Chiari tipo I, la disfagia, cuya omisión puede excluir el diagnóstico o atribuirlo a otra patología. Paciente: Varón joven con cervicalgia y disfagia de 6 meses de evolución que consultó por disnea y fiebre. Ante la sospecha de neumonía broncoaspirativa se realizó una historia clínica completa y dirigida sobre las áreas topográficas que gobiernan la deglución y se realizaron toda una serie de pruebas complementarias para descartar otras causas de disfagia. La RM craneal confirmó el diagnostico de malformación de Chiari tipo I. El paciente fue intervenido quirúrgicamente mediante descompresión suboccipital. Pasados 6 meses mejoró la cervicalgia y desapareció la disfagia. Discusión: La disfagia es un síntoma inusual de la malformación de Chiari tipo I, debido a alteración por compresión del tronco encefálico y/o a elongación de los pares craneales bajos. Para lograr diagnósticos tempranos y el tratamiento adecuado, la exploración fí- sica debe ser completa y dirigida sobre las áreas topográficas que gobiernan la deglución, siendo básica la RM para establecer el diagnóstico causal. Conclusión: En pacientes con disfagia de origen incierto el diagnóstico de malformación de Chiari u otra causa de afectación de pares craneales bajos debe tenerse en cuenta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;36(2): 194-199, 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malformación de Chiari tipo I como causa de disfagia orofaríngea. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1143^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11444^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
