<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78372</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are imaging techniques necessary for defining remission in rheumatoid arthritis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Accurate assessment of inflammatory activity in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is essential to evaluate response to therapy and disease remission. RA remission has been classically assessed by clinical and laboratory parameters. However, subclinical synovitis may explain progression of joint damage in spite of apparent clinical remission in RA patients. Imaging techniques, such as magnetic resonance imaging and high-resolution ultrasonography (US) with Doppler technique, provide a sensitive measure and monitoring of joint inflammatory activity and a more accurate assessment of RA remission than clinical evaluation which may contribute to make optimal treatment decisions. Within the last decade, an increasing number of rheumatologists have progressively incorporated musculoskeletal US as a valuable diagnostic tool in their clinical practice. This technique facilitates the scanning of all peripheral joints as many times as required at the time of consultation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naredo Sánchez, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la actividad inflamatoria en la artritis reumatoide (AR) es esencial para conocer la respuesta al tratamiento y la remisión de la enfermedad. La evaluación de la remisión en la AR se realiza de forma convencional mediante parámetros clínicos y analíticos. Sin embargo, la presencia de sinovitis subclínica puede explicar la progresión de daño estructural en pacientes en remisión clínica aparente. Técnicas de imagen, como la resonancia magnética y la ultrasonografía (US) de alta resolución con Doppler, proporcionan una evaluación y un seguimiento sensibles de la actividad inflamatoria articular y una valoración más real de la remisión de la AR que la clínica, la cual puede contribuir a tomar decisiones terapéuticas óptimas. Durante la última década, un número creciente de reumatólogos ha incorporado de forma progresiva la US musculoesquelética como una herramienta diagnóstica valiosa en su práctica clínica. Esta técnica permite la exploración repetida de todas las articulaciones periféricas simultáneamente a la evaluación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(extr.1): 17-21, abr. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son necesarias las técnicas de imagen para definir la remisión en la artritis reumatoide?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19333</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
