<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112176</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary intake of cancer patients on radiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The dietary intake of cancer patients can affect their nutritional status. Objectives: To assess the dietary intake and nutritional status of head and neck cancer patients on radiotherapy. Methods: 24-hour recalls and anthropometric measures were taken during the first and third weeks of radiotherapy. Results: Of the 62 patients, significant reductions were found in arm muscle area (p = 0.001) and arm muscle circumference (p &lt; 0.001), and 69% of patients had an average weight loss of 5.7% in three weeks. With regards to their dietary intake, reductions were found in energy (26.5 kcal/kg/d-21.3 kcal/kg/d, p &lt; 0.001), carbohydrate (196.9 g/d - 180.5 g/d, p = 0.020), protein (1.19 g/kg/d-0.93 g/kg/d, p = 0.009) and fat (44.4 g/d-33.1 g/d, p &lt; 0.001) intakes during the study period. Discussion: The changes that result from cancer radiotherapy led to reductions in dietary intake and negatively affected body composition measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pistóia, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabito, EI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nunes, CH de Abreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreatta Gottschall, CB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ingesta dietética de los pacientes con cáncer pueden afectar su estado nutricional. Objetivos: Evaluar la ingesta alimentaria y el estado nutricional de los pacientes con cáncer de la cabeza y cuello de la radioterapia. Métodos: Recuerdo de ingesta de 24 horas y valoración del status nutricional por antropometría fueron tomadas durante la primera semana y la tercera de la radioterapia. Resultados: De los 62 pacientes, las reducciones significativas en el área muscular del brazo (p = 0,001) y la circunferencia muscular del brazo (p &lt; 0,001), y el 69% de los pacientes tenían una pérdida de peso promedio de 5,7% en tres semanas. Con respecto a su ingesta, las reducciones fueron encontrados en la energía (26,5 kcal/ kg/día-21,3 kcal/kg/día, p &lt; 0,001), carbohidratos (196,9 g/día-180,5 g/día, p = 0,020), la proteína (1,19 g/kg/día-0,93 g/kg/día, p = 0,009) y grasas (44,4 g/día-33,1 g/día, p &lt; 0,001) la ingesta durante el período de estudio. Discusión: Los cambios resultan en reducción de la ingesta alimentaria y las medidas del cuerpo afectado negativamente a su composición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 1936-1939, nov.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ingesta dietética de los pacientes con cáncer en radioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12271^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
