<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27888</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parkinson´s disease as seen by a patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The idea of writing this paper stemmed from the interest shown by Dr Francisco Javier Jiménez-Jiménez in giving a firsthand description of the experiences of a patient suffering from Parkinson&#146;s disease, as a complement to the scientific view. The author is not a member of the medical profession. Development. This study is based on the analysis of the disease as seen by the person actually suffering from it. From this biography we analyze the possible causes that could have exerted an influence on the development of the disease, and the physical causes are also outlined. We analyze the drugs that are administered as therapy and we establish the relations that exist between the symptoms presented by the author and the possible deterioration of the governing centres of the brain which should control them but, due to the degeneration brought about by the disease, do not. The effects produced by the medication are studied and we also describe how help can be obtained from the outside by employing other types of medicine that are not strictly allopathic. In the final part of the paper the relations between the patient and the people around them are discussed. Conclusions. It becomes clear that there is a void in our knowledge about this disease due to our not knowing what exactly causes it. This means that therapies are directed towards palliating the symptoms rather than fighting the causes. Something that must be highlighted is the important role played by the patient&#146;s will to fight against the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Este artículo se debe al interés del Dr. Francisco Javier Jiménez-Jiménez por dar una visión de primera mano, complementaria de la científica, de las vivencias de un paciente que sufre la enfermedad de Parkinson. El autor no es médico. Desarrollo. Se basa en el análisis de la enfermedad desde el punto de vista de la persona que la vive; de esta biografía se analizan las posibles causas que pudieran haber tenido influencia en el desarrollo de la enfermedad, y se esbozan las causas físicas. Se analizan los fármacos que se administran como terapia y se establecen las relaciones entre los síntomas que presenta el autor y el posible deterioro de los centros rectores del cerebro que los deberían controlar, pero que no controlan debido a la degeneración provocada por la enfermedad. Se estudian los efectos que producen los medicamentos y se describen las ayudas que, desde el exterior, prestan las medicinas no estrictamente alópatas. Hacia el final se explican las relaciones entre el enfermo y quienes lo rodean. Conclusiones. Se deduce que existe ante esta enfermedad, al desconocerse las causas que la motivan, un vacío de conocimientos. Esto hace que las terapias se encaminen a paliar los síntomas y no a combatir las causas. Es de destacar la importancia del enfermo en lo relativo al espíritu de lucha contra la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(4): 391-400, ago. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Parkinson vista por un afectado</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>García Martínez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27888</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15196</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5171</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
