<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050995</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of esophageal stenoses produced by endoscopic sclerotherapy versus variceal ligation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Variceal ligation (VL) eradicates esophageal varices faster than endoscopic sclerotherapy (ES) with a lower rebleeding rate and fewer secondary effects. However, most studies have evaluated the short-term effects of these treatments and some late complications may be overlooked. Patients and methods: To determine the incidence and the characteristics of stenosis, we included 253 cirrhotic patients treated endoscopically for variceal bleeding from 1988 to 2004 in our hospital. ES was carried out with ethanolamine 5% and polidocanol 1.5%. ES and VL were carried out every 15 days until varices were eradicated and then at 3-, 6- and 12-month intervals; if varices reappeared, the initial treatment was repeated. Stenosis was considered mild when esophageal size was more than 10 mm and severe when the endoscope could not be passed through the stricture. Results: We found stenosis in seven out of 105 (6.7%) ES-treated patients and in 10 out of 148 (6.7%) VL-treated patients. The clinical characteristics of the patients and the previous number of endoscopic sessions were similar in both groups. Four out of seven ES patients developed stenosis during the first eradication process (mean: 11 months, 1-60), but this early stenosis was observed in one out of 10 VL patients (mean: 20 months, 1-72). Stenosis was severe in three out of seven ES patients (43%) but in only two out of ten VL patients (20%) (NS). Conclusions: The incidence of esophageal stenosis was similar after treatment of esophageal varices with ES and VL, although VL had a tendency to produce later stenosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña, Joaquín de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alles, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orive, Aitor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ligadura de varices (LV) erradica las varices esofágicas más rápidamente que la escleroterapia (ES), con menos tasa de recidiva hemorrágica y de complicaciones. Sin embargo, la mayoría de los estudios son a corto plazo y algunas complicaciones tardías pueden pasar desapercibidas. Pacientes y métodos: Analizamos la base de datos de 253 pacientes cirróticos, tratados endoscópicamente tras una hemorragia por varices esofágicas desde 1988 hasta 2004 en nuestro hospital, en busca de incidencia y características de estenosis esofágicas. La esclerosis se realizó con etanolamina al 5% intravariz, y polidocanol al 1,5% perivariz. Las sesiones de tratamiento endoscópico se realizaron cada 15 días hasta la erradicación y, posteriormente, a los 3, 6 y 12 meses, repitiendo el mismo tratamiento inicial si reaparecían las varices. La estenosis se consideró leve cuando tenía una luz superior a 10 mm y grave si no permitía el paso del endoscopio. Resultados: Encontramos 7 estenosis en 105 pacientes tratados con esclerosis (6,7%) y en 10 de 148 tratados con ligadura (6,7%). Las características clínicas de los pacientes y el número previo de sesiones endoscópicas fueron similares en ambos grupos. Cuatro de los 7 pacientes del grupo ES presentaron la estenosis durante el primer proceso de erradicación (media 11, meses; rango, 1-60), pero el desarrollo temprano de estenosis sólo se observó en uno de 10 pacientes del grupo LV (media, 20 meses; rango, 1-72). La estenosis fue grave en 3 de 7 (43%) pacientes del grupo ES, pero sólo en 2 de 10 (20%) pacientes del grupo LV (sin diferencias significativas). Conclusiones: La incidencia de estenosis fue similar tras el tratamiento endoscópico de las varices esofágicas con ES y LV, aunque se observó una tendencia al desarrollo de estenosis mas tardío tras LV</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;29(9): 523-527, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050995</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las estenosis esofágicas producidas por escleroterapia o ligadura de varices</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29389</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5030^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23995^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
