<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98391</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological abuse in young couples</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological abuse is one of the most common aggressive behaviors in dating relationships among youths. Thus, acts of constant criticism and/or verbal aggression and/or acts of isolation and dominance are relevant behaviors that are closely related and often precede physical violence. In this paper, we review the most useful assessment tools for the detection of this type of behavior as well as the preventive intervention programs to date. Some recommendations are made for the development of prevention programs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Rivas, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Mª Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graña, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abuso psicológico es uno de los comportamientos agresivos más frecuentes en las relaciones de noviazgo en jóvenes. Así, actos de crítica constantes y/o agresión verbal y/o actos de aislamiento y dominación son conductas relevantes que se relacionan estrechamente y suelen preceder a los actos de violencia física. En el presente trabajo, se revisan los instrumentos de evaluación más útiles para la detección de este tipo de conductas así como de los programas de intervención preventiva realizados hasta la fecha. Se finaliza con algunas recomendaciones para la elaboración de programas de prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(1): 117-131, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso psicológico en parejas jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
