<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131339</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Causes and factors associated with reconciliation errors in medical and surgical services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of this study was to determine the main causes of errors of medication reconciliation at hospital admission in medical and surgical department and establish factors associated with medication reconciliation errors. Material and method: Cross-sectional study. We included all patients admitted to two services and two surgical for a month. To determine the presence of error reconciliation, the pharmacist compared the medication history interview by the order physician. The factors associated with errors were identified by multivariate logistic regression analysis. Results: 221 patients were included, of which 58.4% had at least one error reconciliation. We detected 629 discrepancies,339 (53.9%) reconciliation errors. The incidence of errors in medical services was 24.3% and in the surgical services 43.0%(p &lt;0.001) in both groups being most prevalent error of omission(46.2% and 50.8%). Regarding factors associated, the equation determines that patients older than 65 years, polymedicated and taking oral ant diabetic are more likely to have (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rentero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbieta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iniesta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrigal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las principales causas de errores de conciliación de la medicación al ingreso hospitalario tanto en los servicios médicos, como en los quirúrgicos y que factores se asocian a dichos errores de conciliación. Material y método: Estudio observacional transversal. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes que ingresaron en dos servicios médicos y dos quirúrgicos durante un mes. Para determinar la presencia de error de conciliación se cotejo la historia realizada por el farmacéutico con la del médico prescriptor. Los factores asociados a los errores se identificaron mediante un análisis de regresión logística multivariante. Resultados: Se incluyeron 221 pacientes, de los cuales el 58.4%presentaron al menos un error de conciliación. Se detectaron un total de 629 discrepancias, 339 (53.9%) errores de conciliación. La incidencia de errores en los servicios médicos fue del 24.3% y en los quirúrgicos del 43.0% (p&lt;0.001) siendo en ambos grupos el error más prevalente el de la omisión (46.2% y 50.8%).En cuanto a los factores asociados, la ecuación determina que los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;38(5): 398-404, sept.-oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas y factores asociados a los errores de conciliaciónen servicios médicos y quirúrgicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
