<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043687</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation of acute migraine attack treatment with triptans in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To perform an economic evaluation of migraine attack treatment comparing standard doses of existing triptans in 2003, and using different outcome measurements of anti-migraine effectiveness.         Methods. A cost-effectiveness analysis was performed from the National Health System perspective, using 2003 prices, comparing almotriptan 12.5 mg, eletriptan 40 mg, naratriptan 2.5 mg, rizatriptan 10 mg, sumatriptan 50 mg, sumatriptan 100 mg, zolmitriptan 2.5 mg and zolmitriptan 5 mg. Effectiveness measurements were obtained from an efficacy meta-analysis of published clinical trials, and they consisted of therapeutic gain (crude effect of triptan after placebo effect subtraction) for 2 hanti- migraine response, pain free at 2 h, and 24 h-sustained pain free. Rescue medication use and 24 h-attack relapse rates were assessed.                 Results. Thirty-eight clinical trials (19,872 patients) were used to assess triptans effectiveness. Eletriptan 40 mg and rizatriptan 10 mg showed the highest 24 h-sustained pain free response (20.2 % in both cases), pain-free at 2 h (27.7 % and 32.2 %) and antimigraine response at 2 h (38.6 % and 31.3 %), respectively. Less rescue medication was used with eletriptan 40 mg and sumatriptan 50 mg (21 % and 20 %), and the lowest 24 h-relapse rates were observed with eletriptan 40 mg and naratriptan 2.5 mg (27 % and 21 %). Eletriptan 40 mg and sumatriptan 50 mg showed the lowest costs per successfully treated attacks with 2 h-antimigraine response (16.50 and 17.44e) and with 24 h-sustained pain free (31.47 and 33.61e), while the lowest costs per attack that was pain free at 2 h were observed with rizatriptan 10 mg (21.36e) and eletriptan 40 mg (22.99e).                 Conclusions. Considering the cost-effectiveness measurements assessed, eletriptan 40 mg was the most costeffective triptan in the majority of economic analyses carried out</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorre Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-Naya, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas Gutiérrez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Realizar una evaluación económica del tratamiento del ataque de migraña con triptanes, a sus dosis habituales, utilizando tres medidas de efectividad antimigrañosa.         Métodos. Se realizó un análisis coste/efectividad (ACE) desde la perspectiva del Sistema Nacional de Salud, a precios de 2003, comparando almotriptán 12,5 mg, eletriptán 40 mg, naratriptán 2,5 mg, rizatriptán 10 mg, sumatriptán 50 mg, sumatriptán 100 mg, zolmitriptán 2,5 mg y zolmitriptán 5 mg. Los valores de efectividad se obtuvieron de un metaanálisis de eficacia de ensayos clínicos publicados y fueron la ganancia terapéutica (GT) (efecto antimigrañoso tras sustraer el efecto placebo) de respuesta antimigrañosa a las 2 h, ausencia de dolor a las 2 h y respuesta completa. Se determinaron las tasas de medicación de rescate y recurrencia a las 24 h.                 Resultados. Se incluyeron 38 ensayos clínicos (19.872 pacientes). El eletriptán 40 mg y el rizatriptán 10 mg presentaron la mayor GT en respuesta completa (20,2 % en ambos casos), ausencia de dolor a las 2 h (27,7 y 32,2 %) y respuesta antimigrañosa a las 2 h (38,6 y 31,3 %), respectivamente. Se usó menos medicación de rescate con eletriptán 40 mg y sumpatriptán 50 mg (21 y 20 %) y la recurrencia fue menor con eletriptán 40 mg y naratriptán 2,5 mg (27 y 21 %). Los menores costes por ataque de migraña con respuesta a las 2 h y con respuesta completa se observaron con eletriptán 40 mg (16,50 y 31,47e) y con sumatriptán 50 mg (17,44 y 33,61e), respectivamente, mientras que el menor coste en ausencia de dolor a las 2 h se observó con rizatriptán 10 mg (21,36e) y eletriptán 40 mg (22,99e).                 Conclusiones. Considerando las medidas de coste-efectividad evaluadas, el eletriptán 40 mg fue el triptán más eficiente en la mayoría de los análisis efectuados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;20(3): 121-132, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica del tratamiento de la crisis aguda de migraña con triptanes en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24360^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
