<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163300</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in Mortality From Diabetes Mellitus in Spain: 1998-2013</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Diabetes mellitus (DM) is a leading causes of death, mainly due to cardiovascular complications. The aim of this study was to describe DM mortality in Spain from 1998 to 2013 and to compare it between distinct provinces. Methods: Ecological time-trend study. Data sources consisted of the population register and the death rate figures, by cause of death, from Spain's National Statistics Institute. Rates were age-standardized by the direct method. Standardized mortality rates were calculated for each province every 5 years (1998-2013). Time trends in mortality were established by joint point regression models. Results: The standardized mortality rate for DM fell markedly, by 25.3% in men and by 41.4% in women from 1998 to 2013. At the beginning of the study period, mortality rates were higher in southern than in northern regions, but this difference gradually disappeared in later years. The highest mortality rates were consistently found in the Canary Islands. Conclusions: Mortality from DM fell substantially from 1998 to 2013. The marked geographical clustering showing higher mortality in the south and southeastern areas of the country was significantly reduced during the study period, except in the Canary Islands, where mortality remains strikingly high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, Vicente F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá Munuera, M Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Beltrán, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La diabetes mellitus (DM) es una de las primeras causas de mortalidad fundamentalmente por complicaciones cardiovasculares. El objetivo del estudio es describir la evolución de la mortalidad por DM en España en el periodo 1998-2013 y compararla entre las distintas provincias. Métodos: Estudio observacional ecológico de tendencias temporales. Como fuentes de datos se utilizaron el padrón continuo poblacional y el registro de defunciones, según causa de muerte, del Instituto Nacional de Estadística. Se estandarizaron las tasas por edad mediante método directo, se calculó la tasa de mortalidad estandarizada por provincia cada 5 años (1998-2013) y se analizaron las tendencias temporales mediante ajuste de modelos de regresión de Joint point. Resultados: Se apreció una reducción de la tasa de mortalidad estandarizada por DM del 25,3% en los varones y el 41,4% en las mujeres en el periodo 1998-2013. En los primeros años se observó una mayor mortalidad en las provincias del sur, pero fue desapareciendo en los años analizados. Las mayores tasas de mortalidad se observaron en Canarias. Conclusiones: Se constata una importante reducción de la mortalidad por DM en España en el periodo analizado. Al inicio había una distribución desigual, con mayor mortalidad en el sur y el este del país, pero que se minimizó con los años, a excepción de Canarias, donde se mantiene elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;70(6): 433-443, jun. 2017. mapas, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la mortalidad por diabetes mellitus en España: análisis del periodo 1998-2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
