<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107157</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficiency of the Information Given at Discharge and Adherence of Polymedicated Patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate the utility of a post-discharge pharmaceutical care programme. Method Three-month prospective study where patients were randomised into two groups according to whether or not they received verbal and written information about their treatment at hospital discharge. Treatment compliance was assessed by the Morisky&#150;Green test at discharge and at 30&#150;50days via a telephone interview, also collecting information on patient medication. Results A total of 59 patients were included, 30 in the control group and 29 in the experimental group. 42.1±9.6days had elapsed between discharge and the telephone interview. While a higher percentage of patients were adherent to treatment at discharge in the control group (83.3 versus 62.1%, OR=0.33, 95% CI: 0.1&#150;1.1, P=.07), in the telephone interview the percentage in the experimental group was greater (62.5 versus 88.5%, OR=4.6, 95% CI: 1.1&#150;19.8, P=.03). The differences between the two groups for the rest of the variables (deaths, visits to emergency department and hospital readmissions) were not statistically significant. In the telephone interview, 70% of patients&#146; treatment was changed in some way since hospital discharge. Conclusion A post-discharge pharmaceutical care programme is a tool to improve treatment compliance, which needs continuity due to the large number of treatment changes suffered by these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáez de la Fuente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lechuga Vázquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Asensio, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granja Berná, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Perpiña, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros de Tejada López-Coterilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la utilidad de un programa de información farmacoterapéutica al alta hospitalaria. Método Estudio prospectivo de 3 meses de duración en el que se aleatorizó a los pacientes en 2 grupos según recibieran o no información verbal y escrita sobre su tratamiento al alta hospitalaria. La adherencia se evaluó mediante el test de Morinsky-Green, tanto en el momento del alta, como transcurridos 30-50 días mediante entrevista telefónica. Además se recogió la información sobre la medicación del paciente en ese momento y los cambios respecto a la medicación al alta. Resultados Se incluyeron un total de 59 pacientes, 30 en el grupo control y 29 en el experimental. Entre el alta y la entrevista trascurrieron 42,1±9,6 días. Mientras que en el momento del alta el porcentaje de pacientes adherentes era mayor en el grupo control (83,3 frente a 62,1%, OR=0,33, IC 95%: 0,1 a 1,1, p=0,07), en la entrevista telefónica fue mayor en el grupo experimental (62,5 frente a 88,5%, OR=4,6, IC 95%: 1,1 a 19,8, p=0,03). Las diferencias entre ambos grupos en el resto de las variables (fallecimientos, visitas a urgencias y reingresos hospitalarios) no fueron estadísticamente significativas. En la entrevista telefónica un 70% de los pacientes sufrió algún tipo de cambio respecto al tratamiento al alta hospitalaria. Conclusiones La información al alta por parte del farmacéutico es una herramienta para mejorar la adherencia al tratamiento de los pacientes que debe tener una continuidad debido al elevado número de cambios de tratamiento que sufren estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;35(3): 128-134, Mayo -Jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la información al alta en la adherencia del paciente polimedicado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28889^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
