<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125098</identifier>
<setSpec>0367-2743</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leprosy in Colombia is not considering as a public health problem since a prevalence rate less tan 1/10000 was achieved more than ten years ago. Nevertheless, reports of 2012 from 11 of 27 departments 848%) showed incidence rates from 0.12 to 4.73 cases per 100000 inhabitants. The Ministry of Health and the National Institute of Health directs and organize the National Leprosy Program ( NLP), which plan the activities for prevention, surveillance and control at national level. The operational activities are delegated to the regional levels (municipalities, districts departments) however in many areas poor hospital infrastructure, high costs, lack of health personnel trained, difficult access to the health services are some of the barriers that impede the development and access to the activities that the NLP publishes in guides. The above mentioned facts have as consequence late case detection with 30% of disability rates (grade 1 and 2) at the time of diagnosis. Also, there is not awareness in general population neither in health professionals about the existence of leprosy cases in Colombia. This is a review of the situation of leprosy in Colombia, taking into account not only statistical data, but also some aspects that influence late diagnosis and disability found in patients at the time of diagnosis. In this review may appear author´s personal perceptions that may differ from others (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardona Castro, Nora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hace más de diez años que la lepra en Colombia no se considera un problema de salud pública, ya que la prevalencia es menor de 1/10.000. Si embargo, los informes de 2012 correspondientes a 11 de 27 Departamentos (48%) revelan incidencias de 0.12 a 4.73 casos por 100.000 habitantes. El Ministerio de Sanidad y el Instituto de Salud dirigen y organizan el Programa Nacional de la Lepra (PNL), que planifica las actividades de prevención, vigilancia y control a nivel nacional. La logística está delegada a nivel regional (municipios, distritos, Departamentos), sin embargo en muchas zonas la deficiente estructura hospitalaria, los elevados costes, la falta de personal sanitario formado, o el difícil acceso a los servicios sanitarios son algunas de las barreras que impiden el desarrollo y acceso a las actividades que el PNL publica en sus guías. Lo mencionado anteriormente tiene como consecuencia un diagnóstico tardío con un 30% de discapacidades (grado 1 y 2) en el momento del diagnóstico. Tampoco hay una gran percepción de la enfermedad en la población general ni en los profesionales sanitarios sobre la incidencia de la lepra en Colombia. Esta es una revisión de la situación de la lepra en Colombia, teniendo en cuenta no solamente los datos estadísticos, sino también algunos aspectos que influyen en el diagnóstico tardío y la discapacidad hallados en pacientes en el momento de su diagnóstico. Esta revisión contiene opiniones personales del autor que pueden diferir de las de otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fontilles, Rev. leprol;29(4): 297-308, ene.-abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lepra en Colombia: ¿Se encuentra en la fase de post-eliminación?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9359^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
