<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051120</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adequacy of vesical catheterisation in the prevention of urinary tract infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the adequacy prevalence of vesical        catheterisation in a second level university hospital.        Material and method: a descriptive study was performed on the        patients admitted to hospital in the years 2000, 2001 and 2002,        with a vesical catheterisation. Kunnin criteria were used to evaluate        the correct indication of vesical catheterisation. The medical        history as well as a consultation with the physician and nurse in        charge were both used as instruments for data collection. Descriptive        statistics indexes were computed for data processing.        Results: 214 patients who had a vesical catheter were studied,        mean age 62 years (SD; 15); 68% were males. 35% were postoperative        patients. The percentage of lack of suitability for vesical        catheterisation due to non compliance with Kunnin criteria was        16%. The percentage of major compliance, according to Kunnin        criteria, was the control of diuresis in 59% of cases.        Conclusions: there is a rather significant proportion of patients        (16%) who present an unclear indication for vesical catheterisation.        This leads us to think that a certain percentage of urinary        tract infections could be avoided. It is necessary to make professionals        aware of the possibility to use alternative instrumentalisations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moracho Fuertes, Ignacio Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Pérez, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Navas, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la prevalencia de adecuación del uso de        sondaje vesical en un hospital docente de 2º nivel.        Material y método: estudio descriptivo realizado en la población        ingresada en los años 2000, 2001 y 2002; y portadores de sonda        vesical. Para valorar la correcta indicación del sondaje vesical se utilizaron        los criterios de Kunin. Como instrumentos para la recogida        de los datos se utilizaron la Historia Clínica así como la entrevista al        médico y a la enfermera responsable del paciente. Se computaron        índices de estadística descriptiva en el tratamiento de los datos.        Resultados: se estudiaron 214 pacientes portadores de sondaje        vesical, con una media de edad de 62 años (DE: 15); el 68% eran        hombres. Un 35% eran pacientes postquirúrgicos. El porcentaje        de inadecuación del sondaje vesical por no cumplir ninguno de los        criterios de Kunin fue del 16%. El porcentaje de cumplimentación        mayor, según los criterios de Kunin, fue el estudio del control de la        diuresis, con un 59% de los casos.        Conclusiones: existe una proporción de pacientes no despreciable        (16%) que presenta una indicación no clara de sondaje vesical, lo        cual nos lleva a pensar que un porcentaje de infecciones del tracto        urinario podrían ser evitadas. Es necesario concienciar a los profesionales        de la posibilidad del uso de instrumentalizaciones alternativas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(7): 57-60, sept. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación del sondaje vesical en la prevención de infecciones del tracto urinario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
