<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134497</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional imbalances in the average Spanish diet; barriers to improvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To  analyze  the  main  nutritional  imbalances affecting Spanish population and the difficulties to solve it.  Methods: Literature search regarding the topic. Results: The disturbance of energy balance, associated with growing sedentary lifestyle, favors the increase in overweight and obesity that affects 47.8% of adults and 30.8% of Spanish children. Excessive salt intake (&gt; 5 g / day) was also verified in 88.2% of adults, quantifying urinary sodium excretion. Dietary studies in representative samples of adults, by controlling the intake and using the DIAL program, highlight the existence of a 89.2% and 93.3% people exceeding the recommended fat and saturated fat intakes, while in a 79.2% of cases intake of polyunsaturated  fat  was  insufficient.  A  84.3%,  81.6%,  30.2%  and 85.3% of adults have intakes of calcium, vitamin D, vitamin K and omega-3 fatty acids respectively under the recommended. Moreover, 76.7% and 99.9% of Spanish children have intakes of calcium and vitamin D lower than recommended. In a significant percentage of individuals there are deficiencies related to folic acid, vitamin D, E, B1, B2, B6, calcium, iron, zinc and selenium. The antioxidant capacity and glycemic load of the diet should be improve. Fluid intake is less than adequate in 80-90% of individuals. All these nutritional imbalances are associated with various health problems, particularly insulin resistance, bone deterioration, poorer cognitive function/mood, asthma and  other  disorders.  As  barriers  to  improve  include  the following: not perceived ignorance about nutrition and food, low  energy  intake  associated  to  hypocaloric  diets,  dietary restrictions, sedentary, elderly, increased requirements (joined to worst eating habits) of smokers, children of smokers, individuals with diseases, overweight/obesity... Conclusions: The nutritional status of the population is clearly improvable. Difficulties and barriers, coexist and add each other to hinder achieve the right situation. Therefore, monitoring nutritional problems in different risk groups should be more common in the future as a basis for further improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ortega, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navia Lombán, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Anta, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Sánchez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar los principales desequilibrios nutricionales que afectan a la población española y las dificultades para su resolución. Métodos: Búsqueda bibliográfica en relación con el tema. Resultados: El desequilibrio del balance energético, asociado al creciente sedentarismo favorece el incremento en el padecimiento de sobrepeso y obesidad, problema que afecta a un 47,8% de adultos y a un 30,8% de niños españoles. También se constata una excesiva ingesta de sal (&gt; 5 g/día) en un 88,2% de los adultos, considerando  la  excreción  urinaria  de  sodio.  Los  estudios  dietéticos realizados en muestras representativas de adultos, mediante control de la ingesta y empleo del programa DIAL, ponen de relieve la existencia de un 89,2% y un 93,3% de ingestas de grasa y grasa saturada superior a la aconsejada, mientras que en un 79,2% de los casos la ingesta de grasa poliinsaturada resultó insuficiente. Un 84,3%, 81,6%, 30,2% y 85,3% de los adultos presentan, respectivamente, ingestas de calcio, vitamina D, vitamina K y ácidos grasos omega-3 menores de las recomendadas. Por otra parte, 76,7% y 99,9% de los niños españoles tienen ingestas de calcio y vitamina D menores de las recomendadas. Existen deficiencias en un porcentaje apreciable de individuos en relación con los folatos, vitamina D, E, B1, B2, B6, calcio, hierro, zinc y selenio. La capacidad antioxidante y carga glucémica de la dieta son susceptibles de ser mejoradas. La ingesta de fluidos es menor de la adecuada en un 80-90% de los individuos. Los desequilibrios nutricionales se asocian con diversos perjuicios sanitarios (especialmente en resistencia a la insulina, deterioro óseo, peor función cognitiva/estado de ánimo, padecimiento de asma y otras alteraciones). Como barreras en la posible mejora, se detecta un desconocimiento no percibido en temas de nutrición y alimentación, la baja ingesta energética asociada al seguimiento de dietas hipocalóricas, restricciones alimentarias, sedentarismo, edad avanzada.. y el aumento en las necesidades (unido a peores hábitos alimentarios) de fumadores, hijos de fumadores, individuos con patologías, sobrepeso/obesidad... Conclusiones: La situación nutricional de la población es claramente  mejorable.  Las  dificultades  o  barreras,  al  coexistir  se suman para dificultar el lograr una situación correcta. Por ello, vigilar la problemática nutricional de diversos grupos de riesgo debe ser más habitual en el futuro, como base de posibles mejoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(supl.2): 29-35, oct. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desequilibrios nutricionales en la dieta media española; barreras en la mejora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24379^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
