<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121476</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Updates of analytical quality specifications 2014. Consensus of national scientific societies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to calculate minimum quality specifications (MQS) in urine biochemistry, blood glycosylated hemoglobin and several hematological analytes, and to compare these specifications with those from other countries, as well as to update the values for the 80 analytes studied. Materials used in this work are the results from laboratories participating in the external quality assurance programs organized by four Spanish scientific societies, and obtained in the time period 2007-2010. A total of 13,054 results were obtained for glycosy-lated hemoglobin, and from 14,180 (albumin) to 20,594 (creatinine) for urine biochemistry, andfor hematology, from 1,839 (fetal hemoglobin) to 6,961 (antithrombin).The conclusions found were: to achieve the MQS for glycosylated hemoglobin does not ensure  meeting clinical requirements, whereas MQS for urine biochemistry also meet the requirements based on biological variation. The MQS studied in this work could not be compared witht hose from other countries (there are no published values), and some of them could require calculations stratified according to several concentration levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ricós, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Bassini, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jou, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morancho, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blázquez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es calcular las especificaciones mínimas de la calidad (EMC) en bioquímica de orina, hemoglobina glucosilada en sangre y diversas determinaciones hematológicas, comparar estas especificaciones con las publicadas por organizaciones de diversos países y actualizar el listado con las 80 magnitudes estudiadas. Los materiales empleados en este estudio son todos los resultados de las EMC incluidas en los programas de garantía externa de la calidad organizadas por 4 sociedades científicas españolas, obtenidos desde 2007 hasta 2010. El número total de resultados obtenidos para hemoglobina glucosilada es de 13.054, para orina según cada magnitud va desde 14.180 (albúmina) hasta 20.594 (creatinina), y en hematología desde 1.839 (hemoglobina fetal) a 6.961 (antitrombina). Se concluye que cumplir la EMC de hemoglobina glucosilada no es suficiente para asegurar la calidad analítica según criterios clínicos, mientras que sí lo garantizan las EMC de orina; las magnitudes de hematología estudiadas en esta fase no pudieron compararse con especificaciones de obligado cumplimiento en otros países (no se encuentran publicadas), y algunas de ellas podrían requerir el cálculo de especificaciones diferentes para distintos niveles de concentración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;7(1): 3-8, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de las especificaciones de la calidad analítica 2014. Consenso de las Sociedades Científicas nacionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51548</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33560^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
