<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153779</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The cost of infection in hip arthroplasty: a matched case-control study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Surgical site infection (SSI) represents 30% of all causes of health care&#150;associated infection (HAI) and is one of the most dreaded complications in surgical patients. We estimated the excess direct costs of SSI using a matched nested case-control study in acute-term care at Ramon y Cajal University Hospital in Spain. Material and method. Cases were patients who developed a first episode of SSI according to the criteria established by the CDC's National Healthcare Safety Network. Controls were matched to cases in 1:1 ratio taking into account the American Society of Anesthesiologists score, age, sex, surgery date, and principal diagnosis. Results. This study found that infection in hip replacement increased direct costs by 134%. Likewise, the excess cost due to the infections caused by methicillin resistant Staphylococcus aureus was 69% higher than the excess cost attributable to infections caused by other microorganisms. Conclusions. SSI after hip replacement continues to be a costly complication from the hospital perspective. Costs due to SSI can be used to prioritise preventive interventions to monitor and control HAI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monge-Jodra, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robustillo-Rodela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva-Orbaiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Vélez, AE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Agero-Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La infección de localización quirúrgica (ILQ) representa el 30% de todas las causas de infecciones relacionadas con la atención sanitaria (IRAS), siendo una de las complicaciones más temidas en pacientes quirúrgicos. Se estimó el exceso de costes directos de la ILQ mediante un estudio de casos y controles emparejado y anidado en una cohorte, en un hospital de agudos en España (Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal). Material y método. Los casos fueron pacientes que desarrollaron un primer episodio de ILQ según los criterios establecidos por el National Healthcare Safety Network de los CDC. Los controles fueron emparejados a los casos en una razón de 1:1, teniendo en cuenta la clasificación de la American Society of Anesthesiologists, la edad, el sexo, la fecha de la cirugía y el diagnóstico principal. Resultados. Este estudio encontró que la infección en reemplazo de cadera incrementó los costes directos en un 134%. Asimismo, el exceso de costes debido a la infección causada por Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina fue 69% mayor que el exceso de costes debido a las infecciones causadas por otros microorganismos. onclusiones. La ILQ después de reemplazo de cadera sigue siendo una complicación costosa desde la perspectiva del hospital. Los costes debidos a la ILQ pueden ser utilizados para priorizar intervenciones preventivas de vigilancia y control de las infecciones relacionadas con la atención sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);60(4): 227-233, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El coste de la infección en artroplastia de cadera: estudio de casos y controles emparejado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
