<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038619</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An unusual morphological anomaly in an incisor crown. Anterior dens evaginatus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Exophytic growth of a portion of the tissue structure is one of the various clinical manifestations of the morphological anomalies that can affect the crown of the anterior teeth. The crown form disorder presented in this paper consists of an asymptomatic bulge on part of the vestibular surface of the tooth, due to enamel and dentine growth, with no radiological evidence of the pulp having extended into the protrusion of mineralised tissues. In this case, it only affects one tooth and is not associated with any other dental morphology or structure disorder, or with any of the syndromes that have been described in association with this anomaly. The term to describe this situation in the anterior teeth is not clearly defined in the relevant literature, which employs various names such as talon cusp, accentuated cingulum (when it affects the lingual or palatal surface) ordens evaginatus (evaginated tooth, evaginated odontome), the term that is always used when it is present in the posterior teeth</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llena Puy, Mari Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forner Navarro, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre las diversas manifestaciones clínicas de la anomalías morfológicas que afectan a las coronas de los dientes anteriores se encuentra el crecimiento exofítico de una porción de su estructura tisular. El trastorno de la forma dental que presentamos afecta a la corona del diente, y se caracteriza por un abultamiento parcial de la superficie vestibular, asintomático, a costa del crecimiento del esmalte y de la dentina, sin que radiológicamente se constate ningún prolapso pulpar hacia esta protrusión de tejidos mineralizados. El caso que se describe se manifiesta en un solo diente y no se asocia a ninguna otra alteración dentaria morfológica o estructural, ni tampoco a otros síndromes que sí se han descrito como asociados a esta anomalía. La literatura científica no determina de forma clara la terminología que se debe usar para definir esta situación en los dientes anteriores, empleándose diversas denominaciones, como cúspide en garra, cíngulo pseudocuspídeo (cuando afecta a la superficie lingual o palatina) o diente evaginado, que es como se nombra siempre a esta situación en dientes posteriores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(1): 13-16, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anomalía morfológica coronal inusual de un incisivo. Diente evaginado anterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32883^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
