<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058082</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heart failure units in Spain: state of the art</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heart failure is a huge public health problem. Heart failure units provide better care for patients with this condition. The establishment of such units in hospitals varies greatly between countries. To date, no specific data are available on the current situation with these units in Spain. A short questionnaire was used to evaluate the present-day implementation and characteristics of heart failure units in Spanish hospitals. Of the 110 hospitals surveyed, 45 (41%) had a heart failure unit. The percentage varied significantly with the technological sophistication of the hospital: level 1 (lowest) 8%, level 2 38%, and level 3 (highest) 76%. Some 91% of units were run by cardiology departments. In 78% of the units surveyed, nurses were involved in patient care, though only on a part-time basis in the majority (63%). Their task was primarily patient education, although, in 34%, they only performed basic support tasks (i.e., ECG and monitoring vital signs) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lupón, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia cardiaca es un problema asistencial de gran magnitud. Las unidades de insuficiencia cardiaca ofrecen una mejor atención a los pacientes con este síndrome. La implementación de estas unidades en los hospitales es muy variable en los distintos países. No se conocen datos concretos sobre la realidad de éstas en España. Mediante un breve cuestionario se han evaluado la implementación actual y las características de estas unidades en el ámbito hospitalario en España. De 110 hospitales consultados, 45 (41%) tienen unidad de insuficiencia cardiaca. Este porcentaje varía significativamente en función del nivel tecnológico (nivel 1: 8%, nivel 2: 38%, nivel 3: 76%). El 91% de las unidades depende del servicio de cardiología. El 78% de las unidades encuestadas dispone de enfermería, la mayoría (63%) con dedicación sólo a tiempo parcial; su labor es principalmente educativa, aunque un 34% sólo realiza labor de soporte (electrocardiograma y medición de constantes) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(8): 874-877, ago. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidades de insuficiencia cardiaca en España: situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
