<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108026</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hiding problems sphincters management: report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Toilet training disorders are commonly treated problems in Primary Health Care Pediatrician practice. A case study of a four year-old boy with functional encopresis and stool toileting refusal is presented; the interdisciplinary intervention conducted by specialized Pediatrics and Clinical Psychology is also discussed. This clinical case presentation shows that the same symptoms may underlie different problems which would require different therapeutic interventions. The need to pay attention to the contexts surrounding the child (family, school, professionals) is also highlighted; as well as assessing the interaction and reciprocal influence between the child&#146;s symptoms, the parents&#146; attitudes and other external factors, in order to understand and approach to the problem in a more comprehensive way (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Ceruelo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bezos Saldaña, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos del control de esfínteres son uno de los problemas más comunes en la consulta del pediatra de Atención Primaria. Se expone un caso clínico de un niño de cuatro años que presenta encopresis funcional por rechazo a utilizar el inodoro, así como la intervención llevada a cabo en conjunto por Pediatría y Psicología Clínica. La exposición de este caso muestra cómo la misma manifestación puede esconder distintos problemas que requerirán diferentes abordajes terapéuticos. Asimismo, se pone de manifiesto la necesidad de prestar atención a los diversos contextos que rodean al niño (familia, escuela, profesionales), así como valorar la interacción y la influencia mutua de los síntomas de este con la actitud de los padres y con otros factores externos para entender y abordar el problema de forma más precisa y global (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;14(56): 317-321, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué esconden los problemas del control de esfínteres? A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4769^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51255^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33526^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14427</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33526^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33526^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4769^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4769^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4769^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51255^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
