<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134891</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lung cancer in women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lung cancer is the tenth cause of death worldwide but is predicted to become the fifth cause in the next few years. In Spain, the situation is even worse, with changes in smoking patterns in women providing little cause for optimism. A large number of women in Spain smoke and female smokers are more likely to develop lung cancer than male smokers. After diagnosis, women show differences in histological type and generally live longer than men. Women show better survival after surgery in localized tumors, as well as after chemotherapy in advanced non-small cell tumors and in small cell tumors. These data indicate the need to change the belief that lung cancer affects mainly men and to determine the special characteristics of this disease in women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almonacid Sánchez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Alonso, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de pulmón es la décima causa de muerte en el mundo, pero se estima que pasará a ocupar el quinto lugar en los próximos años. En España esta situación es aún peor, con un futuro poco alentador como consecuencia del cambio en el hábito tabáquico en las mujeres. Además de su incorporación masiva a un hábito de riesgo, las mujeres que fuman son más susceptibles que los varones a desarrollar cáncer de pulmón. Tras un diagnóstico de cáncer de pulmón, las mujeres tienen diferencias en el tipo histológico y, en términos generales, viven más que los varones. En relación con el tratamiento, las mujeres tienen mejores supervivencias tras cirugía en tumores localizados. También viven más tras quimioterapia en tumores de células peque- ñas y en los no microcíticos avanzados. Estos datos nos obligan a cambiar la creencia de que el cáncer de pulmón es una enfermedad que afecta principalmente al sexo masculino y a conocer las peculiaridades que puede presentar en las mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;42(supl.2): 19-24, dic. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cáncer de pulmón en la mujer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
