<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168020</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of the cultural competence model in the experience of care in nursing professionals Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the experiences and perceptions of nurses in providing care and health promotion, women belonging to groups at risk of social vulnerability, applying the model of cultural competence Purnell. Design: Phenomenological qualitative study. Location: Department of Health Elda. Participants: A total of 22 primary care professional volunteers. Method: Semi-structured interviews and focus groups with recording and content analysis, according to the theory model of cultural competence. Results: Socio-cultural factors influence the relationship between professionals and users of the system. The subtle racism and historical prejudices create uncomfortable situations and mistrust. The language barrier makes it difficult not only communication, but also the monitoring and control of the health-disease process. The physical appearance and stereotypes are determining factors for primary care professionals. Although perceived misuse of health services are also talking about changes. The spiritual aspects of religious beliefs alone are taken into account in the case of Muslim women, not being considered as important in the case of Gypsy women and Romanian women. Conclusions: To provide quality care, consistent and culturally competent, it is necessary to develop training programs for professionals in cultural competence, to know the culture of other, and work without preconceived ideas, and ethnocentric; since the greater the knowledge of the cultural group being served, the better the quality of care provided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Estevan, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Ruíz, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las experiencias y percepciones de los profesionales de enfermería en la prestación de cuidados y promoción de la salud, a mujeres pertenecientes a colectivos en riesgo de vulnerabilidad social, aplicando el modelo de competencia cultural de Purnell. Diseño: Estudio cualitativo fenomenológico. Emplazamiento: Departamento de Salud de Elda. Participantes: Veintidós profesionales voluntarios de Atención Primaria. Método: Entrevistas semiestructuradas y grupos focales con grabación y análisis de contenido, de acuerdo con la teoría del modelo de competencia cultural. Resultados: Los factores socioculturales influyen en la relación entre profesionales y usuarias del sistema. El racismo sutil y los prejuicios históricos crean situaciones incómodas y de desconfianza. La barrera idiomática dificulta no solo la comunicación, sino también el seguimiento y control del proceso salud-enfermedad. El aspecto físico y los estereotipos son condicionantes para los profesionales de Atención Primaria. Aunque se percibe que se hace un mal uso de los servicios sanitarios, se escuchan discursos con signo de cambios. Los aspectos espirituales relacionados con las creencias religiosas solo se tienen en cuenta en el caso de mujeres musulmanas, no siendo considerados como algo importante en el caso de mujeres gitanas o rumanas. Conclusiones: Para ofrecer cuidados de calidad, culturalmente congruentes y competentes, es preciso desarrollar programas de formación en competencia cultural para profesionales, con el fin de dar a conocer la cultura del otro, y trabajar sin ideas preconcebidas y etnocentristas; ya que cuanto mayor es el conocimiento del grupo cultural al que se atiende, mejor es la calidad de los cuidados prestados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(9): 549-556, nov. 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La aplicación del modelo de competencia cultural en la experiencia del cuidado en profesionales de Enfermería de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52938^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
