<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131384</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis B serology in immigrant children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Immigration is an important phenomenon in our environment. Some guidelines for the care of the immigrant child include the evaluation of hepatitis B virus (HBV) serology. Objective. To evaluate the need for the systematic measurement of surface antigen (HBsAg), core antigen antibody (HBcAb), and surface antigen antibody (HBsAb) in young immigrants, and to determine the prevalence of HBsAb in those who receive HBV vaccination. Method. HBsAg, HBsAb, and HBcAb values were determined in children from 6 months to 15 years of age who emigrated from low-income countries within the prior 12 months. The prevalence and confidence intervals were calculated. Results. Of the 1,226 children evaluated, HBsAg was measured in 1,098 (89.5%) and was positive in 8 (0.79%, CI 0.37-1.43), including two cases in whom vaccination had been documented; HBcAb was measured in 1,024 and was the only positive HBV marker in 7 cases (0.98%, CI 0.47-1.80); and HBsAb was measured in 987 and was positive in 33.26%. In 30.8% of the children, the only positive marker was HBsAb. Of the 333 children Background. Immigration is an important phenomenon in our environment. Some guidelines for the care of the immigrant child include the evaluation of hepatitis B virus (HBV) serology. Objective. To evaluate the need for the systematic measurement of surface antigen (HBsAg), core antigen antibody (HBcAb), and surface antigen antibody (HBsAb) in young immigrants, and to determine the prevalence of HBsAb in those who receive HBV vaccination. Method. HBsAg, HBsAb, and HBcAb values were determined in children from 6 months to 15 years of age who emigrated from low-income countries within the prior 12 months. The prevalence and confidence intervals were calculated. Results. Of the 1,226 children evaluated, HBsAg was measured in 1,098 (89.5%) and was positive in 8 (0.79%, CI 0.37-1.43), including two cases in whom vaccination had been documented; HBcAb was measured in 1,024 and was the only positive HBV marker in 7 cases (0.98%, CI 0.47-1.80); and HBsAb was measured in 987 and was positive in 33.26%. In 30.8% of the children, the only positive marker was HBsAb. Of the 333 children(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masvidal, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos, Elisa de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estabanell, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La inmigración es importante en nuestro medio. Algunos protocolos de atención al niño inmigrante incluyen la determinación del estado serológico respecto al virus de la hepatitis B (VHB). Objetivo. Valorar la conveniencia de la determinación sistemática del antígeno de superficie (HBsAg), anticuerpo contra el core (HBSerologia del virus de l&#146;hepatitis B en infants recentment immigrats Ana Estabanell 1, Rosa M. Masvidal 2, Elisa de Frutos 2, Dolors Riera 3, Cecilia Cruz 1, Beatriz Miguel 2 1 CAP Gòtic (annex Rull). ABS Gòtic. Institut Català de la Salut. Barcelona. 2 CAP Dr. Lluís Sayé. ABS Raval Nord. Institut Català de la Salut. Barcelona. 3 CAP Drassanes. ABS Raval Sud. Institut Municipal d&#146;Assistència Sanitària de Barcelona. cAc), anticuerpo contra el Ag de superficie (HBsAc), en niños inmigrantes. Determinar la prevalencia del HBsAc positivo en los vacunados contra el VHB. Método. Se determinaron HbsAg, HBsAc, HBcAc en niños de 6 meses a 15 años procedentes de países de baja renta que habían llegado hacía menos de 12 meses. Se registró su estado vacunal. Se estimó la prevalencia y el intervalo de confianza del resultado. Resultados. De los 1.226 niños/as, se determinó el HbsAg en 1.098 (89,5%), siendo 8 positivos: 0,79% (intervalo de confianza (IC) 95%: 0,37-1,43), dos de éstos constaban como vacunados para el VHB. En 1.024 se determinó el HBcAc, siendo el único marcador positivo en 7 casos: 0,98% (IC 0,47-1,80); el HBsAc se determinó en 987 y fue positivo en el 33,23%. De los 333 niños vacunados con tres dosis, en 267 se determinó el HBsAc, siendo positivo en el 59,9% (IC 95%: 55,15-64,45). Conclusiones. Consideramos indicada la determinación del HbsAg a los niños inmigrantes, incluyendo los que aportan datos de vacunación del VHB completa. No creemos justificado solicitar el HBcAc de manera sistemática. En niños inmigrantes vacunados puede estar indicado determinar los HBsAc(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;71(1): 7-12, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El virus de la hepatitis B en niños recién inmigrados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6666^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6665^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6666^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
