<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120811</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of longitudinality, comprehensiveness, coordination and continuity of nursing home care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Home care is essential for dependent persons, in order to support the high levels of morbidity, for the elderly as well as their caregivers, as it enables patients to remain in their familiar environment as long as possible, ful&amp;#64257;lling the wish expressed by most of the population. Home care is the activity that best represents the essential attributes (longitudinality, comprehensiveness, continuity, coordination) of the primary, and that suffers most when these attributes are not included in the activities undertaken by primary care teams, or due to cutsin health-care. Home care requires highly skilled, versatile and committed nursing staff, with whom the population identi&amp;#64257;es as a source of care, and where they are assessed for their relevance and effectiveness. Nurses with wide clinical care skills, with a balanced content of treatment and prevention, and the freedom to develop their work, are needed in order to continuously monitor the health problems of their acute and chronic patients, in the family and community (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomo-Cobos, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corrales-Nevado, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuidados domiciliarios son imprescindibles para las personas dependientes, para las que soportan elevadas cargas de morbilidad, para los ancianos, y también para sus cuidadores, porque permiten a los pacientes continuar en su entorno habitual el mayor tiempo posible, cumpliendo el deseo expreso de la mayoría de la población. La atención domiciliaria es la actividad que mejor representa los atributos esenciales (longitudinalidad, integralidad, continuidad, coordinación) de la atención primaria y la que más se resiente cuando estos atributos no impregnan la actividad realizada por los equipos de atención primaria o cuando se aplican políticas de recorte. El espacio de la atención domiciliaria precisa de una enfermería altamente cualificada, polivalente y comprometida, a la que la población identifique como una fuente de cuidados y donde estos se evalúen con criterios de pertinencia y efectividad. Se necesitan enfermeras con amplias competencias clinicoasistenciales, con gran autonomía para desarrollar su trabajo, que realicen un seguimiento continuo de los problemas de salud de sus pacientes, agudos y crónicos, en el ámbito familiar y de la comunidad, y con contenidos curativos y preventivos equilibrados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(1): 51-58, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La importancia de la longitudinalidad, integralidad, coordinación y continuidad de los cuidados domiciliarios efectuados por enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
