<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167100</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Course and aging in institutionalized schizophrenia: A comparison of cognitive performance profiles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurocognitive deficits in schizophrenia have been studied extensively, but there is no consensus about their course or their analysis in aging population. The objective of the present study is to compare neurocognitive profiles between people over (group A) and under (group B) 65 years of age with schizophrenia and between aging individuals with schizophrenia and healthy individuals of the same age (group C). 90 people enrolled in the study (44 male, 46 female), divided into 3 age groups. The participants were assessed with the Cambridge Cognitive Examination-Revised (CAMCOG-R) and the Memory Subtests of the Barcelona Test - Revised Edition. Worse scores were found (p&lt; .05) when comparing group A with B (except in memory subtests; no difference) and group A with C, being Language the area where more effect size is observed (x2= 0.481). We conclude that the aging process produces more cognitive deficits in schizophrenia than in healthy population and that, in general, the deficits in patients with schizophrenia intensify with age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miguel-De Diego, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pablos, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Villalobos, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanguino-Andrés, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulino-Matos, Pedro M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los deficits neurocognitivos en esquizofrenia han sido muy estudiados, pero no existe consenso sobre su curso ni es abundante su análisis en población envejecida. El objetivo del presente trabajo es comparar perfiles neurocognitivos entre sujetos mayores (grupo A) y menores (grupo B) de 65 años con esquizofrenia y entre sujetos mayores con esquizofrenia y controles sanos de la misma edad (grupo C). Participaron 90 sujetos (44 varones, 46 mujeres) divididos en tres grupos según la edad. Los participantes fueron evaluados con el "Examen cognitivo de Cambridge-revisado" (Cambridge Cognitive Examination-Revised, CAMCOG-R) y los subtests de memoria del "Test Barcelona revisado". Se encuentran peores rendimientos (p&lt; 0,05) en el grupo A frente al B (excepto en subpruebas de memoria) y en el grupo A frente al C, siendo el área del lenguaje en la que se observa mayor tamaño del efecto (x2= 0,481). Se concluye que el proceso de envejecimiento produce déficits cognitivos más acusados en esquizofrenia que en población sana y que en general los déficits de los pacientes con esquizofrenia se intensifican con la edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;25(2): 259-274, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Curso y envejecimiento en la esquizofrenia institucionalizada: comparación de perfiles de rendimiento cognitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50269</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
