<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145576</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcomes of pancreatic surgery in patients older than 70 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The proportion of elderly patients is growing rapidly. Knowing the results of pancreatic surgery in this group of patients would help surgeons to make therapeutic decisions. The objective is to evaluate the surgical outcomes of pancreatic resections in patients over 70 years. Methods: Retrospective study including patients undergoing pancreatic resection during the period 2009-2014. The sample was divided into 2 groups. G1: Patients under 70 years and G2: Patients older than 70 years. Surgical results between the 2 groups were evaluated. Results: Seventy three pancreatic resections were performed, 51 (70%) patients belonged to G1 and 22 (30%) to G2. There were no significant differences between G1 and G2 in terms of operative time and hospitalization days. No significant difference was obtained in the incidence of delayed gastric emptying, pancreatic fistula or biliary fistula. The overall mortality in the series was 4.1% showing difference between both groups, with 2% in G1 and 13.6% in G2 (P=.04). When a sub-analysis in G2 was made, mortality in this group occurred only in patients with significant comorbidities with ASA &amp;#8805; 3 (P=.004). Both groups with oncologic disease had similar overall survival and disease-free survival. Conclusions: Age should not be a limiting factor for pancreatic resections. The elderly have similar results as younger patients and their increased perioperative mortality is due to the presence of important associated comorbidities rather than age as an independent risk factor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>McCormack, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iovaldi, Mario L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schlottmann, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capitanich, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La proporción de pacientes añosos está creciendo rápidamente. Conocer los verdaderos resultados de la cirugía pancreática en este grupo etario ayudaría para la toma de decisiones terapéuticas. El objetivo es evaluar los resultados quirúrgicos de resecciones pancreáticas en pacientes mayores de 70 años. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo que incluye a pacientes tratados mediante resección pancreática en el período 2009-2014. Se dividió la muestra en 2 grupos. G1: pacientes menores de 70 años y G2: pacientes mayores de 70 años. Se compararon los resultados quirúrgicos en ambos grupos. Resultados: Se realizaron 73 resecciones pancreáticas; 51 (70%) pacientes pertenecieron al G1 y 22 (30%) al G2. No hubo diferencias significativas entre G1 y G2 en cuanto al tiempo operatorio ni a los días de internación. Tampoco se obtuvo diferencia significativa en incidencia de retardo del vaciamiento gástrico, fístula pancreática ni fístula biliar. La mortalidad global de la serie fue del 4,1%: del 2% en G1 y del 13,6% en G2 (p: 0,04). Al realizar un subanálisis en G2, la mortalidad en este grupo ocurrió únicamente en pacientes con comorbilidades significativas con ASA &amp;#8805; 3 (p: 0,004). Ambos grupos con enfermedad maligna presentaron similar sobrevida global y libre de enfermedad. Conclusiones: La edad no debería ser un factor limitante para realizar resecciones pancreáticas. Los pacientes añosos presentan similares resultados quirúrgicos, y su mortalidad perioperatoria aumentada se debería a la presencia de comorbilidades importantes asociadas, y no a la edad como variable independiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(10): 638-642, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la cirugía pancreática en pacientes mayores de 70 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10370^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
