<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102286</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profile of children and adolescents with autism spectrum disorders in an institution in Bogota, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To determine the profile of children and adolescents diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) in a comprehensive care centre in Bogota, Colombia. Material and methods: A descriptive-correlational study with a sample of patients who had attended the institution from 2003 to 2009. Demographic and clinical aspects were evaluated and a correlation between the diagnosis and severity being analysed in search for risk factors. Results: A total of138 patients were studied. The average age of onset was 21 months, and diagnosis had been made at 45 months. There was a male predominance (6.15:1). The predominant diagnosis was autistic syndrome (83%), followed by pervasive developmental disorder not otherwise specified (17%). There was no pathological background in the family history, during pregnancy or during the neonatal period. Motor development during the first year was normal but acquisition of language skills was compromised. The specific signs of ASD as regards the disorder in itself, communication skills, spontaneous speech, verbal comprehension, attention, imitation, use of objects, self-care and symbolic play were significantly related to the severity of the disease. Conclusions: Diagnosis of ASD is still delayed in our population and usually after referral from someone other than a health professional. The most important problems were found in communication skills and relationships with peers. The study did not show significant associated risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vélez-Van-Meerbeke, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa, D de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talero-Gutiérrez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Caracterizar la población de niños y adolescentes con diagnóstico de trastornos del espectro autista (TEA) en un centro de atención integral en Bogotá Colombia. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo-correlacional, de la población de pacientes que han asistido al centro desde el año 2003 hasta el 2009. Se evaluaron los aspectos demográficos y clínicos, y se realizó una correlación entre las variables con el diagnóstico y la severidad para la búsqueda de factores de riesgo.Resultados: Se estudió a 138 pacientes. La edad promedio de inicio fue a los 21 meses y el diagnóstico a los 45. Hubo predominancia masculina (6,15:1). El diagnóstico mas frecuente fue síndrome autista (83%), seguido por trastorno generalizado del desarrollo no determinado (17%). No se encontraron antecedentes importantes en la familia, durante el embarazo ni en el periodo neonatal. El desarrollo motor durante el primer año fue normal mientras que el desarrollo de la comunicación verbal se encontró comprometido. Los signos específicos de TEA como el trastorno en referencia a sí mismo, comunicación, habla espontánea, comprensión verbal, atención, imitación, utilización de objetos, autocuidado y juego simbólico se relacionaron significativamente con la severidad del cuadro.Conclusiones: El diagnostico de los TEA continúa siendo tardío en nuestra población y generalmente luego de la remisión de personal ajeno a la salud. Las alteraciones más importantes se encuentran en la comunicación y en la relación con los pares. En el estudio no se evidenciaron factores de riesgo que pudieran estar asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(2): 93-96, mar. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de niños y adolescentes con trastornos del espectro autista en una institución de Bogotá, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2704^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
