<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139059</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parental rearing and eating psychopathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study was to identify the relationship between perceived rearing styles and the clinical expression of Eating Disorders (ED).  Methods. One hundred and ninety-six patients diagnosed of an ED and 127 healthy student as controls selected from the Nursing College were evaluated for general psychopathology (STAI, BDI II, RSE), and for abnormal eating attitudes (EAT, EDI-II, BITE). The EMBU (&#145;my memories of upbringing&#146;) was administered for the assessment of perceived parental rearing styles and we used a questionnaire to assess familial variables. Results. In relation to the control group, patients with ED perceived greater rejection, overprotection and less warmth than the controls. Patients who perceived greater paternal favoritism, maternal overprotection and low paternal emotional warmth, showed higher levels of anxiety. Paternal affection and maternal attitudes of rejection, overprotection and favoritism were related with lower selfesteem. Regarding abnormal eating attitudes, body dissatisfaction inversely correlated with paternal emotional care and maternal favoritism. The EDI subscales: ineffectiveness, perfectionism and ascetism were associated with parental rejection. Maternal rejection also related with drive for thinness, interoceptive awareness and impulse regulation. Perceived emotional warmth was related with perfectionism. Bulimia subscale and BITE scores were inversely associated with paternal overprotection and affection, and scored significantly higher in paternal favoritism and rejection from both parents.   Conclusions. Perceived parental bonding is different in the various subtypes of EDs. Patients diagnosed of Bulimia Nervosa or Eating Disorders Not Otherwise Specified perceived greater rejection, less affection and a greater overprotection than Anorexia Nervosa patients and controls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herraiz-Serrrano, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre-Postigo, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beato-Fernández, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaz-Leal, Francisco JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo-Moreno, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Cano, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es identificar cómo los recuerdos de la crianza podrían influir en la expresión clínica de los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria (TCA). Metodología. Administramos una batería de cuestionarios de psicopatología general (BDI, STAI, RSE) y alimentaria (EAT, EDI-2, BITE, BSQ) a 196 pacientes diagnosticados de TCA y a 127 sujetos sanos reclutados de la Escuela de Enfermería. Todos completaron también un cuestionario sobre &#145;Los recuerdos de mi crianza&#146; (EMBU) y una encuesta de variables familiares. Resultados. En relación al grupo control, los pacientes con un TCA percibían mayor rechazo, sobreprotección y menor afecto que los controles. En el grupo de pacientes, el favoritismo paterno, la sobreprotección materna e inversamente el afecto paterno se relacionaba con la ansiedad estado y rasgo. El afecto paterno, junto al rechazo, la sobreprotección y el favoritismo maternos, también se relacionaba inversamente con la autoestima. Respecto a la psicopatología alimentaria, el rechazo corporal se relacionaba inversamente con afecto paterno y favoritismo materno. La ineficacia, perfeccionismo y ascetismo del EDI con el rechazo global y el rechazo materno con la tendencia a la delgadez, conciencia interoceptiva e impulsividad. El afecto global con perfeccionismo. La subescala bulimia y las puntuaciones del BITE se relacionaban inversamente con sobreprotección paterna y afecto paterno y directamente con favoritismo paterno y rechazo global. Conclusiones. La percepción de la crianza difiere en los subtipos de TCA. Pacientes con bulimia o TCA no especificado recordaban mayor rechazo, menor afecto y mayor sobreprotección que pacientes con anorexia y controles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;43(3): 91-98, mayo-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139059</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la percepción de la crianza y la psicopatología alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12954^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12954^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12954^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12954^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
