<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120272</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Energy availability, menstrual dysfunction and bone health in sports;  an overwiew of the female athlete triad</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The female athlete triad (FAT) is a serious health-related problem that threatens women who exercise. This condition is an interrelated multifactorial syndrome which includes low energy availability, menstrual cycle disturbances and decreased bone mineral density. OBJECTIVE: To review the major components of the FAT and their relationships, as well as strategies for diagnosis and treatment. METHODS: Articles related to the topic were reviewed through PubMed and SportDiscus databases. RESULTS: Interrelationship between components of the FAT may result in clinical manifestations, including eating disorders, amenorrhea and osteoporosis. Clinical conditions are not always exhibited simultaneously. Prevention is important to minimize complications. Diagnosis and treatment is complicated and often must involve an interdisciplinary therapeutic approach. CONCLUSIONS: Understanding of the disease may be facilitated by a unified framework focusing on energy deficiency. Preventive or early interventions require to increase energy availability through a higher total energy intake or a decrease in energy expenditure trough excessive physical exercise. A healthy lifestyle, and support by parents and coaches should be included. Psychotherapy may be necessary when eating disorders are present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molinero, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La tríada de la atleta femenina es un importante problema de salud que amenaza a las mujeres que practican ejercicio. Este trastorno constituye un síndrome multifactorial e interrelacionado que incluye una baja disponibilidad de energía, alteraciones del ciclo menstrual y disminución de la densidad mineral ósea. Objetivo: Revisar los componentes de la tríada de la atleta femenina y sus interacciones, así como las estrategias de diagnóstico y tratamiento. Métodos: Se revisaron artículos relacionados con el tema en las bases de datos Pubmed y Sportdiscus. Resultados: La interrelación entre los componentes de la tríada de la atleta femenina puede resultar en manifestaciones clínicas, que incluyen trastornos de la conducta alimentaria, amenorrea y osteoporosis. Estas manifestaciones no siempre se presentan de forma simultánea. La prevención es importante para minimizar las complicaciones. El diagnostico y el tratamiento son complicados y pueden requerir a menudo un abordaje terapéutico multidisciplinar. Conclusiones: El conocimiento de la enfermedad puede facilitarse por el desarrollo de un marco unificado centrado en la deficiencia de energía. Las intervenciones preventivas y tempranas requieren un incremento de la disponibilidad de energía a través de un mayor aporte energético o una reducción del gasto asociado a un ejercicio físico excesivo. Debe incluirse un estilo de vida saludable y el apoyo por parte de padres y entrenadores. La psicoterapia puede ser necesaria si se presentan trastornos alimentarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(4): 1010-1017, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disponibilidad de energía, disfunción menstrual y salud ósea en el deporte; una revisión de la tríada de la atleta femenina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8768^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
