<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130942</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The correct use of topical steroids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since their discovery in 1852 by Sulzberger and Witten, topic steroids constitute maybe the most widely used topic therapy in dermatology for various diseases. Modifications of their basic structure have been done for obtaining greater effectivity and less side-effects, and at present there are second and third generation products. They act through their anti-inflammatory, vaso-constrictor. immuno-supressor and anti-proliferative activity. There are several classifications according to their potency, but the most practical one is the one that divides them in 4 groups. There are several tests to classify them, but the Mckenzie-Stoughton vaso-constriction or cutaneous whitening test is the most used, Their potency depends on various factors; chemical structure, topography of the area to be treated, conditions of the skin to be treated, age of the patient, vehicle in which the drug is presented, extensión of the area to be treated. There are several risk factors, as well as relative and absolute counter indications for its use. There are many diseases susceptible to this therapy, with different response degrees. They have both local and systemic side-effects. They are very useful, but when they are used, the risk-benefit index should always be valuated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rondón Lugo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su descubrimiento en 1952 por Sulzberger y Witten, los esteroides tópicos constituyen quizás la terapéutica tópica más empleada en dermatología para diversas afecciones. Se han realizado modificaciones en su estructura básica para lograr mayor efectividad y menos efectos secundarios, existiendo los de segunda y luego los de tercera generación. Actúan por su actividad Antinflamatoria, Vasoconstrictora, Inmunosupresora y Antiproliferativa. De acuerdo a su potencia hay varias clasificaciones, pero la más práctica es la que los divide en 4 grupos; existiendo varias pruebas para ubicarlos, siendo la más empleada la prueba de vasoconstricción o blanqueo cutáneo de Mckenzie-Stoughton. La potencia depende de varios factores: estructura química, topografía de la zona a tratar, condiciones de la piel, edad del paciente, vehículo de presentación del medicamento, extensión de la zona en tratamiento. Existen varios factores de riesgo, así como contraindicaciones relativas y absolutas para su uso. Muchas son las afecciones susceptibles a esta terapia, en diferentes grados de respuesta. Tienen efectos secundarios, tanto locales como sistémicos. Son muy útiles pero cuando se empleen siempre hayque valorar riesgo-beneficio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;41(6): 245-253, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Buen uso de los esteroides tópicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
