<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59079</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative management of a ruptured sinus of Valsalva aneurysm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital sinus of Valsalva aneurysms areextremely rare in Spain. The lesion consists of a defectthat allows the aortic media to separate from theannulus fibrosus of the aortic valve, causing it to dilatewith arterial pressure. The natural course of theaneurysm involves the risk of complication due tobacterial endocarditis, with conduction blocks ormyocardial ischemia. Rupture of the aneurysm, usuallyinto a right chamber, causes a left-right shunt that leadsto heart failure and death if untreated. We present thecase of a previously asymptomatic 60-year-old womanwho presented with a clinical picture that led to adiagnosis of hyperthyroidism, and in whom thereoccurred a coincident rupture of a congenital sinus ofValsalva aneurysm. We describe the anestheticprocedure and emphasize the importance ofintraoperative echocardiography throughout theresection of the aneurysm</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llagunes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los aneurismas congénitos del seno de Valsalva sonuna afección muy rara en nuestro medio. La lesión fundamentalconsiste en un defecto entre la capa mediaaórtica y el anillo fibroso de la válvula aórtica, en unpunto que se dilataría por acción de las presiones arteriales.En su evolución natural existe riesgo de complicarsecon una endocarditis bacteriana, con bloqueos deconducción o con isquemia miocárdica. La ruptura delaneurisma a una cavidad, generalmente derecha, originaun cortocircuito izquierda-derecha y da lugar a unainsuficiencia cardiaca de pronóstico fatal dejada a suevolución.Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 60 años, previamenteasintomática que desarrolla un cuadro clínicodiagnosticado como hipertiroidismo que coincide con larotura de un aneurisma congénito del seno de Vasalva.Ponemos de manifiesto la conducta anestésica y laimportancia de la ecocardiografía intraoperatoriadurante todo el procedimiento de la resección del aneurisma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(3): 175-178, mar. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo perioperatorio de un aneurisma de seno de Valsalva roto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7160^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
