<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128113</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness and therapeutic aims of enzyme replacement therapy in mucopolysaccharidosis type II (Hunter Syndrome)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Mucopolysaccharidosis type II (MPS II), or Hunter syndrome, is a lysosomal disease that is transmitted by recessive inheritance linked to the X chromosome and is caused by an iduronate-2-sulphatase enzyme deficit. The treatment of lysosomal diseases in general and MPS in particular has undergone spectacular changes over the last 25 years. At present, the development of enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) is being used as a new therapeutic option in the treatment of lysosomal diseases. Development. The development of ERT has offered these patients the first therapeutic benefits. In 2006, the  US Food and Drug Administration authorised the use of idursulfase, and in Europe it was approved by the European Medicines Agency in January 2007. The following question arises with respect to treatment with idursulfase today: do we treat Hunter syndrome or not? Despite being a promising alternative, at the present time ERT has a number of limitations that make it necessary to pose this question. Throughout this review we will analyse both the beneficial effects and the current drawbacks of ERT. Conclusions. To be able to answer this question properly, the following theoretical objectives have to be accomplished: appraisal of the therapeutic effectiveness and clinical relevance of ERT in MPS II, development of suitable biomarkers for monitoring the treatment and setting suitable therapeutic aims that help us to establish the indications of ERT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Segura, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baldellou Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente Hidalgo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Jiménez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Delgado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López pisón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La mucopolisacaridosis tipo II (MPS II), o síndrome de Hunter, es una enfermedad lisosomal de herencia recesiva ligada al cromosoma X, causada por el déficit de la enzima iduronato 2 sulfatasa. El tratamiento de las enfermedades lisosomales en general, y de las MPS en particular, ha cambiado en los últimos 25 años de forma espectacular. En la actualidad, el desarrollo del tratamiento enzimático sustitutivo (TES) ha emergido en las enfermedades lisosomales como una nueva opción terapéutica. Desarrollo. El desarrollo del TES ha ofrecido a estos pacientes los primeros beneficios terapéuticos. En el año 2006, la Food and Drug Administration estadounidense aprobó el uso de la idursulfasa, y en Europa fue la European Medicines Agency quien lo aprobó en enero de 2007. En torno al tratamiento con la idursulfasa se plantea en la actualidad una reflexión: ¿tratar o no tratar el síndrome de Hunter? El TES, a pesar de ser una alternativa prometedora, tiene hoy por hoy algunas limitaciones que hacen imprescindible este planteamiento. A lo largo de esta revisión se analizan tanto los efectos beneficiosos como las limitaciones actuales con el TES. Conclusión. Para responder adecuadamente a esta cuestión, es necesaria la consecución de los siguientes objetivos teóricos: valorar la eficacia terapéutica y la relevancia clínica del TES en la MPS II, desarrollar los biomarcadores adecuados para la monitorización del tratamiento y marcar unos objetivos terapéuticos adecuados que nos ayuden a establecer las indicaciones del TES (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;47(supl.2): s15-s18, nov. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y objetivos terapéuticos del tratamiento enzimático sustitutivo en la mucopolisacaridosis tipo II (síndrome de Hunter)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53690^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30150^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
