<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80324</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reasons for smoking cessation in Spain by gender and age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo analyze gender- and age-related motivations among smokers wishing to quit.MethodsWe performed a multicenter cross-sectional study in 1,634 smokers attended by general practitioners and specialized physicians in Spain who, after being explicitly asked about their intention to quit smoking, expressed a desire to do so. Sociodemographic data, history of smoking and motivations for cessation were collected. A descriptive statistical analysis was performed.ResultsThe mean age was 45.6 years (SD±12.0 years). Fifty-six percent were men. A total of 35.2% had studied beyond high school. The main motivation expressed by 63.9% of men and 81.1% of smokers older than 60 years old was medical advice; 60.7% of women were motivated by disease prevention; 31.5% of smokers aged between 31 and 45 years old wanted to be a good role model for their children and 11.4% of those aged between 18 and 30 were motivated by esthetic reasons.ConclusionsMen tend to be motivated by medical advice, while women are motivated by a desire to be a role model for their children, to prevent diseases or improve their appearance. The greater the age, the greater the percentage of patients motivated by medical advice. Middle-aged adults want to be good role models for their children while young patients are motivated by esthetic concerns(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramon Torrell, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruguera Cortada, Eugeni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz de Burgoa, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pinilla, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Vázquez,  Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar los motivos para dejar de fumar ligados al sexo y a la edad del paciente fumador que desea abandonar el consumo de tabaco.MétodosEstudio multicéntrico transversal sobre 1.634 fumadores atendidos en consultas de atención primaria y especializada de España, que tras preguntarles explícitamente muestran su deseo de abandonar el consumo de tabaco. Se recopilaron datos sociodemográficos, antecedentes del consumo de tabaco y motivos del deseo de cesar el consumo. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo.ResultadosLa media de edad fue de 45,6 años (desviación estándar±12,0 años). Los varones representaban el 55,9% de la población estudiada. La mayoría (35,2%) tenía estudios por encima del grado secundario. El motivo argumentado para abandonar el tabaquismo por el 63,9% de los varones y el 81,1% de los mayores de 60 años fue la indicación médica; el 60,7% de las mujeres buscaba prevenir enfermedades. El hecho de representar un papel ejemplar para los hijos subyacía en el 31,6% de los fumadores de 31 a 45 años, y los motivos estéticos en el 11,4% de aquellos entre 18 y 30 años.ConclusionesLa indicación médica promueve la voluntad de cesación tabáquica en los varones, mientras que con su decisión las mujeres pretenden representar un papel ejemplar para los hijos, prevenir enfermedades o mejorar su estética. A mayor edad, mayor porcentaje de pacientes que deciden dejar de fumar por indicación médica. El adulto de mediana edad alega querer ser un ejemplo para sus hijos, mientras que los jóvenes actúan movidos por principios estéticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(6): 539-539, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Motivos para dejar de fumar en España en función del sexo y la edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3391</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
