<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91477</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gated myocardial perfusion scintigraphy in children with sickle cell anemia: correlation with echocardiography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The heart is one of the organs affected by sickle cell anemia (SCA). This prospective study has aimed to evaluate myocardial perfusion and left ventricle (LV) function in children with SCA by gated myocardial perfusion scintigraphy (G-MPS) and to compare the results with echocardiographic parameters. Methods. Forty-three patients with SCA were evaluated by G-MPS and echocardiography. Myocardial perfusion and motion with thickening function were analyzed both visually and quantitatively. End-diastolic (EDV), end-systolic volumes (ESV), ejection fraction (EF), lung-to-heart (L/H) ratio were also calculated. Results. None of the patients showed stress perfusion impairment in G-MPS. LV dilatation in 15 patients was observed both by G-MPS and echocardiography. EF values were within normal limits. Correlation between EF values calculated by two methods was not statistically significant. However, LV dilatation detected by both methods and EDV-ESV values in G-MPS were correlated to end-diastolic and end-systolic diameters calculated in echocardiography (p&lt;0.05). M-Mode echocardiography revealed higher myocardial performance index (LV-MPI) in patients with LV dilatation. There was also a significant relationship between LV dilatation and frequent blood transfusions (&gt;5/years) and acute chest syndrome (p&lt;0.05). Conclusion. Myocardial perfusion impairment in children with SCA is not frequently observed. Thus, performing the scintigraphy only in patients with cardiac symptoms should be considered. Since EF values of the children with SCA are not deteriorated in early stages, LV-MPI and LV dilatation should be considered as a significant parameter other than EF or perfusion data(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Unal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balci, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Citirik, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceylan Gunay, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hallioglu, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erdogan, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El corazón es uno de los órganos afectados por la anemia de células falciforme (SCA). El objetivo de este estudio prospectivo es evaluar la perfusión miocárdica y la función del ventrículo izquierdo (LV) en niños con SCA por la gammagrafía de perfusión miocárdica (G-MPS) y comparar los resultados con los hallazgos ecocardiográficos. Métodos. Se evaluaron cuarenta y tres pacientes con SCA mediante estudios de G-MPS y ecocardiografía. La perfusión miocárdica y la función ventricular con la valoración de la motilidad y del engrosamiento se analizaron tanto de forma visual como cuantitativa. Se calcularon el EDV, ESV, EF, y el índice pulmón /corazón (L/H). Resultados. Ninguno de los pacientes presentó deterioro de la perfusión post-estrés en el G-MPS. Se observó dilatación del LV en 15 pacientes, que también estuvo presente en el ecocardio. Los valores de EF se encontraban dentro de los límites normales. La correlación entre los valores de EF, mediante ambos métodos no fueron estadísticamente significativas. Sin embargo la dilatación del ventrículo izquierdo detectados por ambos métodos y los valores de EDV-ESV en la G-MPS se correlacionaron con los diámetros sistólico y diastólico final calculados por la ecocardiografía (p&lt;0,05). La ecocardiografía en modo-M mostró mayor índice de rendimiento miocárdico (LV-MPI) en pacientes con dilatación del LV. También hubo una relación significativa entre la dilatación del ventrículo izquierdo y la frecuencia de transfusiones sanguíneas (&gt; 5/año) y el síndrome torácico agudo (p &lt;0,05). Conclusión. El deterioro de la perfusión miocárdica en los niños con SCA no se observa con frecuencia. Debe considerarse el realizar la gammagrafía sólo en pacientes con síntomas cardíacos. Puesto que los valores de EF de los niños con SCA no se deterioran en las primeras etapas, el LV-MPI y la dilatación del ventrículo izquierdo deberían considerarse como un parámetro significativo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;30(6): 354-359, nov.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91477</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gated-SPECT de Perfusión Miocárdica en Niños con Anemia Falciforme: correlación con ecocardiografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d768^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53211^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
