<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108687</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The International Council of Nurses incidence for the history and socialization of Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The International Council of Nurses (ICN) is a federation of national nurses associations (NNA), created in 1899, by a small group of visionary women, in a milieu of enormous social changes such as industrial revolution and the slavery abolition and with woman´s social rights, including the right for voting, social progressivism and healthcare reform. Against all odds, ICN has survived for over 100 years, due to dedication of three women: Ethel Bedford Fenwick, Lavinia Dock y Agnes Karll who created the very first international health professionals organization. The ICN incidence was very instrumental as nursing was just giving its first steps after being institutionalized as a profession by Florence Nightingale. The ICN diffusion and socialization will also benefit the History of Nursing as a field of study. Being the nurses&#146; voice ICN can make their profession to develop and reach out wider geographical boundaries and to learn better their own profession and the nursing professional identity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oguisso, Taka</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Consejo Internacional de Enfermeras (CIE) es una federación de organizaciones nacionales de enfermería, creada en 1899, por un pequeño grupo de mujeres visionarias en medio a enormes cambios sociales tales como la revolución industrial y la abolición de esclavitud además de la lucha por los derechos de la mujer, el progresivismo social y la reforma de la salud. A pesar de todas las creencias al contrario, el CIE sobrevive por más de 100 años desde que fue fundado básicamente por tres dedicadas mujeres: Ethel Bedford Fenwick, Lavinia Dock y Agnes Karll que crearon la primera organización internacional de profesionales de salud. La incidencia del CIE fue instrumental pues la enfermería estaba dando sus primeros pasos después de la institucionalización de la profesión hecha por Florencia Nightingale. La difusión y socialización del CIE será beneficiosa también para la Historia de la Enfermería, como un campo de estudios. Como portavoz de los enfermeros podrá hacer crecer y alcanzar límites geográficos mucho más amplios para que conozcan mejor su propia profesión y la identidad profesional de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(32): 23-37, ene.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La incidencia del Consejo Internacional de Enfermeras en la historia y socialización de la Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7556^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
