<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121900</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Visceral leishmaniasis in a children´s hospital between 1994 and 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Knowing the incidence of the visceral leishmaniasis in children within our hospital in the last 10 years and comparing it with previous papers. Children and methods. A retrospective study of cases with leishmaniasis between 1993 and June of 2004 in our hospital has been carried out. 18 cases have been obtained, the following features have been collected for them: age, sex, address, personal records, symptoms, physical examination, laboratory testing, diagnosis, treatment and monitoring. Results. The disease incidence was 2-3 cases annually, with the maximum value in 2002; most of them were form Madrid, and only two cases presented animal contact. They were 11 boys and 7 girls, with a range of ages between 4 months and 9 years. Every patient had fever and some of them presented other symptoms such as asthenia and anorexia. The splenomegaly was the principal sign, followed by the pale skin and hepatomegaly. All of them presented anemia and some of them showed low blood platelets, leucopenia and high value of transaminasas and IgG. In every case the parasite could be seen in the bone marrow. 78% of them had positive antileishmania antibodies. The principal drug used within the treatment was the Antimoniato de Meglumina and in just one case Anfotericine B. Conclusions. The leishmaniasis is still a problem in our environment, affecting 1 to 3 years old children because of their immature immunodeficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agüero Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Montes de Neira, E de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la incidencia de leishmaniasis visceral infantil en nuestro Hospital en los últimos 10 años y compararlo con estudios previos publicados. Material y métodos. Se realiza un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los casos de leishmaniasis infantil entre 1993 y junio 2004 en nuestro Hospital. Se obtienen 18 casos de los que recogemos los siguientes datos: edad, sexo, domicilio, antecedentes personales, clínica, exploración, pruebas complementarias, diagnóstico, tratamiento y seguimiento. Resultados. La incidencia de la enfermedad fue de 2-3 casos al año, con un pico máximo en el 2002; la mayoría procedían de Madrid, encontrándose sólo en dos casos antecedentes de interés. En la serie obtenida 11 fueron varones y 7 mujeres, con un rango de edad entre los 4 meses y los 9 años. La fiebre se presentó en todos los pacientes acompañándose de otros síntomas como astenia y anorexia; en la exploración física destacó la esplenomegalia, seguida de la palidez cutánea y hepatomegalia. En los parámetros sanguíneos todos presentaron anemia y en algunos casos otros datos como plaquetopenia, leucopenia, transaminasas e IgG elevadas. En todos los casos fue positivo el aspirado de médula ósea; de éstos un 78% tenía antícuerpos antileishmania positivos. El tratamiento de elección en 17 casos fue antimoniato de meglumina y un caso anfotericina B. Conclusiones. La leishmaniasis continúa siendo un problema en nuestro medio, afectando a niños con edades comprendidas entre 1 y 3 años por la vulnerabilidad de sus sistema inmune y sin tener una historia de contagio aparente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;61(2): 110-113, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121900</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leishmaniasis visceral en un hospital infantil entre 1994 y 2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8072^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8075^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22362^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
