<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68179</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of supply with glutamine on antioxidant system and lipid peroxidation in patients with parenteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the critically ill patient, there is a continuous production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) that need to be neutralized to prevent oxidative stress (OS). Quantitatively speaking, the glutathionesystem (GSH) is the most important anti-oxidant endogenous defense. To increase it, glutamine supplementation has been shown to be effective by protecting against the oxidative damage and reducing the morbimortality. Objective: To assess the effect of adding an alanylglutamine dipeptide to PN on lipid peroxidation lipidica and glutathione metabolism, as well as its relationship with morbidity in critically ill patients. Methods: Determination through spectrophotometry techniques of glutathione peroxidase, glutathione reductase, total glutathione, and maloniladdehyde at admission and after seven days of hospitalization at the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) in 20 patients older than 18 years on parenteral nutrition therapy. Results: The group of patients receiving parenteral nutrition with glutamine supplementation had significant increases in total glutathione (42.35 ± 13 vs 55.29 ±12 &amp;#956;mol/l; p &lt; 0.05) and the enzymatic activity of glutathione peroxidasa (470 ± 195 vs 705 ± 214 &amp;#956;mol/l; p &lt; 0.05) within one week of nutritional therapy, where as the group on conventional parenteral nutrition did not show significant changes of any of the parameters studied(p &gt; 0.05). However, both mortality and ICU stay were not different between the study group, whereas the severity (assessed by the SOFA score) was lower in the group of patients receiving glutamine (SOFA 5 ± 2 vs 8 ±1.8; p &lt; 0.05).Conclusions: Glutamine intake in critically ill patients improves the antioxidant defenses, which leads to lower lipid peroxidation and lower morbidity during admission at the ICU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Planells, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de la Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Torres, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Abúd, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moratalla, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mudarra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abilés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el paciente crítico hay una continua producción de especies reactivas de oxígeno (ERO) que necesitan se neutralizadas para evitar el estrés oxidativo (EO). Entre las defensas antioxidantes endógenas, el sistema glutatión (GSH) es cuantitativamente el más importante, pero en situaciones de estrés severo se encuentra disminuido. Para incrementarlo, la suplementación con glutamina ha demostrado ser efectiva, ejerciendo protección contra el daño oxidativo y reduciendo la morbi-mortalidad. Objetivo: Valorar el efecto de la adición de un dipéptidoal anyl-glutamina a la NP sobre la peroxidación lipídica y el metabolismo del glutatión y su relación con la morbilidad de los pacientes críticos. Métodos: Determinación, mediante técnicas espectrofo-tométricas, de glutatión peroxidasa, glutatión reductasa, glutatión total y malonil aldehído al ingreso y tras siete días de estancia en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) de 20 pacientes mayores de 18 años con tratamiento nutricional parenteral. Resultados: El grupo de pacientes que recibió nutrición parenteral con adición de glutamina experimentó aumentos significativos a la semana de tratamiento nutricional en la concentración del glutatión total (42,35 ± 13 vs 55,29 ± 12 &amp;#956;mol/l; p &lt; 0,05), junto a un incremento de la actividad de la enzima glutatión peroxidasa (470 ± 195 vs 705 ± 214 &amp;#956;mol/l; p &lt; 0,05). En cambio, el grupo con nutrición parenteral convencional no presentó modificaciones significativas en ninguno de los parámetros estudiados (p &gt; 0,05). Sin embargo, tanto la mortalidad como la estancia en UCI no fue diferente para los grupos estudiados, mientras que si se observó una menor gravedad, valorada por e SOFA score, en el grupo de pacientes que recibieron glutamina (SOFA 5 ± 2 vs 8 ± 1,8; p &lt; 0,05).Conclusiones: El aporte de glutamina en pacientes críticos mejora las defensas antioxidantes, lo que repercute en una menor peroxidación lipídica y menor morbilidad durante la estancia en UCI</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(4): 332-339, jul.-ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la suplementación con glutamina sobre el sistema antioxidante y la peroxidación lipídica en pacientes críticos con nutrición parenteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6117^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6122^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
