<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040750</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myocarditis in the child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Myocarditis is an inflammatory process of the myocardium    due to different causes which affect the myocardial    cells, the intersticium and the vascular components.    Its real incidence is unknown because many cases    are not diagnosed. The causes include infectious and noninfectious    agents, but viruses are the most frequent. The    mechanism of the myocardial injury is a complex one and    depends upon the aetiology. The clinical presentation    varies according to the patient&#145;s age, the nutritional status    and the extension of myocardial damage. Clinical spectrum    accounts asymptomatic patients, cardiac arrhythmias,    conduction disturbances, thoracic pain, heart failure,    cardiogenic shock, periferical embolisms, and sudden    death. The electrocardiogram and echocardiography    are important to confirm the diagnosis. The prognosis is    variable and the treatment depends on the way of presentation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saura Hernández, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Clúa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ojeda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La miocarditis es un proceso inflamatorio focal o difuso    del miocardio, debido a múltiples causas que pueden afectar    a la miofibrilla en sí, al intersticio o a sus componentes vasculares.    Su incidencia se desconoce, ya que son muchos los    casos no diagnosticados. Las causas incluyen agentes infecciosos    y no infecciosos, pero, en general, los más frecuentes    son los virus. El mecanismo del daño miocárdico es complejo    y depende de la causa. La presentación clínica también    varía según la edad del paciente, su estado nutricional y la    extensión del daño miocárdico. El espectro clínico abarca    desde pacientes asintomáticos a otros con trastornos del ritmo    cardiaco y/o de la conducción, dolor torácico, insuficiencia    cardiaca, shock cardiogénico, embolismos periféricos y muerte    súbita. Son importantes para reforzar el diagnóstico el electrocardiograma    y la ecocardiografía. El pronóstico es variable    y el tratamiento depende de la forma de presentación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;45(193): 161-169, jul.-sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040750</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miocarditis en el niño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9397^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9397^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9397^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9397</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
