<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99773</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current management of gastric cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gastric cancer is a disease with high incidence and mortality in our population. The prognosis of patients with this disease is closely related to the neoplasm stage at diagnosis, including the following characteristics of the tumor: extension into the gastric wall thickness, spread to locoregional lymph nodes and the ability to generate distant metastases, as described by the TNM classification. For localized tumors characterized only by invasion of mucosa or submucosa at diagnosis, survival at 5 years is between 70 and 95% with exclusive surgical management; however, when extension into the gastric wall is higher and/or there is locoregional nodal involvement, survival decreases to 20-30% at 5 years. Currently, at high-volume centers, the extent of gastrectomy is individualized based on several parameters, which in an increasing number of cases allows a total gastrectomy with D2 lymphadenectomy and preservation of the spleen and pancreas. This improved procedure increases the chance of R0 surgery and improves the relationship between resected and affected lymph nodes, resulting in a decreased risk of the long- term locoregional recurrence. To improve these results, different therapeutic strategies combining chemotherapy or chemoradiotherapy with surgery have been tested. Previously, the Intergroup 0116 clinical trial, published in 2001, which changed clinical practice in the United States, showed that adjuvant chemoradiotherapy improved survival (from 26 to 37 months overall survival) of these patients. In Europe, perioperative chemotherapy has been considered the standard treatment, since the publication of two randomized phase III trials showed an increase at 5 years survival in the group treated with chemotherapy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artajona Rosino, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias de la Vega, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández García, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Murua, Coro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de Liaño, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viúdez Berral, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera García, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer gástrico es un tumor de alta incidencia y mortalidad en nuestro medio, y su pronóstico está íntimamente relacionado con la situación neoplásica al diagnóstico, que incluye su extensión en el grosor de la pared gástrica, sobre los ganglios linfáticos locorregionales y su capacidad de generar metástasis a distancia, extensión basada en la clasificación TNM. En aquellos tumores localizados al diagnóstico, caracterizados por la invasión únicamente de mucosa-submucosa, la supervivencia a 5 años se establece entre el 70 y el 95% con manejo quirúrgico exclusivo, sin embargo, cuando la extensión en la pared es mayor y/o existe afectación ganglionar locorregional, la supervivencia disminuye al 20-30% a 5 años. Actualmente en centros con alto volumen de pacientes, la extensión de la gastrectomía se individualiza en función de varios parámetros, optándose, en cada vez más casos, por la realización de una gastrectomía total con linfadenectomía D2 y preservación esplenopancreática, pues esta aumenta las posibilidades de conseguir una cirugía R0 y mejora la relación entre ganglios resecados y ganglios afectados, lo que se traduce en una disminución del riesgo de recidiva locorregional a largo plazo. Con el objetivo de mejorar estos resultados, se han ensayado distintas estrategias terapéuticas de quimioterapia o quimiorradioterapia asociadas a la cirugía. Entre todas ellas destaca el ensayo 0116 del intergroup, publicado en el 2001, que cambió la práctica clínica asistencial en Estados Unidos, ya que demostró que un tratamiento de quimiorradioterapia tras la cirugía mejoraba la supervivencia (de 26 a 37 meses de mediana) de estos pacientes. En Europa es la quimioterapia perioperatoria el tratamiento estándar habitual, desde que se publicaron dos estudios aleatorizados fase III que demostraron un aumento en la supervivencia a 5 años en el grupo tratado con quimioterapia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;104(3): 134-141, mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual en el tratamiento del cáncer gástrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54677^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54677^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
