<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60886</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heterotopic pregnancy in artificial insemination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of heterotopic pregnancy, which is of interest due to its low incidence and the serious complications that can ensue when diagnosis is delayed. Most of the heterotopic pregnancies described occurred after in vitro fertilization techniques. These pregnancies are less frequent after artificial insemination and are exceptional in spontaneous pregnancies. Our objective is to emphasize the increase in this type of pregnancy in the last few years due to assisted reproduction techniques and to highlight the importance of early diagnosis. The incidence of heterotopic pregnancy is increasing due to the use of assisted reproduction techniques. This entity frequently presents after rupture of the ectopic pregnancy, leading to a gynecological emergency due to maternal bleeding, and requires prompt treatment. Consequently, we stress the importance of diagnosis, which is difficult, in the asymptomatic phase. Furthermore, a high index of suspicion should be maintained in abdominal pain associated with hemoperitoneum in an intrauterine pregnancy obtained after assisted reproduction techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Román Sigler, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aritzeta Iraola, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Verdugo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campelo Martínez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es aportar un caso clínico de gestación heterotópica, interesante por su baja incidencia, y sus graves complicaciones por no diagnosticarse de forma temprana. La mayoría de las gestaciones heterotópicas descritas se producen tras tratamientos con técnicas de fecundación in vitro, menos frecuente tras inseminación artificial y excepcional en gestaciones espontáneas. Nuestro objetivo es resaltar el incremento de este tipo de gestaciones en los últimos años debido a técnicas de reproducción asistida y la importancia de su diagnóstico temprano. La gestación heterotópica está incrementando su incidencia debido a las técnicas de reproducción asistida, su frecuente debut tras la rotura de la gestación ectópica, hace que se convierta en una urgencia ginecológica por el importante sangrado materno que se produce y requiere de una actuación rápida. De ahí, remarcar la importancia de su diagnóstico por otra parte difícil, en fases asintomáticas y su sospecha ante un cuadro de dolor abdominal asociado a hemoperitoneo en una gestación intrauterina conseguida con técnicas de reproducción asistida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(3): 194-197, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60886</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestación heterotópica en inseminación artificial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6617^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
