<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96103</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bispectral index recorded during prehospital cardiopulmonary resuscitation as a predictor of survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To determine the value of the bispectral index (BIS) for predicting survival in patients in cardiorespiratory arrestattended by advanced life support units.Material and methods: One-year prospective observational study of 16 patients in cardiorespiratory arrest in Barcelona who were attended by advanced life support units. The BIS was monitored during prehospital advanced life supportmaneuvers. Results: Basic life support measures were required in the great majority (88%) of cases. The cause of arrest was cardiacrelated in 13 patients and the initial heart rhythm was shockable in 3. Circulation recovered spontaneously in 3 patients,1 of whom died in the hospital. BIS values were lower in patients who recovered circulation spontaneously than in those who did not survive. Patients in cardiorespiratory arrest who received basic life support measures and whose initial rhythm was shockable had lower BIS values.Conclusions: BIS values recorded during prehospital advanced life support maneuvers for cardiorespiratory arrest do not predict survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Fábrega , X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giraldo Sebastià, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona Jiménez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Determinar el valor pronóstico del índice biespectral (BIS) en cuanto a la supervivencia de pacientes con una parada cardiorrespiratoria (PCR) asistidos por unidades de soporte vital avanzado (SVA).Método: Estudio prospectivo observacional durante un año en 16 pacientes que han sufrieron una PCR en Barcelona, que fueron asistidos por unidades de SVA y a los que se les monitorizó los valores del BIS durante todas las maniobras de SVA prehospitalario.Resultados: Se incluyen 18 pacientes. Las PCR fueron presenciadas en el 88% de casos y se les realizó soporte vital básico (SVB) previo a la gran mayoría. La causa fue cardiaca en 13 pacientes y el ritmo inicial fue desfibrilable en 3. Recuperaron circulación espontánea 3 pacientes, de los cuales uno falleció en el hospital y 2 fueron dados de alta con una categoría de perfusión cerebral (CPC) de 1. Los valores BIS fueron inferiores en los pacientes que recuperaron la circulación espontánea que en los que no sobrevivieronpero sin diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Los PCR de etiología cardiaca, a los que se les realizó SVB previo y donde el ritmo inicial fue desfibrilable, tampoco presentaron valores significativamente inferiores del BIS.Conclusiones: Los valores del BIS obtenidos durante las maniobras de SVA no predicen la supervivencia de los PCR prehospitalarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(1): 35-38, feb. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El pronóstico de la supervivencia mediante los valores del índice biespectral obtenidos durante la reanimación cardiopulmonar prehospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10669^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
