<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106053</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of systematic diabetes education in children diagnosed with Diabetes Mellitus type 1 (DM1)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Evaluate the effectiveness of systematic diabetes education in children diagnosed with Diabetes Mellitus type 1 (DM1), in Fuenlabrada University Hospital (Madrid). Methods: A comparative study of two sample groups of children aged 0 to 14 diagnosed with DM1, before and after having been inducted into the diabetes education program. 34 children, admitted with a DM1 diagnosis, both with and without ketoacidosis, and assigned to Fuenlabrada University Hospital were studied. To evaluate the effectiveness of the program, bivariable analysis was undertaken with the objective of finding relationships between systematic diabetes education and the variables. Those variables were; admission days, frequency of visits to the emergency ward due to complications, and permissions to go home and HbA1c at 3 to 6 months after discharge from the hospital. Results: The admission days was reduced 3 days (p&lt; 0.001), the complications within the 6 month after discharge decreased 41,2% and the permissions to go home increased 23,6% (p=0.001). Conclusions: The results of the study suggest the effectiveness of systematic diabetes education (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mena-López, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-de-Andrés, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla-Pérez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Evaluar la efectividad de la educación diabetológica sistematizada en niños que debutan con DM1 en el Hospital Universitario de Fuenlabrada (HUF), Madrid. Metodología: Estudio comparativo entre dos muestras de niños de 0 a 14 años que debutaron con DM1 antes y después de haberse instaurado un programa de educación diabetológica Se estudió a 34 niños adscritos al HUF que ingresaron por debut de DM1. Para evaluar la efectividad del programa se realizaron análisis bivariados con el fin de encontrar relaciones entre la educación diabetológica sistematizada y las variables: días de ingreso, frecuentación a urgencias por complicaciones, permisos domiciliarios y HbA1c a los 3 y 6 meses del alta. Resultados principales: Los días de ingreso se redujeron 3 días (p&lt;0.001), disminuyeron un 41.2% las complicaciones dentro de los 6 meses posteriores al alta (p=0.019) y los permisos domiciliarios aumentaron un 23,6% (p=0.001). Conclusión principal: Los resultados sugieren la efectividad de la educación diabetológica sistematizada en niños que debutan con DM1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(1/2): 18-22, ene.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la educación diabetológica sistematizada en niños que debutan con Diabetes Mellitus tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
