<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92600</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cocaine-induced ischemic colitis in a high-risk patient treated conservatively</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Drug consumption is among the non-occlusive causes of ischemic colitis. We report a case of cocaine-induced ischemic colitis in a 34-year-old man who had undergone sigmoid resection and loop colostomy due to abdominal-pelvic injury 3 months previously. The patient presented with abdominal pain associated with diarrhea and slight transient fever of doubtful etiology and reported intranasal cocaine consumption. He was hemodynamically stable and showed no peritoneal irritation. Traces of blood were found in the colostomy bag. Colonoscopy showed ulcers and necrosis proximal to the stoma. Computed tomography angiography scan showed no abnormalities except filiform inferior mesenteric artery. The symptoms were self-limiting and the patient was discharged 3 days after admission. Subsequently the colostomy was closed without complications. A high degree of suspicion is required in young patients with abdominal pain not identified by conventional methods and a recent history of drug consumption (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roig, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sempere, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir-Labrador, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ferrer, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre las causas no oclusivas de isquemia cólica están las inducidas farmacológicamente. Presentamos un caso de colitis isquémica provocada por consumo de cocaína en un paciente de 34 años de edad con antecedentes de traumatismo abdomino-pélvico tres meses antes, en el que se efectuó resección de sigma y colostomía en asa. Consultó por dolor abdominal asociado a diarrea y febrícula, y refería consumo de cocaína intranasal. Estaba hemodinámicamente estable y sin peritonismo, evidenciándose restos hemáticos en la bolsa de colostomía. Una colonoscopia objetivó úlceras y necrosis proximales al estoma y la angiotomografía no mostró hallazgos patológicos a excepción de una arteria mesentérica inferior filiforme. El cuadro fue autolimitado, y el paciente dado de al tercer día. Más adelante se reconstruyó el tránsito intestinal sin complicaciones. Debe existir un elevado grado de sospecha ante un dolor abdominal no filiado en pacientes jóvenes con antecedentes de consumo reciente de la droga (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(1): 20-23, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colitis isquémica inducida por cocaína en un paciente de riesgo, tratada de forma conservadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30780^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30780^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
