<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103018</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A new familial case of Jackson-Sertoli syndrome. A review of the clinical</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pachyonychia congenita (PC) is a rare keratin disorder which the main clinical sign is onychodystrophy. PC can be classified into two main clinical subtypes: pachyonychia congenita type 1 and 2. The type 2 is associated with mutations in keratin gene: K6b y K17. Steatocystoma multiplex is an uncommon keratin disorder of the pilosebaceous unit characterized by the development of numerous sebum-containing dermal cysts. Mutationsin K17 have been too demonstrated in patients with this entity. We report a family with variable and oligosymptomatic form of pachyonychia congenita and steatocystoma multiplex. The association of both entities according to the Schonfeld classification correspond a new familial case of Jackson-Sertoli syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cammarata-Scalisi, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Flores, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Petrosino, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas de Sotolongo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estéves Guillen, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labrador Chacón, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stock, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La paquioniquia congénita es una alteración infrecuente de la queratina, cuyo principal signo clínico es la onicodistrofia. Puede ser clasificada en dos principales subtipos clínicos: paquioniquia congénita tipo 1 y 2. La tipo 2 esta asociada con la mutación en los genes de queratina: K6b y K17.El esteatocistoma múltiple es una alteración infrecuente de la queratina de la unión pilosebásea caracterizado por el desarrollo de múltiples quistes dérmicos que contienen sebo. La mutación en K17 también se ha demostrado en pacientes con esta entidad. Reportamos una familia con variable y oligosintomática forma de paquioniquia congénita y esteatocistoma múltiple. La asociación de ambas entidades de acuerdo a la clasificación de Schonfeld corresponde un nuevo caso familiar del síndrome de Jackson-Sertoli (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;40(3): 89-93, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un nuevo caso familiar del síndromede Jackson-Sertoli. Revisión de los aspectos clínicos y genéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9451^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52142^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52189</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
