<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164896</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of physical activity in primary health care workers of Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Physical inactivity is the fourth leading risk factor for global mortality, and a significant percentage of the world population does not perform the necessary physical activity for health benefits. Certain professional groups are seen as an example for the general population with whom they interact. Prevalence of physical activity in health workers, one of these reference groups, is mainly unknown. The aim of this study has been to assess the prevalence of physical activity levels in Primary Health Care professionals. Material and methods. A study was conducted on the physical activity levels in Primary Health Care workers who came voluntarily for a medical examination in 2014, and completed the short version of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire activity. Results. A low level of physical activity was reported by 26.5% of those taking part, with 31.5% of the medical group indicating a low level of activity, followed by support staff (28.1%), nurses (24.7%), and finally the administrative staff (19.0%). Conclusions. The physical activity levels of Primary Health Care staff are significantly different from those of the general reference population. The latter has a higher percentage of physical activity of mild to moderate intensity, and below the level of physical activity of high intensity. Although there seems to be a tendency to significantly lower physical activity in other health groups, we do not have sufficiently reliable data to compare them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez San Cirilo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Aragonés, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vizcarro Sanagustín, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La inactividad física es el cuarto factor de riesgo respecto a la mortalidad mundial, y un porcentaje importante de la población mundial no realiza la actividad física necesaria para obtener beneficios para su salud. Determinados grupos profesionales son un ejemplo para la población general con la que interactúan. La prevalencia de actividad física en personal sanitario, uno de estos referentes, es en muchos casos desconocida. Nuestro objetivo ha sido identificar la prevalencia de los niveles de actividad física en profesionales sanitarios del ámbito de la atención primaria. Material y métodos. Se determinaron los niveles de actividad física en aquellos individuos del ámbito de la atención primaria que acudieron voluntariamente a efectuar reconocimiento médico durante el año 2014, mediante la aplicación de la versión corta del Cuestionario internacional de actividad física. Resultados. Un 26,5% de los individuos refirió un grado bajo de actividad física. El 31,5% de individuos del colectivo médico manifestó un nivel de actividad bajo, seguido del personal auxiliar (28,1%), el personal de enfermería (24,7%) y finalmente el personal de administración (19,0%). Conclusiones. Los niveles de actividad física del personal de atención primaria son sensiblemente distintos a los de la población general de referencia. En esta, el porcentaje de actividad física de intensidad leve y moderada es superior, siendo el nivel de actividad física de elevada intensidad inferior. Aunque parece existir una tendencia a valores sensiblemente inferiores de actividad física en otros colectivos sanitarios, no disponemos de datos suficientemente fiables para poder compararlos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(5): 352-357, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de actividad física en profesionales de atención primaria de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
