<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151707</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The minority&#146;s perspective: Stereotypes and emotions between immigrant groups</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study focused on the minority&#146;s perspective, and analyzes the assessments that the three immigrant groups most representative in Spain maintain about each other on the variables defended by the stereotype content model (SCM). Four hundred and nine immigrants participated assessing the other two groups: Moroccan immigrants were assessed by Ecuadorians (EM group, N = 66) and Romanians (RM, N = 76); Romanians were assessed by Ecuadorians (ER, N = 65) and Moroccans (MR, N = 62); and Ecuadorians were assessed by Romanians (RE, N = 80) and Moroccans (ME, N = 60). All participants reported how they perceived the specific group in morality, sociability, and competence, the extent in which they experienced emotions of admiration, contempt, envy and pity, and their perception of status and intergroup competition. Results with minority groups supported most of the SCM predictions already confirmed with majority members. The most valued group in status and stereotypes was the Ecuadorian group (coinciding with the majority&#146;s perception), who also aroused more admiration. These findings are discussed by addressing the applicability of the SCM when analyzing intergroup relations among minority groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Rodríguez, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se centra en la perspectiva de la minoría, y analiza las evaluaciones que los tres grupos inmigrantes más representativos en España mantienen entre sí a partir de las variables contempladas en el modelo del contenido de los estereotipos (MCE). Participaron 409 inmigrantes, que evaluaron a los otros dos grupos: los inmigrantes marroquíes fueron evaluados por ecuatorianos (grupo EM, N = 66) y rumanos (RM, N = 76); los inmigrantes rumanos por ecuatorianos (ER, N = 65) y marroquíes (MR, N = 62); y los inmigrantes ecuatorianos por rumanos (RE, N = 80) y marroquíes (ME, N = 60). Todos ellos indicaron cómo percibían al grupo correspondiente en moralidad, sociabilidad y competencia, en qué grado experimentaban las emociones de admiración, desprecio, envidia y compasión, así como su percepción de estatus y competición exogrupal. Los resultados con grupos minoritarios apoyan, en general, las predicciones del MCE ya confirmadas con miembros de grupos mayoritarios. El grupo más valorado en estatus y estereotipos fue el ecuatoriano (coincidiendo con las valoraciones de la mayoría), el cual también despertaba más admiración. Los resultados se discuten abordando la aplicabilidad del MCE para analizar las relaciones entre grupos minoritarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(2): 535-544, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La perspectiva de la minoría: estereotipos y emociones entre grupos inmigrantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12261^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
