<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125166</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous Manifestations in Children with Diabetes Mellitus and Obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity and diabetes are chronic diseases that affect people all over the world, and their incidence is increasing in both children and adults. Clinically, they affect a number of organs, including the skin. The cutaneous manifestations caused or aggravated by obesity and diabetes are varied and usually bear some relation to the time that has elapsed since the onset of the disease. They include soft fibromas, acanthosis nigricans, striae, xerosis, keratosis pilaris, plantar hyperkeratosis, fungal and bacterial skin infections, granuloma annulare, necrobiosis lipoidica, psoriasis, and atopic dermatitis. In this review article we present the skin changes found in children with diabetes mellitus and obesity and related syndromes and highlight the importance of the skin as a tool for establishing clinical suspicion and early diagnosis of systemic disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Pradilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baselga Torres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad y la diabetes son 2 enfermedades crónicas de distribución mundial, de incidencia en aumento tanto en niños como en adultos. Clínicamente se caracteriza por comprometer distintos órganos, entre ellos la piel. Las manifestaciones cutáneas secundarias o agravadas por la obesidad y la diabetes son variadas, y en su mayoría están relacionadas con el tiempo de evolución. Entre ellas se incluyen: fibromas laxos, acantosis nigricans, estrías, xerosis, queratosis pilar, hiperqueratosis plantar, infecciones cutáneas por hongos y bacterias, granuloma anular, necrobiosis lipoidea, psoriasis y dermatitis atópica, entre otros. En esta revisión presentamos los hallazgos cutáneos en niños con estas 2 enfermedades; como también en los síndromes relacionados, recordando la importancia de la piel como herramienta para la sospecha clínica y el diagnóstico temprano de enfermedades sistémicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(6): 546-557, jul.-ago. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones cutáneas en niños con diabetes mellitus y obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54015^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
