<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71991</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The developments and applications in human biotechnology make us face deep social dilemas, social and ethical, that are associated to the possibility of altering our evolutionary and cultural development, thereby renouncing to principle of Humanity. From a sociological perspective, this text reflects on this matters taking into account how its past and present has shaped a specific operational matrix that is projected towards the future. We shall offer all the public perceptions held on their possibilities in Spain and in the European nations as every advance in scientific and technological matters must take into account the opinion of the citizenry. Finally, there are some final reflections that rather than close the debate leave some questions unanswered. The future should be constructed through dialogue and consensus in a matter of such importance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Morales, M. Rosario H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los desarrollos y aplicaciones en biotecnología humana nos enfrentan a profundos dilemas sociales, éticos y sociales, vinculados a la posibilidad de alterar nuestro desarrollo evolutivo y cultural, renunciando al principio de Humanidad. En este texto, desde una perspectiva sociológica, se reflexiona sobre estas cuestiones presentando como su parado y presente han conformado una determinada matriz operativa que se proyecta hacia el futuro. Ofreceremos las percepciones públicas que en España y en los países europeos. Se tiene sobre sus posibilidades, puesto que todo avance en al materia científico-tecnológica debe tener en consideración la opinión de la ciudadanía. Para finalizar se hacen unas reflexiones finales que, más que cerrar el debate, dejan abiertos interrogantes, pues ante un tema de tanta envergadura el futuro debería ser fruto del diálogo y del consenso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(26): 249-280, ene.-jun. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71991</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
