<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122058</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scientific communication (XI). Basic knowledge to develop a scientific paper (6): The ethics of biomedical publication</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Besides methodologically correct, biomedical research must be ethically good, and it must meet the requirements of the four principles of bioethics: non-maleficence, justice, autonomy and beneficence. We start from the premise that "everything that is not correct from a scientific point of view is ethically unacceptable" although it is true that "not all the right things from a scientific point of view is acceptable from an ethical point of view". The main ethical aspects of the most important scientific publications concern authorship, originality, the peer review process, publication bias, good clinical practice in research, scientific misconduct and conflicts of interest (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Arroyo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aleixandre-Benavent, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Además de metodológicamente correcta, la investigación biomédica tiene que ser éticamente buena, y para ello ha de cumplir con los requisitos exigidos por los cuatro principios de la bioética: no maleficencia, justicia, autonomía y beneficencia. Partimos de la premisa de que «todo lo que no es correcto desde el punto de vista científico es éticamente inaceptable», aunque bien es cierto que «no todo lo correcto desde el punto de vista científico es aceptable desde el punto de vista ético». Los principales aspectos éticos de las publicaciones científicas más relevantes tienen que ver con la autoría, la originalidad, el proceso de revisión por pares, el sesgo de publicación, las buenas prácticas clínicas en la investigación, la mala conducta científica y los conflictos de intereses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(4): e101-e107, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comunicación científica (XI). Conocimientos básicos para elaborar un artículo científico (6): La ética de la publicación biomédica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54358^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22412</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
