<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90071</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis, treatment and prevention of acute otitis media</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute otitis media (AOM) is the most frequent diagnosis in the primary care pediatrician visits and the main reason for the prescription of antibiotics. The world prevalence of the AOM is high, especially during the early childhood. Approximately of every five upper respiratory tract infection one is complicated by an AOM episode. The incidence peak occurs between 6-12 months old. Most of the children suffer at least of one episode before they begin school. A third part develops recurrent acute otitis media (AOMr). Even though very little AOM&#146;s episodes produce serious complications, such as mastoiditis and meningitis, many others can produce hearing loss caused by the persistent presence of fluid in the middle ear. This hypoacusia intermittent or chronic can cause learning disabilities and subsequent problems in the acquisition of language skills (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Renales Toboso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés-Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La otitis media aguda (OMA) es el diagnóstico más frecuente en la consulta de pediatría de atención primaria y motivo habitual de prescripción de antibióticos. La prevalencia mundial de la otitis media es elevada, sobre todo durante la primera infancia. De cada cinco infecciones respiratorias de las vías altas aproximadamente una se complica con un episodio de OMA. El pico de incidencia se produce entre los 6 y los 12 meses. La mayoría de los niños padecen al menos un episodio antes de la edad escolar, y un tercio de ellos desarrolla una OMA recurrente. Aunque pocos episodios de OMA producen complicaciones graves, como mastoiditis y meningitis, muchos otros pueden provocar una disminución de la audición secundaria, debido a la persistencia de líquido en el oído medio. Esta hipoacusia, intermitente o crónica, puede dar lugar a trastornos del aprendizaje y a problemas en el desarrollo del lenguaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(4): 151-155, abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico, tratamiento y prevención de la otitis media aguda en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27801</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35368^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5162^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31428^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12556</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19022^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37552</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
