<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72494</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low bone mineral density and other risk factors in prepubertal children with fracture of the distal forearm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To investigate the relationship between bone mineral density (BMD), age, sex, anthropometric measurements, dietary calcium intake and daily physical activity, in prepubertal children with distal forearm fracture (DFF). Methods: 160 children (80 males, 80 females) 3&#150;10 years of age with DFF; control group of 160 children (age-sex matched) were studied. Age, sex, weight, height, tricipital skin fold thickness (TS), body mass index, daily calcium intake, and level of physical activity (extra-school physical exercise: low &lt;1hour/day, high &gt;1hour/day) registered. BMD assessed by peripheral DXA densitometer. Results: Most fractures were caused by mild-moderate precipitating trauma by accidental fall (85.6%), with radius fracture in most cases (87.5%). BMI was higher in patients (19.14kg/m2±3.50 vs. 17.46kg/m2±2.67; p&lt;0.0001). TS thickness was similar in both groups (20.28mm±8.24 vs. 19.61mm±6.60; p&gt;0.05). Physical activity was lower in study group (extra-school physical activity &gt;1h: 21.25% vs. 46.87%; p&lt;0.001). Daily calcium intake was not associated with DFF incidence (918.75mg/day±338.04 vs. 886.13mg/day±382.77; p&gt;0.05). BMD was lower in fractured children (0.2591g/cm2±0.0413 vs. 0.2801g/cm2±0.0300; p&lt;0.0001). Summary: Our results suggest that significantly reduced bone mineral density, overweight and low physical activity are potential risk factors for fracture of the distal forearm, whilst low dietary intakes of calcium do not seem to be associated. The current epidemic of infantile overweight might explain the increased incidence of fractures of the distal forearm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas López, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barco Gálvez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Salinas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delange Segura, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar la relación entre densidad mineral ósea (DMO), edad, sexo, medidas antropométricas, ingesta dietética de calcio y actividad física diaria en niños prepúberes con fractura de antebrazo distal (FAD). Material y métodos: Ciento sesenta niños (80 varones y 80 mujeres) de 3 a 10 años de edad con FAD y grupo control de 160 niños (pareados por edad y sexo). Se documentaron edad, sexo, peso, talla, pliegue tricipital (PT), índice de masa corporal (IMC), ingesta diaria de calcio y nivel de actividad física (ejercicio físico extraescolar: bajo si &lt;1h/día, alto si &gt;1h/día). La DMO se evaluó por densitómetro periférico DXA. Resultados: El trauma por precipitación leve-moderado (85,6%) fue el causante de la mayoría de las fracturas (fractura del radio en la mayoría de ellas [87,5%]). El IMC fue mayor en los pacientes (19,14kg/m2±3,50 versus 17,46kg/m2±2,67; p&lt;0,0001). El grosor del PT fue similar en ambos grupos (20,28mm±8,24 versus 19,61mm±6,60; p&gt;0,05). La actividad física estaba disminuida en el grupo de fracturados (actividad física extraescolar &gt;1h: el 21,25 versus el 46,87%; p&lt; 0,001). La ingesta diaria de calcio no estuvo asociada con mayor incidencia de FAD (918,75mg/día±338,04 versus 886,13mg/día±382,77; p&gt;0,05). La DMO fue menor en los fracturados (0,2591g/cm2±0,0413 versus 0,2801g/cm2±0,0300; p&lt;0,0001). Discusión: Una significativa reducción de la DMO, el sobrepeso y la escasa actividad física son factores de riesgo potencial para la FAD; la escasa ingesta dietética de calcio no se encuentra asociada. Las intervenciones en el estilo de vida pueden contribuir a reducir el riesgo de FAD en la infancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(5): 383-390, nov. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72494</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disminución de la densidad mineral ósea y otros factores de riesgo en niños prepuberales con fractura del antebrazo distal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23096</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5677^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
