<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048791</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pure alexia secondary to progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy as first manifestation of HIV infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Pure alexia, or alexia without agraphia, is usually caused by disconnection between the gyrus angularis and visual areas of both hemispheres. Cerebrovascular disease is the most frequent cause of this syndrome.         Clinical case: We report the first case of a patient with pure alexia secondary to progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) as the first manifestation of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection. Polymerase chain reaction in cerebrospinal fluid was positive for JC virus. Despite favorable immunological and virological response to highly active antiretroviral therapy, neurological symptoms and demyelinating lesions progressed during the first months, and right homonyous hemianopsia, acalculia, and color anomia were noted. In magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) demyelinating lesions involved white matter of both occipital lobes, with left predominance, forceps major and splenium of the corpus callosum, together with white matter of the left temporal lobe and both hippocampal regions. During the following months, coinciding cidofovir treatment, the patient had partial clinical improvement, but neurological deficits persisted. The size of MRI lesions significantly improved.         Conclusions: PML is frequently the first manifestation of AIDS (acquired immunodeficiency syndrome). It should be considered as a possible diagnosis of pure alexia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quereda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La alexia pura, o alexia sin agrafia, es debida generalmente a la lesión de las fibras que conectan las áreas visuales de ambos hemisferios con el giro angular del hemisferio dominante. La causa más frecuente de este síndrome es la patología cerebrovascular.        Caso clínico. Presentamos el primer caso de alexia pura secundaria a leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva (LMP) que constituyó la primera manifestación de la infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). La reacción en cadena de la polimerasa para virus JC en líquido cefalorraquídeo fue positiva. A pesar de una buena respuesta virológica e inmunológica con terapia antirretrovírica de gran actividad, los síntomas y las lesiones progresaron durante los primeros meses, asociando hemianopsia homónima derecha, anomia para los colores y acalculia. En la resonancia magnética (RM) las lesiones desmielinizantes afectaron a sustancia blanca de ambos lóbulos occipitales, predominando en el lado izquierdo, fórceps mayor y esplenio del cuerpo calloso, así como a sustancia blanca de lóbulo temporal izquierdo y ambas regiones de hipocampo. En los meses siguientes, coincidiendo con tratamiento con cidofovir, el paciente mejoró clínica mente de forma parcial, aunque persistieron los mismos déficit neurológicos. El tamaño de las lesiones en RM disminuyó de forma significativa.        Conclusiones. La LMP con relativa frecuencia constituye la primera manifestación de sida (síndrome de la inmunodeficiencia adquirida) y debe incluirse en el diagnóstico diferencial de la alexia sin agrafia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(4): 213-217, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alexia pura secundaria a leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva como presentación de la infección por VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31867^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3616^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3616^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11184^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34320^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
