<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82771</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of iron in the interaction between host and pathogen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Iron is essential for both pathogenic microbes and their host. Iron status may influence the occurrence and outcome of infections. For many microorganisms, iron is essential for growth, survival, and synthesis of virulence factors. However, because circulating iron is mostly transported bound to proteins and the level of free serum iron is therefore very low, some pathogens have developed complex systems to acquire iron efficiently. Understanding these systems is essential in the design of pharmaceutical agents and vaccines targeting pathogens with iron-linked virulence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>del Castillo-Rueda, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Khosravi-Shahi,  Parham</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hierro participa en la respuesta a la infección de tal forma que su déficit puede impedir o dificultar el desarrollo de patógenos y su exceso favorecer las infecciones o su gravedad. El hierro es esencial para el crecimiento, supervivencia y virulencia de microorganismos, y como su nivel en los líquidos biológicos es muy bajo, algunos patógenos han desarrollado complejos mecanismos para adquirirlo de forma eficiente. Es esencial comprender el funcionamiento de estos mecanismos para el diseño de nuevos fármacos y vacunas contra estos patógenos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);134(10): 452-456, abr. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel del hierro en la interacción entre el huésped y el patógeno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32960^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27832^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52891^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52891^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
