<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136488</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atrial Flutter: an Update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Invasive electrophysiologic studies have changed the clinical outlook for patients with atrial flutter. Recognition of the reentrant circuit responsible for typical atrial flutter has led to the development of catheter ablation techniques that can prevent recurrence in &gt;90% of cases. In addition, general understanding of atrial tachycardias has changed radically, such that ECG-based classifications are now obsolete. Atypical reentrant circuits associated with surgical scars or fibrotic areas in either atrium, which are indistinguishable from focal tachycardias on ECG, have been identified. These circuits also seem amenable to treatment by ablation. Recently, a new type of reentrant tachycardia that could be problematic in the future has emerged in patients who have undergone extensive left atrial ablation for the treatment of atrial fibrillation. These atypical circuits can be characterized using the mapping and entrainment techniques initially developed for typical flutter. In these cases, electroanatomical mapping, involving the construction of a virtual anatomical model of the atria, is extremely helpful. Despite the success of ablation, long-term prognosis is frequently overshadowed by the appearance of atrial fibrillation, which suggests that flutter and fibrillation share a common arrhythmogenic origin that is not modified by cavotricuspid isthmus ablation. In contrast with our clear electrophysiologic understanding of atrial flutter, little is known about the natural history of the condition because the literature has traditionally grouped patients with flutter and fibrillation together. Consequently, the complex relationship between the two arrhythmias has still to be clearly delineated. Primary prevention and preventing the development of atrial fibrillation after ablation remain outstanding clinical challenges (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Cosío, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Ambrosio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magalhaes, Ana P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Awamleh, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios electrofisiológicos invasivos han cambiado la perspectiva clínica de los pacientes con flúter auricular. El conocimiento de la estructura del circuito de flúter típico ha permitido desarrollar técnicas de ablación con catéter que eliminan las recidivas en &gt; 90% de los casos. También ha cambiado el concepto global de las taquicardias auriculares, lo que ha hecho obsoletas las clasificaciones basadas en el electrocardiograma. Se han demostrado circuitos reentrantes atípicos basados en cicatrices quirúrgicas o en zonas fibróticas en ambas aurículas, que son también asequibles a tratamiento por ablación y que en el electrocardiograma son indistinguibles de una taquicardia focal. La ablación amplia de la aurícula izquierda para el tratamiento de la fibrilación auricular está dando lugar a un nuevo tipo de taquicardias reentrantes que puede ser problemático en el futuro. Las técnicas de mapeo y encarrilamiento de los circuitos descritas inicialmente en el flúter permiten definir estos circuitos. El mapeo electroanatómico, que construye moldes anatómicos virtuales de las aurículas, es de gran ayuda en estos casos. A pesar del éxito de la ablación, el pronóstico a largo plazo se ensombrece con frecuencia por la aparición de fibrilación auricular, lo que indica que hay un sustrato arritmogénico común al flúter y la fibrilación, que la ablación del istmo cavotricuspídeo no cambia. En contraste con la clara definición electrofisiológica, hay escasa información sobre el curso clínico del flúter, ya que tradicionalmente la bibliografía se refiere a grupos de «flúter y fibrilación auricular» y las complejas relaciones entre ambas arritmias quedan aún por revelar claramente. La prevención primaria y la prevención de la aparición de fibrilación auricular tras la ablación son retos pendientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(8): 816-831, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Flúter auricular: perspectiva clínica actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1288^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1288^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1288^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1288^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
