<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135318</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence-based nutritional support</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When considering initiation of artificial nutritional support the choice of route of access is determined by the possibility of using the digestive tract safely and effectively. In many patients this decision is problem free. However, there are some situations in which the concept of "usable intestine" is not clear, leading to controversy. Numerous clinical trials have compared the two modalities of artificial nutrition, but unfortunately there are no large prospective randomized trials that provide an adequate level of evidence. In an attempt to meet this need and to extract valid conclusions from the data reported in previous prospective randomized trials, several meta-analyses comparing the use of enteral nutrition (EN) and parenteral nutrition (PN) have been performed. Although there are some discrepancies, the various meta-analyses performed tend to conclude that there are no differences in mortality between EN and PN while EN is associated with a lower risk of infectious complications, especially when initiated early, and that the patients who benefit most from nutritional intervention are those with malnutrition. Because of the poor methodological quality of many of the studies included and their wide heterogeneity, the results should be interpreted with caution. For a sufficient level of evidence to become available, prospective randomized trials with a sufficient number of patients should be performed in specific diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Enterría, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Faedo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laborda González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cuando se plantea el inicio de un soporte nutricional artificial, la elección de la vía de acceso viene determinada por la posibilidad de utilizar, con seguridad y eficacia, el tracto digestivo. La decisión en muchos casos no presenta problemas. Sin embargo, hay situaciones en las que el concepto de "intestino utilizable" no está claro, y en estas circunstancias es cuando se plantea la controversia. Son numerosos los estudios clínicos realizados que comparan las 2 modalidades de nutrición artificial, pero desgraciadamente no existen grandes estudios prospectivos aleatorizados que aporten un nivel de evidencia adecuado. En un intento de obviar esta carencia y extraer conclusiones válidas de los datos aportados en estudios prospectivos aleatorizados previos se han realizado varios metaanálisis en que se compara el uso de la nutrición parenteral y la enteral. Con varias discrepancias, los diversos metaanálisis realizados concluyen que no existen diferencias en la mortalidad cuando se compara la nutrición parenteral y la enteral, mientras que la segunda se asocia con un menor riesgo de presentar complicaciones infecciosas, sobre todo si se inicia de manera temprana; los pacientes malnutridos son los que más se benefician de la intervención nutricional. Los resultados se deben interpretar con cautela debido a la baja calidad metodológica de muchos de los estudios incluidos y a la gran heterogeneidad existente. Se hace necesario disponer de estudios prospectivos aleatorizados con el suficiente número de pacientes con enfermedades concretas que permitan disponer en un futuro de un adecuado nivel de evidencia científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(supl.2): 41-46, mayo 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Soporte nutricional basado en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7438^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32830^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
