<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043878</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Key words analysis in the publications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The specific scientific documentation retrieval in Physiotherapy is still a hard job. There are no specific databases, searchers do not offer exhaustive results, the most distributed spanish journals are not indexed in important databases and the specific terminology is not even registered. Perhaps one of the problems for the document retrieval is consequence of the identification of these articles. The objective of this research is to analyse the identification of articles, by keywords, to determine which descriptors are used by the authors and to check if they are registered or not in the list of the "Medical Subject Heading" (MeSH), for that, the publications studied are: "Fisioterapia" and "Revista Iberoamericana de Fisioterapia y Kinesología". Methodology: Compilation of keywords in english from the primary documents, between the years 2000 and 2003, and check if they belong to MeSH. For registering and analysing the key words the authors have used the program ACCESS 2000 and the statistical program SPSS version 11.5. Results: The 59,1 % of the key words from the journal "Fisioterapia" and the 56,1 % from the publication "Revista Iberoamericana de Fisioterapia y Kinesología" do not belong to the thesaurus MeSH. Conclusions: There are a lot of articles with descriptors that do not belong to the MeSH. The authors identify the articles on the basis of their contents. In the Physiotherapy discipline exist especific key words not registered in the MeSH. The multitude of special fields in Physiotherapy, the lack of analysis and recording of the terminology, carry the difficulty in the identification and document retrieval</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zapico Alonso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Apolo Arenas, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farrona Carretero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Mata, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La recuperación de documentación científica específica de Fisioterapia sigue siendo una tarea difícil. No existen bases de datos específicas, los buscadores te ofrecen resultados poco exhaustivos, las revistas españolas de mayor difusión no están indizadas en bases de datos relevantes y la terminología específica ni siquiera está registrada. Quizás uno de los problemas para la recuperación de documentos sea consecuencia de la identificación de esos artículos. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la identificación de los artículos, mediante las palabras clave, para determinar cuáles son los descriptores utilizados por los autores y comprobar si están registradas o no en la lista del "Medical Subject Heading" (MeSH), para ello se estudian las publicaciones: Fisioterapia y la Revista Iberoamericana de Fisioterapia y Kinesiología. Metodología: Recopilación de las palabras clave en inglés desde el documento primario en el periodo comprendido entre los años 2000-2003 y comprobar si pertenecen al MeSH. Para su registro y análisis se ha utilizado el programa ACCESS 2000 y el programa estadístico SPSS versión 11.5. Resultados: El 59,1 % de las palabras clave de la revista Fisioterapia y el 56,1 % de la Revista iberoamericana de Fisioterapia y Kinesiología no pertenecen al tesauro MeSH. Conclusiones: Hay un gran número de artículos con descriptores no pertenecientes al MeSH. La identificación de los artículos la realizan los autores en base al contenido. Existen palabras clave específicas de la disciplina de Fisioterapia que no se registran en el MeSH. El gran número de especialidades en fisioterapia, la falta del análisis y registro de la terminología, conllevan la dificultad en la identificación y recuperación de los documentos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);8(2): 59-69, jul. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043878</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las palabras clave de las publicaciones Fisioterapia y Revista Iberoamericana de Fisioterapia y Kinesiología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d46^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28994^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
