<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054626</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A descriptive study of childhood epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse the epidemiological characteristics and the relative distribution of the different types of epilepsy        and epileptic syndromes in the childhood population. Patients and methods.We reviewed the medical histories of 365 patients        (192 males and 173 females) with epilepsy. Epidemiological and clinical data were collected, together with information from        complementary examinations. The diagnostic criteria applied were those of the International League Against Epilepsy (ILAE).        Results. The mean age at diagnosis was 5.9 years and the mean follow-up time was 4.6 years. A personal and/or familial        history of febrile convulsions was reported in 13.4% of cases and 23.5% had a history of epilepsy in the family. The aetiology        was idiopathic in 166 cases (45.5%), cryptogenic in 106 (29%) and symptomatic in 93 (25.5%). Of the total number of        patients, 52.9% reported having focal epilepsies, they were generalised in 43.6% and 3.5% had epilepsies with an undetermined        localisation. In each age group the most common epileptic syndromes were: in infants, West&#146;s syndrome (34.1%)        and symptomatic focal epilepsies (24.4%); in preschoolers, idiopathic focal (21.3%) or cryptogenic (17.7%) and myoclonicastatic        epilepsies (12.8%); in school-age children, idiopathic focal epilepsies (27.3%) and absences (24.5%); and in teenagers,        cryptogenic (26.6%) and idiopathic focal epilepsies (23.4%). Conclusions. The initial distinction between epileptic syndromes        is usually difficult to establish and developmental monitoring is essential for reaching a definitive diagnosis and a classification        of their syndromes. Age appears to be a determining factor in the clinical expression of the different types of childhood        epilepsy, and the relative distribution of the epileptic syndromes is different in each age group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yoldi-Petri, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durá-Travé, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallinas-Victoriano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las características epidemiológicas y la distribución relativa de los distintos tipos de epilepsias        y síndromes epilépticos en la población infantil. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron las historias clínicas de 365 pacientes (192        varones y 173 mujeres) con epilepsia. Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, clínicos y exámenes complementarios. Los criterios        diagnósticos aplicados fueron los de la Liga Internacional contra la Epilepsia (ILAE). Resultados. La edad media al        diagnóstico era de 5,9 años, y el tiempo medio de seguimiento de 4,6 años. El 13,4% refería antecedentes personales y/o familiares        de convulsiones febriles, y el 23,5% de epilepsia familiar. La etiología era idiopática en 166 casos (45,5%), criptogénica        en 106 (29%) y sintomática en 93 (25,5%). El 52,9% de los pacientes presentaba epilepsias focales, el 43,6% generalizadas        y el 3,5% de localización indeterminada. En los lactantes, el síndrome de West (34,1%) y las epilepsias focales sintomáticas        (24,4%) eran los síndromes epilépticos más prevalentes; en los preescolares, las epilepsias focales idiopáticas (21,3%) o        criptogénicas (17,7%) y la epilepsia astatomioclónica (12,8%); en los escolares, las epilepsias focales idiopáticas (27,3%)        y las ausencias (24,5%); y en los adolescentes, las epilepsias focales criptogénicas (26,6%) y las epilepsias focales idiopáticas        (23,4%). Conclusiones. La diferenciación inicial de los síndromes epilépticos suele ser difícil de establecer, y el control        evolutivo es decisivo para el diagnóstico definitivo y la clasificación sindrómica. La edad parece representar un factor determinante        en la expresión clínica de los distintos tipos de epilepsia infantil, y la distribución relativa de los síndromes epilépticos        es diferente en cada grupo de edad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(12): 720-724, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de la epilepsia infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
