<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101023</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening distress in cáncer patients using the hospital anxiety and depression scale (HADS</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract: The most commonly used distress screening questionnaire in oncology patients is the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). The aim of this study was to determine the optimal cut-off score to discriminate patients with probable significant clinical symptomatology (anxiety and depression) in a sample of oncology out-patients. The DSM-IV psychiatric diagnosis interview was used as the external criteria. A total of 234 oncology out-patients were assessed using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Disorders (SCID-I) and the HADS. An exploratory factorial analysis with varimax rotation was carried out. The cut-off scores were calculated by the ROC curve. Results show good internal reliability for each subscale, the alpha coefficient was 0,82 for the anxiety subscale, and 0,84 for the depression subscale. Thirty one point two percent of the patients met clinical criteria for psychiatric diagnoses. According to the sensitivity and specificity rates which were approximately 70%, the optimal cut-off score for screening probable significant clinical symptomatology was a score of 8 for the anxiety subscale, and a cut-off score of 4 for the depression subscale. A score of 10 or more on HADS total scale resulted useful for screening significant distress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Pérez, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salamero Baró, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Moncayo, Francisco Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa Requena, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen: Una de las pruebas de cribado más utilizadas para detectar malestar emocional en pacientes oncológicos ha sido la escala de Ansiedad y Depresión Hospitalaria (HADS). El objetivo de este estudio fue calcular los puntos de corte óptimos que permitan detectar probable sintomatología (ansiedad y depresión) clínicamente significativa en pacientes oncológicos, utilizando como criterio externo la entrevista psiquiátrica según criterios DSM-IV. Evaluamos a un total de 234 pacientes oncológicos ambulatorios con la entrevista psiquiátrica para el DSM-IV (SCID-I) y con el HADS. Se realiza un análisis factorial exploratorio con rotación varimax. Los puntos de corte son hallados mediante la curva de ROC. Los índices de fiabilidad para cada subescala son adecuados, el coeficiente alfa en la subescala de ansiedad fue de 0,82 y en la subescala de depresión de 0,84. El 31,2% de pacientes cumplen criterios clínicos para el diagnóstico de trastorno psiquiátrico. Con unos índices de sensibilidad y especificidad de alrededor del 70% el punto de corte optimo para detectar probable sintomatología clínicamente significativa fue una puntuación 8 en la subescala de ansiedad y una puntuación de 4 en la subescala de depresión. Una puntuación total en el HADS mayor o igual a 10 permite discriminar malestar emocional clínicamente significativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;15(2/3): 217-229, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101023</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discriminación del malestar emocional en pacientes oncológicos utilizando la escala de ansiedad y depresión hospitalaria (HADS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
