<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143675</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of training and detraining on glycosylated haemoglobin, glycaemia and lipid profile in type-II diabetics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: the aim of the present study was to determine the effect of training and the consequences of detraining, comparing an aerobic training (AT) protocol with a resistance training (RT) in people with type-II Diabetes Mellitus (DMII). Methods: a total of 30 individuals participated in the study, with ages ranging from 45 to 50 years, all diagnosed with DMII and not currently receiving pharmacological treatment. Participants were divided at random into an AT group (65% of their maximum aerobic capacity) and a RT group (1 x 2 x 3 protocol at 65% of 1RM). Measurements were taken of weight, body mass index, total cholesterol, HDL-C, LDL-C, triglycerides, glycaemia in a fasted state and glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1C) at the beginning and at the end of the 6-week training period, and after a further 6 weeks of detraining. Results: the results show that both physical training protocols are capable of inducing significant modifications in lipid profile, glycaemia in a fasted state and levels of HbA1C; however, after stopping the training programme only the RT group maintained the benefits of the reduction in LDL-C, HbA1C and the increase in HDL-C. Conclusions: resistance exercise in individuals with DMII has an important influence on health and their effects could be maintained even if the training program is interrupted short-term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos-Lozano, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Urra, Patricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristi-Montero, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuing Farias, Tuillang</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el propósito del presente estudio fue determinar el efecto del entrenamiento y las consecuencias del desentrenamiento comparando un protocolo de entrenamiento aeróbico (E-Aer) y otro de sobrecarga (E-Sob). Métodos: participaron 30 personas entre 45-50 años de edad con diagnóstico de diabetes mellitus tipo II (DMII) sin tratamiento farmacológico. Fueron aleatorizados a un grupo de E-Aer (65% de su esfuerzo máximo) o a un grupo de E-Sob (protocolo 1  x  2  x  3 al 65% de 1RM). Se midió el peso, el índice de masa corporal, el colesterol total, HDL-C, LDL-C, triglicéridos, glucemia en ayuno y la hemoglobina glucosilada (HbA1C) al inicio, al finalizar las seis semanas de entrenamiento y tras seis semanas de desentrenamiento. Resultados: los resultados indican que ambos protocolos de entrenamiento físico son capaces de inducir modificaciones significativas en el perfil lipídico, la glicemia en ayuno y los niveles de HbA1C; sin embargo, solo el grupo E-Sob demostró mantener los beneficios logrados tras haber interrumpido el programa de entrenamiento en la reducción del LDL-C, HbA1C y en el incremento del HDL-C. Conclusiones: el ejercicio de sobrecarga en personas con DMII influye de manera importante en la salud, efecto que podría mantenerse incluso si se llega a interrumpir a corto plazo el programa de entrenamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(4): 1729-1734, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143675</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del entrenamiento y el desentrenamiento físico sobre la hemoglobina glucosilada, la glucemia y el perfil lipídico en diabéticos tipo II</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
