<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040988</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Empirical antibiotic therapy for diabetic and non-diabetic foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Neuropathy, ischaemia and infection are the three factors directly related to the appearance        and development of ulcers in diabetic patients. Infection defined by means of clinical parameters and backed up by        microbiological cultures is the main prognostic factor of the lesion. Aims. To study the infectious causation of ulcers in        diabetic and non-diabetic patients, in addition to the in vitro sensitivity to antimicrobials of the microorganisms that        were recovered, in order to enable us to develop a better empirical antibiotic regimen in our health care area. Patients        and methods. We conducted a prospective, cross-sectional, observational study involving 200 consecutive diabetic and        non-diabetic patients who were admitted to hospital due to the presence of ischaemic or neuropathic ulcers with local        signs of infection. Three microbiological samples were taken on the day of admission before administration of the        empirical treatment (ciprofloxacin + clindamycin) and their clinical response and modifications in the specific due to        resistance of the microorganisms were evaluated. Results. Polymicrobial microbiota were recovered from most of the        cultures, with predominance of gram-negative aerobic-anaerobics and gram-positive aerobics. Staphylococcus aureus        (10.6%), Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Bacteroides fragilis were the most frequently recovered micro-organisms. The        empirical therapy had to be modified in over 50% of cases due to resistance. The highest sensitivity in vitro for the grampositive        micro-organisms was to vancomycin, followed by cloxacillin and amoxicillin/clavulanic acid. In the case of        gram-negative aerobic-anaerobics, it was found to be meropenem, tobramycin and imipenem, while the anaerobics were        seen to be more sensitive to imipenem, cefoxitin and amoxicillin/clavulanic acid. Conclusions. Administration of        amoxicillin/ clavulanic acid alone or in association with tobramycin constitutes a wide-spectrum antibiotic regimen for        outpatients. If the patient is hospitalised, the preferred antibiotic would be imipenem, followed by piperacillin/        tazobactam</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bohórquez-Sierra, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Casanova, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Piñero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Calbo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón-González, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doiz-Artázcoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bohórquez-Sierra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La neuropatía, la isquemia y la infección son los tres factores directamente relacionados con la aparición        y desarrollo de las úlceras en los pacientes diabéticos. La infección definida mediante parámetros clínicos y apoyada        por cultivos microbiológicos es el principal factor pronóstico de la lesión. Objetivo. Estudiar la etiología infecciosa de las        úlceras en pacientes diabéticos y no diabéticos, así como la sensibilidad in vitro a antimicrobianos de los microorganismos        aislados, nos permitirá establecer la mejor pauta antibiótica empírica en nuestro medio asistencial. Pacientes y métodos.        Estudio observacional, transversal y prospectivo de 200 pacientes consecutivos, diabéticos y no diabéticos, ingresados por la        presencia de úlceras isquémicas o neuropáticas con signos locales de infección. Toma de tres muestras microbiológicas el día        del ingreso previa administración del tratamiento empírico (ciprofloxacino + clindamicina) y valoración de su respuesta clínica        y sus modificaciones a específico por resistencia de los microorganismos. Resultados. En la mayoría de los cultivos se        aisló microbiota polimicrobiana con predominio de aerobios-anaerobios gramnegativos y aerobios grampositivos. Staphylococcus        aureus (10,6%), Pseudomonas aeruginosa y Bacteroides fragilis fueron los microorganismos más frecuentemente aislados.        La terapia empírica tuvo que modificarse en más del 50% de los casos por resistencia. La mayor sensibilidad in vitro        para los microorganismos grampositivos fue para la vancomicina, seguida de cloxacilina y amoxicilina/clavulánico. En el        caso de aerobios-anaerobios gramnegativos, fue para meropenem, tobramicina e imipenem, y para los anaerobios, imipenem,        cefoxitina y amoxicilina/clavulánico. Conclusiones. La administración de amoxicilina/clavulánico solo o asociado a        tobramicina constituye una pauta antibiótica con amplio espectro para los pacientes ambulatorios. En régimen de ingreso el        antibiótico de elección sería imipenem, seguido de piperacilina/tazobactam</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;57(5): 389-400, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antibioterapia empírica en el pie diabético y no diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
