<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97772</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Levosimendan reduces mortality in cardiac surgery: A systematic review and meta-analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate whether Levosimendan has any impact on peri-operative mortality in cardiac surgery. Material and methods: A literature search was performed with the main purpose of looking for mortality in cardiac surgery. Data tabulated by both the fixed effects model and the random effects model were analysed based on the method by Peto. The statistical heterogeneity and inconsistency was estimated and quantified, as well as performing a sensitivity analysis to test the influence of individual studies on the overall result. All the calculations and statistical analyses were performed using the software; "Comprehensive Meta-Analysis" V2.0 and "StatsDirect statistical software" V 2.7.8. At the same time, possible publication bias was also determined. Results: A total of 169 articles were found, from which 13 studies were finally included in the meta-analysis; 12 randomised and one of them retrospective with paired data. The global analysis showed that the use of levosimendan was associated with a significant reduction in postoperative mortality. Conclusions: The meta-analysis showed that the use of Levosimendan was associated with a reduction in mortality in patients subjected to cardiac surgery, although there is still no definitively clear evidence. Additional randomised and multicentre clinical studies, with a much larger number of patients are required, in which hospital mortality and mortality at 6 months are analysed as the primary outcomes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miranda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar si levosimendán tiene algún impacto en la mortalidad perioperatoria en cirugía cardíaca. Material y métodos: Se realiza una búsqueda bibliográfica cuyo objetivo primario es la mortalidad en cirugía cardíaca. Se analizan los datos tabulados tanto por el modelo de efectos fijo (fixed) como el de efectos aleatorios (random) basado en el método de Peto. Se estima y cuantifica la heterogeneidad estadística y la inconsistencia, y se realiza además un análisis de sensibilidad, para comprobar la influencia de los estudios individuales en el resultado general. Todos los cálculos y análisis estadísticos se realizan con el software Comprehensive Meta-Analysis V2.0 y StatsDirect statistical software V 2.7.8. Asimismo se determinan posibles sesgos de publicación. Resultados: Se encontraron 169 artículos, de los que finalmente se incluyeron 13 en el metaanálisis, 12 aleatorizados y 1 retrospectivo de datos apareados. El análisis general muestra que el uso de levosimendán está asociado con una reducción significativa en la mortalidad postoperatoria. Conclusiones: El uso de levosimendán está asociado con una reducción en la mortalidad de los pacientes sometidos a cirugía cardíaca; sin embargo, aún no se ha establecido evidencia clara. Son necesarios nuevos estudios clínicos, aleatorizados, multicéntricos y con un número de pacientes bastante más elevado, en los que se analicen como objetivos primarios la mortalidad hospitalaria y al menos la mortalidad a los 6 meses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(1): 6-11, ene. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Levosimendán disminuye la mortalidad en cirugía cardíaca: revisión sistemática y metaanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
