<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82511</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological treatment of physical maltreatment and negligence in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a meta-analysis about the efficacy of psychological treatment for children who have suffered physical maltreatment and neglect by their parents or tutors are presented. Sixteen studies that met our selection criteria were included, providing 22 treated groups and 8 control groups. The results showed an absence of clear differences among the diverse treatments, although all of them exhibited a low-to-medium practical significance. The longer they are, the more effective are the treatments and also when neglect was the type of maltreatment suffered by the children. The effect estimates do not seem to be affected by biases. Finally, the clinical implications of the results, as well as those for future research, are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Meca, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Soler, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan los resultados de un meta-análisis sobre la eficacia de los tratamientos psicológicos de menores que han sufrido maltrato físico y negligencia por parte de sus padres o tutores. Se incluyeron 16 estudios que cumplían con los criterios de selección, dando lugar a 22 grupos tratados y 8 grupos de control. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto la ausencia de diferencias claras entre los diferentes tratamientos, si bien sus efectos tienen significación práctica de magnitud media-baja. Los tratamientos son más efectivos cuanto mayor es su duración y con menores que han sufrido negligencia. Las estimaciones de los efectos no parecen verse afectadas por sesgos. Finalmente, se discuten las implicaciones clínicas de los resultados para la investigación futura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(4): 627-633, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento psicológico del maltrato físico y la negligencia en niños y adolescentes: un meta-análisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36435</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
