<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128972</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional hearing deficits in listeners with auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder (ANSD) is a form of auditory dysfunction in which peripheral processes can be normal, but neural transmission through the VIIIth nerve and auditory brainstem is disrupted. The perceptual consequences of ANSD are distinct from those of cochlear hearing loss and most commonly include distortion of temporal (timing) cues and altered frequency discrimination. These basic processing deficits can, in turn, affect functional hearing, resulting in severe impairment of speech perception particularly in the presence of background noise. This article will address the mechanisms underlying ANSD, illustrate it's effects in a detailed case study and show evidence for the use of personal FM devices in affected listeners(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rance, Gary</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno de neuropatía auditiva (ANSD) es un tipo de disfunción auditiva en la que los procesos periféricos pueden ser normales, pero la transmisión neural a través del par craneal VIII y el tronco encefálico auditivo está perturbada. Las consecuencias perceptivas del ANSD difieren de las pérdidas auditivas cocleares y, por lo general, incluyen distorsión de las claves temporales (sincronización) y discriminación de frecuencias alterada. Estos déficit básicos de procesamiento pueden, a su vez, afectar a la audición funcional, lo que da lugar a deficiencias graves en la percepción del habla, sobre todo en la presencia de ruido de fondo. Este artículo abordará los mecanismos subyacentes en el ANSD, ilustrará sus efectos mediante un detallado estudio de caso y presentará pruebas sobre el uso de un sistema FM personal en un oyente afectado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);30(4): 206-212, oct.-dic.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit funcional en la capacidad auditiva de oyentes con trastorno de neuropatía auditiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29323^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6472^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1309^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1309^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1309^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d167^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d167^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d167^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
