<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82469</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tendon rupture in patients with multiple diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fluoroquinolones are a group of antibacterial drugs useful in a wide range of clinical conditions due to their wide spectrum of activity and oral bioavailability. Tendon injury is a rare complication associated to these drugs. Standing out among the risk factors are elderly age, previous treatment with steroids and chronic renal failure. It is very important to carefully measure the risk-benefit profile of those patients who have predisposing factors, and to clearly inform on the consistent symptoms in order to be able to discontinue the treatment early. We present a clinical case of an 86-year old woman with multiple conditions evaluated in primary care and rheumatology after treatment with quinolones who presented unilateral rupture of the Achilles tendon. An indication more adapted to the patient's characteristics could have avoided this effect (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Alonso, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siguero Anguí, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bachiller Corral, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fluoroquinolonas son un grupo de antibacterianos útiles en una amplia variedad de situaciones clínicas por su amplio espectro de actividad y su biodisponibilidad oral. La tendinopatía es una complicación rara asociada a estos fármacos. Entre los factores de riesgo destacan la edad avanzada, el tratamiento previo con esteroides y la insuficiencia renal crónica. Reviste una gran importancia medir cuidadosamente el perfil de beneficio riesgo en aquellos pacientes que presentan factores predisponentes, así como informar con claridad de los síntomas compatibles para poder suspender precozmente el tratamiento. Presentamos un caso clínico de una mujer de 86 años pluripatológica valorada en consultas de atención primaria y de reumatología, que tras el tratamiento con quinolonas presenta ruptura unilateral del tendón de Aquiles. Una indicación más adaptada a las características de la paciente podría haber evitado dicho efecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(9): 540-542, nov. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ruptura tendinosa en paciente pluripatológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36060^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
