<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040234</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What are users&#146; views of medical residents attending primary care consultations?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To find what users think of the presence of medical residents (MIR) at primary care consultations.                 Design. Observational and cross-sectional descriptive study.                 Setting. Urban health centre.                 Patients. 421 patients, selected by systematic sampling, attending consultations of MIR tutors.                 Method. A structured questionnaire was drawn up, with some closed questions with multiple-option replies on the Likert scale; and others with a yes/no or "indifferent" reply. The questionnaires were filled out in the waiting-rooms.                 Results. 100% (63% women, 37% men) answered the questionnaire. 71% preferred to be seen by the same doctor; and 68% thought they were better treated if they were always seen by the same doctor. 89% thought that the presence of the resident was a necessary part of his/her training; 90% were not bothered by his/her presence during the consultation; 82% thought the resident did not obstruct in any way their relationship with the doctor; 94% thought that the presence of the resident had never stopped them mentioning something important; 55% thought that patients had the right to an opinion on the presence of the resident.                 Conclusions. Most patients valued the presence of residents at consultations positively and thought it a necessary part of their training</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Perpiñá, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabaneque Mallén, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Sanjaime, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoño Domínguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dolz Domingo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Domingo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la opinión de los usuarios acerca de la presencia de médicos internos residentes (MIR) en las consultas de atención primaria.                 Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, observacional y transversal.                 Emplazamiento. Centro de salud urbano.                 Participantes. Se seleccionó por muestreo sistemático a 421 pacientes de las consultas de los tutores de los MIR.                 Medición. Se elaboró un cuestionario estructurado de preguntas cerradas de respuestas alternativas de múltiples opciones con escala de Likert, y otras de respuesta dicotómica a la que se añadió la respuesta: «es indiferente». Las encuestas se realizaron en las salas de espera.                 Resultados. Todos los pacientes respondieron al cuestionario (un 63% mujeres y un 37% varones). El 71% prefiere que le atienda el mismo médico; el 68% considera estar mejor tratado si le atiende siempre el mismo. El 89% cree que la presencia del MIR es necesaria para su formación, al 90% no le molesta su presencia en la consulta, el 82% cree que el MIR nunca entorpece la relación con el médico y el 94% declara que nunca ha dejado de expresar algo importante ante la presencia del MIR en la consulta. El 55% piensa que el paciente tiene derecho a opinar sobre la presencia del residente en la consulta.                 Conclusiones. La mayoría de los pacientes considera positiva la presencia de los MIR en las consultas de atención primaria y la cree necesaria para la formación de éstos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;36(1): 25-30, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué opinión tienen los usuarios de la presencia de los médicos residentes en las consultas de atención primaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
