<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157542</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interadministrative collaboration for public health management in municipalities with less than 10, 000 residents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyses which administrative body local councils use to carry out their basic public health responsibilities. The study sample includes data from municipalities with less than 10,000 residents, which we believe is a first for studies published in academic journals in Spain. The data used was obtained by means of a survey administered by trained personnel. 93.7% of all the municipalities in the province of Girona, the area under study, responded to the survey. The analysis shows that there is a statistically significant difference between municipalities with more and less than 10,000 residents with regards to which administrative body local councils use for managing public health responsibilities. The results of this study suggest that in the ongoing debate over the streamlining of local government, the current situation regarding public health responsibilities in municipalities with less than 10,000 residents needs to be taken into account (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alabert López, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbussà Reixach, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Zafra, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza cuál es el ente administrativo de referencia al que acuden los ayuntamientos para el desarrollo de sus competencias mínimas en salud pública. La muestra del estudio incorpora, creemos que por primera vez en los estudios académicos en España, datos de municipios de menos de 10.000 habitantes. Los datos provienen de un cuestionario administrado por personal entrenado y se obtuvo respuesta del 93,7% de los municipios de la provincia de Girona. El análisis muestra que la gestión municipal de las competencias de salud pública difiere de forma estadísticamente significativa, en cuanto al ente de referencia al que acuden los ayuntamientos, entre los municipios de más y de menos de 10.000 habitantes. Los resultados indican la necesidad de tener en cuenta la situación actual del desarrollo de las competencias municipales en salud pública en los municipios de menos de 10.000 habitantes en el debate sobre la racionalización de la Administración local (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(6): 480-482, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colaboraciones interadministrativas en la gestión de la salud pública en municipios menores de 10.000 habitantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23547^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
