<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149475</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in public health: the role of the state and the autonomous governments. SESPAS Report 2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The first responsibilities in health passed on to the autonomous governments were those referring to public health. However, the decentralization process has not been accompanied by an updated management of the collective efforts to promote and protect health, or by a greater weight of public health within the system. To carry out such a reform, public health authorities and the central and autonomic administrations must assume their corresponding roles. The leading role should correspond to the central administration and includes the coordination and evaluation of the entire process, while the regional public health authorities should be in charge of providing public health services to the population, promoting innovations, and collaborating among themselves as well as with the central administration. Recent legal initiatives show some political sensitivity and may provide an opportunity, in addition to those provided by the economic crisis, to emphasize the role of guarantor rather than that of supplier for the state. Paradoxically, the marginality of public health could facilitate the necessary political agreements, even though party interests may be an obstacle. The influence of professional associations could be important (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oñorbe de Torre, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Benedicto, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque las primeras competencias sanitarias transferidas a las comunidades autónomas fueron las de salud pública, la descentralización no se ha asociado a una renovación de la gestión de las actividades colectivas de promoción y protección de la salud, ni ha supuesto un aumento del peso de la salud pública en el sistema. Para llevar a cabo tal reforma es necesario que las administraciones responsables asuman los papeles que les corresponden: el de motor, liderazgo, referencia, coordinación y evaluación por parte del estado, y el de provisión de los servicios a la población, innovación y colaboración (entre ellas y con el estado) por parte de las autonomías. Las recientes iniciativas legales muestran cierta sensibilidad política que puede convertirse en una oportunidad, junto a las que proporciona la crisis económica, para acentuar el papel garante, en lugar de proveedor, del estado. La marginalidad de la salud pública puede facilitar, paradójicamente, los necesarios acuerdos políticos, aunque los intereses partidistas los dificulten. La influencia de las sociedades profesionales podría tener su importancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(supl.1): 19-22, dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149475</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la salud pública: el papel del estado y de las autonomías. Informe SESPAS 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
