<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80739</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intrabdominal pressure variability in patients under abdominoplasty procedure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A randomised, prospective, descriptive study was realized in 100patient who had an abdominoplasty procedure by one of 15 different surgeons at the Salvador B. Gautier Hospital and the Centro de Cirugía Plástica y Especialidades Santo Domingo, of the Dominican Republic, during a five month period, July and August 2003 and from July to September 2004. Intra-abdominal pressure was measured by a Foley catheter, after elimination of bladder content followed by direct bladder administration of 100 cc 0.9% saline solution, and measuring in cm on a water column, taking as reference point(point cero) the pubic symphisis before and during surgical procedure, with the patient laying on her back in an horizontal position and flexed at 45 degrees and 12 and 24 hours after the procedure inflexed position. The obtained values were correlated with parameters like plicatura diameter, body weight index, cardiac and respiratory frequency. All the patients were female. About ages, 47 were 30 to 39 years old, 34 patients were 40 or older, 18 patients were 20 to 29 years old and only 1 patient was younger than 20 years old. Sixty six patients had a history of previous abdominal surgery, mainly the gynaecological procedures. Plicatura diameter was between 8 and 10 cm in 70patients.We demonstrate variations in intra-abdominal pressure measured in pre, trans and postoperative periods, in horizontal and flexed positions, and how this pressure was higher in patients with overweight and obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aquino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercedes, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, E. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos un estudio prospectivo, descriptivo, clínico-quirúrgico y aleatorio sobre 100 pacientes sometidos a abdominoplastia por 15 cirujanos distintos en el Hospital Salvador B. Gautier y el Centro de Cirugía Plástica y Especialidades Santo Domingo, de la República Dominicana, a lo largo de un periodo de 5 meses, Julio y Agosto de 2003 y de Julio a Septiembre de 2004. Medimos la presión intrabdominal (PIA) de forma estandarizada mediante cateterismo vesical, vaciando la vejiga urinaria e introduciendo100 ml de solución salina al 0,9%. La medición se hizo en una columna de agua graduada en centímetros que tenía como punto cero la sínfisis del pubis, antes y durante la intervención en posición plana y flexionando el tronco a 45 grados y entre 12 a 24horas después del procedimiento quirúrgico, en posición flexionada. Correlacionamos los valores obtenidos con parámetros tales como: diámetro de la plicatura, índice de la masa corporal, frecuencias cardiaca y respiratoria. Las 100 pacientes del estudio fueron de sexo femenino. Por edades,47 tenían entre 30 y 39 años de edad, 34 tenían 40 años o más,18 tenían entre 20 y 29 años y solo 1 era menor de 20 años. Del total, 66 pacientes tenían antecedentes de cirugía abdominal, destacándolos procedimientos ginecológicos. Había también 75 pacientes con sobrepeso o algún grado de obesidad. El diámetro de la plicatura muscular realizada osciló entre los 8 y los 10 cm en el 70%de los casos. Demostramos variaciones de la PIA medida en el preoperatorio, intraoperatorio y postoperatorio, tanto en posición plana como flexionada, así como que el aumento de la PIA se produce con mayor frecuencia en pacientes que presentan sobrepeso u obesidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;35(4): 261-270, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad de la presión intrabdominal en pacientes sometidos a abdominoplastia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
