<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058761</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abdominal wall endometriomas. Report of 17 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Endometriosis is defined as the presence of endometrial glands and stroma outside the uterus. This finding occurs in 3 to 15% of women of reproductive age, and is most frequently located in the abdominal cavity. Occasionally, endometriosis is present as a painful mass in the abdominal wall, near a surgical scar, or in the umbilical or inguinal area. The aim of the present study was to review the incidence, location, symptoms and treatment of abdominal wall endometriomas in our center. Patients and methods: Prompted by a new case of endometrioma arising from a Pfannenstiel scar, we reviewed 17 cases of abdominal wall endometrioma (AWE) diagnosed since 1990, Symptoms, location, clinical findings, and the various etiopathogenic theories were analyzed. Results: Since 1990, 17 patients with AWE underwent surgery. Two endometriomas were located in the umbilical area, 4 in the inguinal region, and 11 arose from surgical scar sites from prior gynecological or obstetric surgery. Most of the tumors were incidental findings during surgical procedures. Preoperative diagnosis with computed tomography (CT) scan was made in 4 patients. Treatment was wide surgical excision. All patients were subsequently referred to the gynecology service for follow-up and further treatment. Conclusions: Although AWE are uncommon, these tumors should be suspected in women of reproductive age with any mass in the inguinal or umbilical region, or near a gynecologic or obstetric scar. Abdominal CT scanning and fine-needle biopsy may confirm the diagnosis. Treatment consists of surgical excision (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farreras, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz de Zárate, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buqueras, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Santín, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bachs, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La endometriosis se caracteriza por la presencia de tejido endometrial fuera del cuerpo uterino. Su frecuencia oscila del 3 al 15% de las mujeres en edad fértil. La localización más habitual es la intraabdominal, pero puede presentarse en forma de nódulos dolorosos en la pared abdominal, cicatrices de intervenciones previas, fundamentalmente ginecológicas u obstétricas, o como nódulos inguinales o umbilicales. El objetivo del presente trabajo es revisar su incidencia, localización, clínica y tratamiento. Pacientes y métodos: A partir de un nuevo caso de endometrioma, originado en una cicatriz de Pfannenstiel, se revisan 17 casos diagnosticados desde 1990, analizando su forma de presentación y características clínicas, así como las diferentes teorías etiopatogénicas. Resultados: Desde 1990 se han intervenido 17 casos de endometriomas de pared abdominal, 2 localizados a nivel umbilical, 4 en la región inguinal y 11 tumoraciones en cicatrices de intervenciones quirúrgicas previas, ginecológicas u obstétricas. En la mayoría de los casos se trató de un hallazgo casual dentro del acto quirúrgico y en 4 casos se realizó una tomografía computarizada (TC) abdominal previa al tratamiento quirúrgico. El tratamiento consistió en exéresis amplia de la lesión. Posteriormente todas las pacientes fueron derivadas al servicio de ginecología para completar su estudio y tratamiento. Conclusiones: A pesar de que la incidencia de endometriomas de pared abdominal es baja, ante cualquier nódulo de características anómalas en la región inguinal o umbilical, o tumoración sobre cicatriz ginecológica u obstétrica en una mujer de edad fértil, se ha de sospechar la presencia de un endometrioma. La TC abdominal y la punción-aspiración con aguja fina pueden ayudar al diagnóstico. El tratamiento es quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);35(1): 2-6, ene. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058761</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriomas de la pared abdominal. Revisión de una serie de 17 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13890^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10719^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
