<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140544</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the awareness of the risk of nuts aspiration related to the occupation of parents?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the social awareness of the risk of nuts aspiration and the relationship with the occupation of parents. Material and methods. From January 2013 to January 2014, a self-designed survey was distributed to 247 parents of patients under 14 years admitted to our centre, regardless of the reason for admission. The statistical significance was calculated using confidence intervals (CI). The Pearson Chi-square test was used to analyse the ignorance of this problem depending on the educational level extrapolated from the occupation of respondents. Results. 247 parents responded to the survey. 60.3% (95% CI 54.1- 66.2%) confirmed that nuts were included in birthday parties. 30.4% (95% CI 25-36.4%) confirmed that celebrations with nuts at their children&#146;s nursery were made. 42.1% (95% CI 36.1-48.3%) believed that nuts were harmless for their young children. The age of administration of nuts was independent on the educational level extrapolated of parents (&amp;#967;²=10.721, p = 0.295), although it did influence on the ignorance of the danger of nuts (41.2% (95% CI 30.3-53%) of respondents with occupations that required higher educational level compared to 55.4% (95% CI 42.4-67.6%) of those with occupation that required less educational level (&amp;#967;²=14.678, p = 0.002)). Conclusions. Regardless of the occupation, there is widespread ignorance concerning the age of introduction of nuts in children&#146;s diet. Given the incidence and severity of the risk of aspiration, more prevention programs are necessary, and Health Authorities should take side in public awareness of this problem (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carazo Palacios, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moratalla Jareño, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domènech Tàrrega, AB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez San Román, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Carbó, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar el desconocimiento social acerca del riesgo de aspiración de frutos secos y su relación con la profesión que ocupan sus padres. Material y métodos. Desde enero 2013 a enero 2014 se distribuyó una encuesta autodiseñada a 247 padres de pacientes menores de 14 años ingresados en nuestro centro, independientemente del motivo de ingreso. Para el análisis se calculó la significación estadística mediante intervalos de confianza (IC). Se valoró el desconocimiento de este problema en función del nivel de estudios extrapolado a partir de la ocupación de los encuestados mediante el test de Chi-cuadrado de Pearson. Resultados. 247 padres respondieron a la encuesta. El 60,3% (IC95% 54,1-66,2%) confirmó que en las fiestas de cumpleaños a las que asistían sus hijos había frutos secos. El 30,4% (IC95% 25-36,4%) afirmó que en las guarderías de sus hijos se realizaban celebraciones con frutos secos. El 42,1% (IC95% 36,1-48,3%) creía que los frutos secos no suponían en absoluto un peligro para sus hijos pequeños. El nivel de estudios extrapolado de los encuestados resultó independiente en la edad de administración de frutos secos (&amp;#967;²=10,721, p=0,295), aunque sí influyó en el desconocimiento de la peligrosidad de los frutos secos (41,2% (IC 95% 30,3-53%) de los encuestados con ocupaciones que exigían tener estudios superiores frente al 55,4% (IC 95% 42,4-67,6%) de aquellas ocupaciones que requerían un menor nivel de estudios (&amp;#967;²=14,678, p=0,002)). Conclusiones. Independientemente de la ocupación, existe un desconocimiento generalizado relativo a la edad de introducción de los frutos secos en la dieta. Se precisan más campañas de prevención dada la incidencia y gravedad del riesgo de aspiración, por lo que las autoridades responsables deberían tomar partido en la concienciación pública de este problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(4): 169-172, oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Influye la profesión de los padres en la concienciación del riesgo de aspiración de frutos secos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5639^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5822^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52104^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
