<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18130</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implicit attitude change</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent attitude research has focused considerable attention on the distinction between implicit and explicit social judgments. Relative to explicit measures, implicit measures (e.g., sequential priming, Implicit Associative Test) are more likely to assess judgments that are fast, unintentional, uncontrollable, unconscious, or nonreactive. In contrast, explicit measures (e.g., questionnaire measures) often assess intentional judgments that involve greater awareness, control, deliberation, or social editing. The general assumption is that implicit attitudes (i.e., automatic evaluation) are strong, stable, and resistant to change. Our research suggested that implicit attitudes are not immutable and can be persuaded. Participants were asked to read a persuasive message, composed by strong or weak arguments. Both explicit and implicit attitudes toward the proposal were assessed. The explicit measures of the attitudes did not reveal any change, whereas the implicit measures showed a significant effect of the argument quality, specially for those participants high in need for cognition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Horcajo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falces, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briñol, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Benjamín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las medidas explícitas de las actituides (e.g. auto-informes y cuestionarios) hacen referencia a juicios evaluativos relativamente controlados, deliberados y conscientes. Las medidas implícitas de las actitudes (e.g., priming y test de actitudes implícitas) constituyen evaluaciones más rápidas, insconcientes y difíciles de controlar. De estas últimas se derivan las denominadas actitudes implícitas de las personas, que se caracterizan por su fuerza, estabilidad y duración en el tiempo. La presente investigación demuestra que tales evaluaciones automáticas son objeto de persuasión. Se pidió a un grupo de sujetos que leyeran un mensaje persuasivo compuesto por argumentos fuertes o débiles y se midieron las actitudes hacia la propuesta, tanto de forma explicita como implícita. Los resultados demuestran que, si bien las actitudes explícitas de los participantes no se ven influidas por los mensajes, las actitudes implícitas reflejan el efecto la calidad de los argumentos, sobre todo para aquellos participantes con mayor motivación para elaborar la información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(4): 771-775, nov. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambio de aptitudes implícitas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7768</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
