<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167682</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of caring behaviors of patients and oncology nursing: comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hematology, and Emergency. Methodology. This was a descriptive comparative study conducted with 131 patients and 78 members from the nursing staff in three oncology services. The perception of care was evaluated with Homer&#146;s Professional Caring Behaviors Instrument. Comparison was performed through non-parametric tests. Results. Patients were on average 54 years of age, mostly females, independent, with low schooling and presented a perception of nursing care behaviors of 77.3%, with hematology averaging better (81.3%), followed by internal medicine (77.3%) and lower in emergency (73.3%). They perceive, in order, attributes of courtesy, relationship, commitment, and interaction. The nursing staff were 19% professionals, 81% aides, mostly females with over six years experience, presented perception of caring behaviors of 85.9% and similar in the three services. Conclusion. The characteristics of patients and of the nursing staff in the different services are similar. For patients, the perception of nursing care behaviors per total services and in the dimensions of interaction and commitment is positive and different (p &lt; 0.05). For the nursing staff, the perception of caring behaviors is similar among services and above that of the patients in their totality and in the dimensions of courtesy and interaction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Lilia Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Herrera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mabel Carrillo, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, Narda Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir y comparar la percepción del comportamiento del cuidado de los pacientes y el personal de enfermería en servicios de hospitalización, hematología y urgencias en una institución de oncología de referencia de Bogotá. Metodología. Estudio descriptivo comparativo realizado con 131 pacientes y 78 integrantes del personal de enfermería en tres servicios oncológicos. La percepción de cuidado se valoró con el Instrumento comportamiento profesional de cuidado de Horner. La comparación se realizó con pruebas no paramétricas. Resultados. Los pacientes de 54 años en promedio, mayoría femenina, independientes, con baja escolaridad presentaron una percepción de comportamientos de cuidado de enfermería de 77,3% en promedio siendo mejor en hematología (81,3%), seguida de medicina interna (77,3%) y más baja en urgencias (73,3%). Ellos perciben en su orden atributos de cortesía, relación, compromiso e interacción. El personal de enfermería con el 19% profesional, 81% auxiliar, de mayoría femenina con más de 6 años de experiencia, presentó una percepción de comportamientos de cuidado de 85,9% siendo similar en los tres servicios. Conclusión: Las características de los pacientes y del personal de enfermería en los diferentes servicios son similares. Para los pacientes la percepción de comportamientos de cuidado de enfermería por servicios total y en las dimensiones interacción y compromiso es positiva y diferente (p &lt; 0,05). Para el personal de enfermería la percepción de comportamientos de cuidado es similar entre servicios y superior a la de los pacientes en su totalidad y en las dimensiones cortesía e interacción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(2/3): 267-278, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de comportamientos de cuidado de pacientes y de enfermería oncológica: estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
