<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040977</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Future role of glitazones in the therapy of type 2 diabetes. On-going clinical trials with rosiglitazone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 2 diabetes is a common disease associated with an increased risk of long-term complications. Current guidelines recornmend certain therapy targets which have been shown to be difficult to achieve. As we have leamed from the UKPDS data, treatment with metformin, sulfonylureas or insulin improve glycemic control in the short term but do not prevent progressive beta cell failure or long term deterioration of glycemia. Insulin resistance is a common defect in these patients and is related with this deterioration of the beta cell function, as well as with the development of other cardiovascular risk factors. Glitazones improve insulin sensitivity and, subsequentiy, patients experience beneficial changes which may go beyond glycaemic control. Whether these benefits result in a modification of the course of type 2 diabetes is something that the ongoing clinical trials programme will probably answer. DREAM (Diabetes REduction Approaches with Ramipril and Rosiglitazone Medications), ADOPT (A Diabetes Outcomes and Progression Trial), RECORD (Rosiglitazone Evaluated for Cardiac Outcomes and Regulation of glycaemia in Diabetes) and BARI 20, PPAR, APPROACH are some of the studies being made to clarify these questions, within the rosiglitazone clinical trials programme, which includes more than 29000 patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montoto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes tipo 2 es una enfermedad común asociada con un incremento del riesgo de complicaciones a largo plazo. Las guías terapéuticas actuales recomiendan ciertos objetivos de tratamiento que son a veces complicados de conseguir. Como ya se vio en el estudio UKPDS, el tratamiento con metformina, sulfonilureas o insulina, mejora el control glucémico a corto plazo pero no previene el progresivo deterioro en la función de las células Beta o el deterioro a largo plazo de la glucemia. La resistencia a la insulina es un defecto común en estos pacientes y se relaciona con este deterioro de la célula Beta, así como con el desarrollo de otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Las glitazonas mejoran la sensibilidad a la insulina y, debido a esto, producen una serie de cambios beneficiosos más allá del propio control de la glucemia. Si estos beneficios determinan una modificación del curso de la diabetes tipo 2, es algo que responderán los programas de ensayos clínicos en marcha. El estudio DREAM (Diabetes REduction Approacbes witb Ramipril and Rosiglitazone Medications), el estudio ADOPT (A Diabetes Outcomes and Progression Trial), el RECORD (Rosiglitazone Evaluated for Cardiac Outcomes and Regulation of glycemia in Diabetes) y el estudio BARI 20, el estudio PPAR, el APPROACH... son algunos de los trabajos en marcha en el programa de ensayos clínicos de rosiglitazona, para clarificar estas preguntas y que incluyen en total a más de 29.000 pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(supl.2): 118-124, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Futuro de las glitazonas en el tratamiento de la diabetes tipo 2. Programa de ensayos clínicos con rosiglitazona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23164^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
