<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140877</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Distension test in passive external rotation: Validation of a new clinical test for the early diagnosis of shoulder adhesive capsulitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study is to evaluate the internal validity of a clinical test for the early diagnosis of shoulder adhesive capsulitis, called the Distension Test in Passive External Rotation (DTPER). Material and method. The DTPER is performed with the patient standing up, the arm adducted, and the elbow bent at 90°. From this position, a smooth passive external rotation is started, the affected arm being supporting at the wrist with one hand of the examiner and the other maintaining the adducted elbow until the maximum painless point of the rotation is reached. From this point of maximum external rotation with the arm in adduction and with no pain, an abrupt distension movement is made, increasing the external rotation, causing pain in the shoulder if the test is positive. This term was performed on a group of patients with shoulder pain of many origins, in order to analyse the predictive values, sensitivity, specificity, and the likelihood ratio. Results. The DTPER showed a sensitivity of 100% (95% CI; 91.8 to 100%) and a specificity of 90% (95% CI; 82.4 to 94.8%). The positive predictive value was 0.62 and a likelihood ratio of 10.22 (95% CI; 5.5 to 19.01). False positives were only found in patients with subscapular tendinopathies or glenohumeral arthrosis. Discussion. The DTPER has a high sensitivity for the diagnosis of adhesive capsulitis, and is excluded when it is practically negative. False positives can easily be identified if there is external rotation with no limits (subscapular tendinopathy) or with a simple shoulder X-ray (glenohumeral arthrosis) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noboa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antuña, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Graña, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito de este estudio es evaluar la validez interna de una prueba clínica descrita para el diagnóstico precoz de la capsulitis adhesiva de hombro: el Test de Distensión en Rotación Externa Pasiva (TDREP). Material y método. El TDREP se realiza con el paciente de pie, el brazo adducido y el codo flexionado a 90°. Desde esta posición, se inicia un movimiento suave de rotación externa pasiva, sosteniendo el brazo afectado con una mano del examinador en la muñeca y otra manteniendo el codo abducido hasta que se alcanza el punto máximo de rotación indolora. Desde este punto de máxima rotación externa con el brazo en aducción y sin dolor, se realiza un movimiento brusco de distensión, incrementando la rotación externa, causando dolor en el hombro si la prueba es positiva. Es test se realizó en un grupo de 155 pacientes con dolor de hombro de múltiples orígenes para analizar los valores predictivos, la sensibilidad, especificidad y razón de verosimilitud. Resultados. El TDREP mostró una sensibilidad de 100% (IC 95%, de 91,8 a 100%) y una especificidad del 90% (IC 95%, de 82,4 a 94,8%). El valor predictivo positivo fue de 0,62 y la razón de verosimilitud de 10,22 (IC 95%: 5,5 a 19,01). Los falsos positivos se encontraron solo en enfermos con tendinopatías del subescapular o con artrosis glenohumeral. Discusión. El TDREP tiene una alta sensibilidad para diagnosticar CA y cuando es negativo prácticamente la excluye. Los falsos positivos se pueden identificar fácilmente si existe una rotación externa sin limitación (tendinopatía subescapular) o con una radiografía simple de hombro (artrosis glenohumeral) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(5): 354-359, sept.-oct. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140877</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Test de Distensión en Rotación Externa Pasiva (TDREP): validación de una nueva prueba clínica para el diagnóstico precoz de la capsulitis adhesiva de hombro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
