<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143947</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scientific communication (XXVI). How to increase the spread and impact of papers in Pediatrics through the open science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Open science is the movement that pretends to make the scientific research and the dissemination of data accessible to all levels. It involves open access publication and the generated research data publication and reuse (open research data). Participating in open science and sharing publications and research data promotes scientific work, increases their citation and impact and contributes to the advancement of science.  The main strategies to increase the spread and impact of the papers are: 1) to publish quality papers; 2) to publish in the best journals; 3) to publish in open access journals; 4) to publish and to share raw research data; 5) to include papers in Google Scholar and to create a Google Scholar Citations profile, and 6) to take advantage of web 2.0 tools, such as including content in wikis, participating in social networks, uploading professional videos to the Internet, publishing your own website and blog, sharing bibliographic references and slides, participating in mailing lists and providing an ORCID profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Sapena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Arroyo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal-Infer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, RL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aleixandre-Benavent, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ciencia abierta (open science) es el movimiento que pretende hacer accesible a todos los niveles la investigación científica y la difusión de los datos. Implica la publicación en abierto (open access) y la publicación y reutilización de los datos generados en las investigaciones (open research data). Participar en la ciencia abierta y compartir las publicaciones y los datos de investigación estimula el trabajo científico, aumenta su citación e impacto y contribuye al avance de la ciencia. Las principales estrategias para aumentar la difusión y el impacto de los trabajos son las siguientes: 1) publicar trabajos de calidad; 2) publicar en las mejores revistas; 3) publicar en abierto; 4) publicar y compartir los datos brutos de investigación; 5) incluir los trabajos en Google Scholar y crear un perfil en Google Scholar Citations, y 6) aprovechar las herramientas de la web 2.0, como incluir contenidos en las wikis, participar en redes sociales, colgar vídeos profesionales en la red, difundir una web y un blog propio, compartir referencias y presentaciones de diapositivas, participar en listas de distribución y disponer de un perfil en ORCID (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(8): 203-210, sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comunicación científica (XXVI). Cómo aumentar la difusión y el impacto de los trabajos pediátricos participando en la ciencia abierta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50163</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3329^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32710</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8180^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8180^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3329^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3329^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19200^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
