<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039107</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantitative evaluation of 123I-FP-CIT SPECT: validation of a semiautomated method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the utility of a quantification of the 123I-FP-CIT uptake by the definition of some reference values, normal range values and interobserver variation. Patients and method: Fifty patients with a 123I-FP-CIT SPECT: 25 patients had a pathological SPECT with the diagnosis of Parkinson's disease and the remaining had a qualitative normal SPET, with the diagnosis of 14 drug-induced Parkinsonism and 11 with psychogenic Parkinsonism. In the transversal slices, the best central slice that showed the nuclei of the base best was selected and standard ROIs (Region Of Interest) were applied. Specific (caudate and putamen) versus non specific (occipital) and laterality ratios were calculated. A normal statistical analysis for independent quantitative samples was used (mean, standard deviation and range) as well as variation coefficient and correlation coefficient of two observers and the 10th and 90th percentile. Results: The variation coefficient interobserver was 3.24-5.61 and the correlation coefficient was 0.89-0.99. Cut-off values between both populations were established at 2.10 in the right putamen and at 2.05 in the left. Cut-off values definition in caudate were not assessable due to overlapping of ratios of both populations. Conclusions: This quantification method is highly reproducible. It makes it possible to obtain reference values and to define normal range</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo i Bosquet, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caresia, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castell Conesa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuberas Borrós, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguadé Bruix, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la utilidad de un método de cuantificación de la captación de 123I-FP-CIT mediante la definición de unos valores de referencia, la validación del rango de normalidad y la variación interobservador.Pacientes y método: Se seleccionan 50 pacientes con un SPET con 123I-FP-CIT: 25 patológicos con el diagnóstico clínico de una enfermedad de Parkinson y 25 estudios cualitativamente normales, con el diagnóstico de catorce con un parkinsonismo farmacológico y once con un parkinsonismo psicogénico. En los cortes transversales, se seleccionó el corte central que mejor visualiza los núcleos de la base, y sobre éste se posicionan las áreas de interés (Region Of Interest-ROI) estandarizadas. Se calcularon los índices de captación específica (caudado y putamen) vs no específica (occipital) y las ratios de lateralidad. Se determinaron las variables cuantitativas (media, la desviación estándar y el rango) de ambos grupos, el percentil 10, el percentil 90 y el coeficiente de variación y de correlación entre los resultados de dos observadores. Resultados: Los coeficientes de variación interobservador obtenidos oscilaron entre 3,24 y 5,61. Se obtuvieron unos coeficientes de correlación entre 0,89 y 0,99. El dintel de separación estimado entre ambas poblaciones en el putamen fue en el derecho de 2,10 y en el izquierdo de 2,05. Con respecto a los caudados, existió un solapamiento entre ambas poblaciones que no permitió establecer un límite de separación. Conclusiones: Este método de cuantificación es reproducible, permite definir unos valores de referencia y determinar el límite de la normalidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;24(4): 244-249, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación cuantitativa del SPET con 123I-FP-CIT: validación de un método semiautomático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34223^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3358^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
