<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040662</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hereditary neuromuscular diseases in paediatrics. Our experience over the last 14 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hereditary neuromuscular diseases are disorders which can vary largely in their age of onset, symptomsand severity. Many are severe, disabling and have an important personal, familial and social impact and can restrict theprognosis for survival. The constant progress being made in diagnostics makes it necessary to continually update knowledgeand information. Patients and methods. We carried out a review of the hereditary neuromuscular diseases contained in theNeuropaediatrics database at the Hospital Miguel Servet in Zaragoza from May 1990 to October 2004. Results. Of the 7,805patients in the database, 123 (1.5% of the total) were patients with hereditary neuromuscular diseases, of whom 71 were malesand 52 females. These included: 35 sensory-motor hereditary neuropathies, 17 dystrophinopathies, 10 myotonic dystrophies, 10spinal muscular atrophies, four merosin-deficient congenital dystrophies, four other muscular dystrophies, three mitochondrialmyopathies, three myasthenias, two familial neuropathies with insensitivity to pain, two Friedreich&#146;s ataxias, one familialneuropathy with liability to pressure palsies, one case of Walker-Warburg syndrome, five polyneuropathies associated toleukodystrophy and another 25 cases that could not be classified. Genetic studies provided a diagnosis in 36 cases (29.2%):nine myotonic dystrophies, eight dystrophinopathies, eight cases of spinal muscular atrophy, four demyelinating sensory-motorhereditary neuropathies, two instances of Friedreich&#146;s ataxia, two limb-girdle muscular dystrophies, one congenital myasthenia,one McArdle&#146;s disease and one case of Kearns-Sayre syndrome. Conclusions. Genetic studies enable us to establish diagnosesthat were previously limited to the realm of assumption, and allow us to avoid the need for muscle tissue biopsies, which is awelcome development, especially when dealing with children. Immunohistochemical studies need to be updated and biologicalsamples should be systematically saved in cases where no diagnosis is reached</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colomer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capablo-Liesa, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bestué, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz de Cabezón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro-Torres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebage, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agua, C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pisón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baldellou-Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Segura, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las enfermedades neuromusculares hereditariasson trastornos heterogéneos en edad de inicio, clínica ygravedad. Muchas son graves, discapacitantes y con gran impactopersonal, familiar y social, y pueden limitar el pronóstico vital. Seproducen continuos avances diagnósticos que exigen una permanenteactualización. Pacientes y métodos. Revisión de las enfermedadesneuromusculares hereditarias de la base de datos de Neuropediatríadel Hospital Miguel Servet de Zaragoza de mayo de 1990a octubre de 2004. Resultados. De 7.805 pacientes de la base dedatos figuran 123 casos (el 1,5% del total) con enfermedades neuromusculareshereditarias: 71 varones y 52 niñas. Son: 35 neuropatíashereditarias sensitivomotoras, 17 distrofinopatías, 10 distrofiasmiotónicas, 10 atrofias musculares espinales, cuatro distrofiascongénitas deficientes en merosina, otras cuatro distrofias musculares,tres miopatías mitocondriales, tres miastenias, dos neuropatíasfamiliares con insensibilidad al dolor, dos ataxias de Friedreich,una neuropatía familiar con parálisis sensibles a la presión,un síndrome de Walker-Warburg, cinco polineuropatías asociadasa leucodistrofia y otros 25 casos sin tipificar. Los estudiosgenéticos han sido diagnósticos en 36 casos (29,2%): nueve distrofiasmiotónicas, ocho distrofinopatías, ocho atrofias muscularesespinales, cuatro neuropatías hereditarias sensitivomotoras desmielinizantes,dos ataxias de Friedreich, dos distrofias muscularesde cintura, una miastenia congénita, una enfermedad de McArdle yun síndrome de Kearns-Sayre. Conclusiones. La genética establecediagnósticos que previamente sólo pueden ser de presunción, y permiteevitar biopsias musculares, lo que es satisfactorio especialmenteen niños. Es necesaria la actualización en los estudios inmunohistoquímicosy guardar sistemáticamente muestras biológicasen los casos sin diagnóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(3): 145-150, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades neuromusculares hereditarias en pediatría. Nuestra experiencia de 14 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
