<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131446</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional health and the development of nursing wellbeing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Current scientific evidence shows the importance entailed by the development of Emotional Intelligence (EI) for Nursing professionals, and this encourages the development of training programs in this area, due to the high prevalence of Burnout Syndrome and work-related stress in professionals, because EI development is associated with the prevention of both conditions. EI development in nursing professionals is particularly important, because its benefits include enhancing the emotional balance, thus contributing to good health and preventing diseases which might cause permanent emotional disorders such as anxiety, fear, distress or anger, among others, and offering defenses for a positive reaction to tension and stress. The purpose of this article is to create awareness about the importance and necessity of creating and implementing training programs on Emotional Intelligence for nurses, due to the advantages this would entail both for an improvement in patient care and an improvement in the health of professionals. This necessity is increased due to the current shortage of training programs on EI during high education, as in the specific case of Nursing, an aspect which apparently has not been sufficiently considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bajo Gallego, Yeudiel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Hervías, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evidencia científica actual pone de manifiesto la importancia que supone el desarrollo de la inteligencia emocional (IE) para los profesionales de la Enfermería, lo cual invita a desarrollar programas de formación en este área debido a la alta prevalencia del síndrome de burnout y de estrés laboral en la profesión, puesto que el desarrollo de la IE se relaciona con la prevención de ambos fenómenos. El desarrollo de la IE en los profesionales enfermeros es de especial importancia, pues entre sus beneficios se encuentra favorecer el equilibrio emocional, contribuyendo de esta forma a la buena salud, previniendo enfermedades que pueden producir desequilibrios emocionales permanentes como la ansiedad, el miedo, la angustia o la ira, entre otros, brindando defensas para la reacción positiva a la tensión y al estrés. El propósito de este artículo es concienciar sobre la importancia y necesidad de creación e implementación de programas de formación en inteligencia emocional para las enfermeras y enfermeros, debido a las ventajas que esto supondría tanto para la mejora en la atención a los pacientes como para la mejora en la salud de los propios profesionales. Esta necesidad se ve incrementada debido a la escasez actual de programas de formación en IE durante la educación superior, como es en el caso concreto de la Enfermería, aspecto que, según parece, no está lo suficientemente considerado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(10): 12-16, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La salud emocional y el desarrollo del bienestar enfermero</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
