<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113988</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with clinical symptomatology of fear and anxiety in dental patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Estimate the degree of association between factors associated with clinical symptomatology of fear and anxiety in adult patients at the Faculty of Dentistry of the university of Cartagena de Indias (Colombia). Design: Cross sectional observational study. Location: Faculty of Dentistry of the university of Cartagena de Indias (Colombia). Participants: 460 adult patients selected by simple random sampling. Main Surveyed Data: An instrument which included socio-demographic and behavioural factors was used and a screening questionnaire: Goldberg scale, Kleinknecht`s Dental Fear Survey (DFS) and Short Version Dental Anxiety Scale (SDAI). Data were analysed based on proportions, assuming a 95% confidence interval, odds ratio and logistic regression, using the STATA programme version 10.0®. Results: The prevalence of clinical symptomatology of fear and dental anxiety was 77.1% (IC 95% 73.3-81) and 62.8% (IC 95% 58.3-67.2) respectively. Statistically significant dental fear associated with the female sex was recorded (OR=1.9; IC95% 1.2&#150;2.9) and previous traumatic experience in the dental surgery (OR=3.2; IC95% 1.73&#150;6.28) and anxiety in the dental surgery with the female sex (OR=2; IC95% 1.3-2.9), previous traumatic experience in the dental surgery (OR=2.2; IC95% 1.4-3.6), negative influence from members of the family (OR=1.5; IC95% 1.07-2.2), patient&#146;s perception of dental health (OR= 1.5; IC95% 1.04-2.2), and fear in the dental surgery (OR=39.8 IC95% 19.2&#150; 82.5). Conclusions: Prevalence of dental fear and anxiety in the subjects was high; the female sex, negative influence from members of the family and previous traumatic experiences in the dental surgery are risk factors causing fear and anxiety in the dental surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrieta Vergara, Katherine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verbel Bohórquez, Johana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cárdenas, Shyrley</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hawasly Pastrana, Nathalie</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar el grado de asociación entre factores asociados a sintomatología clínica de miedo y ansiedad dental en pacientes adultos de la Facultad de Odontología de la Universidad de Cartagena de Indias (Colombia). Diseño del estudio: Estudio observacional transversal. Emplazamiento: Facultad de Odontología de la Universidad de Cartagena de Indias (Colombia). Participantes: 460 pacientes adultos seleccionados por muestreo aleatorio simple. Mediciones principales: Se utilizó un instrumento que incluyó factores socio-demográficos y conductuales, y los cuestionarios de cribado: Escala de Goldberg, Kleinknecht`s Dental Fear Survey (DFS) y Short Version Dental Anxiety Scale (SDAI). Los datos fueron analizados a partir de proporciones, asumiendo intervalos de confianza del 95%, razones de disparidad (Odds ratio) y regresión logística, utilizando el programa STATA versión 10.0®. Resultados: La prevalencia de sintomatología clínica de miedo y ansiedad dental fue 77,1% (IC 95% 73,3-81) y 62,8% (IC 95% 58,3-67,2) respectivamente. Se presentó asociación estadísticamente significativa del miedo dental con el sexo femenino (OR=1,9; IC95% 1,2 &#150; 2,9) y la experiencia traumática previa en la consulta odontológica (OR=3,2; IC95% 1,73 &#150; 6,28) y de la ansiedad en la consulta odontológica con el sexo femenino (OR=2; IC95% 1,3-2,9), la experiencia traumática previa en la consulta odontológica (OR=2,2; IC95% 1,4-3,6), influencia negativa de los familiares (OR=1,5; IC95% 1,07-2,2), percepción del paciente acerca de su salud oral (OR= 1,5; IC95% 1,04-2,2), y el miedo en la consulta odontológica (OR=39,8 IC95% 19,2&#150; 82,5). Conclusiones: La prevalencia de miedo y ansiedad dental en los sujetos fue alta; el sexo femenino, la influencia negativa de familiares y las experiencias traumáticas previas en la consulta odontológica son factores de riesgo para la aparición de miedo y ansiedad en la consulta odontológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;6(1): 17-24, 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a sintomatología clínica de miedo y ansiedad en pacientes atendidos en Odontología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
