<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148106</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alagille's syndrome associated with proximal radio-ulnar synostosis: clinical case and a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alagille's syndrome is an infrequent genetic condition with autosomal inheritance and variable expression. The complete form exhibits 5 clinical signs, chronic intrahepatic cholestasis, characteristic facies, cardiovascular anomalies, posterior embryotoxon, and vertebral defects. If only 3 or 4 of these are present the case is considered as an incomplete form. The association of Alagille's syndrome with radio-ulnar synostosis is extremely rare. There is only one case described in the indexed literature. A case is presented of Alagille's syndrome with bilateral proximal radioulnar synostosis. To the best of our knowledge this is the second reported case of this association (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Couceiro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Alagille es una condición genética infrecuente, con herencia autosómica dominante y expresividad variable. En su forma completa presenta 5 signos clínicos característicos: colestasis intrahepática crónica, una facies característica, anomalías cardiovasculares, embriotoxon posterior y defectos vertebrales. Si solo 3 o 4 de estos están presentes se dice que es una forma incompleta del síndrome. Es extremadamente infrecuente su asociación con sinostosis radiocubitales, habiendo solo un caso descrito de esta asociación en la literatura indexada. Presentamos un caso de síndrome de Alagille asociado a una sinostosis radiocubital proximal bilateral. Que los autores tengan noticia, es el segundo caso de esta asociación publicado en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);60(1): 81-85, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Alagille asociado a sinostosis radiocubital proximal: caso clínico y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13961^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12318^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14856^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
