<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95091</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Haemato-oncological disease and inmigration: itineraries for exclusión?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Health Services have to deal with new and frequent social phenomena of migratory flows. There are many factors related to the health/illness process among the immigrants, resulting sometimes in exclusion itineraries. The present study pretends to describe the psychosocial variables related to immigrant patients with a haematological disease in a specialized hospitalization setting. We evaluated a sample of sixty immigrant patient´s hospitalized at the Haematology Service of the University Hospital La Paz. Most of them were women and the mean of age was 40 years old. A great number of these patients were from Latin-America. They were married, but without primary caregiver, although, they perceived family and social support. They presented economic difficulties and poor social-economic resources being most of them unemployed. Not significant levels of anxiety and /or depression were reported. Our study reflects a precarious scene for these patients when they face the double challenge of the immigration and the threat of the haematological disease. From the research we can take out concrete improvement proposals in order to reinforce our specific compromise against the suffering experience related to the disease and the exclusion experience. We realize that these kind of research helps to preserve the most disfavoured rights. We understand that this type of investigations helps to preserve the rights of the most disfavoured (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázque, Nika</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coca, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los servicios sanitarios nos encontramos con el nuevo y frecuente fenómeno social de los flujos migratorios. Muchos son los factores que repercuten en el proceso de salud/enfermedad de los inmigrantes, convirtiéndose en ocasiones en itinerarios de exclusión. Este estudio pretende describir las variables psicosociales de los pacientes inmigrantes con una enfermedad onco-hematológica en atención especializada hospitalaria. Para ello se evaluó a un grupo de 60 pacientes inmigrantes ingresados en el Servicio de Hematología del Hospital Universitario La Paz; la mayoría eran mujeres y la edad media era de 40 años. Un gran número procedía de Latino-América, estaban casado pero carecían de cuidador principal; a pesar de esto, sentían que tenían apoyo emocional familiar y social. Presentaban dificultades económicas y escasos recursos, estando la mayoría en una situación de desempleo. No informaban de significativos niveles de ansiedad o depresión. Nuestro estudio refleja un escenario de enorme precariedad psico-social en estos pacientes, cuando se enfrentan doblemente, al hecho de la inmigración y a la amenaza de la enfermedad onco-hematológica. De la investigación salen propuestas concretas de mejora que traen un compromiso específico, frente a la experiencia de sufrimiento que trae la enfermedad y frente a la experiencia de exclusión. Entendemos que este tipo de investigaciones ayuda a preservar los derechos de los más desfavorecidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);4(1): 165-177, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad onco-Hematológica e inmigración: ¿Itinerarios para la exclusión?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
