<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126382</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An experimental model of mass-type brain damage in the rat: Expression of brain damage based on neurospecific enolase and protein S100B</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether a model of transient mass-type brain damage (MTBD) in the rat produces early release of neurospecific enolase (NSE) and protein S100B in peripheral blood, as an expression of the induced brain injury. Design: An experimental study with a control group. Setting: Experimental operating room of the Institute of Biomedicine (IBiS) of Virgen del Rocío University Hospital (Seville, Spain).Participants: Fourteen adult Wistar rats. Interventions: Blood was sampled at baseline, followed by: MTBD group, a trephine perforation was used to insert and inflate the balloon of a catheter at a rate of 500 _l/20 sec, followed by 4blood extractions every 20 min. Control group, the same procedure as before was carried out, though without trephine perforation. Primary study variables: Weight, early mortality, serum NSE and S100B concentration. Results: Differences in NSE and S100B concentration were observed over time within the MTB Dgroup (P &lt; .001), though not so in the control group. With the exception of the baseline determination, differences were observed between the two groups in terms of the mean NSE andS100B values. Following MTBD, NSE and S100B progressively increased at all measurement timepoints, with r = 0.765; P = .001 and r = 0.628; P = .001, respectively. In contrast, the control (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Sánchez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Cabezas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egea-Guerrero, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-Justel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo-Escobar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revuelto-Rey, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilches-Arenas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar si un modelo experimental de lesiones tipo masa (LM) transitoria en rata produce la liberación precoz a sangre periférica de enolasa neuroespecífica (NSE) y proteínaS100B como expresión del daño cerebral inducido. Diseño: Estudio experimental con grupo control. Ámbito: Quirófano experimental del Instituto de Biomedicina (IBiS) del Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocío. Participantes: Catorce ratas adultas Wistar. Intervenciones: Se extrajo muestra sanguínea basal y posteriormente se realizó: grupo LM, através de un trépano, se infló el globo de una sonda con 500 _L/20 s; posteriormente, se realizaron4 extracciones sanguíneas cada 20 min. Grupo control, se repitieron de forma sistemática todos los pasos salvo que no se realizo trépano. Variables de interés principal: Peso, mortalidad precoz, concentración en suero de NSE yS100B.Resultados: Encontramos diferencias entre las concentraciones de NSE y S100B a lo largo del tiempo dentro del propio grupo LM (p &lt; 0,001), no sucediendo este hecho en el grupo control. Excepto en la determinación basal, encontramos diferencias en los valores medios de NSE yS100B entre ambos grupos. Tras el daño cerebral, la NSE y la S100B presentaron un incremento progresivo en el tiempo en todas las determinaciones realizadas con una r = 0,765; p = 0,001,y r = 0,628; p = 0,001, respectivamente. Por contra, en el grupo control no encontramos dicha correlación para ninguno de los dos (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);38(4): 218-225, mayo 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126382</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo experimental de lesión cerebral tipo masa en rata: expresión del daño cerebral mediante enolasa neuroespecífica y proteína S100B</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10944^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
