<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151838</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodology for health assets mapping in a community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Within the development of a regional strategy for community health engagement in Asturias (Spain), and connected to the Health Observatory, we carried out a methodology to initiate the mapping of health assets at a local level. This methodology begins with a description of the most formal resources and of the pre-existing community activities, together with a characterization of the most informal, personal and symbolic health resources. We introduce our tools, grouped for the development of mapping, and explain their connection with the theoretical models of salutogenesis, asset model and community development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Botello, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Margolles, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernán, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cofiño, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro del proceso regional de desarrollo de una estrategia de participación comunitaria en salud en Asturias, y en el contexto del Observatorio de Salud, hemos desarrollado una metodología para iniciar el mapeo de los activos en salud de ámbito local. En esta metodología se parte de una descripción de los recursos más formales y de las actividades comunitarias existentes, junto con una caracterización de los recursos en salud más informales, personales y simbólicos. Se presentan las herramientas agrupadas para el desarrollo del mapeo y su conexión con los modelos teóricos de la salutogénesis, asset model y del desarrollo comunitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(2): 180-183, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología para el mapeo de activos de salud en una comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6446^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27804</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
