<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102926</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coexistence of Peutz-Jeghers&#146; syndrome and Lynch&#146;s syndrome in the same patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract Peutz-Jeghers&#146; syndrome is an uncommon polyposis syndrome characterized by the presence of hamartomatous polyps in the gastrointestinal tract and mucocutaneous pigmentation (especially in the oral-nasal and perianal areas and hands and feet). Inheritance is autosomal dominant, caused by a germline mutation in the STK11 (LKB1) gene. The risk of breast and gastrointestinal cancer is increased in this syndrome. Lynch&#146;s syndrome is also known as hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer. This syndromeis caused by a mutation in DNA mismatch repair genes and increases the risk of colon and endometrial cancer, as well as that of other neoplasms (ovary, upper urological tract, gastric, small intestine, pancreas, skin and brain). We present the case of a young woman with colorectal cancer and the coexistence of both syndromes. This association has not previously been reported in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jorge Cerrudo, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Carretero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño González, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Amate, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen El síndrome de Peutz-Jeghers es un síndrome polipósico infrecuente, definido por la presencia de pólipos hamartomatosos en el tracto gastrointestinal y por la presencia de pigmentación mucocutánea (especialmente en región buconasal, perianal, manos y pies).Es un trastorno autosómico dominante causado por una mutación germinal en el STK11 (LKB1). El riesgo de cáncer de mama y gastrointestinal está aumentado en esta entidad. El síndrome de Lynch forma parte del síndrome de cáncer colorrectal hereditario no asociado a poliposis. Está causado por una mutación en los genes reparadores del ADN y aumenta el riesgo de cáncer de colon y endometrio, así como otros tipos de neoplasias (ovario, tracto urológico alto, gástricas, de intestino delgado, páncreas, piel y cerebro).Presentamos el caso de una mujer joven con cáncer colorrectal en la que se demostró la coexistencia de ambos síndromes, una asociación aún no descrita en la literatura hasta la fecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;35(6): 395-399, jun. -jul. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102926</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coexistencia de síndrome de Peutz-Jeghers y síndrome de Lynch en un mismo paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22610^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24009^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
