<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86582</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internal attribution of outcome moderates the cortisol response to a cooperative task in women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several ethological reports have indicated that cooperative behaviors play an adaptive role. However, research has focused on competition in men, and there have been few studies on cooperation. This study aims to analyze the cortisol and psychological responses in women to a cooperative situation compared with a competitive situation in a laboratory context. The sample was distributed into four groups depending on the task and the outcome obtained: Positive cooperation, negative cooperation, competition with victory, and competition with defeat. Our results show that, in comparison with competition, cooperation produces different effects in cortisol, but not in psychological states. Nevertheless, these effects occur only when the task outcome and its appraisal are considered. Only the participants who cooperated and obtained a positive outcome and those who competed and lost showed significant decrements of cortisol. Internal attribution was higher in groups with more stable cortisol levels, suggesting a possible modulator effect of controllability in the way the situation was experienced. These results could be generalized to situations in which negotiation, mediation, and cooperative strategies are relevant for making decisions and/or solving problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Bono, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Martínez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Albiol, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sariñana-González, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés García, Sara de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchos-Calatayud, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las observaciones etológicas actuales indican que las conductas cooperativas desempeñan un papel adaptativo. En humanos, las situaciones competitivas han sido mayoritariamente investigadas en varones, aunque en escasas ocasiones se ha estudiado la cooperación. Se pretende analizar la respuesta psicológica y del cortisol a una situación cooperativa, en comparación con una competitiva en el laboratorio en mujeres. Se establecieron cuatro grupos en función de la tarea y su resultado: cooperación positiva, cooperación negativa, competición con victoria y competición con derrota. La cooperación produce efectos diferentes en cortisol que la competición, pero no en las variables psicológicas, aunque estos efectos únicamente se producen cuando se considera el resultado y su atribución. Solo las participantes que cooperaron y fueron evaluadas positivamente y las que compitieron y perdieron mostraron descensos significativos de cortisol. La atribución interna se asocia a niveles de cortisol más estables, sugiriendo un efecto modulador de la controlabilidad en la vivencia de la situación. Estos resultados podrían hacerse extensibles a situaciones en las que la negociación, la mediación y las estrategias cooperativas son relevantes para la toma de decisiones y/o resolución de conflictos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(2): 196-202, abr.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La valoración del resultado modula la respuesta del cortisol a una tarea cooperativa de laboratorio en mujeres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d533</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
