<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62156</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is risk-free minimally invasive humeral shaft osteosynthesis possible? A cadaver study (technique and anatomy)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the feasibility of using minimally invasive percutaneous plate osteosynthesis (MIPPO) in the treatment of humeral shaft fractures and analyze the anatomical relations of the different bodily structures with the fixation plate. Introduction: Humeral shaft fractures account for 1.6% of all surgical fractures. Open reduction and compression plate fixation is a universally accepted method, but since it requires an extended dissection it could cause a lesion to the radial nerve. Another alternative is to use intramedullary nails, but the percentage of complications associated to them is similar. Materials and methods: We conducted a study of 5 cadavers. At the proximal level, we carried out a deltopectoral mini approach; the distal incision was performed at about 5 centimeters proximally to the elbow flexure in the inferomedial region of the arm. Once the two mini approaches were completed, a blunt instrument was used to drive an anterior extraperiosteal subbrachial tunnel on the anterior aspect of the humerus through which a 10-hole straight narrow plate was introduced from proximal to distal. Results: Once the osteosynthesis was completed, we identified the relationship of the different anatomical structures with the plate, extending both incisions without finding any significant anatomical structure on the anterior aspect of the humerus that could be damaged. Conclusions: Even if technically challenging, the MIPPO technique described herein is less invasive or traumatic than open reduction and plate fixation, and it is not associated with any special risks of injury to the radial or musculocutaneous nerves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Arévalo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narváez-Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Medina, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cara-Del Rosal, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar la viabilidad de aplicar la técnica MIPPO (minimally invasive percutaneous plate osteosynthesis, &#147;osteosíntesis percutánea con placa mínimamente invasiva&#148;) en el tratamiento de las fracturas diafisarias de húmero, y observar las relaciones anatómicas de las distintas estructuras nobles con la placa de osteosíntesis. Introducción: Las fracturas de la diáfisis humeral representan el 1,6% del total de las fracturas quirúrgicas. La reducción abierta y la osteosíntesis con placa a compresión es un método aceptado universalmente pero, al requerir una disección extensa, hay posibilidades de dañar el nervio radial; otra alternativa es el uso de clavos intramedulares, pero el porcentaje de complicaciones es similar. Material y método: Para esto, se realizó un estudio en 5 cadáveres. Se procedió a realizar un miniabordaje deltopectoral en la zona proximal y se realizó la incisión distal a unos 5 cm, proximal a la flexura del codo en la región inferoexterna del brazo. Una vez realizados los 2 miniabordajes, se procedió a realizar un túnel subraquial anterior extraperióstico con un objeto romo, siempre por la cara anterior del húmero, y se introdujo una placa recta estrecha de 10 orificios de proximal a distal. Resultados: Una vez realizada la osteosíntesis, se procedió a identificar la relación de las distintas estructuras anatómicas con la placa prolongando ambas incisiones: no se encontró ninguna estructura anatómica noble en la cara anterior del húmero que pudiera dañarse. Conclusiones: Aunque pueda ser técnicamente difícil, la técnica MIPPO descrita aquí es menos invasiva y traumática que la reducción abierta y la colocación de una placa, además no supone riesgos especiales de lesión en el nervio radial o musculocutáneo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);53(5): 305-311, sept.-oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Es posible la osteosíntesis mínimamente invasiva de la diáfisis del húmero sin riesgos? Estudio en el cadáver (técnica y anatomía)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6962^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
