<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74719</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of procainamide in the treatment of refractory ventricular fibrillation: report of 4 cases and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ventricular fibrillation is the most common malignantarrhythmia, found in up to 55% of patients who go on toexperience cardiac arrest. Only monophasic or biphasicdefibrillation has been shown to be effective. Theefficacy of antiarrhythmic drugs is much lower anddepends on how much time has elapsed since the onsetof symptoms. In patients with persistent ventricularfibrillation refractory to shocks, treatment options arelimited. We report 4 cases in which procainamide wasadministered at a dosage of 17 mg/kg in 1 minute. Heartrhythm was restored and pulse rate recovered in lessthan 3 minutes in all cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Zúñiga, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ximena Zuluaga, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación ventricular es la arritmia maligna másfrecuente en los pacientes con parada cardiaca. Hasta enel 55% de los pacientes que presentan una parada cardiacase documenta una fibrilación ventricular. El únicotratamiento efectivo comprobado es la desfibrilación yasea con desfribrilador monofásico o bifásico. Los antiarrítmicostienen una efectividad mucho menor y su efectividaddepende del tiempo transcurrido. En casos defibrilación ventricular incesante, refractaria a tratamientoresistente a las descargas, el manejo es limitado.A continuación se presentan 4 casos clínicos en los que seadministró procainamida a dosis de 17 mg/kg administradaen 1 minuto con restauración de ritmo efectivo yrecuperación de pulso en un tiempo inferior a 3 minutos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(8): 511-514, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74719</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de procainamida en el tratamiento de la fibrilación ventricular refractaria: descripción de 4 casos clínicos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11778^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
