<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154016</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive ventilation in &#145;do-not-intubate&#146; patients in a chronic disease hospital. One year follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Elderly patients with multiple morbidity and do not intubate (DNI) orders frequently present with acute respiratory failure. There are data supporting the effectiveness of non-invasive ventilation (NIV) in this context. Our chronic disease hospital developed an integrated care clinical pathway for the use of NIV in acute respiratory failure in the emergency room and wards in 2010. The aim of this study was to assess the outcome of NIV in patients with acute respiratory failure who had a DNI order in a sub-acute care hospital. Methods. Observational, one year-follow up study. The main variables were in-hospital mortality and one year mortality. Other variables recorded were: demographics, clinical data, functional data, performance of daily life activities, dementia, arterial blood gases and re-admissions. Results. The study included a total of 102 patients, of which 22% were in institutions. The mean age 81 ± 7.47% males, with a Charlson index 3.7 ± 1, and Barthel index 54 ± 31. The overall mortality during the admission was 33% (34 patients). Among those patients ventilated outside the protocol indication, the mortality was significantly greater, at 71% (P &gt; .05). Overall one-year survival rate was 46%. This survival rate was statistically higher in patients with obesity hypoventilation syndrome and a Barthel &gt; 50. Conclusions. NIV is a useful technique in a hospital for chronic patients in an elderly population with a therapeutic ceiling. Despite their disease severity and comorbidity, acceptable survival rates are achieved. A correct case selection is needed. Obesity hypoventilation syndrome and those with Barthel index &gt; 50 have a better prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Molet, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Alaña, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alkiza Basañez, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tabernero Huguet, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana-Arri, Eunate</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Citores Martín, Leyre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernandez Gil, Aníbal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El fracaso ventilatorio agudo, especialmente en la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica, es una causa frecuente de ingreso en pacientes ancianos con pluripatología y limitación de esfuerzo terapéutico. Cada vez hay más datos de la utilidad de la ventilación mecánica no invasiva (VMNI) en este contexto. Nuestro centro desarrolló en 2010 una vía clínica integrada urgencias-hospitalización para el uso de la VMNI en el fracaso ventilatorio agudo. El objetivo de este trabajo fue evaluar el resultado de la VMNI en el fracaso ventilatorio agudo en pacientes con orden de no intubar en un hospital de subagudos. Material y método. Estudio observacional, con un año de seguimiento. Las variables principales son la mortalidad al ingreso y al año. Se recogen todos los casos que reciben VMNI, a través de un registro específico. Otras variables recogidas son: datos demográficos, clínicos y funcionales, enfermedad de base, situación funcional basal, gasometría, estancia y reingresos. Resultados. Se incluyeron 102 pacientes con una edad media de 81 años, un índice de Charlson de 3,7 y un índice de Barthel de 54, estando el 22% institucionalizados. La mortalidad durante el ingreso fue del 33%. Entre los pacientes sin indicación ajustada a protocolo, la mortalidad fue del 71%. La supervivencia global al año fue del 46%, resultando asociada en el análisis estadístico multivariante a obesidad-hipoventilación e índice de Barthel &gt; 50. Conclusiones. La VMNI es una técnica de utilidad en pacientes ancianos con limitación de esfuerzo terapéutico. A pesar de la severidad y la comorbilidad, se obtienen tasas aceptables de supervivencia. Los pacientes con mejor situación funcional basal y obesidad-hipoventilación tienen mayor supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);51(4): 221-224, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154016</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la ventilación mecánica no invasiva en pacientes no candidatos a intubación en un hospital de subagudos. Estudio de seguimiento a un año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1811^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24402^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30472</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
