<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60498</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New antibiotics against Gram-positive microorganisms: linezolid, tigecycline, daptomycin, dalbavancin, telavancin, ceftobiprole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Six new antibiotics against Gram-positive bacteria havebeen developed in the last few years, three of which arealready available for clinical use. One of these drugs is acompletely new synthetic antibiotic (linezolid). Another isa semisynthetic lipopeptide derived from a species ofStreptomyces (daptomycin). The remaining agents aremodifications of tetracyclines (tigecycline), glycopeptides(dalbavancin and telavancin) or cephalosporins(ceftobiprole). The most important feature of theseantibiotics is their activity against Gram-positiveorganisms, including methicillin-resistant Staphylococcusaureus, vancomycin-intermediate S. aureus, andvancomycin-resistant and -sensitive enterococci. Some ofthese agents (linezolid, tigecycline and ceftobiprole) arealso active against Gram-negative bacteria. Four of these(daptomycin, dalbavancin, telavancin and ceftobiprole)have a general bactericidal effect. All of these antibioticsare administered intravenously by continuous infusion,although linezolid, due to its excellent bioavailability, canalso be administered orally. The recommended doses foradults are highly varied (from 100 to 1500 mg/day), withintervals ranging from 12 hours (linezolid, tigecycline andceftobiprole), 24 hours (daptomycin and telavancin) to 7days (dalbavancin). These antibiotics are mainly excretedthrough the kidney (daptomycin, dalbavancin, telavancinand ceftobiprole) or liver (linezolid and tigecycline). Thepharmacodynamic indexes that are correlated withtherapeutic efficacy, always bearing in mind the freeantibiotic fraction, is the area AUC /MIC ratio (linezolid,tigecycline, daptomycin, dalbavancin and telavancin) orthe time in which the serum concentration of the antibioticis above the MIC of the pathogen (ceftobiprole)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se han desarrollado 6 nuevosantibióticos activos frente a bacterias grampositivas, 3 delos cuales ya están disponibles para uso clínico. Uno deestos fármacos es un antibiótico de síntesiscompletamente nuevo (linezolid). Otro es unalipopeptidolactona, derivado semisintético de una especiede Streptomyces (daptomicina). El resto consiste enmodificaciones de tetraciclinas (tigeciclina), glucopéptidos(dalbavancina y telavancina) o cefalosporinas(ceftobiprole). Lo más relevante de estos antibióticos es suactividad frente a organismos grampositivos, incluidosStaphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina, S. aureuscon sensibilidad intermedia a la vancomicina, yenterococos sensibles y resistentes a la vancomicina.Alguno de ellos (linezolid, tigeciclina y ceftobiprole) posee,además, actividad frente a bacterias gramnegativas.Cuatro de ellos (daptomicina, dalbavancina, telavancina yceftobiprole) poseen un efecto generalmente bactericida.Todos estos antibióticos se administran por víaintravenosa en infusión continua, aunque linezolid, debidoa su excelente biodisponibilidad, puede tambiénadministrarse por vía oral. Las dosis recomendadas para eladulto son muy variadas (de 100 a 1.500 mg/día), conintervalos que van desde las 12 h (linezolid, tigeciclina yceftobiprole), 24 h (daptomicina y telavancina) o 7 días(dalbavancina). Estos antibióticos se eliminan,predominantemente, por vía renal (daptomicina,dalbavancina, telavancina y ceftobiprole) o hepática(linezolid y tigeciclina). Los índices farmacodinámicos quese correlacionan con eficacia terapéutica, teniendo encuenta siempre la fracción libre del antibiótico, es la tasaárea bajo la curva/concentración mínima inhibitoria (CMI)(linezolid, tigeciclina, daptomicina, dalbavancina ytelavancina) o el tiempo en que la concentración sérica delantibiótico supera la CMI del patógeno (ceftobiprole)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.2): 13-20, ene. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos antibióticos frente a grampositivos: linezolid, tigeciclina, daptomicina, dalbavancina, telavancina, ceftobiprole</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23258^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6244^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
