<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100471</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Returning to the approaches of sensitive nursing care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">SensitiveThe sensible care includes sensitiveble reasoning, creativity, aesthetics, solidarity, freedom, partnership and,, by association, with the human care. Objectives: To reflect on the problems of nursing in the sensitiveble care approach and analyze some ways forto approach professionals to approachon the sensitivity care. Methodology: This is a reflective study conducted from a literature review ofin texts on about sensitiveble care and sensitivity. The survey usedwas done in the database in the Virtual of Health Library in the last decadeand found 23 full text publications in national literature., Descriptors related to: Nursing, Nursing Care, and Humanized Assistance. Results: The study shows that sensitiveble care, although not a descriptor in the nursing literature, is expressed in solidarity, love and professional contacts, in the availability, dispositionsal, with one attentive listening, and interested in dialogue, in the conversation-dedicated therapy, and in everything that involves the affective dialogue. Conclusions: The study revealedevoked the need for paradigm shifts in nursing care, towards a another order more organic, affective, more humane order, that invests in the subjectivity, that valuesvaluing the lived complexity of feelings that accompany the physical and emotional disorders of the user of the consumer&amp;#8223;s healthy service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camargo, CL de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza da Silva, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribero de Oliveira, RC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cuidado sensible contempla la razón sensible sensible, la creatividad, la estética, la solidaridad, la libertad de asociación en relación con el cuidado humano. Objetivos: Reflexionar sobre las demandas del cuidado de enfermería en el orden sensible y analizar los enfoques profesionales relativos a la sensibilidad en el cuidado. Metodología: Se trata de un estudio reflexivo-analítico realizado a partir de una revisión bibliográfica sobre el cuidado sensible y la sensibilidad. Levantamiento realizado en la Biblioteca Virtual de Saúde - BVE, de publicaciones de los últimos diez años, se encontraron 23 publicaciones indirectas, en textos completos en la literatura nacional, identificados con los descriptores: Enfermería, Cuidados de Enfermería y Humanización de la Asistencia. Resultados: El estudio reveló que el cuidado sensible a pesar de no ser descrito en la literatura de enfermería, se identifica con la solidariedad, amor y afectividad de los contactos profesionales; en la disponibilidad, en la entrega, en la escucha atenta; en el diálogo objetivo e interesado, en la conversación dedicada, em la conversación terapéutica o todo aquello que implica el diálogo afectivo en la práctica humanizada del cuidado. Conclusiones: Los resultados destacan la necesidad de cambios de paradigma en el cuidado, de otra manera más orgánica, afectiva, más humana, que invierta en la subjetividad del ser, valorando lo vivido, la complejidad de los sentimientos que acompañan los desórdenes físicos y emocionales del usuario de los servicios de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(25): 343-355, ene. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Volviendo a los planteamientos de la atención sensible</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
