<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106854</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous laser ablation of a foetal cardiac teratoma and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac teratomas are benign tumors, but in about half of affected fetuses there is intrauterine death due to cardiac tamponade and hydrops. In some cases there have been apparent improvements in prognosis after intrauterine drainage of the pericardial effusion. We report a case of cardiac teratoma presenting at 30 weeks gestation with cardiac tamponade, treated by ultrasound-guided laser ablation of the teratoma and pericardiocentesis. The infant was born at 35 weeks gestation and survived after post-natal tumor resection. Laser ablation of the tumor might slow down the growth and the re-accumulation of pericardial effusion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina, Francisca Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomez, Luisa F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ablación láser de la lesión puede enlentecer el crecimiento tumoral y la re- acumulación de líquido pericárdico. Los teratomas cardiacos son tumores benignos aunque la mitad de los fetos afectos por ellos mueren intraútero debido a taponamiento cardiaco e hidropesía fetal. En algunos casos se ha documentado una mejoría del pronóstico fetal tras el drenaje intrauterino de la efusión pericárdica. Exponemos un caso de teratoma cardiaco diagnosticado en la semana 30 de embarazo con signos de taponamiento cardiaco que fue tratado intraútero de forma percutánea mediante ablación láser de la lesión bajo control ecográfico y pericardiocentesis. El feto nació mediante cesárea electiva en la semana 35 realizándose cirugía resectiva tumoral postnatalmente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);23(4): 154-159, oct.-dic. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ablación láser percutánea de un teratoma cardiaco fetal y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23685^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
