<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104021</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Damage control surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Damage control surgery (DCS) seeks to improve outcome in critical trauma patients with abdominal injuries and diminished physiological reserve. DCS is a staged approach to surgery that starts with a rapid intervention to control bleeding and contamination; this step is followed by a period of reanimation and eventually the definitive repair of lesions. Fast decision-making and selection of candidates, whether they have multiple injuries or not, are fundamental in DCS. We review the indications, stages, and surgical procedures to follow in DCS. We also discuss prognostic factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Guerra, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Fernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Rojas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía de control de daños o  damage control surgery (DCS) intenta mejorar los resultados de los traumatismos abdominales en pacientes críticos con escasa reserva fisiológica. Se define como una &#147;cirugía por etapas&#148;, con un primer tiempo quirúrgico corto para controlar el sangrado y la contaminación, seguido de un periodo de reanimación y, finalmente, de reparación definitiva de las lesiones. Debe basarse en la toma rápida de decisiones, identificando aquellos pacientes, politraumatizados o no,que pueden ser candidatos a esta cirugía. Se revisan las indicaciones, las etapas, los procedimientos quirúrgicos y los factores pronósticos de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(3): 219-224, jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de control de daños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54490^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54251^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
