<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149369</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pathogenic ability and saline stress tolerance of two Fusarium isolates from Odontesthes bonariensis eggs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Several fungal species represent a potential risk to embryos of Odontesthes bonariensis (Cuvier and Valenciennes, 1835), a euryhaline freshwater fish that lives in the Pampean inland waters and has potential economic relevance. Aims. To identify two fungi isolated from O. bonariensis eggs exposed to saline conditions and to characterize their pathogenicity and tolerance to sodium chloride solutions. Methods. The isolates were identified by morphological features, and a preliminar phylogenetic analysis using sequences of translation elongation factor 1-alpha (EF-1&amp;#945;) and calmodulin (CAM) was performed. Koch's postulates were tested to identify the causative agent of fungal infection. The influence of NaCl on the fungal growth was evaluated in in vitro assays. Results. The isolates LPSC 1001 and 1002 were identified as representatives of the genus Fusarium, and belonging to the Fusarium incarnatum-Fusarium equiseti species complex (FIESC) and the Fusarium solani species complex (FSSC), respectively. Histological observations on eggs exposed in vitro to both isolates in infectivity assays confirmed the ability of the fungal isolates to penetrate to egg's chorionic membrane, leading to the death of embryos. Increasing NaCl concentration in the culture medium reduced the growth of the isolates LPSC 1001 and 1002, being completely inhibited at 160 and 120 g/l NaCl respectively. Conclusions. The isolates LPSC 1001 (FIESC) and 1002 (FSSC) were identified as fungal pathogens to O. bonariensis eggs. The use of NaCl solutions as antifungal treatment was not effective to control the infection with these strains (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salibián, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Marino, Suani G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dinolfo, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello, Marta N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stenglein, Sebastián A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saparrat, Mario CN</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Diversas especies de hongos pueden representar un riesgo importante para los embriones de Odontesthes bonariensis (Cuvier &amp; Valenciennes 1835), un pez de agua dulce eurihalino que vive en las aguas interiores pampeanas y tiene una relevancia económica potencial. Objetivos. Identificar dos especies de hongos de huevos de O. bonariensis expuestos a condiciones salinas y caracterizar su patogenicidad y tolerancia a las soluciones de cloruro de sodio. Métodos. Se identificaron los aislamientos por sus características morfológicas, y se realizó un análisis filogenético preliminar utilizando secuencias de traslación del factor 1 alfa elongación (EF- 1&amp;#945;) y calmodulina (CAM). Se llevaron a cabo los postulados de Koch para identificar el agente causante de la infección fúngica. La influencia de NaCl sobre el crecimiento fúngico se evaluó en ensayos in vitro. Resultados. Se identificaron los aislamientos LPSC 1001 y 1002 como representantes del género Fusarium, y pertenecientes al complejo de especies Fusarium incarnatum-Fusarium equiseti (FIESC) y al complejo de especies de Fusarium solani (FSSC), respectivamente. Las observaciones histológicas en los huevos expuestos in vitro a ambos aislamientos en los ensayos de infectividad confirmaron la capacidad de estos para penetrar en la membrana coriónica, lo que condujo a la muerte de los embriones. El aumento de la concentración de NaCl en el medio de cultivo redujo el crecimiento de los aislamientos LPSC 1001 y 1002, quedando completamente inhibidos a 160 y 120 g/l de NaCl, respectivamente. Conclusiones. Se identificaron los aislamientos LPSC 1001 (FIESC) y 1002 (FSSC) como hongos patógenos para los huevos de O. bonariensis; el uso de soluciones de NaCl como tratamiento antifúngico no resultó eficaz para el control de la infección con estas cepas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(1): 13-20, ene.-mar. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149369</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patogenicidad y tolerancia al estrés salino de dos aislamientos de Fusarium aislados de huevos de Odontesthes bonariensis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4698^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4698^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4698^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4659^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4601^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4601^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5535^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4697^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5535^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4697^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2180</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
