<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117389</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to prescribe for patients with dysphagia: a review for the adaptation of the pharmaceutical guide in a socio-sanitary hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pourpose: The aims of this paper are to review the pharmaceutical guide in order to include suitable dosage forms for patients with dysphagia and to establish specific recommendations for the drug administration. Methods: A comprehensive literature review was performed to develop general recommendations. Three topics were checked for every drug: a) alternative dosage forms suitable to patients with dysphagia; b) appropriateness of crushing tablets and opening capsules; and c) are these drugs suitable be mixed with food? Results: An algorithm was designed in order to help clinicians to select the best pharmaceutical form and its optimal administration method. The former pharmaceutical guide was modified and handling recommendations were made for each drug. Eleven dispersable, 26 liquid and 8 powder new forms were included. Conclusions: This work has turned the pharmaceutical guide of the hospital in a useful tool for the prescription, validation and administration of medicines to patients with dysphagia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Navarro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa Ballester, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vial Escolano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forcano García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Revisar la guía farmacoterapéutica del hospital para incluir formas farmacéuticas adaptadas a pacientes con disfagia y recomendaciones para la administración de medicamentos en estos pacientes. Método: Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica para elaborar las recomendaciones generales de administración de medicamentos en disfagia. Se comprobó para cada principio activo: a) si existían comercializadas otras formas farmacéuticas más recomendables; b) si había posibilidad de manipular los comprimidos o cápsulas, y c) si eran compatibles con alimentos. Resultados: Se desarrolló un algoritmo de decisión para ayudar en la selección de la forma farmacéutica y de su método de administración. Se incluyó un apartado de recomendaciones de administración para cada principio activo. La búsqueda supuso la inclusión de once formas bucodispersables, veintiséis líquidas y ocho como polvo. Conclusiones: La revisión mejorará la utilidad de la guía como instrumento para la prescripción, validación y administración de medicamentos en disfagia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(3): 198-208, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación de la guía farmacoterapéutica de un hospital sociosanitario a pacientes con disfagia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27864</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
