<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050501</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposals for the reform of public health services in Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the year 2004 the government of Catalonia undertook a processto reform its public health services. In this context, it created aworking groupinvolving experts from diverse backgrounds toanalyse the reforms to be undertaken, the Scientific Committee forthe Reform of Public Health in Catalonia. Its members producedeight documents on specific aspects of public health, from which aglobal report of the Committee was compiled by the end of 2005.This paper makes a synthesis of their production, and includes asan annex their recommendations and proposals. Public health policiesshould be structured around three main goal: the reduction ofhealth inequalities, the control and removal of social and environmentalrisks, and effective improvements in quality of life. Toreach them, common criteria are defined as main directions. Theseare based in favouring decentralization of public health servicesand their administration, linking public health activities with healthcare services, designing interventions with a population perspective,and reinforcing cross-sectional implications of public health.The work of this Committee is produced in the context of an internationaldebate on the future of public health services and the disproportionbetween its contribution to health and well being and itsresources and visibility. The Committee produced proposals andrecommendations which can be grouped in five facets: consolidatinga solid and coherent system, developing an organizationalreform, defining a port-folio of services, adopting improvements inmanagement, and taking into account cross sectional aspects relatingto public health</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antó, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalbí, Joan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pané, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peray, Josep L. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el año 2004 el gobierno de Cataluña planteó la necesidad deabordar la reforma de sus servicios de salud pública. En este contextocreó un Comité Científico con expertos de diversas procedencias.Sus miembros generaron ocho documentos específicos sobredistintos aspectos de la salud pública, y de ellos surgió un informeglobal colegiado del Comité, el cual se presentó a finales del año2005. En este artículo se presenta un resumen de estas aportacionesy en anexo sus recomendaciones y propuestas. Se propone que laspolíticas de salud pública se habrían de articular en torno a tres grandesobjetivos generales: la reducción de las desigualdades de salud,el control y eliminación de los riesgos ambientales y sociales; y lamejora efectiva en la calidad de vida. Para impulsar estos objetivosse adoptan unos criterios comunes como ejes de trabajo. Estos sebasan en: favorecer la descentralización de la oferta de servicios ysu gestión, vincular las actividades de salud publica a las estructurasasistenciales, diseñar las intervenciones con una perspectiva poblacional,y potenciar las implicaciones transversales de la salud pública.Las aportaciones de este Comité se producen en un contextointernacional de debate sobre el futuro de los servicios de saludpública y la desproporción existente entre su aportación al bienestary la salud, su visibilidad y recursos. El Comité produjo una serie derecomendaciones y propuestas que se pueden agrupar en cincograndes ejes: consolidar un sistema sólido y coherente, desarrollaruna reforma organizativa, definir una cartera de servicios, aplicarmejoras de gestión, y tener en cuenta los aspectos transversales queafectan a la salud pública</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(5): 567-583, sept.-oct. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050501</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuestas de reforma de los servicios de salud pública en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32485</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22552^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16672</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
