<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75878</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nodal management in preservation protocols</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Preservation protocols in patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck should include treatment of the nodal areas. After treatment with radiotherapy or chemoradiotherapy, patients with suspected persistence of nodal disease are candidates for surgical treatment. However, there is no agreement in the literature on the management of patients in whom conservative treatment achieves complete response of the cervical tumor. Some authors choose dissection independently of the grade of response achieved, while others believe that watchful management should be used in patients with complete response. If surgery is required, there is widespread consensus that, when correctly indicated, selective dissection is as effective as more extensive dissection in disease control. Persistence of residual nodal disease after radiotherapy or chemoradiotherapy has prognostic implications, including in patients with fewer possibilities of disease control and reduced survival(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los protocolos terapéuticos de preservación en los pacientes con carcinomas escamosos de cabeza y cuello deben integrar el tratamiento de las áreas ganglionares. Después de un tratamiento con radioterapia o quimiorradioterapia, los pacientes en los que hay una sospecha de persistencia de enfermedad ganglionar son candidatos a tratamiento quirúrgico. Sin embargo, no hay acuerdo en la bibliografía en el manejo de los pacientes en los que el tratamiento conservador consigue una respuesta completa del tumor cervical. Unos autores optan por la realización de vaciamientos, independientemente del grado de respuesta conseguido, en tanto que otros consideran que estos pacientes con respuesta completa serían tributarios de observación. En caso de requerir un tratamiento quirúrgico, hay unanimidad en considerar que, convenientemente indicados, los vaciamientos selectivos cuentan con una capacidad de control de la enfermedad similar a la conseguida con vaciamientos más extensos. La persistencia de enfermedad residual ganglionar después de un tratamiento con radioterapia o quimiorradioterapia tiene implicaciones pronósticas, contando los pacientes con menores posibilidades de control de la enfermedad y una reducción en la supervivencia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;60(supl.2): 34-42, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75878</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo ganglionar en pacientes sometidos a protocolos de preservación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
