<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60366</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical&amp;-Pathological Features of Cutaneous Melanomas Diagnosed in a Mediterranean Tertiary Hospital Between 1990 and 2004: A Comparison Between Sexes and Age Groups and Analysis of Long&amp;#8209;term Outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The incidence of malignant melanoma has increased over recent decades. Early diagnosis continues to be essential for effective treatment. Our objective was to analyze cutaneous malignant melanomas diagnosed over a 15-year period in a tertiary hospital for trends towards earlier diagnosis and to identify subgroups with poorer prognosis. Material and methods. Retrospective analysis of primary cutaneous melanomas analyzed in the pathology department of Hospital La Paz, Madrid, Spain, between 1990 and 2004. Results. In total, 526 melanomas were diagnosed. The mean (SD) Breslow thickness was 2.63 (4.84) mm and the median thickness was 0.98 mm (range, 0-65 mm). The mean size (widest point) was 16.59 (12.11) mm. The most common histological type was surface-spreading melanoma and the most common site was the trunk. Melanomas detected in men were generally larger and thicker than in women (P = 0.05). Individuals aged over 60 years consulted for significantly thicker and larger tumors than younger individuals. The incidence of malignant melanomas has increased steadily over the years whereas the mean Breslow thickness and size have decreased. Conclusions. Diagnosis of melanoma in Spain is made increasingly earlier, although locally advanced tumors are still sometimes seen in men and in individuals aged over 60 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado-Jiménez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Beato, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayor-Arenal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villeta-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arranz-Sánchez, DM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia-Delfa, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En las últimas décadas está aumentando la incidencia de melanoma maligno (MM) y el diagnóstico precoz sigue siendo esencial para conseguir su curación. Nuestro objetivo fue analizar los MM cutáneos diagnosticados durante 15 años en un hospital terciario para comprobar si existe una tendencia favorable hacia un diagnóstico cada vez más precoz e intentar identificar grupos de población con MM de peor pronóstico. Material y métodos. Análisis retrospectivo de los melanomas cutáneos primarios analizados en el Departamento de Anatomía Patológica del Hospital La Paz entre 1990 y 2004. Resultados. Se diagnosticaron en total 526 melanomas. El espesor medio de Breslow fue de 2,63 mm (desviación estándar [DE] 4,84) y la mediana de 0,98 mm (0-65 mm); el tamaño medio (diámetro mayor) fue de 16,59 mm (DE 12,11); el tipo histológico más frecuente fue el melanoma de extensión superficial y la localización más habitual el tronco. Los melanomas detectados en varones tendieron a ser más grandes y de mayor espesor (p = 0,05) que los de las mujeres. Los mayores de 60 años consultaron con tumores significativamente más gruesos y de mayor diámetro que los pacientes más jóvenes. A lo largo de estos años, ha aumentado progresivamente el número de MM, pero han disminuido el Breslow medio y el tamaño. Conclusiones. El diagnóstico del melanoma en nuestro medio es cada vez más precoz, pero los varones y los mayores de 60 años en ocasiones aún consultan con tumores localmente avanzados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(6): 476-485, ago. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60366</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características-patológicas de los melanomas cutáneos diagnosticados en un hospital terciario mediterráneo entre 1990 y 2004: comparación entre sexos, por grupos de edad y evolución a lo largo del tiempo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
