<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111839</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reversed differential cyanosis: what does it mean?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Differential cyanosis &#150;better oxygenation of the upper (preductal) part of the body with respect to the lower (postductal) part&#150; is a well-known condition in pediatrics, being persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn its most common cause. On the other hand, reversed differential cyanosis (RDC) &#150;upper body less oxygenated than the inferior&#150; is a rare condition. This report describes two newborns presenting RDC: a case with transposition of the great arteries with pulmonary hypertension and a case with supracardiac total anomalous pulmonary vein connection. We review the existing literature and discuss its physiopathological bases, demonstrating that this condition is pathognomonic of severe congenital cardiopathy. Therefore, simultaneous preductal and postductal oxygen saturation should be always documented as part of the evaluation of the cyanotic newborn(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perin, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin Álvarez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Sánchez la Fuente, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briales Casero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vázquez del Rey, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cianosis diferencial &#150;término que indica una mejor oxigenación de la parte superior del cuerpo (preductal) respecto a la inferior (posductal)&#150; es un hallazgo bien conocido en pediatría, y su causa más frecuente es la hipertensión pulmonar persistente del recién nacido. Por otro lado, hay casos excepcionales en los que se registra una cianosis diferencial inversa y la parte superior del cuerpo está peor oxigenada que la inferior. En este trabajo presentamos 2 casos clínicos con dicho hallazgo: un recién nacido con transposición de grandes vasos con hipertensión pulmonar y otro con drenaje venoso pulmonar anómalo total supracardiaco. Se revisa la bibliografía y se explica la fisiopatología de la cianosis diferencial inversa, demostrándose que es patognomónica de una cardiopatía congénita severa. Concluimos que la medición simultánea de la saturación en el territorio preductal y posductal mediante pulsioximetría debería ser siempre parte integrante de la valoración del recién nacido cianótico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;71(4): 111-111[e82-e87], abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111839</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cianosis diferencial inversa: ¿qué significa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
