<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91845</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxious symptomatology and Joint Hypermobility Syndrome (JHS) in a group of Chilean undergraduate students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To test the relationship between anxiety, joint hypermobility syndrome (JHS) and other associated variables, and identify physical and psychological variables that distinguish individuals with and without JHS. Method: One hundred undergraduate students were assessed using the following instruments: Brighton´s criteria for JHS, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI), Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS), Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), a questionnaire of neuropsychosomatic affections (ALPIN) and a questionnaire of anxiety disorders. Results: Anxiety scores measured by the HADS and STAI (state scale) were significantly higher among participants with JHS. A set of physical and psychological variables turned out to be statistically significant when distinguishing students with or without JHS. Conclusions: Participants with JHS reported relatively higher levels of anxiety than those without JHS in this study. We suggest it is possible to detect the presence of JHS by assessing physical and psychopathological symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bulbena Vilarrasa, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Silva, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baeza Velasco, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la relación entre ansiedad, Síndrome de Hiperlaxitud Articular (SHA) y otras variables asociadas, e identificar las variables físicas y psicológicas que en conjunto distinguen a las personas con SHA. Método: Estudio caso-control con 100 estudiantes evaluados con los criterios de Brighton para SHA, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI), Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS), Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), un cuestionario de afecciones neuropsicosomáticas (ALDIA) y un cuestionario de trastornos de ansiedad. Resultados: Las puntuaciones obtenidas mediante el HADS ansiedad y STAI estado fueron significativamente mayores entre los estudiantes con SHA. Un conjunto de variables físicas y sicológicas resultaron significativas para distinguir a los participantes con SHA. Conclusiones: Los estudiantes con SHA presentan niveles de ansiedad relativamente mayores que los estudiantes sin SHA en este estudio. Se sugiere que mediante la exploración de síntomas físicos y también psicopatológicos es posible detectar la presencia de SHA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;16(1): 1-12, jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sintomatología ansiosa y síndrome de hiperlaxitud articular en un grupo de universitario chilenos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7761^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
