<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158374</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Portal vein thrombosis as a cause of thrombocytopenia persistent in neonatal alloimmune neutropenia HNA-2a</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The alloimmune neonatal neutropenia (NAN) is a rare condition that affects newborn maternal IgG antibody production against specific antigens of neutrophils (HNA) of paternal inheritance and not present on neutrophils from the mother and in antigens present in the fetus. These maternal antibodies pass the fetus through the placenta causing the elimination of the fetal neutrophils, increasing the risk of infection during the neonatal period. There are seven subtypes of HNA, but the most often related to NAN are the HNA-1a, HNA-1b and HNA-2a. The treatment of choice is G-CSF and refractory cases, intravenous immunoglobulin or corticosteroids, are other treatment options. Neonatal sepsis and persistent thrombocytopenia are two complications frequently associated with NAN. Thrombocytopenia in NAN, commonly occurs by three mechanisms: sepsis own, iatrogenic effect of G-CSF and cross-reactivity between antibodies and platelets anti-HNA. In our case report we present a fourth mechanism, so multifactorial and associated with the previous three mechanisms explains the persistent thrombocytopenia in our case NAN (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urán Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocamora Romero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morena Campillo, A de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echenique Lara, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gramage Tormo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neutropenia aloinmune neonatal (NAN) es una patología poco frecuente, que se debe a la producción materna de anticuerpos IgG frente a antígenos específicos de los neutrófilos fetales (HNA), de herencia paterna y no presentes en los neutrófilos de la madre. Estos anticuerpos maternos pasan al feto a través de la placenta, provocando la eliminación de los neutrófilos fetales e incrementando el riesgo de infección durante el periodo neonatal. Existen siete subtipos de HNA, pero los que más a menudo se relacionan con la NAN son el HNA-1a, el HNA-1b y el HNA-2a. El tratamiento de elección es el factor estimulante de colonias granulocíticas (G-CSF) y, en casos refractarios, otras opciones terapéuticas son la gammaglobulina intravenosa o los corticoides. La sepsis neonatal y la trombopenia persistente son dos complicaciones frecuentemente asociadas a la NAN. La trombopenia en la NAN se produce comúnmente por tres mecanismos: la propia sepsis, el efecto yatrogénico del G-CSF, y por reacción cruzada entre los anticuerpos anti-HNA y las plaquetas. En este caso clínico presentamos un cuarto mecanismo que, de forma multifactorial y asociado a los tres mecanismos previos, explica la trombopenia persistente en nuestro caso de NAN (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;74(10): e222-e225, nov. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis portal como causa de trombopenia persistente en la neutropenia aloinmune neonatal con anticuerpos HNA-2a</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
