<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053998</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of surgery in metastases from breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with distant metastases from breast cancer have always been considered terminally ill and as such candidates for palliative treatment only. However, due to new therapeutic modalities in oncology, survival in these patients has improved. Furthermore, in 5% of patients, metastasis from breast cancer is limited to a single solid organ (oligometastatic state). Because of these two factors, surgery is now being performed as a component of multidisciplinary treatment for hepatic, lung and bone metastases from a primary breast tumor. In the present article, we review the different published series, focussing discussion on two issues: selecting candidates for liver, lung or bone resection, and identifying prognostic factors for recurrence and/or survival following surgical excision of metastases to these sites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellón, Juan M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, Hipólito J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Siempre se ha considerado que el cáncer de mama con metástasis a distancia es una enfermedad incurable y, consecuentemente, la paciente es candidata a recibir sólo tratamiento médico paliativo. Sin embargo, la obtención de mayores éxitos de supervivencia tras los nuevos regímenes terapéuticos en el cáncer de mama diseminado y la existencia de un 5% de enfermas con cáncer de mama metastásico confinado a un solo órgano sólido (estado oligometastásico) son dos aspectos determinantes en la introducción de la cirugía como parte integral en el tratamiento multidisciplinario de las metástasis hepáticas, pulmonares y óseas de origen mamario. Esta revisión actualiza las diferentes series publicadas centrando la discusión en dos aspectos: la selección de las candidatas ideales para la cirugía exerética de hígado, pulmón o partes óseas y la identificación de los factores pronósticos de recurrencia y/o supervivencia tras la extirpación de tales metástasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);82(1): 3-10, jul. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053998</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la cirugía en las metástasis del cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
