<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155918</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: current epidemiology, therapeutic regimens, new drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multidrug and extensively resistant tuberculosis are especially severe forms of the disease for which no efficacious therapy exists in many cases. All the countries in the world have registered cases, although most of them are diagnosed in resource-limited countries from Asia, Africa and South America. For adequate treatment, first- and second-line antituberculosis drugs have to be judiciously used, but the development of new drugs with full activity, good tolerability and little toxicity is urgently needed. There are some drugs in development, some of which are already available through expanded-access programs (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivancos, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ayerbe, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tuberculosis multirrresistente y extremadamente resistente constituyen formas especialmente graves de la enfermedad, al no existir en muchos casos fármacos eficaces en su tratamiento. Afecta a todos los países del mundo, aunque la inmensa mayoría de los casos se concentran en los países con pocos recursos de Asia, África y América del Sur. El tratamiento contempla el uso adecuado de los fármacos de primera y segunda línea de los que se dispone, pero se hace precisa la incorporación de nuevos fármacos con actividad plena, buena tolerabilidad y poca toxicidad. Hay algunos fármacos en desarrollo, algunos de los cuales se encuentra disponible en programas de acceso expandido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(supl.1): 35-38, sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155918</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis multirresistente: epidemiología actual, esquemas terapéuticos, nuevos fármacos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24471</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30997^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
