<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103744</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An interesting experience on the use of information and population data bases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In order to support decisions and analyze outcomes, the Spanish Health System has shown a great interest in developing data bases and high quality information systems. Nevertheless the use of these data bases are limited, not very systematized and, some times, their accessibility may be difficult. Material and methods. We describe in this review the experience in using the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Science (ICES, Ontario, Canada) as an efficient model to improve the usefulness of these data bases. Results. Under restrictive conditions of confidentiality and privacy, the ICES has the legal capacity to use several population based data bases, for research projects and reports. ICES's functional structure (with an administrative and scientific level) is an interesting framework since it guarantees its independent and economic assessment. Discussion. To date, its scientific production has been high in many areas of knowledge and open to those interested, with points of view of many health care professionals (including management), for whom the quality of research is of the ultimate importance, to be able to access these resources(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Expósito, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Johnson, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El adecuado funcionamiento de nuestro sistema sanitario requiere de bases de datos y sistemas de información de calidad para basar sus decisiones y analizar los resultados. Sin embargo, pese a los tenaces esfuerzos de recogida de datos llevados a cabo, la utilización de este tipo de bases es escasa, poco sistematizada y con excesivas cortapisas para lograr acceder a ellas. Material y métodos. Describimos en esta revisión la experiencia del Institute for Clinical Evaluative Science (ICES, Ontario, Canadá) como modelo eficiente y que puede servir de referente en nuestro país para mejorar la utilización de los sistemas de información. Resultados. El ICES está legalmente capacitado para, bajo condiciones estrictas de confidencialidad y seguridad, utilizar numerosas bases de datos poblacionales estatales para elaborar informes y proyectos de investigación. Su estructura de funcionamiento (con un nivel administrativo y un nivel científico) constituye un marco de trabajo interesante ya que garantiza su autonomía de criterio y económica. Discusión. Hasta la fecha su nivel de producción científica ha sido elevado, sobre áreas de conocimiento muy diversas y abierta a los intereses y puntos de vista de muchos profesionales de la salud (asistenciales y gestores), para los cuales la calidad de la investigación es a la postre el criterio de mayor importancia para acceder a estos recursos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;27(5): 288-294, sept.-oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una experiencia interesante en el uso de la información y de las bases de datos poblacionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51835^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51835^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
