<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038581</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Topiramate: an alternative for patients with neuropathic pain refractory to treament with opiates and other anticonvulsants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuropathic pain in cancer patients is a difficult problem,given the limited effectiveness of treatments that raisea therapeutic challenge for health professionals providingcare to these patients. Recent studies have shownagain the effectiveness of opiates for the management ofthis type of pain. The introduction of gabapentin has givenhope to patients and health professionals, but it has therapeuticfailures with a difficult rescue.We present a series of 16 patients with advanced cancerand neuropathic pain refractory to prior treatments, includinggabapentin, that received low doses of topiramate asrescue therapy. Pain relief was satisfactory in 7 of the 16patients treated and pain severity score improved morethan 50%.We describe the patient characteristics, the assessment scalesthat were used and the side effects that were reported. Threepatients discontinued the study medication before the endof the study because of psychological effects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cevas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Llano, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Somovilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor neuropático en los pacientes oncológicos representaun reto difícil, con tratamientos poco exitosos, querepresentan un desafío terapéutico para los clínicos dedicadosal cuidado de estos pacientes. Recientes estudios hanvuelto a demostrar la utilidad de los tratamientos con opiáceosen este tipo de dolor. La introducción de la gabapentinaha representado una esperanza para los pacientes y lossanitarios, pero presenta fracasos terapéuticos de difícilrescate.Se presenta una casuística de 16 pacientes afectos decáncer avanzado, con dolor neuropático resistente a lostratamientos empleados, inclusive la gabapentina, introduciendoen ellos el topiramato a dosis bajas como forma detratamiento de rescate. De los 16 pacientes tratados, 7 logranun control satisfactorio del dolor, rebajando la escalade intensidad del dolor más de un 50%.Se reflejan las características de los pacientes, las escalasde valoración empleadas y los efectos secundarios registrados.Tres de los pacientes abandonaron la medicaciónantes de tiempo por efectos psicológicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(2): 93-97, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Topiramato: una alternativa para los pacientes con dolor neuropático de baja respuesta a los opioides y otros anticonvulsivantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9194^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
