<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159744</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal scarring in children under 36 months hospitalised for acute pyelonephritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Acute pyelonephritis (APN) is one of the most common causes of serious bacterial infection in infants. Renal scarring is the most prevalent long-term complication. Objectives. To review the incidence of renal scarring within 6 months after an episode of APN in children under 36 months and its relationship with imaging studies, clinical settings, and bacteriology. Method. A retrospective study of previously healthy patients aged one to 36 months, admitted for a first episode of APN, with a minimum follow-up of 6 months. Demographic and clinical variables were collected along with bacteriology, renal and bladder ultrasound scan, voiding cystourethrography, DMSA-scintigraphy, and re-infection events. Results. A total of 125 patients were included in the study, of which 60% were male, the large majority (92%) febrile, and due to E. coli (74.6%). There was a history of prenatal ultrasound scan changes in 15.4%. Ultrasound scan found dilation of the urinary tract in 22.1%. Voiding cystourethrography was performed on 70 patients: 54.3% no abnormalities, 12.8% vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) grade i-iii, and 32.9% iv-v grade VUR. Six patients had iv-v grade VUR with a normal ultrasound scan. Adherence to DMSA-scintigraphy at 6 months was only 61% of that indicated. Renal scarring was found in 44.3% of those in which it was performed (60 cases). Conclusions. Almost half (44%) DMSA-scintigraphy in children aged one to 36 months hospitalised for APN show renal scarring at 6 months, which was found to be associated with the re-infection events and the iv-v grade VUR. There was no relationship between scarring and the bacteriology or the elevations of inflammatory biochemical markers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchiz Cárdenas, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordón Martínez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Pérez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urda Cardona, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carazo Gallego, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Azor, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Fernández, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Una de las causas más frecuentes de infección bacteriana grave en lactantes es la pielonefritis aguda (PNFA), cuya secuela más prevalente a largo plazo es la instauración de cicatrices renales. Objetivos. Revisar la incidencia de cicatrices renales a los 6 meses de un episodio de PNFA en niños menores de 36 meses y su relación con la clínica, las pruebas de imagen y la bacteriología. Método. Estudio retrospectivo de pacientes de uno a 36 meses previamente sanos ingresados por un primer episodio de PNFA, con un seguimiento mínimo de 6 meses. Se recogieron las variables demográficas junto con bacteriología, ecografía, cistourografía miccional seriada, recidivas y gammagrafía-DMSA. Resultados. Se incluyeron 125 pacientes, 60% varones, la mayoría febriles al ingreso (92%), debido a E. coli (74,6%). Existía antecedente de alteración ecográfica prenatal solo en el 15,4%. La ecografía detectó dilatación de la vía urinaria en el 22,1%. En 70 pacientes se indicó cistourografía miccional seriada: 54,3% sin anomalías, 12,8% con reflujo vesicoureteral (RVU) grado i-iii y 32,9% con RVU iv-v. Seis pacientes presentaban RVU iv-v con ecografías normales. La adherencia a la gammagrafía DMSA a los 6 meses fue solo del 61% de los indicados. De los efectuados (60 casos), en un 44,3% se hallaron cicatrices renales, relacionadas significativamente con la recurrencia y el RVU iv-v, pero no con la bacteriología ni con la elevación de reactantes. Conclusiones. El 44% de las gammagrafías-DMSA de pacientes de uno a 36 meses hospitalizados por PNFA desarrolla cicatrices renales a los 6 meses. Estas se relacionaron con las recurrencias y el RVU grave, pero no con la bacteriología y los reactantes inflamatorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(2): 76-80, feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cicatrices renales en menores de 36 meses ingresados por pielonefritis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d683^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
