<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128365</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality standards in a rheumatology day-care hospital unit. The proposal of the Spanish Society of Rheumatology Day Hospitals&#146; Working Group</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. In recent years, the Rheumatology Day-Care Hospital Units (DHUs) have undergone extensive development. However, the quality standards are poorly documented and mainly limited to structure items rather than including broad and specific areas of this specialty. Objective. To develop specific quality standards for Rheumatology DHUs. Methods. After a systematic review of the literature and related documents, a working group (WG) involving 8 DHU-experienced rheumatologists developed an initial proposal of the quality standards, under the supervision of an expert methodologist. A second round was held by the WG group to review the initial proposal and to consider further suggestions. Once the content was agreed upon by consensus, a final report was prepared. Results. Seventeen structure standards, 25 process standards and 10 results standards were defined, with special emphasis on specific aspects of the Rheumatology DHU. The proposal includes: (1) essential standards to (2) excellent standards, (3) a Rheumatology DHU services portfolio and (4) performance criteria. Conclusions. The proposed quality standards are the basis for developing the indicators and other management tools for Rheumatology DHU, thereby ensuring a patient-oriented practice based on both the evidence and the experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Centeno, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Fernández, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vicuña, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egües Dubuc, César Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustabad Reyes, Sagrario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pampín, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Ivorra, José Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsa, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loza, Estíbaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. En los últimos años, las Unidades de Hospitalización de Día (UHdD) en Reumatología han experimentado un amplio desarrollo. Sin embargo, existe escasa documentación respecto a estándares de calidad, que mayoritariamente se limita a la estructura y no incluye aspectos específicos de la especialidad. Objetivo. Desarrollar estándares de calidad específicos para las UHdD en Reumatología. Métodos. Tras una revisión sistemática de la literatura y de documentos relacionados, un grupo de trabajo (GT) de 8 reumatólogos, bajo la supervisión de un metodólogo experto, elaboró una primera propuesta de estándares de calidad. Se realizó una segunda ronda para su revisión y sugerencias por todo el GT. Consensuado el contenido, se realizó un informe final. Resultados. Se definieron 17 estándares de estructura, 25 de proceso y 10 de resultados, con especial énfasis en aspectos específicos de una UHdD de Reumatología. La propuesta incluye: 1) estándares imprescindibles; 2) estándares de excelencia; 3) cartera de servicios de una UHdD reumatológica, y 4) criterios de funcionamiento. Conclusiones. Los estándares de calidad propuestos son la base para la elaboración de indicadores y de otras herramientas de gestión para las UHdD reumatológicas que garanticen una práctica homogénea, centrada en el paciente y basada en la evidencia y en la experiencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);10(6): 380-388, nov.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128365</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estándares de calidad en una Unidad de Hospitalización de Día reumatológica. Propuesta del Grupo de Trabajo de Hospitales de Día de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
