<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86257</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Snake venom poisoning in the Iberian peninsula</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thirteen species of snakes are native to the Iberian peninsula. Ten belong to the Colubridae family and, except for the Montpellier snake and the False smooth snake, they are not poisonous. The three species of Viper (Asp viper, Snub-nosed viper and Seoane&#146;s viper) are poisonous and are the most common cause of snake venom poisoning in Spain. A number of features differentiate the two families and even enable individual species to be identified. This identification of the species, as well as the signs and symptoms of poisoning are important for correct patient management. This update outlines the key features that enable the various species of snakes to be identified, and the basis of outpatient (first aid and initial medical treatment) and hospital treatment of snake bites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogué Xarau, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sierra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la península Ibérica hay 13 especies autóctonas de ofidios. Diez de ellas pertenecen a la familia de los colúbridos, que no son venenosos excepto la culebra bastarda y la culebra de cogulla. Las 3 especies de vipéridos (víbora áspid, víbora hocicuda y víbora de Seoane) son venenosas y son la causa más frecuente de envenenamiento por ofidios en España. Una serie de rasgos permiten diferenciar ambas familias e incluso identificar a cada una de las especies. La identificación de la especie y de los signos y síntomas de envenenamiento son importantes para el correcto tratamiento del paciente. En esta actualización se exponen las claves que permiten diferenciar las diversas especies de ofidios, así como las bases de la terapéutica extrahospitalaria (primeros auxilios y tratamiento inicial en el centro de salud) y hospitalaria de las mordeduras de serpiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(3): 136-141, mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ofidismo en la península Ibérica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13290^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13290^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13291^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13290^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23120^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
