<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165346</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in body image of young normal weight and overweight/obese people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obesity is a chronic and growing problem. Its study requires the understanding of multiple associated variables. Body image has an important role in the health condition. The purpose of this study was to compare the perception of body image of young normal weight and overweight/obese people. Material and methods: A sample of 376 young men and women aged 18 to 25 was compared. Body mass index classified them in two groups: normal weight and overweight/obese. To evaluate body image participants answered the Multidimensional Body Self Relations Questionnaire (MBSRQ). To evaluate eating behavior they answered the Eating Disorders Inventory (EDI-3). Results: Overweight/obese young people are less satisfied with their appearance and their body when it is evaluated separately. They evaluate their physical condition and their physical abilities badly. They show fewer behaviors intended to maintain or improve their physical appearance, perceive a worse diagnosis of their health and show less body satisfaction. They are more concerned about their weight and they are obsessed about thinness. In addition, women, compared to men, have a worse negative assessment of their body image. Conclusion: Despite the low assessment that overweight/obese students made in relation to their body, they are not willing to perform activities that allow them to change their condition. Further research is needed in order to develop preventive programs and more treatments that are effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruzat-Mandich, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Castrillón, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aravena Winkler, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haemmerli Delucchi, Constance</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizana Calderón, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la obesidad es un problema crónico y en aumento. Su estudio requiere comprender múltiples variables asociadas. La imagen corporal tiene un papel importante en esta condición de salud. El propósito de este estudio fue comparar la percepción de imagen corporal de jóvenes normopeso y con sobrepeso/obesidad. Material y métodos: se comparó a 376 jóvenes de ambos sexos, de una muestra general y sin tratamiento, de entre 18 y 25 años de edad, clasificados por su índice de masa corporal en dos grupos: grupo normopeso y grupo sobrepeso u obesidad. Para evaluar imagen corporal, los participantes respondieron el Multidimensional Body Self Relations Questionnaire (MBSRQ) y el Eating Disorders Inventory (EDI-3). Resultados: los participantes con sobrepeso/obesidad están menos satisfechos con su apariencia y con su cuerpo cuando este es evaluado por partes, evalúan peor su estado físico y/o sus capacidades físicas, presentan menos conductas orientadas a mantener o mejorar su forma física, perciben un peor diagnóstico de su salud y tienen menor satisfacción corporal. Asimismo, están más preocupados por su peso, se autoclasifican más por su peso y presentan una mayor obsesión por la delgadez. Además, las mujeres, en comparación con los hombres, presentan una evaluación más negativa de su imagen corporal. Conclusión: a pesar de la mala evaluación que los estudiantes con sobrepeso/obesidad realizan en relación a su cuerpo, no están dispuestos a realizar actividades concretas que les permitan cambiar su estado. Es necesario seguir investigando con el fin de desarrollar programas preventivos y de tratamiento más efectivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 847-855, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en imagen corporal de jóvenes con normopeso y con sobrepeso/obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
