<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116895</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantification of the loss of opportunity in professional medical responsibility</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The doctrinal and jurisprudential creation of the «loss of a chance» concept has helped mitigate the existing shortcomings regarding compensation of defects of praxis cases. However, the challenge remains to standardize criteria to quantify fairy and equally these «loss of a chance» cases. The amounts for compensation in the event of lack of information, gestational ultrasound control errors or diagnostic delay in neoplasia can be very different today. Whilst in lack of information cases the criterion of using a correction factor of around 50% to compensation can be considered practically established, in the remaining two cases the options proposed by this article can be considered a trend, not yet consolidated. Homogenization of the legal criteria for evaluating these cases, by applying the quantification adjustments presented in this article, would contribute to substantial improvements in this area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Durán, Esperanza L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arimany-Manso, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saigí-Ullastre, Umbert</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La creación doctrinal y jurisprudencial del concepto de pérdida de oportunidad ha contribuido a aminorar las carencias existentes en materia de indemnización ante supuestos defectos de praxis. Sin embargo, persiste el reto de sistematizar los criterios para poder cuantificar de forma equitativa y justa estos supuestos de pérdida de oportunidad. Las cuantías indemnizatorias en los supuestos pragmáticos de defecto de información, error en el control ecográfico gestacional o retraso diagnóstico en procesos neoplásicos, resultan muy dispares en la actualidad. Si bien en los supuestos de defecto de información se puede considerar prácticamente establecido el criterio de utilizar un factor de corrección aproximado del 50% a la indemnización, en los restantes 2 supuestos las opciones propuestas por este artículo pueden considerarse una tendencia aún no consolidada. La homogeneización de los criterios jurisprudenciales vigentes de valoración de los supuestos mediante la aplicación ajustada al caso de las propuestas de cuantificación que presenta este artículo contribuiría a mejoras sustanciales en este área (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;39(4): 157-161, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116895</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuantificación de la pérdida de oportunidad en responsabilidad profesional médica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7520^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36311^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36311^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
