<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117763</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Puberal gynecomastia: a comparison between the inferior periareolar approach and the concentric circle technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/purpose. The main reason to indicate the surgical treatment in pubertal gynecomastia is the psychological effect on the adolescent. The aim of this paper is to describe our experience in the surgical treatment of this condition, comparing the results obtained depending on the type of approach used. Material and methods. In our department, the approach for the subtotal mastectomy depends mainly on the gynecomastia grade. We use an inferior periareolar incision in grades I and II, and a concentric circle technique in grade III of Simon&#146;s classification. A retrospective review was conducted to identify all adolescent patients that underwent to gynecomastia surgical treatment between 2007 and 2012. We compared the results obtained in each incision group by parametric statistical tests. Results. A total of 29 mastectomies were performed in 15 patients. The mean age of surgery was 13.75 ± 1.06 years ([11-15] years). The presentation in all cases consisted in a progressive increase in size of the mammary gland, without associated symptoms. In half of patients there was a history of obesity or overweight. We performed the concentric (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Bueno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Atuan, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Esgueda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galeano Ricaño, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragagnini Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estors Sastre, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. El principal motivo de consulta e indicación de tratamiento quirúrgico en la ginecomastia puberal es la afectación psicológica que produce en el adolescente. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de esta patología, comparando los resultados obtenidos según el tipo de abordaje utilizado. Material y métodos. En nuestro Servicio, el abordaje empleado para la mastectomía subtotal depende del grado de ginecomastia, utilizándose la incisión periareolar inferior en los grados I-II y el doble anillo cutáneo en el tipo III según la clasificación de Simon. Hemos estudiado de forma descriptiva retrospectiva a los pacientes intervenidos de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;26(3): 129-134, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ginecomastia puberal: comparación entre el abordaje periareolar inferior y el de doble anillo cutáneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30787^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6328^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7796^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
