<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25896</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Discriminal desviation parameter in the Law of Comparative Judgment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In different publications (López &amp; Hidalgo, 2001, p. 331; Luce et al., 1990; Cliff, 1993; Lee, 2001) it has offered itself evidence brings over of the limitations that the tests of adjustment present at the moment of verify the suppositions of a model that uses a functional representation. An example of such types of models they are the based ones on the Law of the Thurstone&#146;s comparative Judgment. The results of this study do not recommend to interpret the parameter of disciminal desviation of the Law of the Comparative Judgment, as an index of the degree of confusion that provoke the stimuli in the judges and in turn will be the possibility that really they are the scale values obtained with the above mentioned model, which should be interpreted as an index of the degree confusion that they provoke in the subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herencia-Leva, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Meléndez, Cristino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En diferentes publicaciones (López e Hidalgo, 2001, p. 331; Luce et al., 1990; Cliff, 1993; Lee, 2001) se ha ofrecido evidencia acerca de las limitaciones que las pruebas de ajuste presentan a la hora de comprobar los supuestos un modelo que utiliza una representación funcional. Un ejemplo de tales tipos de modelos son los basados en la Ley del Juicio Comparativo de Thurstone (1927a). Los resultados de este estudio no recomiendan interpretar el parámetro de desviación discriminante de la Ley del Juicio Comparativo como un índice del grado de confusión que provocan los estímulos en los jueces y a su vez abre la posibilidad de que realmente sean los valores escalares obtenidos con dicho modelo los que se deban interpretar como un índice del grado confusión que provocan en los sujetos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(3): 489-492, ago. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El parámetro de desviación discriminante en la Ley del Juicio Comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24884</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7382</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
