<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155916</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resistant gram-negative bacteria. Therapeutic approach and risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The rapid spread of multidrug-resistant bacteria has become a serious threat, especially in critical care units, thereby prolonging the hospital stay. Enterobacteriaceae have a high capacity to adapt to any environment. Plasmids are the reason behind their expansion. The choice of empiric therapy for intra-abdominal or urinary infections requires knowledge of the intrinsic microbiological variability of each hospital or critical care unit, as well as the source of infection, safety or antibiotic toxicity, interaction with other drugs, the dosage regimen and the presence of risk factors. Carbapenems are the drug of choice in the case of suspected infection by ESBL-producing Enterobacteriaceae. The new ceftazidime/avibactam and ceftolozane/tazobactam drugs are opening up promising new horizons in the treatment of multidrug-resistant Enterobacteriaceae (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salgado, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maseda, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La rápida diseminación de las bacterias multirresistentes se ha convertido en una grave amenaza, especialmente en las unidades de cuidados críticos, prolongando la estancia hospitalaria. Las enterobacterias tienen una alta capacidad de adaptación a cualquier medio. Son los plásmidos los que les facilita su expansión. La elección de un tratamiento empírico adecuado para la infección intraabdominal complicada y para la infección urinaria exige el conocimiento de la variabilidad microbiológica intrínseca de cada hospital o unidad de cuidados críticos, así como el origen de la infección, la seguridad o la toxicidad del antibiótico, la interacción con otras fármacos, la pauta de administración y la presencia de factores de riesgo. Los carbapenémicos son el fármaco de elección ante la sospecha de enterobacterias productoras de b-lactamasas de expectro extendido (BLEE). Los nuevos antimicrobianos, ceftazidima-avibactam y ceftolozano-tazobactam, abren nuevos horizontes esperanzadores en el tratamiento de enterobacterias multirresistentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(supl.1): 26-30, sept. 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación terapéutica empírica a la infección por gramnegativos resistentes. Valor de los factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10599^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4836^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
