<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054510</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systematic review: are major opioids effective in the treatment of musculoskeletal pain?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To evaluate the efficacy of major opioids in the treatment of musculoskeletal pain. Material and method: Systematic review. A sensitive search strategy was undertaken in MEDLINE and EMBASE up to April 2005. The Cochrane Library and the abstracts of the 2004-2005 meetings of the American College of Rheumatology were also hand searched. All randomized controlled trials of major opiods in patients with musculoskeletal pain were selected. An analytical review was performed and evidence tables produced. A meta-analysis was run when appropriate. Results: We obtained 427 references from the search, (27 duplicated from MEDLINE and EMBASE, 2 from the Cochrane Library, and 5 abstracts), of which 68 articles plus one meeting abstract were selected for detailed analysis. Of these, 23 finally met the inclusion criteria. Combined analysis of oral major opioids versus placebo showed significant improvement in pain relief in patients with osteoarthritis. Conclusions: Specific major opioids can reduce pain in patients with chronic musculoskeletal disorders. The clinical trials report positive effects on pain and the meta-analysis confirms these effects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abásolo, Lydia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la eficacia de los opiáceos mayores en el tratamiento del dolor osteomuscular. Material y método: Revisión sistemática. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica mediante una estrategia sensible en MEDLINE y EMBASE hasta abril de 2005. Además, se revisó la Cochrane Library y los resúmenes enviados al American College of Rheumatology en los últimos 2 años. Se seleccionaron todos los ensayos clínicos aleatorizados y controlados de fármacos opiáceos mayores en pacientes con dolor osteomuscular. Se realizó una revisión analítica, se produjeron tablas de evidencia y se realizó un metaanálisis en las comparaciones homogéneas. Resultados: Se obtuvieron 427 referencias totales mediante la búsqueda (27 duplicados de MEDLINE y EMBASE, 2 de la Cochrane Libray y 5 resúmenes), de las cuales se seleccionaron 68 artículos y un resumen de un congreso para análisis detallado. De ellos, 23 cumplían finalmente los criterios de inclusión. En el análisis combinado frente a placebo, se observa que los opiáceos mayores por vía oral mejoran significativamente el dolor de los pacientes con artrosis. Conclusiones: Algunos opiáceos mayores son capaces de reducir el dolor de los pacientes con enfermedades osteomusculares crónicas. Los ensayos originales informan de efectos positivos contra el dolor y los metaanálisis confirman estos efectos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(8): 291-301, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054510</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática: ¿son eficaces los opiáceos mayores en el tratamiento del dolor osteomuscular?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
