<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142710</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Throughout History, the problem of human freedom has clashed with two opposing determinisms: ambientalism considers that humans are &#147;programmed&#148; by the environment while instintivism considers him a slave of its nature. During 26 centuries these polar positions have changed the language that expresses them but have failed to integrate in a satisfactory synthesis. The arrival of Psychoanalysis provides a new perspective to the problem. Freud proposes the search of a synthesis with his &#147;complementary series&#148; and other psychoanalysts have adopted different positions. In this work we review how psychoanalysis has kept polar positions, like Melanie Klein´s instintivism, but has also opened new approaches that lead beyond the determinisms to the justification of human freedom. Among these approaches we highlight that of Winnicott and his transitional space (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ángel Sánchez Bahíllo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de la historia el problema de la libertad humana ha chocado con dos determinismos opuestos: el ambientalismo que entiende que el hombre es &#147;programado&#148; por el medio y el instintivismo que entiende que el hombre es esclavo de su naturaleza. Durante 26 siglos estas posturas polares han cambiado el lenguaje con el que se expresan pero han tenido poco éxito en integrarse en una síntesis satisfactoria. La llegada del psicoanálisis aporta una nueva perspectiva al problema. Freud propone la búsqueda de una síntesis con sus &#147;series complementarias&#148; y otros psicoanalistas han ido tomando distintas posturas. En este trabajo revisamos cómo el psicoanálisis ha mantenido posturas polares, como el instintivismo de Melanie Klein, pero también ha abordado nuevos enfoques que abren la puerta a la superación de los determinismos y a la justificación de la libertad humana. Entre estos enfoques destacamos el de Winnicott y su espacio transicional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(58): 25-30, 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El problema de la libertad: determinismos y psicoanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12824^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
