<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86230</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Future perspectives in the treatment of chronic hepatitis C</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main lines of research into new drugs and treatment strategies against type C viral hepatitis are described. This disease is a major public health problem, with more than 700,000 people affected by the illness in Spain and with a high degree of prevalence amongst prison inmates. Limitations on current treatment for viral hepatitis C have led to research into new drugs in the form of two main product lines, some of which are soon to be available on the market: NS3/4ª serine-protease inhibitors (telaprevir, boceprevir, danoprevir and vaniprevir) and the NS5B RNA polymerase inhibitors (RG-7128, RG-7227, Filibuvir, ANA-598). The latter are in a somewhat earlier stage of development. It is expected that these new drugs will have to be used alongside the current standard treatment of pegylated interferon plus ribavirin and under these conditions of use the new drugs have already shown greater effectiveness than the current standard treatment. Despite this encouraging perspective, the new medicines have limitations such as the development of resistances, toxicity, and the little knowledge available of their effectiveness on viral genotypes that are different from 1. That being said, their appearance opens up new possibilities in the treatment of this disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Montero, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se exponen las principales líneas de investigación en nuevos fármacos y estrategias de tratamiento contra la hepatitis vírica tipo C. Esta es una enfermedad que supone un importante problema de salud pública, con más de 700.000 afectados en España y con una importante prevalencia entre las personas privadas de libertad. Las limitaciones del actual tratamiento contra la hepatitis vírica C han forzado la investigación de nuevos fármacos que se van sustanciando en dos líneas principales de productos, algunos de ellos pronto disponibles en el mercado: los inhibidores de la serín-proteasa NS3/4ª (telaprevir, boceprevir, danoprevir o vaniprevir) y los inhibidores de la RNA-polimerasa NS5B (RG-7128, RG-7227, Filibuvir, ANA-598), estos últimos en una fase de desarrollo algo más temprana. Previsiblemente habrá que utilizar estos nuevos fármacos añadidos al tratamiento estándar actual de interferón pegilado más ribavirina y en esas condiciones de uso todos estos fármacos han demostrado ya una mayor efectividad que el tratamiento estándar actual. A pesar de este esperanzador panorama, estos fármacos tienen limitaciones como el desarrollo de resistencias, la toxicidad o el poco conocimiento que tenemos de su efectividad en genotipos virales distintos del 1. No obstante su aparición abre muchas nuevas posibilidades en el tratamiento de esta enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;13(1): 21-29, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86230</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectivas futuras en el tratamiento de la hepatitis crónica C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9892^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
