<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118856</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary practices of Brazilian mountain bikers before and during training and competition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The quality of the consumed diet is important for the improvement in performance during training and the achievement of positive results on competitions. The objective of study was to investigate the breakfast practices, and nutritional strategies used before and during training and competition of cyclists participating in the biggest mountain biking competition of Brazil. Methods: The participants (n = 146) were asked to complete a questionnaire during the distribution of kits on the day before the competition. The questionnaire included 13 questions about the participants&#146; characteristics, pre-training and pre-competition usual breakfast and meal consumption, and systemic or gastrointestinal symptoms during exercise. All statistical analyses were conducted using Sigma Stat 3.1 software. Results: 97.54% of participants consumed breakfast pre-training, while all participants consumed a pre-competition breakfast. After the analyses, banana and bread were the most consumed foods for pre-training and competition breakfast. Fort-two percent and 58 % of the participants consumed some supplement during the morning of the training and competition, respectively. Most participants indicated the consumption of some form of supplement during training (88.35%) and competition (97.25%). About 30% and 54% used three or more types of energy replenishment strategies during the training and the competition, respectively. 86% of the participants reported some form of adverse symptom during the training or race. Conclusions: Our study demonstrated that most of the mountain bikers interviewed consumed breakfast before exercise, although most of the foods chosen for breakfast were not appropriate for a pre-exercise meal. Moreover, these cyclists had a high ingestion of supplements before and during exercise, often being used as substitutes for food. The information obtained about these supplements was provided by unreliable sources in 43% of athletes. It is also suggested that these athletes should be better informed about risks and benefits of supplements use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Amorim, Paulo Roberto dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gouveia Peluzio, Maria do Carmo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melo Cazal, Mariana de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouzas Marins, João Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayumi Nakajima, Vânia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves Alfenas, Rita de Cássia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Volpe, Stella Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La calidad de la dieta es importante para la mejora del rendimiento tanto a la hora de entrenar como para obtener el logro de resultados positivos en competiciones. El objetivo del estudio fue investigar las prácticas dietéticas en el desayuno, y las estrategias nutritivas usadas antes y durante el entrenamiento y la competición en ciclistas de montaña que participan en la mayor prueba de ese tipo en Brasil. Metodología: Los participantes (n = 146) fueron reclutados para completar una encuesta durante la recogida de materiales de identificación de los equipos en el día previo a la competición. La encuesta incluyó 13 preguntas sobre sus conductas nutricionales, pre-entrenamiento y pre-competición sobre el desayuno usual y consumo de la comida, síntomas sistémicoso gastrointestinales durante el ejercicio. Para el análisis estadístico se utilizó el programa Sigma Stat 3.1. Resultados: Un 97,54% del total aseguraron tomar el desayuno antes del entrenamiento, y todos los participantes desayunaron antes de la competición. Después de los análisis, el plátano y pan estaban en la mayoría de las comidas pre-entrenamiento y competición. 42% y 58% de los participantes consumieron algún suplemento por la mañana antes del entrenamiento y competición, respectivamente. La mayoría de los participantes indicó el consumo de algún tipo de suplemento durante el entrenamiento (88,35%) y competición (97,25%). Aproximadamente, 30 y 54% usaron tres o más tipos de estrategias para reponer energía durante el entrenamiento y la competición, respectivamente. Un total de 86% de los participantes informaron haber tenido algún síntoma adverso durante el entrenamiento o competición. Conclusiones: Se demostró que la mayoría de los ciclistas realizan algún desayuno antes del ejercicio, aunque la mayoría de los alimentos escogidos no eran apropiados para una comida pre-ejercicio. Los ciclistas tenían una ingestión alta de suplementos antes y durante el ejercicio, usándose a menudo como sustitutivo de la comida. La información obtenida sobre estos suplementos fue proporcionada por las fuentes no fiables en 43% de los deportistas. También se sugiere que estos atletas se informen bien sobre los riesgos y beneficios del consumo de suplementos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;30(154): 83-90, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas dietéticas de los ciclistas de montaña brasileños antes y durante el entrenamiento y la competición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23100^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
