<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89642</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although the economic crisis and the unemployment, as any another psychosocial situation, are not uniform experiences and depend on factors mediators (age, sex, social class, implication,&#133;), in general, the unemployed people experience greater levels of depression, anxiety and general psychological deterioration, at the same time that lower levels of self-esteem and confidence. Other authors indicate that during the periods of economic crisis produces and increase in the psychiatric pathology, what would involve, a priori, an increase of the number of urgencies by this(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raygal Fernández, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánovas Gaspar, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vigueras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro Meca, R. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Retuerto, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vigueras, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que la crisis económica y el desempleo, como cualquier otra situación psicosocial desestabilizadora, no son experiencias uniformes y dependen de factores mediadores (edad, sexo, clase social, implicación, etc.), en general, las personas desempleadas experimentan mayores niveles de depresión, ansiedad y deterioro psicológico general, a la vez que menores niveles de autoestima y confianza. Otros autores indican que durante los periodos de crisis económica se produce un aumento en la patología psiquiátrica, lo que implicaría, a priori, un aumento del número de urgencias por esta(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;11(1): 0-0, 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La crisis económica y las urgencias hospitalarias generales y psiquiátricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14877^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
