<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69622</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A case of labial adhesions in an elderly woman is reported. The patient was admitted in the urology department since she related urinary symptoms. The diagnosis was been made by simple inspection of the genital region. Under anaesthesia, surgical procedure was done by sharp dissection, and dressing ointment was recommended at discharge. An excellent result was obtain. The estrogens deficiency seems to be the origin of this rare disease and it is not unusual the presence of another circumstances like lichen sclerouset atrophicus, diabetes mellitus or decreasing sexual activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosa Arias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Aramburu, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de fusión labial en una mujer anciana. La paciente fue atendida en el servicio de urología al referir síntomas miccionales. El diagnóstico se realizó por la mera inspección de la región vulvar. Bajo anestesia se practicó tratamiento quirúrgico con disección roma, y con la aplicación de pomadas de estrógenos al alta, se consiguió un resultado exitoso. El déficit estrogénico parece estar en la base de este raro proceso al que se pueden añadir circunstancia como liquen esclero atrófico, diabetes, o disminución de la actividad sexual entre otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(10): 1037-1038, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69622</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15246^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15246^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5972^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5972^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
