<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036590</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of an abnormal ankle-brachial index in relation to the cardiovascular risk estimated by the Framingham function</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: The measurement of the ankle-brachial index (ABI) is a straight forward method for the detection of atherosclerosis in the lower limbs. An abnormal ABI ( 1.4) is associated with the development of cardiovascular disease and cardiovascular and all cause mortality. Despite this, its measurement in clinical practice is underused. The objective of the present study was to evaluate the relation of the ABI with the cardiovascular risk determined by traditional risk functions in a population in primary prevention. PATIENTS AND METHOD: 1001 subjects without known cardiovascular disease attended in primary care were invited to participate in the study. Cardiovascular risk and ABI measurements were calculated in all participants. RESULTS: A low ( 1.4) was found in 6.4% of all subjects, 5.2% females and8.8% males. In a multivariable analysis age (OR = 1.09 for each year; 95% CI 1.03-1.15),smoking habit (OR = 2.96; 95% CI 1.51-5.80), HDL-cholesterol levels (OR = 0.98 for each mg/dl; 95% CI, 0.95-0.99) and hypertension (OR = 1.80; 95% CI, 1.05-3.06) were related with an abnormal ABI. Subjects were divided according to their risk stratification. The percentage of low, moderate and high risk individuals with an abnormal ABI was 2.6%, 8.7% and14.9% respectively. CONCLUSIONS: In primary prevention, one in ten individuals with moderate risk and one in six individuals with high risk have an abnormal ABI. In these subjects there is an indication for intensive preventive strategies and antiagregation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Iglesias, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahoz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terol, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostaza, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: La medición del índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) es un método sencillo para detectar la presencia de arteriosclerosis en miembros inferiores. Un valor inferior a 0,9 o superiora 1,4 se asocia con un riesgo elevado de enfermedad cardiovascular, cerebrovascular y/o muerte por cualquier causa. A pesar de ello, su implantación en la práctica clínica es escasa. El objetivo del presente estudio fue determinar la prevalencia de un ITB patológico en una población en prevención primaria clasificada según su riesgo vascular calculado por la función de Framingham recomendada por el National Cholesterol Education Program en su documento Adult Treatment Panel III. PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Participaron en el estudio 1.001 sujetos sin enfermedad vascular conocida atendidos en atención primaria. A todos ellos se les estimó el riesgo vascular y se les midió el ITB. RESULTADOS: El ITB fue bajo (menor de 0,9) en un 3,8% de los participantes (un 3,9% de las mujeres y un 3,6% de los varones). Se consideró patológico (inferior a 0,9 o mayor de 1,4) en un 6,4% (un 5,2% de las mujeres y un 8,8% de los varones). En el análisis multivariante los factores que se asociaron con un ITB patológico fueron la edad odds ratio (OR) = 1,09 porcada año de edad; intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95%, 1,03-1,15), el tabaquismo (OR = 2,96;IC del 95%, 1,51-5,80), la concentración de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad(OR = 0,98 por cada mg/dl; IC del 95%, 0,95-0,99) y la presencia de hipertensión arterial (OR =1,80; IC del 95%, 1,05-3,06). Al ser clasificados según su riesgo vascular, el porcentaje de sujetos de riesgo bajo, intermedio y alto con un ITB patológico fue del 2,6, el 8,7 y el 14,9%,respectivamente. CONCLUSIONES: En prevención primaria, uno de cada 10 sujetos con riesgo intermedio y uno década 6 con riesgo elevado presentan un ITB patológico. En estos sujetos están indicadas lasmedidas preventivas enérgicas y la antiagregación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(17): 641-644, mayo 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de un índice tobillo-brazo patológico según el riesgo cardiovascular calculado mediante la función de Framingham</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d856^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1136^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
