<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88006</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A bilingual script in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">English language skills are growing fast among the world's population, and especially in Europe. Health professionals cannot and should not be excluded from this group, as achieving fluent and effective communication with foreign patients is a basic skill in our profession. The basic purpose of this paper is to provide a simple bilingual script that may help to prepare a medical record in emergency medical situations in rural areas. The knowledge of English for any professional in the area of Health is an obvious need in a world where the language of communication is English. The bilingual script contributes to the achievement of an initial syndromic diagnoses in the urgent care of a foreign patient, and with this script, we make it easier to register the foreign patients treated in our health area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morea Colmenares, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillermo Ruberte, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana Alonso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balerdi Zabala, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contín Pescacen, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El conocimiento del inglés avanza a pasos de gigante entre la población mundial, y muy especialmente entre la europea, una tendencia de la que los profesionales sanitarios ni debemos ni podemos quedar al margen, porque lograr una comunicación fluida y eficaz con los pacientes es una de las competencias básicas de nuestra profesión. Lo que pretendemos con este artículo es facilitar con un guión de conversación bilingüe (español-inglés), la elaboración de una historia clínica en urgencias graves rurales. El conocimiento del inglés para cualquier profesional en el área de la salud constituye una necesidad evidente en un mundo donde la lengua de comunicación por excelencia es la inglesa. El guión bilingüe contribuye a la realización de un diagnóstico sindrómico inicial en la atención urgente de un paciente extranjero y al mismo tiempo mediante el guión facilitamos la cumplimentación del registro de pacientes extranjeros atendidos en nuestra zona básica de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(4): 199-203, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guión bilingüe en urgencias de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3175</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
