<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116751</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">RibeiroSocial Skills in Career Development Strategy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article presents a proposal for intervention in the Career Management Center for Graduate Program in Business Administration from the University of Taubaté, whose goal is to guide development planning, management and career in executives professionals in training, in the project entitled Development of Social Skills for Leadership. Describes the implementation stages of promotion of social skills, formed by the evaluation of social skills, social skills training and evaluation of the results of social skills training. The systematic development of these interventions is to promotean environment of personal development, discussion of career opportunities and the development of behavioral skills(social and leadership) required by changes in the complexity of the work environment and recognition of these aspects help articulate more efficient interactions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araujo, Elvira Aparecida Simões de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, Maria Júlia Ferreira Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tadeucci, Marilsa de Sá Rodrigues</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se presenta una propuesta de intervención en el Núcleo de Gestión de Carrera del Programa de Postgrado en Administración de Empresas de la Universidad de Taubaté, cuyo objetivo es guiar la planificación del desarrollo, la gestión y la carrera de los ejecutivos en formación en el proyecto denominado &#147;Desarrollo de Habilidades Sociales para el Liderazgo&#148;. Se describen las fases de aplicación de promoción de las competencias sociales, formadas por (1) la evaluación de las habilidades sociales, (2) el entrenamiento en habilidades sociales y (3) la evaluación de los resultados de éste. El desarrollo sistemático de estas intervenciones tiene por objeto promover un ambiente de desarrollo personal, la discusión de las oportunidades de carrera y el desarrollo de habilidades de comportamiento (social y liderazgo) requeridas por los cambios en la complejidad del ambiente de trabajo, el reconocimiento de estos aspectos ayudan a articular interacciones más eficientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(1): 93-99, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencias sociales en la estrategia de desarrollo de carrera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
