<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106818</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability and construct validity of an instrument to asses the self-perception of family health status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Family health determines and it is determined by family´s capacity to function effectively as a biosocial unit in a given culture and society. The main of study has been to test reliability and construct validity of an instrument to asses the Self-perception of Family Health Status. Methods: We validated its content by an on-line Dephi panel with experts. We surveyed 258 families in them homes or in primary health centres fromSeville, Spain.We administered the instrument that has five Likert scales: Family climate, Family integrity, Family functioning, and Family resistance. We tested reliability by Cronbach Alpha and construct validity by exploratory factor analysis. Results: The five scales obtained values &amp;#945; between 0.73 for the Family Climate and 0.89 for Family Integrity. They showed evidence of one-dimensional interpretation after factor analysis, a) all items got weights r&gt;0.30 in first factor before rotations, b) the first factor explained a significant proportion of variance before rotations, and c) the total variance explained by the main factors extracted was greater than 50%. Conclusions: The scales showed their reliability and validity. They could be employed to assess the self-perception of family health status(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Picón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima Serrano, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Sánchez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima Rodríguez, Joaquín Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La salud familiar determina y está determinada por la capacidad de funcionamiento efectivo de la familia como unidad biopsicosocial, en el contexto de una cultura y una sociedad. El objetivo del estudio ha sido comprobar la fiabilidad y validez de un cuestionario diseñado para medir la autopercepción del estado de salud familiar. Métodos: Se contó con 258 familias de la provincia de Sevilla a las que se aplicó el cuestionario que constaba de cinco escalas: Clima Familiar, Integridad Familiar, Funcionamiento Familiar, Resistencia Familiar y Afrontamiento Familiar, Likert, autoadministrado en su domicilio o en centros de salud. Se determinó la fiabilidad mediante la prueba alpha de Cronbach y la validez de constructo mediante análisis factorial exploratorio. Resultados: Se obtuvieron valores &amp;#945; comprendidos entre 0,73 para Clima familiar y 0,89 para Integridad Familiar. El análisis factorial mostró datos a favor de su unidimensionalidad, a) todos los ítems obtuvieron pesos r&gt;0,30 en el primer factor, b) éste explicaba una proporción importante de la varianza con respecto a los demás, c) la varianza total explicada por los factores principales era mayor al 50%. Conclusiones: Las escalas demostraron su validez y fiabilidad y pueden ser utilizadas para valorar la autopercepción del estado de salud familiar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(5): 509-521, sep.-oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consistencia interna y validez de un cuestionario para medir la autopercepción del estado de salud familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
