<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72936</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">MADAI project: an epidemiologic study about the perioperative pain tnanagetnent and treattnent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo obtain descriptive information about patient treatment with acute peri-operative pain receiving parenteral analgesics in hospitalenvironments.MethodologyEpidetniologic descriptive multicentre study. Patients ad-mitted in the following Surgery services: General, Thoracic, Cardio-vascular,Angiology, Gynaecology, Orthopaedic and Urology.ResultsParticipation of 76 hospitals, distributed along the country; and 439 investigators. 1972 patients were assessed. 43.9% and 25.5% wereadmitted in General and Orthopaedic surgery services respectively. 52.8% of patients were over 60 years oíd. 31.2% did not present anyconcomitant illness. 36.78% had arterial hypertension and 16.5% diabetes melli-tus. Pain scales to measure pain intensity, were used by5.8% of patients at admission. In the following visits, these per-centages ranged from 10% to 15%. During postoperative pe-riod NSAIDswere the most widely used (specially metamizol, administrated from 63.6% to 40.5% of the patients) and ace-taminophen which was usedby 41.3% of the patients in the first 12 hours and 27% in the 4th day. The percentage of patients that received rescue medication decreasesfrom 25.7 % at first control to 6% at 4th day control; being acetaminophen the most commonly used medication.ConclusionsDespite pain treatment is considered important in surgi-cal environments, treatment protocols are seldom used. The elaboration and the useof therapeutics guidelines for perioperative pain treatment could improve the patient comfort and their recuperation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, L. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balibrea, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Timoneda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoObtener información descriptiva sobre el abordaje y el manejo del paciente con dolor agudo periquirúrgico tratado con analgésicosparenterales en el ámbito hospitalario.MetodologíaEstudio epidemiológico, descriptivo, multicéntrico. Pacientes ingresados en los servicios de cirugía general, torácica, cardio-vascular,angiología y cirugía vascular, ginecología, traumatología y urología.ResultadosParticiparon 76 hospitales distribuidos por las diferentes comunidades autónomas y un total de 439 investigadores. Se evaluaron 1972pacientes de los que el 43.9% y 25.5%, respectivamente pertenecieron a los servicios de cirugía general y traumatología. El 52.8% de lospacientes tenían más de 60 años, un 31.2 % no presentaron ninguna enfermedad concomitante, el 36.7% padecían hipertensión y un 16.5%diabetes. En el 5.8% de los pacientes se utilizaron escalas para valorar la intensidad del dolor al ingreso. En las sucesivas visitas, esteporcentaje oscila entre el 10 % y el 15%. En el postoperatorio, los principales analgésicos administrados son los AINE (sobre todo elmetamizol, que utilizan del 63.6% al 40.5% del total de pacientes del estudio) y el paracetamol, que utilizan el 41.3% a las 0-12horas y el27% el día 4. El porcentaje que recibe medicación de rescate va disminuyendo, desde el primer control (25.7%), al del cuarto día (6%),siendo la medicación más utilizada el paracetamol.ConclusionesA pesar de que en el ámbito de la cirugía se considera importante el tratamiento del dolor, la utilización de protocolos no es habitual. Laelaboración y utilización de guías terapéuticas para el tratamiento del dolor peri quirúrgico podría mejorar el confort del paciente y surecuperación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(4): 209-218, may.2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Proyecto MADAI: un estudio epidemiológico sobre el abordaje y manejo del dolor agudo periquirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
