<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70071</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this study was to describe the characteristics of health care provided to arriving African immigrants, including primary care, hospital emergency care, and hospital admissions. Methods: A descriptive cross-sectional study was carried out from August 15 to December 31, 2006. Three datasets were used. One included all primary care visits. The second comprised all visits to hospital emergency rooms. The third covered all patients admitted to the 5 university hospitals on Tenerife and Grand Canary islands. The first 2 datasets included the entire area of the Spanish autonomous community of the Canary Islands. Results: A total of 3658 primary care visits and 1122 emergency room visits were recorded during the study period; 111patients were hospitalized. Most primary care visits were for a general health check-up, for trauma, or for gastrointestinal disorders. Fever and abdominal pain were the most common reasons for emergency visits. Malaria and dehydration or electrolyte imbalance were the reasons for most hospital admissions. Conclusions: The boat crossings of thousands of kilometers affect the health of many immigrants to greater or lesser degrees. Health care was managed according to the number of patients who had to be attended, the time available, and the seriousness of the condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Bilbao, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Carlos, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez del Rosario, Coromoto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Rodríguez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mahtani Mahtani, Vijay</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Palmero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrero Rodríguez, Lucina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huerga Moreno, Santiago de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orihuela Martínez, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características de la asistencia sanitaria a la llegada de los inmigrantes tanto en el ámbito de atención primaria (AP) como en el hospitalario, y, en este último, tanto la atención en urgencias y como en hospitalización. Método: Se diseñó un estudio descriptivo y transversal. El periodo de estudio comprendió desde el 15 de agosto hasta el 31 de diciembre de 2006. Se utilizaron tres tipos de población: una incluyó la totalidad de las asistencias realizadas en AP. La segunda abarcó el total de las asistencias realizadas en las urgencias hospitalarias y la tercera comprendió el total de pacientes ingresados en los 5 hospitales universitarios de Tenerife y Gran Canaria. Para las dos primeras el ámbito geográfico fue toda la Comunidad Autónoma de Canarias. Resultados: Durante el periodo del estudio se realizaron en AP 3.658 asistencias y en las urgencias de los hospitales 1.122. El número de pacientes hospitalizados fue de111. Los motivos de asistencias más importantes fueron la revisión del estado de salud, los traumatismos y trastornos gastrointestinales en AP; el síndrome febril y el dolor abdominal en las urgencias hospitalarias; y los motivos más frecuentes de ingreso en los hospitales fueron el paludismo y los trastornos hidro-electrolíticos. Discusión: La llegada de embarcaciones con inmigrantes tras haber recorrido miles de kilómetros de distancia afectó en menor o mayor medida al estado de salud de muchos de ellos. Su asistencia sanitaria se gestionó en base al número de pacientes a atender en un intervalo de tiempo y por la gravedad de sus enfermedades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);20(6): 411-418, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70071</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15068^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5453^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
