<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94771</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Computed tomography in endodontics: Uses and applies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to explain what conventional tomography, which uses can be applied in endodontic. To this  end we select five teeth and put it through: an analysis Computed Tomography (CT) with subsequent reconstruction. Among the possibilities for CT include: knowing the length of the pulp chamber, namely the number and arrangement of canals, to assess the presence of lateral canals, isthmuses union between canals, known to the diameter o the canal along the entire root system and evaluate the angle and radius of curvature. The result represents great potential in understanding and behavior of teeth instrumentation systems during the preparation of the canal, as well as knowledge of anatomy external and internal canal root system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estévez Luaña, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre de la Fuente, F de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranguren Cangas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Bautista, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es explicar en qué cosnste la tomorafía convencional, y qué usos podemos aplicarle en el campo de la endodoncia. Para ello seleccionamos cinco dientes y los sometemos a un anáisis tomográfico computarizdo (TC) con reconstrucción posterior. Entre las posibilidades de la TC se encuentra: conocer la longitud de la cámara pulpar tanto en sentido mesio distal como en sentido vestíbulo-lingual, saber el número y la disposicion de los conductos, evaluar la presencia de conductos laterales, istmos de unión entre los conductos , conocer el diámetro del conducto a lo largo de todo el sistema radicular y ealuar el ángulo y radio de curvatura. El resultado supone grades posibilidades en el entendimiento y comportamietno de los sitemas de insrumentación durante la preparación del canal, así como el conocimiento de la antamía externa e interna del sistema de conductos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);27(2): 80-85, abr.-jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tomografía computarizada en endodoncia: usos e indicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32944</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
