<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043224</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors predicting óbice handicap index</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess factors that may be predictive    of patient perception of dysphonia severity, as quantified    by the Voice Handicap Index (VHI) score. Material and methods:    A prospective study is carried out in 81 voice samples    from patients diagnosed with benign vocal fold lesions. Variables    assessed for predictive value to VHI score are maximum    fonation time, narrow band spectrogram, jitter, shimmer,    HNR, NNE, F0 and the auditory perceptual evaluation    of severity of dysphonia GRABS. Results: HNR, F0 and B    and S parameters of GRABS were predictors of total VHI    score, functional and emotional subscales. No parameter    was found to predict the physical subscale. Conclusions: VHI    score is correlated with the perceived breathy voice and its    acoustic attributes, such as signal-to-noise ratio. In other    studies, patient perception of dysphonia is independent of    many factors commonly assessed during the evaluation of    voice disorders. It is reasonable to assume that the severity    of glottic gap caused by benign vocal folds lesions is related    to a low signal-to-noise ratio and the breathy phonation as    its perceptual correlate. The physical subscale appears to be    an independent element in the assessment of the patient    perception of dysphonia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corte Santos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Nieto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Señaris González, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Batalla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los factores que pueden influir    en la percepción de la disfonía por parte del paciente, cuantificada    mediante el Índice de Incapacidad Vocal (VHI). Material    y método: Se realiza un estudio prospectivo de 81 registros    vocales de pacientes diagnosticados de una patología    benigna de las cuerdas vocales. Las variables analizadas para    calcular la predicción sobre el VHI son: tiempo máximo    de fonación, análisis del espectrograma, jitter, shimmer,    HNR, NNE, Fo y el análisis perceptual de la disfonía    (GRABS). Resultados: Los parámetros predictivos de la puntuación    total del VHI fueron la relación armónico ruido    (HNR), la frecuencia fundamental (F0) y los parámetros B y    S del sistema GRABS. Conclusiones: La puntuación del VHI    se correlaciona con la percepción de la voz aérea y sus atributos    acústicos, como la relación señal-ruido. En otros estudios,    la percepción de la disfonía por parte del paciente es    independiente de muchos factores que se valoran de forma    rutinaria en la evaluación de los trastornos de la voz. Parece    razonable asumir que el grado de insuficiencia glótica causada    por lesiones vocales benignas se relacione con una baja    relación señal-ruido y con la voz aérea como su característica    perceptual. La subescala física parece ser un elemento independiente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;57(2): 101-108, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Índice de Incapacidad Vocal: factores predictivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15228^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
