<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104273</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, with a sample of 160schizophrenia outpatients, are reviewed preliminary results which establishes the existence of two factors of insight: one which refers to a general knowledge about illness; and a second one refers to a more specifics knowledge about illness and its consequences. Also, the relationships between these factors and clinical and sociodemographic variables are examined. The results confirm the existence of both factors and the relationship between a general knowledge about illness with psychotic symptoms, depression, anxiety and satisfaction with treatment; whereas more specific knowledge of the disease is associated with lower cognitive impairment and not with other variables. The results are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prat Solíz, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Solero, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Sanz, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta Rodríguez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Modamio, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Calleja, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lastra Martínez, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce López, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bengoechea Seco, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio, realizado con una muestra de 160 sujetos diagnosticados de esquizofrenia, se revisan resultados previos donde se establece la existencia de dos factores de insight: un factor que hace referencia a un conocimiento general de la enfermedad; y otro referido a un conocimiento más específico de la misma. Se estudian las relaciones entre estos factores y diferentes variables clínicas y sociodemográficas. Los resultados corroboran la existencia de ambos factores y relacionan un conocimiento más general de la enfermedad con síntomas psicóticos, depresión, ansiedad y satisfacción con el tratamiento; mientras que un conocimiento más específico de la enfermedad se relaciona con un menor deterioro cognitivo y no con otras variables. Se hace una valoración de los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(201): 341-353, jul.-sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre insight y otras variables clínicas en esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
