<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90440</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prostate cancer: to screen or not to screen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper evaluates the use of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) as a screening tool for prostate cancer. A current and contentious issue in both public and medical spheres, we are still lacking clear evidence and guidelines. Here, the Wilson and Jungner screening criteria are used as a framework to suggest that PSA-testing is not yet a proven tool for population screening. Additionally, the conflicting results of two recent randomised controlled trials are compared. The European Randomised trial of Screening for Prostate Cancer (ERSPC) found that PSA screening reduced prostate cancer-related deaths by 20% (adjusted p=0.04). Meanwhile the North American Prostate, Lung, Colon and Ovarian cancer trial (PLCO) found no significant impact of screening on mortality. The reasons for these differing outcomes are discussed in greater detail under the categories of methodology, study size, screening interval, cause of death and tumour demographics. The authors of this article conclude that PSA screening, at best, has a moderate impact on prostate cancer mortality. PSA-screening does, however, pose a high risk of over-diagnosis and over-treatment with its associated morbidity. Furthermore, economic and quality of life evaluations are lacking at present. Data are awaited from the UK Department of Health- funded ProtecT study,as well as longer-term outcomes of the ERSPC(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brewster, Simon F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bailey, Sarah-Jane V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo valora el uso del PSA (Antígeno prostático específico) como instrumento de cribado en cáncer de próstata. Siendo un tema de actualidad y polémico, tanto en la esfera médica como en la pública, todavía carecemos de evidencia clara y guías de actuación. Aquí, los criterios de cribado de Wilson y Jungner se utilizan como marco para sugerir que la prueba de PSA no es todavía un instrumento probado de cribado poblacional.Además, se comparan los resultados en conflicto de dos estudios aleatorizados controlados. El ERSPC (European Randomised trial of Screening for Prostate Cancer) encontró que el cribado con PSA reducía un 20% la mortalidad relacionada con cáncer de próstata (ajustada, p=0,04). Mientras que el ensayo PLCO (North American Prostate, Lung, Colon and Ovarian cancer Trial) no encuentra impacto significativo del cribado en la mortalidad. Las razones de estas diferencias de resultados se discuten en gran detalle bajo las categorías de metodología, tamaño del estudio, intervalo de cribado, causa de la muerte y datos demográficos del tumor. Los autores de este artículo concluyen que el cribado con PSA tiene, como mucho, un impacto moderado en la mortalidad por cáncer de próstata. Sin embargo, el cribado con PSA representa un problema de sobrediagnóstico y sobretratamiento con su morbilidad asociada. Más aun, faltan evaluaciones económicas y de calidad de vida en el presente. Se esperan los datos del estudio Protect &#150;T financiado por el Departamento de Salud del Reino Unido, así como los resultados a más largo plazo del ERSPC(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(5): 406-418, jun. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de próstata: ¿hacer o no hacer cribado?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
