<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138361</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Legitimacy and efficacy at work: when entitlement legitimizes and deservingness qualifies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The structural model of deservingness () posits that entitlement and deservingness are two different predictors of perceptions of legitimacy. Specifically, entitlement refers to the accomplishment of established social rules, whereas deservingness relates to the outcomes that individuals earn as products of their actions. Although both factors are good predictors of perceived legitimacy, previous works show different conclusions about their relevance. The aim of this paper is to further examine the influence of entitlement and deservingness on legitimacy perceptions and on the consequences expected for a candidate who has been elected for a power position. Results showed that whereas a high-entitlement candidate is perceived as more legitimate, a high-deservingness candidate is expected to perform better. Besides, results hint that the level of personal implication with the candidate election plays also a relevant role in combination with entitlement and deservingness, when individuals evaluate the expected consequences of the decision (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Willis, Guillermo B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Moya, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nonami, Hiroshi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Mantas, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Bailón, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo estructural del merecimiento () establece dos factores que afectan a las percepciones de legitimidad: el derecho (merecer algo por cumplir las normas establecidas para ello) y el merecimiento (merecerlo por las acciones pasadas realizadas). A pesar de la relevancia de ambos factores, trabajos previos muestran conclusiones diferentes respecto a qué factor es un mejor predictor de la legitimidad. El objetivo de este artículo es explorar la influencia de estos factores al juzgar la legitimidad y las consecuencias positivas asociadas a la elección de un aspirante para un puesto de poder. Los resultados mostraron que mientras que un candidato con derecho para ocupar el puesto se percibe más legítimo, un candidato que merece ese puesto predice unas consecuencias más positivas como resultado de dicha elección. Además, los resultados sugieren que el grado de implicación de los individuos con la elección interactúa con el derecho y el merecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);31(2): 59-68, ago. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138361</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Legitimidad y desempeño en el trabajo: cuando el derecho legitima y el merecimiento cualifica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4596^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
