<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99823</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Zuska disease. Diagnosis and treatment in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A fistula is an abnormal pathological communication which links two organs together or with the exterior. They are fibrous paths internally coated with granulation tissue, extending from an internal o primary opening to one or more openings located outside or on the skin. The recurrent mastitis that some patients suffer is due to a fistula between a lactiferous duct and the limit of the areola, and this condition is called a recurrent periareolar fistula.To incorporate this clinical condition into the proposed terminology, Zuska disease, is essential to believe in its existence, in order to to treat it from the source. The knowledge of this disease, a proper diagnosis and treatment will prevent the constant recurrence of mastitis as presented by these patients, avoiding their pilgrimage to various specialists. In this article we review this disease, methods of diagnosis and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Monje, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Cordovés, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirpuri-Mirpuri, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una fístula es una comunicación anómala patológica que comunica 2 órganos entre sí o con el exterior. Son trayectos fibrosos con revestimiento interno de tejido de granulación, que se extienden desde un orificio interno o primario hasta uno o varios orificios externos o secundarios situados en la piel. La constante recidiva de una mastitis suele ser consecuencia de una fístula entre conductos galactóforos y el límite areola-piel de la mama, llamándose a esto fistulización periareolar recidivante. Para integrar este cuadro en la terminología propuesta, enfermedad de Zuska, es indispensable pensar primero en su existencia para enfocar el tratamiento en su origen. El conocimiento de esta enfermedad y su diagnóstico y tratamiento correctos impedirán las constantes recidivas en forma de mastitis que presentan estas pacientes, evitando así su peregrinaje por distintos especialistas. En este artículo revisamos esta entidad, métodos diagnósticos y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(3): 178-180, abr. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de zuska. Diagnóstico en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54519^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8584^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54519^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6248^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
