<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117408</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of newspaper for the terminology appropriation by first year medical students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To describe and analyze a formative task of appropriation of medical and scientific terminology by students of first year at medical school. Subjects and methods. Participants were 161 students distributed in groups of five or six to perform the proposed assignments in form of seminars. The students selected science and medicine news, published in national and regional newspapers, to analyze different characteristics of these articles. The instructions for the task as well as some examples were available in the university's virtual campus at the beginning of the course. Results. Students chose 103 news; only six of natural sciences and the rest related to Medicine, being predominant those related to neurology. Medical terms identified in those articles were 316. Moreover 219 items in general news were chosen. The 88.3% of the terms were documented via consulting dictionaries. The 51.5% of the students answered a survey in which, the task got an average score of 3.2 out of 5 possible points. Conclusions. The study shows that medicine and health information is common in national and regional press. The students think that this activity promotes medical and scientific vocabulary acquisition while it favors the approach to the social aspects of medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantabrana, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bordallo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez, Brezo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Presentar y analizar una tarea formativa de apropiación de terminología médica y científica por los estudiantes de primer curso de medicina. Sujetos y métodos. Participaron los 161 alumnos matriculados en primer curso que fueron distribuidos en grupos de cinco o seis para realizar el trabajo propuesto en forma de seminario. Los alumnos seleccionaron noticias relacionadas con ciencia y medicina publicadas en diarios de ámbito nacional o regional para estudiar diferentes características. Las instrucciones para la realización de la tarea, así como algunos ejemplos, estuvieron disponibles en el campus virtual de la universidad al comienzo de curso. Resultados. Los alumnos seleccionaron 103 artículos, de los que sólo seis trataban de ciencias naturales no relacionadas con la medicina, predominando en estos últimos los dedicados a neurología. En esos 103 artículos se identificaron 316 términos médicos; otros 219 términos fueron seleccionados en artículos generales. El 88,3% de los términos fueron documentados mediante distintos diccionarios. El 51,5% de los alumnos contestaron una encuesta sobre la actividad formativa en la que otorgaron una calificación de 3,2 puntos sobre 5. Conclusiones. El estudio demuestra que las noticias sobre medicina y salud son habituales en la prensa nacional y regional. Los alumnos consideraron que la actividad favorece la adquisición de vocabulario médico y científico, a la vez que facilita la aproximación a los aspectos sociales de la medicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);16(3): 145-151, sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apropiación de terminología médica por estudiantes de primer curso del grado en medicina a través de prensa diaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50135</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
