<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136180</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurring post-traumatic growing skull fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Growing skull fracture, also known as post-traumatic bone absorption or leptomeningeal cyst, is a rare complication of traumatic brain injuries and occurs almost exclusively in children under 3 years of age. Case report. We report the case of a 6-month-old child who presented, two months after an apparently unimportant traumatic skull injury, persistence of left temporoparietooccipital cephalohaematoma with no other signs. A transfontanellar ultrasonography scan revealed a bone defect with brain herniation, and computerised tomography and magnetic resonance imaging also confirmed the existence of a growing fracture. Excision of the leptomeningeal cyst, dural closure and repair of the bone defect with plates and lactate material were performed. Three months after the operation, the patient still presented collection of fluid and recurrence of the growing fracture was confirmed. Following the second operation, a baby helmet was fitted in order to prevent renewed recurrences. One year after the traumatic injury occurred, the patient remains asymptomatic. Conclusions. Any child under 3 years of age with a post-traumatic cephalohaematoma should be checked periodically until the full resolution of the collection of fluid, especially if they present a fractured skull. The presence of a cephalohaematoma that remains more than two weeks after traumatic brain injury must make us suspect a growing fracture and reparation of the dura mater and a cranioplasty will be needed to treat it. The use of resorbable material allows it to be remodelled as the patient&#146;s skull grows, but its fragility increases the risk of recurrence. The use of a baby helmet after the operation could prevent complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yoldi Petri, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zazpe Cenoz, Idoya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Albesa, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La fractura craneal evolutiva, también llamada absorción ósea postraumática o quiste leptomeníngeo, es una rara complicación de los traumatismos craneoencefálicos y ocurre de forma casi exclusiva en niños menores de 3 años. Caso clínico. Niño de 6 meses que presentaba, dos meses después de un traumatismo craneal aparentemente banal, persistencia de cefalohematoma temporooccipital izquierdo sin otros signos. El estudio de ecografía transfontanelar reveló un defecto óseo con herniación cerebral, y la tomografía computarizada y la resonancia magnética confirmaron, además, una fractura evolutiva. Se realizó resección del quiste encefalomeníngeo, cierre dural y reparación del defecto óseo con placas y material de lactato. Tres meses después de la intervención, presentaba persistencia de colección líquida y se confirmó recidiva de la fractura evolutiva. Tras la reintervención, se colocó casco ortésico para evitar nuevas recidivas. Un año después del traumatismo, el paciente continúa asintomático. Conclusiones. Todo niño menor de 3 años con cefalohematoma postraumático debería ser revisado de forma periódica hasta comprobar la resolución de la colección, en particular si presenta fractura craneal. La presencia de un cefalohematoma persistente más de dos semanas después de un traumatismo craneoencefálico debe hacernos sospechar un proceso de fractura creciente, y son necesarias la reparación de la duramadre y una craneoplastia para su tratamiento. La colocación de material reabsorbible permite su remodelación con el crecimiento craneal del paciente, pero su fragilidad conlleva riesgo de recidiva. La colocación de un casco ortésico tras la intervención podría prevenir complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(8): 351-354, 16 abr., 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136180</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura craneal evolutiva postraumática recidivada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53699^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53699^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
