<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102652</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Revision of studies and researches related with diagnostic comorbidity of Autism Spectrum Disorder-High Functioning and anxiety disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to review the state of the art of research on comorbidity of Autism Spectrum Disorder-High Functioning (ASD-AF) and anxiety disorders with a threefold purpose: a) to analyse the methodological problems of research studies, b) to present hypothesis on comorbidity, adopting an approach taking into account the new proposal of DSM-V (APA, 2011), and c) to suggest future research lines. Our study concludes that there is an urgent need to develop specific strategies and instruments that help the differential assessment of comorbidity symptomatology and that favour proposals of more efficient treatments. An out-standing lack of research studies on this topic in spanish-speaking countries is highlighted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivar, José Sixto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia, Miriam de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objeto del estudio es revisar las investigaciones sobre la comorbilidad entre los Trastornos del Espectro del Autismo de Alto Funcionamiento (TEA-AF) y los trastornos de ansiedad con un triple propósito: a) analizar los problemas metodológicos de los estudios de investigación, b) plantear las hipótesis explicativas sobre la comorbilidad, con un posicionamiento y propuesta sobre las mismas teniendo en cuenta las nuevas propuestas del DSM-V (APA, 2011) y c) proponer líneas futuras de investigación. Se concluye que hay una necesidad urgente de desarrollar estrategias e instrumentos específicos que ayuden a la evaluación diferencial de la sintomatología comórbida y que favorezcan propuestas de tratamientos más eficaces. Se destaca la llamativa escasez de estudios de investigación sobre este tema en países de lengua hispana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(3): 823-833, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de estudios e investigaciones relacionadas con la comorbilidad diagnóstica de los Trastornos del Espectro del Autismo de Alto Funcionamiento (TEA-AF) y los trastornos de ansiedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
