<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162866</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-2345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of the catalase antioxidant enzyme in vascular calcification and bone demineralization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: Assess the role of the catalase antioxidant enzyme in the vascular calcification process associated with chronic renal failure (CRF) and its effect on bone mass. Material and methods: Wild type C57/BL6J mice (WT) and transgenic mice (TG) were used, that overexpress the catalase enzyme, to which CRF was induced. Control WT and TG mice were used in simulated intervention. After 16 weeks, the mice were sacrificed, with serum samples taken for biochemical markers as well as residual pieces of kidney, aorta and tibias. An in vitro model of primary culture of smooth vascular muscle cells (SVMC) taken from the WT and TG aorta which underwent eight days of 3 mM phosphorus and 2 mM calcium calcifying medium. Results: A significant increase in Runx2 gene expression, calcium renal deposit and bone structure deterioration at trabecular level was only detected in WT mice with CRF. This was not observed in TG mice with CRF. Only in the case of WT mice SVMC, did added calcification medium raise calcium levels, proteic Runx2 expression and the reactive oxygen species of mitochondria with low catalase enzyme. Conclusions: Calcifying catalase over-expression was observed in both in vivo and in vitro, with in vivo showing that this reduction was accompanied by an improvement in bone parameters under study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora Valenciano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Vázquez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Arias, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Añón Álvarez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naves Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo López, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martín, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cannata Andía, JB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirós González, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Torres, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panizo García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar el papel de la enzima antioxidante catalasa sobre el proceso de calcificación vascular asociada a insuficiencia renal crónica (IRC) y su efecto sobre la masa ósea. Material y métodos: Se utilizaron ratones C57/BL6J salvajes (WT) y transgénicos (TG), que sobreexpresan la enzima catalasa, a los que se les indujo IRC. Se utilizaron como control ratones WT y TG con intervención simulada. Transcurridas 16 semanas los animales se sacrificaron, obteniendo suero para analizar marcadores bioquímicos, el trozo residual de riñón, la aorta y las tibias. Se utilizó igualmente un modelo in vitro de cultivo primario de células de músculo liso vascular (CMLV) procedentes de aorta de ratón WT y TG sometidas durante 8 días a un medio calcificante con 3 mM de fósforo y 2 mM de calcio. Resultados: Solo en animales WT con IRC se observó un incremento significativo en la expresión génica de Runx2 y del depósito renal de calcio y un deterioro de la estructura ósea a nivel trabecular. Este efecto no se observó en ratones TG con IRC. Solo en las CMLV de ratones WT, la adición de medio calcificante produjo un aumento del contenido en calcio, de la expresión proteica de Runx2 y de las especies reactivas de oxígeno mitocondriales con una menor expresión proteica de la enzima catalasa. Conclusiones: La sobreexpresión de la enzima catalasa redujo el proceso de calcificación tanto in vivo como in vitro, mostrando in vivo que ese descenso se acompañó de una mejora en los parámetros óseos estudiados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. osteoporos. metab. miner. (Internet);9(1): 13-19, ene.-mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la enzima antioxidante catalasa en la calcificación vascular y desmineralización ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54540^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22944</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2418^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32334^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54540^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
