<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110275</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and use of medicinal plants by the users of a basic health área of Gran Canaria (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives and measurements: To know which medicinal plants are known to the users of the basic health área of Ingenio (Gran Canaria), the frequency of consumption, the most used species, where the herbs are obtained, the uses and satisfaction with their use, through a survey done with the 5 first patients of the day, along 3 weeks in March. Results: 354 surveys were completed. Mean age 48.31+/- 16.9. consumption percentages: ca. 30% in younger than 40 years and ca. 70% in older than 40 years. Most cited plants: chamomile (47.9%), lime flower (28.3%) pennyroyal (25.8%) valerian (19.5%) and lemon verbena (16.1%). 41.2% had used one PM the previous week and 62.7% the previous year. Uses anxiety  (26.3%), digestive disorders (19.8%), flu-like cold symptoms (18.7%) and &#147;fruition&#148; (12.9%). Place obtention: supermarket (42.7%), field collection (25.5%), market (12.5%) Pharmacy (12.3%) Herbalist (7%). Conclusions: We found high consumption of medicinal plants in the studied health area. The medicinal plants used and the reasonsfor use found in the present study are consistent with other similar studies. There is a need of greater knowledge on medicinal plants by family physicians(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Péres Yuste, Matilde Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Díaz, Manuel Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corujo Díaz, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolaños León, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Díaz, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana Quílez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos y mediciones: averiguar que plantas medicinales conocen los usuarios de la zona básica de salud de Ingenio (Gran Canaria), su frecuencia del consumo, las especies más utilizadas, su procedencia, las indicaciones y la satisfacción con su uso, mediante una encuesta a los 5 primeros pacientes de cada día durante 3 semanas en el mes marzo. Resultados: 354 encuestas. Edad media 48,31+/- 16,9. Porcentaje de consumo: cerca del 30% en menores de 40 años y del 70% en mayores de 40 años. Plantas más citadas: manzanilla (47,9%), tila (28,3%), poleo (25,8%), hierbaluisa (19,5%) y valeriana (16,1%). El 41,2% habían consumido alguna planta medicinal la semana anterior y el 62,7% el año anterior. Usos: ansiedad (26,3%), trastornos digestivos (19,8%), síntomas catarrales-gripales (18,7%) y &#147;por gusto&#148; (12,9%). Procedencia: supermercado (42,7%), recogida en el campo (25,5%), mercado (12,5%), herbolario (12,3%) y farmacia (7%). Conclusiones: constatamos un alto consumo de plantas medicinales en la zona estudiada. Tanto las plantas medicinales más usadas como los motivos coinciden con otros estudios similares. Consideramos necesario un mayor conocimiento de las plantas medicinales por parte de los médicos de familia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;12(1): 65-70, jul.2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110275</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento y uso de plantas medicinales por parte de los usuarios de una zona básica de salud de Gran Canaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d26923^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34571^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34146^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15036^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15036^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34146^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
