<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057796</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the use of health care resources and        the associated costs in patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA)        treated with three biological disease-modifying anti-rheumatic        drugs (bDMARDs): etanercept, infliximab and adalimumab.        Method: Design: observational, retrospective, multicentre        study. Length of study: 6 months. Target population: patients        with RA, who have been undergoing treatment for at least one        year. Scope: Spanish National Health System hospitals. Use of        resources: review of the patient records of all patients included in        the study by the Hospital Pharmacy Departments. Health care costs: the unit costs were obtained from Spanish databases; disease        costs per patient were estimated from the use of resources        results (&#128; in July 2006). Sensitivity analysis: univariate of base        case. Budget impact analysis: replacement of infliximab and        adalimumab by etanercept for three hospital populations.        Results: 1,111 patient records from 41 Spanish hospitals were        reviewed, 432 patients were treated with etanercept, 396 were        treated with infliximab and 283 with adalimumab. Mean doses:        etanercept: 48.90 mg per week; infliximab: 4.14 mg/kg every 8        weeks; adalimumab: 41.58 mg every two weeks (97.8, 138 and        104% respectively, of recommended doses). Treatment with etanercept        led to fewer costs. Compared to infliximab, six-monthly costs        per patient were reduced with etanercept as follows: bDMARD        treatment (&#128; 232.23), treatment failure (&#128; 163.42), consultations        (&#128; 54.88), tests ( 22.52) and costs associated to bDMARD administration        (&#128; 474.42). The saving per patient treated with etanercept        compared to infliximab for six months was 577.94. With respect        to adalimumab, the savings with etanercept were mainly related to        bDMARDs (&#128; 1,111.74) and test costs (&#128; 10.16), obtaining a sixmonthly        saving of &#128; 906.68 per patient treated with etanercept.        Sensitivity analysis confirmed the robustness of the base case in the        majority of cases, with six-monthly savings of &#128; 395.79-644.32 per        patient compared to infliximab and of &#128; 672.09-1.159.46 compared        to adalimumab. Infliximab treatment was less expensive than        etanercept and adalimumab treatment when taking into consideration        the minimum possible number of doses of infliximab (3 doses        for six months). Hospital budget savings could be obtained as a consequence        of a reduction in costs due to use of etanercept, ranging        from &#128; 14,500-231,100 when replacing infliximab with etanercept        and from &#128; 22,600-362,600 when replacing adalimumab with        etanercept, according to the hospital population included (50 to        200 patients).        Conclusions: Our results showed that in most cases, the        treatment of rheumatoid arthritis with etanercept compared to        infliximab and adalimumab reduced hospital costs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Investigadores del Estudio PRAXIS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la utilización de recursos sanitarios en la        artritis reumatoide (AR) y los costes asociados en los pacientes tratados        con tres medicamentos modificadores biológicos de la enfermedad        (MBE): etanercept, infliximab y adalimumab.        Método: Diseño: observacional, reprospectivo, multicéntrico.        Horizonte temporal: 6 meses. Población: pacientes con AR; al        menos 1 año de tratamiento. Perspectiva: hospitales del Sistema        Nacional de Salud. Utilización de recursos: revisión, por los servicios        de farmacia hospitalaria, de las historias clínicas de todos        los pacientes incluidos. Costes sanitarios: los unitarios obtenidos        de bases de datos españolas; los de la enfermedad por paciente        con cada MBE, estimados de los resultados de utilización de recursos        (&#128; de julio de 2006). Análisis de sensibilidad: simples unifactoriales        del caso básico. Análisis del impacto presupuestario: de        la sustitución de infliximab o adalimumab por etanercept sobre el        presupuesto de tres poblaciones hospitalarias.        Resultados: 1.111 historias clínicas revisadas, de 41 hospitales,        432 pacientes tratados con etanercept, 396 con infliximab y        283 con adalimumab. Dosis promedio: de etanercept 48,90 mg        semanales; de infliximab 4,14 mg/kg cada 8 semanas; de adalimumab        de 41,58 mg cada dos semanas (97,8, 138 y 104% de        las dosis recomendadas, respectivamente). El tratamiento con etanercept        generó menos costes. Frente a infliximab, con etanercept        se redujeron los costes semestrales por paciente del tratamiento        con el MBE (232,23 &#128;), por fracasos terapéuticos (163,42 &#128;),        por consultas (54,88 &#128;), por pruebas (22,52 &#128;) y por la administración        del MBE (474,42 &#128;). El ahorro por paciente con etanercept        durante seis meses fue de 577,94 &#128;, en comparación con        infliximab. En comparación con adalimumab, los ahorros con etanercept        se produjeron principalmente en los costes del MBE        (1.111,74 &#128;) y en las pruebas (10,16 &#128;) con un ahorro total        semestral por paciente tratado con etanercept de 906,68 &#128;. Los        análisis de sensibilidad confirmaron la estabilidad del caso básico        en la mayoría de los supuestos considerados, con ahorros semestrales        por paciente que oscilaron entre 395,79 y 644,32 &#128; en        comparación con infliximab y entre 672,09 y 1.159,46 &#128; en        comparación con adalimumab. El tratamiento con infliximab fue        más barato que con etanercept y adalimumab cuando se consideró        el mínimo número posible de dosis del primero (3 dosis al        semestre). La reducción en los costes de los pacientes tratados        con etanercept, podría generar ahorros en el presupuesto hospitalario        que oscilarían, aproximadamente y según la población considerada        (50 a 200 pacientes), entre 14.500 y 231.100 &#128; si etanercept        sustituyera infliximab y entre 22.600 y 362.600 &#128;, si        etanercept sustituyera adalimumab.        Conclusiones: De acuerdo con los resultados obtenidos, en la        mayoría de los escenarios el tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide        con etanercept reduce los costes sanitarios hospitalarios, en comparación        con infliximab y adalimumab</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;31(2): 78-92, mar.-abr.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización y coste de los modificadores biológicos de la artritis reumatoide en España (estudio PRAXIS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4537</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
