<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128471</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of Peripheral Pulmonary Lesions With Radial Probe Endobronchial Ultrasound-Guided Bronchoscopy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The diagnosis of peripheral pulmonary lesions (PPLs) is a challenging task for pulmonologists. Radial probe endobronchial ultrasound (R-EBUS) has been developed to enhance diagnostic yield. The objective of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of R-EBUS in the diagnosis of PPLs. Methods: A retrospective study was conducted on 174 patients diagnosed with PPLs who underwent EBUS-guided bronchoscopy. Histological examination of specimens obtained by transbronchial lung biopsy (TBLB) and cytological examinations of brushing smear, brush rinse fluid and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) were evaluated for the diagnosis. Results: The mean diameter of the PPLs was 25.1 ± 10.7 mm. The final diagnoses included 129 malignancies and 45 benign lesions. The overall diagnostic yield of EBUS-guided bronchoscopy was 79.9%. Neither size nor etiology of the PPLs influenced the diagnostic performance of EBUS-guided bronchoscopy (82.9% vs 74.6% for PPLs &gt;20 mm and PPLs &amp;#8804;20 mm; P=0.19, and 82.9% vs 71.1% for malignancy and benign diseases; P=0.09). TBLB rendered the highest yield among these specimens (69.0%, 50.6%, 42.0%, and 44.3% for TBLB, brushing smear, brush rinse fluid, and BALF, respectively; P&lt;0.001). The combination of TBLB, brush smear, and BALF provided the greatest diagnostic yield, while brush rinse fluid did not add benefits to the outcomes. Conclusion: R-EBUS-guided bronchoscopy is a useful technique in the diagnosis of PPLs. To achieve the highest diagnostic performance, TBLB, brushing smear and bronchoalveolar lavage should be performed together (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kanoksil, Wasana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laungdamerongchai, Sarangrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boonsarngsuk, Viboon</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El diagnóstico de las lesiones pulmonares periféricas (LPP) constituye un verdadero reto para los neumólogos. La ecografía endobronquial radial (R-EBUS) es una técnica que se ha desarrollado para mejorar el rendimiento diagnóstico. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la efectividad de la R-EBUS en el diagnóstico de las LPP. Métodos: Se llevó a cabo un estudio retrospectivo en 174 pacientes a los que se habían diagnosticado LPP y a los que se practicó una broncoscopia bajo guía de EBUS. Para el diagnóstico se evaluó el examen histológico de las muestras obtenidas mediante biopsia pulmonar transbronquial (BPTB) y los exámenes citológicos del frotis de cepillado, líquido de irrigación del cepillado y líquido de lavado broncoalveolar (LLBA). Resultados: El diámetro medio de las LPP fue de 25,1 ± 10,7 mm. Los diagnósticos finales fueron 129 enfermedades malignas y 45 lesiones benignas. El rendimiento diagnóstico global de la broncoscopia bajo guía de EBUS fue del 79,9%. Ni el tamaño ni la etiología de las LPP mostraron influencia alguna en el rendimiento diagnóstico de la broncoscopia bajo guía de EBUS (82,9% frente al 74,6% para las LPP de tamaño &gt; 20 mm y las LPP de tamaño &amp;#8804; 20 mm; p = 0,19, y 82,9% frente al 71,1% para las enfermedades malignas y benignas; p = 0,09). La BPTB fue la que obtuvo el máximo rendimiento de entre estas diversas muestras (69,0, 50,6, 42,0 y 44,3% para las muestras de BPTB, frotis de cepillado, líquido de irrigación de cepillado y LLBA, respectivamente; p &lt; 0,001). La combinación de BPTB, frotis de cepillado y LLBA aportó el máximo rendimiento diagnóstico, mientras que el líquido de irrigación de cepillado no añadió una mejora adicional de los resultados. Conclusión: La broncoscopia bajo guía de R-EBUS es una técnica útil en el diagnóstico de las LPP. Para alcanzar el máximo rendimiento diagnóstico deben utilizarse conjuntamente la BPTB, el frotis de cepillado y el lavado broncoalveolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;50(9): 379-383, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de lesiones pulmonares periféricas con broncoscopia bajo guía de ecografía endobronquial radial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53085^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53085^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
