<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66829</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Lithium salts have been mainly used in the treatment of bipolar disorder. Because of its narrow therapeutic range, and several well characterised adverse effects, serum lithium levels must be monitored regularly in patients given lithium treatment in order to prevent intoxication. Objetive: To describe the clinic and toxic characteristics in inpatients at our Clinic Toxicologic Unit. Material and methods: Descriptive and retrospective study of lithium intoxications in 150 inpatients between 2003 and 2006. Patients were classified based on their neuropsychiathric symptom profile and serum lithium levels. Results: Sixteen of 150 inpatients had lithium intoxication: 58.3% women and 43.8% men; 49.19% ± 18.49% years old. Lithium was used as treatment of bipolar disorder in 87.5% of cases. The most frequent cause of intoxication was attempted suicide. Using neuropsychiatric parametres, intoxication was moderate in 50% of cases, and mild in 25% and severe or very severe in 25%. Using serum lithium levels, intoxication was very severe in 31.35%, severe in 25%, and slight-moderate in 43.7%. Conservative measures were used as the most frequent treatment (50%), and haemodial filtration was needed in 37.5%. Mean stay was 4,8 days in acute intoxication, and 11.2 days in chronic. Sequelaes were found in two patients (ataxia). Death was not present. Conclusions: Lithium intoxications can involve severe complications, even death. Narrow control is encouraged in polymedicated and elderly patients, and in concommitant treatment with antidepressant and neuroleptics</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera de Pablo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Escribá, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Silvestre, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Pablo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El litio, utilizado principalmente en el tratamiento de los trastornos bipolares, presenta un estrecho margen terapéutico, que junto a sus múltiples interacciones y farmacocinética obliga a una monitorización estrecha de concentraciones plasmáticas para evitar intoxicaciones. Objetivo: Describir características clínicas y toxicológicas de los pacientes ingresados en la Unidad Toxicología Clínica (2003-2006). Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo de 16 intoxicaciones por litio, de 150 pacientes ingresados entre los años 2003-2006. Se han utilizado dos escalas: según la clínica y los valores séricos de litio. Resultados: Dieciséis pacientes incluidos (58,3 mujeres y 43,8% hombres, 49,19 ± 18,49 años). Trastorno psiquiátrico más frecuente asociado bipolar (87,5%). Causa más frecuente de intoxicación, intento autolisis (56,3%). Según escala neurológica, 50% intoxicación moderada, 25% leve y grave o muy grave el 25% restante. En relación a los niveles de litemia, 31,35% muy grave, 25% graves, 43.7 % leve-moderado.Tratamiento más utilizado en un 50% conservador, hemodiálisis 37,5%, estancia media 4,8 días en intoxicaciones aguda, y 11,2 días en crónicas. Secuelas sólo en dos pacientes (ataxia), sin ninguna muerte. Conclusiones: Las intoxicaciones por litio conllevan gravedad clínica, complicaciones y graves secuelas, incluso la muerte. Se recomienda vigilancia estrecha en pacientes polimedicados, edad avanzada o en tratamiento concomitante de antidepresivos y neurolépticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(5): 209-212, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66829</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31698^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8267^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
