<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61348</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adult herpes simplex encephalitis: Fifteen years&#146; experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Herpes simplex encephalitis (HSE) is the most frequent cause of sporadic necrotizing encephalitis in adults. The aim of this study is to describe the characteristics of HSE and the factors influencing its outcome. Material and methods: Retrospective study of patients diagnosed with HSE in a tertiary care teaching hospital over a 15-year period. Diagnosis was based on a consistent clinical profile for HSE, plus either a PCR-positive CSF HSV study or consistent brain neuroimaging findings. Patients were divided into 2 groups according to the modified Rankin Scale: good outcome (Grades &amp;#8804;2) and poor outcome (Grades &amp;#8805;3).Results: Thirty-five patients were included. Mean age was 53.9 years. More than half presented febricula or fever, headache, disorientation, behavioral changes, decreased level of consciousness, or neurological deficit. CSF glucose concentration was normal in all patients and WBC count was normal in 8 (23%). PCR for HSV was positive in 92% and cranial MRI was suggestive of HSE in 100% of patients. Mortality was 8.6%. In relation to outcome, age (OR=1.079; 95% CI, 1.023&#150;1.138) and serum albumin level at admission (OR=0.87; 95% CI, 0.794&#150;0.954) were independent prognostic factors at discharge. At 6 months, days of fever after initiation of acyclovir therapy (OR=1.219; 95% CI, 1.046&#150;1.422) and serum albumin level at admission (OR=0.917; 95% CI, 0.87&#150;0.967) were independent prognostic factors.Conclusions: Normal brain MRI or detection of low CSF glucose concentration requires consideration of diagnoses other than HSE. Age, serum albumin level at admission, and days of fever after initiation of acyclovir therapy were independent prognostic factors of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabellos, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-Mestre, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Yelamos, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Viladrich, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gubieras, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la encefalitis herpética (EH) es la causa más frecuente de encefalitis necrosante esporádica del adulto. El objetivo es describir las características de la EH y sus factores pronósticos. Material y métodos: estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes ingresados en un hospital universitario de tercernivel y diagnosticados de EH durante un periodo de 15 años. El diagnóstico se estableció según el cuadro clínico compatible, junto con una prueba de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa(PCR) positiva para el virus del herpes simple (VHS) y/o una prueba de neuro imagen compatible. Se dividió a los pacientes en dos grupos de acuerdo con la Escala de Rankin modificada: buen pronóstico (grados p2) y mal pronóstico(grados X3).Resultados: se estudió a un total de 35 pacientes con una media de edad de 53,9 años. La mayoría presentaba febrícula o fiebre, cefalea, desorientación, alteración conductual, disminución del nivel deconciencia o focalidad neurológica. Todos los pacientes presentaron normoglucorraquia y el recuento leucocitario en el líquido cefalorraquídeo fue normal en 8 (23%)pacientes. La PCR para VHS resultó positiva en el 92% y la resonancia magnética (RM) craneal fue compatible con EH en el 100% de los pacientes. La mortalidad fue del 8,6%. La edad (odds ratio [OR] ¼ 1,079; intervalo de confianza [IC]del 95%, 1,023&#150;1,138) y las concentraciones de seroalbúmina al ingreso (OR ¼ 0,87; IC del 95%, ,0,794&#150;0,954) resultaron factores pronósticos independientes al alta. A los 6 meses, los días de fiebre después de la instauración del tratamiento con aciclovir (OR ¼ 1,219; ICdel95%, 1,046&#150;1,422) y las concentraciones de seroalbúmina al ingreso (OR ¼ 0,917; IC del 95%, 0,87&#150;0,967) resultaron factores pronósticos independientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;27(3): 143-147, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61348</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalitis herpética del adulto: experiencia de 15 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31042^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34168^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34168^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34168^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
