<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126901</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a male patient aged 28, with no toxic habits with a history of an episode of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation, which was cardioverted, and structural pathology discarding added to the picture. Diagnosed following a box pleuritic pain with low grade fever of lobar and segmental pulmonary thromboembolism bilateral pleural effusion with passive atelectasis predominantly left lower lobe, which evolved favorably with anticoagulants. It was performed thrombophilia in two determinations confirmed the deficit of protein C (chromogenic), so it is recommended to maintain anticoagulation indefinitely. This case raises the importance of differential diagnosis of embolic disease in young patients with pleuritic symptoms and family histories and the need to study associated coagulopathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ancochea-Bermúdez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segrelles-Calvo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Castillo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Pérez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Riolobos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente varón de 28 años, sin hábitos tóxicos, con antecedentes de un episodio aislado de fibrilación auricular paroxística, que fue cardiovertido, descartándose patología estructural subyacente. Es diagnosticado, tras un cuadro de dolor pleurítico con febrícula, de tromboembolismo pulmonar lobar derecho y segmentario bilateral con derrame pleural bilateral de predominio izquierdo con atelectasia pasiva del lóbulo inferior izquierdo, que evolucionó de forma favorable con tratamiento anticoagulante. Posteriormente, se realizó estudio de trombofilia, confirmándose en dos determinaciones, el déficit de proteína C (cromogénica), por lo que se recomendó mantener la anticoagulación de forma indefinida. Este caso plantea la importancia  del diagnóstico diferencial de patología embólica en pacientes jóvenes con síntomas pleuríticos, antecedentes familiares y lanecesidad de estudio de coagulopatías asociadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;17(3): 104-106, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor pleurítico en varón joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
