<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039385</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the neurologist in the pain unit?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:In the Multidisciplinary Chronic Pain Unit at the University Hospital &#147;12 de Octubre&#148; work a full-time anesthesiologist, a full-time specialist in internal medicine and a fulltime rheumatologist. They are supported by an occupational therapist and a psychologist. We review the usefulness of a neurology support service, which was originally aimed to contribute to the management of patientswith neuropathic pain, an specialty that in our hospital setting has traditionally not been involved in the care of these patients referred to pain units. Methods: We describe the activity of a neurology service over a sixmonth period. Such service is integrated in the Pain Unit and it is staffed by a neurologist that one day during the week assesses the patients referred to him by the Unit, issuesan interconsultation report and discuss his/her opinion with the referring physician or with the whole Unit. Demographic data, source of referrals to the Unit, reason of the referral to the Unit, reason of the referral to the neurology service, prior treatment, pain severity, length of evolution,diagnosis, presence and severity of neuropathic pain, presence or absence of occupational or legal psychiatric disorders, and whether the etiological diagnosis changed after consultation, physiopathogenic mechanisms involved in pain, and study plan, treatment, follow-up and destination. Results: The analysis of our study population, compared to the overall population of patients referred to the Unit, shows that our subpopulation has a greater mean age comparedto the population referred to the Unit and is of a high complexity, not only due to pain, but also to chronicity, severity and a long history of prior treatments. Interestingly, a significant percentage of the patients referred did not have neuropathic pain. Etiological diagnosis was changed in afew cases, but is most of them a better exploration of physiopathogenic mechanisms involved in neuropathic pain resulted in the variation of diagnosis study, therapeutic options and prognosis. Finally, when comparing the patients referred to our service with those of an outpatient neurologyservice, the absence of headaches and central pain conditions that could benefit from therapeutic options provided by a pain unit is surprising. Conclusions: We have shown how a consultant neurologist can be useful in a Pain Unit in order to contribute to the etiological diagnosis of complex patients, to confirm or discard the presence of neuropathic pain, to contribute to the study anddescription of several positive phenomena that are present and its potential relationship with specific physiopathological mechanisms, as the basis for ordering additional tests and treatments aimed to such mechanisms, to explain the patient the nature of his/her pain, and to help in the followup and prognosis. We believe that the model of a consultant neurologist integrated in a multidisciplinary chronic pain unit or working in parallel with an existing pain unit, improvesthe health care and the range of therapeutic options provided to patients with chronic painIntroduction:    In the Multidisciplinary Chronic Pain Unit at the University    Hospital &#147;12 de Octubre&#148; work a full-time anesthesiologist,    a full-time specialist in internal medicine and a fulltime    rheumatologist. They are supported by an    occupational therapist and a psychologist. We review the    usefulness of a neurology support service, which was originally    aimed to contribute to the management of patients    with neuropathic pain, an specialty that in our hospital setting    has traditionally not been involved in the care of these    patients referred to pain units.    Methods:    We describe the activity of a neurology service over a sixmonth    period. Such service is integrated in the Pain Unit    and it is staffed by a neurologist that one day during the    week assesses the patients referred to him by the Unit, issues    an interconsultation report and discuss his/her opinion    with the referring physician or with the whole Unit. Demographic    data, source of referrals to the Unit, reason of the    referral to the Unit, reason of the referral to the neurology    service, prior treatment, pain severity, length of evolution,    diagnosis, presence and severity of neuropathic pain, presence    or absence of occupational or legal psychiatric disorders,    and whether the etiological diagnosis changed after    consultation, physiopathogenic mechanisms involved in    pain, and study plan, treatment, follow-up and destination.    Results:    The analysis of our study population, compared to the    overall population of patients referred to the Unit, shows    that our subpopulation has a greater mean age compared    to the population referred to the Unit and is of a high complexity,    not only due to pain, but also to chronicity, severity    and a long history of prior treatments. Interestingly, a    significant percentage of the patients referred did not have    neuropathic pain. Etiological diagnosis was changed in a    few cases, but is most of them a better exploration of physiopathogenic    mechanisms involved in neuropathic pain resulted    in the variation of diagnosis study, therapeutic options    and prognosis. Finally, when comparing the patients    referred to our service with those of an outpatient neurology    service, the absence of headaches and central pain conditions    that could benefit from therapeutic options provided    by a pain unit is surprising.    Conclusions:    We have shown how a consultant neurologist can be useful    in a Pain Unit in order to contribute to the etiological diagnosis    of complex patients, to confirm or discard the presence    of neuropathic pain, to contribute to the study and    description of several positive phenomena that are present    and its potential relationship with specific physiopathological    mechanisms, as the basis for ordering additional tests    and treatments aimed to such mechanisms, to explain the    patient the nature of his/her pain, and to help in the followup    and prognosis. We believe that the model of a consultant    neurologist integrated in a multidisciplinary chronic pain unit    or working in parallel with an existing pain unit, improves    the health care and the range of therapeutic options provided    to patients with chronic pain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Salio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acedo, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción:La Unidad Multidisciplinaria de Dolor Crónico del Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre está compuesta por una anestesióloga, una internista y un reumatólogo con dedicación absoluta. Con ellos colaboran una rehabilitadora y una psicóloga. Se analiza la utilidad de una consulta de apoyode neurología, en principio destinada a contribuir al manejo de pacientes con dolor neuropático, especialidad que en nuestro medio tradicionalmente no ha participado en la atención a estos pacientes dentro de las Unidades del Dolor. Métodos: Se describe la actividad de la consulta de neurología durante seis meses. Dicha consulta está integrada en la Unidad, es desempeñada por un neurólogo que un día a la semana valora a los pacientes remitidos por la propia Unidad,emite un informe de interconsulta y discute con el médico remitente, o con toda la Unidad, su opinión. Se analizan las características demográficas, lugar de procedencia a la unidad,motivo de consulta en la unidad, motivo de consulta neurológico, tratamiento previo, intensidad del dolor, tiempo de evolución, diagnóstico, presencia e importancia del dolor neuropático, presencia o ausencia de patología psiquiátrica, laboral o judicial, y si hubo o no tras la consulta, modificación en el diagnóstico etiológico, de los mecanismos fisiopatogénicos involucrados en el dolor, en el plande estudio, tratamiento, seguimiento y destino. Resultados: Al analizar nuestra población, en comparación con el conjunto de la población de la Unidad destaca que este subgrupo es de mayor edad que el atendido en la Unidad y es de gran complejidad, no sólo debido a su dolor sinotambién a su cronicidad, intensidad y larga historia de tratamientos previos. Llama la atención que en un porcentaje significativo de los pacientes remitidos no había dolor neuropático,se modificó el diagnóstico etiológico en una minoría, pero en la mayoría una mejor exploración de los mecanismos fisiopatogénicos del dolor neuropático contribuyó a la variación del estudio diagnóstico, opciones de tratamiento y pronóstico. Por último, al comparar los pacientesatendidos con los de una consulta de neurología ambulatoria sorprende la ausencia en esta no sólo de cefaleas sino también de pacientes con dolores centrales que se podrían beneficiar de las posibilidades terapeúticas de una unidad del dolor. Conclusiones: Demostramos cómo un neurólogo consultor en una Unidad del Dolor puede ser útil para contribuir al diagnóstico etiológico de pacientes complejos, confirmar o descartar la presencia de dolor neuropático, contribuir al estudio y disección de los diferentes fenómenos positivos presentes y su posible adscripción a mecanismos fisiopatológicos concretos, base de la indicación de pruebas complementarias,de tratamientos dirigidos a esos mecanismos, explicar al paciente la naturaleza de su dolor, ayudar al seguimiento y pronóstico. Creemos que el modelo de un neurólogo consultor integrado en una Unidad Multidisciplinar de Dolor Crónico, frente a otros modelos de consultas unidisciplinareso en paralelo con las unidades de dolor ya existentes, enriquece la atención y la gama de opciones terapéuticas de los pacientes con dolor crónico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(3): 146-153, abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039385</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Para qué sirve un neurólogo en una Unidad del Dolor?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
