<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166167</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular magnetic resonance in the assessment of valvular heart disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Noninvasive imaging is extremely important in the assessment of a patient with valvular heart disease. It is essential for visualizing valvular morphology, including valve cusps, rings and the subvalvular apparatus, for assessing disease severity, and for providing data on ventricular dimensions and function, and aortic dimensions. With phasecontrast cardiovascular magnetic resonance, it is possible to measure regurgitant volume and peak flow velocity directly, thereby enabling the pressure gradient across a stenosis to be estimated. In addition, cardiac chambers and flow jets associated with a stenosis or regurgitation can be imaged exceptionally well using cine cardiovascular magnetic resonance. Furthermore, since ventricular dimensions and function can be measured accurately and reproducibly, it is possible to carry out follow-up studies. In this article, the main cardiovascular magnetic resonance techniques used in valve assessment are reviewed, with reference to the advantages and limitations of using cardiovascular magnetic resonance to provide clinically useful information in patients with valvular heart disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Igual Muñoz, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los métodos diagnósticos de imagen son importantes en la evaluación de las valvulopatías y necesarios para definir la morfología valvular, incluidos las valvas, el anillo y el aparato subvalvular, evaluar la gravedad de la afección, y obtener datos de volúmenes, función ventricular y diámetros aórticos. Con cardiorresonancia magnética (CRM), utilizando secuencias de contraste de fase, podemos medir directamente el volumen regurgitante, la velocidad pico y estimar así el gradiente a través de una estenosis. Las secuencias de cine nos permitirán una visualización privilegiada del tamaño de las cámaras cardiacas y de los jets de estenosis o regurgitación. Los volúmenes y la función ventricular pueden ser medidos de forma precisa y reproducible, lo que permite estudios de seguimiento. Revisaremos las principales técnicas que se utilizan en CRM para evaluar la función valvular, y sus ventajas y limitaciones para proporcionar información clínicamente útil en el paciente con afección valvular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.E): 15e-20e, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166167</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia cardiaca en el estudio de las valvulopatías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1028^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1027^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
