<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82636</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence based ophthalmology: critical appraisal skills on clinical trials on treatments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analyse and provide the tools to answer three questions that must be askedabout a clinical trial on treatments: evaluation of validity (internal validity, so that resultsare not biased); clinical importance of these results and their application to individualpatients. We provide simple statistics tools, clinical trial design, and clinical epidemiologyfor the evaluation and analysis of clinical trials on treatments.Methods: Review of the medical literature.Results: For the evaluation of papers on treatment and for using a treatment efficiently, weneed to know if the clinical trials that support it are trustworthy, if the treatment hasclinical importance and if it can be applied to my patients.Conclusions: It is of paramount importance to check that the sample of the clinical assayhas been correctly randomized, because randomization is necessary to comply withmathematical laws of application of statistical tests. Follow-up of patients must becomplete in order to measure precision of results and evaluate the efficacy of treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rouras-López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabiró-Badimón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta-Monnet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amías-Lamana, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa-Gutiérrez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar y proporcionar las herramientas para contestar a las tres preguntas quedebe responder un ensayo clínico aleatorizado (ECA) sobre tratamiento: la evaluación de lavalidez de los resultados (o validez interna, que garantiza que los resultados del estudio noestán sesgados); la importancia clínica de dichos resultados y si se pueden aplicar a pacientesindividuales. Suministraremos una serie de conocimientos sencillos de estadística,diseño de investigaciones y epidemiología clínica que nos permitirán evaluar y analizar losECA de tratamiento.Método: Revisión de la literatura.Resultados: Para evaluar artículos sobre tratamiento y para utilizar eficientemente un tratamientonecesitamos saber si los resultados de los ECA que los recomiendan son fiables,si tienen importancia clínica y si se pueden aplicar dichos resultados a mis pacientes.Conclusiones: Es absolutamente fundamental comprobar que en el ensayo clínico exista unadistribución aleatoria, ya que el muestreo aleatorio es imprescindible para que se cumplanlos requisitos matemáticos de aplicación de las pruebas estadísticas. El seguimiento de lospacientes debe ser completo y debe medir la magnitud de los resultados y su precisiónpara así poder medir la eficacia del tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;85(1): 2-10, ene. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82636</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Oftalmología basada en evidencias: evaluación crítica de los ensayos clínicos sobre tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
