<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042631</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary intraosseous carcinoma and odontogenic cyst. Three new cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Odontogenic Primary Intraosseous Carcinoma (PIOC) are a rare group of malignant tumours with strict clinic and anatomy pathological diagnosis criteria. The different classification suggested for these tumours and the small amount of cases described in literature makes it hard to know exactly how many of the cases published until now are real.Material and methods: We present three new cases of PIOC originated from a previous cystic lesion that where treated in our Hospital. Two of them in the posterior jaw region where is more frequent, and the third in the upper jaw. We explain the procedure we used in each case and the aesthetic-functional reconstruction used witches are two fibula osseomiocutaneousfree flaps and a bone graft of iliac crest and further placing of implants. The classification, the clinical and radiological diagnosis, the treatment and its survival are discussed.Results: in all three cases we were able to see in the anatomy pathological study an epithelial, exclusively without surrounding oral mucosa affectation or tissues near the lesion as well as the lack of tumorous pathology in other parts of the body. One of the patients died because of premature massive cervical recidiva while the other two patients are currently free form illness, for ten years one of them and fifteen months the other.Conclusions: the anatomy pathological study of all of the lesions of cystic characteristics at jaw level is very important because of the risk of coexisting with carcinomatous cells. The treatment of these tumours consists in practising aggressive surgery and, in some cases, radio and/or chemotherapy post intervention</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aboul-hosn Centenero, Samir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluch, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marí Roig, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Carandell, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez Escalona, Inma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monner Diéguez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piulachs Clapera, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pericot Ayats, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los Carcinomas Intraóseos Primarios Odontogénicos (PIOC) son un raro grupo de tumores malignos con unos estrictos criterios diagnósticos clínicos y anatomo-patológicos. Las diferentes clasificaciones sugeridas para estos tumores y el escaso número de casos descritos en la literatura hacen difícil conocer con exactitud cuantos son los casos reales publicados hasta el día de hoy. Material y métodos: presentamos tres nuevos casos de PIOC originados a partir de una lesión quística previa que fueron tratadosen nuestro centro. Dos en región posterior mandibular que es el lugar de más frecuente aparición, y un tercero en maxilar superior. Explicamos el tipo de cirugía llevado a cabo en cada caso y la reconstrucción estético-funcional utilizada que son dos injertos osteomiocutáneos de peroné y un injerto de hueso de cresta iliaca con posterior colocación de implantes. Se discute la clasificación, el diagnóstico clinico-radiológico, el tratamiento y su supervivencia.Resultados: en los tres casos se pudo constatar en la anatomía patológica un epitelio celular bien diferenciado acompañando a células carcinomatosas afectando al hueso exclusivamente sin afectación de la mucosa oral circundante ni de tejidos vecinos a la lesión así como ausencia de patología tumoral en otra zona del organismo. Uno de los pacientes falleció por recidiva cervical masiva precoz mientras que los otros dos están libres de enfermedad en la actualidad después de 10 años en uno de ellos y 15 meses en el otro. Conclusiones: es muy importante el análisis anatomo-patológico de todas las lesiones de características quísticas a nivel maxilarpor el riesgo de coexistir con células carcinomatosas. El tratamiento de estos tumores debe ser la práctica de una cirugía agresiva y, en algunos casos, asociados a radio y/o quimioterapia post intervención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(1): 61-65, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma primario intraóseo y quiste odontogénico. Tres casos clínicos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24222^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24222^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24222^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
