<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96749</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contained laparostomy with a Bogota bag. Results of case series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The «Bogota bag» (BB) is one of the options for contained laparostomy (CL). The aim of this study was to report the procedure associated hospital morbidity (PAHM) in patients undergoing relaparotomy followed by a laparostomy using the BB. Material and method: Between 2002 and 2008, a prospective series of patients who underwent relaparotomy at the Hospital Hernan Henrýquez, Temuco (Chile) was evaluated. The main end point was «development of PAHM». Secondary end points were: indications of the CL, time to first change of the BB, type of abdominal wall repair, hospital mortality and development of ventral hernia. Descriptive statistics were used, with the calculations of percentages and measures of central tendency and dispersion. Results: The BB was used in 86 patients (median age of 53 years, 63% female). The PAHMwas38% (surgical-site infection and enterocutaneous fistula). The most frequent indication of CL was intra-abdominal sepsis (60%). The median time until the first change of the BB, the time period between surgical operations, and the time until removal of the BB were 65 hours,2 days and 9 days, respectively. Laparostomy was repaired exclusively with skin, fascia closure or dermal-epidermal graft in 50, 39 and 10%, respectively. In hospital mortality was12%. Sixty percent of the patients developed a ventral hernia within a 48 month follow-up. Conclusions: CL with a BB is associated with a high rate of PAHM and delayed complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urrutia, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraga, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manterola, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Una opción de laparostomía contenida (LC) es la «bolsa de Bogotá» (BB). El objetivo de este estudio es comunicar los resultados observados en una serie de pacientes relaparotomizados con LC utilizando la BB, en términos de morbilidad hospitalaria asociada al procedimiento (MHAP). Material y método Serie de casos prospectiva de pacientes relaparotomizados en el Hospital Hernán Henríquez de Temuco, entre 2002 y 2008. La variable resultado fue «desarrollo de MHAP». Otras variables de interés fueron: indicaciones de la LC, tiempo hasta el primer recambio de la BB, periodicidad de las intervenciones quirúrgicas, tiempo hasta la retirada de la BB, tipo de reparación de la pared abdominal, mortalidad hospitalaria y desarrollo de hernia incisional. Se utilizó estadística descriptiva; con cálculo de porcentajes, medidas de tendencia central y dispersión. Resultados En el período de estudio, se utilizó la BB en 86 pacientes (63% eran de género femenino), con una mediana de edad de 53 años. La MHAP fue 38% (infección de sitio operatorio y fístula enterocutánea). La indicación más frecuente de LC fue sepsis intra-abdominal (60%). Las medianas del tiempo hasta el primer recambio de la BB, periodicidad de las intervenciones quirúrgicas y tiempo hasta la retirada de la BB fueron 65 horas, 2 días y 9 días, respectivamente. La reparación de la laparostomía fue con cierre de piel exclusivo, cierre aponeurótico o injerto dermoepidérmico en 50, 39 y 10%, respectivamente. La mortalidad hospitalaria fue 12%. Tras un seguimiento de 48 meses se verificó que el 60% de los pacientes desarrollaron hernia incisional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(6): 379-385, jun.-jul. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Laparostomía contenida con bolsa de Bogotá. Resultados de una serie de casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54251^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
