<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163527</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastric lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma: diagnostic criteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gastric lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma is a rare and poorly characterized condition which historically has not been considered a specific entity, usually being considered synonymous with medullary carcinoma and conventional gastric carcinoma with lymphoid stroma. However, the differentiation of this entity is of clinical and prognostic importance. We report a case of a 77 year old man who presented with a gastric ulcer in the fundus. Histological examination revealed the presence of neoplastic glandular structures with marked lymphoid stroma. The immunohistochemical staining showed strong expression for Epstein-Barr virus and DNA repair proteins with a distinctive lymphoid cell distribution. The aim of our study is to determine criteria useful in the recognition of this unusual condition and assess the inmunophenotype of the lymphoid population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar-Rodríguez, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Caulo, Adrián P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Domingo, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Rodríguez, Katherine M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El carcinoma gástrico tipo linfoepitelioma es una entidad poco frecuente y mal caracterizada. Históricamente no se ha considerado una entidad como tal y frecuentemente se ha utilizado como sinónimo del carcinoma medular y del carcinoma gástrico convencional con estroma linfoide. Diferenciar esta entidad tiene mucha relevancia tanto clínica como pronóstica. Se describe un caso de un hombre de 77 años con una lesión ulcerada en fundus. El examen histológico reveló unas estructuras neoplásicas glandulares acompañadas de un marcado estroma linfoide. Dicha lesión presentó intensa expresión del virus de Epstein-Barr, expresión de las proteínas reparadoras del ADN y una distribución característica de las poblaciones linfoides. El objetivo de este estudio es definir criterios útiles que permitan distinguir esta inusual lesión y estudiar el inmunofenotipo de las poblaciones linfoides (AU9</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;50(3): 174-178, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma gástrico de tipo linfoepitelioma: criterios diagnósticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33083^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23303^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
