<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050114</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical insulin management of the diabetic patient in the hospital setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The acknowledgement of hyperglycemia as a key factor in the life    expectancy of patients suffering from acute vascular events    together with the introduction of the new insulin analogues has led    to the revision of the guidelines for insulin administration to the    hospitalized diabetic patient. The current goal is to implement    practical protocols to improve glycemic control in the hospital    setting without increasing the burden of the people involved in    patient care. First of all, the target blood glucose level has to be    well defined, taking into account the prior control and the degree of    insulin deficiency. Secondly, it is necessary to maintain or even    improve the previous treatment, particularly for patients under    intensive insulin schedules or wearing insulin pumps. Additionally,    insulin requirements change throughout the hospital stay. Thus, the    insulin doses have to be reviewed and adjusted frequently. In    summary, the two cornerstones of inpatient insulin therapy are: the    use of intravenous insulin infusion during the acute process and a    basal-bolus regimen for subcutaneous treatment. These strategies    deliver sufficient insulin to prevent substrate mobilization while    fasting and provide effective postprandial insulin levels. Another    aspect to be taken into account is the risk of hyperglycemia or    hypoglycemia when the patient is transferred from the critical care    unit to the conventional care setting, and from hospital to    ambulatory care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rigla Cros, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El reconocimiento de la hiperglucemia como factor clave en el pronóstico    vital del paciente ingresado por patología vascular aguda y la introducción    de nuevos análogos de insulina han hecho revisar los protocolos de    tratamiento del paciente diabético ingresado. A partir de antiguos    esquemas de tratamiento con pautas de insulina supuestamente    correctoras, se está intentando implementar sistemas terapéuticos que,    siendo seguros, ofrezcan al paciente un mejor grado de control sin    sobrecargar la tarea diaria de los profesionales sanitarios. En primer lugar,    se han de defi nir claramente los objetivos de glucemia y valorar el grado    de control y de insulinopenia previo. En segundo lugar, se ha de    mantener o mejorar el esquema de tratamiento anterior al ingreso,    especialmente en pacientes con terapia intensiva o tratados con infusores    de insulina. Por otro lado, hay que considerar que las necesidades de    insulina constituyen una variable cambiante a lo largo del ingreso, lo que    difi cultará la estabilidad del control y obligará a revisiones muy frecuentes    de la pauta de tratamiento. En resumen, estas pautas se basan en dos    pilares: el tratamiento con insulina intravenosa (i.v.) en fase crítica y el    esquema basal-bolo en las pautas de insulina subcutáneas (s.c.). Así,    debe garantizarse el aporte básico de insulina que inhiba la movilización    de sustratos en ausencia de ingestiones y que permita disponer de una    insulinemia posprandial eficaz. Otro punto importante es el riesgo de    hiper- o hipoglucemia en la transición de las unidades de críticos a las    salas convencionales, y de éstas al domicilio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;22(3): 200-206, jul.-sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pautas de tratamiento insulínico en el paciente diabético hospitalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38089^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
