<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76426</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sudden myositis of the posterior cervical muscular compartment. Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An atypical case of deep neck infection is presented with muscular involvement as the main feature. Streptococcus pyogenes was the causal agent and abrupt haemodynamic impairment and severe systemic failure characterized its clinical course, requiring emergency surgical examination and subsequent admission to the critical care unit. After the diagnosis of Streptococcal Myositis was obtained and the antibiotic treatment adjusted, the patient progressively recovered completely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quer Agustí, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol Olmo, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Aguín, Zenaida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virós Porcuna, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarraonandia Andraca, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de infección cervical profunda atípica con afectación principalmente muscular, cuyo agente causal fue Streptococcus pyogenes, y cuya clínica y evolución se caracterizaron por un brusco deterioro hemodinámico y fallo sistémico severo que hizo necesaria una exploración quirúrgica urgente y su posterior ingreso en la UCI. Tras el diagnóstico de miositis estreptocócica y el pertinente cambio de pauta antibiótica, el paciente presentó una mejoría progresiva hasta su restitución completa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;61(1): 81-84, ene.-feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miositis fulminante del compartimento muscular cervical posterior. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10600^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
