<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130763</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">RIU project: Perceived changes by health agents and professionals after a health intervention in an urban area of socioeconomic disadvantage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe how health agents and professionals working in a community project perceive the changes related to the population health status and their use of health-care services after the RIU intervention in an urban area of socioeconomic disadvantage. Design: A qualitative descriptive study based on individual and group interviews and participant observation conducted between October 2008-July 2009. Location: Raval (Algemesí-Valencia) Participants: We selected by purposive sample 7 women health agents, all persons who completed the intervention, and 10 professionals for their involvement in the intervention. Method: We conducted a group interview with the women at 6 months and a group and 7 individuals interviews both at 9 months of intervention. We realized a thematic descriptive analysis from health promotion framework. We used participant observation in a meeting with professionals at 9 months and analyzed field notes as: appraisal project, detected changes, challenges and recommendations. Results: Women acquired information about health, contraception, pregnancy and heath services; they noted changes in self-care and social skills and leadership; they internalized the role of health worker disseminating what they learned and showed improvement in self-esteem and social recognition. They caused changes in the people related on health care and access to services. Professionals didn&#146;t incorporate at their work the community perspective; they valued positively the project; professionals and women agreed on improving access and use of services and closeness population-professionals. Conclusions: RIU increases the capabilities of the participants, their social recognition and improves access and use of health services (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>La Parra Casado, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Dardet, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró-Pérez, Rosana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes-Carbonell, Joan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aviñó, Dory</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los cambios percibidos por la población y los profesionales en relación con la salud y el uso de servicios tras la intervención RIU con agentes comunitarios en un barrio vulnerable. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo cualitativo con entrevistas individuales y grupales y observación participante de octubre de 2008 a julio de 2009. Emplazamiento: Barrio Raval (Algemesí-Valencia). Participantes: Selección por muestreo opinático de 7 mujeres agentes de salud, todas las que finalizaron la intervención, y 10 profesionales implicados en la misma. Método: Con las mujeres se mantuvo una entrevista grupal a los 6 meses, y una entrevista grupal y 7 individuales a los 9 meses de intervención. Se realizó un análisis temático de tipo descriptivo desde el modelo de promoción de salud. Con los profesionales se utilizó observación participante en una reunión a los 9 meses, analizándose las notas de campo según: valoración del proyecto, cambios detectados, dificultades y recomendaciones. Resultados: Las mujeres adquirieron información sobre salud, anticoncepción, embarazo y servicios sanitarios; señalaron cambios en autocuidados y habilidades sociales y liderazgo; interiorizaron el rol de agente de salud difundiendo lo aprendido y manifestando mejor autoestima y reconocimiento social. Provocaron cambios en su entorno relativos al cuidado de la salud y el acceso a los servicios. Los profesionales no incorporaron a su trabajo la perspectiva comunitaria; valoraron el proyecto, coincidieron con las mujeres en la mejora del acceso y uso de servicios y en el acercamiento población-profesionales. Conclusiones: RIU aumenta las capacidades de las personas participantes, su reconocimiento social y mejora el acceso y uso de servicios sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(10): 531-540, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Projecte RIU: cambios percibidos por agentes de salud y profesionales tras una intervención en salud en un barrio en situación de vulnerabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
