<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92099</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approach to the scientific work of medical Commander Fidel Pagés Miravé</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A. Faulconer in his book «Foundations of Anesthesiology», referring to Pagés says: «There are little data on the life of this important Spanish surgeon». This conclusive statement attached to unforgivable omissions to the figure of Pagés by historians of anesthesia or surgery, and to serious errors in facts about his life or work, led us to make an approximation as accurate as possible, to the scientific work of the Medical commander Fidel Pagés Miravé. Few figures have been the Spanish who have made some interesting news to the world of anesthesia. But none so wronged and forgotten like Pagés, a true pioneer of epidural anesthesia, that he would call Metameric Anesthesia in his article published in the month of March, 1921, in the Spanish Journal of Surgery, founded by him. Years later, in 1931, Dogliotti, Professor of Surgery in Modena published his experiences on the epidural, which he called Segmental Epidural Anesthesia, ignoring the work published ten years earlier by Pagés. Dogliotti&#146;s work was quickly recognized, assuming all the merits of the paternity of the epidural technique, being Pagés relegated to an unfair oblivion that this work is trying to repair. Feeling the need to locate Pagés on the environment in which he developed his scientific work, we try to realize a vision of the main surgical and anesthetic contributions of surgeons who were contemporaries with Pagés. With special sake, we delve into the historical precedents of spinal or caudal anesthesia techniques, as well as Pagés later descriptions on the lumbar approach of the epidural route. At the same time, we conducted a comparative analysis of the work of Pagés on metameric anesthesia in relation to the current force that may have their comments, descriptions, indications and contraindications. The central idea of the work will focus on the recognition of Pagés as a true promoter of the epidural approach with surgical aims. And to evaluate a work which, though short, may well be included among the best spanish surgeons in the beginning of the century. We focus for the collection of data on their records (Zaragoza and Madrid), on his records as a military doctor and on publications about the History of Anesthesia, history of Surgery and of the Military Health. To better know his character we have located his family and review the official journals of the Ministry of War, the complete collections of the main newspapers of the time, especially in Madrid and Melilla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velázquez Rivera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A. Faulconer en su libro «Foundations of Anesthesiology» refiriéndose a Pagés afirma: «No se encuentran apenas datos sobre la vida de este importante cirujano español». Esta concluyente afirmación unida a imperdonables omisiones de la figura de Pagés por historiógrafos de la anestesia o de la cirugía, y a graves errores en datos sobre su vida u obra, nos movió a realizar una aproximación, lo más exacta posible, a la obra científica del Comandante Médico Fidel Pagés Miravé. Escasas han sido las figuras españolas que hayan aportado alguna interesante novedad al mundo de la anestesia. Pero ninguna tan injustamente tratada y olvidada como la de Pagés, verdadero pionero de la anestesia epidural, que él denominaría Anestesia Metamérica en su artículo publicado en el mes de marzo de 1921 en la Revista Española de Cirugía, por él fundada. Años después, en 1931, Dogliotti, Profesor de Cirugía de Modena publicó sus experiencias sobre la anestesia epidural, a la que llamó Anestesia Peridural Segmentaria, ignorando el trabajo de Pagés publicado diez años antes. El trabajo de Dogliotti fue rápidamente reconocido, asumiendo todos los méritos de la paternidad de la técnica epidural, quedando Pagés relegado a un olvido injusto que con este trabajo tratamos de reparar. En la necesidad de ubicar a Pagés en el entorno en el que desarrolló su obra científica, tratamos de realizar una visión de las principales aportaciones quirúrgicas y anestésicas de aquellos cirujanos que fueron coetáneos con nuestro personaje. Con especial abundamiento, profundizamos en los precedentes históricos de las técnicas de anestesia intradural o caudal, así como las descripciones posteriores a Pagés sobre el abordaje lumbar de la vía epidural. A su vez realizamos un análisis comparativo del trabajo de Pagés sobre la anestesia metamérica, en relación con la actual vigencia que puedan tener sus observaciones, descripciones, indicaciones y contraindicaciones. La idea central del trabajo versará sobre el reconocimiento de Pagés como verdadero promotor del abordaje epidural con fines quirúrgicos. Así como valorar una obra que, aunque corta, bien pudiera incluirse entre los mejores cirujanos españoles de principio de siglo. Nos centramos, para la recopilación de datos, en sus expedientes académicos (Zaragoza y Madrid), en su hoja de servicios como Médico Militar y en las publicaciones sobre Historia de la Anestesia, Historia de la Cirugía y de la Sanidad Militar. Para mejor conocer al Personaje hemos localizado a su familia y revisamos los diarios oficiales del Ministerio de la Guerra las colecciones completas de la principal prensa de la época, especialmente las de Madrid y Melilla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(supl.1): 193-238, jul.  2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación a la obra científica del Comandante médico Fidel Pagés Miravé</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
