<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138411</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of hippotherapy on postural stability in cerebral palsy: report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The lack of postural control is often the limiting factor to participate in activities of daily life. It has been identified as the major limitation for motor development of children with cerebral palsy. Therefore, assessment of postural control and balance in cerebral palsy is especially important for orienting the treatment in clinical practice. This study has aimed to show the evolution of postural stability in a child with cerebral palsy who receives hippotherapy. Case description: We present the case of an 8-year old girl suffering right-hemiparesis as a result of a cerebral palsy. Intervention Fourteen 14 hippotherapy sessions were performed, each of them once a week with 45 minute duration. Postural stability was evaluated with a pressure platform, performing two measurement types: static and posturological, with open and closed eyes. Results: The results indicate that there were positive changes after the intervention of the distribution of footprint, location of the center of gravity and postural stability in anteroposterior direction. The average lateral axis expressed the less improvement. Furthermore, the best exchange rates occurred with closed eyes. Discussion The literature shows a significant improvement in postural stability after having conducted hippotherapy treatment. The changes produced by therapeutic intervention can be seen when performing a comprehensive assessment and the use of a barometric platform (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-García, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Apolo-Arenas, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gutiérrez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caña-Pino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: La falta de control postural es a menudo el factor limitante para participar en actividades de la vida diaria, identificándose como la mayor limitación para el desarrollo motor de los niños con parálisis cerebral. Es por ello de especial importancia la valoración del control postural y del equilibrio en la parálisis cerebral, para la orientación del tratamiento en la práctica clínica. El objetivo de este estudio es mostrar la evolución de la estabilidad postural en una niña con parálisis cerebral que recibe hipoterapia. Descripción del caso: Se presenta el caso de una niña de 8 años con hemiparesia derecha como resultado de una parálisis cerebral. Intervención: Se han realizado 14 sesiones de hipoterapia llevadas a cabo una vez por semana y con duración de 45 min cada sesión. La valoración de la estabilidad postural se ha analizado con una plataforma de presión, realizando 2 tipos de medición: estática y posturológica, con ojos abiertos y cerrados. Resultados: Tras la intervención, existen modificaciones positivas en la distribución de la huella plantar, la ubicación del centro de gravedad y la estabilidad postural en sentido antero-posterior, siendo el eje medio-lateral el que ha manifestado menos variabilidad de mejora. Además, los mejores porcentajes de cambio se han producido con los ojos cerrados. Discusión: La literatura nos muestra que se produce una mejoría significativa de la estabilidad postural después de haber llevado a cabo un tratamiento de hipoterapia. Realizando una valoración exhaustiva y con la utilización de una plataforma barométrica podemos observar las modificaciones producidas por la intervención terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(3): 135-139, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la hipoterapia en la estabilidad postural en parálisis cerebral infantil: a propósito de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
