<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80738</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of full thickness defects on the chest wall. Presentation of 8 complex cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of full thickness defects on the chest wall is controversial and require the use of complex techniques that combine autologous tissue and/or alloplastic materials. Thus it is a challenge for plastic surgeons since it needs a suitable and functional reconstruction. The aethiology for these defects include tumoral surgery (primary wall tumors, or recurrences or metastasis), infections, radiation injury, trauma and congenital defects. Otherwise, first surgical treatment require wide resection of the tumor or ischaemic or radiated tissue and control of the infection, but these principles could not be safely faced without the multiple reconstructive techniques that can afford the use of well vascularized, large or bulky tissues to reconstruct this anatomical area in combination with alloplastic materials, in order to give a solid stabilization. Thanks to these advances, we can actually perform our objectives in only one procedure. We present a selection of complex chest wall defects tha thave been operated in the last years by our surgical team. We will describe the solutions and the results obtained by means of a variety of possible flaps and synthetic materials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uceda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasso, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Cano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las lesiones de gran tamaño en el tórax, requieren casi siempre para su reparación plastias complejas, que en algunos casos han de combinar el uso de tejidos autólogos y/o materiales sintéticos. Por tanto, la reconstrucción de la pared torácica supone un desafío desde el punto de vista reconstructivo en el que es fundamental el papel de los cirujanos plásticos. Los grandes defectos torácicos suelen ser secundarios a exéresis tumoral (tumores parietales de origen primario o secundario), infecciones, radionecrosis, traumatismos y malformaciones congénitas. Si bien los principios de la reconstrucción del tórax exigen una escisión amplia de la lesión, desbridamiento de los tejidos desvitalizados o irradiados y control de la infección local, dichas actuaciones no podrían abordarse con seguridad si no dispusiéramos de un amplio arsenal de técnicas reconstructivas, capaces de aportar tejidos sanos y bien vascularizados o voluminosos y amplios en superficie, junto con soportes rígidos mediante materiales aloplásticos. Gracias a estos avances, en la mayoría de los casos conseguimos el objetivo con sólo una intervención, cuando hace unos años necesitábamos varios procedimientos quirúrgicos. Presentamos una muestra variada de la experiencia de nuestro Servicio en el tratamiento de grandes defectos del tórax, en el que resumimos las distintas posibilidades que podemos encontrar en la práctica clínica diaria, y las soluciones que mejor se adaptan a las mismas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;35(4): 249-260, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción de defectos torácicos de espesor total. Presentación de 8 casos de especial complejidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
