<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81158</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The celiac axis compression syndrome (CACS): critical review in the laparoscopic era</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The celiac axis compression syndrome (CACS) due to medianarcuate ligament (MAL) was first described by Harjola in 1963;originating postpandrial abdominal pain, weight loss, epigastricbruit and celiac axis stenosis &gt; 75% in angiographic studies. Thisclinical condition has been the origin of controversies about itspathogenesis, diagnosis and its long term clinical results.Advances in diagnostic imaging as 64 multidetector&#150;row CT(MDCT), 3-D reconstruction, magnetic resonance (MR) and colorduplex ultrasonography, provide better understanding of the syndromeand allow to identify the best candidates for surgical divisionof MAL fibers.Since the introduction of laparoscopic approach, and also endovascularprocedures, in 2000, a new perspective has establishedin this challenging syndrome. With the occasion of our ownexperience, a critical review of the syndrome is presented(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arredondo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rotellar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valentí, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cienfuegos, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de compresión del tronco celiaco fue descrito porHarjola en 1963 como la compresión extrínseca del tronco celiacopor las fibras tendinosas del ligamento arcuato; causando uncuadro de dolor intenso post-pandrial en epigastrio, pérdida depeso, soplo epigástrico y estenosis mayor del 75% en la angiografíaselectiva. Desde entonces, dicho síndrome ha sido motivo demúltiples controversias relacionadas con su patogenia y la variabilidadde los resultados obtenidos con la cirugía.Debido a la proliferación y accesibilidad de técnicas de imagenmás precisas y menos invasivas (angio-TAC multicorte, angio-RMN, eco-doppler), el diagnóstico de dicho síndrome puede realizarsecon mayor precisión y sentar las bases de la indicación quirúrgicacon mayor seguridad y eficacia.La introducción, en el año 2000, de técnicas laparoscópicasen la liberación del tronco celiaco, junto con procedimientos endovascularescomplementarios, ha representado un notable avanceen el tratamiento del síndrome.Basados en nuestra experiencia personal, presentamos una revisióncrítica y propuesta terapéutica del síndrome(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;102(3): 193-201, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de compresión del tronco celiaco. Revisión crítica en la era de la cirugía laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22421^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2480^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
