<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97800</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Krukenberg tumor secondary to carcinoma of the colon during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Krukenberg tumor is defined as a metastatic uni- or bilateral ovarian tumor that contains significant amounts of signet ring cells and whose origin is mainly gastrointestinal. The incidence of metastatic tumors of the ovary is very small (1-5%), and that of the concurrence of an ovarian mass with metastatic malignant features and pregnancy is negligible. We report the case of a 19-year-old woman who, 18 months after diagnosis of a mucinous adenocarcinoma of the colon, was diagnosed with a Krukenberg tumor in the 29th week of pregnancy. Initially, cesarean section together with tumoral resection was performed. In a second stage, cytoreductive surgery was performed with hyperthermic intraoperative intraperitoneal chemotherapy. The patient is currently in clinical remission and is monitored by the oncology service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Martí, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcalde Pérez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Pinel, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Partal Lorente, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallarés Ayuso, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena Ramírez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor de Krukenberg se define como aquel tumor metastásico en ovario uni o bilateral que contiene cantidades importantes de células en anillo de sello y cuyo origen es principalmente digestivo. La incidencia de tumores metastásicos en ovario es muy pequeña (1-5%); asimismo la coincidencia de una masa ovárica de características malignas metastásicas con una gestación es ínfima. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 19 años que tras el diagnóstico de un adenocarcinoma mucinoso de colon, a los 18 meses presenta un tumor de Krukenberg en la semana 29 de gestación. En un primer momento se le realizó cesárea junto a cirugía resectiva del tumor. En un segundo tiempo se le practicó cirugía citorreductora asociada a quimioterapia intraperitoneal intraoperatoria hipertérmica, encontrándose actualmente en remisión clínica y en seguimiento por el servicio de oncología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(3): 121-124, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de Krukenberg secundario a carcinoma de colon durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31745^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31806^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31745^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31745^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
