<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80338</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drawing of blood and anemia of the critical patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the hemoglobin level variations in non-bleeding patients, itspossible relationship with the blood volume drawn and number of extractions.Methods. An observational, prospective study conducted from April to August 2007. Hemoglobinvalues during the ICU stay, blood volume drawn in each phlebotomy, fluid balance,APACHE II and other demographic variables were determined.Results. One hundred and twenty four patients were studied. Of these, 59.7% experienceda mild decrease of hemoglobin levels (&lt; 2g/dl) whereas 21.8% presented a more severe reduction (&gt; 2g/dl). These decreases were correlated with the blood volumewithdrawn and number of phlebotomies performed (r= 0.557, p &lt; 0.000). There was nosignificant relationship between fluid balance and decrease in hemoglobin.Conclusion. Anemia in critical ill patient seems to be related to blood volume drawn andnumber of phlebotomies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Delgado, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suero Zun¨®n, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>S¨¢nchez S¨¢nchez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las variaciones de hemoglobina en pacientes no sangrantes, su posiblerelaci¨®n con volumen de sangre extra¨ªdo y n¨²mero de extracciones.M¨¦todos. Estudio observacional y prospectivo realizado desde abril hasta agosto de 2007.Se determinaron los valores de hemoglobina durante la estancia en Unidad de CuidadosIntensivos, volumen extra¨ªdo en cada anal¨ªtica, balance h¨ªdrico, APACHE II (Acute Physiologyand Chronic Health Evaluation II) y otras variables demogr¨¢ficas. Aplicamos an¨¢lisisdescriptivo y de regresi¨®n lineal para conocer el comportamiento de estas variables.Resultados. Se estudiaron 124 pacientes. El 59,7% sufri¨® una disminuci¨®n leve de hemoglobina(descenso de hemoglobina ¡Ü 2g/dl), siendo ¨¦sta m¨¢s grave (p¨¦rdida de hemoglobina¡Ý 2 g/dl) en el 21,8%. Estas disminuciones se correlacionaron con el volumen extra¨ªdoy el n¨²mero de flebotom¨ªas, r = 0,557 (p: ns). No se encontr¨® relaci¨®n entre balanceh¨ªdrico y disminuci¨®n de hemoglobina.Conclusiones. La anemia en el paciente cr¨ªtico se relaciona con altos vol¨²menes de sangreextra¨ªda y n¨²mero de extracciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;20(4): 141-147, dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Extracciones de sangre y anemia del paciente cr¨ªtico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22198^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
