<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96082</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Commotio cordis as a cause of sudden cardiac death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Commotio cordis is responsible for the sudden cardiac death of an individual with an anatomically normal heart after moderate precordial impact with a blunt object. Victims are usually young and typically players of contact sports,although cases have also occurred during normal daily activities. The pathogenesis seems to be related to occurrence ofthe R-on-T phenomenon at a moment when the heart is particularly vulnerable to repolarization; ventricular fibrillation then triggers cardiorespiratory arrest. Recently, patient registries have been established to allow study of theepidemiologic characteristics and test physical medicine approaches to preventing commotio cordis. However, even if basic life support and chain-of-survival measures have taken place promptly, the rates of recovery from cardiorespiratory arrest due to commotio cordis are markedly lower than might be expected from the age and health status of the victims.The condition is generally fatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Malagón Caussade, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Blas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los eventos de muerte súbita cardiaca (MSC) en corazones estructuralmente normales causados por impactos de escasa entidad en la región precordial se denominan commotio cordis. Las víctimas suelen ser muy jóvenes, habitualmente se produce en el contexto de prácticas deportivas, aunque también se ha descrito su aparición durante actividades cotidianas. La patogenia parece estar relacionada con un fenómeno de &#147;Rs obre T&#148; en un instante particularmente vulnerable de la repolarización cardiaca, que desencadena una parada cardiorrespiratoria (PCR) por fibrilación ventricular. Recientemente, la aparición de registros específicos de casos ha permitido indagar sobre las características epidemiológicas y ensayar medios físicos de prevención de la commotio cordis. Sin embargo, aunque se produzca una instauración precoz del soporte vital básico y la activación de la cadena de supervivencia, las tasas de recuperación de PCR causadas por commotio cordis son bastante inferiores a lo esperable por la edad y el estado de salud de las víctimas; y con un desenlace, generalmente fatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(6): 471-478, dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Muerte súbita cardiaca causada por commotio cordis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
