<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103659</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Agreement in height for age between growth references. Caldas, Colombia. 2006-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: different anthropometric references have been proposed and even used in Colombia. However, there are few previous studies reporting results when these references are used and there is no consensus about the ideal reference to be adopted. The objective of this study was to evaluate the concordance between three different anthropometric references in the assessment of height for age in a population under 17 years of age that attended the nutritional program at CONFAMILIARES, Caldas, Colombia, between 2006 and 2009. Methods: a descriptive study of 31.961 children under 17 years attending the nutrition program CONFAMILIARES, Caldas, Colombia between 2006 and 2009. The variables were the height for age and sex. Anthropometric classification with references from the National Center for Health Statistics of the United States (NCHS) and the World Health Organization (WHO) was carried out with Anthro and the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) with EpiInfo 6.04. Z score was calculated differentiated by sex. Kappa coefficient was estimated to assess the correlation between anthropometric categories and classified it with cutoff Altman DG. Results: the highest concordance was found between the NCHS reference and WHO (girls: 0,854; children: 0,899, p = 0,000), followed by the CDC versus the NCHS (girls: 0,787; children: 0,860, p = 0,000) and the CDC compared with WHO (girls: 0,754; children: 0,829, p = 0,000). Conclusions: according to the results could be used any of the three growth references for assessing the height for age in this population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benjumea Rincón, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Leyton, Mylene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Osorio, Aníbal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: en Colombia se han propuesto diversas referencias antropométricas para su uso en salud pública sin contar con un consenso sobre el ideal y han sido adoptadas sin estudios previos de validación. El objetivo de este estudio fue medir la concordancia en la clasificación de la talla para la edad entre tres referencias antropométricas para menores de 17 años asistentes al programa de nutrición de CONFAMILIARES, Caldas, Colombia. Métodos: estudio descriptivo de 31.961 menores de 17 años asistentes al programa de nutrición de CONFAMILIARES, Caldas, Colombia, entre 2006 y 2009. Las variables fueron la talla para la edad y el sexo. La clasificación antropométrica con las referencias del Centro Nacional de Estadísticas en Salud de Estados Unidos (NCHS) y de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) se llevó a cabo con Anthro y la del Centro para el Control de Enfermedades (CDC) con EpiInfo 6.04d. Se calculó el puntaje Z diferenciado por sexo. Se estimó el coeficiente kappa para evaluar la concordancia entre las categorías antropométricas y se clasificó ésta con los puntos de corte de Altman DG. Resultados: la concordancia más alta se encontró entre las referencias del NCHS y de la OMS (niñas: 0,854; niños: 0,899, p=0,000), seguida de las del NCHS frente al CDC (niñas: 0,787; niños: 0,860, p=0,000) y de la del CDC comparada con la OMS (niñas: 0,754; niños: 0,829, p=0,000). Conclusiones: de acuerdo con los resultados podría usarse cualquiera de las tres referencias para evaluar la talla en este grupo de edad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(4): 393-407, jul.-ago.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103659</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia en la talla para la edad entre diferentes referencias de crecimiento. Caldas, Colombia. 2006-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9932^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
