<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104932</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of congenital malaria by Plasmodium vivax: an incidental case within the context of neonatal sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital malaria is a disease relatively rare in the context of neonatal pathologies. We report the case of an infant of twenty days of life with malaria congenital whose a plasmodium vivax, the diagnosis was made incidentally while processing a laboratory sample in the context of neonatal sepsis. The patient was from non-endemic area but with no previously know maternal history of gestational malaria seven months, which was no treated by omission of the la patient. The nonspecific clinical manifestations were similar to those of neonatal sepsis and antimalarial treatment with chloroquine was carried out with adequate clinical response and confirmed by thick smear negative at the end of treatment. Hence it is considered very important to have more and more into account as differencial diagnosis in patient from risk areas besides the differential diagnosis of neonatal sepsis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, DP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flórez Díez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trujillo Honeysberg, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustamante Agudelo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia Libreros, DL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe Murillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe Macías, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La malaria congénita es una patología relativamente rara en el contexto de las patologías neonatales. Presentamos el caso de una lactante de 20 días de vida con malaria congénita por Plasmodium vivax cuyo diagnóstico fue realizado de forma incidental al analizar una muestra de laboratorio en el estudio de sepsis neonatal. La paciente era procedente de una zona no endémica de Colombia pero con antecedente materno de malaria gestacional diagnosticada al 7º mes, la cual no fue tratada por omisión de la paciente. Las manifestaciones clínicas fueron inespecíficas, similares a las de una sepsis neonatal y el tratamiento antimalárico fue realizado con cloroquina, con adecuada respuesta clínica, confirmada mediante negativización de gota gruesa al finalizar el tratamiento. Se considera de gran importancia tenerla malaria congénita cada vez más en cuenta como diagnóstico diferencial de la sepsis neonatal sobre todo en pacientes procedentes de zonas de riesgo o endémicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;52(219): 33-36, ene. -mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malaria congénita por Plasmodium vivax: un caso incidental en contexto de sepsis neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11398^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
