<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62770</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A assess the efficacy of mirtazapine in the treatment of depression with somatic symptoms in a3-months follow-up study. Material and methods. Design: multicenter, prospective, observational, open-label, and non controlled study. Sample: seven hundred and eleven patients recruited in outpatient psychiatric consultations by 98 psychiatrists nationwide. Instruments: 17-Item Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAMD-17) and Standardized Polyvalent Psychiatric Interview (SPPI), somatic symptoms section. Patients were assessed pretreatment and at 15, 30 and 90 days post-treatment. Results. Severity of depression assessed by HAMD-17significantly decreased (p&lt;0.0001) from 23.27 in the pretreatment assessment to 6.75 at 3 months post-treatment. Severity of somatic symptoms assessed by EPEP significantly decreased (p&lt;0.0001) from 7.68 in the pre-treatment assessment to 2.28 at 3 months post-treatment. Mirtazapine modifies attribution of somatic symptoms in somatizers: in pretreatment assessment, 41.3 % of the sample attributed somatic symptoms to a psychological origin, while at 3 months post-treatment this percentage significantly increased (p&lt;0.05) to 63.94%. Nearly half of the sample (48.52%) took benzodiazepines at the start of the study; but at 3 months post-treatment only 6.71% of the patients needed them. The incidence of adverse effects was 13.36% of the patients. From the total dropouts4% were due to adverse events. Conclusions. Mirtazapine is an effective and safe antidepressant for the treatment of depression with somatic symptoms and is able to modify attribution of somatic symptoms in somatizing patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Campayo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se evalúa la evolución clínica de la depresión con síntomas somáticos durante los primeros 3 meses de tratamiento con mirtazapina. Material y métodos. Diseño: estudio multicéntrico, prospectivo, observacional, abierto y no controlado. Muestra: 711 pacientes seleccionados por 98 psiquiatras de todo el territorio español que trabajaban en consultas externas de psiquiatría. Instrumentos: se utilizó la Escala de Depresión de Hamilton de 17 ítems (HAMD-17) y la Entrevista Psiquiátrica Estandarizada Polivalente (EPEP), sección síntomas somáticos. Los pacientes fueron evaluados pre tratamiento y a los 15, a los 30 y a los 90 días postratamiento. Resultados. La intensidad de la depresión medida con laHAMD-17 disminuye significativamente (p&lt;0,0001) desde23,27 pretratamiento hasta 6,75 a los 3 meses. La intensidad de la sintomatología somática medida con la EPEP disminuye significativamente (p &lt; 0,0001) desde 7,68 pretratamiento hasta 2,28 a los 3 meses. Mirtazapina modifica la atribución de los síntomas somáticos en somatizadores: en la visita basal el 41,37% de la muestra pensaba que la causa de los síntomas era psicológica, mientras que a los 3 meses el porcentaje se había incrementado significativamente (p&lt;0,05) a un63,94%. La mitad de la muestra (48,52%) tomaba benzodiacepinas al inicio del estudio; mientras que tras 90 días de tratamiento, sólo precisaron asociar benzodiazepinas un 6,71% de los pacientes. La incidencia de efectos adversos fue del 13,36% de los pacientes. Del total de los abandonos del estudio, solamente un 4% fueron debidos a acontecimientos adversos. Conclusiones. Mirtazapina es un antidepresivo eficaz y seguro para el tratamiento de los pacientes depresivos con síntomas somáticos asociados y es capaz de modificar la atribución de los síntomas en pacientes somatizadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;36(1): 25-32, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62770</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
