<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118413</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a functional plan for caregivers in hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND: The care of dependent persons has increased, as such that healthcare reforms are taking caregivers into account. A functional plan in hospitalization was developed for caregivers, and his study aims to investigate its implementation, identifying the strengths and weaknesses that promote changes between the formal and informal system. METHODS: A qualitative study was designed, using nursing professionals and caregivers identified in the hospital as subjects. A focus group technique was used with 8 people selected for each segment. Two scripts were developed with questions on the evaluation criteria included in the plan: identification/recruitment, reception, rest, diet, health care, information/health education, management and implementation of the plan and other proposals. The data were collected during May 2011.RESULTS: Difficulties were encountered in identifying caregivers, as an initial evaluation was not made. As regards the reception, in some cases the information brochure was not given. Rest was not possible as the caregivers did not want to move away from the patient. Diet was the main cause of the conflict, highlighting the lack of health education to continue in home care. Circuits of preferential care in emergency were positively valuated. Nurses consider the plan as an extra task. CONCLUSIONS: The strengths and weaknesses identified should enable improvements to be made in the implementation of the plan, in order to achieve changes in specific aspects such as information/education, health, rest and diet of the caregivers. We emphasize the need to enhance the model change (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quiñoz-Gallardo, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vellido-González, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Guerrero, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto-Poyato, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral-Rubio, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Berrido, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Campos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vellido-González, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El cuidado de personas dependientes se ha incrementado, por lo que las reformas del sistema sanitario están visibilizando a las personas cuidadoras. Se desarrolló un plan funcional para personas cuidadoras en hospitalización, y esta investigación pretende indagar cómo ha sido su implementación, identificando puntos fuertes y débiles que promuevan cambios entre el sistema formal e informal. Métodos Se diseñó un estudio cualitativo, considerando como sujetos de estudio a los profesionales de enfermería y personas cuidadoras identificadas en el Hospital. Se utilizó la técnica de grupo focal seleccionando 8 personas en cada segmento. Se elaboraron 2 guiones de preguntas con los criterios de evaluación recogidos en las líneas estratégicas del plan: identificación/captación, acogida, descanso, dieta, atención sanitaria, información/educación sanitaria, gestión e implementación y otras propuestas. Los datos se recogieron durante mayo de 2011.ResultadosSe encontraron dificultades en la identificación y captación de las personas cuidadoras, por no realizar su valoración inicial. En cuanto a la acogida, en algunos casos no se entregaba folleto informativo. El descanso no es posible por la renuncia a alejarse de su familiar. La dieta es la principal causa del conflicto y destaca la falta de educación sanitaria para continuar con los cuidados domiciliarios. Se valoran positivamente los circuitos de atención preferente en urgencias. Los profesionales de enfermería consideran que el desarrollo del plan supone una sobrecarga de trabajo. Conclusiones Los puntos fuertes y débiles identificados permitirán establecer mejoras en la implementación del plan para conseguir el cambio en aspectos específicos como la información/educación, atención, descanso y dieta de la persona cuidadora. Destacamos la necesidad de potenciar el cambio de modelo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);23(6): 262-270, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del plan funcional dirigido a personas cuidadoras en hospitalización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
