<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59420</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence-based medicine: Its concept and applicability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To introduce the concept of evidence-based medicine (EBM) and its applicability to clinical practice.Development. EBM is defined as &#145;the conscious, explicit and judicious use of the best available scientific evidence forclinical decision making&#146;. The medical act is understood as an experience of interpersonal relationship in which thephysician&#146;s values and experience, together with the patient&#146;s preferences, have an eminent role, to which the systematicevaluation of scientific evidence must be added as a crucial element. EBM considers the scientific method to be the besttool available today to learn about reality and express it in an intelligible and synthetic way. It helps develop a reasoningand a method which tries to transform the clinical data into scientifically valid, statistically precise and clinicallyrelevant knowledge for modern medical practice. It intends for physicians to learn how to adequately apply the resultsof scientific investigation, in addition to their experience and clinical abilities, in order to improve the quality of medicalpractice. The process consists of the identification of gaps in knowledge, the formulation of well-structured clinicalquestions, the systematic and efficient search of the available evidence, the critical evaluation of its quality, theinterpretation of the results and the application of the investigation findings to clinical decision making. Conclusions.EBM supplies a conceptual framework for the solution of clinical problems, bringing data of clinical investigationcloser to medical practice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Allegue-Allegue, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-de Céniga, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellmunt-Montoya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Espada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-Vázquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solanich-Valldaura, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Pardo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Introducir el concepto de medicina basada en la evidencia (MBE) y su aplicabilidad en la práctica clínica.Desarrollo. La MBE se define como &#145;el uso consciente, explícito y juicioso de la mejor evidencia científica disponiblepara tomar decisiones sobre los pacientes&#146;. El acto médico se entiende como una experiencia de relación interpersonal en laque los valores y la experiencia del médico, junto con las preferencias de los pacientes, tienen un papel preeminente, a lo quedebe añadirse como elemento crucial la evaluación sistemática de la evidencia científica. La MBE considera el método científicocomo la mejor herramienta de que se dispone hoy día para conocer la realidad y expresarla de forma inteligible y sintética.Ayuda a desarrollar un razonamiento y un método que persigue transformar los datos clínicos en conocimiento científicamenteválido, estadísticamente preciso y clínicamente relevante para la moderna práctica médica. Pretende que los médicosasistenciales, además de su experiencia y habilidades clínicas, sepan aplicar de manera adecuada los resultados de lainvestigación científica, a fin de mejorar la calidad de la práctica médica. El proceso consiste en la identificación de lagunasde conocimiento, la formulación de preguntas clínicas bien estructuradas, la búsqueda sistemática y eficiente de la evidenciade la que se dispone, la evaluación crítica de su calidad, la interpretación de los resultados y la aplicación de los hallazgosde la investigación a la toma de decisiones. Conclusiones. La MBE aporta un marco conceptual para la resolución de problemasclínicos, acercando los datos de la investigación clínica a la práctica médica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;61(1): 29-34, ene.-feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59420</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicina basada en la evidencia: concepto y aplicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
