<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056008</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bilateral renal lymphangiomatosis: conservative management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Lymphangiomatosis is a benign disease of difficult diagnosis. The bilateral form is very rare, being in some cases an incidental finding.    METHODS: We report the case of a female patient with the incidental radiological diagnosis of bilateral lymphangiomatosis,    who did not present symptoms in relation to the disease.    RESULTS: After a meticulous study with ultrasound, abdominal    CT scan and the MRI the diagnosis was asymptomatic bilateral lymphangiomatosis and expectant management was decided with good outcome.    CONCLUSIONS: Most cases reported have been treated by nephrectomy for diagnosis, but in our case it was possible to do precise diagnosis adding the experience of the radiologist    and the urologist and she had a good outcome with conservative management</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Albacete, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás Torralba, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojados Castejón, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tornero Ruiz, Jesús Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Bregante, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La linfangiomatosis es una enfermedad    benigna pero de difícil diagnóstico. La forma bilateral es muy rara, pudiendo tratarse en algún caso de un hallazgo casual.    MÉTODOS: Presentamos el caso de una paciente diagnosticada    radiológicamente de linfangiomatosis bilateral de forma casual pues no presentaba síntomas derivados esta patología.    RESULTADOS: Después de un estudio minucioso con ecografía,    TAC-abdominal y RNM y con el diagnóstico de linfangiomatosis bilateral asintomática, se decidió actitud expectante con buena evolución posterior.    CONCLUSIONES: La mayoría de casos descritos han recurrido    a la nefrectomía para su diagnóstico, pero como en nuestro caso, es posible un diagnóstico certero con la experiencia del radiólogo y urólogo y un manejo conservador    con buena evolución</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(7): 812-814, sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056008</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfangiomatosis renal bilateral: actitud conservadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
