<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166219</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Normal sinus rhythm. Recent anatomical and physiological insights into the sinus node. The If current</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sinus node is a highly specialized structure. It contains cells that generate repetitive spontaneous depolarizations at a variable frequency that determines the heart rate. The nodal cells, which are packed within a dense matrix of connective tissue, are arranged in interlacing strands that, at their periphery, intermingle with contractile atrial myocytes. The central region, which is responsible for impulse generation, is relatively uncoupled from the rest of the atrium, whereas the degree of coupling increases progressively in peripheral areas. The nodal cells exhibit a diastolic phase characterized by slow progressive depolarization that raises the resting potential to the excitability threshold, thereby generating a new action potential. Activation of the If current is responsible for this diastolic phase, and is also involved in heart rate modulation by the autonomic nervous system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cinca, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El nodo sinusal es una estructura altamente especializada, cuyas células generan despolarizaciones espontáneas repetidas a una frecuencia variable que determina la frecuencia cardiaca. Las células nodales se disponen sobre una matriz de tejido conectivo denso formando cordones entrelazados, que en la periferia se mezclan con los miocitos auriculares contráctiles. La zona central, encargada de generar los impulsos, se caracteriza por estar relativamente desacoplada del resto de la aurícula, mientras que la zona periférica presenta un grado de acoplamiento cada vez mayor. Las células nodales presentan una fase diastólica caracterizada por una despolarización lenta progresiva que transporta el potencial de reposo al umbral de excitabilidad y genera un nuevo potencial de acción. La activación de la corriente If genera esta fase diastólica y está implicada también en el control del ritmo cardiaco mediado por el sistema nervioso autónomo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.D): 26d-31d, 2007. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166219</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ritmo sinusal normal. Nuevos conceptos anatómicos y fisiológicos del nódulo sinusal. Corriente If</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13230^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
