<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70872</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The article sets off considering the Feminist Movement as something critical and plural; in ideas, reports, and claims as a result of the social conflict generated by women&#146;s subordination and inequality position. Some of its characteristics are described as a new subject configuration coming from women double process: individual and collective, or multidimensional character of their action, and its transformer character. In a second part the peculiar relationship between the Movement and society is raised, after considering some of the dilemmas, which faces. The constant redefinition of dialectic between public and private is analyzed from its action in social ground. Practical and theoretic implications of women tenseness between their individuality and gender belonging are expounded. And finally a feminist practice, which combines cultural identity elements with a social politics of justice and equality, protection measures together with politics, which promote autonomy and freedom for women, is defined</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero, Justa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo parte de la consideración del feminismo como un movimiento plural y crítico; de ideas, denuncia y reivindicación, producto del conflicto social que genera una posición de subordinación y desigualdad de las mujeres. Se describen algunos de sus características como la configuración de un nuevo sujeto a partir de un doble proceso: individual y colectivo de las mujeres, o el carácter multidimensional de su acción y su carácter transformador. En una segunda parte se plantean los peculiares relaciones del movimiento con la sociedad a partir de considerar algunos de los dilemas a los que se enfrenta. Se analiza la constante redefinición, a partir de su acción en el campo social, de la dialéctica entre lo privado y lo público. Se abordan las implicaciones teóricas y práctica de la tensión entre la individualidad de los mujeres y su pertenencia de género. Y por último se defiende una práctica feminista que combine elementos culturales de identidad con una política social de justicia e igualdad, medidas de protección junto con políticas que avancen en la autonomía y libertad de las mujeres</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;15(2): 167-180, mayo-ago. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70872</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33188</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
