<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114211</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profile of Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms in the Male and Their Impact on Quality of Life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Following current European Guidelines, Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms (LUTS) are produced by several causes and, thus, thorough clinical assessment should be undertaken for a correct therapeutic management. This study was conducted in order to assess the symptoms profile and their impact on Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQL) of male patients attending urology outpatient clinics.Material and methodsEpidemiological, cross-sectional study including adult male patients (n = 826) presenting with at least one de novo previously untreated LUTS. Socio-demographic and clinical variables were collected. Patients completed IPSS, Bladder Control Self-Assessment Questionnaire (B-SAQ) and SF-12 questionnaires.Results: Mean age (SD) was 65 (10) years. A combination of storage, voiding and post-micturition symptoms were present in 69% of subjects and 30% showed &amp;#8805; 2 urgency episodes and &amp;#8805;6 micturitions daily (storage symptoms &#150;SS&#151; sub-population). Storage symptoms were the reason for consultation in 86%. Mean peak urinary flow (Qmax) was 11.4 mL/s, in 44% of patients,prostate volume was 20-40 mL and 91% showed moderate or severe symptoms on IPSS with an overall mean (SD) score of 17 (7). SS sub-population had higher B-SAQ scores (6,9 vs 4,8 for symptoms; 7,8 vs 5,1 for bother), and worse HRQL (IPSS item 8).Conclusions: These findings support the importance of addressing treatment adequately according to patient profile, bothersomeness and impact on HRQL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Errando, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cambronero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La etiología multifactorial de los síntomas del tracto urinario inferior (STUI) justifica su evaluación detallada para un adecuado abordaje terapéutico según las guías europeas actuales. Para conocer el perfil sintomático e impacto en la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) de pacientes varones que acuden a consulta de urología se desarrolló el siguiente estudio. Material y métodos: Estudio epidemiológico, transversal en 826 varones adultos con &amp;#8805; 1 STUI de novo no tratados previamente. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas y clínicas. Los pacientes cumplimentaron la Puntuación internacional de síntomas prostáticos (IPSS), Cuestionario de autoevaluación del control vesical (CACV) y cuestionario SF-12. Resultados: La edad media (DE) fue de 65 (10) años. El 69% presentaba una combinación de síntomas de llenado, vaciado y posmiccionales. El 30% tenía &amp;#8805; 2 episodios de urgencia y &amp;#8805; 8 micciones al día (subpoblación con síntomas de llenado [SLL]). Los SLL fueron el motivo de consulta en el 86% de los casos. El flujo urinario máximo medio fue 11,4 ml/s y el 44% tenía volumen prostático entre 20-40 cc y el 91% síntomas moderados o graves (IPSS) con puntuación media (DE) de 17 (7). La subpoblación con SLL tenía puntuaciones mayores del CACV (síntomas 6,9 vs 4,8; molestias 7,8 vs 5,1). La subpoblación con SLL presentaba peor CVRS (IPSS ítem 8). Conclusiones: Estos hallazgos evidencian que es importante conocer el perfil de síntomas de cada paciente y el grado de molestia e impacto en la calidad de vida para orientar adecuadamente el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(7): 401-407, jul.-ago. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114211</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de síntomas del tracto urinario inferior en el varón y su impacto en la calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14951^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14951^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
