<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054892</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Item characteristics that predict response latency in personality measures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study assesses some item characteristics that are expected to affect response latencies in the computerized administration of a personality questionnaire. First, some previous empirical results are discussed, and a theoretical framework from which predictions can be made is proposed. Second, the predictions are empirically assessed using two data-sets, one of them based on binary items, and the other one based on graded-response items. Some of the results obtained are new, whereas the remaining agree with previous empirical results. The implicatons of the present results in applied research, and particularly for the use of latencies, is discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Demestre, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando, Pere J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evalúan algunas características de los ítems de personalidad que se espera afecten al tiempo de respuesta obtenido en una administración informatizada. En primer lugar, se discuten los resultados de estudios previos y se propone un marco teórico general desde el que establecer una serie de predicciones. En segundo lugar, estas predicciones se contrastan empíricamente utilizando dos conjuntos de datos, uno de ellos basado en ítems binarios y el otro en ítems de respuesta graduada. Algunos de los resultados obtenidos son nuevos, y el resto tiende a concordar con los resultados obtenidos en estudios previos. Se discuten las implicaciones de los resultados para la utilización de las latencias en estudios de tipo aplicado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);19(2): 337-342, mayo 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características del ítem que predicen el tiempo de respuesta en medidas de personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19269^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
