<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119134</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natural evolution of excess body weight (overweight and obesity) in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the chronological evolution of excess body weight (overweight and obesity)in order to raise public awareness within the different areas of intervention (family, school, business environment, health services) and to take effective actions. Material and methods: Weight, height and body mass index (BMI) of 604 healthy subjects (307males and 297 females) have been recorded at birth and at the age of 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and14 years. The excess body weight has been calculated according to national references from Ferrández et al. Results: Prevalence of excess body weight at age 14 years was significantly higher (P&lt;.05) in males (29%) than in females (12.8%). BMI (kg/m2) was significantly higher (P&lt;.05) for both sexes in every age period, except for birth and age 1 year, in those patients with excess body weight at age 14, with respect to patients with normal nutritional status of the same age. Those groups with excess body weight at age 14 showed a BMI (Z-score) reaching overweight or obesity levels at age 4, and progressively increasing. Conclusions: Excess body weight probably starts at early stages in life, when dietary habits of the child depends almost exclusively on family habits, and may be aggravated during school attendance. Finally, a disproportionate weight increase occurs in adolescence that is probably related to unhealthy dietary habits and way of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallinas Victoriano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la evolución cronológica del exceso de peso corporal (sobrepeso y obesidad) para sensibilizar a los diferentes ámbitos de intervención (familiar, escolar, empresarial y sanitario) a adoptar las medidas oportunas. Material y métodos: Se han registrado retrospectivamente pesos, tallas e índice de masa corporal (IMC) de 604 sujetos sanos (307 varones y 297 mujeres) al nacimiento y a las edades de 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 y 14 años. Se ha calculado el exceso de peso corporal con las referencias nacionales de Ferrández et al. Resultados: La prevalencia del exceso de peso corporal a los 14 años de edad era significativamente superior (p &lt; 0,05) en los varones (29%) respecto a las mujeres (12,8%). En ambos sexos, el IMC (kg/m2) era significativamente superior (p &lt; 0,05) en cada una de las edades consideradas, salvo al nacimiento y al año de edad, en los pacientes con exceso de peso corporal a los 14 años de edad respecto al grupo normonutrido a la misma edad. En los grupos que a los 14 años tenían exceso de peso corporal, el IMC (Z-score) ya alcanzaba rango de sobrepeso u obesidad a los 4 años de edad, que se iría incrementando progresivamente. Conclusiones: El exceso de peso corporal comenzaría en edades tempranas de la vida, cuando la dieta del niño depende casi exclusivamente de los hábitos familiares, que luego se agravaría con la escolarización y, por último, en la adolescencia tendría lugar un desproporcionado incremento ponderal probablemente relacionado con unos hábitos alimentarios y estilos de vida adquiridos poco saludables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(5): 300-306, nov. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución natural del exceso de peso corporal (sobrepeso y obesidad)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
