<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92692</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of lymphadenectomy on axillary recurrence and morbidity of the upper limb in breast cancer patients with negative sentinel node. A prospective randomised study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To determine the impact of axillary lymphadenectomy on regional recurrence, the overall and disease free survival, and upper limb morbidity in patients with breast cancer and negative sentinel node (SN). Patients and methods: A total of 176 patients with breast cancer and negative SN (pN0sn) were either randomised to lymphadenectomy (Group I) or to observation only (Group II). The triple technique was used to identify and remove the SN. Follow-up was carried out every 3 months for the first 3 years, and then every 6 months up to 5 years. Pain, numbness (paresthesia), limitations in shoulder mobility, and arm oedema were recorded. Results: No axillary lymph node recurrence was detected in the patients of Group II after 60months follow up. The overall and disease free survival was similar in both groups. The proportion of patients with morbidity and who had more than two complications was significantly higher in Group I. Conclusions: Axillary lymphadenectomy may be avoided in patients with negative SN without compromising lymph node extension studies and the patient treatment results. Axillary lymphadenectomy is associated with a higher morbidity of the upper limb compared to SN biopsy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reis, Paulo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fougo, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dias, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dinis-Ribeiro, Mário</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Hernâni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giesteira, Laurinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araújo, Cláudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Determinar el impacto de la linfadenectomía axilar sobre la recurrencia regional, la supervivencia global y libre de enfermedad y la morbilidad del miembro superior en pacientes con cáncer de mama y ganglio centinela (GC) negativo. Pacientes y métodos Ciento sesenta y seis pacientes con cáncer de mama y GC negativo (pN0sn) fueron aleatorizados a linfadenectomía (Grupo I) o solo observación (Grupo II). Se utilizó una técnica triple para identificar y extirpar el GC. El seguimiento se realizó cada 3 meses durante los 3 primeros años y, posteriormente, cada 6 meses, hasta los 5 años. Se registraron el dolor, entumecimiento (parestesias), la limitación de movilidad del hombro y el edema del brazo. Resultados Tras un seguimiento mínimo de 60 meses, no se detectó recurrencia ganglionar axilar en los pacientes del Grupo II. La supervivencia global y la libre de enfermedad fueron similares en ambos grupos. La proporción de pacientes con morbilidad y los que tuvieron más de dos complicaciones fue significativamente mayor en el Grupo I. Conclusiones Se puede evitar la linfadenectomía axilar en pacientes con GC negativo sin comprometer el estudio de extensión ganglionar o los resultados del tratamiento. La linfadenectomía axilar se asocia a una más elevada morbilidad de la extremidad superior en comparación a la biopsia del GC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(5): 307-316, mayo 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92692</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la linfadenectomía sobre la recurrencia axilar y la morbilidad del miembro superior en pacientes con cáncer de mama y ganglio centinela negativo. Estudio prospectivo aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32331^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
