<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93563</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive-behavioral therapy in the treatment of generalized anxiety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Generalized anxiety disorder is a common condition in the general population. It is a state of constant worry and anxiety about many events or activities. It usually appears at puberty or in adult hood, although it can occur since childhood. Objective: To review the effectiveness of cognitive-behavioral therapy in the treatment of generalized anxiety.Methodology: Review of clinical practice guidelines, systematic reviews and clinical trials have been conducted in the following international databases: Medline, National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC), Tripdatabase,New Zealand Guideline, EBM Guidelines, National Healthand Medical Research Council (Australia), National Institute for Healthand Clinical Excellence (NICE), CMA Infobase (Canada) and Cochrane Library Plus.Results and conclusions: The studies show that cognitive behavioral therapy is one of the most useful methods for the treatment of generalized anxiety due to its effectiveness in reducing symptoms. In primary care centers generalized anxiety is the most common mental problem, and it is therefore necessary to provide further knowledge and cognitive and behavioral skills to professionals working in these centers with the aim of reducing the prevalence of this mental disorder and there by, the economic and social burdens that it generates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, R. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desorden de ansiedad generalizada es una condición común en la población general. Se trata de un estado de preocupación y ansiedad constantes acerca de muchos acontecimientos o actividades. Suele manifestarse en la pubertad o en la edad adulta, aunque puede darse desde la infancia.Objetivo: revisar la eficacia de la terapia cognitivo-conductual en el tratamiento de la ansiedad generalizada. Metodología: la revisión de guías de práctica clínica, revisiones sistemáticas y ensayos clínicos se ha realizado en las siguientes bases de datos internacionales: Medline, National Guideline Clearinghouse (NGC), Tripdatabase,New Zealand Guideline, EBM Guidelines, National Health andMedical Research Council (Australia), National Insitute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE), CMA Infobase (Canadá) y Cochrane Library Plus. Resultados y conclusiones: los estudios muestran que la terapia cognitivo-conductual es uno de los métodos más útiles para el tratamiento de la ansiedad generalizada por su efectividad en la reducción de los síntomas.En los centros de Atención Primaria la ansiedad generalizada constituye el problema mental más frecuente, por lo que resulta necesario instruir en el conocimiento y desarrollo de habilidades cognitivas y conductuales a los profesionales de estos centros con la finalidad de disminuirla prevalencia de este trastorno mental y, con ello, las cargas económicas y sociales que genera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(10): 70-73, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La terapia cognitivo-conductual en el tratamiento de la ansiedad generalizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
