<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050294</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse effects and expected effects of the cannabis consumption in dependent users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The present study reviews the effects of the cannabinoids on health and the subjective effects reported by the consumers. Material and method. It is an extensive review of the literature published on this subject. Results. The cannabis consumption produces several physical effects: on a cardiovascular level it induces tachycardia and postural hypotension; on a respiratory level, it causes bronchodilatation and histopathological changes. It induces changes on the immunological system, on the levels of sexual hormones, through the hypothalamic-hypophyseal-adrenal axis, so as an impairment on the frontal brain information processing. Among the various subjective effects reported by consumers, the most expected ones are relaxation so as positive change in mood. The less expected effects are the physical adverse reactions, psychiatric symptoms, and working functioning impairment. Conclusions. The cannabis consumption produces adverse acute and chronic effects on the physical and mental health of the consumer. The expected effects reported by the consumers, themselves, makes an important emphasis on the mediating role of cognitive expectancies in the final effects really experiences by these consumers after the use of cannabinoids</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robert Segarra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Campo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de lps Cobos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero Pociello, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El presente estudio pretende revisar los efectos adversos sobre la salud de los cannabinoides y los efectos subjetivos autoinformados por los consumidores. Material y métodos. Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica de la literatura publicada sobre este tema. Resultados. El consumo de cannabis produce taquicardia e hipotensión postural a nivel cardiovascular. En el sistema respiratorio causa broncodilatación y alteraciones histopatológicas. Los cannabinoides, además, alteran el sistema inmunológico y las hormonas sexuales a través del eje hipotálamo-hipófiso-adrenal, y se relacionan con alteraciones frontales en el procesamiento de la información. En cuanto a los efectos informados por los consumidores, los más esperados son relajación y potenciación del humor. Los menos esperados son complicaciones físicas, síntomas psiquiátricos y deterioro sociolaboral. Conclusiones. El uso de cannabis supone efectos adversos agudos y crónicos sobre la salud física y mental del consumidor. Los efectos esperados informados por los propios consumidores ponen de relieve el papel de las expectativas de estos efectos en los patrones de consumo de cannabinoides</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;8(3): 148-154, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050294</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos esperados y adversos del consumo de cannabis en sujetos dependientes de los tetrahidrocannabinoides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14138^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3263^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
