<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143247</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors predicting survival of out-of-hospital cardiac arrest managed with semiautomatic external defibrillators in Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine prognostic factors in out-of-hospital cardiac arrests managed with semiautomatic external defibrillators (SAEDs) by emergency health service responders in Galicia, Spain. Method. Retrospective descriptive study of out-of-hospital cardiac arrests treated with SAEDs over a period of 5 years. We collected Utstein outcome data from the database and analyzed the following variables: sex, age, date and time of cardiac event, rural vs urban setting, type of location, witnessed or not, bystander resuscitation attempts or not, time first heart rhythm was detected, use of orotracheal intubation or not, time of call for help, and time to arrival of emergency responders. Results. We analyzed 2005 cases (0.14/1000 person-years; 68.2% male, 70.8% in rural locations, 61% at home). Return of spontaneous circulation (ROSC) was achieved in situ in 10.9% (in 29.9% of patients with shockable rhythms and in 3.3% of those in asystole). Intubation was necessary in 15.7%; ROSC was achieved in 24.8% of the intubated patients. ROSC was achieved in significantly more patients when responders arrived soon after the call for help (mean: 12 minutes, 26 seconds) than when arrival was delayed (mean: 16 minutes, 16 seconds when ROSC was not achieved; P &lt;001 ). The presence of a shockable rhythm was also significantly more frequent when response time was faster (P&lt;001 ). Asystole, on the other hand, reduced the likelihood of survival (P&lt; 005). Conclusion. Prognostic factors related to survival of SAED-managed out-of-hospital cardiac arrest in Galicia were the presence of a shockable rhythm, shorter response time, continuation of basic life support measures including advanced airway management, bystander life-support maneuvers, an urban location, and night timing of the arres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Santos, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias-Vázquez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto-Araujo, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-González, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa-Parcero, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Núñez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar los factores pronóstico de las paradas cardiacas extrahospitalarias (PCE) atendidas por el servicio de emergencias médicas (SEM) en Galicia en las que se utilizó un desfibrilador externo semiautomático (DESA).Método. Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de las PCE atendidas con DESA durante un periodo de 5 años, con recogida de datos según el estilo Utstein. Las variables analizadas fueron: sexo, edad, fecha y hora del suceso, asistencia en medio rural o urbano, localización, PCE presenciada, inicio maniobras por testigos, primer ritmo cardiaco monitorizado, intubación orotraqueal (IOT), y tiempos de alerta y asistenciales. Resultados. Se analizaron 2.005 casos (0,14/1.000 habitantes-año), 68,2% varones, 70,8% atendidos en medio rural y 61% con localización en el domicilio. Se logró la reanimación cardiaca extrahospitalaria (RCE) in situ en el 10,9% de los pacientes (29,9% en los casos encontrados en ritmos desfibrilables y 3,3% en aquellos en asistolia). Se realizó IOT en el15,7% de los casos, de los que lograron RCE el 24,8%. La disminución del tiempo medio entre la alerta y la asistencia (12:26 minutos en los que se logró la RCE y de 16:16 minutos en los fallecidos) resulta significativo para el aumento de la RCE (p &lt; 0,001), así como los ritmos desfibrilables (p = 0,001). Contrariamente los ritmos asistolia disminuyen las posibilidades de supervivencia (p &lt; 0,005).Conclusiones: La presencia de ritmos desfibrilables y los tiempos asistenciales breves son los factores significativamente relacionados con la supervivencia de la PCE atendida con DESA en Galicia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(5): 307-312, oct. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronóstico de supervivencia en la parada cardiaca extrahospitalaria atendida con desfibriladores externos semiautomáticos en Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53989^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
