<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106538</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To achieve effective hemostasis it is needed an adequate level of fibrinogen. Fibrinogen is the first factor in getting low levels in plasma in case of severe hemorrhage, and platelet aggregation is facilitated and when fibrinogen is activated by thrombin, fibrin polymers can be formed, which is the basis of clot formation. The dilution with intravenous fluids in severe bleeding affects coagulation factors facilitating the development of a coagulopathy. Plasma fibrinogen levels can predict perioperative bleeding. We can provide fibrinogen with fresh frozen plasma, cryoprecipitate and fibrinogen concentrate. Fibrinogen does not require compatibility testing for its administration and it can be administered quickly. European guidelines recommend administration of fibrinogen in patients with severe haemorrhage secondary to a bleeding trauma, whenever the thromboelastogram parameters show its deficit  and / or plasma fibrinogen levels are less than 2 g / L. Retrospective reviews of trauma with bleeding suggest that administration of fibrinogen with / without prothrombin complex and reposition guided by thromboelastography, reduces transfusion rate. Fresh frozen plasma contains about 2 g / l of fibrinogen, so it requires a large volume of plasma to increase plasmatic levels significatively. The cryoprecipitate is a plasma derived product, which contains a high fibrinogen concentration. The usual dose administered is from 2-4 g. Fibrinogen is a safe drug (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guasch Arévalo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schiraldi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brogly, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para lograr una hemostasia eficaz son necesarios niveles adecuados de fibrinógeno. El fibrinógeno es el primer factor del plasma en deplecionarse  en la hemorragia, facilita la agregación plaquetaria y cuando se activa mediante la trombina, forma polímeros de fibrina, que son la base de la formación del coágulo. La fluidoterapia en la hemorragia grave diluye los factores de la coagulación facilitando la aparición de una coagulopatía. Los valores de fibrinógeno plasmático predicen la hemorragia perioperatoria. Podemos aportar fibrinógeno mediante plasma fresco congelado, crioprecipitados y concentrado de fibrinógeno. El fibrinógeno no requiere pruebas de compatibilidad para su administración y se administra con rapidez. Las guías europeas de hemorragia recomiendan la administración de fibrinógeno en los traumatismos con hemorragia grave, siempre que el tromboelastograma muestre déficit del mismo y/o los niveles plasmáticos de fibrinógeno sean inferiores a 2 g/l. Revisiones retrospectivas de traumatismos con hemorragia sugieren que la administración de fibrinógeno con/sin complejo protombínico y  guiadas por el tromboelastograma, reduce la tasa transfusional. El plasma fresco congelado contiene aproximadamente 2 g/l de fibrinógeno, por lo que se requiere un volumen importante de plasma. El crioprecipitado es un producto derivado del plasma, que contiene unas concentraciones de fibrinógeno más elevadas. La dosis más habitual administrada es de 2-4 g. El fibrinógeno es un fármaco seguro(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;22(3): 5-10[3], jul.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentrado de fibrinógeno. Su uso en la práctica clínica anestesiológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1805^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23108^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23521^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
