<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152236</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Delphi The burnout syndrome in athletes: pilot study on the perception of sports psychologist through the Delphi method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of the current research is to conduct a preliminary study concerning perception of sport psychologists, regarding to burnout syndrome which athletes often experience. For this study, Delphi methodology has been utilized and data has been collected from a sample of 23 experts in Sport Psychology with extensive experience in psychological training with athletes. Three semi-structured Delphi questionnaires were sent consecutively by email that focused on burnout in athletes. The experts were asked about various aspects such as the definition and symptoms of burnout, physiological consequences, the stress-burnout relationship, and strategies or psychological intervention techniques. The second and third questionnaires were based on the analysis of the information extracted from the first one. Results show that the huge majority of experts believe that stress symptoms are linked with the loss of control of life -factors which are directly associated to burnout. 100% of the experts also believe that the self-concept of sports and leisure activities are variables that can affect burnout. According to the experts, the physiological consequences of burnout in athletes are tension, fatigue and irritability, emotions which do not fit well with the sport, difficulty in experiencing positive emotions like hope, positive expectations, energy, etc., a tendency where enthusiasm disappears in sports. With reference to the experts, psychological intervention strategies of choice includes: emotional control, improved self-esteem and self-concept, goal setting, intervention focused on needs, social support, organization and time management, cognitive restructuring, stress management, problem solving, and facilitation of satisfactory alternative activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Francisco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Jarillo, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés de Los Fayos, Enrique J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal de este trabajo es realizar un estudio preliminar sobre la percepción que tienen los psicólogos del deporte del síndrome de burnout en deportistas. Para ello, se ha llevado a cabo un estudio utilizando la técnica Delphi en una muestra de 23 expertos en Psicología del Deporte con amplia experiencia en entrenamiento psicológico con deportistas. Se les envió de forma sucesiva tres cuestionarios semiestructurados por correo electrónico sobre el burnout en deportistas, en los que se les preguntaba por diversos aspectos del síndrome como síntomas, consecuencias, relación estrés-burnout, y estrategias o técnicas de intervención psicológicas, elaborándose el segundo y el tercer cuestionario a partir del análisis de la información de las respuestas dadas en los anteriores. Los resultados muestran que la gran mayoría de los expertos plantea el estrés junto con la pérdida de control en la vida del deportista como factores directamente relacionados con el síndrome de burnout, y el 100% considera que el autoconcepto deportivo y extradeportivo es una variable que incide en el burnout. Las consecuencias fisiológicas del burnout en deportistas referidas por los expertos son tensión, fatiga e irritabilidad no acordes con el momento deportivo, dificultad para experimentar emociones positivas como ilusión, expectativas positivas, energía, etc., y tendencia a que desapareciese el entusiasmo en el deporte. Las estrategias de intervención psicológica de elección referidas por los expertos incluyen control emocional, mejora de la autoestima y autoconcepto, establecimiento de objetivos, intervención centrada en necesidades, apoyo social, organización y gestión del tiempo, reestructuración cognitiva, control del estrés, resolución de problemas, y facilitación de actividades alternativas satisfactorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 243-250, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El síndrome de burnout en deportistas: estudio piloto sobre la percepción del psicólogo deportivo a través del método</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56106^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
