<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95000</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-2885</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Percutaneous coronary intervention began to be realized in the middle of the 80s as an alternative to aortocoronary surgery in patients with ischemic cardiopathy. At the end of the 90s, more than 1 million of percutaneous procedures had been carried out around the world. As time passes by, it is more frequent to treat patients carrying coronary stents and in double antiaggregation agent therapy to urologic surgery. In these cases we face the dilemma to stop the antiplatelet agent therapy previous to the surgery to avoid the bleeding risk or, to maintain the treatment to avoid the risk of cardiovascular complications by thrombosis in the post-operatory period. Aspirin must be maintained whenever it is possible and we should delay the elective surgery until the security time is spent form implants greater than 6 weeks in conventional stents and greater than a year in farmacoactive stents. When valuing risk-be-nefit form the antiaggregation therapy, we believe pertinent to individualize each case, taking these recommendations as a guide, in order to reduce to the mobility and mortality in the perioperatory period and in long term by thrombosis in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Nieto, A. E. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intervención coronaria percutánea (ICP) comenzó a realizarse a mediados de los años 80 como alternativa a la cirugía de derivación aortocoronaria en pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica. A finales de los años 90 ya se habían llevado a cabo a nivel mundial más de un millón de procedimientos percutáneos. Cada vez es más frecuente que se someta a pacientes portadores de stents coronarios y en tratamiento antiagregante a cirugía urológica. En estos casos nos enfrentamos al dilema de suspender los antiagregantes previamente a la cirugía para evitar el riesgo de sangrado o bien, mantener el tratamiento para evitar el riesgo de complicaciones cardiovasculares por trombosis en el postoperatorio. Se debe mantener la aspirina siempre que sea posible y demorar la cirugía si es electiva hasta pasado el tiempo de seguridad desde el implante que es mayor de 6 semanas en los stent convencionales y mayor a un año en los stent farmacoactivos. Al valorar el riesgo-beneficio de la antiagregación, creemos pertinente individualizar cada caso, tomando estas recomendaciones como guía, a fin de reducir la morbimortalidad perioperatoria y a largo plazo por trombosis del stent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Fund. Puigvert;28(2): 65-75, abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95000</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antiagregación perioperatoria en pacientes portadores de stent coronario convencional y farmacoactivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
