<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69715</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: In general, articles on diagnostic tests have a very poor methodological quality. If we translate their conclusions to daily practice without a proper analysis it is easy to see a typical trend: physicians use new (and expensive) tests without increasing diagnostic capacity; they only increase the health budget. Evidence-based medicine (EBM) consists of using the best evidence in decision-making. It deals with selected and relevant information, supported by data obtained through the most rigorous scientific method: epidemiology and statistics. Critical evaluation of papers related to diagnostic tests is our aim. We provide with basic skills for evaluation and analysis of papers by means of simple topics on statistics, design of clinical assays and clinical epidemiology. Methods: Review of the medical literature. Results: To evaluate papers on diagnostic tests and to use a test correctly, it is necessary to know its diagnostic capacity, the level of certainty to start treatment, the probability of having the disease before using the test and the test capacity to change that probability. Conclusions: The maximum performance of a testis reached when it is used in a maximum uncertainty situation (disease probability 50%). Its highest usefulness is obtained when pre-test probability is maximal, after a careful review of the patient&#146;s history and a complete patient examination (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arruga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mascaró, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En general, los artículos sobre diagnóstico suelen adolecer de una calidad metodológica muy pobre. Si trasladamos sus conclusiones a nuestra práctica cotidiana sin un análisis detenido entenderemos fácilmente un fenómeno creciente: incorporamos acríticamente a nuestras estrategias diagnósticas las novísimas (y carísimas) pruebas sin que con ello aumente significativamente el rendimiento diagnóstico de tales estrategias; sólo se incrementades orbitadamente el gasto. La Medicina Basada en Evidencias es el uso de la mejor evidencia disponible en la toma de decisiones. Se trata de actuar utilizando información seleccionada y avalada por datos obtenidos a través del método científico más riguroso: la epidemiología y la estadística. La evaluación crítica de artículos relacionados con pruebas diagnósticas constituirá nuestro objetivo. Suministraremos las habilidades básicas para la evaluación y análisis de artículos científicos mediante el uso de una serie de conocimientos sencillos de estadística, diseño de investigaciones y epidemiología clínica. Método: Revisión de la literatura. Resultados: Para evaluar artículos sobre pruebas diagnósticas y para utilizar eficientemente una prueba diagnóstica necesitamos conocer su capacidad diagnóstica, el nivel de certeza que queremos tener para llevar a cabo una actitud terapéutica, la probabilidad de que el paciente tenga la enfermedad antes de utilizar la prueba y la capacidad que dicha prueba tiene de modificar tal probabilidad. Conclusiones: El rendimiento máximo de una prueba se obtiene cuando nos encontramos en una situación de máxima incertidumbre (probabilidad de enfermedad del 50%). Su mayor utilidad se obtiene cuando aumentamos al máximo la probabilidad preprueba, tras una minuciosa anamnesis y exploración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;83(11): 639-652, nov. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69715</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28635</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28605</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24768</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
