<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113974</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Angular tests for estimating hamstring flexibility: description of their measurement method and reference values</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment tests based on angular measurements are widely used to estimate and monitor hamstring muscle flexibility in both clinic and scientific settings. Several angular assessment tests have been described in the scientific literature, among which stand out: a) the straight leg raise test; b) the knee extension test; and c) the assessment tests that study the hip position and the caudal portion of lumbar spine at maximal trunk flexion position, distinguishing between "vertical hip joint angle" and "horizontal hip joint angle". Several limitations have been reported regarding the precision of these tests to estimate hamstring flexibility, such as: the influence of pelvis and spine movements, the position of the ankle joint (neutral position vs. dorsi-flexion), the use of different cut off values, the magnitude of the strength and speed used to carry on the tests, the warm-up design and the variability of the measurement tools used. This variability in the assessment methodologies might affect the final decision of choosing one or another assessment test by scientists, clinicians, and sport practitioners. Therefore, the main purposes of the current literature review are: to describe the assessments methodology of the most common angular tests used in clinic and scientific settings, as well as to report the cut-off values, which could be used for practitioners in order to categorize the hamstring flexibility as normal or limited(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sainz de Baranda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cejudo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santonja, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las pruebas de valoración basadas en medidas angulares son empleadas frecuentemente en el ámbito clínico y científico para estimar y monitorizar la flexibilidad de la musculatura isquiosural. Son varias las pruebas angulares descritas en la literatura científica, entre las que se destacan: a) la prueba de elevación de la pierna recta; b) la prueba del ángulo poplíteo; y c) las pruebas que estudian la disposición de la pelvis y la porción caudal del raquis lumbar en posición de máxima flexión de tronco, diferenciando entre "pruebas lumbo-vertical en flexión" y "pruebas lumbo-horizontal en flexión". Se han descrito limitaciones e inconvenientes para todos los protocolos, fundamentalmente en cuanto a la posible participación de pelvis y raquis, posición de la articulación del tobillo (en flexión dorsal o posición neutra), diferentes límites de normalidad en las exploraciones, aplicación de distinta velocidad y fuerza en la realización de los tests, existencia o no de calentamiento previo y variabilidad de los instrumentos empleados. Esta especificidad metodológica puede repercutir en la decisión final de elección de una u otra prueba por parte de científicos, clínicos y demás profesionales del ámbito de las Ciencias del Deporte. Por ello, los objetivos principales de esta revisión bibliográfica son: describir la metodología de valoración de las pruebas angulares más empleadas en el ámbito clínico y científico; así como aportar valores de referencia que puedan ser utilizados por los profesionales para categorizar la flexibilidad isquiosural como normal o acortamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;6(3): 120-128, sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pruebas angulares de estimación de la flexibilidad isquiosural: descripción de los procedimientos exploratorios y valores de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10733^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9261^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
