<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119762</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Looking for a tool for early detection of cognitive impairment in multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Cognitive impairment is highly prevalent in multiple sclerosis (MS). But detection remains difficult and late. Neuropsychological tests remain being the best screening tools used. Recently, it has been suggested that objective and quantifiable variables, such as cognitive evoked potentials (P300) and optical coherence tomography (OCT), may be useful in cognitive assessment. Objectives: to conduct a comparative study between Paced Auditory Serial- Addition -Test (PASAT) and Faces- Symbol- Test (FST) and then apply OCT and P300, and assess the degree of agreement between these tests and neuropsychological tests. Methods: MS patients were selected, belonging to the Neurology Xeral Hospital of Vigo, who met the study inclusion criteria The FST and PASAT were applied and the time taken to complete them was recorded. One Subjective Rating Scale was given to patients to  asses both tests. Finally, the study was completed with the applicationof OCT and P300. Results: 25 patients were included in the study. The statistical analysis observed a high degree of concordance between the PASAT and FST in terms of diagnostic capability. However PASAT required more time to be completed and was considered an uncomfortable  test. In turn, an acceptable level of agreement between the FST, the OCT and the P300 was observed. The PASAT showed no such correlation. Conclusions: FST provides results that overlap those of PASAT regarding detection of cognitive impairment in MS patients. Turn, has a high degree of concordance with objective markers such as OCT and  P300 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Midaglia, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dieguez Varela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el deterioro cognitivo tiene una elevada prevalencia en Esclerosis Múltiple (EM). Sin embargo su detección continúa siendo difícil y tardía. Los tests neuropsicológicos continúan siendo las herramientas de screening más utilizadas. Recientemente, se ha sugerido, que variables objetivas y cuantificables, como potenciales evocados cognitivos (onda P300) y la tomografía de coherencia óptica (OCT), podrían ser útiles en la evaluación cognitiva. Objetivos: realizar un estudio comparativo entre Paced-Auditory-Serial-Addition-Test (PASAT) y Faces-Symbol-Test (FST); posteriormente aplicar OCT y P300  y valorar el grado de concordancia existente entre estas pruebas y los tests neuropsicológicos. Material y métodos: se seleccionaron pacientes con EM, pertenecientes a la consulta de Neurología del Hospital Xeral de Vigo, que cumplieran con los criterios de inclusión del estudio. Se aplicaron el FST y PASAT, registrándose el tiempo empleado para su realización. Se entregó una Escala Subjetiva de Valoración de ambos tests. Finalmente, se completó el estudio con la aplicación de OCT y P300. Resultados: se incluyeron 25 pacientes. El análisis estadísitico observó un alto grado de concordancia entre el PASAT y el FST en cuanto a capacidad diagnóstica. Sin embargo el PASAT precisó más tiempo para su realización y fue considerado un test incómodo. A su  vez se objetivó un grado aceptable de concordancia entre el FST, la OCT y la P300. El PASAT no demostró dicha correlación. Conclusiones: el FST ofrece resultados superponibles a los del PASAT en cuanto a la detección del deterioro cognitivo en pacientes con EM. A su vez, presenta un elevado grado de concordancia con marcadores objetivos como la OCT y la onda P300 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;4(1): 3-7, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Buscando una herramienta para la detección precoz de deterioro cognitivo en esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32754</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5168</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
