<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051254</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ATYPICAL ATTENTION An alternative to pharmacological treatment of expectation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Since functional neuroimaging techniques highlight the role of attention in the pathophysiology of mental disorders, it seems appropriate to look for new alternatives to pharmacological treatments that can influence the neural substrates of attention. Objetives: To enhance our knowledge of how attention can be perceived as an organ system and to demonstrate how suggestion can focally modify it. Discussion: Hypnosis or atypical attention is a form of attentive-receptive concentration that, together with the proper instruction, can help a subject modify the functional activation pattern of such brain areas as the anterior cingular cortex and prefrontal cortex activation and to suppress an involuntary process such as the word reading. Hypnotherapy has been used successfully in the regulation of pain, tics, conversion disorders, and anxiety. Hypnotic susceptibility can be measured using standardized scales with excellent psychometric functions. It peaks in puberty, which makes it attractive for treating adolescents. ConcIusions: Attention is centrally involved in the pathophysiology of certain mental disorders. Hypnosis can influence the neural substrate of attention. Susceptibility to hypnosis peaks in puberty. Hypnotherapy may constitute a viable alternative to pharmacological treatments in Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Iñiguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las técnicas de neuroimagen funcional destacan el papel de la atención en la fisiopatología de algunos trastornos mentales, por lo que parece adecuado buscar nuevas alternativas al tratamiento farmacológico que puedan influir funcionalmente sobre los sustratos neurológicos de la atención. Objetivos: Reforzar nuestro conocimiento acerca de la atención, percibida funcionalmente como un sistema, y demostrar cómo la sugestión puede modificada focalmente. Desarrollo: La hipnosis o atención atípica es una forma de concentración atento-receptiva que, adecuadamente instruida, puede ayudar al sujeto a modificar el patrón de activación funcional de áreas cerebrales como las cortezas cingular anterior y prefrontal, y suprimir procesos automáticos como la lectura. La hipnoterapia ha sido empleada con éxito en la regulación del dolor, tics, trastornos conversivos y ansiedad. La susceptibilidad a la hipnosis puede medirse mediante escalas validadas con excelentes propiedades psicométricas y es mayor durante la pubertad, lo que resulta atractivo para el tratamiento de adolescentes. Conclusiones: La atención está centralmente implicada en la fisiopatología de algunos trastornos mentales. La hipnosis puede influir en el sustrato neurológico de la atención. La susceptibilidad a la hipnosis presenta un pico en la pubertad. La hipnoterapia puede constituir una alternativa terapéutica viable en Psiquiatría Infanto-juvenil</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;22(3): 64-73, jul.-sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">ATENCIÓN ATÍPICA. Una alternativa al tratamiento farmacológico de expectación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7167</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13790</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
