<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100325</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current research in specific language impairments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the publications appearing in the last year in the new ProQuest platform on specific language impairment (SLI). There were 87 articles, which were classified into the following sections: basic research, screening / assessment and treatment. Research in 2011 was mostly basic and little was published in the areas of assessment and treatment. Some sub-categories of basic research (cognitive-psycholinguistic, linguistic, behavioral, educational, psychobiology / neuropsychology and comparative disorders) have been established. Some of the publications found are briefly discussed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se lleva a cabo una revisión de las publicaciones aparecidas en el último año en la nueva plataforma ProQuest sobre el Trastorno Específico del Lenguaje (TEL). Se han encontrado un total de 87 artículos, y se han categorizado en los siguientes apartados: investigación básica, screening/evaluación y tratamiento. La investigación durante el año 2011ha sido mayoritariamente básica y bastante reducida en las áreas de evaluación y tratamiento. Se establecen subcategorías de investigación básica (cognitiva-psicolingüística, lingüística, conductual, educativa, psicobiología/neuropsicología y comparativa de trastornos). Se comentan brevemente algunas de las publicaciones encontradas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);32(2): 75-86, abr.-jun.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100325</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La investigación actual en el Trastorno Específico del Lenguaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
