<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101801</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemicrania continua: characteristics and therapeutic experience in a series of 36 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hemicrania continua is characterised by a continuous unilateral pain, which frequently gets worse in association with autonomic symptoms. It is probably little known and underdiagnosed. Its diagnosis requires a responseto indomethacin, which is not always well tolerated. Aims. We report a series of 36 cases of hemicrania continua that were treated in the headache service of a tertiary hospital. We analyse their demographic and clinical features and the therapeutic alternatives to indomethacin. Patients and methods. Between January 2008 and April 2012, 36 patients (28 females, eight males) were diagnosed with hemicrania continua from among 1800 (2%) who were treated in that service Results. The age of onset was 46.3 ± 18.4 years. In four patients (11.1%) there were pain remissions that lasted overthree months. The baseline pain was chiefly oppressive or burning with an intensity of 5.2 ± 1.4 on the verbal analogue scale. Exacerbations lasted 32.3 ± 26.1 minutes, were of a predominantly stabbing nature with an intensity of 8.3 ± 1.4, and in 69.4% of cases were accompanied by autonomic symptoms. Altogether 16.7% of the patients did not tolerate indomethacin beyond an indotest and 50% did so with side effects. In 13 cases at least one anaesthetic blockade was performed in the supraorbital or the greater occipital nerve or a trochlear injection of corticoids was carried out with a fullresponse in 53.8% and a partial response in 38.5%. Conclusions. Hemicrania continua is not an infrequent diagnosis in a headache clinic and, because it is a treatablecondition, further knowledge on the subject is needed. Anaesthetic blockades of the supraorbital or greater occipital nerves or a trochlear injection of corticoids are the therapeutic options that must be taken into consideration whenindomethacin is not well tolerated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortijo, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Carolina de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Peral, Ángel L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Martínez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulero, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco LLorente, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Velázquez, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Blanco, Dulce M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barón, Johanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedraza, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hemicránea continua se caracteriza por un dolor unilateral, continuo, con exacerbaciones frecuentementeasociadas a síntomas autonómicos. Es probablemente poco conocida e infradiagnosticada. Su diagnóstico requiere respuesta a la indometacina, no siempre bien tolerada. Objetivo. Se presenta una serie de 36 casos de hemicránea continua atendidos en la consulta de cefaleas de un hospitalterciario. Analizamos sus características demográficas y clínicas y las alternativas terapéuticas a la indometacina.Pacientes y métodos. Entre enero de 2008 y abril de 2012, 36 pacientes (28 mujeres, ocho varones) fueron diagnosticadosde hemicránea continua entre 1.800 (2%) atendidos en dicha consulta.Resultados. La edad al inicio fue de 46,3 ± 18,4 años. En cuatro pacientes (11,1%) existían remisiones del dolor superioresa tres meses. El dolor basal era principalmente opresivo o quemante, y su intensidad era de 5,2 ± 1,4 en la escala analógicaverbal. Las exacerbaciones tenían una duración de 32,3 ± 26,1 minutos, carácter  predominantemente punzante,intensidad de 8,3 ± 1,4, y en el 69,4% de casos se acompañaban de síntomas autonómicos. El 16,7% de los pacientes no toleró la indometacina más allá de un indotest, y un 50% lo hizo con efectos adversos. En 13 casos se llevó a cabo al menos un bloqueo anestésico en el nervio supraorbitario o el occipital mayor, o una inyección de corticoides en la tróclea con respuesta completa en el 53,8% y parcial en el 38,5%.Conclusiones. La hemicránea continua no es un diagnóstico infrecuente en una consulta de cefaleas, y es necesario aumentarsu conocimiento al tratarse de una entidad tratable. Los bloqueos anestésicos del nervio supraorbotario o del occipital mayor o la inyección de corticoides en la tróclea son una opción terapéutica que se debe considerar cuando la indometacina no se tolera bien (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(5): 270-278, sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemicránea continua: características y experiencia terapéutica en una serie de 36 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28146^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
