<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056460</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs): Clinical aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) are the        most common mesenchymal tumors in the gastrointestinal tract.        One of their features is the expression of the c-KIT / CD117 receptor.        Aims and methods: we will focus on describing the symptoms,        clinical studies prior to diagnosis, histologic and immunohistochemical        characteristics, as well as the progression of disease in        a group of patients.        Results: seventeen cases were diagnosed between December        1999 and April 2005. Mean age of patients was 64.5 (± 11.9);        47% were women. Tumor location was as follows: 52.9% in the        jejunum or ileum, 29.4% were gastric, 11.7% were in the duodenum,        and 5.8% were located in the mesentery. Tumor size was        6.0 cm on average (± 5.0); 47% were asymptomatic, and to a        lesser degree caused abdominal pain or digestive bleeding; 94.1%        of tumors expressed CD117. Most of them were discovered while        performing a laparotomy or ultrasound scan; 94.1% of tumors        were removed; 35.2% (6 out of 17) of patients suffering from        GIST met consensus criteria for aggressive behavior. Over 25.6        months (± 22.5) metastasis or tumor relapse occurred in 23.5%        (4 out of 17) of patients &#150; those with more frequent high-risk criteria,        symptomatic and bigger tumors, and tumors not expressing        CD117. The three patients with tumor relapse were prescribed        imatinib mesylate. Three patients died because of the tumor, and        four from other causes unrelated to GIST.        Conclusions: GIST was diagnosed in around 12 cases per million        a year. Its diagnosis was usually an incidental finding during a        medical evaluation, and tumors were malignant in nearly one fourth        of cases. We can predict its outcome depending on different aspects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aller de la Fuente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velayos Jiménez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Rubiales, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Salazar, L. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Gago, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Hernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los tumores GIST son los tumores mesenquimales        más frecuentes del tubo digestivo. Se caracterizan por la expresión        del receptor c-KIT/CD 117.        Objetivos y métodos: pretendemos describir las manifestaciones        clínicas, las exploraciones que llevan al diagnóstico, los aspectos        histológicos e inmunohistoquímicos, la evolución y factores        predictores de esta a partir de una serie de pacientes.        Resultados: se han diagnosticado 17 casos de GIST entre diciembre        de 1999 y abril de 2005. La edad media de los pacientes        fue 64,5 años (± 11,9). El 47% eran mujeres. La localización de los        tumores por paciente fue: yeyuno-íleon en el 52,9%, gástrica en el        29,4%, duodenal en el 11,7% y mesentérica en el 5,8%. Los tumores        medían 6,0 cm (± 5,0). El 47% eran tumores asintomáticos, menos        frecuentemente produjeron dolor abdominal o hemorragia digestiva.        El 94,1% de los tumores expresaba CD 117. Se        diagnosticaron principalmente durante una laparotomía o con ecografía.        Se extirparon el 94,1% de los tumores. En el 35,2% (6/17)        de los pacientes había criterios de alto riesgo de malignidad según el        consenso establecido. A lo largo de 25,6 meses (± 22,5) las metástasis        o la recidiva tumoral se dieron en el 23,5% (4/17) de los pacientes        y en estos fueron más frecuentes: los criterios de alto riesgo, los        tumores sintomáticos, los de mayor tamaño y los que no expresan        CD 117. Los tres pacientes con recidiva recibieron imatinib mesilato.        Tres pacientes fallecieron por causa del tumor. Otros 4 pacientes        fallecieron por otras causas no relacionadas con el GIST.        Conclusiones: se diagnosticaron aproximadamente 12 casos        por millón de habitantes y año. Su diagnóstico con frecuencia es        casual. Son malignos en cerca de la cuarta parte de los casos.        Existe la posibilidad de predecir la evolución en función de diferentes        aspectos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(1): 19-24, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056460</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores de la estroma gastrointestinal (GIST): aspectos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30496^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32639^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8820^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8814^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
