<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040862</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results and complications of expanded polytetrafluoroetylene in frontalis suspension ptosis surgery. Study of 59 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To evaluate the functional results and complications of the use of expanded polytetrafluoroethylene (ePTFE) in frontalis suspension surgery for the treatment of moderate-severe palpebral ptosis (&gt;3 mm) with poor or absent levator muscle function.                Methods: Retrospective study of 59 frontalis suspension procedures performed between 1992 and 2003 on 38 patients with palpebral ptosis (21 bilateral). Seventeen (44.7%) cases were women and 21 (55.3%) men. The mean age was 51.7 S.D. 27.6 years (range, 2 to 87). The surgical techniques used were performed by a Wright fascia needle. The etiology, ptosis grade, levator function, Bell&#146;s phenomenon and frontalis compensation were studied.                Results: After a median follow-up time of 35.9 S.D. 18.5 months (range, 6 to 72), we observed that the functional results were good in 55 cases (93.2%). Infection with preseptal celulitis appeared in 1 case (1.7%) and required removal of the material, and in 2 cases (3.4%) there were foreign body granulomas that were resolved by excision. Two cases (3.4%) had to be reoperated due to recurrence.                Conclusions: The ePTFE, in our experience, is a good material with excellent functional results and relatively few complications in the surgical treatment of eyelid ptosis for frontalis suspension. Other synthetic materials or fascia lata may be used, but all carry the risk of potential infection, extrusion, granuloma formation or recurrence</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mencía-Gutiérrez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo-Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monsalve-Córdova, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clariana-Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar los resultados funcionales y complicaciones del uso de politetrafluoroetileno expandido (PTFEe) en la técnica de suspensión al frontal para el tratamiento quirúrgico de la ptosis palpebral moderada-severa (&gt;3 mm) con mala o nula función del músculo elevador.Material y Método: Estudio retrospectivo de 59 suspensiones al frontal realizadas entre los años 1992 y 2003, en 38 pacientes con ptosis palpebral (21 bilaterales). Diecisiete (44,7%) fueron mujeres y 21 (55,3%) hombres. La edad media fue de 51,7 D.E. 27,6 años (rango, 2 a 87 años). Las técnicas quirúrgicas empleadas se realizaron mediante una aguja de fascia de Wright. Se estudia además la etiología, el grado de ptosis, la función del músculo elevador, el reflejo de Bell y la compensación frontal.Resultados: Tras un período de seguimiento medio de 35,9 D.E. 18,5 meses (rango, 6 a 72) pudimos observar que los resultados funcionales fueron buenos en 55 casos (93,2%). Infección con celulitis preseptal apareció en 1 caso (1,7%) que requirió la retirada del material, y en 2 casos (3,4%) se presentaron granulomas a cuerpo extraño que se solucionaron con su escisión. Se reintervinieron 2 casos (3,4%) por recurrencia.Conclusiones: El PTFEe, según nuestra experiencia, es un buen material en el tratamiento quirúrgico de la ptosis palpebral mediante suspensión al frontal, con excelentes resultados funcionales y relativamente escasas complicaciones. También pueden usarse otros materiales sintéticos o fascia lata en este procedimiento, aunque todos tienen el riesgo potencial de infección, extrusión, formación de granulomas o recurrencias</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(8): 443-448, ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados y complicaciones del politetrafluoroetileno expandido en la cirugía de ptosis palpebral por suspensión al frontal. Estudio de 59 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1788^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1788^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
