<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141989</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of sexual function in women with macromastia and their partners</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To investigate the sexual function in patients with macromastia and their partners. Materials and methods. 48 patients with macromastia and 30 healthy controls and their partners were enrolled in the study. The sexual function of the women and their partners was evaluated by using the Index of Female Sexual Function (IFSF) and International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF), respectively. Results. Mean ages of the patients and controls were respectively, 33.27 ± 5.24 and 32.06 ± 3.91 (p &gt; 0.05). Mean IFSF scores of the patients and controls were 23.21 ± 3.16 and 27.33 ± 4.94 (p = 0.00), respectively. All of the subscale scores of IFSF in the patient group were significantly lower than in the control group. Mean IIEF scores of the patients&#146; and controls&#146; partners were 60.33 ± 11.46 and 65.25 ± 6.18 (p = 0.04), respectively. Conclusion. In this study, Macromastia was shown to affect sexual function of women and their partners adversely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Keçeci, Yavuz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aksoy, Alper</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sir, Emin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Üçer, Oktay</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Güngör, Melike</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gümüç, Bilal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Investigar la función sexual en pacientes con macromastia y en sus parejas. Material y método. 48 pacientes con macromastia y 30 controles sanos y sus parejas fueron inscritos en el estudio. La función sexual de las mujeres y sus parejas fueron evaluadas usando el Índice de Función Sexual Femenina (IFSF) y el Índice Internacional de Función Eréctil (IIEF), respectivamente. Resultados. La edad media de los pacientes y controles era de respectivamente 33,27 ± 5,24 y 32,06 ± 3,91 (p &gt; 0,05). Las puntuaciones medias de los pacientes y los controles eran de respectivamente 23,21 ± 3,16 y 27,33 ± 4,94 (p = 0,00). Todas las puntuaciones en subescalas de IFSF en el grupo de los pacientes eran significativamente más bajas con respecto al grupo de control. La media de las puntuaciones del IIEF en las parejas de los pacientes y de los controles eran de respectivamente 60,33 ± 11,46 y 65,25 ± 6,18 (p = 0,04). Conclusiones. En este estudio, se demostró que la macromastia afecta la función sexual de las mujeres y sus parejas negativamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);13(3): 82-85, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Evaluación de la función sexual en mujeres con macromastia y sus parejas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
