<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113757</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Socio-sanitary Characteristics of Patients seen by Hospital Case Management Nurses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to identify the socio-sanitary profile of patients seen by the Hospital Case Management Nurse (HCMN), to learn about their dependency situation, diagnosis by the nursing staff, foreseen results, and interventions in said patients. Materials and methodology: descriptive study of patients seen by HCMNs in the Hospital General de Granada. Discharge reports issued by HCMNs were used as data collection tool. The socio-demographic and sanitary variables of dependent persons and their main caregivers were studied (Caregiver Strain Index (CSI)); as well as the patient&#146;s level of dependency (Barthel Index, Pfeiffer Test and Braden Scale); diagnosis by the nursing staff, results and nurse interventions. Results: the study was conducted on 218 patients; 59.2% of said patients were male. Their average age was 71.12 years. Of these patients,46.8% had severe dependency. Most patients lived alone (28.9%)or with a partner (23.7%). In 43.8% of cases, the main caregiver role was played by their children. The average hospitalization days were 20.06.In 89.9% of cases, patients returned home after discharge. The main diagnosis by nursing staff for those patients seen was &#147;deterioration of the skin integrity&#148;. Conclusions: the profile of patients managed by HCMNs could be defined as an elderly population, with complete or severe dependency, with prolonged hospitalizations and a high prevalence of &#147;deterioration of the skin integrity&#148; as nursing staff diagnosis. The HCMNs&#146; activity in terms of coordination with other professionals and departments, as well as their management of materials, makes home care continuity easier, in coordination with Primary Care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schmidt Río-Valle, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vellido González, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: identificar el perfil sociosanitario de los pacientes atendidos por la enfermera gestora de casos hospitalarios (EGCH), conocer la situación de dependencia, los diagnósticos de Enfermería, los resultados previstos y las intervenciones en estos pacientes. Material y método: estudio descriptivo sobre los enfermos atendidos por las EGCH del Hospital General de Granada. Como instrumento para la recogida de los datos se utilizaron los informes al alta emitidos por las mismas. Variables estudiadas: sociodemográficas y sanitarias de las personas dependientes y sus cuidadores principales (índice de esfuerzo del cuidador (IEC)); situación de dependencia del paciente (índice de Barthel, test de Pfeiffer y escala de Braden); diagnósticos de Enfermería, resultados e intervenciones enfermeras. Resultados: fueron estudiados 218 pacientes. El 59,2% eran hombres. La media de edad fue de 71,12 años. Un 46,8% tenían dependencia severa. La mayoría viven solos (28,9%) o en pareja (23,7%). En un 43,8%de los casos, la figura de cuidador principal recaía en los hijos. La media de días de ingreso fue de 20,06. En un 89,9% el destino al alta fue el domicilio. El principal diagnóstico de Enfermería en los pacientes atendidos fue el &#147;Deterioro de la integridad cutánea&#148;. Conclusiones: el perfil del paciente atendido por la EGCH se corresponde con población anciana, con dependencia total o severa, con ingresos hospitalarios prolongados y con una alta prevalencia del diagnóstico de Enfermería &#147;Deterioro de la integridad cutánea&#148;. La actividad de las EGCH de coordinación con otros profesionales y servicios, así como las funciones de gestión de material, facilita la continuidad de los cuidados en el domicilio, en coordinación con Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;16(4): 19-26, mayo 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características sociosanitarias de los pacientes atendidos por las enfermeras gestoras de casos hospitalarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
