<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042490</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subaortic stenosis more than twenty years after surgical repair of a partial atrial septal defect in an adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Subaortic stenosis after surgical correction of a partial atrioventricular septal defect is uncommon. When it occurs, it is usually diagnosed 6-8 years after early surgical repair in childhood. We present a female patient who underwent mitral valve cleft repair and closure of a partial atrial septal defect with a Teflon patch at the age of 48 years. Twenty-two years later, she presented with severe subaortic stenosis that required surgical repair. We analyze the intracardiac morphological factors associated with the development of late subaortic stenosis. We recommend long-term follow-up, even after surgical repair in adults</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fulquet Carreras, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gualis Cardona, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascal Hinojal, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estenosis subaórtica tras la corrección quirúrgica de una comunicación interauricular tipo ostium primum es muy infrecuente. Generalmente, se diagnostica 6-8 años tras la cirugía efectuada en una etapa temprana de la vida. Presentamos el caso de una paciente intervenida a los 48 años en la que se realizó un cierre con parche de la comunicación y la reparación de la hendidura mitral. Veintidós años después fue intervenida por estenosis subaórtica severa. Analizamos los factores morfológicos intracardíacos que predisponen a esta enfermedad y obligan a un seguimiento prolongado para su diagnóstico, incluso en correcciones en adultos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(1): 72-74, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estenosis subaórtica veinte años después de la reparación quirúrgica de un defecto septal auricular parcial en el adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35316^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35316^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35316^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6497^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
