<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145777</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Porphyria and inappropriate antidiuretic hormone síndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 37-years-old woman with inappropriate antidiuretic hormone syndrome due to an attack of acute porphyria. The patient was admitted to our hospital for abdominal pain, sleepiness and pink urine. Family and personal history were normal. Seven days before the admission the patient had a laparoscopy operation for endometriosis in her left ovary. The patient had had two normal pregnancies. The physical examination was normal, the skin turgor was good and no edema was present, the blood pressure was 140/90 mmHg. Her serum sodium was 114 mEq/L, serum osmolality 243 mOsm/kg, urine sodium 146 mEq/L and urine osmolality 457 mOsm/kg. Values from laboratory examination revealed a normal peripheral haematogram, a normal kidney function, normal liver, adrenal and thyroid function. The urine tested for amino-levulinic acid, coproporphyrin and uroporphyrin was strongly positive. This findings are compatible with Porphyria Variegata or Coproporphyria Hereditary. A diagnosis of Porphyria acute with SIADH was made, and water fluid restriction, i.v. hypertonic saline infusion and furosemida to correct the hyponatremia was begun. In 1966, lesions of the median eminence of the hypothalamus and both hypothalamic &#150;hypophyseal tracts were described in a patient with Porphyria acute intermittent and SIADH. It was suggested that SIADH occurred because of damage to these areas of the brain from excessive exposure to porphyrins (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lopez Montes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez Martinez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Describimos el caso de una mujer de 37 años que ingresa en el Servicio de Cirugía General por un cuadro de dolor abdominal y niveles hidroaéreos en la radiografía simple de abdomen con el diagnóstico de Suboclusión Intestinal. La paciente era madre de dos hijos y no tenía antecedentes de interés personales ni familiares. Siete días previos al ingreso había sido sometida a una intervención vía laparoscópica por una Endometriosis ovárica izquierda. Al ingreso la paciente refería dolor abdominal intenso y continuo acompañado de orinas rosadas, sin síndrome miccional y con cierta tendencia al sueño. Analíticamente destacaba una hiponatremia de 114 mEq/l con osmolalidad plasmática de 243 mOsm/kg, sodio en orina de 146 mEq/l, osmolalidad urinaria de 457 mOsm/kg con función renal y sedimento urinario normal. En el examen físico la paciente estaba normohidratada con buen estado general y sin signos de irritación peritoneal, con ruidos hidroaéreos disminuidos. Se diagnostica de Síndrome de secreción inadecuada de hormona antidiurética (SIADH) por lo que se trata con restricción hí- drica, suero salino hipertónico y furosemida. Con la presencia de un SIADH y ante el cuadro que presentaba la paciente se sospecha una porfiria aguda, siendo los niveles de uroporfirinógeno, ácido delta amino-levulínico y coproporfirinas en orinas altos, compatible con Porfiria Variegata o Coproporfiria hereditaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;24(supl.3): 85-88, 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de secreción inadecuada de hormona antidiurética y porfiria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3326^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10227^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d632^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7354^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30605^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7354^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7354^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14980^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30605^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4294^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12837^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
