<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037943</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal respiratory failure associated with mutation in the surfactant protein C gene</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Respiratory insufficiency in a term infant during the    first weeks of life is unusual. Possible causes include interstitial    or diffuse lung disease, which are a heterogeneous    group of mostly idiopathic disorders, characterized    by diffuse infiltrates, restrictive functional defect, and disordered    gas exchange. A form of interstitial lung disease    that can affect infants, children or young adults is that associated    with congenital surfactant protein B or C deficiency,    in which the inflammatory process leading to interstitial    fibrosis is preceded by the accumulation of    proteinaceous material in the alveolar space.    We assessed the role of potential abnormalities in the    surfactant proteins B and C in a Spanish family in which    two infants showed progressive neonatal respiratory failure    associated with radiological and pathological alterations    compatible with interstitial lung disease. The father    had a history of respiratory disease since childhood.    The two affected children in this family had abnormal    expression of surfactant C precursor protein, with markedly    decreased levels of the mature protein. Moreover, a previously    unreported mutation in the gene encoding surfactant    protein C, which was found in this family, is described</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bastero Miñón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Montero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alzina de Aguilar, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álava, E. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaboli, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia respiratoria en el recién nacido a término    durante las primeras semanas de vida extrauterina    es una situación poco frecuente. Entre sus causas se incluyen    las enfermedades difusas del intersticio pulmonar, un    grupo heterogéneo de enfermedades, la mayoría idiopáticas,    caracterizadas por infiltrados difusos, alteraciones    funcionales de tipo restrictivo y afectación del intercambio    gaseoso. Una forma de enfermedad pulmonar intersticial    que puede afectar a lactantes, niños o adultos jóvenes    es la que se asocia al déficit congénito de proteínas B o C    del surfactante pulmonar. En estos casos los procesos inflamatorios    que evolucionan hacia la fibrosis pulmonar están    precedidos por la acumulación de material proteináceo    en el alvéolo.    Se indagó la presencia de mutaciones en los genes de    las proteínas B y C del surfactante en una familia española    en la cual dos lactantes presentaron insuficiencia    respiratoria progresiva desde el nacimiento, con alteraciones    radiológicas y anatomopatológicas compatibles    con enfermedad del intersticio pulmonar, y el padre    refería historia de problemas respiratorios desde la infancia.    Se encontró que los dos hermanos de esta familia afectados    por la enfermedad presentaban una expresión anómala    del precursor de la proteína C del surfactante y concentraciones    muy bajas de proteína madura. Se describe    además una mutación nueva en el gen que codifica la proteína    C del surfactante y que cosegrega con la enfermedad    en esta familia</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);62(3): 210-214, mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia respiratoria neonatal asociada a mutación en el gen de la proteína C del surfactante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37474^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37474^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37473^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19398^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12095^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12095^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
