<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74801</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Delirium in patients aged more the 94 years with femur fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: delirium is a frequent problem during hospital admissionin the elderly. The aim of the present study was to evaluatethe occurrence of delirium in patients aged more than 94 yearsadmitted to hospital for femur fracture. A further aim was toanalyze the possible existence of differences in length of hospitalstay or in-hospital mortality according to the presence or absenceof delirium.Material and methods: a total of 25 patients (mean age 96.8years) admitted for femur fracture were included. Functionalstatus was determined through the Barthel index and comorbiditythrough Charlson&#146;s index. Diagnosis of delirium was basedon the Confusional Assessment Method.Results: there were 13 women (52%) and 12 men. The meanBarthel score before admission was 64.6 ± 22 and the meanCharlson Index was 1.4 ± 1. The mean length of hospital stay was15.2 ± 1.4 days. Five patients (20%) died during admission.Twelve patients (48%) developed delirium. Mortality (25% vs15.4%) and the mean number of days of hospital stay (17.5 vs 13days) were higher in patients with delirium, although thesedifferences were not statistically significant.Conclusions: practically half the patients aged more than 94years with fracture of the femur had an episode of delirium duringadmission(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Formiga, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-Mestre, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chivite, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el delirium es un problema frecuente durante el ingresohospitalario en los pacientes de edad avanzada. El objetivo delestudio es evaluar la aparición de delirium en los pacientes mayoresde 94 años hospitalizados por una fractura de fémur. Unsegundo objetivo es analizar si existen diferencias en relacióncon la estancia hospitalaria o el número de fallecimientos, segúnlos pacientes tengan o no delirium.Material y métodos: se incluyó a 25 pacientes (edad media, 96,8años) ingresados por fractura de fémur. Se cuantificó la funcionalidadmediante el índice de Barthel y la comorbilidad mediante elíndice de Charlson. Se utilizó el Confusional Assessment Methodpara el diagnóstico de delirium.Resultados: se trataba a 13 mujeres (52%) y 12 varones. La media± desviación estándar (DE) del índice de Barthel previo al ingresoera de 64,6 ± 22 y la media ± DE del índice de Charlson, de1,4 ± 1. La estancia media ± DE hospitalaria fue de 15,2 ± 1,4días; 5 pacientes (20%) fallecieron durante el ingreso y 12 pacientes(48%) presentaron delirium. El porcentaje de pacientes fallecidos(el 25 frente al 15,4%), así como el número de los días de estanciamedia hospitalaria (17,5 frente a 13 días) eran mayores enlos pacientes con delirium, sin alcanzar significación estadística.Conclusiones: prácticamente la mitad de los pacientes mayoresde 94 años ingresados por fractura de fémur tiene un episodio dedelirium durante un ingreso hospitalario por fractura de fémur(AU9</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);43(3): 154-156, may.2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Delirium en pacientes mayores de 94 años con fractura de fémur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
