<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136205</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic Expanded Endonasal Approaches to the Caudo-Ventral Skull Base</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transsphenoidal approaches were used in the last century to resect pituitary or other sellar tumors. Recently, standard endonasal approaches have been extended to provide access to other parasellar lesions. With the incorporation of endoscopes, this expansion is potentially of great importance in the resection of skull base lesions. The anatomical reference points and the surgical techniques used in extended endoscopic approaches to the sellar region,  clivus and cervico-medullary junction are reviewed and illustrations from the cases described are provided. The sellar region, the caudal portion of the medial anterior skull base and the cervico-medullary junction have been divided into modules for their approach: sellar, transellar, subsellar, middle third of the clivus, lower third of the clivus and the cervico-medullary junction. Dedicated courses and a progressive escalation of surgical case complexity are the keys to adequate training to achieve safe access to the lesions and regions described. Extended endoscopic approaches are feasible and will potentially reduce morbidity. The effectiveness and appropriate use of this technique should be critically evaluated. As the technique becomes more widely used, patient outcomes should be closely followed-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Snyderman, Carl H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kassam, Amin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gardner, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prevedello, Daniel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massegur, Humbert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrau, Ricardo L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintz, Arlan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los abordajes transesfenoidales se han usado en el último siglo para la resección de tumores hipofisarios u otros tumores sellares. Recientemente los abordajes endonasales estándar se han ampliado para proporcionar acceso a otras lesiones parasellares. Con la incorporación de los endoscopios, esta expansión tiene un potencial muy importante para la resección de las lesiones de la base de cráneo. Se revisan y se presentan los puntos de referencia anatómicos y las técnicas quirúrgicas empleadas en los abordajes endoscópicos ampliados a la región sellar, el clivus y la unión cervicomedular, acompañadas de ilustraciones de los casos descritos. La región sellar, la porción caudal de la base anterior de cráneo medial y la unión cervicomedular se han dividido en módulos para su abordaje: sellar, transellar, subsellar, tercio medio de clivus, su tercio inferior y la unión cervicomedular. Se proponen módulos de aprendizaje y progresión en la técnica quirúrgica para alcanzar los niveles adecuados de entrenamiento para poder acceder, con garantías, a las lesiones y regiones descritas. Los abordajes endoscópicos  ampliados son factibles y reúnen un gran potencial para disminuir la morbilidad. Se debe evaluar críticamente la efectividad y el uso apropiado de la técnica y hacer un estrecho seguimiento de la evolución de los casos según vayan aumentando en los años venideros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.1): 14-30, oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136205</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordajes endonasales endoscópicos ampliados a la base de cráneo caudoventral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53414^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3404^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9491^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9491^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14819^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13899^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3404^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53414^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14819^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
