<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163838</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Absence of the right superior vena cava and persistence of the left superior vena cava: antenatal diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Persistence of the left superior vena cava is the most common vascular anomaly in the thoracic venous system. However, the specifi c combination of a persistent left superior vena cava and absent right superior vena cava is extremely rare. Cases have been reported in children and adults but reports of antenatal diagnosis are extremely scarce. We report the fi ndings in an antenatal case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López García, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La persistencia de la vena cava superior izquierda se puede considerar la anomalía venosa más común en el tórax. Sin embargo, la persistencia de vena cava superior izquierda con ausencia de la vena cava superior derecha supone una alteración muy infrecuente. Existen casos comunicados en adultos o niños, sin embargo existe muy escasa literatura sobre esta malformación en diagnóstico prenatal. Se presentan hallazgos en caso fetal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(2): 66-68, mar.-abr. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ausencia de vena cava superior derecha con cava superior izquierda persistente: diagnóstico fetal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1289^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15085^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15085^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1289^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52512^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52512^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
