<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34499</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological tests abbreviated and adapted to spanish speakers: review of previous findings and validity studies for the discrimination of patients with anterior vs. posterior lesions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. There is a lack of neuropsychological tests for Spanish-speakers validated by the cerebral location of the injury. Then the antecedents of the present instrument are described. Aims. To study the validity of the battery for the differentiation of healthy subjects versus patients and, in patients, anterior versus posterior telencephalic lesions. Subjects and methods. 37 patients with frontal lesions, 37 with posterior lesions and 148 healthy subjects were studied. The three groups were matched by sex, age, years of study, and manual preference, and the two groups of patients also by laterality of the injury, type of lesion and time since onset of condition. Results. The discriminant analysis reached a percentage of correctly predicted cases of 86% for posterior lesions, 85% for anterior lesions, and 99% for healthy subjects. The analysis of the initial interview, only with the group of patients, resulted in a correct prediction of the observations of 90% or over for both lesions. In general, tests which best discriminated anterior from posterior lesions were the ones that worst discriminated anterior lesion from healthy subjects with exception of an easy paired-associated word learning test which turned out to be valid for the discrimination of the three groups. Conclusion. Present results demonstrated that this battery of abbreviated tests adapted to Spanish speakers was valid for the discrimination of the three studied groups. Methodological approaches based on objective evaluations and multiple comparisons rather than on clinical appreciation are proposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existe una carencia de tests neuropsicológicos para hispanoparlantes validados por la localización cerebral de la lesión. Se describen entonces los antecedentes del presente instrumento. Objetivos. Estudiar la validez de la batería para la diferenciación de sanos frente a pacientes y de pacientes con lesiones telencefálicas anteriores y posteriores. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron 37 pacientes con lesiones anteriores, 37 con lesiones posteriores y 148 sujetos sanos. Los tres grupos se parearon por sexo, edad, años de estudio, preferencia manual, y los dos grupos de pacientes, también por lateralidad de la lesión, tipo de lesión y tiempo de evolución. Resultados. El análisis discriminante llegó a un porcentaje de predicción correcta de las observaciones de: 86 por ciento para las lesiones posteriores, 85 por ciento para las lesiones anteriores y 99 por ciento para los sanos. Analizando la entrevista inicial, solamente con el grupo de pacientes, la predicción correcta fue del 90 por ciento o superior para ambas lesiones. En general, los tests que mejor discriminaron a los lesionados anteriores de los posteriores fueron los que peor discriminaron a los lesionados anteriores de los sanos, con excepción de un test de aprendizaje de pares de palabras simples apareadas, que resultó válido para la discriminación de los tres grupos. Conclusión. Los presentes resultados demuestran que esta batería de test abreviados y adaptados para hispanoparlantes resultó válida para la discriminación de los tres grupos estudiados. Se proponen enfoques metodológicos basados en evaluaciones objetivas y comparaciones múltiples, más que en la apreciación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(3): 205-212, ago. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tests neuropsicológicos abreviados y adaptados para hispanoparlantes: revisión de hallazgos previos y estudios de validez para la discriminación de pacientes con lesiones anteriores frente a posteriores</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vigliecca, NS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34499</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
