<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126671</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship of nickel and gingival enlargement: Review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gingival overgrowth is common among patients and can be caused by a variety of etiological factors. The most common reason is gingival inflammation caused by poor oral hygiene and high bacterial load. Other factors include systemic drugs, like channel blockers are calcium, immunosuppressants and anticonvulsants. Some gingival overgrowth are associated with hormonal conditions such as puberty, pregnancy or diabetes or be a symptom of a systemic disease and rarely the gingival overgrowth is associated with genetic factors, who is called hereditary gingival fibromatosis. Another cause of gingival overgrowth has been presented in dentistry and is related to fixed orthodontic appliances, whose specific cause is not fully defined yet. This article is a narrative review which aims to describe the generalities of gingival overgrowth and reports in the literature of the effect of fixed orthodontic appliances in gingival overgrowth because nickel probably is another factor causing this condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fang Mercado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Arcila, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El agrandamiento gingival es común entre los pacientes y puede ser causado por una variedad de factores etiológicos. La razón más común es la inflamación gingival provocada por mala higiene oral y alta carga bacteriana. Otros factores implicados son los medicamentos sistémicos, en donde se encuentran bloqueadores de los canales de calcio, inmunosupresores y anticonvulsivantes. Algunos crecimientos gingivales podrían estar asociados a condiciones hormonales como la pubertad, el embarazo o la diabetes o ser un síntoma de una enfermedad sistémica y en raras ocasiones el agrandamiento gingival se asocia a factores genéticos y hereditario llamado fibromatosis gingival. Otra causa del agrandamiento gingival se viene presentando en la consulta odontológica y es la relacionada con la aparatología ortodóncica fija, cuya causa específica no está totalmente definida aún. El presente artículo es una revisión narrativa cuyo objetivo es describir las generalidades del agrandamiento gingival y reportes en la literatura sobre la acción de la aparatología ortodóncica fija en el agrandamiento gingival, pues se presume del níquel como otro factor causal de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;26(2): 83-89, ago. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El níquel y su vínculo con el agrandamiento gingival: Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9717^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6024^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32943^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6021^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10145^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
