<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051661</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Voice pathology in teachers: influence of occupational and non-occupational factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To assess the importance of work-related factors (work load) on voice pathologies suffered by teachers;.To ToTo study the characteristics of exposure time and hourly dosage in voice use..Toidentifyeffect-modifyingfactors. To identify effect-modifying factors.. Methods. A cross-sectional study was conducted with a two-tiered sample. The study involved 245 teachers from the primary, secondary and university levels, using a self-administered questionnaire with subsequent statistical analysis of the data. Results. Eighty-five subjects exhibited symptoms (34.7% prevalence rate). The main symptom was alteration of voice tone (95.3%). Of those studied, 31.8% indicated complete voice loss. Voice disorders were more frequent among the most veteran teachers (exposure time), women, those suffering from sleep disorders, anxiety and gastroesophageal reflux, exhibiting statistically significant differences. Those affected turn more frequently to speech therapists for help when symptoms have already manifested themselves, and the number of teachers with voice disorders on sick-leave increases. No differences were found between symptomatic and asymptomatic subjects with regard to exposure time, tobacco use and consumption of alcohol or pharmaceuticals. Conclusions. A high percentage of teachers exhibiting voice-related symptoms, especially functional disorders, was found. This draws attention to the need for early detection of these disorders and for preventive measures. The questionnaire could be a good tool for initial detection of the problem</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano Estrada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Pulgarín, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gañet Benavente, R. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Valorar la importancia de la carga de trabajo en la patología vocal de los docentes considerando el tiempo de exposición y la dosis horaria, así como los efectos de otros factores potencialmente asociados a dichas alteraciones.Métodos. Se realiza un estudio transversal con muestreo bietápico a partir del registro del Servicio de Prevención de ASEPEYO en Madrid. Se estudian 245 docentes procedentes de centros de enseñanza primaria, secundaria y universitaria a través de un cuestionario de autoaplicación, con posterior análisis estadístico de los datos.Resultados. Se identifican 85 profesores con síntomas de patología vocal (prevalencia 34,7%). El síntoma principal es la alteración del timbre de la voz (95,3%). Un 31,8% pierde la voz por completo. Son más frecuentes los trastornos de la voz en quienes han trabajado más años (tiempo de exposición), en las mujeres y en los que padecen trastornos del sueño, ansiedad y reflujo gastroesofágico, con diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Además, hay más consultas al logopeda y aumenta el número de bajas laborales en los que padecen alteraciones de la voz. No existen diferencias entre sintomáticos y asintomáticoscon respecto a la dosis horaria de uso de la voz, consumo de tabaco o alcohol, ni consumo de medicamentos.Conclusiones. Se ha encontrado una proporción alta de docentes con sintomatología relacionada con la voz, principalmentetrastornos de carácter funcional. Se pone de manifiesto la necesidad de detectar precozmente estas alteraciones y establecer medidas preventivas. El cuestionario puede ser un buen método de detección inicial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);10(1): 12-17, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología vocal en trabajadores docentes: influencia de factores laborales y extralaborales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
