<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044651</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pure red blood cell aplasia associated with neutralizing antibodies against erythropoietin induced by epoetin alfa: a new form of acquired erythroblastopenia in uremic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a woman with end-stage renal disease on maintenance    hemodialysis and treated with recombinant human erythropoietin (epoetin alfa) administered subcutaneously, who developed a pure red cell aplasia secondary to    the development of neutralizing antibodies anti-erythropoietin after 8 months of    treatment.    Despite epoetin withdrawal and immunosuppressive treatment with corticosteroids    and gammaglobulins the patient still has high red blood cell transfusion requirements    and undetectable plasma erythropoietin levels.    Pure red cell aplasia secondary to the development of neutralizing antibodies    anti-erythropoietin is a rare but severe complication associated with the use of recombinant    human erythropoietin in uremic patients. In recent years, the incidence    of this complication has sharply increased, specially associated with the use    of epoetin alfa administered subcutaneously. For this reason, the Spanish Drug    Agency has recently contraindicated treating uremic patients with epoetin alfa administered    subcutaneously</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cases, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esforzado, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el caso de una paciente con insuficiencia renal crónica terminal en    programa de hemodiálisis y en tratamiento con eritropoyetina recombinante humana    (epoetina alfa) por vía subcutánea, que a los 8 meses de tratamiento presentó    una aplasia pura de la serie roja secundaria al desarrollo de anticuerpos    neutralizantes anti-eritropoyetina.    A pesar de la retirada del tratamiento y de haberse ensayado tratamiento inmunosupresor    con corticoides y gammaglobulinas la paciente sigue presentando    unos requerimientos transfusionales muy elevados y niveles circulantes de eritropoyetina    indetectables.    La eritroblastopenia secundaria al tratamiento con eritropoyetina recombinante    humana es una complicación rara pero grave en pacientes urémicos. En los últimos    años se ha descrito un aumento de su incidencia, especialmente en pacientes    tratados con epoetina alfa por vía subcutánea. Por ello, recientemente la Agencia    Española del Medicamento ha contraindicado administrar epoetina alfa por    vía subcutánea en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(3): 266-270, mayo-jun. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplasia pura de la serie roja asociada a anticuerpos neutralizantes frente a eritropoyetina inducida por epoetina alfa: una nueva forma de eritroblastopenia adquirida en pacientes urémicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1329^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55967^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30412^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30412^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55967^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
