<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159374</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inventory of Overburden in Alzheimer&#146;s Patient Family Caregivers with no Specialized Training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/Objective: Alzheimer-type dementia is one of the most frequent causes of dependence in an aging population, which combines with a considerable demand for care. Furthermore, when the caregiver is a family member or person without specialized training, such care impacts on that person&#146;s health. The Inventory of Overburden in Alzheimer&#146;s Patient Family Caregivers with no Specialized Training (IPSO-CA24) was designed to find out the needs of these caregivers and evaluate the caregiver&#146;s burden or distress. Method: The psychometric properties of the questionnaire were analyzed (in a reliability analysis, exploratory factor analysis and confirmatory analysis) based on the responses of 255 caregivers. Results: The factor analyses showed a six-factor structure (Reaction to diagnosis, Physical health, Psychological symptomatology (caretaker), Behavioral symptomatology (patient), Knowledge of the illness, and Level of dependence) explaining 66.52% of the total variance with a reliability of .75 to .93. Support was also found for its convergent validity. Conclusions: The IPSO-CA24 responds to the need for an instrument enabling multidimensional evaluation of the burden on the family caregiver without specialized training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Fuentes, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Fernández, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gázquez Linares, José Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero Jurado, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes/Objetivo: La demencia tipo Alzheimer es una de las causas más frecuentes de dependencia en población mayor, a lo que se une, la considerable demanda de cuidados. Además, cuando el cuidador es un familiar o una persona sin formación especializada, el cuidado tiene un impacto sobre su salud. Para conocer las necesidades de estos cuidadores y evaluar el nivel de sobrecarga o malestar del cuidador, se realiza la propuesta del Inventario de Sobrecarga en Cuidadores Familiares sin Formación Especializada de Enfermos de Alzheimer (IPSO-CA24). Método: En base a las respuestas de 255 cuidadores, se analizaron las propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario, mediante análisis de fiabilidad, análisis factoriales exploratorios y confirmatorios. Resultados: Los análisis factoriales informan de una estructura de seis factores relacionados (Reacción ante el diagnóstico, Salud física, Sintomatología psicológica (cuidador), Sintomatología conductual (enfermo), Conocimientos de la enfermedad y Nivel de dependencia), con una fiabilidad entre 0,75 y 0,93, que explican el 66,52% de la varianza total. También se obtiene apoyo para su validez convergente. Conclusiones: El IPSO-CA24 viene a dar respuesta a la necesidad de un instrumento que permita una valoración multidimensional de la sobrecarga del cuidador familiar sin formación especializada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);17(1): 56-64, ene.-abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inventario de Sobrecarga en Cuidadores Familiares sin Formación Especializada de Enfermos de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
