<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164278</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of complications of arteriovenous fistula for hemodialysis according to the puncture technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The arteriovenous fistula is the standard vascular access for the treatments in hemodialysis, punctured periodically three times per week. There are three types of puncture techniques: ladder, puncture area and buttonhole. Conventional techniques cause great morbidity in the medium and long term, however, a priori, the buttonhole technique is associated to the improvement of those problems. Objective: To compare the buttonhole puncture technique with respect to conventional techniques for vascular access cannulation in the treatment of hemodialysis, depending on the degree of pain associated with the technique, associated infection rates and the repercussion on vascular access survival. Material and Method: Narrative bibliographic review. Experimental and observational studies in English and Spanish published between 2010 and 2015 were included, comparing the conventional puncture technique versus the Buttonhole puncture technique. Initial selection by title and summary. The CASPe and STROBE scales were used for the methodological evaluation. Results: 1.827 studies were identified, of which 13 were selected after the critical evaluation process. The heterogeneity of results does not allow to affirm improvements of any of the techniques analyzed in puncture pain or survival of the access, nevertheless, it is associated an increase of infectious events with the Buttonhole technique. Conclusion: Any arguments have been found to ensure that Buttonhole technique can be considered as first choice due to the heterogeneity of the measurement methods of the reviewed studie (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calero, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Mavillard, Ian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Rojas, Cynthia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fístula arteriovenosa es el acceso vascular de elección para los tratamientos en hemodiálisis, puncionado periódicamente tres veces por semana. Existen tres tipos de técnicas de punción: en escalera, en área de punción y buttonhole. Las técnicas convencionales son causantes de gran morbilidad a medio y largo plazo, sin embargo, el Buttonhole está asociado a priori a la mejoraría de esos problemas. Objetivo: Comparar la técnica de punción de buttonhole con respecto a las técnicas convencionales para la canulación del acceso vascular en el tratamiento de Hemodiálisis, en función del grado de dolor asociado a la técnica, tasas de infección asociadas y la repercusión sobre la supervivencia del acceso vascular. Material y Método: Revisión bibliográfica narrativa. Se incluyeron estudios experimentales y observacionales en inglés y castellano publicados entre 2010 y 2015, que compararan la técnica de punción convencional respecto a la técnica de punción Buttonhole. Selección inicial por título y resumen. Se utilizaron las escalas CASPe y STROBE para la evaluación metodológica. Resultados: Se identificaron 1.827 estudios, de los que seleccionamos 13 tras el proceso de evaluación crítica. La heterogeneidad de resultados no permite afirmar que ninguna de las técnicas analizadas mejore los resultados en dolor en la punción o supervivencia del acceso, sin embargo, se asocia un aumento de eventos infecciosos con la técnica de Buttonhole. Conclusión: no se han hallado argumentos para asegurar que el Buttonhole pueda ser considerado una técnica de primera elección, debido a la heterogeneidad de las formas de medida de los estudios revisados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;20(2): 167-177, abr.-jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164278</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de complicaciones de la fístula arteriovenosa para hemodiálisis según la técnica de canalización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
