<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86833</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac abnormalities in osteogenesis imperfecta. Case-control echocardiographic study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives:  Osteogenesis imperfecta is a rare disease with abnormal synthesis of type 1 collagen that affects diverse extra-skeletal tissues. Aortic root dilatation and valvular dysfunction have been described. Our purpose was to evaluate the prevalence of cardiac abnormalities in patients with osteogenesis imperfecta in comparison with an age and sex-matched control group of healthy people. Patients and methods: We prospectively studied 26 patients with osteogenesis imperfecta and compared them with 25 healthy people. All patients underwent a transthoracic standard M-mode, 2D and colour Doppler study. Results: We did not find significant differences between both groups in the left ventricular diastolic and systolic function and the incidence of valvulopathies. The dimensions of the aortic root, left atrium and left ventricle when indexed by body surface area were significantly larger in patients with osteogenesis imperfecta compared with the control group, which was probably due to the reduced body surface of these patients. However there was a significant difference in the aortic root/telediastolic diameter of left ventricle ratio independent of the body surface, which was higher in patients with osteogenesis imperfecta.Conclusions: The incidence of valvular disease in osteogenesis imperfecta is similar to that of the normal population. However aortic root is larger in the former patients and is related to the left ventricular diastolic diameter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alverca Vela, Maria Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonilla Jiménez, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra Falero, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bolaño, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Guardiola, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: La osteogénesis imperfecta (OI) se caracteriza por una síntesis anómala del colágeno tipo i, que ocasiona fragilidad ósea y otras manifestaciones extraesqueléticas. Se han descrito diversas manifestaciones cardiovasculares, incluyendo la disfunción valvular (en especial el prolapso mitral) y la dilatación de la raíz de la aorta (AO). Nuestro objetivo es evaluar la prevalencia de anomalías cardiacas en los pacientes con OI en comparación con un grupo control de individuos sanos de la misma edad y sexo. Pacientes y método:Se estudió de forma prospectiva a 26 pacientes diagnosticados de OI y los comparamos con 25 pacientes sanos. Se llevó a cabo en todos ellos un estudio ecocardiográfico en modo M, 2D y Doppler color. Resultados:No encontramos en nuestro estudio diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos en cuanto a la función sistólica y diastólica del ventrículo izquierdo (VI) ni en la incidencia de valvulopatías. Las dimensiones de la AO, la aurícula izquierda y el VI únicamente al ajustarlas a la superficie corporal eran significativamente mayores en los pacientes con osteogénesis frente al grupo control, probablemente debido a la menor superficie corporal de estos pacientes. Sin embargo, existía una diferencia significativa al calcular la proporción AO/diámetro telediastólico del VI, independiente de la superficie corporal, que era mayor en los pacientes con OI.Conclusiones: No encontramos una mayor incidencia de valvulopatías respecto al grupo control y sí encontramos una raíz de la AO de mayor tamaño en relación con el tamaño del VI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);135(15): 681-684, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones cardiacas en la osteogénesis imperfecta. Estudio ecocardiográfico de casos y controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10192^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29446^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1023^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
