<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138600</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of excess resources in patients with catheter-related infection (bacteremia), postoperative pulmonary embolism or deep vein (DVT-PTE) or postoperative sepsis in the National Health System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the excess of length of stay (LOS) attributable to the presence of adverse events in patients who were operated. Methodology: Observational, cross-sectional study on the basis of clinical and administrative hospital discharge data. Discharge chosen were produced in 2009 and 2010 in acute hospitals of the 17 Spanish autonomous communities of the National Health System, which are part of the project Atlas of Variability in Medical Practice in the National Health System (Atlas VPM Group). Results: Excess of LOS was 28 days, 10 days and 14 days in the catheter-related infection (bacteremia), postoperative pulmonary embolism or deep vein (DVT-PTE) or postoperative sepsis stays. The predictor variables of the patient (age, sex and Elixhauser) influence in the excess of LOS. Conclusion: Adverse events are associated with a significant increase of excess of LOS. The discharge minimum basic dataset (CMBD) allows to estimate the impact of adverse events in the Spanish hospitals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ridao-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seral Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Delgado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Lizaga, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo Pueyo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comendeiro-Maalooe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar el exceso de estancia atribuible a la presencia de eventos adversos en pacientes que han sido sometidos a una intervención quirúrgica en el mismo episodio. Población y métodos: Estudio observacional, transversal, sobre bases de datos clínico-administrativos al alta hospitalaria. Las altas elegidas fueron producidas en los años 2009 y 2010 en los centros hospitalarios de agudos de las 17 comunidades autónomas del SNS español, las cuales forman parte del proyecto Atlas de Variabilidad de la Práctica Médica en el Sistema Nacional de Salud (Atlas VPM). Resultados: El exceso de estancia fue de 28, 10 y 14 días en las altas con infección debida a uso de dispositivo vascular, altas con tromboembolismo o trombosis venosa profunda tras la cirugía y altas con sepsis post-quirúrgica, respectivamente. Las variables predictoras del paciente (edad, sexo, Elixhauser) influyen en el exceso de estancia. Conclusión: Los eventos adversos están asociados a un incremento significativo de exceso de estancia. El CMBD (Conjunto Mínimo Básico de Datos hospitalario) permite hacer una estimación del impacto que esto tiene en los hospitales españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);26(1): 62-68, ene.-mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del exceso de consumo de recursos en pacientes con enfermedad tromboembólica tras cirugía, infección por uso de dispositivo vascular postoperatorio o sepsis post-quirúrgica en el Sistema Nacional de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
