<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19354</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-cultural adaptation into spanish of the Vecú et Sante Perçue de l'Adolescent (VSP-A) into Spanish: a generic measure of quality of life for adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Different measures of health related quality of life for use exclusively in children and adolescents have been developed over the last ten years. However, few instruments of this type have been adapted in Spain. The VSP-A is a generic health related quality of life measure for adolescents aged 11-17 developed in France. The objective of this study was to adapt the VSP-A into Spanish as a first step towards obtaining this questionnaire. Methods: The version of the VSP-A including 39 questions was adapted following the foward-backward translation methodology, including two translations into Spanish, scoring of difficulty (0 min-10 max.) and classification of semantic and conceptual equivalence, two panel discussions with adolescents, as well as meetings of consensus with the original authors. Finally, a backward translation (translation back into the original language) was carried out into French, and the final pre-test version was administered in a pilot test.  Results: Most of the questions were classified as equivalent (24/39). Following the meetings with adolescents, changes were made in some questions. After the back-translation into French, three questions required some minor changes. Conclusions: The Spanish version of the VSP-A seems to be semantically and culturally equivalent to the original version and suitable for adolescents in Spain. The inclusion of easy statements in the original version, the comments of the adolescents and the involvement in the adaptation process of the original authors has offered the possibility of achieving a suitable pre-test version. The next phase of the study will involve the questionnaire's reliability and validity testing. The VSP-A is expected to be useful for measuring the health-related quality of life in health surveys or as a screening tool in schools and primary care centers in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En la última década se han desarrollado diversas medidas de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud para uso exclusivo en niños/as y adolescentes. No obstante, existen pocos instrumentos de estas características adaptados en España. El Vecú et Sante Perçue de l'adolescent (VSP-A) es un instrumento genérico de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud para adolescentes de 11 a 17 años desarrollado en Francia. El objetivo de este estudio fue adaptar al español el VSP-A, como primera fase para la obtención del cuestionario. Métodos: Se adaptó la versión del VSP-A de 39 preguntas siguiendo la metodología de traducción directa e inversa incluyendo: 2 traducciones al español, puntuación del grado de dificultad (0 min-10 máx) y clasificación de equivalencia semántica y cultural, 2 reuniones y discusión en paneles de adolescentes, así como reuniones de consenso del equipo de investigación. Finalmente se realizó una traducción inversa (retro-traducción) al francés y se administró la versión final pre-test en la prueba piloto. Resultados: La mayoría de las preguntas se clasificaron como equivalentes (24 sobre 39). Tras las reuniones con adolescentes se modificaron algunas preguntas. Tras la retro-traducción, 3 preguntas necesitaron cambios menores. Conclusiones: La versión española del VSP-A parece semántica y culturalmente equivalente a la versión original en francés y adecuada para adolescentes en España. La sencillez de las preguntas, los comentarios de los adolescentes y la participación de los autores originales en el proceso de adaptación ha permitido obtener una versión pre-test adecuada. La siguiente fase del estudio es la comprobación de la fiabilidad y validez. Se espera que el VSP-A sea de utilidad para medir la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en encuestas de salud o como instrumento de cribado en colegios o centros de atención primaria en nuestro medio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(6): 701-712, nov. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación al español del cuestionario vecú et sante perçue de l'adolescent (VSP-A): una medida genérica de calidad de vida para adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Herdman, Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Sutton, Vicky</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santed, Rosalía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Auquier, Pascal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siméoni, Marie Claude</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rajmil, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19354</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5737</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
