<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86876</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurocognitive dysfunction in electrical status epilepticus during slow-wave sleep syndrome: can the natural course of the syndrome be modified with early pharmacological treatment?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Epileptic syndromes with continuous spike wave in slow-wave sleep (CSWS), including electrical status  epilepticus in sleep (ESES) and Landau-Kleffner syndrome, are true epileptic encephalopathies where sustained epileptic activity is related to cognitive and behavioural decline. Aims. To review the natural course of ESES, to define the general principles of treatment of epileptic syndromes with CSWS, to delineate the different options that are currently available for treating these epileptic encephalopathies, and to analyze the prognostic factors linked to pharmacological treatment of ESES. Development. Epileptic syndromes with CSWS are initially treated with a pharmacologic intervention with polytherapy of  antiepileptic drugs in most cases. However, due to the poor response that CSWS often have to antiepileptic drugs, nonpharmacologic treatment options are an important part of a comprehensive treatment plan for this group of children. This article discusses the use of corticosteroids, intravenous immunoglobulins, ketogenic diet, vagus nerve stimulation, and epilepsy surgery in the treatment of patients with epileptic syndromes with CSWS. Conclusions. Treatment of ESES extends beyond just control of the seizures; amelioration of the continuous epileptiform discharge must occur to improve neuropsychological outcome. There is a significant correlation between the length of the  ESES period and the extent of residual intellectual deficit at follow-up. According to this knowledge, there is a well defined therapeutic interval where our different strategies of treatment may be useful, and the upper limits of this time frame to a critical period of 12-18 months (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Peñas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los síndromes con punta-onda continua en sueño (POCS), incluyendo el estado de mal eléctrico durante el sueño lento (ESES) y el síndrome de Landau-Kleffner, son auténticas encefalopatías epilépticas en las que la actividad epiléptica mantenida produce un deterioro cognitivo y conductual evolutivo. Objetivos. Revisar la evolución natural del síndrome ESES, conocer las bases generales del tratamiento de los síndromes con POCS, repasar las distintas alternativas terapéuticas disponibles y analizar cuáles son los factores pronósticos del ESES ligados al tratamiento farmacológico. Desarrollo. Los síndromes con POCS se tratan inicialmente con distintas combinaciones de fármacos antiepilépticos en  politerapia. Sin embargo, debido a la falta de eficacia global de los fármacos antiepilépticos sobre el patrón eléctrico de la POCS y el perfil neurocognitivo del síndrome, se debe considerar siempre la posibilidad de utilizar otras opciones terapéuticas, incluyendo terapia inmunomoduladora con corticoides y/o inmunoglobulinas intravenosas, dieta cetogénica, estimulación del nervio vago y diversas técnicas de cirugía de la epilepsia. Conclusiones. Existe una correlación evidente entre el tiempo que los pacientes permanecen en POCS y el grado de déficit neurocognitivo evolutivo que desarrollan. De acuerdo con esta premisa, es importante conocer que existe un intervalo terapéutico bien definido en el que podemos realizar nuestro tratamiento de forma eficaz, y que estos límites se enmarcan en un período crítico que oscila entre los 12 y los 18 meses de duración de la POCS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(supl.3): s37-s47, mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción neurocognitiva en el síndrome de estado de mal eléctrico durante el sueño lento: ¿podemos modificar la evolución natural del síndrome con un tratamiento farmacológico precoz?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
