<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66123</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arthrosis is, as we all know, a disease having high prevalence that uses a large amount of health care resources in both Primary Health Care and in the Hospital. The present &#147;Good clinical practice recommendations in arthrosis&#148; Guide aims to provide basic knowledge in this disease and to help to reach the best objectives on the diagnostic and therapeutic levels to incorporate them into our daily clinical activity. These options should be based on tests supported categorically and that will be indicated within the context and development of this Guide. Even so, the lines of research for arthrosis regarding action on the risk factors and on the use of drugs that can only be developed from the natural history of the disease and from the long term follow-up over years, that is from Primary Health Care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casals Sánchez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Marqués, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panero Hidalgo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Basallote, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artrosis constituye, como todos sabemos, una patología de alta prevalencia y de gran consumo de recursos sanitarios tanto en Atención Primaria como a nivel hospitalario. La presente Guía de &#147;Recomendaciones de buena práctica clínica en artrosis&#148; pretende dar a conocer conocimientos básicos en esta patología y alcanzar los objetivos idóneos tanto a nivel diagnóstico como terapéutico para plasmarlos en nuestra actuación clínica diaria. Dichas opciones han de estar basadas en pruebas avaladas de forma categórica y que se irán señalando dentro del contexto y desarrollo de esta Guía. Aún así, la artrosis presenta líneas abiertas de investigación en actuación sobre los factores de riesgo y sobre el uso de fármacos, que sólo desde la historia natural de la enfermedad y desde un seguimiento largo y de años, es decir desde Atención Primaria, se pueden ir desarrollando</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(3): 143-148, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66123</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
