<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048235</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pathophysiology of neuromuscular impairments in the critically ill patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the causes and manifestations of muscle weakness that critically ill patients develop during their staying at the ICU, and literature review.  Development: in the early 1980s, a mixed axonal polyneuropathy was described in septic critically ill patients, which clinically manifested by muscle weakness of variable severity, leading to quadriplegia and/or ventilator dependency in its most severe presentation. Almost at the same time, an acute intensive care myopathy was described in asthmatic patients admitted to the ICU for asthma exacerbation. Later on, this myopathy was also observed in transplanted, septic, or burnt patients. Several authors consider acute intensive care myopathy as the main cause of muscle weakness in the ICU. Conclusions: in this article, we describe the clinical presentation, etiopathogenesis, diagnosis, and treatment of polyneuropathy of the critically ill patient and of acute intensive care myopathy. Both clinical pictures may be differentiated, with neurophysiological studies and eventually muscle biopsy being of great help. Although some authors rather include these conditions under the name of polyneuromyopathy, we propose the general denomination of Acute Neuromuscular Syndrome of the Critically Ill Patient, a more descriptive term no presupposing a single mechanism or etiology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Lorenzo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Montes, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar las causas y manifestaciones de la debilidad muscular que desarrollan los pacientes críticos durante su estancia en la UCI y revisar la bibliografía.  Desarrollo: A principios de los años 80 se describió en pacientes críticos sépticos una polineuropatía axonal mixta que clínicamente se caracterizaba por una debilidad muscular de intensidad variable que en su vertiente más grave producía tetraplejia y/o dependencia del ventilador. Casi paralelamente se describió la miopatía aguda de los cuidados intensivos en pacientes asmáticos que eran ingresados en la UCI por exacerbación de su enfermedad. Con posterioridad se observó que esta miopatía se presentaba también en pacientes trasplantados, sépticos o quemados. Hay autores que consideran a la miopatía aguda de los cuidados intensivos como la primera causa de debilidad muscular en la UCI. Conclusiones: En este artículo se describen la clínica, etiopatogenia, diagnóstico y tratamiento de la polineuropatía del paciente crítico y de la miopatía aguda de los cuidados intensivos. Los dos cuadros clínicos son diferenciables en muchas ocasiones, siendo de gran ayuda los estudios neurofisiológicos y eventualmente la biopsia muscular. Aunque algunos autores prefieren englobar estas entidades bajo el nombre de polineuromiopatía, proponemos la denominación general de Síndrome Neuromuscular Agudo en el paciente crítico término más descriptivo, que no presupone un mecanismo ni una etiología única (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(supl.3): 96-103, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048235</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiopatología de las alteraciones neuromusculares en el paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11553^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33110</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
