<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155292</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prebiotics and nucleotides in infant nutrition; review of the evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Most of the initiation and maintenance pediatric formulas commercialized in Spain contain prebiotics and/or nucleotides aiming at achieving beneficial effects on prevention of different pathologies and immune protection, similar to human breast milk. However, according to the current legislation, its inclusion is optional since sufficient scientific evidences supporting its mandatory inclusion is lacking. Objective: To systematically review the scientific evidence from randomized clinical studies with a control group allowing determining the beneficial role for infant health derived from the inclusion of prebiotics and/or nucleotides in pediatric formulas. Methodology: We looked for and selected both original papers and reviews in Spanish and English language of placebo controlled randomized clinical studies published in the databases MEDLINE/PubMed, Scielo, Science Direct, and Scopus, until October of 2011. Results: We found 43 randomized clinical trials meeting the inclusion criteria. Conclusions: More long-term randomized studies with higher number of patients, and standardized supplemental amounts and experimental conditions are needed to establish healthy statements with stronger scientific support regarding the addition of a mixture of prebiotics (GOS/FOS) and/or nucleotides in pediatric formulas. The current trend to include them in pediatric formulas may be justified based on the currently available evidence, as well as their safety and their presence in human breast milk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacomba, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Llatas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Una gran mayoría de preparados infantiles de inicio y continuación comercializados en España presentan en su formulación prebióticos y/o nucleótidos, con objeto de lograr efectos beneficiosos en la prevención de diferentes patologías y protección inmunológica, similares a los de la leche materna. No obstante, atendiendo a la reglamentación vigente, su adición es opcional, ya que no existe suficiente evidencia científica que certifique la obligatoriedad de su inclusión. Objetivo: Revisar sistemáticamente la evidencia científica proveniente de estudios clínicos aleatorizados con grupo control que permita determinar el papel beneficioso para la salud de los lactantes derivada de la adición de prebióticos y/o nucleótidos en preparados infantiles. Metodología: Se buscaron y seleccionaron tanto artículos originales como revisiones en inglés y español de estudios clínicos aleatorizados con grupo control, publicados en las bases de datos de MEDLINE/PubMed, Scielo, Science Direct y Scopus, hasta octubre de 2011. Resultados: Se encontraron 43 ensayos clínicos aleatorizados que cumplieron con los criterios de inclusión. Conclusiones: Son necesarios más estudios a largo plazo, con mayor número de individuos y aleatorizados, así como estandarización de las cantidades suplementadas y demás condiciones experimentales, para poder establecer declaraciones saludables con mayor base científica respecto a la adición de la mezcla de prebióticos (GOS/FOS) y/o nucleótidos en preparados infantiles. La tendencia actual a su inclusión en preparados infantiles puede justificarse en base a las evidencias científicas disponibles hasta el momento, así como a su seguridad y a su presencia en la leche materna (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(4): 1037-1048, jul.-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prebióticos y nucleótidos en alimentación infantil; revisión de la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9897^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7406</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53615^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
