<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046415</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation and diagnosis of patients with genetic mental retardation: standardised clinical evaluation protocols</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims. Mental retardation (MR) affects approximately 2-3% of the general population and around75% of the known causes of MR are thought to have a genetic origin. The aim of this work is to describe a standardised model ofdiagnostic approach to patients with mental retardation of a genetic origin (MRGO). Development. The clinician has to draw upa detailed case history and carry out a thorough dysmorphological physical examination that enables a reasonable differentialdiagnosis to be reached. The next step will be to request the complementary studies needed to confirm or reject the initialsuspected diagnosis. Accurate information about the personal, prenatal (pregnancy) and perinatal (childbirth) history must alsobe collected. The postnatal history will also provide relevant clinical information. The familial history is a fundamental elementof any genetic disease and must be gathered by drawing up the family tree or lineage. The physical and dysmorphologicalexamination must be ordered, completed and detailed, and measurements of the somatometric parameters required to demonstrateand quantify the existence of an anomaly in any anatomical structure will also have to be made. Photos of the patient are a greataid because they allow comparison with recognisable dysmorphic syndromes. The last phase involves requesting complementarystudies, including consultations with other specialists. The confirmation or exclusion of MR usually results from biochemicalmetabolic,cytogenetic or molecular studies. Conclusions. In cases of MRGO a good patient record accompanied by a thoroughphysical and dysmorphological study allow the clinical geneticist to orientate the diagnosis in the right direction and to requestthe specific genetic laboratory tests to confirm (or reject) its causation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Fuentes, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. El retraso mental (RM) afectaaproximadamente al 2-3% de la población general. De las causasde RM conocidas, alrededor del 75% se consideran de base genética.El objetivo de este trabajo es exponer un modelo estandarizadode aproximación diagnóstica al paciente con retraso mental de origengenético (RMOG). Desarrollo. El especialista clínico deberárealizar una anamnesis detallada y una exploración física dismorfológicacompleta que le permitan obtener un diagnóstico diferencialrazonable. El siguiente paso será solicitar los estudios complementariosnecesarios para confirmar o descartar la sospecha diagnósticacorrespondiente. Deberá obtenerse información precisa sobrelos antecedentes personales, prenatales (embarazo), perinatales(parto). La historia posnatal también proporcionará informaciónclínica relevante. La historia familiar es un apartado fundamentalen cualquier enfermedad genética y debe recogerse en elcorrespondiente árbol familiar o pedigrí. La exploración física ydismorfológica debe también ordenarse, completarse y detallarse,y obtener las mediciones de parámetros somatométricos necesariaspara demostrar y cuantificar la existencia de una anomalía en cualquierestructura anatómica. La toma de fotografías del paciente esde gran ayuda para la comparación con síndromes dismórficos reconocibles.En la última fase se solicitarán los estudios complementarios,con inclusión de las interconsultas con otros especialistas.La confirmación o exclusión de RM suele proceder de estudiosbioquimicometabólicos, citogenéticos o moleculares. Conclusión.En los casos de RMOG, una buena historia clínica acompañada deuna exploración física y dismorfológica completa permiten al genetistaclínico orientar adecuadamente el diagnóstico y solicitarlos estudios genéticos de laboratorio específicos para confirmar (odescartar) su etiología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(supl.1): s93-s98, ene. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y diagnóstico del paciente con retraso mental de origen genético: protocolos estandarizados de evaluación clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
