<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047461</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between creativity and mental illness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relationship between genius and madness has attracted attention through the centuries. These concepts have been replaced by those of creativity and mental illness, remaining the interest in the subject. This article presents a revision of the current literature on the topic grouped in three sections: 1. Biographcial studies that conclude higher frequency of mental illness among creators, especially affective disorders; 2. Studies in living artist focused especially in writers and that confirm discoveries of biographical studies; 3. Studies of creativity in mentally ill patients that show great diversity in methodology and results, pointing to greater creativity in subjects with mild affective disorders (mainly bipolar) and their relatives. As a conclusion of the revision, it is appreciated strong evidence of the relationship between creativity and mental illness, although it is not still elucidated the nature of this relationship and the work focused in other creative areas different from literature are scarce</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Bravo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Calvete, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La relación entre genio y locura ha atraído la atención a través de los siglos. Sustituidos estos términos por los de creatividad y enfermedad mental, se ha mantenido el interés por el tema. En el presente artículo se realiza una revisión de la bibliografía existente agrupada en tres apartados: 1. Estudios biográficos, que evidencian mayor frecuencia de enfermedades mentales, especialmente trastornos afectivos, entre creadores; 2. Estudios sobre artistas vivos, especialmente sobre escritores y que confirman los hallazgos de los estudios biográficos; 3. Estudios de creatividad en pacientes con enfermedades psiquiátricas, con gran diversidad en su metodología y resultados, apuntando a mayor creatividad en sujetos con trastornos afectivos (especialmente bipolares) leves y sus familiares. Como conclusión, se aprecian fuertes evidencias sugerentes de la relación entre creatividad y enfermedad mental, aunque queda por dilucidar la naturaleza de dicha relación y escasean los trabajos centrados en otras áreas creativas diferentes de la literatura</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;22(3): 120-132, mayo-jun.2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre creatividad y enfermedad mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23291^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
