<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90979</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric and behavioral aspects ofcCardiovascular disease: epidemiology, mechanisms, and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychosocial and behavioral factors, including mood (depression, anxiety, anger, and stress), personality (Type A, Type D, and hostility), and social support, are associated with both the development and progression of cardiovascular disease. &#147;Negative&#148; emotions have been associated with increased rates of cardiovascular death and recurrent cardiac events, although the mechanisms responsible for this association remain unclear. A number of pathophysiological mechanisms have been proposed to explain these relationships, including hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis dysregulation, platelet activation, and inflammation. Behavioral factors also have been implicated, such as nonadherence to prescribed medical therapies and physical inactivity. Several randomized trials of patients with cardiovascular disease have examined the impact of pharmacologic and behavioral treatments on hard cardiovascular disease events as well as on cardiovascular disease biomarkers of risk. Although psychological treatments generally have been shown to improve quality of life and psychological functioning among cardiac patients, the benefit of psychological interventions with respect to improving clinical outcomes has not been conclusively demonstrated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Smith, Patrick J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blumenthal, James A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los factores psicosociales y conductuales, incluido el estado de ánimo (depresión, ansiedad, enojo y estrés), la personalidad (Tipo A, Tipo D y hostilidad) y el apoyo social se asocian tanto al desarrollo como a la progresión de enfermedad cardiovascular. Las emociones «negativas» se han asociado a un aumento de las tasas de muerte cardiovascular y a eventos cardiacos recurrentes, aunque continúan sin estar claros los mecanismos que explican esta asociación. Se han propuesto diversos mecanismos fisiopatológicos para explicar estas relaciones, como la alteración de la regulación del eje hipotálamo-hipófiso-suprarrenal, la activación plaquetaria y la inflamación. Se han involucrado también factores conductuales, como la falta de adherencia a los tratamientos médicos prescritos y la inactividad física. En varios ensayos aleatorizados llevados a cabo en pacientes con enfermedad cardiovascular, se ha examinado el impacto de los tratamientos farmacológicos y conductuales en las variables «duras» de eventos cardiovasculares y en los biomarcadores del riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular. Aunque en general se ha observado que los tratamientos psicológicos mejoran la calidad de vida y la función psicológica en los pacientes cardiacos, el efecto beneficioso de las intervenciones psicológicas en cuanto a la mejora de los resultados clínicos no se ha demostrado de manera concluyente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(10): 924-933, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos psiquiátricos y conductuales de la enfermedad cardiovascular: epidemiología, mecanismos y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
