<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164361</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship of transformational leadership style with employee health and well-being: the mediating role of trust in the leader</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examined the relationship between transformational leadership and employee well-being indicators in developing countries, as well as the mediation role of trust in the leader. Five hundred ninetyseven employees of Colombian and Mexican organizations answered a questionnaire. Results indicated that transformational leadership relates positively with job satisfaction and negatively with distress symptomatology. No relationship was established between transformational leadership and psychological well-being. Trust in the leader mediated totally the relationship between transformational leadership and job satisfaction and symptoms of distress. These results confirm the previously described relationship between transformational leadership, less distress, and higher job satisfaction. However, it suggests too that the possible effect of transformational leadership on employees health and well-being would be limited to promoting affective aspects of well-being, but not psychological well-being. This result invites to a thorough review of the meaning and use of the concepts affective and psychological well-being and the differences between them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ortiz, Viviola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esperanza Perilla-Toro, Lyria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analizó la relación entre liderazgo transformacional e indicadores de bienestar y malestar de empleados de países en desarrollo, así como la mediación de la confianza en el líder. Quinientos noventa y siete empleados de organizaciones colombianas y mexicanas respondieron un cuestionario. Los resultados indicaron que el liderazgo transformacional se relaciona de forma positiva con la satisfacción laboral y de forma negativa con los síntomas de malestar y que estas relaciones están mediadas totalmente por la confianza en el líder; no se encontró relación entre el liderazgo transformacional y el bienestar psicológico. Estos resultados confirman la relación, descrita en estudios previos, entre liderazgo transformacional, menor malestar psicológico y mayor satisfacción laboral; sin embargo, sugieren que el efecto del liderazgo transformacional sobre la salud y el bienestar del empleado se limitaría a promover aspectos afectivos del bienestar, pero no del bienestar psicológico. Este resultado invita a una revisión profunda del significado de los conceptos bienestar afectivo y psicológico y las diferencias entre ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);33(2): 95-108, ago. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164361</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación del estilo de liderazgo transformacional con la salud y el bienestar del empleado: el rol mediador de la confianza en el líder</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
