<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115099</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SER Consensus statement on the use of biologic therapy for systemic lupus erythematosus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To provide a reference to rheumatologists and other physicians involved in the treatment of systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) who are using, or about to use biologic therapies. Methods: Recommendations were developed following a nominal group methodology and based on systematic reviews. The level of evidence and degree of recommendation were classified according to a model proposed by the Center for Evidence Based Medicine at Oxford. The level of agreement was established through a Delphi technique. Results: We have produced recommendations on the use of belimumab, the only biological agent with approved indications for SLE, and other biological agents without an indication for SLE. The objective of treatment is to achieve a complete clinical response, taken as the absence of perceived or evident disease activity. Nuances regarding the use of biologic therapies in SLE were reviewed as well, such as the evaluation that should be performed prior to administration and the follow up of patients undergoing these therapies. Conclusions: We present the SER recommendations for the use of biological therapies in patients with SLE(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Taboada, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Fernández, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Alén, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Úcar-Angulo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pego-Reigosa, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivé, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva-Fernández, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Elaborar unas recomendaciones que sirvan de referencia a los reumatólogos y otros profesionales implicados en el tratamiento del lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) que vayan a utilizar o consideren la utilización de terapias biológicas en su manejo. Métodos: Las recomendaciones se emitieron siguiendo la metodología de grupos nominales y basadas en revisiones sistemáticas. El nivel de evidencia y el grado de recomendación se clasificaron según el modelo del Center for Evidence Based Medicine de Oxford y el grado de acuerdo se extrajo por técnica Delphi. Resultados: Se realizan recomendaciones sobre el uso de belimumab, actualmente única terapia biológica con aprobación para el tratamiento del LES, y otras terapias biológicas sin indicación aprobada en LES. El objetivo del tratamiento es la respuesta clínica completa, entendida como la ausencia de actividad clínica percibida o constatable. Se matiza el uso de terapias biológicas en LES y cuál debe ser la evaluación previa y la vigilancia del paciente que recibe estos fármacos. Conclusiones: Se presentan las recomendaciones SER sobre el uso de terapias biológicas en el LES(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);9(5): 281-296, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología sobre el uso de terapias biológicas en el lupus eritematoso sistémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25575^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
