<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039038</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of arrival time in vehicle and video</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The equivalence of arrival-time estimations performed in vehicle and using video images was studied. The design consisted in 2 Sexes x (2 Tests x 4 Speeds x 4 Distances). The participants, 20 men and 20 women, seated in the front passenger&#146;s seat of an automobile and temporarily deprived of sight, estimated the car&#146;s arrival time at targets. The times to be estimated were generated by varying 4 speeds by 4 distances. The same subjects estimated the same arrival times in a video, filmed from the same position and scenario. Findings indicated high equivalence of vehicle and video in experimental results (underestimation of time, increase of errors with the time to be estimated). However, when considered individual skills, both estimations had a moderate relationship (r= .52), which, for applied purposes, does not justify substituting estimation in vehicles with that performed using videos</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nunes, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recarte, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conchillo, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estudia la equivalencia entre las estimaciones de tiempo de llegada realizadas en un automóvil y las realizadas en imágenes de vídeo. Los participantes, 20 hombres y 20 mujeres, sentados en el asiento del acompañante de un automóvil y privados temporalmente de visión, estiman el tiempo de llegada del automóvil a unas dianas. Los tiempos se generan variando ortogonalmente 4 velocidades y 4 distancias. Los mismos sujetos estiman los mismos tiempos de llegada en un vídeo tomado desde esa misma posición y escenario. Los resultados indican una alta equivalencia entre ambos métodos en los resultados experimentales; sin embargo, consideradas como habilidades individuales, ambas estimaciones tienen una relación moderada (r= .52) que para propósitos aplicados no justifica la sustitución de la estimación en automóvil por la estimación en vídeo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 112-117, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039038</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación del tiempo de llegada en vehículo y vídeo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
