<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-10588</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical education on alcohol: the way ahead</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study is to review the current situation of medical education in Europe and to present some proposals for the future. With this aim, a thorough bibliographic review has been performed and several professionals and European universities have been contacted. The collected information shows that medical education on alcohol is still a pending subject in Europe. A basic training plan should cover the 3 levels of the medical career. Key components (knowledge, skills and attitudes) and training strategies, mainly aimed at GPs and focussed on early identification and brief intervention are described. Training objectives are: to know the facts, to identify alcohol problems, to distinguish whose patients may benefit from a brief intervention and to develop skills to apply it. Final goal should be the development of a therapeutic commitment. Educational principles and models are suggested and experts are invited to advocate for a common model and to strive for a European training network (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar la situación actual de la formación médica en Europa y presentar algunas propuestas para el futuro. Para ello se realizó una amplia revisión bibliográfica y se contactó con profesionales y universidades de toda la región europea. De la información recogida, se desprende que la formación de los profesionales europeos todavía tiene muchas lagunas. Se propone un plan de formación básico destinado a cubrir los 3 niveles de la carrera médica y se sugieren componentes educativos clave (conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes) estrategias de formación básicas destinadas sobre todo a capacitar a los médicos de atención primaria para identificación precoz e intervención breve. Los objetivos del aprendizaje son: conocer los hechos, identificar los problemas de alcohol, distinguir a los pacientes que pueden beneficiarse de una intervención breve y adquirir habilidades para aplicarla. El objetivo final sería desarrollar un compromiso terapéutico. Se proponen principios y modelos educativos y se invita a los expertos a que aboguen por un modelo común e impulsen una red de formación europea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(1): 91-105, ene. 2002. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educación Médica sobre alcohol: perspectiva de futuro</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-10588</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3730</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5998</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5737</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1549</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35176</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
