<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111091</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Statistical analysis of ordinal scales. Field applications of Pediatrics and Child Health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Research in different areas of knowledge involves a large number of variables that can be evaluated with mono-variable and multi-variable techniques and parametric or nonparametric tests. The researcher decision depends on the validation of the assumptions inherent in each, the type of variables and sample sizes. We began with a systematic literature review, which included scientific articles that had as an instrument of data collection, a range of assessment/psychometrics in the health of children and youth. After the inclusion criteria were defined, 189 papers were selected and 127 articles were used for the exploratory analysis of research methodologies. The exploratory data analysis allowed us to identify the type of statistical techniques used by investigators when the instruments are composed of ordinal variables and analyze whether they met the assumptions inherent in the use of statistical techniques with this type of variables with small and large samples(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Curado, Mª Alice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitorino Teles, Júlia Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marôco, João</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación en diferentes áreas del conocimiento implica un gran número de variables que pueden ser evaluadas con técnicas univariantes y multivariantes y test paramétricos o no paramétricos. La decisión depende de la validación de los supuestos inherentes a cada uno, el tipo de variables y tamaño de la muestra. Comenzamos con una revisión sistemática de la literatura, que incluía artículos científicos cuyo instrumento de recolección de datos era una escala de evaluación/psicometría en el área de salud de niños y jóvenes. Definidos los criterios de inclusión, se seleccionaron 189 trabajos y 127 fueron sometidos a análisis exploratorio de las metodologías de investigación utilizadas. El análisis exploratorio de datos ha permitido identificar el tipo de técnicas estadísticas utilizadas por los investigadores cuando los instrumentos utilizados están compuestos de variables ordinales y analizar si se cumplían los supuestos inherentes al uso de las técnicas estadísticas con este tipo de variables, y con muestra de pequeñas o de gran tamaño(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(30): 434-445, abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis estadístico de escalas ordinales. Aplicaciones en el Área de Salud infantil y Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5204^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
