<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121828</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radical prostatectomy. Detailed surgical margins. Prognostic value of multifocal involvement in pT2(+)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We intend to analyze the prognostic value of positive surgical margins depending on their number and location in pT2 patients. METHODS: We analyze 448 (34.3%) patients with positive surgical margins from a series of 1,310 T1-T2 patients treated with radical prostatectomy between 1989-2012. Of them 164 are pT2(+). 119 (72.6%) have unifocal affectation (41 (34.5%) unifocal in right lobe; 35 (29.4%) unifocal in left lobe, 40 (33.6%) unifocal in apex, 3 (2.5%) unifocal proximal) and 45 (27.4%) multifocal involvement. RESULTS: Unifocal and multifocal pT2(+) patients have not evidenced significant differences in any of the clinicopathologic variables compared. However the BPFS at 5 and 10 years is significantly worse in the multifocal group, (p&lt;0.000). In the BPFS multivariate study of 164 pT2(+)influential variables are: multifocal involvement (HR: 3.4; 95%IC 1.7-6.9 p&lt;0.000) and PSA (HR: 1.03; 95%IC 1.02-1.05 p&lt;0.000), being PSA &gt;15 ng/ml (HR: 3.7; 95%IC 2.1-6.6 p&lt;0.000) the best cut-off point. Risk groups: Using the independent influence variables, the best model (using Cox models) includes two risk groups: Group 1 (0 variables): They are pT2(+) with unifocal affectation and PSA&lt;15 ng/ml, (63%). Their BPFS are 81±4% and 77±4% (5 and 10 years). Grupo 2 (1-2 variables): They are pT2(+) with multifocal involvement, PSA&gt;15 ng/ml or both of them, (37%). Their BPFS are 46±6% and 26±7% (5 and 10 years). The BPFS differs significantly between the two groups (p&lt;0.000). The Group 1 BPFS is similar to the pT2(-) patients, (p:0.242). The Group 2 BPFS is similar to the pT3(+) patients, (p:0.637). The model explained significantly better the BPFS than any of the individual variables analyzed. CONCLUSIONS: In pT2(+) patients the prognosis is significantly worse in multifocal involvement. In addition two groups of patients can be clearly distinguished from the BPFS point view according to their influential variables. The data suggest that since the prognostic point view the second group is understaged while the first is overstaged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diez-Caballero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hevia, Mateo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tienza, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, José Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, Imanol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velis, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algarra, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zudaire, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Pretendemos analizar en los pacientes pT2 con márgenes afectados el valor pronóstico real de los márgenes en función de su número y localización. MÉTODOS: Analizamos 448 (34,3%) pacientes con márgenes afectados de una serie de 1.310 pacientes T1-T2 tratados mediante prostatectomía radical entre 1.989-2.012. De ellos 164 son pT2(+), 119 (72,6%) tienen afectación unifocal 41 (34,5%) unifocal en lóbulo derecho; 35 (29,4%) unifocal en lóbulo izquierdo, 40 (33,6%) unifocal en ápex, 3 (2,5%) unifocal proximal) y 45 (27,4%) afectación multifocal. RESULTADOS: Los pT2(+) unifocales y multifocales no evidencian diferencias significativas en ninguna de las variables clínico-patológicas comparadas. Sin embargo la Supervivencia Libre de Progresión Bioquímica (SLPB) a 5 y 10 años es significativamente peor en el grupo multifocal, (p&lt;0,000). En el estudio multivariado son influyentes en la SLPB de los 164 pT2(+): afectación multifocal (HR: 3,4; IC 95% 1,7-6,9 p&lt;0,000) y PSA (HR: 1,03; IC 95% 1,02-1,05 p&lt;0,000) siendo el mejor punto de corte, PSA &gt;15 ng/ml (HR: 3,7; IC 95% 2,1-6,6 p&lt;0,000). Grupos de Riesgo: Utilizando las variables de influencia independiente el mejor modelo utilizando los modelos de Cox incluye dos grupos de riesgo: Grupo 1 (0 variables presentes): Son pT2(+) con afectación unifocal y PSA&lt;15 ng/ml, (63%). Su SLPB es 81±4% y 77±4% (5 y 10 años). Grupo 2 (1-2 variables presentes): Son pT2(+) con afectación multifocal, PSA&gt;15 ng/ml o ambas, (37% restante). Su SLPB es 46±6% y 26±7% (5 y 10 años). La SLPB es significativamente diferente entre ambos grupos (p&lt;0,000). La SLPB del Grupo 1 es similar a la de los pacientes pT2 márgenes (-), (p=0,242). La SLPB del Grupo 2 es similar a la de los pT3 márgenes (+), (p=0,637). El modelo explica significativamente mejor la SLPB que cualquiera de las variables analizadas individualmente (estudio multivariado, modelo de Cox). CONCLUSIONES: En los pT2(+) el pronóstico es significativamente peor cuando la afectación es multifocal. Además pueden diferenciarse claramente dos grupos de pacientes desde el punto de vista de la SLPB según sus variables influyentes. Los datos sugieren que desde el punto de vista del pronóstico el segundo grupo está infraestadiado mientras que el primero está sobreestadiado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(3): 249-258, abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prostatectomía radical. Margen quirúrgico pormenorizado. Valor pronóstico de la multifocalidad en pT2 con márgenes afectados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
