<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054473</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">contributions of neuroscience to the diagnosis and educational treatment of developmental dyslexia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To examine the advances made in the fields of cognitive psychology, neuroscience and education and how    they have contributed to each other. Development. The paper offers a review of the current models of dyslexia and analyses the    relation between these models and neuroimaging studies and educational intervention. The first model presented here is the    &#145;phonological deficit&#146; model, which is the most widely proven and accepted today. People with dyslexia have difficulty in    completing tasks that involve segmenting language at a phonological level. Neuroimaging studies also reveal the existence of    atypical brain activation in dyslexics while performing tasks that require phonological processing. Intervention programmes    of a phonological nature have proved to be effective on both a behavioural and a neurophysiological level. Given the    complexity of the reading process, further research is currently looking into other models. Although the &#145;temporal processing&#146;    deficit model is more controversial and not as widely accepted as the previous model, some reports provide both behavioural    and neurophysiological evidence for the existence of differences in the visual and auditory processing of dyslexic and control    subjects. Different educational approaches to put this temporal processing deficit to rights have been tested in dyslexic    children with successful outcomes. Finally, the present status between neuroscience and education in the area of reading    disorders is examined and future implications concerning the different approaches and methods used in current research are    analysed. Conclusions. Although we are still a long way from understanding the causes of reading deficiencies, collaboration    between neuroscience, psychology and education does help further our understanding of the psychology of reading, its    diagnosis and its intervention</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Escribano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Examinar las contribuciones y el avance entre psicología cognitiva, neurociencia y educación. Desarrollo.    Se presenta una revisión de los modelos actuales de dislexia y se analiza la relación de estos modelos con los estudios de    neuroimagen y de intervención educativa. El primer modelo presentado es el del &#145;déficit fonológico&#146;, que es el más ampliamente    demostrado y aceptado en la actualidad. Las personas con dislexia presentan dificultades en tareas que implican segmentación    fonológica del lenguaje. Los estudios de neuroimagen muestran, también, una activación cerebral atípica en disléxicos    durante tareas que requieren procesamiento fonológico. Los programas de intervención de tipo fonológico han mostrado    ser efectivos tanto en relación con la conducta como neurofisiológicamente. Dada la complejidad del proceso lector, se    investigan otros modelos en la actualidad. Aunque el modelo del déficit en el &#145;procesamiento temporal&#146; es más controvertido,    y no tan ampliamente aceptado, comparado con el modelo anterior, algunos trabajos muestran evidencia tanto conductual    como neurofisiológica de que existen diferencias en el procesamiento visual y auditivo entre sujetos disléxicos y controles.    Diferentes aproximaciones educativas para remediar este déficit de procesamiento temporal se han probado con éxito en    niños disléxicos. Finalmente se examina el estado actual entre neurociencia y educación en el área de las dificultades de lectura    y se analizan implicaciones futuras relacionadas con los diferentes enfoques y métodos utilizados en la investigación    actual. Conclusiones. A pesar de que todavía queda un largo camino para comprender las causas de los déficit lectores, la    colaboración entre la neurociencia, la psicología y la educación contribuye a una mejor comprensión de la psicología de la    lectura, de su diagnóstico y de su intervención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(3): 173-180, feb. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054473</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribuciones de la neurociencia al diagnóstico y tratamiento educativo de la dislexia del desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13452^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9144</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
