<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146151</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep quality, excessive daytime sleepiness and insomnia in Chilean paralympic athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the sleep takes part in diverse biological and physiological functions, associating his restriction, with minor performance in the sport, nevertheless the quantity and quality of sleep is not known in paralympic athletes. Objective: to determine the sleep quality, insomnia and excessive daytime sleepiness in Chilean paralympic athletes. Methods: descriptive transverse Study, the sample included 33 paralympic athletes (24.2% women), those who were practicing swimming, tennis of table, football 5, powerlifting and tennis chair. The studied variables measured up across two surveys of dream: the Questionnaire of Insomnia and the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. Results: the paralympic athletes sleep were 6.9 ± 1.4 hours, 27.7% presents daytime sleepiness, 69.6 % insomnia (Survey of insomnia =7), whereas 78.7 % exhibits a bad sleep quality. The age showed a positive correlation with latency to the sleep (r=0.417 *), the insomnia with latency to the sleep (r=0.462 **), the Pittsburg score was correlated negatively by the sleep duration (r =-0.323) and latency to the sleep is correlated positively by the Pittsburgh score (r=0.603 **). Conclusion: the chilean paralympic athletes, present a low sleep quality, insomnia and excessive daytime sleepiness, situation that might influence negatively the sports performance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moya Cantillana, Cristobal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Jofre, Patricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Valenzuela, Tomas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varas Standen, Camila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés-Badilla, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Robledo, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el sueño participa en diversas funciones biológicas y fisiológicas, asociando su restricción con menor rendimiento en el deporte; sin embargo, se desconoce la cantidad y calidad del sueño en deportistas paralímpicos. Objetivo: determinar la calidad del sueño, el insomnio y la somnolencia diurna en deportistas paralímpicos de elite chilenos. Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo transversal. La muestra incluyó 33 deportistas paralímpicos (24,2% mujeres), quienes practicaban natación, tenis de mesa, futbol 5, powerlifting y tenis silla. Las variables estudiadas se midieron a través de dos encuestas de sueño: el Cuestionario de Insomnio y el Índice de Calidad del Sueño de Pittsburgh. Resultados: los deportistas paralímpicos chilenos duermen 6,9 +- 1,4 horas, un 27,7% presenta somnolencia diurna excesiva y el 69,6% insomnio (Encuesta de insomnio &gt;=7), mientras que el 78,7% exhibe una mala calidad del sueño. La edad mostró una correlación positiva con latencia al sueño (r=0,417*), el insomnio con latencia al sueño (r=0,462**), el puntaje de Pittsburgh se correlacionó negativamente con la cantidad de sueño (r= -0,323) y latencia al sueño se correlaciona positivamente con el puntaje de Pittsburgh (r=0,603**). Conclusión: los deportistas paralímpicos chilenos presentan una baja calidad del sueño, insomnio y somnolencia diurna excesiva, situación que podría influir negativamente sobre el rendimiento deportivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2832-2837, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad del sueño, somnolencia e insomnio en deportistas paralímpicos de elite chilenos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
