<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165975</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exercise and Alzheimer's: the body as a whole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Alzheimer's disease has been studied from various areas of knowledge (biomarkers, brain structure, behavior, cognitive impairment). Our aim was to examine the effects of an exercises protocol developed using complexity theory concepts. Method. Exercise improves neuroplasticity (neuronal ability to change and adapt as a result of experience) through mental and physical skills linked to cognitive-associative brain circuits. Introducing controlled physical and cognitive stimuli, self-organization and connectivity among brain systems enhance. We used tasks with non-linear outputs (several solutions) and learning as order parameter. Tasks were performed simultaneously, at the edge of the error seeking self-organized criticality. Results. Screening tests data showed a reduction in cognitive impairment, which suggests a reduction disease progression, in terms of executive function. There was a marked improvement in the physical tests: 30seconds chair stand test (PRE: 8.78±3.46; POST: 9.44±3.68 repetitions) and foot up and go test (PRE: 11.95±5.19; POST: 11.69±4.43seconds). Conclusion. Results showed that patient's self-organization was increased; behaviors atrophied or inhibited reappeared. Using these controlled perturbations, Alzheimer's Disease patients were able to manifest improvements in both their mental and physical abilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quiroga Escudero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Manso, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmiento Montesdeoca, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Matoso, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Valdivielso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saá Guerra, Y de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Ruiz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín González, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La enfermedad de Alzheimer ha sido estudiada desde varias áreas del conocimiento (biomarcadores, estructura cerebral, conducta, discapacidad cognitiva). Nuestro objetivo ha sido examinar de un protocolo de ejercicio diseñado usando conceptos de la teoría de los sistemas complejos. Método. El ejercicio mejora la neuroplasticidad (habilidad neuronal para el cambio y adaptación como resultado de la experiencia) a través de las habilidades mentales y físicas vinculadas a los circuitos cerebrales cognitivo-asociativos. La inclusión de estímulos físicos y cognitivos controlados mejora la autoorganización y la conectividad entre los sistemas cerebrales. Hemos utilizado tareas con soluciones no lineales (varias soluciones) y hemos analizado el aprendizaje. Las tareas se realizaron simultáneamente en el límite del error buscando la autoorganización crítica. Resultados. El análisis de nuestros datos mostró una reducción del deterioro cognitivo, lo que sugiere un enlentecimiento de la progresión de la enfermedad, en términos de la función ejecutiva. Se constató una marcada mejoría en las pruebas físicas: Test de sentarse y levantarse durante 30&amp;#8242; (PRE: 8.78±3.46; POST: 9.44±3.68 repeticiones) y Test de levantarse y caminar (PRE: 11.95±5.19; POST: 11.69±4.43 segundos). Conclusión. Los resultados mostraron que la autoorganización del paciente mejoró y que reaparecieron conductas atrofiadas o inhibidas. Utilizando estos estímulos controlados, los pacientes con Alzheimer fueron capaces de manifestar mejoras en sus capacidades mentales y físicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;10(3): 120-124, sept. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165975</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ejercicio y enfermedad de Alzheimer: el cuerpo como un todo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
