<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166398</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing myocardial viability by myocardial perfusion gated SPECT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment of myocardial viability is an important part of the management of patients with coronary artery disease and ischemic ventricular dysfunction. Nuclear cardiology techniques play a vital role because they are reliable and readily available. The images of glucose metabolism provided by positron-emission tomography (PET) are regarded as a reference standard for all other imaging techniques. However, myocardial perfusion SPECT, using a thallium or technetium compound, is extremely effective in assessing myocardial viability. In addition, synchronizing image acquisition with the cardiac cycle (i.e., in gated SPECT) enables myocardial wall thickening and motion to be evaluated and ventricular volumes and ejection fractions to be calculated. The resulting information has a fundamental role to play in optimizing the evaluation of myocardial viability and in providing prognostic variables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albert-Bertran, Francesc Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castell-Conesa, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La valoración de la viabilidad miocárdica es un aspecto importante en el tratamiento de los pacientes con enfermedad coronaria y disfunción ventricular isquémica. Las técnicas de cardiología nuclear ocupan un lugar destacado por su fiabilidad y accesibilidad. Las imágenes de tomografía por emisión de positrones (PET) para analizar el metabolismo de la glucosa están consideradas como un referente para el resto de técnicas de imagen, pero la tomografía computarizada por emisión de fotón único (SPECT) de perfusión miocárdica, con la utilización de talio o compuestos tecneciados, es una herramienta muy efectiva para la valoración de la viabilidad. La adquisición de las imágenes sincronizadas con el ciclo cardíaco (gated-SPECT) permite, además, la valoración del engrosamiento y el desplazamiento del miocardio, el cálculo de volúmenes y la fracción de eyección ventricular. Toda esta información tiene una relevancia fundamental para mejorar la valoración de la viabilidad y aportar parámetros pronósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.B): 35b-48b, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la viabilidad miocárdica mediante gated-SPECT de perfusión miocárdica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12306^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
