<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114902</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The progression of liver fibrosis in prison inmates co-infected by HIV and HCV who started on boosted protease inhibitor therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyse the progression of liver fibrosis as measured by elastography and biochemical testing in prison inmates co-infected by HIV and HCVwho started on ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor (PI) therapy. Methods: A prospective, observational and multi-centre study. The progression of liver fibrosis as measured by transient elastography (FibroScan) and biochemical testing was monitored for 48 weeks in a Spanish prison population co-infected with HIV and HCV. Results: Of the 94 patients included, 54 (57.4%) were followed-up for 48 weeks. At week 48, no significant changes were seen in the grade of fibrosis measured using FibroScan (8.1 kPa vs. 8.3 kPa; p=0.20) or the Forns index (5.6 vs. 5.1; p=0.50), although significant changes were detected using the APRI (0.7 vs. 0.6; p=0.05) and the FIB-4 indexes (p= 0.02).When measurement was done compared to baseline fibrosis, it was seen that therapy reduced the percentage of patients with fibrosis &amp;#8805;3 but &lt;4 (50% vs. 15%; p=0.001), but no change was seen in those found to have grade 4 fibrosis at baseline (20.4% vs. 20.4%). Conclusion: The inmates co-infected with HIV and HCV who were started on antiretroviral therapy with the boosted protease inhibitor (PI) showed stasterilizationbilisation of the liver fibrosis as measured with FibroScan after one year of follow-up. Overall, the therapy improved fibrosis when measured using the APRI or FIB-4 indexes, but not when using the Forns index or elastography (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero Matías, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Ramírez, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Burgos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz de la Hoya Zamácola, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portilla Sogorb, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alía Alía, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la evolución de la fibrosis hepática medida por elastografía y pruebas bioquímicas en reclusos coinfectados por VIH y VHC que han iniciado tratamiento antirretroviral con lopinavir/ritonavir u otros inhibidores de la proteasa potenciados con ritonavir. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo, observacional y multicéntrico. Se comprobó durante 48 semanas la evolución de la fibrosis hepática medida mediante elastografía de transición (FibroScan) y pruebas bioquímicas en población penitenciaria española coinfectada por VIH y VHC. Resultados: De los 94 pacientes incluidos, 54 (57,4%) fueron seguidos durante 48 semanas. En la semana 48, no hubo cambios significativos en el grado de fibrosis medida mediante FibroScan (8,1 Kpa vs 8,3; p=0.20) o índice de FORNS (5,6 vs 5,1; p=0,50), aunque sí con el índice APRI (0.7 vs 0.6; p=0.05) y el índice FIB-4 (p=0,02). Cuando la medición se realizó en función del grado de fibrosis basal, se observó que el tratamiento redujo el porcentaje de pacientes con fibrosis basal de grado 3/4 (50% vs 15%; p=0,001), pero no hubo cambios en los que ya tenían basalmente grado 4 (20,4% vs 20,4%). Conclusión: Los reclusos coinfectados por VIH y VHC que inician tratamiento antirretroviral con lopinavir/ritonavir muestran una estabilización de la fibrosis hepática medida con FibroScan® tras un año de seguimiento. En conjunto, el tratamiento mejoró la fibrosis cuando la referencia de medición fue el índice APRI y el FIB-4, pero no con el índice FORNS o la elastografía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;15(2): 54-62, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la fibrosis hepática en reclusos coinfectados por VIH y VHC que inician tratamiento con inhibidores de la proteasa potenciados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52855^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32994^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52855^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52855^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28981^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54552^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11924^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
