<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142429</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postoperative anxiety in Day Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anxiety is an unpleasant mood including physiological, psychological and behavioral components. It has been shown that a good preoperative information decreases pre- and postoperative anxiety. We intend to verify the hypotheses are diverse and focus on socio-demographic factors patient environment, state of the same in the preoperative CMA aspects of information received in the preoperative and what influence they have in the immediate postoperative anxiety CMA. The results indicate that while 25 % showed anxiety in the immediate postoperative period, they present modal values (4) and lower average (5.22). 62.5 of foreign-born patients had an anxiety level equal to or higher than 4 while only 20.99 of the Spanish patients presented it. No significant differences were observed between sexes in those patients with anxiety, although women globally have an average value somewhat larger scale Goldberg. Although it has not obtained a significant relationship between the level of patient information and the value obtained in the scale of Goldberg, yes that is a trend to greater dispersion in the values of Scale Goldberg in patients who claim to have received a less information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Carrillo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle, M. Antònia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ansiedad es un estado anímico desagradable que incluye componentes fisiológicos, psíquicos y conductuales. Se ha demostrado que una buena información preoperatoria disminuye la ansiedad pre y postoperatoria. Las hipótesis que pretendemos verificar son diversas y se centran en los factores del entorno sociodemográfico del paciente, estado del mismo en el preoperatorio de CMA, aspectos relacionados con la información recibida en el preoperatorio y qué influencia tienen en la ansiedad en el postoperatorio inmediato de CMA. Los resultados indican que aunque un 25 % mostró ansiedad en el postoperatorio inmediato, estos presentan valores modales (4) y promedio bajos (5,22). Un 62,5 % de los pacientes de origen extranjero presentaron un nivel de ansiedad igual o superior a 4 mientras que solo el 20,99 % de los pacientes españoles lo presentaron. No se han observado diferencias significativas entre sexos en aquellos pacientes que presentaron ansiedad, a pesar de que globalmente las mujeres presentan un valor promedio de escala de Goldberg algo mayor. Aunque no se ha obtenido una relación significativa entre el nivel de información del paciente y el valor obtenido en la escala de Goldberg, sí que se observa una tendencia a una mayor dispersión en los valores de Escala de Goldberg en los pacientes que dicen haber recibido una menor información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;20(2): 69-73, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad en el postoperatorio de CMA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
