<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63993</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of the OTFC as analgesic, sedative and anxiolytic in patients who undergo diagnostic and therapeutic hysteroscopy. Methods: We carried out a prospective study in 40 patients who were programmed for diagnostic and therapeutic hysteroscopy. The inclusion&amp;#146;s criteria were: Patients with ASA I y II and who were nil by mouth for 8 hours. The exclusion&amp;#146;s criteria were: pregnancy and ASA &gt; 3. None of the patients consumed antidepressants and/or anxiolytics. The patients were divided en 2 groups. Group A (n =20), patients planned for undergo diagnostic hysteroscopy received OTFC 20 minutes before surgery. The doses administrated were 200 &amp;#956;g. In those patients in which the diagnostic procedure was converted to the therapeutic, and the doses were insufficient an other dose of 200 &amp;#956;g was given 30 minutes after the first one. Group B (n = 20), patients planned for therapeutic hysteroscopy received 400 &amp;#956;g, 20 minutes before the procedure. In those patients in which we consider that the initial dose was insufficient, we given them a second dose of 200 &amp;#956;g 30 minutes after the first one. It was studied: 1. Blood pressure, heart rate and oxygen saturation, every 10 minutes from the premedication up to the discharge. 2. Level of analgesia, sedation and anxiety from the premedication up to the discharge. 3. Times between premedication up to the discharge. 4. Side effects. 5. Satisfaction of the patients: bad, regular, good and excellent. To evaluate the pain, we used a scale from 1 to 5. To evaluate the level of sedation, we used the scale of Ramsay from 1 to 6. To evaluate the grade of anxiety we used the Spilberger State-Trait Inventory sort form. Results: The blood pressure, heart rate and pulse oxymetry were constant in both groups from from the premedication up to the discharge. The level of analgesia, the grade of sedation and anxiety in both groups were satisfactory. The average of OTFC used was 210 &amp;#956;g and 434.78 &amp;#956;g in the group A and B respectively. Times between the premedication up to the discharge were: A 1.8 ± 0.7 h. y B 2.6 ± 1 1 h. 99.3% of the patients found OTFC excellent. Conclusions: This study demonstrates that the OTFC is an effective anxiolytic in patients who undergo diagnostic and therapeutic hysteroscopy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánovas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEl objetivo de este estudio fue valorar la eficacia del fentanilotransmucosa oral como analgésico, sedante y ansiolítico en pacientes sometidas a histeroscopia diagnóstica y terapéutica.MétodosSe estudiaron 40 pacientes programadas para histeroscopiadiagnóstica y/o terapéutica. Los criterios de inclusión fueron:pacientes ASA I y II, con 8 h. de ayuno. Los criterios deexclusión fueron: embarazo y ASA &gt;=3. Ninguna de las pacientesestaba en tratamiento con antidepresivos y/o ansiolíticos.Se dividieron en 2 grupos: Grupo A (n=20), pacientesprogramas para histeroscopia diagnóstica, que recibieron 200 mg de CFOT 20 min. antes del procedimiento. A aquellas pacientesen las que el procedimiento diagnóstico se convertíaen terapéutico, o la dosis era insuficiente, se les administrabaotra dosis de 200 mg. Grupo B (n=20), pacientes programadaspara histeroscopia terapéutica, que recibieron 400 mg.A aquellas pacientes en las que se consideraba que la dosisinicial era insuficiente, se les administraba otra dosis de 200 mg. Se estudiaron: 1. Presión arterial (PA), Frecuencia Cardiaca(FC) y Saturación de O2 (Sat O2), cada 10 min. 2. Nivelde analgesia, sedación y grado de ansiedad, durante todoel proceso. Tiempo transcurrido desde la premedicación hastael alta. Efectos indeseables. Satisfacción del paciente. Parala valoración del dolor se utilizó una escala de 1 a 5. Parael nivel de sedación, se utilizó la escala de Ramsay de 1 a 6.Para el grado de ansiedad se utilizó Spielberger State-TraitAnxiety Inventory Short Form. Resultados: La PA, FC y SatO2, se mantuvo estable en todas las pacientes desde la premedicaciónhasta el alta. El nivel medio de analgesia, el gradode sedación y de ansiedad fue satisfactorio durante todo elestudio. La dosis de CFOT consumido A: 210 mg y B 434.78mg y los tiempos premedicación - alta fueron: A 1.8 ± 0.7 h.y B 2.6 ± 1 1 h.La satisfacción fue buena/excelente en el 99.3% de loscasos. Conclusiones: este estudio demostró que el CFOT esun buen analgésico, ansiolítico y sedante en histeroscopias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;13(8): 533-537, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63993</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d286</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
