<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121928</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trapping of the fetal head in a septate uterus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Septate uterus, which occurs in approximately 1% of fertile women, is considered the most common uterine anomaly but is associated with the poorest reproductive results. Uterine anomalies are especially associated with difficulty in maintaining a pregnancy to full term, often leading to late miscarriage or preterm delivery. We present a case of fetal microcephaly in a woman with septate uterus as a consequence of trapping of the fetal head between the septum and one of the uterine walls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno García, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Alonso, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ostos Reyes, Florentina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Muñoz, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fischer Suárez, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiol Ruiz, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El útero septo, presente en el 1% de la población en edad fértil, es la malformación uterina más frecuente, pero también la que da lugar a peores resultados reproductivos. La afección obstétrica que con más frecuencia se asocia a esta anomalía mülleriana es aquella relacionada con el mantenimiento de la gestación, como son los abortos tardíos o el parto pretérmino. Presentamos el caso de una paciente en la que la existencia de un septo en la cavidad uterina dio lugar a una microcefalia fetal como consecuencia del atrapamiento de la cabeza fetal entre el septo y una de las paredes uterinas. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(5): 208-211, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atrapamiento de cabeza fetal en útero septo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9020^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9020^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9287^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52656^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9287^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
