<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-1426</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The usefulness of craniocorpography in diagnosing patients with dizziness and increasing muscle tension in the neck</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">By the moment, craniocorpographic record of the Romberg test has been scarcely used in clinical practice. Since craniocorpography is a method for recording oscillations of the head and shoulders, it can show characteristic patterns in patients with vertigo caused by increased muscle tension in the neck. In order to confirm this hypothesis, a prospective comparative study was performed with 329 patients. They were included in three different groups: patients with cervical vertigo, patients with vestibular pathology and a healthy control group. Movements of the head (with static shoulders) are more usual in patients with cervical vertigo (67%) than in those with vestibular pathology (27%) and healthy subjects (31%). With regard to the kind of head oscillations, front-back flexions and oscillations in all directions were the most frequent (36% and 34%, respectively). Nevertheless, the only movements previously reported (cervical rotation or torsion) only were 3% of total head movements in our study. We concluded that static craniocorpography is an useful method in diagnosing vertigo secondary to increased muscle tension in the neck (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El registro craneocorpográfico del test de Romberg apenas ha sido utilizado en la clínica hasta el momento. Puesto que registra los movimientos de la cabeza y de los hombros, puede presentar patrones característicos en pacientes con vértigo secundario a contractura de la musculatura cervical. Para tratar de confirmar esta hipótesis, se ha realizado un estudio prospectivo comparativo con un total de 329 sujetos, divididos en tres grupos: pacientes con vértigo cervical, con patología vestibular y un grupo control de personas normales. La presencia de desplazamientos cefálicos (movimientos de la cabeza, con hombros quietos) es más frecuente en los pacientes con vértigo cervical (67 por ciento) que en los afectados de patología vestibular (27 por ciento) y en los sujetos normales (31 por ciento). En cuanto al tipo de desplazamiento cefálico, los más frecuentes son las flexiones antero-posteriores (36 por ciento) y la oscilación en todos los planos (34 por ciento), mientras que los únicos movimientos de este tipo descritos previamente (la rotación o torsión cervical) no representan en nuestro estudio más que un 3 por ciento de los desplazamientos cefálicos. Concluimos que la craneocorpografía estática es una técnica útil como apoyo en el diagnóstico de los pacientes con vértigo secundario a contractura cervical muscular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;52(5): 398-403, jun. 2001. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La utilidad de la craneocorpografía en el diagnóstico de pacientes con alteraciones del equilibrio asociadas a contracturas de la musculatura cervical</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vaamonde Lago, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labella Caballero, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Varela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-1426</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9525^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6408^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9261^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9309^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
