<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120376</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association of consumption of carbonated beverages and decalcification in woman on reproductive and non-reproductive age of mexico city</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: There is not enough information about carbonated beverages (CB) consumption in Mexican women and its association with bone mineral density (BMD). The objective was to identify the association of CB consumption with BMD in two groups of Mexican women. Methods: Transversal study with 328 women in reproductive age (WRA) and not reproductive (WNRA) with diet and anthropometric evaluation and BMD. Results: Mean age of 18.7 years in WRA and 47 in WNRA. Energy adequacy percentage was lower in WNRA (98 ± 28% vs 144 ± 55) (p = 0.001), calcium intake was &lt; 700 mg/day in women with osteopenia of both groups and median consumption of CB was higher in WRA, with 200 mL/day (0-462) vs 0 (0-250) in WNRA (p = 0.001), WRA with osteopenia drank 500 mL/day (253-750) of CB vs 100 (0-200) in who had not (p = 0.001). Anthropometric parameters were higher in WNRA (p &lt; 0.002) and femoral neck BMD was lower (1.031 ± 0.14 vs 1.107 ± 0.10) (p = 0.001) and higher in L2-L4 (1.114 ± 0.13 vs 1.003 ± 0.09) (p = 0.001) in WRA. Variables associated with risk of osteopenia: drink CB (OR 11.186, p = 0.001), consuming &lt; 700 mg of calcium (OR 5.774, p = 0.001) and dinner no milk (OR 1.942, p = 0.042). Conclusions: To drink CB increases risk of osteopenia in both groups, WRA drink more CB than WNRA and they will have high probability of fractures younger (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Bertha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Flores, Mayra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ventura, Ana Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramirez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rojano, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godínez Martínez, Estela Ytelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Bernarda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sámano, Reyna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: No hay información suficiente sobre el consumo de bebidas carbonatadas (BC) y su asociación con la densidad mineral ósea (DMO) en mexicanas. El objetivo fue identificar la asociación del consumo de BC con la DMO en dos grupos de mujeres mexicanas. Métodos: Estudio transversal con 328 mujeres en edad reproductiva (MER) y no reproductiva (MENR), con evaluación dietética, antropométrica y DMO. Resultados: Edad promedio de 18,7 años en MER y 47 años en MENR. El porcentaje de adecuación del consumo de energía fue inferior en MENR (98 ± 28% vs 144 ± 55) (p = 0,001), el consumo de calcio fue &lt; 700 mg/día en mujeres con osteopenia de ambos grupos y la mediana del consumo de BC fue mayor en MER, con 200 mL/día (0462) vs 0 (0-250) en MENR (p = 0,001), las MER con osteopenia bebían 500 mL/día (253-750 mL/día) de BC/día vs 100 (0-200 mL/día) en las que no la presentaron (p = 0,001). Los parámetros antropométricos fueron superiores en MENR (p &lt; 0.002) y la DMO en cuello de fémur fue inferior 1,031 ± 0,14 vs 1,107 ± 0,10 (p = 0,001), en MER fue mayor en L2-L4: 1,114 ± 0,13 vs 1,003 ± 0,09 (p = 0,001). Variables asociadas al riesgo de osteopenia: beber BC (OR 11,186; p = 0,001), consumir &lt; 700 mg de calcio (OR 5,774; p = 0,001) y no cenar leche (OR 1,942; p = 0,042). Conclusiones: Beber BC aumenta el riesgo de osteopenia en ambos grupos, las MER consumen más BC que las MENR y tienen aún más probabilidad de fracturas a edades más tempranas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(5): 1750-1756, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación del consumo de bebidas carbonatadas y descalcificaciónen mujeres en edad reproductiva y no reproductiva de la Ciudad de México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2292^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2293^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3666^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54019^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
