<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048534</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trichinellosis: epidemiological, clinical and laboratory aspects. A retrospective study (1994-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Trichinellosis is a parasitic zoonosis caused by ingestion of infected meat containing cysts of Trichinella spp. Objectives. To analyze the epidemiological, clinical and laboratory findings of trichinellosis patients in our center and compare the results with those from published series. To analyze the relationship between the clinical symptoms and laboratory findings. Materials and methods. The clinical records of 127 patients were retrospectively analyzed. Results. Epidemiological: 61% were male and mean age was 32 years; 95% were associated with other cases. The food implicated was always pork. Clinical: 45% presented gastrointestinal symptoms and 98% systemic symptoms. Three patients required intensive care unit hospitalization and one died. In 53%, treatment consisted of associated antiparasitic and anti-inflammatory drugs. Laboratory: 59% presented leukocytosis and 72% absolute eosinophilia. Creatine phosphokinase was elevated in 62%, lactic dehydrogenase in 56% and glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (GOT) in 30%. Among 52 patients, 65% had positive serology; trichinoscopy of food samples was positive in three outbreaks. The population studied had a mean of 5 signs and/or symptoms. The patient group with more than 5 signs and/or symptoms presented higher white blood cell counts and GOT levels (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions. Our results were comparable to those of other series; however, there was a low rate of complications. An association was found between a larger number of signs and symptoms and higher leukocyte counts and GOT levels. The relevance of these findings should be assessed in future studies. There is no agreement as to the best therapeutic option, a fact reflected in the various treatment modalities seen in our study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ambrosioni, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biscione, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cecchini, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orduna, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellaro, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloveras, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La triquinosis es una zoonosis parasitaria que se adquiere por consumo de carne infectada con quistes de Trichinella spp. Objetivos. Analizar las características epidemiológicas, clínicas y de laboratorio de los pacientes asistidos en nuestro centro y comparar los resultados con otras series publicadas. Analizar la relación entre variables de laboratorio y clínicas. Materiales y métodos. Análisis retrospectivo que incluyó 127 pacientes durante el período 1994-2003. Resultados. Epidemiológicos: sexo masculino 61%, edad promedio de 32 años; 95% con casos acompañantes. El alimento implicado fue siempre la carne porcina. Clínicos: el 45% presentó síntomas gastrointestinales y el 98%, síntomas extragastrointestinales. En total de 3 pacientes requirieron asistencia en unidad de terapia intensiva y uno falleció. El 53% recibió asociación de tratamiento antiparasitario y antiinflamatorio. Laboratorio: presentó leucocitosis el 59% y eosinofilia absoluta el 72%. Presentó elevación de creatinfosfocinasa el 62%, de lactato deshidrogenasa el 56%, y de transaminasa glutamicooxalacética el 30%. De 52 pacientes, el 65% presentó serología positiva; el examen microscópico de la fuente alimentaria fue positivo en 3 brotes. La población estudiada presentó un promedio de 5 signos y/o síntomas. El grupo de pacientes con más de 5 signos y/o síntomas presentó valores más elevados de transaminasa glutamicooxalacética y leucocitos (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos fueron comparables a los de otras series; sin embargo, hubo un bajo porcentaje de complicaciones. Los pacientes plurisintomáticos tuvieron valores más elevados de transaminasa glutamicooxalacética y leucocitos, por lo que hay que analizar su significado en estudios futuros. Las distintas modalidades terapéuticas indicadas reflejan la falta de consenso sobre el tratamiento óptimo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(7): 440-444, ago. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Triquinosis: aspectos epidemiológicos, clínicos y de laboratorio. Estudio retrospectivo a 10 años (1994-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14632^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22835^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d981^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14631^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14632^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14632^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14631^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
