<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85496</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strategy for the prevention of adverse events in the hospitalized elderly patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are multiple and cumulative causes of functional declineamong hospitalized elderly patients Hospitalization itself mayfrequently cause a state of irreversible functional decline, leadingto complications not related to the initial reasons for the hospitaladmission. Moreover, this lower functional status may carry risksof adverse events, potentially reducing quality of life. Our generalgoal was to design a specific program to prevent adverse eventsrelating to hospitalized frail elderly patients. We determined intrinsicand extrinsic risk factors within our security strategies, includingactions to minimize or even mitigate adverse events accordingto a pre-established risk priority. Evaluations wereperformed over 3 consecutive days during 3 different months.Subjects of this prospective study were 133 hospitalized patients80 years old or older, representing 20% of the patients in ourcenter during the time of research. The outcome of our study is avaluation of the adverse events affecting hospitalized elderly patients,allowing the development of a plan for risk prevention,which includes specific care measures for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintela Porro, Vallea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Mella, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Vila, Alejandraa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez de Salamanca, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezpeleta Sáenz de Urturi, Estíbaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Barbosa, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hospitalización deriva frecuentemente en una declinaciónirreversible del estado funcional, pudiendo darcomo resultado complicaciones no relacionadas con elproblema de admisión y producir una cascada de eventosadversos (EA) que pueden culminar con la disminuciónde la calidad de vida. Las causas en los pacientesmayores son múltiples y acumulativas. Nuestro objetivogeneral fue diseñar un programa específico para la prevenciónde eventos adversos relacionados con la hospitalizacióndel paciente anciano frágil, determinando paraello los factores de riesgo, tanto intrínsecos como extrínsecos,para establecer estrategias de seguridad que incluyanacciones que minimicen o eliminen los EA según laprioridad de riesgo establecida. Se trata de un estudioprospectivo de los pacientes ingresados en el hospitalque cumplen el criterio de edad mayor o igual a 80años. Las evaluaciones fueron realizadas durante 3 díasconsecutivos en 3 meses diferentes. La muestra totalanalizada fue de 133 pacientes, que representa el 20%de los pacientes ingresados en nuestro hospital duranteel período de estudio. Como resultado hemos obtenidouna valoración de los EA de la población anciana (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(3): 118-122, sep. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia para la prevención de eventos adversos en el anciano hospitalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
