<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168050</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience in real clinical practice with new direct acting antivirals in chronic hepatitis C</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: Inclusion of direct-acting antivirals into clinical practice in patients with chronic HCV (CHC) has been a milestone in medicine. Patients and methods: Analytical, prospective study, involving 126 patients with chronic HCV treated with direct-acting antivirals. Efficacy and safety of treatment and factors associated with failure treatment were evaluated. Results: Age 54±10. Male (70%). Cirrhosis (60%). Distribution according to genotypes: G1a (31%), G1b (42%); G3 (14%); G4 (13%). Child-Pugh B and C (n=15). Naïve (56%). SVR rate was (87.3%): Child-A (91%), Child-B (75%) and Child-C (60%). The best cure rates were achieved with a 3D/2D±ribavirin (SVR=97.4%;n=39) and sofosbuvir/ledipasvir±ribavirin (RVS=93.1%; n=29) combination. An SVR rate of &lt;90% was achieved with sofosbuvir+simeprevir±ribavirin (SVR=88%, n=25), simeprevir+daclatasvir±ribavirin 73%, n=15). The association of ribavirin to these last three therapeutic options (n=19) improved cure rates (SVR=94.7%, 18/19) compared to its absence (n=39;SVR=77%). Improvement in MELD (40%). Output transplant list (20%). Substitutions associated with resistors NS3: G1a (positions 80K; n=5); G1b and G4 (position 168 and 36; n=4), while for NS5a: G1a (position 30; n=2) and G1b and G3 (position 93; n=3). Variables associated with failure in multivariate analysis (p&lt;0.05): presence of ascites, G3 and ribavirin dosage&lt;600mg/day. Discussion: The presence of genotype 3, ascites or dosage of ribavirin&lt;600mg/day were associated with higher failure rates. The use of ribavirin&gt;600mg/day in cirrhotic G1 or G3, who will be treated with sofosbuvir+simeprevir or daclatasvir is recommended where no baseline resistance test is available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas Casafranca, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraver Zamora, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correia-Varela-Almeida, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello Fernández, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Macías, Fernando Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Lora, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Herrera, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: La inclusión en práctica real de los antivirales de acción directa en pacientes con hepatitis crónica por VHC ha supuesto un hito histórico en Medicina. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio analítico, prospectivo que incluyó 126 pacientes con hepatitis crónica por VHC tratados con antivirales de acción directa. Evaluamos la eficacia y seguridad del tratamiento y factores asociados a fracaso terapéutico. Resultados: Edad 54±10 años. Varón (70%). Cirrosis (60%). Distribución según genotipos: G1a (31%), G1b (42%); G3 (14%); G4 (13%). Child-Pugh B y C (n=15). Naïve (56%). Tasa RVS fue (87,3%): Child-A (91%), Child-B (75%) y Child-C (60%). Las mejores tasas de curación se alcanzaron con las combinaciones Combo 3D/2D±ribavirina (RVS=97,4%; n=39) y sofosbuvir/ledipasvir±ribavirina (RVS=93,1%; n=29). Tasas&lt;90% se registraron con: sofosbuvir+simeprevir±ribavirina (RVS=88%; n=25), simeprevir+daclatasvir±ribavirina (RVS=78%; n=18) y sofosbuvir+daclatasvir±ribavirina (RVS=73,3%; n=15). La adicción de ribavirina a estas 3 últimas opciones terapéuticas (n=19) mejoraba las tasas de curación (RVS=94,7%; 18/19) frente a su ausencia (n=39; RVS=77%). Mejoría MELD (40%). Salida lista trasplante (20%). Sustituciones asociadas a resistencias NS3: G1a (posiciones 80K; n=5); G1b y G4 (posición 168 y 36; n=4), mientras para NS5a: G1a (posición 30; n=2) y G1b y G3 (posición 93; n=3). Variables asociadas al fracaso en análisis multivariante (p&lt;0,05): presencia de ascitis, G3 y dosis de ribavirina&lt;600mg/día. Discusión: La presencia de genotipo 3, ascitis o dosis de ribavirina&lt;600mg/día se asoció a mayores tasas de fracasos. Sería recomendable el uso de ribavirina&amp;#8805;600mg/día en cirróticos G1 o G3, que vayan a ser tratados con sofosbuvir+simeprevir o daclatasvir, si no hubiese disponibilidad de un test de resistencia basal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);149(9): 375-382, nov. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia en práctica clínica real con los nuevos antivirales de acción directa en hepatitis crónica C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30472</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
