<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154707</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of simple in the perception of the sports services through the generalizability theory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study uses the Generalizability Theory (GT) apply into the sport management area aiming to know the accurate sample size to evaluate the perceived quality. For this purpose, a compound structure was used for the participants (P) and items (I) aspects, with a fully crossed design. Applying general linear model (GLM), with both aspects, a variance analysis was realised and it estimated the generalization&#146;s precision. The instrument was a survey composed for 25 items and the sample, in total 330, comes from a fitness centre in the city of Malaga. The obtain results shows a number of participants using a reliable register (&amp;#958;&amp;#961;²(&amp;#948;) = 0.98), and it estimates the precision level in the generalization to the sample size used (generalizability coefficient, &amp;#958;&amp;#961;²(&amp;#916;) = 0.96), assuming in this side an important progress in relation to the efficiency in upcoming evaluations in sports services (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baena Arroyo, Manuel Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Villaseñor, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Oliver, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Ruiz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presente investigación utiliza la Teoría de la Generalizabilidad (TG) aplicada al ámbito de la gestión deportiva con el objetivo de conocer el tamaño muestral adecuado para la evaluación de la calidad percibida. Para ello, se utilizó una estructura compuesta por las facetas ítems (I) y participantes (P), con un diseño totalmente cruzado. Dentro del Modelo Lineal General (GLM), con estas dos facetas, se realizó un análisis de la varianza y se estimó la precisión de generalización. La herramienta empleada fue un cuestionario compuesto por 25 ítems y los participantes, un total de 330, pertenecían a una instalación deportiva de la ciudad de Málaga. Los resultados muestran que el número de participantes utilizado obtuvo un registro fiable (&amp;#958;&amp;#961;²(&amp;#948;) = 0.98), y permitió estimar el nivel de precisión en la generalización para el tamaño muestral empleado (coeficiente de generalizabilidad, &amp;#958;&amp;#961;²(&amp;#916;) = 0.96), suponiendo de esta manera un importante avance en cuanto a la eficiencia en futuras evaluaciones de servicios deportivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(supl.1): 65-68, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación muestral en la percepción de los servicios deportivos a través de la teoría de la generalizabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11773</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
