<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109731</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Presurgical endovascular treatment of symptomatic carotid stenosis caused by a meningioma of the planum sphenoidale</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Rodríguez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Valverde, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán-Romero, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Gómez, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduction. Cerebral infarction is a very rare presenting symptom of a meningioma. This form of clinical onset poses the challenge of treating ischaemic events before dealing with the tumour surgically. Case report. A 48-year-old woman from Georgia who visited due to loss of strength in the right-hand side of the body, intense headache and self-limiting episodes of forgetting her own language. Computerised axial tomography scans of her head revealed a left frontal expansive process and hypodense lesions in the left caudate nucleus. The patient underwent an unfavourable progression, with episodes of neurological deterioration and hemiparesis of the right-hand side and aphasia, which alternated with periods of improvement. Magnetic resonance imaging and an angiographic study revealed tumour occlusion of the left middle cerebral artery, secondary to a clinoidal meningioma. Treatment involved endovascular recanalisation of the middle cerebral artery and later surgical removal of the meningioma. Conclusions. Endovascular treatment by means of angioplasty, prior to the surgical excision of the tumour, is a technique that enables the incidence of ischaemic events to be diminished(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(3): 157-160, feb. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular prequirúrgico de la estenosis carotídea sintomática provocada por un meningioma del plano esfenoidal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13485^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13485^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
