<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052353</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric cataracts: epidemiology and diagnosis. Retrospective review of 79 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the epidemiology, diagnosis        and treatment features in a group of pediatric        patients with cataracts treated at our hospital. The        aim was to improve the visual prognosis in these        patients.        Methods: 79 children with cataracts were reviewed        retrospectively during an 18 year period (1986-        2004). This involved patients with congenital cataracts        and those who acquired them later. Most of the        latter group had a traumatic etiology (90%).        Results: The etiology of most cataracts was idiopathic        (68%) for the congenital group and traumatic        (90%) for the acquired group. Congenital cataracts        were frequently nuclear in type (31%) with        56% being bilateral. 27% of the congenital group        were associated with dysmorphic eye features, the        most frequent being microphthalmos. The most frequent        presenting feature was leucokoria, seen in        44% of patients. 75% of congenital cataracts were        diagnosed within one month of clinical manifestation.        58% of the congenital cataracts were treated        by surgery and 50% of these were performed within        one month of the diagnosis. 90% of the acquired cataracts were treated surgically, and 95% of these        were performed less than one month after diagnosis.        Conclusions: We attained a prompt diagnosis and        treatment in a high percentage of cases. Prompt        diagnosis and treatment will determine the visual        prognosis of these patients. We must continue        trying to shorten this period of time in order that all        children with this condition are diagnosed and treated        urgently and efficiently</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perucho-Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejada-Palacios, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De-la-Cruz-Bertolo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las características epidemiológicas,        diagnósticas y terapéuticas de un grupo de        cataratas de nuestro medio con el propósito de        mejorar el pronóstico visual de estos pacientes.        Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de 79 casos de        cataratas pediátricas durante un periodo de 18 años        (1986-2004). Hemos diferenciado dos grupos etiológicos        de trabajo: cataratas congénitas y cataratas        adquiridas.        Resultados: La causa más frecuente entre las congénitas        fue la idiopática (68%) y la más frecuente        de las adquiridas fue traumática (90%). La morfología        más frecuente de las congénitas fue la nuclear        0,31 (31%). El 56% de las cataratas congénitas fueron        bilaterales. El 27% de las cataratas congénitas        se asociaban a otras anomalías oculares y la más        frecuente fue el microftalmos. El signo clínico de        presentación más frecuente de las cataratas congénitas        fue la leucocoria, en 0,44 (44%). El 75%        (0,75) de las cataratas congénitas de nuestro medio        tardan menos de un mes en diagnosticarse desde la        manifestación clínica. El 58% (0,58) de las cataratas        congénitas se trataron con cirugía y el 50% de ellas tardaron menos de 1 mes en operarse. El 90%        (0,9) de las adquiridas se trataron con cirugía y el        95% de ellas tardaron menos de un mes en operarse.        Conclusiones: En nuestra serie conseguimos un        diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz en un alto porcentaje        de pacientes. El pronóstico visual de estos        niños viene determinado por la precocidad en el        diagnóstico y el tratamiento, es por ello que debemos        continuar intentando acortar este período de        tiempo y conseguir que todos los niños sean diagnosticados        y tratados precozmente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;82(1): 37-42, ene. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cataratas pediátricas: estudio epidemiológico y diagnóstico. Análisis retrospectivo de 79 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33371^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28171^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
