<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047818</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatrics and its subspecialties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatrics has evolved from a discipline focusedon fighting against traditional diseases leading tomorbidity and mortality in children into the currentPediatrics and his subspecialties. This change is coherentwith the consideration of the child as a wholeand with the biological, psychological and socialfoundations that characterize childhood and adolescence.From 1965 on, an apparently endless processto obtain the official recognition of &#147;Pediatric Subspecialties&#148;(Areas of Specific Skills) is being followed.Only two of the numerous proposal presented to theNational Council of Medical Specialties were informedfavorably (years 1989 and 2002). Nowadays,their development waits the application of the lawthat regulates the Health-related Professions, the firstlegislative document that explicitly acknowledges theexistence of Areas of Specific Skill. The study presentedhere analyzes the current status of &#147;Pediatricsand its Specialties&#148; in Spain from the historical,formative and legislative points of view</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Pediatría ha evolucionado desde la lucha frentea la morbimortalidad tradicional a la actual Pediatríay sus subespecialidades. Este cambio es coherentecon la visión integral del niño y con los fundamentosbiológicos, psicológicos y sociales que caracterizanniñez y adolescencia. Desde 1965 seguimosun proceso que parece no tener fin, para conseguirel reconocimiento oficial de las &#147;subespecialidadespediátricas&#148; (Áreas de capacitación Específica).De las numerosas propuestas presentadas enel Consejo Nacional de Especialidades Médicas solamentedos fueron informadas favorablemente(años 1989 y 2002). En el momento actual su desarrolloestá pendiente de la aplicación de la Ley deOrdenación de la Profesiones Sanitarias, primer documentolegislativo que recoge de forma explícita laexistencia de las Áreas de Capacitación Específica.En este trabajo se analiza, desde el punto de vistahistórico, formativo y legislativo, el estado actual de&#147;La Pediatría y sus Especialidades&#148; en España</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);26(6): 185-195, jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Pediatría y sus subespecialidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2608^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
