<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106226</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lipid profile and cardiovascular risk in anorexia nervosa; the effect of nutritional treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to explore the lipid profile in patients with anorexia nervosa (AN), and the changes with refeeding. Methods: The sample comprised 102 AN outpatients (mean age 22.32 ± 3.17). Blood tests, after 12-hour overnight fast, were performed before refeeding (M0) and after weight restoration (M1). Total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoproteins (HDL), low-density lipoproteins (LDL) and triglycerides (TRG) were determined and the following cardiovascular risk markers were calculated: LDL/HDL and TC/HDL ratios. These cut-off points were considered: TC &lt; 200 mg/dl; HDL &gt; 40 mg/dl; LDL &lt; 100 mg/dl and TRG &lt; 150 mg/dl. Results: The time leading to weight restoration was 8.16 ± 7.35 months. Considering patients with scores higher and lower than the corresponding cut-off points, X2-test revealed a significant difference (M0-M1) in case of TC (p &lt; 0.05) as well as between LDL/HDL0 and LDL/HDL1 (p &lt; 0.05) and between TC/HDL0 and TC/HDL1 (p &lt; 0.01). Significant differences were found between HDL0 and HDL1 (p &lt; 0.01) and between TRG0 and TRG1 (p &lt; 0.01). Significant and negative associations between BMI0 and TC0 (r = -0.331; p &lt; 0.05) and between TRG0 and HDL0 (r = -0.387; p &lt; 0.05) were found. The association between TRG1 and LDL1 was significant and positive. Discussion: Weight restoration tends to decrease the TC/HDL and LDL/HDL ratios despite a considerable percentage of patients maintain scores on the different variables of the lipid profile usually considered at risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Fernández, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolaños-Ríos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaúregui-Lobera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui-Garrido, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue explorar el perfil lipídico en pacientes con anorexia nerviosa (AN) y los cambios con la realimentación. Métodos: Se estudiaron 102 pacientes ambulatorios con AN (edad media de 22,32 ± 3,17). Se determinaron en sangre, tras de 12 horas en ayunas, antes de la realimentación (M0) y después de la recuperación del peso (M1), colesterol total (CT), lipoproteínas de alta densidad (HDL), lipoproteínas de baja densidad (LDL) y triglicéridos (TRG) y se calcularon los siguientes marcadores de riesgo cardiovascular: LDL/HDL y CT/HDL ratios. Se consideraron los siguientes puntos de corte: CT &lt; 200 mg/dl, HDL &gt; 40 mg/dl, LDL &lt;100 mg/dl y TRG &lt; 150 mg/dl. Resultados: El tiempo para la recuperación del peso fue de 8,16 ± 7,35 meses. Teniendo en cuenta los pacientes con puntuaciones superiores e inferiores a los correspondientes puntos de corte, el test de &amp;#935;2 reveló una diferencia significativa (M0-M1) en el caso de CT (p &lt; 0,05), así como entre LDL/HDL0 y LDL/HDL1 (p &lt; 0,05) y entre TC/HDL0 y TC/HDL1 (p &lt; 0,01). Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre el HDL0 y HDL1 (p &lt; 0,01) y entre TRG0 y TRG1 (p &lt; 0,01). Se obtuvieron asociaciones significativas y negativas entre BMI0 y CT0 (r = -0,331, p &lt; 0,05) y entre TRG0 y HDL0 (r = -0,387, p &lt; 0,05) se encontraron. La asociación entre TRG1 y LDL1 fue significativa y positiva.  Debate: La recuperación del peso tiende a disminuir los índices TC/HDL y LDL/HDL a pesar de que un considerable porcentaje de pacientes mantiene puntuaciones en las distintas variables del perfil lipídico generalmente consideradas de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(3): 908-913, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil lipídico y riesgo cardiovascular en anorexia nerviosa; efecto del tratamiento nutricional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53105^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
