<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113379</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A new self-report assessment measure of social phobia/anxiety in children: the Social Anxiety Questionnaire for Children (SAQ-C24)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Social phobia/anxiety is a topic that has received considerable attention in adults and, to a lesser extent, in children and adolescents. One of the more widely debated issues in this area of research involves the assessment of social phobia/anxiety with self-report measures. Prior research papers (Caballo et al., 2010, 2012) have developed and validated a psychometrically sound instrument for assessing social anxiety in adults. This paper is the culmination of several years of research aimed at developing a new self-report measure for the assessment of social anxiety in children between the ages of 9 and 15, namely, the &#147;Social Anxiety Questionnaire for Children&#148; (SAQ-C24). The final version of this instrument for children consists of 24 items and almost fully replicates the factor structure of the prior questionnaire for adults, providing only one extra factor (six in total): 1) Speaking in public/Interactions with teachers, 2) Interactions with the opposite sex, 3) Criticism and embarrassment, 4) Assertive expression of annoyance or disgust, 5) Interactions with strangers, and 6) Performing in public. Furthermore, the questionnaire&#146;s other psychometric properties are reported, and the results are compared for girls and boys. This research appears to confirm the structure of social phobia/anxiety centered on five/six dimensions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ollendick, Thomas H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderero, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Isabel C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irurtia, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballo, Vicente E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ansiedad/fobia social constituye un tema de constante investigación en adultos y, en menor medida, en niños y adolescentes. Una de las áreas más controvertidas es el de la evaluación por medio de medidas de autoinforme. Trabajos previos (Caballo et al., 2010, 2012) han desarrollado y validado un sólido instrumento de evaluación para la ansiedad social en adultos. El presente trabajo culmina varios años de investigación dirigidos al desarrollo de un nueva medida de autoinforme para la evaluación de la ansiedad social en niños de 9 a 15 años, el &#147;Cuestionario de ansiedad social para niños&#148; (CASO-N24). La versión final de este instrumento para niños consta de 24 ítems y replica casi por completo la estructura factorial del cuestionario anterior para adultos, encontrando sólo un factor más (6 en total): 1) Interacción con el sexo opuesto, 2) Hablar en público/Interacción con profesores, 3) Quedar en evidencia/Hacer el ridículo, 4) Interacción con desconocidos, 5) Expresión de molestia, desagrado o enfado y 6) Actuar en público. Se presentan además otras propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario y se comparan los resultados obtenidos por niños y niñas en cada una de las dimensiones. El presente trabajo parece confirmar la estructura de la ansiedad/fobia social en torno a cinco/seis dimensiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(3): 485-503, sept.-dic. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/Un nueva medida de autoinforme para evaluar la ansiedad/fobia social en niños: el &#147;Cuestionario de ansiedad social para niños&#148; (CASO-N24)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
