<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81506</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To supervise to a group and to his work is one of the biggest responsibilities. The supervision, more that to inspect and to check is the acquisition of knowledge for the employment of the senses. It is necessary to observe the attention to the patient of individual and global form, to achieve it it will be necessary observe not only the physical accomplishment of the work, but also the manifestations of those aspects, abstract, that should include the emotions and the comprehension(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Díaz, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Nieva Lozano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Arteaga, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Supervisar a un grupo y su trabajo es una de las más grandes responsabilidades. La supervisión, más que inspeccionar y revisar, es la adquisición de conocimientos por el empleo de los sentidos. Es necesario observar la atención al paciente de forma individual y global; para lograrlo se necesitará observar no sólo la realización física del trabajo, sino también las manifestaciones de aquellos aspectos abstractos, que incluyan las emociones y la comprensión(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;10(2): 69-71, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81506</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia un nuevo modelo de gestión y supervisión en Urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
