<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164817</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Claims about the Nursing Staff submitted by the users of the Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to describe the characteristics of the claims by users of the Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra (CHN), regarding the Nursing staff at the centre.  Method: a descriptive longitudinal study of the requests received in writing at the Patient Care Unit of the CHN, regarding the Nursing staff of the centre, between January, 1st and December, 31st, 2013. Any explicit demand by a user seen at the CHN was considered a request (claim, complaint, objection, report or suggestion), when submitted in writing to the PCU of the centre. In order to collect this information, the variables of interest were implemented based on criteria by consensus: age and gender of the claimant, age and gender of the patient, and relationship existing between claimant and patient, reason for the claim, professional category involved, Nursing Unit subject to the claim, time to response, and outcome of the claim. Descriptive statistics were used for statistical analysis, using the version 19.0 of the SPSS program. Results: there were 289 requests: 32% of these were claims. Regarding the claimants, 74% were women, with 48 years as mean age. Regarding patients affected by the claims, 62% of them were women also, with 55 years as mean age. Regarding origin, 65% of the claims came from the Hospitalization Units.  The most frequent reasons for claims were: &#145;disagreement with patient&#146;s attention&#146; (23%) and &#145;dissatisfaction with care or techniques administered&#146; (20%). The professional category most frequently involved: nurses (30%) and nursing assistants (15%). Most frequent type of settlement: explanation and/or written apology (84%).Conclusions: claims regarding the Nursing staff can be associated with the time of exposure and contact between patients and professionals, and this reinforces the need perceived by other research studies in terms of encouraging communication skills and the ability to apologize. These will be typically solved with an explanation or written apology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Pérez, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín Rodríguez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir las características de las reclamaciones de los usuarios del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra (CHN), dirigidas al personal de Enfermería del centro. Método: estudio descriptivo longitudinal de los requerimientos recibidos por escrito en la Unidad de Atención al Paciente del CHN, dirigidos al personal de Enfermería del centro, entre el 1 de enero y el 31 de diciembre de 2013. Se consideró requerimiento (reclamación, queja, objeción, denuncia o sugerencia) a toda demanda explícita de un usuario atendido en el CHN, presentada por escrito en la UAP del centro. Para proceder a la extracción de la información se operativaron las variables de interés en función a criterios consensuados: edad y sexo del demandante, edad y sexo del paciente y relación establecida entre demandante y paciente, motivo de reclamación, categoría profesional implicada, unidad de Enfermería objeto de reclamación, tiempo de respuesta y resultado de la reclamación. Para el análisis estadístico se utilizó estadística descriptiva. Se usó el programa estadístico SPSS versión 19.0. Resultados: 289 requerimientos, el 32% fue una reclamación. 74% de las demandantes fue mujer. Edad media: 48 años. 62% de los pacientes afectados por las reclamaciones fue mujer también. Edad media: de 55 años. El 65% de las reclamaciones procedía de las unidades de hospitalización. Motivos de reclamación más frecuentes: &#145;desacuerdo con el trato&#146; (23%) y &#145;disconformidad con cuidados o técnicas administradas&#146; (20%). Categoría profesional implicada con mayor frecuencia: enfermeras (30%) y auxiliares de Enfermería (15%). Tipo de resolución más habitual: explicación y o petición de disculpas por escrito (84%). Conclusiones: las reclamaciones dirigidas al personal de Enfermería pueden tener relación con el tiempo de exposición y contacto entre pacientes y profesionales, y refuerzan la necesidad percibida por otros investigadores de fomentar el desarrollo de habilidades de comunicación y de saber pedir disculpas. Habitualmente se resuelven con una explicación o petición de disculpas por escrito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(6): 14-19, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reclamaciones dirigidas al Área de Enfermería de los usuarios del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7520^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17646^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9929^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
