<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164000</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meningioma during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a pregnant woman of 35 weeks of pregnancy who came to the emergency room with symptoms of disorientation, disconnection with the way and aphasia which, in the next minutes, continued with a tonic- clonic seizure and nistagmo. After the stabilization of the symptoms, we decided to do an urgent caesarean, having a male new born. Firstly, we thought about an eclampsia but the proteinuria was negative and, the cranial computarized tomography was informed about an extra axial left injury with mass effect over the adjacent parenchyma compatible with meningioma, because of that we rejected the diagnosis of eclampsia. In the puerperium, an elective craneotomy was done, because of the neurological stability of the patient. Brain tumors are very infrequent in pregnancy and the incidence of meningioma in pregnant women and not pregnant women is the same. However, nowadays, it is known that meningioma grow up during pregnancy because of the increase of the vascularization and the intracellular or extracellular edema that occurs during pregnancy and because of the expression, of such tumors, of progesterone receptors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Santana, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albi, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Segovia, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una gestante de 35 semanas que acudió al servicio de urgencias con un cuadro de desorientación, desconexión con el medio, disartria que en los siguientes minutos continuó con una crisis tónico clónica y nistagmo. Tras la estabilización del cuadro, se decidió realizar una cesárea urgente, obteniéndose un feto varón vivo y una craneotomía electiva posterior, dado a la estabilidad neurológica de la paciente. Inicialmente se pensó en una eclampsia, pero tras proteinuria negativa y una tomografía axial computarizada craneal que informó de lesión extra axial izquierda con efecto masa sobre el parénquima adyacente compatible con meningioma se descartó esta posibilidad. Los tumores cerebrales son muy infrecuentes en el embarazo y la incidencia de meningiomas en mujeres embarazadas y no embarazadas es la misma. No obstante, hoy en día se sabe que los meningiomas aumentan su tamaño durante la gestación por el aumento de la vascularización y edema intracelular o extracelular que ocurre durante la misma y por la expresión, de dichos tumores, de receptores de progesterona, sobre todo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(6): 420-425, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164000</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningioma durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28203^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
