<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043275</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Burnout Syndrome in Physiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Burnout Syndrome refers to a kind of occupational stress that can have psychosomatic, behavioural, emotional, familial, and social repercussions; it can also cause loss of effeciancy at work. The aim of this study is to determine the prevalence of Burnout syndrome in physiotherapists, who belong to Servicio Andaluz de Salud and redeem their professional activity in hospital and health centres from Granada (city). Material and methods: A cross-sectional study was designed in a sample of 46 physiotherapists, who were given the Maslach Burnout Inventory to measure the degree of Burnout syndrome. Results: The 37 % of the staff interviewed presented a high percentage in the degree of Burnout for the emotional exhaustion, the 17.40 % presented a high depersonalization, and 69.50 % presented a low personal execution. The Burnout Syndrome is in the 10.87 % of the staff. Conclusion: In general the prevalence of Burnout syndrome is relatively low in base to following criteria elevated emotional exhaustion, low personal execution and high depersonalization</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Claro, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Sánchez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Lorenzo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Morales, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Burnout es un tipo de estrés laboral que puede tener repercusiones psicosomáticas, conductuales, emocionales, familiares y sociales, que pueden ser motivo de bajo rendimiento laboral. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer la prevalencia del síndrome de Burnout en los Fisioterapeutas, pertenecientes al Servicio Andaluz de Salud, que desarrollan su actividad profesional en hospitales y centros de salud de Granada (capital). Material y métodos: Se diseñó un estudio observacional transversal sobre una muestra de 46 fisioterapeutas, a los que se les administró el Maslach Burnout Inventory para medir el grado de Síndrome de Burnout. Resultados: El 37 % de los encuestados presentó un porcentaje elevado en el grado de Burnout para el cansancio emocional, el 17,40 % presentó una alta despersonalización, y un 69,50 % presentó una baja realización personal. El Síndrome de Burnout se encuentra en el 10, 87 % (n = 5) de la muestra. Conclusiones: En general, la prevalencia del síndrome de Burnout es relativamente baja, en base al siguiente criterio: elevado agotamiento emocional, baja realización personal y alta despersonalización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(1): 17-22, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043275</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del Síndrome de Burnout en Fisioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
