<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166295</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute bacterial gastroenteritis: 729 cases recruited by a Primary Care national network</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the main clinical and epidemiological features of bacterial gastroenteritis in our environment. Patients and methods: An observational study of a Spanish population in 17 Autonomous Communities. Questionnaires of children with a stool positive culture to bacteria were collected over a one year period. A bivariate analysis was performed on the variables involved, as well as two multivariate models (for antibiotic treatment variables, and comparison Campylobacter/Salmonella). Results: A total of 729 bacterial gastroenteritis episodes were recorded in the 17 Spanish autonomous regions, of which 41.2% were girls and 58.8% boys. The median age was 3.41 years old (interquartile range 1.55 to 6.72). The bacteria isolated were 59.9% Campylobacter, 31.8% non-Typhi Salmonella, 2.7% Aeromonas, 2.4% Yersinia, and 1.5% had more than one strain. Most infections (70%) were direct contacts, and food poisoning was less probable (25.9%). Salmonella is significantly less frequent than Campylobacter in children under the age of 3 years (adjusted OR 0.61; 95%CI: 0.43 to 0.86; P=.005), and Campylobacter is more frequent in rural areas (adjusted OR 1.48; 95%CI: 1.07 to 2.07; P=.012). Antibiotic was prescribed in 33.2% of cases. There was a greater significant difference if stools contained blood or mucus (adjusted OR 1.53; 95% CI: 1.04 to 2.27; P = .031), if the symptoms lasted more than 7days (adjusted OR 2.81; 95% CI: 2.01 to 3.93; P &lt; .000), or if the child was admitted to hospital (adjusted OR 1.95; 95% CI: 1.08 to 3.52; P = .027). Conclusions: The aetiology of bacterial diarrhoea in paediatrics is typical of that of a developed country. The transmission mechanism is mainly direct, and more cases than appropriate are treated with antibiotics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Aurrecoechea, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Aguas, Guadalupe del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza Olcina, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rubio, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vera, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ventura, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual Gil, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las principales características clínicas y epidemiológicas de la gastroenteritis bacteriana pediátrica en nuestro medio. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional en el ámbito de la población española. Recogida de encuestas durante un año de niños con coprocultivo positivo a bacterias. Análisis bivariado y 2 modelos multivariantes (para las variables tratamiento antibiótico, y comparación Campylobacter/Salmonella). Resultados: Un total de 729 episodios de gastroenteritis bacteriana en las 17 comunidades autónomas (41,2% mujeres y 58,8% varones). La mediana de la edad fue 3,41 años (rango intercuartílico 1,55 a 6,72). El 59,9% de los aislamientos fueron Campylobacter, el 31,8% Salmonella no tifoidea, el 2,7% Aeromonas, el 2,5% Yersinia y más de un germen el 1,5%. La mayoría de contagios (70%) son directos, y la intoxicación alimentaria es más improbable (25,9%). Salmonella es significativamente menos frecuente que Campylobacter en menores de 3 años (OR ajustada: 0,61; IC95%: 0,43 a 0,86; p = 0,005), y Campylobacter es más habitual en el medio rural (OR ajustada 1,48; IC95%: 1,07 a 2,07; p = 0,012). Se indicó antibiótico en el 33,2% de los casos, significativamente más si hubo productos patológicos en heces (OR ajustada: 1,53; IC95%: 1,04 a 2,27; p=0,031), duró más de 7 días (OR ajustada: 2,81; IC95%: 2,01 a 3,93; p&lt;0,000), o se hospitalizó (OR ajustada: 1,95; IC95%: 1,08 a 3,52; p=0,027). Conclusiones: La etiología de la diarrea bacteriana pediátrica es la propia de un país desarrollado. El mecanismo de contagio es principalmente directo, y se tratan con antibióticos más casos de los que parecería recomendable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(3): 128-134, sept. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166295</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gastroenteritis aguda bacteriana: 729 casos reclutados por una red nacional de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
