<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98983</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Whiplash. Epidemiological characteristics of patients evaluated in the Assessment of Disability Unit of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Whiplash Syndrome (SLC) is a very common disease in primary care centers and in disability assessment units. Objetive:  To determine the epidemiological characteristics of patients with SLC that, despite having no relevant anatomical changes, have had an unfavorable development that requires the assessment of disability for work. Method: A descriptive study was carries out collecting data of all the patients evaluated in the Medical Unit of The National Institute of Social Security of Madrid in the period from January 1, 2006 to December31, 2010 with the diagnosis of SLC. In order to exclude the most severe cases we discarded those with relevant anatomical changes, those which had required surgery and those with moderate - severe impairment in the neurophysiologic study. In order to minimize the influence of other diseases, we also excluded patients with other important diagnoses from the point of view of disability assessment. We studied the variables age, gender, professional occupation, marital status, Social Security characteristics, common disease or labor disease, presence of anxiety-depressive symptoms and / or fibromyalgia. Result: The total number of patients studied was 203. In comparison with the general occupied population in our area with the same age range, we observed 15% more women (p = 0.015, prevalence ratio= 1.37), 23% more unmarried people (p &lt;0.001 and reason prevalence ratio 1.63), 8% less intellectual scientific occupations, 8% more unskilled workers, a higher frequency of patients with psychiatric and / or fibromyalgia and advanced middle age. Conclusion: Our results are similar to those reported in the literature for the overall SLC for the variables age, gender and the presence of psychological disorders. They also allow to make a hypothesis such as marital status and occupation may act as predictors of poor outcome for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regal Ramos, Raúl Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Latigazo cervical (SLC) es una patología muy frecuente en las consultas de Atención Primaria y también en las de los médicos evaluadores de discapacidades. Objetivo: Conocer las características epidemiológicas de los pacientes con SLC que, pese a no tener alteraciones anatómicas relevantes, han tenido una evolución tan desfavorable que acaban requiriendo la valoración de una incapacidad laboral Método: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo en el que se recogieron todos los pacientes evaluados en el Equipo de Valoración de Incapacidades (EVI) de la Dirección Provincial del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social de Madrid en el período comprendido entre el 1 de enero 2006 al 31 de diciembre de 2010 con el diagnóstico de SLC. Con el fin de excluir los casos más graves se descartaron aquellos con alteraciones anatómicas relevantes, los que habían requerido intervención quirúrgica y los que presentaban afectación moderada-severa en el estudio neurofisiológico. Con la finalidad de minimizar la influencia de otras patologías, se excluyeron también los pacientes que asociaban otros diagnósticos importantes desde el punto de vista de la valoración de incapacidades. Estudiamos las variables edad, sexo, ocupación profesional, estado civil, régimen de afiliación a la SS, contingencia común o laboral, presencia de clínica ansioso-depresiva y /o fibromialgia. Resultado: El total de pacientes estudiados fue de 203. Respecto a la población general ocupada de nuestro entorno con el mismo rango de edad, observamos un 15% más de mujeres (p: 0,015, razón de prevalencia =1,37), un 23% más de no casados (p &lt;; 0,001 y razón de prevalencia 1,63), un 8% menos de ocupaciones científico intelectuales, un 8% más de trabajadores no cualificados, una mayor frecuencia de pacientes con clínica psiquiátrica y/o fibromialgia y una edad media más avanzada. Conclusión: Nuestros resultados son similares a los recogidos en la bibliografía médica para el global de SLC respecto a las variables edad, sexo y la presencia de trastornos psicológicos. Además permiten lanzar la hipótesis de que el estado civil y la ocupación pueden comportarse como factores predictores de mala evolución de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;57(225): 348-360, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de latigazo cervical. Características epidemiológicas de los pacientes evaluados en la Unidad Médica de Valoración de Incapacidades de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15311^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
