<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84321</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peer attachment during adolescence and emerging adulthood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present research analyzes how peer attachment changes during adolescence and emerging adulthood. The influence of the early affective relationships established between adolescents and their parents and possible differences associated with sex are considered. Using a longitudinal methodology, a sample of 90 adolescents were interviewed at the age of 13, 15, 18 and 22. At the age of 13, they completed the Parental Bonding Instrument of Parker, Tuplin and Brown (1979), which evaluated the adolescents&#146; memories of their early attachment established with their parents. Also, they completed the Inventory of Peer Attachment of Armsden and Greenberg (1987). Adolescents completed again the last inventory at the age of 15, 18 and 22. Results show that peer attachment increases with time. At the same time, adolescents who remembered a high parental affect demonstrate higher scores in peer attachment than adolescents who remembered low parental affect. The most significant differences are found in early and middle adolescence. These results support the idea of the continuity between affective relations established in these periods of time. Moreover, maternal influence on peer attachment was higher than that of fathers. Related to sex differences, girls demonstrate higher scores in peer attachment compared to boys, although these differences decrease over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliva Delgado, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Queija, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Gallego, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio analiza la evolución del apego a los iguales en la adolescencia en función del sexo y del recuerdo de la relación afectiva establecida en la infancia con el padre y la madre. Utilizando una metodología longitudinal, se entrevistó a una muestra de 90 adolescentes cuan-do tenían 13, 15, 18 y 22 años. A los 13 años cumplimentaron el Parental Bonding Instrument de Parker, Tuplin y Brown (1979) que evalúa el recuerdo de la historia de apego, así como el cuestionario de apego al grupo de iguales de Armsden y Greenberg (1987), que también fue cumplimentado en las posteriores recogidas de datos. Los resultados mostraron un aumento en el apego a iguales asociado al paso del tiempo. Por otra parte, aquellos adolescentes que recordaban un alto afecto parental obtuvieron puntuaciones superiores en apego a iguales. Las diferencias más significativas se encontraron en la adolescencia inicial y media, apoyando así la continuidad entre relaciones afectivas en estos momentos temporales. Asimismo, la influencia materna en las relaciones de apego con los iguales resultó superior a la paterna. Por otra parte, las chicas obtuvieron mayores puntuaciones en apego a iguales que los chicos, aunque las diferencias se diluyeron a medida que aumentaba la edad de los sujetos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 155-163, ene.-abr. 2011. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apego a los iguales durante la adolescencia y la adultez emergente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37729^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
