<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84627</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incident of the backache in secondary education professors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The backache is one of the problems associate sanitary more pressing in the current world, which for years has centred the researcher&#146;s attention of the sanitary area, sociologists, statesmen &amp;mldr; The educational community is not sufficiently studied from the perspective of the impact of the vertebral pains. Probably for the already rejected belief that they are pathologies that only concern population groups with a great physical wear. It has been decided to approach the research from a qualitative methodology, being the type of used method the descriptive study. The study realizes on 66 subjects that they are educational in an Institute of Secondary Education. A questionnaire is delivered them by three differentiated well parts: demographic information, medical record and Index of Oswestry's disability. In the results there is obtained a high index of participation (71%), emphasizing that 68% of the subjects demonstrates to have or to have had backache. The attributed mainsprings are wrong positions and not physical activity. And the treatment was principally medical therapy. As for the most affected regions they are cervical and dorsal, and 64 % of the sample has 10 % in the Index of Oswestry's disability. One concludes that, to weighing the high incident of the backache between the professors, it is not a habitual motive of labour fall. There is demonstrated that though it is not a disease that proves very disability for the professors, that is very frequent that concerns some tasks recovered in day after day(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrera Picado, Jesús Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor de espalda es uno de los problemas sociosanitarios más acuciantes en el mundo actual y, desde hace años, ha centrado la atención de investigadores del ámbito sanitario, sociólogos, estadistas... La comunidad docente no está lo suficientemente estudiada desde la perspectiva del impacto de las algias vertebrales. Quizás por la creencia -ya desechada- de que son patologías que sólo afectan a grupos poblacionales con un gran desgaste físico. Se ha decidido abordar la investigación desde una metodología cualitativa, siendo el tipo de método utilizado el estudio descriptivo.  El análisis se realiza sobre 66 docentes en un Instituto de Enseñanza Secundaria. Se les entrega un cuestionario con tres partes bien diferenciadas: datos demográficos, historial médico e Índice de Discapacidad de Oswestry. En los resultados se obtiene un elevado índice de participación (71%), destacando que un 68% de los sujetos manifiesta tener o haber tenido dolor de espalda. Las causas principales atribuidas son malas posturas y falta de ejercicio. Y el tratamiento seguido principalmente terapia medicamentosa. En cuanto a las regiones más afectadas se mencionan la cervical y dorsal; el 64% de la muestra obtiene un 10% en el Índice de Discapacidad de Oswestry. Se concluye que, a pesar la elevada incidencia del dolor de espalda entre el profesorado, no es motivo habitual de baja laboral. Se demuestra que, aunque no se trata de una dolencia muy incapacitante para el profesorado, sí que es muy frecuente que afecte a algunas tareas desempeñadas en el día a día(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(1): 50-56, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84627</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia del dolor de espalda en el profesorado de Enseñanza Media</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
