<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21152</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oromandibular reconstruction using free fibula flaps with osseointegrated implants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Free fibula flaps have proved to be one of the most versatile for oromandibular reconstruction due to the available length of bone and the possibility of incorporating a long skin paddle to cover intraoral soft tissues. The use of a osseointegrated dental implants is an important technique for the oral rehabilitation of these patients. Osseointegrated implants provide the most rigid prosthetic stabilization available to withstand masticatory forces. These implants can be placed immediately or in second time procedure. In our case, implantation in the fibula free flap is done after 6-9 months because of the large amount of osteosynthesis material required for the fixation of the flap. Four or six months later, when osseointegration has taken place, the implants are loaded with a dental rehabilitation. We analize 10 cases of mandibular reconstruction with fibula free flap and their aesthetic and functional rehabilitation with osseointegrated implants with a 2 year follow up. Forty-six dental implants were placed developing all of them but one a correct osseointegration. All these patients recovered masticatory function and underwent a considerable improvement in labial competence, salivary continence, speech articulation and facial harmony (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El colgajo de peroné ha demostrado ser el más versátil para la reconstrucción oromandibular, gracias a la gran longitud ósea que podemos utilizar y a la posibilidad de incorporar una amplia paleta cutánea para cobertura de tejidos blandos intraorales. El uso de implantes dentales osteointegrados proporciona un importante método terapéutico para la rehabilitación oral de estos pacientes. Los implantes osteointegrados proporcionan la forma más rígida de estabilización protésica para soportar las fuerzas masticatorias. Estos implantes pueden ser insertados de forma inmediata o diferida. A la hora de utilizar el colgajo libre de peroné realizamos la implantología de forma diferida a los 6-9 meses debido a la gran cantidad de material de osteosíntesis necesaria para la fijación del colgajo. Cuatro o seis meses después, cuando el proceso de osteointegración ha ocurrido, los implantes son cargados con una rehabilitación dental. Analizamos 10 casos de reconstrucción mandibular con colgajo libre de peroné y su rehabilitación estética y funcional con implantes osteointegrados y un seguimiento mínimo de 2 años. Se han colocado un total de 46 implantes, presentando todos ellos excepto uno, una correcta osteointegración. Todos estos pacientes han recuperado la función masticatoria, y mejorado de forma considerable la competencia labial, la continencia salival, la pronunciación y la armonía facial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;54(1): 54-64, ene. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción oromandibular con colgajo libre de peroné e implantes osteointegrados</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Plasencia Delgado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Vila, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Gil, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cuéllar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra Martínez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acero Sanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochandiano Caicoya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Atalaya, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21152</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
