<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73429</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identity development in the adolescence and emergent adulthood: a comparison of global identity versus identity in specific domains</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this study were to examine the development and structure of identity across adolescence and the influence of the main social support sources and selfesteem in this process. Measures were taken in a sample of 283 young people between 14 and 22 years, including two measures of identity development (global identity and domain specific identity, relational and school identity), perceived social support and global selfesteem. Results pointed out a progressive development of the identity, especially at the late adolescence and in school domain. Sex differences highlighted faster identity development in girls, both in relational and school domain. The moderate, but consistent, contribution of selfesteem and social support to identity development is also discussed. Peer social support is a decisive factor in identity development, more than parental support(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iborra Cuéllar, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Desfilis, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zacarés González, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Miguel, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos de este estudio fueron examinar el desarrollo y estructura de la identidad a lo largo de la adolescencia y la influencia de las principales figuras de apoyo social y de la autoestima en este proceso. En una muestra de 283 adolescentes entre 14 y 22 años se tomaron dos medidas del desarrollo de la identidad (identidad global e identidad en los dominios relacional y escolar), del apoyo social percibido y de la autoestima global. Los resultados indican una maduración en el desarrollo de la identidad, especialmente durante la adolescencia tardía y en el área escolar. Las diferencias entre sexos identificadas muestran un avance evolutivo más rápido en las chicas en la formación de identidad y tanto en el dominio relacional como en el escolar. Se discute también la moderada pero consistente contribución de la autoestima y el apoyo social a la formación de la identidad. El apoyo relacional de los iguales, más que el de los padres, se muestra como un factor decisivo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;25(2): 316-329, dic. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de la identidad en la adolescencia y adultez emergente: Una comparación de la identidad global frente a la identidad en dominios específicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
