<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84822</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Horner syndrome and brachial plexus blockade after epidural anesthesia for obstetric labor and cesarean section</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 30-year-old woman (ASA II, obese) in her 40th week of a first pregnancy required epidural analgesia for labor. When the cervix had dilated to 5 cm, the epidural infusion was started with a 9-mL bolus of 0.2% ropivacaine and 50 mg of fentanyl, after a negative test dose. An infusion of 0.2% ropivacaine and 1 mg/mL of fentanyl was started at a rate of 8 mL/h. A cesarean section was required after insufficient progress was made during 8 hours of labor. Eight milliliters of 0.75% ropivacaine was administered to provide anesthesia to T4; cesarean delivery was completed without complications. Early during postoperative recovery, in addition to motor blockade of the legs, the patient experienced a right brachial plexus blockade and Horner syndrome on the same side. Both effects disappeared spontaneously (1 and 4 hours later, respectively)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molins Ballabriga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vacas, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mailan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente gestante de 30 años, ASA II, obesa, prímipara en la semana en la semana 40 de gestación, que requirió analgesia epidural para el trabajo de parto. Se instauró la analgesia epidural a los 5 cm de dilatación cervical con un bolus de 9 ml de ropivacaína 0,2% y 50 mg de fentanilo previa dosis test negativa. Posteriormente se inició una perfusión de ropivacaína 0,2% y fentanilo 1 mg/ml a 8 ml/h. Tras 8 horas de evolución hubo que realizar cesárea por distocia de progresión. En el quirófano se administraron 8 ml de ropivacaína 0,75% y se alcanzó un nivel anestésico T4. Se realizó la cesárea sin complicaciones. En el postoperatorio inmediato la paciente presentó además del bloqueo motor de extremidades inferiores un bloqueo del plexo braquial derecho y un síndrome de Horner ipsilateral. Tanto el bloqueo del plexo como el síndrome de Horner desaparecieron espontáneamente 1 y 4 horas después respectivamente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(1): 54-56, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Horner y bloqueo del plexo braquial tras anestesia epidural para trabajo de parto y cesárea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33110^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28095^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37660^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
