<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162309</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementing telemedicine, ehealth and telephonic nursing assistance in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Tele-Health or eHealth are defined as diversified health services provided remotely by a team of professionals using ICT (Information and Communication Technology) to improve the health of a user or population. Development. The development of ICT during the 2000 and 2010 decades allowed for a wider applicability of these services. Techniques like teleradiology and telepathology appeared. Tele-nursing began to be practiced through teleconsultations. Tele-nursing emerged from consulting telephone nurses in the United Kingdom and Canada. In 2005, the WHO established the Global eHealth Observatory to review the benefits of ICT. Currently in Spain, 061 Cat Salut Respon, managed by nurses, gives coverage to Catalonia through its website, telephone, email or chat. In Andalusia, Salud Responde is a service and information center providing citizens with remote healthcare. Conclusions. Health systems offer services through multichannel schemes and specific applications (apps) improving accessibility anytime, anywhere, provided with internet connection. The involvement of nurses in eHealth programs, such as telenurses, is increasingly spreading in Spain, mirroring the trend at an international level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sarriá Guerrero, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guix Comellas, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isla Pera, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los términos «telesalud» o «eSalud» definen los servicios sanitarios diversificados prestados a distancia por un equipo de profesionales usando las TIC para mejorar la salud de un usuario o una población. Desarrollo. El desarrollo de las TIC en las décadas del 2000 y del 2010 hizo posible una mayor aplicabilidad. Aparecieron técnicas de telerradiología y telepatología. Mediante las teleconsultas se empezó a practicar la teleenfermería. Los inicios prácticos de la teleenfermería, surgieron a partir de consultorías enfermeras telefónicas en Reino Unido y Canadá. La OMS estableció, en 2005, el Observatorio Mundial de eSalud para revisar los beneficios de las TIC. Actualmente, en España, 061 Cat Salut Respon, gestionado por enfermeras, da cobertura a Cataluña a través de su página web, teléfono, correo electrónico o chat. En Andalucía, Salud Responde es un centro de información y servicios para dar atención sanitaria a la ciudadanía. Conclusiones. Los sistemas de salud ofrecen servicios a través de sistemas multicanal y aplicaciones específicas (apps) que permiten mejorar la accesibilidad, en cualquier momento, desde cualquier punto con conexión a Internet. La implicación de las enfermeras en programas de eSalud, como las tele-nurses, está cada vez más extendida en España, tal y como ocurre a nivel internacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;40(4): 254-258, abr. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162309</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de la telemedicina, eSalud y atención telefónica de enfermería en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
