<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85016</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A three year follow-up of a prospective open randomized trial to compare tension-free vaginal tape with Burch colposuspension for treatment of female stress urinary incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Evidence comparing the effectiveness of tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) with Burch colposuspension (CS) over a long-term follow-up is scarce. Purpose: To compare TVT with CS as primary treatment for female stress urinary incontinence (SUI). Design: Open randomised clinical trial with a three-year follow-up period. Participants: 49 consecutive women aged 35 to 70 with SUI demonstrated by a urodynamic study. Setting: Urology department of Severo Ochoa general hospital in Leganés, Madrid, Spain. Intervention: 24 random patients treated with TVT and 25 with CS. Measurements: Main variable: assessment before treatment and at six months, one year and three years after the operation using the incontinence severity symptoms index (SSI) and the incontinence impact symptoms index (SII). Secondary variable: three groups for assessing cure, improvement and failure rates. Results: Time in surgery, consumption of postoperative analgesics and length of the postoperative hospital stay were lower in the TVT group (41.1 ± 10.9 minutes; 6 [2.8-10.5]capsules and 1 [1-2] days vs. 57.1 ± 18.3 minutes, 23.5 [18.0-31.5] capsules and 3 [3-3] days[p &lt; 0.0001]). There was a significant reduction in SSI and SII scores in both groups and no differences in surgical complications, urgency, obstruction, one-hour pad test, urineculture, flowmetry, costs and cure rates at any moment during follow-up (cured/improved76.2%, 78.3% and 77.3% at six months, one year and three years for TVT vs. 87.5%, 87.5%and 91.3% for CS; p = 0.32, p = 0.4 and p = 0.19). Limitations: The trial is open, which can create observer bias. A study with a higher number of patients or a longer follow-up time could show differences between the procedures that we were unable to observe in this study, due to our budget and time limits. Discussion: Based on both short-term and long-term results, TVT is as effective as CS for the treatment of SUI, and has similar subjective cure and surgical complication rates. Time in surgery, consumption of analgesics and length of postoperative hospital stay are all lower in the TVT group. In our clinical setting, with a one-day postoperative stay for TVT, the two procedures have similar costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fouz López, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lucas, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez Martínez-Fornés, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrego Hernando, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Las evidencias que comparan la eficacia a largo plazo de TVT (tensión freevaginal tape) y la de colposuspensión (CS) de Burch son escasas. Objetivos: Comparar la eficacia de TVT con CS como tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo femenina (IUE).Diseño: Estudio clínico, aleatorizado, abierto, de 3 años de seguimiento. Participantes: Se incluyó a 49 mujeres consecutivas de 35  a 70 años con IUE demostrada en estudio urodinámico. Ámbito de estudio: Servicio de Urología del Hospital Severo Ochoa de Leganés (Madrid), España. Intervención: Se aleatorizó a 24 pacientes a tratamiento con TVT y 25 con CS. Mediciones: Variable principal: evaluación antes del tratamiento y a los 6 meses, 1 año y 3 años postoperatorios con un cuestionario de severidad de síntomas de incontinencia (SSI) y de impacto de síntomas de incontinencia (SII). Variable secundaria: 3 grupos para evaluar las proporciones de curación, mejoría y fallo. Resultados: El tiempo quirúrgico, el consumo de analgésicos postoperatorios y la estancia postoperatoria fueron inferiores en el grupo TVT (41,1 ± 10,9 min, 6 [2,8-10,5] dosis y 1 [1-2] días frente a 57,1 ± 18,3 min, 23,5 [18-31,5] dosis y 3 [3-3] días [p &lt; 0,0001]). Las puntuaciones SSI y SII se redujeron significativamente en ambos grupos después del tratamiento y no hubo diferencias significativas en las complicaciones operatorias, urgencia, obstrucción, test de la compresa de 1 h, urocultivo, flujometría, costes totales y proporciones de curación en ningún momento del seguimiento (curación/mejoría del 76,2, el 78,3 y el 77,3% a los 6 meses, 1 y 3 años con TVT, y del 87,5, el 87,5 y el 91,3% con CS; p = 0,32, p = 0,4 y p = 0,19). Limitaciones: El estudio es abierto, lo que puede generar sesgos. Un número mayor de pacientes o un mayor tiempo de seguimiento podrían demostrar diferencias entre los procedimientos que no se han observado en el estudio, pero las limitaciones presupuestarias y en el tiempo no lo han permitido. Discusión: Tanto a corto como a largo plazo, la técnica TVT es tan eficaz como la CS para el tratamiento de la IUE femenina, con una proporción similar de curaciones subjetivas y de complicaciones. El tiempo quirúrgico, consumo de analgésicos y la estancia postoperatoria son inferiores con TVT. En nuestro medio, con 1 día de estancia postoperatoria con TVT, los dos procedimientos tienen costes totales similares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(10): 1088-1096, nov.-dic. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85016</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo clínico, aleatorizado, abierto y prospectivo, de 3 años de seguimiento, que compara la eficacia del TVT y la colposuspensión de Burch como tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo femenina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
