<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051735</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mental health referrals of patients without diagnosable psychiatric pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze the characteristics of referral from primary health care to mental health of patients with no diagnosable mental disorder.                 Methods. Consecutively and without exemptions, all persons attending for first-time consultation a mental health centre in the course of a year were clinically examined. We measured the incidence of conditions not attributable to a mental disorder using ICD-10 (Z codes). Information was collected on whose idea it was that they attended, and who, how and with what treatment they were referred. In addition, data about their social, demographic and clinical characteristics were collected.                 Results. Of the 1004 persons examined, 244 (24.4%) (95% CI, 21.6-27) did not meet the ICD-10 diagnosis criteria for mental disorders. They themselves or their family tended to request the Z codes (54.5%) (95% CI, 48.3-60.8]. Mental health referral was almost always through the PC doctor (95.5%) (95% CI, 92.1-97.7). Half the patients were already receiving drug therapy under their general practitioner before their visit and 20.9% (95% CI, 15.8-26) were referred as priority patients.                 Conclusions. Our study found that a large number of patients with no diagnosable mental disorder at the mental health centre, many of them with drug treatment prescribed, were referred. This places a question-mark over the function of primary care as a filter for these patients. The population´s indiscriminate health care demand and the steady increase in treating mental health with drugs partially explain this phenomenon</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Salvanés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González González, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Lobo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las características de la derivación desde atención primaria a un centro de salud mental de los pacientes sin trastorno mental diagnosticable.                 Metodología. Se evaluó clínicamente a todos los pacientes nuevos (n = 1.004) que acudieron de manera consecutiva, sin excluir a ninguno, durante un año, a un centro de salud mental para determinar cuántos no pudieron ser diagnosticados de un trastorno mental según la CIE-10 (códigos Z). Se recabó la información sobre quién tuvo la idea de consultar, quién los derivó, cómo y con qué tratamiento. Además, se obtuvo información sobre sus características sociodemográficas, clínicas y asistenciales.                 Resultados. De un total de 1.004 pacientes evaluados en el año, 244 (el 24,4%) (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 21,6-27) no reunieron criterios para ser diagnosticados de trastorno mental según la CIE-10. Los pacientes con un diagnóstico de un código Z tienden a solicitar, ellos mismos o su familia (54,5%) (IC del 95%, 48,3-60,8), la remisión a un servicio de salud mental, que se hace casi en su totalidad (95,5%) (IC del 95%, 92,1-97,7) a través del médico de atención primaria. Más de la mitad recibe psicofármacos pautados principalmente por el médico de cabecera y un 20,9% (IC del 95%, 15,8-26) es remitido con carácter preferente.                 Conclusiones. En nuestro estudio se observa que hay una cantidad excesiva de pacientes que no presentan un trastorno mental diagnosticable y que son remitidos al centro de salud mental, muchos con tratamiento psicofarmacológico pautado, lo que pone en cuestión la función de filtro asistencial de la atención primaria con estas personas. Probablemente, la indiscriminada demanda asistencial de la población junto con una tendencia excesiva en la utilización de psicofármacos en la salud mental explican parte de este fenómeno</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(10): 563-569, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La derivación a salud mental de pacientes sin un trastorno psíquico diagnosticable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
