<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129104</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary patterns in adult Latin-American immigrants at Macarena District in Seville (Spain): a pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Immigrants who arrive in our country suffer from an abrupt change in their lives. Besides, they face an immigration process with consequences in their wellbeing; in fact, food is one of the most important altered factors. Our goal is to describe the daily dietary intakes in the adult  immigrant Latin-American population in Macarena District during 2010. Method: A descriptive, cross-sectional, observational  prevalence study was carried out in 34 individuals, 16 men  and 18 women, aged 25 to 44 years. A questionnaire that  unified the tools SIVFRENT-A and BRFSS was used for data collection. Results: 95,1% of the sample eats the three main meals  throughout the day. 71,5% said that they included meat at  lunch and dinner. 85,3% have not made any diet in the last six months. Conclusions: Knowledge about the daily dietary intake of  immigrants in the community study shows the good supply of nutrients. It is necessary to pursue further studies on the assessment of nutritional status of the diet of this emerging population group, to guide the design and implementation of differential interventions from the health perspective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-López, José Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lomas-Campos, María de las Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Gázquez, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Los inmigrantes que llegan a nuestro país  sufren un cambio brusco en sus vidas y afrontan un proceso migratorio con consecuencias en su estado de salud,  siendo la alimentación uno de los factores que más se ve  alterado. Nuestro objetivo es describir las pautas  nutricionales diarias en la población latinoamericana  inmigrante adulta del Distrito Macarena de Sevilla, durante el año 2010. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal, de prevalencia y  observacional. Se realizó en 34 personas, 16 hombres y 18 mujeres, de 25 a 44 años. Para la recogida de datos se  utilizó un cuestionario que unificaba los instrumentos SIVFRENT-A y BRFSS. Resultados: El 95,1% de la muestra realiza las tres  principales ingestas de alimentos a lo largo del día. Un 71,5 % manifestó incluir carne en la comida y la cena. El 85,3% no ha realizado ninguna dieta en los últimos seis meses. Conclusiones: El conocimiento sobre las pautas  nutricionales en el colectivo inmigrante estudiado señala el buen aporte de nutrientes. Es pertinente continuar  realizando nuevos estudios dietéticos que permitan completar la valoración del estado nutricional de este  colectivo de población emergente, con el fin de orientar el  diseño y la implementación de actuaciones diferenciales  desde la perspectiva sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(1): 27-31, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pautas nutricionales en inmigrantes latinoamericanos adultos. Distrito Macarena, Sevilla (España). Estudio Piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9932^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
