<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81297</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidural analgesia during labour of a patient with multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a disease of the central nervous system (CNS), and twice as prevalent in women, 70% of whom are of fertile age. From an anaesthetics point of view, due to it being a disease with a high neurological susceptibility it can be aggravated by, the surgery itself, the anaesthetic technique and the medication used. On the other hand, it is about how to meet the demand for analgesia during labour by women with MS, which is the age group with a higher incidence of the disease. We present the case of a 37 year-old woman who was diagnosed 3 years before with a remitting, recurring Multiple Sclerosis. The patient was admitted in dilation in the 37th week of gestation. Labour was progressing well and the foetus was in a longitudinal lie and cephalic presentation. The Anaesthesia Department was informed to assess the indication of an epidural for analgesia during labour. The patient had been seen previously in a pre-anaesthesia clinic were she was informed of the risks and benefits of the technique and in her case in particular. Having understood the possible complications arising from this, she had signed the informed consent. We prefer to use the local/regional epidural technique, bearing in mind the potential risk of an urgent caesarean. This is also to avoid, as is the cases when performing an intra-spinal technique or general anaesthesia, the possibilities of triggering a rash, which can occur with these techniques. Besides giving comfort to the patient during labour, it provides analgesia, and for this reason reduces stress in the patient, as well as being able to prevent a rash appearing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caba Barrientos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Cordero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayorga Buiza, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Esclerosis Múltiple (EM), es una enfermedad del SNC siendo 2 veces más frecuente su aparición en mujeres, el 70% de ellas en edad fértil. Desde el punto de vista anestésico nos encontramos ante una enfermedad con elevada susceptibilidad neurológica que podría agravarse tanto por la propia cirugía, la técnica anestésica como por la medicación utilizada. Por otra parte se plantea como atender la demanda de analgesia para el trabajo de parto en mujeres con EM, que es el grupo de edad con mayor incidencia de la enfermedad. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 37 años diagnosticada de esclerosis múltiples 3 años antes, forma recidivante, remitente. La paciente es ingresada en dilatación con 37 semanas de amenorrea, presentando una buena evolución del trabajo de parto y encontrándose el feto en situación longitudinal y presentación cefálica. Avisan al Servicio de Anestesia para valoración de la indicación de epidural para analgesia del parto. La gestante previamente había acudido a consulta de preanestesia donde se le había informado del riesgo beneficio de la técnica y en concreto en su caso, habiendo entendido perfectamente las posibles complicaciones derivadas de la misma y firmado el consentimiento informado. Nosotros hemos preferido utilizar una técnica locoregional, vía epidural considerando también el riesgo potencial de cesárea urgente, para evitar, dado el caso la realización de una técnica intraraquídea o una anestesia general, con las posibilidades de desencadenar un brote que tienen estas técnicas. Además de aportar confort a la paciente durante el trabajo de parto, proporcionar analgesia durante el mismo, disminuye por este motivo el estrés de la gestante pudiendo paralelamente evitar la aparición de un brote (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(5): 239-241, jun.-jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia epidural para el trabajo de parto en gestante con esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9657^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
