<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154265</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Focal Laser Ablation and Photodynamic Vascular Therapy with soluble TOOKAD® in the treatment of low risk prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increase of the diagnosis of low risk prostate cancer translates into a new clinical entity, for which active surveillance may not be always enough and conventional therapies are clearly overtreatment. Faced with the necessity of giving a therapeutic answer to these patients, and facilitated by the technological advances in the imaging field and new energy sources, the interest is centered in the clinical development of focal therapies as an alternative with minimal morbidity and oncologically safe. As a part of the review carried out in this monographic issue, this article focus on the features relative to the preclinical and clinical development of laser ablative therapy and the innovative photodynamic vascular therapy with soluble TOOKAD®. With this aim we performed an exhaustive bibliographic search, updated to February 2016, in the greater databases, including original articles and reviews in reference to the object of this review, without restrictions for year of publication. This article reviews the preclinical and clinical development of these innovative ablative techniques in the field of focal therapy for low risk prostate cáncer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casanova Ramón-Borja, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Escrig, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El incremento en el diagnóstico de Cáncer de Próstata (CaP) de bajo riesgo se traducen una nueva entidad clínica, para la cual, la vigilancia activa puede no ser siempre suficiente y para la que las terapias convencionales suponen un claro sobre-tratamiento. Ante la necesidad de dar una respuesta terapéutica a estos pacientes, y facilitado por los avances tecnológicos en el campo de la imagen y nuevas fuentes de energía, el interés se centra ahora en el desarrollo clínico de las terapias focales, como una alternativa de mínima comorbilidad y oncológicamente segura. Como parte de la revisión llevada a cabo por este monográfico, este artículo se centrará en aspectos referentes al desarrollo pre-clínico y clínico de la terapia ablativa con láser y de la novedosa terapia vascular fotodinámica con TOOKAD® Soluble. Con esta finalidad, se realizó una exhaustiva búsqueda bibliográfica, actualizada en Febrero de 2016, de las mayores bases reprográficas, incluyendo publicaciones originales y revisiones referentes al objeto de esta revisión, sin restricciones por año de publicación. Este artículo revisa el desarrollo pre- y clínico de estas novedosas técnicas ablativas en el campo de la terapia focal del CaP de bajo riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;69(6): 327-336, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ablación Focal con Láser y Terapia Vascular Fotodinámica con TOOKAD® soluble, en el tratamiento del cáncer de próstata de bajo riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53691^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53691^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53691^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
