<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120931</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">De novo growth of a capillary hemangioma of the conjunctiva</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: A 22-year-old woman patient, diagnosed with an inclusion cyst of the conjunctiva in the nasal sector of the left eye, who after 2 shot/needle injections in the lesion came to our clinic with a dense subconjunctival hemorrhage in four quadrants and with severe pain. After excision biopsy, a capillary hemangioma of the conjunctiva was diagnosed. Discussion: Conjunctival capillary hemangioma is mainly a benign lesion, asymptomatic and mostly congenital in origin, its progression or de novo growth is rare in adulthood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Vega Cueto, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz, M. F. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tresserra, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 22 años, diagnosticada previamente de quiste de inclusión conjuntival en el sector nasal del ojo izquierdo y tratada mediante dos drenajes incisionales, que acude a nuestra consulta con hiposfagma universal acompañado de intenso dolor. Tras realizar una biopsia escisional, fue diagnosticada de hemangioma capilar conjuntival. Discusión: El hemangioma capilar conjuntival es una lesión mayoritariamente benigna, asintomática y congénita, siendo rara pero posible su evolución o su aparición de novo en edades adultas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(3): 127-129, mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crecimiento de novo de un hemangioma capilar conjuntival</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3254^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31420^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
