<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151654</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical practice guidelines for systemic lupus erythematosus: Recommendations for general clinical management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a complex rheumatic multisystemic disease of autoimmune origin with significant potential morbidity and mortality. It is one of the most common autoimmune diseases with an estimated prevalence of 20-150 cases per 100,000 inhabitants. The clinical spectrum of SLE is wide and variable both in clinical manifestations and severity. This prompted the Spanish Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality to promote and fund the development of a clinical practice guideline (CPG) for the clinical care of SLE patients within the Programme of CPG in the National Health System which coordinates GuiaSalud. This CPG is is intended as the reference tool in the Spanish National Health System in order to support the comprehensive clinical management of people with SLE by all health professionals involved, regardless of specialty and level of care, helping to standardize and improve the quality of clinical decisions in our context in order to improve the health outcomes of the people affected. The purpose of this document is to present and discuss the rationale of the recommendations on the general management of SLE, specifically, clinical follow-up, general therapeutic approach, healthy lifestyles, photoprotection, and training programmes for patients. These recommendationsare based on the best available scientific evidence, on discussion and the consensus of expert groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trujillo Martín, María M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabio Sánchez, José Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Irastorza, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pego Reigosa, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Aguilar, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rúa Figueroa Fernández de Larrinoa, Iñigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) es una compleja enfermedad reumática multisistémica de origen autoinmune con una morbimortalidad importantes. Es una de las enfermedades autoinmunes más comunes, con una prevalencia estimada de 20-150/100.000 habitantes. El espectro clínico del LES es amplio y variable tanto en manifestaciones clínicas como en gravedad. Esto ha hecho que el Ministerio de Sanidad, Servicios Sociales e Igualdad haya promovido y financiado el desarrollo de una guía de práctica clínica (GPC) sobre el LES dentro del Programa de GPC en el Sistema Nacional de Salud que coordina GuiaSalud. Esta GPC pretende ser el instrumento de referencia en el Sistema Nacional de Salud para dar soporte a la gestión clínica integral de las personas con LES por parte de todos los profesionales sanitarios implicados, independientemente de la especialidad y el nivel asistencial, contribuyendo a homogeneizar y mejorar la calidad de las decisiones clínicas en nuestro entorno con el objetivo de mejorar los resultados de salud de las personas afectadas. En el presente artículo se presentan y discuten las recomendaciones formuladas en relación con el manejo general de la enfermedad, en concreto, el seguimiento clínico, el abordaje terapéutico general, los estilos de vida saludables, la fotoprotección y la formación para los pacientes. Recomendaciones basadas en la mejor evidencia científica disponible y en la discusión y consenso de grupos de expertos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(9): 413.e1-413.e14, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de práctica clínica para el lupus eritematoso sistémico: recomendaciones para el abordaje clínico general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54578^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22210^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1808</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13861^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29510</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
