<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114985</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementation of the techniques in nursing care: A challenge for clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In clinical practice the meaning and nature of nursing care are overshadowed by the various techniques and activities that the staff nurse. The purpose of this study is to understand the meaning of nursing care by nurses in the clinic. Know how to assemble the technical and nursing care. It is a qualitative research study of the methodology of grounded theory, semistructured interviews with care on primary care nurses in hospitals. Results: among nurses conceptual ambiguity persists about care. The Interrelation staff, professional autonomy and clinical judgment are the hallmark of care. Conclusion: the techniques and procedures are not integrated into care is an additional threat to the principles of discipline and nursing profession (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casabona Martínez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talens Belén, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la práctica clínica el significado y la naturaleza de los cuidados de enfermería son eclipsados por las distintas técnicas y actividades que desarrolla la enfermera asistencial. El propósito del estudio es comprender el significado de los cuidados de enfermería por las enfermeras en la clínica. Conocer como ensamblan las técnicas y los cuidados de enfermería. Es un estudio de investigación cualitativa desde la metodología de la Teoría Fundamentada, con entrevistas semiestructuradas a enfermeras asistenciales sobre cuidados básicos en el ámbito hospitalario. Resultados: entre las enfermeras persiste cierta ambigüedad conceptual en torno a los cuidados. La Interrelación personal, autonomía profesional y el juicio clínico constituyen el sello de identidad de los cuidados. Conclusión: las técnicas y procedimientos que no estén integrados en los cuidados suponen una amenaza a los principios de la disciplina y profesión enfermera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;22(1/2): 7-11, ene.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementación de las técnicas en los cuidados de Enfermería: Un reto para la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
