<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047990</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sarcoidosis in 23 year old patient. Are there therapeutic possibilities?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Twenty-three year old patient with constitutional syndrome who is diagnosed of stage II pulmonary sarcoidosis with bilateral hilar lymph nodes and pulmonary infiltrates. The poor evolution after oral glucocorticoid treatment and multiple adverse effects that they have caused make it necessary to reconsider what alternative should be used with these patients and if we are really improving their future. We analyze different current treatments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arbolí Iriarte, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Aguilera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Ramos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Laso, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 23 años con síndrome constitucional, que es diagnosticada de sarcoidosis pulmonar en estadio II, con adenopatías hiliares bilaterales e infiltrados pulmonares. La mala evolución tras la terapia con glucocorticoides orales y los múltiples efectos secundarios que le han producido, obliga a replantearnos qué alternativa debemos utilizar con estos pacientes y si verdaderamente estamos mejorando su futuro. Hacemos una revisión de los diferentes tratamientos actuales</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(7): 354-357, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sarcoidosis en paciente de 23 años. ¿Hay posibilidades terapéuticas?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31059^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31059^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
