<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045119</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurotrophic actions of growth hormone during development and brain aging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have previously reported that Growth Hormone (GH) inducesproliferation and differentation of prenatal cerebrocortical cells. The roleof GH in oligodendrocyte (OD) development and myelination is poorlyunderstood. The aim of the study was to investigate whether GH promotesOD maturation and to establish the signaling pathways involved in itsaction. Also, the action of GH on brain remyelination during aging wasstudied. Prenatal rat cerebrocortical cells incubated in DMEM 15% FCSfor 6 h were cultured for 4 days in defined medium with 25ng/ml bFGFand treated for 8 days with 50 ng/ml human recombinat GH. Kinase inhibitors,when used, were added 30 minutes before GH treatment. Adult(3 months) and 27 month-old Wistar rats were treated subcutaneouslywith rhGH (150 µg/12hr). To verify the effect of GH on OD developmentand myelination, pre-OD and mature OD were detected by immunocytochemistryusing O4 and myelin basic protein (MBP) antibodies respectively.MBP was detected in brain by immunohistochemistry. GH increasedthe number of O4 (Control: 100%; GH: 166±5%) and MBPpositive cells. To elucidate whether the MAPK and PI3K signaling pathwayswere involved in GH-induced OD development, the kinase inhibitorsPD 098059 (10, 30 and 50µM) and LY294002 (2.5, 5.10 and 20µM)were used. GH-induced and basal appearance of O4 and MBP positivecells was completely prevented by 30µM PD and 2.5µM LY and partly by10µM PD. GH treatment increased the expression of MBP in the old rats.These results indicate that GH promotes oligodendrogenesis by increasingthe number of pre-OD and myelination. They also show that the activationof MAPK and PI3K pathways is crucial for GH induction of ODas well as basal OD development. In addition, GH promotes remyelinationin the CNS during aging</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cacicedo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Franco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Grandes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En estudios previos hemos demostrado que la hormona de crecimiento(GH) induce la proliferación y diferenciación de células cerebrocorticalesembrionarias. El papel de la GH en el desarrollo de los oligodendrocitos(OD) y mielinización es poco conocido. Es este estudio se pretendió investigarsi la GH promueve el desarrollo de oligodendrocitos y los mecanismosde señalización implicados en este proceso. También se estudió, la acción deGH en remielinización cerebral durante el envejecimiento. Células cerebrocorticalesembrionarias se cultivaron en DMEM, 15% de FCS, durante6 horas, se mantuvieron 4 días en medio definido con FGFb (25ng/ml) y seexpusieron a GH (50ng/ml) durante 8 días. Los inhibidores de quinasas seañadieron 45 minutos antes que la GH. Ratas adultas (3 meses) y viejas (27meses) se trataron con GH subcutánea (150 µg/12hr) durante 7 días. Paraverificar el efecto de GH en desarrollo de oligodendrocitos y mielinogenesis,pre-OD y oligodendrocitos maduros se detectaron por inmunocitoquímicacon anticuerpos frente a O4 y proteína básica de mielina (MBP) respectivamente.MBP se analizó en cerebro por inmunohistoquímica. GHincrementó el número de células positivas a O4 (Control: 100%; GH:166±5%) y MBP. Para establecer si las vías de señalización MAPK y PI3Kparticipaban en la acción de GH sobre oligodendrogénesis, los inhibidoresde quinasas PD 098059 (10, 30 and 50 µM) y LY294002 (2,5, 5,10 y 20µM)respectivamente. Tanto la expresión basal como la inducida por GH de O4y MBP se abolió totalmente por PD 30µM y LY 2,5µM, y parcialmente porPD 10µM. El tratamiento con GH también incrementó la expresión deMBP en cerebro de ratas viejas. Estos resultados indican que la GH promuevela oligodendrogénesis incrementando el número de pre-OD y la mielinogénesis.También indican que la activación de las vías MAPK y PI3-Kes necesaria para la inducción de OD por GH y así como para el desarrollobasal de los OD. Además, este estudio demuestra que la GH induce el procesode remielinización en el cerebro de la rata vieja</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;16(3): 195-208, jul. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acciones neurotróficas de la hormona de crecimiento durante el desarrollo y envejecimiento cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22677^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14549</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9378^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27723^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
