<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115379</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating disorders and personality: a comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Personality disorders associated to Axis I disorders have become ever-present topics in current psychological research. A descriptive, comparative and transversal study was designed to compare the personality scales in a clinical sample of 67 patients with TCA and a control group by means of the MCMI-II and to analyze the existence of aggregation of styles of personality depending on the topography of the TCA. We did not find significant differences in the aggregation of styles of personality among clinical groups, though differences did appear with regard to the control group in the majority of the pathological scales. we discuss the scales in which no differences were found between both groups (dependent, histrionic, narcissist and compulsive) and the possibility that it should be due to the influence of certain widely accepted social values common to both samples</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sánchez, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Murcia, Francisco Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cangas Díaz, Adolfo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Pérez, Eugenia M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de personalidad asociados a trastornos del Eje I se han erigido como unos de los principales tópicos actuales en la investigación psicológica. Se diseñó un estudio descriptivo, comparativo y transversal cuyos objetivos fueron comparar las escalas de personalidad en una muestra clínica de 67 pacientes con TCA frente a un grupo control a través del MCMI-II y analizar la existencia de agregación de estilos de personalidad en función de la topografía del TCA. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en la agregación de estilos de personalidad entre grupos clínicos, aunque si respecto al grupo control en la mayoría de las escalas patológicas. Se discute sobre las escalas en las que no se encontró diferencia entre ambos grupos (dependiente, histriónica, narcisista y compulsiva) y sobre la posibilidad de que ello se deba a la influencia de ciertos valores sociales imperantes y por tanto comunes a ambas muestras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;16(2): 189-205, mayo-ago. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos de la conducta alimentaria y personalidad: un estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
