<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129933</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mediastinal hibernoma: singular appearance on computed tomography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hibernomas are very uncommon benign tumors of brown fat; they are rarely located within the thorax and are even rarer in the mediastinum. We present the case of a 14-year-old girl with a hibernoma seen on CT as a homogeneous fat density mass located in the anterior mediastinum. Histological study revealed the typical microscopic characteristics of these tumors. To our knowledge, this is the first report of these CT imaging characteristics in association with a hibernoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Román, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Castillo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez De Septien, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arauzo Álvarez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los hibernomas son tumores benignos de grasa parda, muy poco frecuentes, cuya localización intratorácica es rara, y más aún en el mediastino. Presentamos un caso de hibernoma en una niña de 14 años, que se manifestó en la tomografía computarizada (TC) como una masa homogénea de densidad grasa situada en el mediastino anterior y, cuyas características microscópicas fueron las típicas de estos tumores. Hasta donde sabemos, esta apariencia en TC no ha sido nunca descrita en la bibliografía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(6): e50-e53, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hibernoma mediastínico con apariencia singular en tomografía computarizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8647^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8645^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8645^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2029^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2029^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
