<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162457</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient safety in antibiotics administration: risk assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the level of risk in the preparation and administration of antibiotics frequently used in the Intensive Care Unit using a risk matrix. Material and method. A study was conducted using situation analysis and literature review of databases, protocols and good practice guidelines on intravenous therapy, drugs, and their administration routes. The most used antibiotics in the ICU registered in the ENVIN-HELICS program from 1 April to 30 June 2015 were selected. In this period, 257 patients received antimicrobial treatment and 26 antibiotics were evaluated. Variables studied: A risk assessment of each antibiotic using the scale Risk Assessment Tool, of the National Patient Safety Agency, as well as pH, osmolarity, type of catheter recommended for administration, and compatibility and incompatibility with other antibiotics studied. Results. Almost two-thirds (65.3%) of antibiotics had more than 3 risk factors (represented by a yellow stripe), with the remaining 34.7% of antibiotics having between 0 and 2 risk factors (represented by a green stripe). There were no antibiotics with 6 or more risk factors (represented by a red stripe). Most drugs needed reconstitution, additional dilution, and the use of part of the vial to administer the prescribed dose. Conclusion. More than half of the antibiotics studied had a moderate risk level; thus measures should be adopted in order to reduce it. The risk matrix is a useful tool for the assessment and detection of weaknesses associated with the preparation and administration of intravenous antibiotics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Juan, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Palau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar el nivel de riesgo en la preparación y administración de los antibióticos de uso frecuente en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos utilizando una matriz de riesgo. Material y método. Se realizó un análisis de situación y una revisión bibliográfica en bases de datos, protocolos y guías de buenas prácticas sobre terapia intravenosa, medicamentos y vías de administración. Se llevó a cabo una selección de los antibióticos más utilizados en nuestra unidad registrados en el programa ENVIN-HELICS desde el 1 de abril al 30 de junio del 2015. Los pacientes que recibieron tratamiento antimicrobiano en este periodo fueron 257. Se evaluaron 26 antibióticos. Variables a estudio: evaluación del riesgo de cada antibiótico mediante la escala Risk Assessment Tools, de la National Patient Safety Agency, incluyendo pH, osmolaridad, tipo de catéter recomendado para su administración y compatibilidad e incompatibilidad con el resto de los antibióticos estudiados. Resultados. El 65,3% de los antibióticos tuvieron más de 3 factores de riesgo representados con una franja amarilla, y el 34,7% entre 0 y 2 factores de riesgo (franja verde.) No hubo ningún antibiótico con 6 o más factores de riesgo (franja roja). La mayoría de los fármacos necesitaron reconstitución, dilución adicional y la utilización de parte del vial para administrar la dosis prescrita. Conclusión. Más de la mitad de los antibióticos estudiados son de riesgo moderado, por lo que se deberían adoptar medidas para disminuirlo. La matriz de riesgo es una herramienta útil para la evaluación y detección de los puntos débiles asociados a la preparación y administración de antibióticos intravenosos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(3): 178-186, mayo-jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad del paciente en la administración de antibióticos: evaluación del riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4406</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
