<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78983</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of (RS)-2-chloro-5-hydroxyphenylglycine (CHPG) on agonistic behavior in mice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have indicated that ionotropic glutamate receptors (especially NMDA and AMPA) are involved in the modulation of aggressive behavior in animal models. In contrast, the role of metabotropic glutamate receptors (mGlu) is less well known. mGlu5 receptors are found in high concentrations in the limbic brain structures implicated in emotional behaviors, including aggression. This study examines the effects of CHPG (0.75, 1.5, 3, 6 and 12 mg/kg, ip), a selective mGlu5 receptor agonist, on agonistic behavior elicited by isolation in male mice. Individually housed mice were exposed to an anosmic opponent in a neutral area 30 min after drug administration. In addition to other behaviors, aggressive (threat and attack) and exploratory behaviors were evaluated for 10 min using an ethologically based analysis. The results indicate that CHPG administration produced no significant effects on agonistic behavior at any of the doses used. These findings could be related to several factors such as the specific characteristics of the ligand used (partial vs total agonist), the chosen dose range, or the interval between drug administration and the evaluation of its effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huertas, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burón, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-López, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos trabajos han implicado a los receptores ionotrópicos de glutamato (especialmente NMDA y AMPA) en la modulación de la conducta agresiva en modelos animales. En contraste, el papel de los receptores metabotrópicos de glutamato (mGlu) es menos conocido. Los receptores mGlu5 se localizan en altas concentraciones en estructuras del sistema límbico implicadas en procesos emocionales, como la agresión. Este estudio examina el efecto de administrar (RS)-2-cloro-5-hidroxifenilglicina (CHPG, 0,75; 1,5; 3; 6 y 12 mg/kg), un agonista selectivo de los receptores mGlu5, sobre la conducta agonística en ratones machos utilizando un modelo animal de agresión inducida por aislamiento. Ratones aislados individualmente fueron enfrentados a oponentes anósmicos en un área neutral 30 min después de la administración del fármaco. Además de otras conductas, se evaluaron las conductas agresivas (amenaza y ataque) y exploratorias durante 10 min utilizando un análisis etológico. Los resultados indicaron que la administración de CHPG no produjo efectos significativos en la conducta agonística con ninguna de las dosis utilizadas; estos resultados pueden deberse a diversos factores, como las características propias del ligando utilizado (agonista parcial contra agonista total), el rango de dosis elegido o el intervalo utilizado entre la administración del fármaco y la evaluación de sus efectos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);14(6): 199-203, nov. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la administración de (RS)-2-cloro-5-hidroxifenilglicina (CHPG) sobre la conducta agonística en ratones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d382^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d382^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
