<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94086</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Grounded theory as a qualitative research methodology in nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Grounded theory is a qualitative research design used at an international level. It has been applied as a methodology to develop theories about relevant health phenomena. However, in the Spanish nursing context, grounded theory has received very little attention. This article focuses on this qualitative methodology and illustrates its contribution to nursing research in Spain and its relevance for nursing. Moreover, the main methodological characteristics of grounded theory are briefly presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arantzamendi, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Dicastillo, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordo Luis, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivar, Cristina G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La teoría fundamentada (TF) es un diseño de investigación cualitativa, reconocido a nivel internacional, que ha sido utilizado para desarrollar teorías sobre fenómenos de salud relevantes. Sin embargo, en el ámbito de la enfermería española, la TF ha tenido escasa consideración. Por ello, este artículo se centra en esta metodología cualitativa e ilustra su contribución en la investigación enfermera en España y su utilidad para la Enfermería. También, se presentan brevemente las características metodológicas distintivas de la teoría fundamentada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(4): 283-288, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94086</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Teoría Fundamentada como Metodología de Investigación Cualitativa en Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
