<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80562</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycohemoglobin HbA1c. First part: to know it</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetes is a chronic disease with a high prevalence, which goes increasing gradually until getting features of epidemic. Since )Diabetes Control and Complications Trial* (DCCT) and )United Kingdon Prospective Diabetes Study* (UKPDS) were released in the 90&#146;s, Glucohemoglobin (HbA1c)has become the glycemic control imagine. This fact is responsible for its use as fundamental piece in the journey of the care of the patients with Diabetes. In spite of its importance and its applications, HbA1c is not generally known. In this work we expect to give the knowledge of many aspects of HbA1c from its definition to its diary clinic application. In this first part, we will revise the different points of the )Diabetes complex* where HbA1c is used and we will know its chemical definition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Domínguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano-Serrano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Pintado, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes es una enfermedad crónica con una elevada prevalencia, que va aumentando progresivamente hasta alcanzar rasgos de epidemia. A raíz de la publicación en la década de los noventa de los estudios «Diabetes Control and Complications Trial» (DCCT) y «United Kingdom Prospective Diabetes Study» (UKPDS), la glucohemoglobina (HbA1c) se ha convertido en la imagen del control glucémico. Esto ha hecho que sea utilizada como pieza fundamental en el día a día del cuidado de los pacientes con diabetes. A pesar de su importancia y de sus aplicaciones, la HbA1c no es generalmente muy conocida. En este trabajo pretendemos dar a conocer muchos de los aspectos de la HbA1c desde su definición hasta su aplicación clínica diaria. En esta primera parte, repasaremos los distintos puntos del «complejo Diabetes» donde se usa la HbA1c y conoceremos su definición química (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(2): 82-88, feb. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80562</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glucohemoglobina HbA1c. Primera parte: conocerla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
