<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91087</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological examination and primary care. Block II: voluntary motility. Higher cortical functions. Abnormal movements</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The neurological examination is, along with the anamnesis, the basis of the diagnosis of nervous system disease. The Primary Care doctor, with limited access to high resolution tests, must know the most important aspects of this examination; the most important being that this is carried out systematically. In the first Block, the examination of the cranial pairs, sensitivity, meningeal signs, cerebellum and coordination were looked at. In this second Block, motor function, higher cortical functions and abnormal movements are analysed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Villuendas, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Robres, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ballesteros, J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La exploración neurológica es, junto con la anamnesis, la base del diagnóstico de la patología del sistema nervioso. El médico de Atención Primaria, con un acceso limitado a pruebas de alta resolución, debe de conocer los aspectos más importantes de dicha exploración, siendo importante que esta se realice de manera sistemática.En un primer bloque se abordó la exploración de los pares craneales, la sensibilidad, los signos meníngeos, el cerebelo y la coordinación, y en esta segunda parte se analizan la función motora, las funciones corticales superiores y los movimientos anómalos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(8): 418-425, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91087</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exploración neurológica y atención primaria. Bloque II: motilidad voluntaria, funciones corticales superiores y movimientos anómalos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4484^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2869^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9652^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34317^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1043^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9652^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9652^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9312^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1043^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1272^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9399^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9323^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12439^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
