<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-20018</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can treatment associated with ticlopidine and nifedipine increase serum levels of phenobarbital?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We report a case in which the association between ticlopidine, nifedipine and phenobarbital was linked with a higher than expected phenobarbital concentration in serum, which suggested a possible interaction between these drugs. Case report. A 67-year-old male who received treatment with phenobarbital, digoxin, nifedipine, ticlopidine, paroxetine and clorazepate dipotassium. The first control of the level of phenobarbital in serum was performed without any symptoms or signs of toxicity or ineffectiveness. A phenobarbital concentration in serum of 21.4 mg/L was obtained, with a serum level/dosage ratio of 16.7. Discussion. The serum level/dosage ratio of phenobarbital that was found in this case is almost twice as high as expected. In the absence of other factors that can explain this finding, we believe that two drugs (ticlopidine and nifedipine) may be involved in an interaction with phenobarbital. Conclusions. The high value of the serum level/dosage ratio that was found makes it advisable to monitor the concentrations of phenobarbital in serum in treatment associated with ticlopidine or nifedipine, especially when adjusting the dosage, beginning or ending treatment with these drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Describimos un caso en que la asociación de ticlopidina, nifedipina y fenobarbital se asoció con una concentración sérica de fenobarbital mayor que la previsible, que sugirió una posible interacción entre estos fármacos. Caso clínico. Varón de 67 años en tratamiento con fenobarbital, digoxina, nifedipina, ticlopidina, paroxetina y cloracepato dipotásico. Se realizó el primer control del nivel sérico de fenobarbital, sin ningún síntoma o signo de toxicidad o ineficacia. Se obtuvo una concentración sérica de fenobarbital de 21,4 mg/L, con un índice nivel sérico/dosis de 16,7. Discusión. El índice nivel sérico/dosis de fenobarbital que se encontró en este caso es casi el doble que el previsible. En ausencia de otros factores que puedan explicar este resultado, creemos que dos fármacos (ticlopidina y nifedipina) pueden estar implicados en una interacción con fenobarbital. Conclusiones. El alto valor del índice nivel sérico/dosis que se encontró hace aconsejable monitorizar las concentraciones séricas de fenobarbital en el tratamiento asociado con ticlopidina o nifedipina, especialmente al ajustar las dosis, iniciar o suspender el tratamiento con estos fármacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(5): 433-434, mar. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Puede el tratamiento asociado con ticlopidina y nifedipina aumentar los niveles séricos de fenobarbital?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Durán Quintana, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Delgado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-20018</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d10826</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
