<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111581</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reality versus theory: trace elements, their involvement in the prevention and / or treatment of the wounds</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The wound healing is a methodical, dynamic process of biological events, established in a concrete time with the purpose of repairing the wound, certain nutrients intervene as modulators in this course. The intention of this literary review is to investigate on the efficiency of trace elements in the prevention or cure of the wounds of different etiologies, across the summary of clinical recent researches on the hypothesis to study, contributing new scientific knowledge on this tendency. The reality differs of the theory: Theoretically the trace elements play indirectly an important role in the process wound healing, coexisting a bidirectional inter -relationship between: &#147; Deficit, is equal to delayed wound healing &#147;,&#148; Supplement is equal to optimized wound healing&#147;. The reality is different, the clinical experimental studies on the nutritional interventions with (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrera Castro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cicatrización es un proceso, metódico, dinámicode acontecimientos biológicos, establecidos en untiempo concreto con la finalidad de reparar la herida,determinados nutrientes intervienen como moduladores en este transcurso. El propósito de esta revisión literaria es indagar sobre la eficacia de los elementos traza en la prevención o curación de las heridas de diferentes etiologías, a través de la recopilación de investigaciones clínicas recientes sobre la hipótesis a estudio, adquiriendo nuevos conocimientos científico sobre esta tendencia. La realidad discrepa de la teoría: Teóricamente los elementos traza juegan indirectamente un papel importante en el proceso de cicatrización de la heridas, coexistiendo una interrelación bidireccional entre: &#147;Déficit símil demora de cicatrización&#148;, &#147;Suplementación símil potenciación de la cicatrización&#148;. La realidades otra, los estudios clínicos experimentales sobre (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;33(1): 61-72, ene.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Realidad versus teoría: elementos traza, su implicación en la prevención y/o tratamiento de las heridas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14523^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
