<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156270</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal outcome of macrosomic infants born to diabetic versus non-diabetic mothers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the incidence and perinatal complications of macrosomic infants born to diabetic and non-diabetic mothers. Patients and methods. A six-year retrospective study of newborns at our hospital. A total of 996 macrosomic newborns were found. Maternal characteristics, mode of delivery, and perinatal outcomes were studied. Results. Of 18005 newborns, 996 were macrosomic infants (5.53%). Of these, 103 (10.3%) were born to diabetic mothers. Diabetic mothers had higher parity (1.89 vs. 1.35; P&lt;0.000), cesarean section rate (52.4 vs. 31.1%; P&lt;0.05), and resuscitation rate (5.8 vs. 1.8%; P&lt;0.006; RR: 2.9; 95% CI: 1.42-5.9), and greater need for hospitalization (19.4 vs. 9.6%; p&lt;0.002; RR: 2; 95% CI: 1.3-3.2) and intensive care (5.8 vs. 0.7%; P&lt;0.000; RR: 5.3; 95% CI: 2.8-10) mostly for hypoglycemia (7.8 vs. 1%; P&lt;0.000; RR: 5; 95% CI: 2.8-8.3), jaundice (8.7 vs. 2.1%; P&lt;0.000; RR: 3.1; 95% CI: 1.9-5.9), respiratory distress (4.9 vs. 1.3%; P&lt;0.009; RR: 2.9; 95% CI: 1.4-6.7), and asphyxia (2.9 vs. 0.4%; P&lt;0.005; RR: 4.3; 95% CI: 1.8-11.1). No differences were found in birth trauma. Conclusions. Macrosomic infants born to diabetic mothers have an increased risk of hospital admission in the neonatal period for hypoglycemia, jaundice, respiratory distress, and asphyxia, and a greater need of intensive care. Obstetric trauma rates were similar in both groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lloreda-García, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sánchez, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Ruiz, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Martínez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla-Denia, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo. Determinar la incidencia y las complicaciones perinatales de los recién nacidos macrosomas hijos de madre diabética y macrosomas hijos de madre no diabética. Pacientes y método. Estudio retrospectivo de 6 años de los macrosomas nacidos en nuestro hospital. Se encontraron 996 macrosomas. Se estudiaron características maternas, tipo de parto y resultados perinatales. Resultados. De 18.005 neonatos, 996 fueron macrosomas (5,53%), siendo 103 hijos de madre diabética (10,3%). La madres diabéticas tenían mayor paridad (1,89 vs. 1,35; p&lt;0,000), porcentaje de cesáreas (52,4 vs. 31,1%; p&lt;0,05), porcentaje de reanimación (5,8 vs. 1,8%; p&lt;0,006; RR: 2,9; IC 95%: 1,42-5,9), mayor necesidad de ingreso hospitalario (19,4 vs. 9,6%; p&lt;0,002; RR: 2; IC 95%: 1,3-3,2) y en cuidados intensivos (5,8 vs. 0,7%; p&lt;0,000; RR: 5,3; IC 95%: 2,8-10); mayor cantidad de ingresos por hipoglucemia (7,8 vs. 1%; p&lt;0,000; RR: 5; IC 95%: 2,8-8,3), ictericia (8,7 vs. 2,1%; p&lt;0,000; RR: 3,1; IC 95%: 1,9-5,9), distrés respiratorio (4,9 vs. 1,3%; p&lt;0,009; RR: 2,9; IC 95%: 1,4-6,7) y asfixia (2,9 vs. 0,4%; p&lt;0,005; RR: 4,3; IC 95%: 1,8-11,1). No existieron diferencias en cuanto a traumatismos obstétricos. Conclusiones. Los recién nacidos macrosomas hijos de madre diabética tienen mayor riesgo de ingreso en el periodo neonatal, incluidos los ingresos por hipoglucemia, ictericia, asfixia, distrés respiratorio y mayor necesidad de cuidados intensivos. Los traumatismos obstétricos son similares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(8): 409-413, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados perinatales entre macrosomas hijos de madre diabética y macrosomas hijos de madre no diabética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11696</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
