<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97288</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus statements from the Workshop 'Probiotics and Health: Scientific Evidence'</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This report shows the level of scientific consensus on definition, characteristics and health benefits of probiotics. The content of the report has derived from the scientific meeting: Workshop on Probiotics and Health. Scientific evidence, that congregated several Spanish experts, including gastroenterologists, microbiologists, nutritionists, immunologists and food technologists, among others, who have agreed with the statements shown in this document. Each statement has been sustained with the most relevant scientific aspects that were discussed during the Workshop and the following evaluation of there port by all experts who approved and signed it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guarner, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este documento se muestra una base de consenso entorno a la definición, características y propiedades beneficiosas de los probióticos. El contenido fue generado a partir de la reunión científica Workshop Probióticos y Salud. Evidencia Científica, que agrupó a una variedad de expertos españoles gastroenterólogos, microbiólogos, nutricionistas, inmunólogos y tecnólogos de alimentos, entre otros, que se han adherido en su mayoría a las sentencias que constituyen este documento. Para cada sentencia se establecen las aspectos científicos más relevantes que la respaldan y que son consecuencia del acuerdo al que se ha llegado tras el debate surgido en la reunión y la evaluación posterior del contenido por todos los expertos que han firmado este documento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(5): 700-704, sept.-oct. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Declaraciones consensuadas del Workshop: &#147;Probióticos y Salud: Evidencia Científica&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10777^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
