<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17793</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Veredict and deliberation content analysis of judges and juries in the Spanish legal context. A contrastive approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bearing in mind that jury performance has been subject to considerable criticism in various countries, the aim of the present paper is to contrast the judges&#146; and jury performance. A total of 15 nine-member juries and 15 three-member panels of judges deliberated and reached a verdict on real cases. The results of a contrastive analysis reveal a) neither judges nor juries perform in a normative way; b) juries perform worse than judges; c) judges and juries perform different tasks, driven to the defence by the juries and to the prosecution by the judges; and d) the juries&#146; deliberations are not more exhaustive than the judges&#146; as would be expected in order to compensate for their lack of legal knowledge and experience, and tend to be redundant in content. Finally, the practical implications are discussed as well mechanisms designed to mitigate the non-normative decision-making of judges and juries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arce, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tortosa, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Sobre la base de que son numerosas y consistentes inter-contextos jurídicos las críticas a la eficacia de los Tribunales de Jurados, nos hemos planteado un estudio comparativo de la ejecución de Tribunales de Jueces y Jurados en el ordenamiento jurídico español (L.O. 5/1995). Tomando como material estimular tres casos reales, formamos 15 Tribunales de Jurados y 15 Tribunales de Jueces, que emitieron el objeto del veredicto tras la discusión grupal. Los resultados mostraron que tanto Jueces como Jurados no ejecutan de un modo normativo; que la ejecución de los Jurados es de peor calidad; que jueces y Jurados ejecutan tareas distintas, más orientados a la defensa los Jurados y más a la acusación los Jueces; y que las deliberaciones de los Jurados no son más profundas para compensar su falta de conocimientos en la materia. Finalmente, discutimos las complicaciones para contrarrestar estos déficit en la actuación de Jueces y Jurados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(1): 127-135, feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Veredictos y análisis del contenido de las deliberaciones de los Tribunales de Jueces y Jurados en el contexto jurídico español</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7768</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36421</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
