<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108009</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Discrepancy in the disk diffusion susceptibility test of Pseudomonas aeruginosa strains isolated from cystic fibrosis patients after anaerobic preincubation and its potential clinical relevance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In cystic fibrosis, the Pseudomonas aeruginosa cells grow inside the thick mucus layer. In spite of being an obligate aerobe, P. aeruginosa is able to grow in a limited oxygen environment. Bacterial cells could be suddenly exposed to high oxygen levels due to the movements of the mucus mass. The aim of study was to determine the impact of a previous anaerobic incubation on the antimicrobial susceptibility of P. aeruginosa strains isolated from patients with cystic fibrosis. Materials and Methods. Four P. aeruginosa strains were used in this study (ATCC 23389 and 3 clinical isolates). The disk diffusion method was used to determine the antimicrobial susceptibility. Results. The anaerobic pre-incubation produced changes on the susceptibility in all studied strains. All susceptible strains after an aerobic incubation remained susceptible after an anaerobic incubation except one clinical strain, which became resistant to betalactams. The response was strain-dependent and the most significant increase in susceptibility was observed in two of the three clinical isolates when ciprofloxacin was used. Conclusions. The antimicrobial susceptibility of P. aeruginosa strains varies after their exposure to anaerobic conditions. Treatments promoting mucus fluidization could contribute to increase the antimicrobial efficacy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomez-Lus, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rey, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cafini, Fabio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bas, PEdro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En la fibrosis quística las células de Pseudomonas aeruginosa crecen en el interior de la espesa mucosidad, y pese a ser un organismo aerobio estricto, se desarrolla en un ambiente donde la presión de oxígeno es muy limitada. Posibles movimientos de la masa mucosa podrían dejar expuestas de forma súbita a las células de P. aeruginosa a concentraciones altas de oxígeno. El objetivo del estudio fue determinar cómo afecta a la sensibilidad antibiótica de P. aeruginosa un período de incubación anaerobia. Material y métodos. Se emplearon 4 cepas de P. aeruginosa (NTCC 23389 y 3 aislados clínicos). Para la determinación de la sensibilidad antibiótica se empleó el método de difusión en agar. Resultados. La preincubación anaerobia produce cambios en la sensibilidad en todas las cepas estudiadas. Todas las cepas sensibles en aerobiosis resultaron también sensibles tras la incubación anaerobia a excepción de la cepa 2 para los betalactámicos. El tipo de respuesta resulta dependiente de cada cepa, siendo especialmente significativo el incremento en la sensibilidad observado en el caso de ciprofloxacino para dos de los tres aislados clínicos. Conclusiones. La sensibilidad de cepas P. aeruginosa varía si han sido previamente expuestas a condiciones de anaerobiosis. Tratamientos que favorezcan la fluidificación de la mucosidad podrían contribuir aumentando el éxito del tratamiento con ciertos antibióticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;25(4): 269-273, dic.2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discordancia en los resultados de sensibilidad mediante método de difusión en agar de aislados de Pseudomonas aeruginosa en pacientes con fibrosis quística tras pre-incubación anaerobia y su potencial relevancia clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d367^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d707^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d367^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32446^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19602^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14419^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
