<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167385</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Graduated Nurses reflections from the University of La Laguna (Spain) about making a mistake in job's context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To deepen the experience of the graduated nurses from the University of La Laguna between 2009 and 2014 regarding responsibility, insecurity and fear of error in the labor context of Tenerife (Spain). Methodology: a qualitative research is carried out with hermeneutical phenomenological approach through discourse analysis, having used as a data collection tool the semi-structured interview. Nineteen nurses participate, randomly selected and for convenience. Results: the main category is "do". It is established as the main category of the study. Of the same the following subcategories are broken down: "to make a mistake"; "Different mistakes"; "Medication errors"; "Work overload errors"; "To cause death"; "Recognize mistakes and learn from them" and "act wisely". Discussion and conclusions: The meanings of the experiences are centered on making a possible mistake and its consequences. The experiences referred by the nurse with respect to responsibility are attributed fundamentally to being able to perform an adequate praxis in their work, being aware that they deal with people for it is an experience that brings much meaning to the nurse once it begins to work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marrero González, Cristo Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernández, Alfonso Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Profundizar en las vivencias de las enfermeras egresadas de la Universidad de La Laguna entre 2009 y 2014 con respecto a la responsabilidad, la inseguridad y el temor al error en el contexto laboral de Tenerife (España). Metodología: se realiza una investigación cualitativa con enfoque fenomenológico hermenéutico mediante el análisis del discurso, habiendo utilizado como herramienta de recogida de datos la entrevista semiestructurada. Participan 19 enfermeras, elegidas aleatoriamente y por conveniencia. Resultados: se establece como principal categoría del estudio la denominada "hacer". De la misma se desglosan las siguientes subcategorías: "cometer un error"; "diferentes errores"; "errores en la medicación"; "errores por sobrecarga de trabajo"; "provocar la muerte"; "reconocer los errores y aprender de los mismos" y "actuar con prudencia". Discusión y conclusiones: Los significados de las vivencias están centrados en cometer un posible error y en sus consecuencias. Las vivencias referidas por la enfermera con respecto a la responsabilidad se atribuyen fundamentalmente a poder realizar una adecuada praxis en su trabajo, al ser conscientes de que tratan con personas por ello es una vivencia que aporta mucho significado para la enfermera una vez que comienza a trabajar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;21(48): 51-60, mayo-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167385</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones de enfermeras egresadas de la Universidad de La Laguna (España) sobre la comisión de un error en el contexto laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4727^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
