<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138840</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-3655</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An exploratory study of the patient experience of pharmacist supplementary prescribing in a secondary care mental health setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Management of chronic disease has become an increasing challenge to the National Health Service in the United Kingdom. The introduction of supplementary prescribing was seen as a possible mechanism to address the needs of this patient group. Individuals with mental illness were considered particularly suitable for management in this way. Objective: To explore the views and experiences of patients with mental illness on being managed by a pharmacist supplementary prescriber in a secondary care outpatient setting. Methods: A study of patient experiences utilising semi-structured interviews and self-completion diaries was adopted. Eleven patients participated in the study. Data were analysed utilising code and retrieve, and content analysis respectively. Results: Patients valued the increased accessibility to, and continuity of, their prescriber compared with their experience of other healthcare professionals. Patients reported they were able to trust the pharmacist&#146;s knowledge of medication, were provided with sufficient information regarding reasons for treatment and side effects, and felt that they had an active role in decisions concerning their healthcare. Conclusions: This exploratory study showed that patients had positive views of being managed by a supplementary prescriber. However, it should be noted that the number of participants was small. It is therefore important that further, more wide ranging research is conducted to evaluate pharmacist prescribing within mental health settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>John, Dai N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deslandes, Rhian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deslandes, Paul N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El manejo de las enfermedades crónicas se ha convertido en un reto para el Sistema Nacional de Salud del Reino Unido. La introducción dela prescripción suplementaria fue vista como un mecanismo para afrontar las necesidades de este grupo de pacientes. Los individuos con problemas de salud mental fueron considerados particularmente apropiados para teste tipo de manejo. Objetivo: Explorar las visiones y experiencias de los pacientes con salud mental al ser manejados por un farmacéutico prescriptor suplementario en una clínica ambulatoria de cuidaos secundarios. Métodos: Se adoptó un estudio de las experiencias de los pacientes utilizando entrevistas semiestructuradas y diarios auto-cumplimentados. Once pacientes participaron en el estudio. Los datos se analizaron usando codificación y recuperación, y un análisis de contenido respectivamente. Resultados: Los pacientes valorizaron el aumento de accesibilidad y la continuidad de su prescriptor comparado con otros profesionales de la salud. Los pacientes comunicaron que eran capaces de confiar en los conocimientos sobre medicación del farmacéutico, que les proporcionaba con suficiente información sobre los motivos de su tratamiento y efectos adversos, y sentían que tenían un papel activo en las decisiones sobre su salud. Concusiones: Este estudio exploratorio mostró que los pacientes tenían visiones positivas al ser manejados por un prescriptor suplementario. Sin embargo, debe reconocerse que el número de participantes fue pequeño. Por ello es importante que se realice más investigación y más amplia para evaluar la prescripción farmacéutica en las clínicas de salud mental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. pract. (Granada, Internet);13(2): 0-0, abr.-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138840</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio exploratorio de la experiencia de los pacientes sobre la prescripción farmacéutica suplementaria en una clínica secundaria de salud mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
