<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107855</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resistance patterns of Neisseria gonorrhoeae isolated in patients from the area of cuenca (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A retrospective study was conducted to determine the antibiotic susceptibility of Neisseria gonorrhoeae isolates from genital samples of patients over the last four years in Cuenca (Spain), in order to establish what would be the best treatment regimens for this disease in our region. Of a total of 26 isolates of Neisseria gonorrhoeae, fluoroquinolone resistance was 61.54%. All strains were susceptible to cefotaxime, so we believe that the choice of empirical treatment of uncomplicated gonococcal infections should be third generation cephalosporins in our region (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sendra Fontán, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Escudero, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada de Medio, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seseña del Olmo, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Medina, Mari Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo es un estudio retrospectivo para conocer la sensibilidad antibiótica de los aislados de Neisseria gonorhoeae de muestras genitales de pacientes durante los últimos 4 años en el área de Cuenca (España) para así establecer cuáles serían las mejores pautas de tratamiento para esta enfermedad en nuestra región. De un total de 26 cepas aisladas de Neisseria gonorrhoeae, la resistencia a fluorquinolonas fue del 61,54%. Todas las cepas fueron sensibles a cefotaxima, por lo que consideramos que el tratamiento empírico de elección de las infecciones gonocócicas no complicadas en nuestro medio debería ser las cefalosporinas de tercera generación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;5(4): 195-197, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones de resistencia de Neisseria gonorrhoeae aisladas en el área de Cuenca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19603^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34387^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
