<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044512</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment with sildenafil of cold glands síndrome after inflatable penile prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the effect of sildenafil on the response of glans penis during sexual intercourse in patients with penile prosthesis who show cold glans syndrome symptoms. MATERIAL AND METHODS: Fourteen patients who had undergone three-piece inflatable penile prosthesis implantation were evaluated. In spite of the normal functioning of the device all of them complained of a degreeof dissatisfaction during SI due to a lack of engorgement in the glans penis. The patients were advised to have adose of 100 mg VO sildenafil about 45 minutes before activating the PP and starting SI. All of them followed this scheme at least three times. They ticked questions 7, 8, 13 and 14 of the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) questionnaire with/without having had sildenafil. RESULTS: Twelve out of thirteen patients (85,7%) indicated a more pleasant SI on sildenafil. It was related toan increase in penile glans engorgement and sensitivity. The scores obtained in the IIEF questions showed a significant increase on taking sildenafil. The partners also talked of a more comfortable SI that they related to aless painful penetration. Sildenafil-related morbidity was not found. CONCLUSIONS: Sildenafil could be used to improve functional results of the penile prosthesis in those patients with CGS and seems to increase satisfaction during SI</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moncada Iribarren, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara Rascón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Chamorro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente Abarca, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lledó Garcia, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Evaluar el efecto de sildenafilo en la respuesta peneana glandular durante la relación sexual (RS) en pacientes con prótesis de pene que muestran síntomas sugerentes de síndrome de glande frío (SGF). MATERIAL Y MÉTODO: Evaluamos catorce pacientes a quienes se había implantado una prótesis de pene (PP) hidráulica de tres piezas. A pesar de un funcionamiento normal del dispositivo, todos los pacientes se quejaban de diversos grados de insatisfacción durante la RS debido a falta de incremento de volumen en glande. Se recomendó a los pacientes la ingestión de una dosis de 100 mg de sildenafilo unos 45 minutos antes de activar la PP e iniciar la RS. Todos ellos siguieron este esquema al menos en tres ocasiones. Respondieron las cuestiones 7, 8, 13 y 14 del Índice Internacional de Función Eréctil (IIEF) con/sin dosis previa de sildenafilo. RESULTADOS: Doce de los catorce pacientes (85,7%) indicaron una RS más placentera tras ingerir sildenafilo. Este hecho fue relacionado especialmente con un incremento en la sensibilidad y volumen del glande. Las puntuaciones obtenidas en las cuestiones del IIEF mostraron un incremento significativo al tomar sildenafilo. Las parejas también referían una RS más confortable que relacionaron con una PV menos dolorosa. No se objetivó morbilidad relacionable con sildenafilo. CONCLUSIONES: Sildenafilo puede ser utilizado para mejorar los resultados funcionales de las PP en pacientes con síndrome de glande frío y parece incrementar la satisfacción durante la RS</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;28(6): 443-446, jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con sildenafilo del síndrome de glande frio tras implante de prótesis hidráulica de pene</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15068^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19636^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10603^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10604^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24829^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10603^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
