<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94450</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Living with dialysis: coping strategies and quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to learn about the influence of coping strategies on quality of life and satisfaction of patients undergoing dialysis treatment. Material and method: observational, cross-sectional study of a sample consisting of 93 people under the age of 70 receiving HDH and DPCA treatment in 3 Nephrology units in 3 different hospitals. Questionnaires on coping strategies, quality of life (SF36) and satisfaction with life were administered. Statistical analyses were adjusted by age and sex.Results: 93 patients with a mean age of 53,67 years were included. 61 of these patients were under HDH treatment and 32 under CAPD treatment. The most frequently employed coping strategies were: search of information and problem solving,cognitive restructuration and regulated expression of emotions. The mental health component presented a significant negative association with escape/avoidance, musings, social isolation, emotional release and opposition/confrontation. Satisfaction with life presented a significant positive associationwith seeking of social support and cognitive restructuration and a negative association with escape/avoidance and desperation/abandonment.Conclusions: dialysis patients who manifest poorer mental health cope with their illness by employing maladaptive avoidance mechanisms based on tension release,eating and drinking disorders, hiding their feelings, and musing. They also blame and isolate themselves as they release their emotions and anger. These behaviours stem from experiencing an intense situation which they feel they have little control over. Avoidance causes discomfort and uneasiness and mental health deterioration, while satisfaction with life (subjective well-being) is associated with finding meaning to the experience (positive reinterpretation) and social support (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echebarri Escribano, Miren</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Alegría Fernández de Retana, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Prado, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basabe Barañano, Nekane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños Baños, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogales Rodríguez, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la influencia de las estrategias de afrontamiento en la calidad y satisfacción con la vida en los pacientes sometidos a tratamiento de diálisis. Material y método: estudio transversal observacional con una muestra formada por 93 personas en tratamiento en HDH y DPCA en tres unidades de nefrología de 3 hospitales, edad&lt;70 años. Se aplicaron los cuestionarios de estrategias de afrontamiento, calidad de vida (SF36) y satisfacción con la vida. Los análisis estadísticos se ajustaron por edad y sexo.Resultados: se incluyeron 93 pacientes con media de edad 53,67 años, 61 seguían tratamiento mediante HDH y 32 mediante CAPD. Las estrategias de afrontamiento más frecuentemente utilizadas fueron: búsqueda de información y resolución de problemas, reestructuración cognitiva y expresión regulada de emociones.El componente de salud mental se asoció significativamente en sentido negativo con huída/evitación, rumiación, aislamiento social, descarga emocional y oposición/confrontación. La satisfacción con la vida se asoció significativamente ensentido positivo con búsqueda de apoyo social y reestructuración cognitiva y en sentido negativo con huída/evitación y desesperación/abandono.Conclusiones: los pacientes de diálisis que presentan peor salud mental afrontan la enfermedad con formas de evitación poco adaptativas, basadas en la descarga de la tensión, comiendo y bebiendo, ocultando sus sentimientos, con pensamientos rumiativos; también se autoculpan, se aislan, a la vez que descargan las emocionesy el enojo. Dichas conductas se derivan de vivir una situación intensa y sobre la que se percibe poco control. La evitación produciría displacer y deterioro de la saludmental, mientras que la satisfacción con la vida (bienestar subjetivo) se vincula a dar un sentido a la experiencia (reinterpretación positiva) y al apoyo social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(9): 27-32, nov. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vivir en diálisis: estrategias de afrontamiento y calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3982^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
