<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166242</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The technical perfection of the surgery has provoked the appearance of a new generation of healthcare instruments that offers unprecedented therapeutic perspectives, but in turn, make their reprocessing  more complex. This fact favors its treatment as unique elements, scarce in the hospital and therefore, undergoing a great surgical pressure to which is added its high rotation of use. Due to their constructive nature, much of these materials will require low temperature sterilization methods. MATACHANA&#146;s history as a manufacturer of this type of technology has been long-standing, starting in the 70&#146;s with the first equipment of ethylene oxide mixture and passing through formaldehyde sterilizers of various generations, including the model 130LF that operates under Low Temperature Steam with 2% formaldehyde. This technology is still  used in the hospital centers, worldwide. As a culmination of this journey and after a research process of more than 4 years, MATACHANA presents the vaporized hydrogen peroxide equipment with plasma  phases, Matachana 130HPO®. This sterilizer assumes  the  application of the same stringency required for steam sterilization, but for a device that uses H2O2, technology for which there are still no specific rules. This generates therefore some doubts and controversies about certain aspects: cycle profile, load release, limitation of lumens sterilization, biological monitoring, process validation, etc. This article answers these questions by technically analyzing how MATACHANA has sought a solution for all those concerns, ponding and advocating for the future standardization of the system. At the same time, this development has revealed that, for certain types of materials, hydrogen peroxide technologies will have to be complemented with other low temperature equipment, especially because of the challenge and difficulty of structurally complex devices to H2O2 sterilization. The 130HPO(R) sterilizer is the starting point for a whole line of low temperature sterilizers that will respond to the current and future needs of the Health Centers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Marfil, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tecnificación actual de la praxis quirúrgica, así como la evolución tecnológica vivida por el instrumental sanitario en los últimos años, ha provocado la aparición de toda una serie de productos médicos inteligentes que proporcionan nuevas perspectivas terapéuticas pero que a su vez, dificultan enormemente su reprocesamiento. Cirugía robótica, técnicas híbridas rígido-flexibles, ópticas de imagen 3D, cirugía eco guiada con sondas intraoperatorias... Nuevas prácticas intervencionistas aparecen día a día en los hospitales, con dispositivos altamente complejos y de elevado coste que incluyen nuevos desarrollos de lentes, chips electrónicos, novedosos polímeros plásticos, lúmenes flexibles de diámetros mínimos o resinas de adhesión de nueva generación, por lo que habitualmente se requerirán sistemas de esterilización por baja temperatura. Todos estos factores favorecen su tratamiento como elementos muy singulares, escasos en el hospital y por tanto, sometidos a una gran rotación y presión quirúrgica. Con este panorama, los fabricantes de equipos relacionados con el control de la infección y el reprocesamiento de dispositivos médicos han ido adaptándose a esta nueva realidad, para buscar soluciones de limpieza, desinfección y esterilización que aporten la misma  seguridad que las tecnologías hasta ahora conocidas, pero con una respuesta mucho más inmediata. La esterilización por vapor, gracias a su solidez normativa, se ha mantenido constante y tan sólo se han producido ligeros cambios debidos a un intento de optimización de los tiempos de proceso, mejora de la calidad del secado o incremento de la ergonomía con la automatización máxima de los accesorios periféricos que rodean al esterilizador. Por ello, la investigación industrial se ha focalizado en la Baja Temperatura, para buscar aquel agente esterilizante que compense la incompatibilidad del vapor con todos estos nuevos desafíos, ya sea por su alta temperatura o por tratarse de un sistema húmedo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;22(1/2): 67-72, 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Más allá de la esterilización por Baja Temperatura: experiencia y visión de futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7015^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51509</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
