<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112224</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dialectical behavioural therapy for oppositional defi ant disorder in adolescents: a case series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Oppositional defiant disorder (ODD) is characterised as a recurrent pattern of defiant behaviour towards authority figures, irritability and difficulties in regulating emotions. ODD in adolescents presents similar symptomatology to borderline personality disorder (BPD). A treatment programme that has been shown to be effective for treating problems related to emotion dysregulation such as BPD is dialectical behavioural therapy (DBT). The aim of this article is to outline a case series in which we applied DBT to two adolescents diagnosed with ODD, in addition to psychiatric comorbidity and parasuicidal behaviours. Method: We applied a training programme of 24 sessions in DBT skills, along with individual therapy. Results: The results showed a decrease in impulsive behaviours, maladaptive behaviours to regulate affect, self-mutilation behaviour, number of hospitalisations, anger and depressive symptoms. The data also showed an increase in positive emotions. Conclusion: These results suggest that DBT can be an alternative for the treatment of ODD in adolescents with psychiatric comorbidity and parasuicidal behaviours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Botella, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Palacios, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heliodoro Marco, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el trastorno negativista desafiante (TND) se caracteriza por un patrón consistente de conductas oposicionistas hacia las figura de autoridad, irritabilidad y dificultades de regulación emocional. El TND en adolescentes presenta sintomatología común con el trastorno límite de la personalidad (TLP). Un programa de tratamiento que se ha mostrado eficaz para el tratamiento de trastornos caracterizados por dificultades graves en la regulación emocional como el TLP es la terapia dialéctica comportamental (DBT). El objetivo de este trabajo es mostrar una serie de casos en los que se aplica la DBT a dos adolescentes diagnosticadas de TND, con comorbilidad psiquiátrica y conductas parasuicidas. Método: se aplicó el programa de entrenamiento en habilidades de la DBT y sesiones de terapia individual. Resultados: los resultados indican una disminución de las conductas impulsivas, desadaptativas de regulación del afecto, autolesiones, ingresos hospitalarios, síntomas depresivos y de la ira. También se produjo una mejora del estado de ánimo y el afecto positivo. Conclusión: estos resultados sugieren que la DBT puede ser una alternativa para el tratamiento del TND en adolescentes con comorbilidad psiquiátrica y conductas parasuicidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(2): 158-163, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la terapia dialéctica comportamental al trastorno negativista desafiante en adolescentes: una serie de casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
