<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67650</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate weight change in workers participating in a multidisciplinary program (medical, psychologicaland dietary) intended to reduce body weight.Methods: All workers in a company from Barcelona with body mass index (BMI) over 25kg/m2 were invited to participatein a one year program. Psychological and dietary interventions were structured over a six-month period, and includedone individual and eight group sessions; medical monitoring was maintained throughout the entire year. The program includedcognitive-behavioural therapy, dietary counselling, promotion of physical activity and medical monitoring. Results: 88 workers of both sexes with a mean (± standard deviation) age of 50 (± 6) years and mean BMI of 30.7 (±3.4) kg/m2 participated in the program. A reduction of 5-10% of the initial body weight was obtained in 57% of the workerswho completed the program. Moreover, fi nal values of waist circumference, systolic and diastolic blood pressure and glucoselevels improved with regard to baseline values (p&lt;0.05).Conclusions: The results of this multidisciplinary experience in the treatment of overweight and obesity in a companyshowed benefi ts in terms of weight loss for most participants. A combination of medical monitoring, psychological counselling,nutritional education by the dietitian and physical activity promotion could be a key factor for success of this kind of programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador Salvador, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñals Miralles, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Agustench, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la evolución del peso en trabajadores participantes en un programa multidisciplinar (médico, psicológicoy dietético) para reducir peso.Métodos: Todos los empleados de una empresa de Barcelona que presentaban un índice de masa corporal (IMC) por encimade 25kg/m2 fueron invitados a participar en el programa de un año de duración. La intervención psicológica y dietéticase estructuró a lo largo de seis meses en una sesión individual y ocho sesiones grupales, mientras que la vigilancia médicafue mantenida durante todo un año. El programa incluía terapia cognitivo-conductual, educación dietética, promociónde la actividad física y seguimiento médico.Resultados: 88 empleados de ambos sexos de una media (± desviación típica) de edad de 50 (± 6) años y con un IMCmedio de 30,7 (± 3,4) kg/m2 participaron en el programa. Se consiguió una disminución del 5-10% del peso corporal inicialen el 57% de los participantes que lograron fi nalizar el programa. También se obtuvo mejoría en los valores fi nales del perímetrode la cintura, los niveles de tensión arterial sistólica y diastólica o los niveles de glucosa respecto a los valores iniciales(p&lt;0,05).Conclusiones: Los resultados del programa para el tratamiento del sobrepeso y obesidad en la empresa muestran beneficios ponderales en la mayoría de los participantes. La combinación de control médico, apoyo psicológico, educación alimentariapor parte de un dietista y promoción de la práctica de ejercicio físico podría ser el factor clave a la hora de conseguirefectos positivos en este tipo de programas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 188-195, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67650</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16509^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
