<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76292</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eosinophilic esophagitis is an unusual and emerging disease in the last years that is recognizedby the presence of more than 20 eosinophils per high-powered field on esophageal tissuebiopsy. It is described in all ages although apparently is more frequent in children. It is suggestedthat atopy or allergic mechanisms play an important role in the development of this diseasebut the etiology is not clear yet. The more frequent symptoms are dysphagia and food impactionamong the varied clinical manifestations. No specific treatments exist but topical swallowedsteroids are the first choice although an exclusion diet is preferred in children with foodallergy. We report the case of a 12-year-old child, suffering from atopic dermatitis and otherallergies, admitted to hospital for an episode of melena and urticaria and discuss the diagnosisand the treatment of this pathology(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Encinas Bascones, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones Martínez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballón Hurtado, AE</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esofagitis eosinofílica es una enfermedad inusual y emergente en los últimosaños que se caracteriza por un infiltrado de más de 20 eosinófilos por campo de gran aumentoen la biopsia del tejido esofágico. Se describe en todas las edades aunque aparentementees más frecuente en niños. La etiología no está clara pero se sugiere que la atopiao las alergias juegan un rol importante en el desarrollo de la enfermedad. Lapresentación clínica es variada: la disfagia y la impactación alimentaria son las más frecuentes.No existe un tratamiento específico. Los corticoides tópicos deglutidos son losfármacos de elección, pero en niños con alergia alimentaria el tratamiento se basa endietas de exclusión. Presentamos el caso clínico de un niño de 12 años con antecedentede dermatitis atópica y alergia que es hospitalizado por presentar un cuadro de melenacon urticaria aguda. A su vez, se hace una breve revisión del diagnóstico y el tratamientode esta patología(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(44): 625-630, oct.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esofagitis eosinofílica: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28168^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28168^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
