<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139701</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurofibromatosis type 2 (NF2). Study of 7 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this paper is to present the cases of 7 young children and young adult with type 2 neurofibromatosis (NF2). Material and methods: Seven patients, 5 females and 2 males, aged 2 to 33 years, were studied by intracranial and spinal magnetic resonance (MRI) and clinically. In 5 patients, the symptoms because around the time of the diagnosis while 2 patients, who had no previous symptoms, were diagnosed by MRI after undergoing the test because a parent had been diagnosed of NF2 by MRI. Results: All 7 patients had bilateral vestibular schwannomas (VS) and only two had no associated intracranial and/or spinal tumors. Four patients had intracranial meningiomas, mainly located in the lesser wing of the temporal fossa and in the falx, and 5 had spinal cord tumors (ependymomas and meningiomas). An attempt to made to remove the VS in all but one case, however, it was not possible to remove completely the tumors in any case. Deafness was the common sequel in all operated cases, associated with permanent bilateral facial paralysis in one and unilateral facial parenthesis in another. Conclusion: A comparison of our series of NF1 and NF2 cases shows that the ratio of NF2:NF1 in childhood is approximately 1:100, and that the clinical features of NF2 are considerably more severe than in NF1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Pascual, SI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Castroviejo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viaño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Presentar 7 pacientes de edades infantil y adulto joven con neurofibromatosis tipo 2 (NF2). Material y métodos. Siete pacientes, 5 mujeres y 2 varones, con edades comprendidas entre 2 y 33 años fueron estudiados clínicamente y por resonancia magnética (RM) intracraneal y espinal. En 5 pacientes los síntomas comenzaron a manifestarse en fechas en que se hizo el diagnóstico. En 2 pacientes, sin sintomatología previa, el diagnóstico fue hecho por RM tras habérselo hecho a sus progenitores con NF2. Resultados. Los 7 pacientes presentaban schwannoma vestibular (SV) bilateral y en sólo dos de ellos no existía asociación con otros tumores intracraneales y/o espinales. Cuatro pacientes tenían meningiomas intracraneales localizados principalmente en la zona de fosa temporal-ala menor del esfenoides y en la hoz del cerebro, y 5 tumores espinales (ependimomas y meningiomas). Se intentó la extirpación de los SV en todos los casos menos en uno y no se consiguió de forma completa en ninguno, quedando sordera en todos ellos. En uno también quedó parálisis facial bilateral permanente postquirúrgica y en otro parestesias faciales en el lado operado. Conclusión. A la vista de nuestras series de NF1 y NF2 en la infancia, la proporción NF2:NF1 es de 1:100, con una incomparable mayor repercusión clínica sobre los pacientes en la NF2 que en la NF1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(7): 457-461, sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurofibromatosis tipo 2 (NF2). Estudio de 7 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
