<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107296</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Venous embolization - treatment of choice in varicoceles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Varicocele consists of the varicose expansion of the spermatic vein. It&#146;s more frequently in the left side (10:1) as consequence of an evilfunctioning or absence of the valves of the spermatic left vein. Between March 1999 and December 2009 there have been gathered a total of 37cases diagnosed of varicocele in the pediatric population of our center. After a local anesthetic we created a femoral aproach. We advanceinto the left renal vein using a catheter Simmons type I and then we position the top of the catheter beyond the ostium of the spermatic veinto fulfil the renal left vein by means of the administration of contrastiodized and gonadal vein could be visualized using retrograde phlebography .Transcatheter embolization will carry out across the introduction of coils (approximately from 6 to 8) of 0.038 using a hidrofiliccatheter of 4 or 5F.Of the total of the 37 cases, we obtained correctly embolization in33 patients (89.2%), being necessary a reembolization in three cases(10.8%) of which one finished in surgery. Only in a case (2.7%) surgerywas practised for embolization incomplete (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casatellví, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isnard, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampere, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrerol, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perich, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muxart, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El varicocele es la dilatación varicosa de la vena espermática y del plexo pampiniforme. Se origina más frecuentemente en el lado izquierdo(10:1) como consecuencia de un mal funcionamiento o ausencia delas válvulas de la vena espermática izquierda. Entre marzo del 1999 y diciembre del 2009 se han recogido un total de 37 casos (17,9%) de los diagnosticados de varicocele en la población pediátrica de nuestro centro, que requirieron tratamiento. Mediante anestesia local se crea un acceso femoral empleando un catéter Simmons tipo I. Posicionamos la punta del catéter más allá de lostium de la vena espermática para realizar el venograma de la venarenal izquierda mediante la administración de contraste yodado, que fluirá de forma retrógrada hasta testes. La embolización se realizará através de la introducción de coils metálicos (aproximadamente de 6 a8) de 0.038 empleando un catéter hidrofílico de 4 o 5F.Del total de los 37 casos tratados, se consiguieron embolizar correctamente33 pacientes (89,2%), siendo necesario una reembolización entres casos (10,8%) de los que uno acabó en cirugía. Tan sólo en un caso(2,7%) se practicó cirugía por embolización incompleta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;24(1): 55-58, ene. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La embolización venosa, tratamiento de elección en los varicoceles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22360^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15049^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
