<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141004</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health technology assessment in public health interventions: is prevention better than cure?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Medical activities are increasingly performed with preventive purposes, as part of community programs for secondary prevention but also as part of many clinical activities. However, there are few evaluations of preventive and health promotion activities and, in general, these evaluations only assess aspects of efficacy/effectiveness with little consideration of cost and cost-effectiveness and even less of the ethical, legal, social or organizational consequences. Given the growing interest in evaluation of these interventions from different perspectives, health technology assessment (HTA) has emerged as a multidisciplinary analysis strategy with distinct methodological approaches that may be useful to health administrations and policy-makers for decision making at different levels (micro, meso and macro). This manuscript discusses the characteristics and differential aspects related to assessment of preventive and health promotion activities. This type of evaluation poses constraints, limitations and challenges that should be considered during the process of HTA. In the case of public health there are additional challenges, because the evidence must satisfy a diverse audience, including public health professionals, clinicians, politicians, managers, economists and consumers. The challenge is even greater when evaluating complex, integrated community interventions in which local and contextual aspects are of tremendous importance. In addition, assessment of ethical issues is of the utmost importance since these issues comprise the origin of health services and the target populations are usually healthy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solà-Morales, Oriol de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almazán, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, Joan MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espallargues, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada vez se llevan a cabo más actuaciones de medicina clínica con fines preventivos, como parte de los programas comunitarios de prevención secundaria, pero también de muchas actividades clínicas. Sin embargo, se dispone de pocas evaluaciones de actividades preventivas y de promoción de la salud, y en general sólo valoran aspectos de eficacia/efectividad, con poca consideración del coste y el coste-efectividad y menos de los aspectos éticos, legales, sociales u organizativos. Dado el interés creciente por evaluar este tipo de intervenciones desde diferentes perspectivas, la evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias se postula como una estrategia de análisis multidisciplinario que con diferentes enfoques metodológicos puede ser útil a las administraciones sanitarias y a los decisores para la toma de decisiones a diferentes niveles (micro, meso y macro). Se presentan aquellas características y aspectos diferenciales relacionados con la evaluación de las actividades preventivas y de promoción de la salud. Esto conlleva limitaciones, dificultades y desafíos importantes que deberían considerarse durante el proceso de evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias. En el caso de la salud pública hay retos adicionales, puesto que la evidencia debe satisfacer a una audiencia diversa, que incluye profesionales de la salud pública, clínicos, políticos, gestores, economistas y consumidores. El reto es aún mayor cuando se trata de evaluar intervenciones comunitarias complejas e integradas, en las cuales los aspectos locales y contextuales tienen una relevancia enorme. Además, la valoración de los aspectos éticos cobra suma importancia puesto que su origen corresponde a los servicios sanitarios y se dirigen a poblaciones mayoritariamente sanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(supl.1): 40-48, jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141004</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias en intervenciones de salud pública: ¿más vale prevenir que curar?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34589^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
