<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162107</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">OSaNAIA: new care management too</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The evolution of the nursing profession in the last years and the achievement of the new competences give the ability to the professionals to work in an independent way and in collaboration with other professionals. The nurses records are legal documents with a great value that shows the autonomous role of nursing professionals and highlight care work complexity. In order to facilitate registration and to comply with current legislation and management of care and evidence-based practice, the Basque Health Care Service (Osaki-detza) has implemented a new tool called OsaNAIA. In the Ambulatory Surgery Unit in Basurto Hospital (05I-Bilbao Basurto), the incorporation of this tool has been a major change; developing the system from a paper format to a computer application registration. Ambulatory Surgery patient care plans establishe focusing action in the acute process, prioritizing the diagnoses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Landaluze Okeranza, MG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Núñez, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tíscar González, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valtierra Aragón, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Molinuevo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de la profesión enfermera en los últimos años y la adquisición de nuevas competencias capacitan a los profesionales enfermeros para trabajar de forma independiente y en colaboración con otros profesionales. Los registros enfermeros son documentos jurídico-legales de gran valor que evidencian el rol autónomo del profesional enfermero y destacan la complejidad de los cuidados que realizan. Para poder facilitar el registro, cumplir con la legislación vigente y favorecer la gestión del cuidado y la práctica clínica basada en evidencia científica, el servicio Vasco de Salud (Osakidetza) ha implementado una nueva herramienta; esta herramienta es OsaNAIA. En la unidad de cirugía sin ingreso del Hospital de Basurto, perteneciente a la 05I-Bilbao Basurto, la incorporación de la herramienta ha supuesto un cambio muy importante: el paso del registro en papel al registro en una aplicación informática. Los planes de cuidados de los pacientes sometidos a Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria (CMA) se establecen focalizando la actuación en el proceso agudo, priorizando los diagnósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;22(1): 29-32, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">OsaNAIA: nueva herramienta de gestión de cuidados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
