<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112857</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Affordability of alcohol and alcohol-related mortality in Belarus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alcohol abuse has numerous adverse health and social consequences. The consumer response to changes in alcohol affordability is an important issue on alcohol policy debates. Studies from many countries have shown an inverse relationship between alcohol prices and alcohol consumption in the population. There are, however, suggestions that increasing the price of alcohol by rising taxes may have limited effect on alcohol-related problems, associated with long-term heavy drinking. The aim of the present study was to evaluate the relationship between alcohol affordability and alcohol-related mortality rates in post-Soviet Belarus. For this purpose trends in alcohol-related mortality rates (mortality from liver cirrhosis, pancreatitis, alcoholism and alcohol psychoses) and affordability of vodka between 1990 and 2010 were compared. The time series analysis revealed that 1% increase in vodka affordability is associated with an increase in liver cirrhosis mortality of 0,77%, an increase in pancreatitis mortality of 0.53%, an increase in mortality from alcoholism and alcohol psychoses of 0,70%. The major conclusion emerging from this study is that affordability of alcohol is one of the most important predictor of alcohol-related problems in a population. These findings provide additional evidence that decreasing in affordability of alcohol is an effective strategy for reducing alcohol consumption and alcohol-related harm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Razvodovsky, Yury E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abuso del alcohol tiene numerosas consecuencias negativas tanto sociales como para la salud. La respuesta de los consumidores a los cambios en la accesibilidad al alcohol es un problema importante de los debates sobre políticas sobre el alcohol. Los estudios realizados en varios países han demostrado una relación inversa entre los precios del alcohol y el consumo de alcohol en la población. Existen, sin embargo, dudas acerca de si el aumento del precio de alcohol a través de impuestos puede tener un efecto notorio sobre los problemas relacionados con el alcohol, de los bebedores excesivos a largo plazo pesado. El objetivo del presente estudio fue evaluar la relación entre la accesibilidad al alcohol y las tasas de mortalidad relacionadas con dicha sustancia en la Bielorrusia post-soviética. Con este propósito las tendencias en las tasas de mortalidad relacionadas con el alcohol (mortalidad por cirrosis hepática, pancreatitis, alcoholismo y psicosis alcohol) se compararon con la accesibilidad al vodka entre 1990 y 2010. El análisis de series temporales reveló que un 1% de aumento en la accesibilidad del vodka se asocia con un aumento en la mortalidad por cirrosis hepática de 0,77%, un aumento en la mortalidad por pancreatitis del 0,53% y un aumento en la mortalidad por alcoholismo y por psicosis alcohólica del 0,70%. La principal conclusión de este estudio es que la accesibilidad al alcohol es uno de los más importantes predictores de problemas relacionados con el alcohol en una población. Estos resultados proporcionan evidencia adicional de que una disminución en la accesibilidad al alcohol es una estrategia efectiva para reducir el consumo de alcohol y los problemas relacionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);25(2): 156-162, abr.-jun. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accesibilidad al alcohol y mortalidad relacionada con el alcohol en Bielorrusia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
