<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048282</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuronal migration disorders: a cause of curable medication resistant epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Focal cortical dysplasia is a neuronal migration disorder that appears with bouts of epileptic seizuresthat are usually medication resistant. The improvements introduced into neuroimaging techniques in recent years have madeit possible to diagnose and offer surgical treatment to certain patients who have been under polytherapy for many years withpoor control over their seizures. Case report. We report the case of a 22-year-old male with epileptic fits since the age of 18months, who was refractory to multiple combinations of oral antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) with electroencephalograms thatdisplayed frontal, fast spike-wave discharges, with greater expression on the left side and findings from neuroimaging techniquesthat were repeatedly normal. After being readmitted to hospital because his seizures had got worse, the neuroimaging studywas repeated and left frontal focal cortical dysplasia was observed, which led us to start considering neurosurgery. At present,six months after the intervention, the patient has had no further convulsive fits and therapy with oral AEDs is being reduced.Conclusions. Neuroimaging studies must be repeated in patients that have already been examined because in this way it maybe possible to save a group of patients (who would otherwise have to resign to poor control over their seizures as well as theside effects of many AEDs) from becoming medication resistant</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puerta González-Miró, I. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostacero-Miguel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumiá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauri-Llerda, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñol-Ripoll, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La displasia cortical focal es una alteraciónde la migración neuronal que se manifiesta con crisis epilépticashabitualmente farmacorresistentes. La mejoría en las técnicasde neuroimagen durante los últimos años ha permitido el diagnósticoy tratamiento quirúrgico de algunos pacientes tratados en politerapiadurante muchos años con mal control de las crisis. Caso clínico.Varón de 22 años con crisis epilépticas desde los 18 meses,refractario a múltiples combinaciones de fármacos antiepilépticos(FAE) orales con electroencefalogramas que mostraban descargasfrontales, punta-onda rápida, de mayor expresión izquierda y técnicasde neuroimagen repetidamente normales. Tras su último ingresopor reagudización de las crisis se repitió el estudio de neuroimageny se observó displasia cortical focal frontal izquierda, por loque se inició valoración neuroquirúrgica. En la actualidad, seis mesesdespués de la intervención, el paciente no ha presentado nuevascrisis epilépticas y se ha iniciado la reducción del tratamiento conFAE orales. Conclusión. Resulta necesario repetir estudios de neuroimagenen pacientes estudiados previamente ante la posibilidadde rescatar de la refractariedad a un grupo de pacientes condenadosa mal control de sus crisis junto con los efectos secundarios demuchos de los FAE</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(1): 20-24, jul. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones de la migración neuronal: una causa de epilepsia farmacorresistente curable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2500^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
