<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98362</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive models of depression: a synthesis and new proposal based on 30 years of research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cognitive approaches have been very fruitful for the understanding of depression. Cognitive models have inspired current evidence-based treatments of depression while providing useful frameworks to understand the causes of this disorder. However, empirical research in the last years has improved the explanatory power of these models substantially. In this paper we review a number of recent developments of well-established elements of the cognitive models as well as new concepts and variables which have just been incorporated in these models. Thus, we describe conceptual and empirical advancements on the role of negative schemata, attributions, self-esteem, attributional style or memory processes. Furthermore, we also describe new research on the role that processes like a ruminative style of processing or thought suppression mechanisms may have in the onset and maintenance of depression. Finally, based in these new developments, we present a comprehensive model of depression which expands older well-known cognitive models</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Carmelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernangómez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La perspectiva cognitiva ha sido de gran utilidad en el campo del estudio de la depresión. Dicha perspectiva, además de posibilitar el desarrollo de tratamientos psicológicos eficaces, nos ha permitido comprender algunos importantes procesos por los cuales las personas se deprimen. Sin embargo, lejos de ser un modelo rígido y estancado, ha ido evolucionando a lo largo del tiempo, especialmente en los últimos años. En este artículo se revisan los nuevos desarrollos elaborados con relación a aspectos cruciales del modelo cognitivo de la depresión así como los nuevos procesos que se han comenzado a estudiar. Así, se describen los avances realizados en la comprensión de los esquemas negativos, la autoestima, el estilo atribucional o los procesos de memoria. Asimismo, se detalla el papel del estilo rumiativo o la supresión del pensamiento en los procesos de vulnerabilidad a la depresión. Por último, a modo de resumen, se plantea un modelo reformulado que integra los avances más recientes dentro del esquema clásico del modelo cognitivo para la depresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;18(1): 139-165, ene.-abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98362</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos cognitivos de la depresión: una síntesis y nueva propuesta basada en 30 años de investigación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
