<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14565</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric analysis of two scales to evaluate parents´ educational styles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The psychometric properties of two scales related to parents&#146; educational styles are analyzed. The Warmth Scale have two factors (warmth-communication and criticism-rejection); and the Rules-Demands Scale is divided in three factors regarding the way compliance to rules is established and demanded (inductive, strict and indulgent styles). In both scales, there are two versions. The child&#146;s version is used to evaluate the perception adolescents have of their father and mother&#146;s educational style. In the parents&#146; version, parents fill in certain items regarding specific behaviors towards their child. All the scores showed a satisfactory internal consistency reliability; the convergent and discriminant validity rests on the correlations with IPPA (Armsden and Greenberg, 1987), PAQ (Buri, 1991), and 4E (Palacios, 1994). On the other hand, a low rate of agreement was found between the information provided by parents and children, which suggests the need to evaluate the educational styles from both perspectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Motrico, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bersabé, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se analizan las propiedades psicométricas de dos escalas para evaluar estilos educativos parentales. La Escala de Afecto consta de dos factores (afecto-comunicación y crítica-rechazo), mientras que la Escala de Normas y Exigencias se divide en tres factores sobre la forma de establecer y exigir el cumplimiento de las normas (forma inductiva, rígida e indulgente). Ambas escalas se presentan en dos versiones: hijos y padres. En la versión de los hijos, se evalúa la percepción que el adolescente tiene del estilo educativo de su padre y de su madre. En la versión de los padres, éstos contestan los ítems refiriéndose a cómo es su conducta concreta con su hijo/a. Todas las puntuaciones mostraron una adecuada consistencia interna; la validez convergente y discriminante se apoya en las correlaciones con el IP-PA (Armsden y Greenberg, 1987), PAQ (Buri, 1991) y 4E (Palacios, 1994). Además, se halló una baja concordancia entre la información aportada por los padres y sus hijos, lo que sugiere la necesidad de evaluar los estilos educativos parentales desde ambas perspectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(4): 678-684, nov. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14565</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis psicométrico de dos escalas para evaluar estilos educativos parentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
