<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90417</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive study on the outcome of clinical care of the type 2 diabetes population in the Community of Madrid. Type 2 diabetes follow-up (ESD-2)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To study the level of control of cardiovascular risk factors, and prevalence of chronic complications in type 2 diabetic (T2D) patients in daily practice in the Community of Madrid. Design. An epidemiological cross-sectional study in T2D patients attending 51 general practitioner clinics, with the participation of 134 health professionals from all the health areas in the Madrid Community. The sample was obtained by systematic sampling. Measurements. Sociodemographic, biological/biochemical processes and outcomes of the clinical care were recorded. For the statistical analysis the software SPSS 15.0 was used. Results. A total of 3268 T2D patients were studied, 50.3% men and 49.7% women, mean age 68.8±10.9 years, and with a mean duration of diabetes of 7.9±7.4 years and a median of 6 years. High blood pressure was observed in 70.4% of T2D patients, and 48.4% were obese. Mean systolic blood pressure was 131.7±14.5 mmHg, and 35.3% of patients had a systolic pressure less than 130 mmHg. Mean diastolic pressure was 76.1±9 mmHg, and in 51.4% of the patients it was below 80 mmHg. A systolic/diastolic blood pressure below 130/80 mmHg was found in 25.3% of T2D patients. A high prevalence of macrovascular complications (18.3%) was found in our study. No differences in the prevalence was found for chronic complications of diabetes compared with that previously published, except for retinopathy, with a prevalence of 8% in our study, probably reflecting a low case register. Conclusions. The level of integrated control in T2D (HbA1C &lt; 7%, LDL &lt; 100 and BP &lt; 130/80 mmHg), was only observed in 4.5% of the patients. The study shows the difficulty of achieving integral control of T2D patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinero, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abanades, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsa, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogales, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamarrón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñera, Marbella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Clotilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Carretero, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusiones. El grado de control integral (hemoglobina glucosilada &lt; 7%, lipoproteínas de baja densidad &lt; 100 y presión arterial &lt; 130/80 mmHg) sólo lo alcanza el 4,5% de la población. En nuestro estudio son evidentes las dificultades de alcanzar un control integral del paciente con DM2(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;27(2): 53-60, mar.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de la evolución clínico-asistencial de la población con diabetes tipo 2 en la Comunidad de Madrid. Estudio de seguimiento diabético tipo 2 (ESD-2)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
