<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89463</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do general practitioners follow the therapeutical recommendations of cystitis in women?. INURA study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The management of lower urinary tract infections varies from physician to physician. The aim of this study was to assess whether general practitioners follow the evidence-based guidelines for the management of cystitis in women. Methods: Cross-sectional study carried out from March to July 2009 in which physicians consecutively registered in a template during a 8-week period the first six episodes of cystitis by means attended at the medical consultation. Age, episode of infection, associated morbidity, antibiotic prescription, and type of antibiotic course (short or long regimen) were determined. Results: Out of 176 physicians invited to participate, 110 included 658 women with lower urinary tract infections with antibiotic treatment being administered in 634 cases. Short courses were given to 385 women (60.7%) and 249 women were given long schedules (39.3%). A total of 343 out of all noncomplicated cystitis were treated with short courses (62.9%) and 75 out of complicated cystitis were treated with long courses (66.4%). First-choice antibiotics were administered as empiric treatment in only 111 women (17.5%). Conclusions: These results highlight a poor adherence of general practitioners to current recommendations of clinical practice guidelines in cystitis with a low utilization of first-choice antibiotics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maria Cots, JOsep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabanaque, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llor, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Existe variabilidad entre los médicos de Atención Primaria en el manejo de las infecciones del tracto urinario. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar si los médicos de Atención Primaria siguen las recomendaciones terapéuticas en el manejo de las cistitis de la mujer. Métodos: Estudio transversal realizado de marzo a julio de 2009 en el que participaron médicos de Atención Primaria de España que registraron en una hoja de recogida de datos durante ocho semanas las 6 primeras cistitis atendidas en la consulta. Se determinaron edad, episodio de la infección, antecedentes, tratamiento antibiótico y tipo de pauta antibiótica (corta o larga). Resultados: Fueron invitados a participar en este estudio un total de 176 médicos, de los cuales 110 incluyeron 658 mujeres con infecciones del tracto urinario, de las que en 634 casos se administró tratamiento antibiótico. Un total de 385 pautas prescritas fueron cortas (60,7%) y 249 fueron largas (39,3%). Un total de 343 pautas administradas en las cistitis no complicadas fueron cortas (62,9%) y en 75 de las infecciones complicadas se indicaron pautas largas (66,4%). Sólo en 111 casos se pautaron de forma empírica antibióticos de primera elección a la dosis y pauta definidas (17,5%). Conclusiones: Estos resultados demuestran un pobre seguimiento de los médicos a las recomendaciones actuales de las guías de práctica clínica en la cistitis con una baja utilización de antibióticos de primera elección(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;24(2): 79-83, jun.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Siguen los médicos de Atención Primaria las recomendaciones terapéuticas de las cistitis en la mujer? Estudio INURA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3574^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3574^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
