<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039191</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Digitalis intoxication secondary to treatment with clarithromycin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The goal of this study was to investigate the percentage of patients concurrently receiving digoxin and clarithromycin who exhibited serum digoxin concentrations above the therapeutic range because of a likely interaction between both drugs, and whether digitalis intoxication ensued. Method: A descriptive, retrospective study carried out from January 2002 to December 2003 in all inpatients concurrently receiving digoxin and clarithromycin whose serum digoxin concentrations were monitored by the Pharmacy Department&#146;s Pharmacokinetics Section. Results: Twenty-six patients having received digoxin and clarithromycin concurrently during their hospital stay were included in the study. Of these, 12 patients (46.2%) had serum digoxin concentrations above the therapeutic range: 7 received digoxin indoses unsuited for their age and/or renal function, and 2 fell short of the mean period of time considered adequate for an interaction to occur. Therefore, only 3 patients had serum digoxin concentrations above the therapeutic range, probably because of an interaction with clarithromycin, and all three had digitalis intoxication symptoms. Conclusions: According to the results of our study, 11.5% of patients concurrently receiving digoxin and clarithromycin had serum digoxin concentrations above the therapeutic range because of a likely interaction between these two drugs, with digitalis intoxication ensuing. Thus, we deem it necessary to monitor serum digoxin concentrations in patients receiving clarithromycin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Díaz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Silveira, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonilla Porras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramallal Jiménez del Llano, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucena Campillo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio es conocer el porcentaje de pacientes en tratamiento simultáneo con digoxina y claritromicina que presentaron concentraciones séricas de digoxina superiores al rango terapéutico debido a una probable interacción entre ambos fármacos y como consecuencia si existió intoxicación digitálica. Método: Estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo realizado entre enero de 2002 y diciembre de 2003 de todos aquellos pacientes que durante su ingreso hospitalario fueron tratados simultáneamente con digoxina y claritromicina y cuyas concentraciones séricas de digoxina fueron monitorizadas por la sección de farmacocinética del servicio de farmacia. Resultados: Se incluyeron en el estudio 26 pacientes que habían recibido con comitantemente digoxina y claritromicina durante su estancia en el hospital. De ellos, 12 pacientes (46,2%) tuvieron concentraciones séricas de digoxina superiores al rango terapéutico: 7 tenían una dosis de digoxina no adecuada para su edad y/o función renal y 2 no superaban el tiempo medio considerado suficiente para que tuviera lugar la interacción. Por lo tanto, sólo 3 pacientes tuvieron concentraciones séricas de digoxina superiores al rango terapéutico debido probablemente a la interacción con claritromicina y los tres presentaron síntomas de intoxicación digitálica. Conclusiones: Según los resultados de nuestro estudio un 11,5% de los pacientes en tratamiento simultáneo con digoxina y claritromicina presentaron concentraciones séricas de digoxina superiores al rango terapéutico, debido a una probable interacción entre ambos fármacos, y como consecuencia tuvo lugar la intoxicación digitálica. Por ello consideramos necesaria la monitorización de las concentraciones séricas de digoxina en pacientes tratados con claritromicina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;29(3): 209-213, may.-jun. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intoxicación digitálica secundaria al tratamiento con claritromicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4109^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30785^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
