<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105996</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivations for adolescent pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify the motivations (beliefs, values) for adolescent pregnancy among girls aged lessthan 17 years old.Method: We performed a phenomenological qualitative study with audio recording of in-depth interviewswith12pregnant adolescents betweenMarchandSeptember 2008. Purposive sampling ofpregnantadolescents (14-16 years) in the high-risk obstetric unit of the Hospital of Jaen (Spain) was performed,using education, voluntariness of pregnancy, urban-rural setting of the family residence and familysocioeconomic status as heterogeneity criteria. A content analysis was performed with coding, triangulation of categories, and extraction and veri&amp;#64257;cation of results.Results: The adolescent&#146;s sociocultural context was of considerable weight in sexual and reproductivedecisions. Adolescents with unplanned pregnancies felt that their responsibility was relative, showingan attitude of acceptance and resignation, which later became a tendency to rationalize the events andclaim that the child was wanted or even planned. Girls with a wanted pregnancy did not have a clear ideaof the consequences of having a child. Previous ideas about pregnancy were mainly related to physicalchanges without taking into account other changes that occur during and after pregnancy.Conclusions: The family context and socialization of girls are based on a traditional division of genderroles in which the traditional role of the female caregiver is strongly internalized. The reasons for teenagepregnancy are unclear; pregnant adolescents lacked a sense of self-determination and felt that their liveswere determined by circumstances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor Moreno, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Olalla, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Nieto, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Abad, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Martos, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer las motivaciones (creencias, valores) de las mujeres menores de 17 años para el embarazo adolescente.MétodoDiseño cualitativo fenomenológico con audiograbación de entrevistas en profundidad (12 adolescentes embarazadas), entre marzo y septiembre de 2008. Muestreo intencional de adolescentes embarazadas (14-16 años) de la consulta de alto riesgo obstétrico del Complejo Hospitalario de Jaén (España), usando nivel educativo, voluntariedad del embarazo, hábitat de residencia y nivel social de la familia como criterios de heterogeneidad. Análisis de contenido: codificación, triangulación de categorías y obtención/verificación de resultados.ResultadosEl contexto sociocultural de la adolescente tiene un peso considerable en la toma de decisiones sexuales y reproductivas. Las adolescentes que no planearon su embarazo perciben que su responsabilidad es relativa, y muestran una actitud de conformismo y resignación, resultando posteriormente una tendencia a la racionalización de los acontecimientos en la que afirman que el hijo/a es deseado/a e incluso planeado/a. Las adolescentes que deseaban su embarazo no tienen una imagen definida ni valoran las consecuencias que éste supone. Las ideas previas sobre una gestación están básicamente referidas a cambios físicos, sin tener en cuenta otros cambios que ocurren durante y tras el embarazo.ConclusionesEl contexto familiar y de socialización de las chicas se basa en una distribución tradicional de roles en función del género, en el cual posicionamiento y rol tradicional de mujer cuidadora está muy interiorizado. Las motivaciones para el embarazo adolescente no están claras; hay una falta de sentido de la autodeterminación y son las circunstancias las que deciden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(6): 497-503, Nov. -Dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Motivaciones para el embarazo adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
