<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131296</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are there psychosocial benefits for Pilates practice? An analysis of the scientific literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last 5 years, the analyzed databases show a remarkable increase in the number of publications on Pilates. the enormous popularity of Pilates may be due to physical and psychological benefits that people could get to their practice. From the scientific field, there is a need to evaluate objectively the existing results on the potential benefits of the Pilates Method. So this work is to check whether there is a sufficient scientific basis to justify their psychological health benefits practitioners. For this we have performed a systematic search, using as search criteria the word &#147;Pilates&#148; in databases: Science Direct, Pubmed, Lilacs, PsycARTICLES, CSIC-ISOCand Dialnet. Among the psychological variables that have been studied the most relevant have proven the quality of life, depression, mood, generalized self-efficacy and aspects of sleep. Also taking into account the peculiarities of the method itself will narrow future research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boix Vilella, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Zarceño, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Rosa, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos 5 años, las bases de datos analizadas muestran un notable incremento en el número de publicaciones sobre Pilates. La enorme difusión y popularidad del método Pilates podría deberse a los beneficios físicos, psíquicos y sociales que las personas podrían obtener con su práctica. Desde el ámbito científico, existe la necesidad de actualizar y evaluar objetivamente los resultados ya existentes sobre los posibles beneficios que puede producir la práctica de Pilates sobre la salud. Esta revisión, pretende comprobar si hay una suficiente fundamentación científica que justifique sus beneficios en la salud psicológica de los practicantes de Pilates. Para ello se ha realizado una búsqueda sistemática, utilizando como criterio de búsqueda la palabra &#147;Pilates&#148;, en las bases de datos: ScienceDirect, Pubmed, Lilacs, Psyc ARTICLES, CSIC-ISOC y Dialnet. Entre las variables psicoló-gicas que han sido estudiadas las más relevantes han resultado ser la calidad de vida, la depresión, el estado de ánimo, la auto eficacia generalizada y los aspectos relativos al sueño. Por otro lado, teniendo en cuenta las singularidades del propio método se van a exponer futuras líneas de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(3): 117-128, sept.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Hay beneficios psicosociales por la práctica Pilates? Un análisis de la literatura científica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
