<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050075</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The caring process in cancer: needs and propects of the recipients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer is currently one of the most relevant health problems because its high frequency, risingincidence and chronic nature. It is necessary to evaluate how care is applied to cancer patients in orderto develop strategies aimed at incorporating the patients' prospects to the care provision measures.The use of semi-structured interviews as a qualitative method facilitates the analysis about howoncological patients perceive the administered care, and permits to recognize the strong and weakpoints of it.The screening and diagnostic stages were identified as the most difficult moments of theoncological care process. Other aspects to be improved were found in relation to the absence ofpsychological support, appropriate everyday material conditions, and adequate continuity of posthospitalcare</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabeza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suess, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallicer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La identificación del cáncer como uno de los problemas sanitarios más relevantes, su creciente incidenciay carácter como enfermedad crónica apuntan hacia la necesidad de una evaluación de su procesoasistencial y el desarrollo de estrategias de mejora bajo la inclusión de la perspectiva de los usuarios.El análisis de la calidad percibida por pacientes oncológicos en diferentes fases del proceso asistenciala través de una metodología cualitativa (entrevistas semiestructuradas) permite identificar fortalezasy debilidades y ayudar al diseño de estrategias de mejora del proceso asistencial de cáncer.Como momento de mayor dificultad dentro del proceso asistencial oncológico se nombra la fase dedetección y diagnóstico. La falta de atención psicológica, condiciones tangibles adecuadas y continuidadasistencial posthospitalaria constituyen otros puntos de mejora</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;29(9): 357-367, jun. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El proceso asistencial de cáncer: necesidades y expectativas de los usuarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29924^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
