<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050007</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the body mass index a good predictor of excess body fat and cardiovascular risk in children and adolescents?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Body mass index (BMI) values vary during childhood and adolescence depending on age and gender. The BMI is the parameter most frequently used for the screening of excess body fat because it is easy to determine and it tends to correlate well with body fat. International Obesity Task Force(IOTF) BMI cut off points for the definition of excess weight and obesity have recently been proposed for each age and sex, corresponding to adult BMI values of 25 and 30 at the age of 18 years. In addition to excess body fat, the BMI has been correlated with various components of metabolic syndrome: dyslipidemia, hypertension, insulin resistance/hyperinsulinemai and impaired glucosetolerance/type 2 diabetes. The BMI is not a reliable predictor of the percent fat mass at the individual level, but is a good index of adiposity. Nevertheless, despite its acceptable sensitivity and specificity, the BMI may classify as obese or overweight individuals who do not really have excess adiposity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Aznar, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Vela, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fleta Zaragozano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El índice de masa corporal (IMC) varía considerablemente durante la infancia y la adolescencia según la edad y el sexo. El IMC es el parámetro que más frecuentemente se utiliza para predecir el exceso de grasa corporal porque se determina fácilmente y se correlaciona bien con la adiposidad. Recientemente, se han propuesto los puntos de corte internacionaleds e IMC(International Obesity Task Force) para la definición de sobrepeso y obesidad en niños y adolescentes, para cada edad y sexo. Además de con el exceso de grasa corporal, el IMC se correlaciona con varios componentes del síndrome metabólico: dislipemia, hipertensión, resistencia a la insulina/hiperinsulinismoe intolerancia a los carbohidratos/diabetes mellitus tipo 2. El IMC no es capaz de predecir con fiabilidad el porcentaje de masa grasa específicamente en un individuo, pero es un buen indicador indirecto de adiposidad. Por otro lado, pese a su aceptable sensibilidad y especificidad, puede clasificar como obesos o con sobrepeso a los individuos que no tengan realmente exceso de grasa corporal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(10): 476-481, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050007</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El índice de masa corporal, ¿predice adecuadamente el nivel de adiposidad y el riesgo cardiovascular en niños y adolescentes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
