<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039197</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement in quality of life and adverse effects in patients with chronic arterial occlusive disease treated with alprostadil alpha-cyclodextrin through the peripheral venous route</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate local and systemic complications in patients treated with alprostadil alpha-cyclodextrin (AAC) through the peripheral venous route, as well as changes in the quality of life of these patients. Method. A descriptive, observational, prospective study was performed. All patients admitted to the Angiology and Vascular Surgery Unit of the University Hospital of Albacete who fulfilled the criteria for therapeutic indication of AAC administration between September 2001 and April 2002 were included. Each patient received the treatment according to a protocol previously established through consensus in the unit. Sociodemographic variables, associated disease, type and degree of arterial disease, local and systemic complications with administration of each of the cycles, and quality of life at the beginning and end of the treatment were studied. Results. Forty-four patients were studied. A total of 65.5% had arterial disease in the most advanced stage. The most frequent systemic complications were allergic reactions and nausea; treatment had to be discontinued in 11.4% of patients. Local complications consisted of pain and erythema in the area of the venous line (mean 1.29 every 10 treatment doses); there was a mean of 0.97 line changes every 10 doses and 38.6% of the changes was due to phlebitis. The results of the EUROQOL questionnaire showed improvement in: mobility, ability to perform personal care, ability to perform daily activities, pain, and anxiety/depression. Conclusions. Treatment with AAC according to the established protocol is safe and improves perceived quality of life</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Risueño Álvarez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córcoles Jiménez, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia Gil, MarÍa Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita Toledo, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros Sáez, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomariz García, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Gómez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar las complicaciones locales y sistémicas que se presentan en pacientes tratados con alprostadil-alfa-ciclodextrina (AAC) por vía venosa periférica, así como los cambios que se producen en la calidad de vida de estos pacientes. Método. Estudio descriptivo observacional prospectivo. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes ingresados en la Unidad de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Albacete que cumplían los criterios de indicación terapéutica para la administración de AAC entre septiembre de 2001 y abril de 2002. Cada paciente recibió el tratamiento según un protocolo previamente consensuado en la Unidad. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas, enfermedades asociadas, tipo y nivel de la enfermedad arterial, complicaciones locales y sistémicas en la administración de cada uno de los ciclos, calidad de vida al inicio y final del tratamiento. Resultados. Se estudiaron 44 pacientes. El 65,5% presentaba enfermedad arterial en su estadio más avanzado. Las complicaciones sistémicas más frecuentes fueron las reacciones alérgicas y las náuseas; el tratamiento tuvo que ser suspendido en el 11,4% de los casos. Como complicaciones locales aparecieron dolor y eritema en la vía venosa (media de 1,29 por cada 10 dosis de tratamiento); se cambió la vía 0,97 veces de media cada 10 dosis, el 38,6% de las veces debido a flebitis. Los resultados del cuestionario EUROQOL muestran mejoría en movilidad, capacidad para el cuidado personal, capacidad para realizar actividades cotidianas, dolor y ansiedad/depresión. Conclusiones. El tratamiento con AAC según el protocolo establecido ofrece seguridad a los pacientes y produce una notable mejora en la calidad de vida percibida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(4): 206-212, jul. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejoría de la calidad de vida y efectos adversos en pacientes con enfermedad arterial obstructiva crónica tratados con alprostadil-alfa-ciclodextrina por vía venosa periférica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9517^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23226^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23226^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
