<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122497</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bicycle use and protective use of helmets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The Spanish government issued a proposal of a law to mandate the use of helmet for bicycle riders in the cities; this law generated significant controversy and was eventually amended to mandate the use of helmets to riders younger than 18 years of age only. Objective. To review the status of the legislation on the use of helmet for bicycle riders globally, and to describe the profile of the riders, the mechanisms of accident and its resulting major injuries, and the  protective effect of the helmet and its regulatory framework. Method. Literature review using the PubMed database including articles related to bicycle helmet use in the last 15 years in the English or Spanish language. Results. There is not a uniform approach to the regulation of helmet use for bicycle riders in the different countries. Young men are the most common users of bicycles in the cities. Falls without another vehicle involved in the accident are the most common events (77.5%), and the most common lesions are those resulting from head and upper extremity trauma (both around 40%). The helmets sold in Europe comply with the rule EN 1078:1996. Most  studies confirm the protective effect of the helmet in craniofacial trauma. The pediatric population is especially susceptible of suffering head trauma; the use of the helmet in this age group may offer better protection than in adults. Conclusion. The bicycle helmet is very useful in the prevention of head trauma and its use should be recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Roig, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mur Sierra, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El gobierno español realizó la propuesta de ley de obligar al uso del casco ciclista en las ciudades, medida que generó una fuerte opinión en contra, y que finalmente ha quedado  reducida a los menores de 18 años. Objetivo. Conocer la situación global de la legislación del casco ciclista, los usuarios de la bicicleta, los mecanismos de accidente y las  principales lesiones, el efecto protector del casco y su regulación. Método. Búsqueda bibliográfica, principalmente a través de la base de datos PubMed, de los artículos más relevantes relacionados con el uso del casco ciclista en los últimos 15 años y en lengua inglesa o española. Resultados. Entre los diferentes países no hay unanimidad en obligaral uso del casco ciclista. Los hombres jóvenes son los principales usuarios de la bicicleta. Las caídas sin implicar a otro vehículo son el mecanismo de accidente más habitual (77,5%) y las lesiones más frecuentes son los traumatismos craneales y las  lesiones de las extremidades superiores (ambas cerca de un 40%). Los cascos ciclistas vendidos en Europa se rigen por la norma EN 1078:1996. La mayoría de estudios confirman el papel protector del casco en las lesiones craneales y de la zona alta y media facial. La población pediátrica es especialmente susceptible a sufrir un traumatismo craneal y el casco puede ofrecer mayor protección que en adultos. Conclusión. El casco ciclista es útil en la prevención de las lesiones craneales y hay que recomendar su uso universal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;74(1): 15-20, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de la bicicleta y utilidad protectora del casco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6411^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
