<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046969</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do our patients sleep well?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies appear to confirm that the rest and sleep pattern isaltered during the hospital stay. Many factors are involved in the alteredsleep pattern of the hospitalised patient. These factors can be dividedinto two main groups: internal and external.Objective: to determine how well hospitalised patients sleep and toidentify what factors, in the patients´ opinions, make their rest and sleepdifficult.Material and methods: a descriptive study was conducted on adultpatients hospitalised in general units using a self-designed questionnairethat compiled data on the difficulties perceived to sleep and to rest andthe internal and external factors associated with such ability.Results: 249 patients were studied, 45% of which (111) had difficultyto sleep whilst in hospital and 35% (87) experienced difficulties to sleepin their own house. Factors deriving from the health problem and surroundingsaffect sleep patterns the most, followed by those relating tocomfort and nursing care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Arce, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escoda Pellisa, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Villarroya, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Nicolás, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martín, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá Miravete, M. Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varios estudios parecen confirmar que el patrón de descanso y sueñoestá alterado durante el ingreso hospitalario. Son muchos los factoresimplicados en la alteración del sueño del paciente ingresado, pero estosse pueden dividir en dos grandes grupos: internos y externos.Objetivo: conocer cómo duermen los pacientes ingresados e identificarqué factores, en opinión de los pacientes, dificultan el descanso y sueño;Material y método: se realizó un estudio descriptivo con pacientesadultos hospitalizados en unidades generales, mediante un cuestionariode elaboración propia, que recoge datos sobre las dificultades percibidaspara el sueño y el descanso y los factores internos y externos asociadosa la misma.Resultados: han sido estudiados 249 pacientes, de los cuales un 45%(111) tuvo dificultades para dormir en el hospital y el 35% (87) tenía dificultadespara dormir en el domicilio. Los factores derivados del problemade salud y los del entorno, son los que más dificultan el sueño, seguidosde los relacionados con el confort y los cuidados enfermeros</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(4): 68-73, mayo 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo duermen nuestros pacientes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12566</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
