<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103379</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of concordance between the bioelectrical impedance vector analysis and the bioelectrical impedance spectroscopy in haemodialysis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The values of body composition provided by the two most commonly used bioelectrical impedance systems in Spain, single-frequency bioelectrical impedance vector analysis (SF-BIVA) and multi-frequency bioelectrical impedance spectroscopy (MF-BIS) are different and not comparable. Objective: Analyse whether the inter-method variability is due to bioelectrical variables measured by the different monitors, or rather due to the equations used to calculate body volume and mass. Another objective was to determine whether, despite the inter-method variability, the classification of hydration status by the two methods is consistent. Material and Methods: Bioelectrical impedance was measured by SF-BIVA and MF-BIS immediately before a dialysis session in 54 patients on haemodialysis. In 38 patients, the study was repeated by SF-BIVA at the end of the same dialysis session. Results: Resistance and phase angle values provided by the two monitors at a frequency of 50kHz were consistent. For resistance, variability was 1.3% and the intra-class correlation coefficient was 0.99. For phase angle, variability and the intra-class correlation coefficient were 11.5% and 0.92, respectively. The volume values  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomis-Couto, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Roso, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Mendiola, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera-Gorrin, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lucas, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quereda, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teruel-Briones, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ramírez, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los valores de los compartimentos corporales proporcionados por los dos sistemas de bioimpedancia más utilizados en España (bioimpedancia de monofrecuencia vectorial [BIVA] y bioimpedancia multifrecuencia espectroscópica [BIS]) son diferentes y no pueden intercambiarse. Objetivo: Analizar si la variabilidad intermétodo es debida a la diferente lectura de las variables bioeléctricas realizadas por los monitores o a las ecuaciones utilizadas por cada uno de ellos para el cálculo de los volúmenes y masas corporales. Otro objetivo fue comprobar si, a pesar de la variabilidad intermétodo, la clasificación de los estados de hidratación definidos por ambos monitores es concordante. Material y métodos: Estudio de corte transversal. En 54 enfermos tratados con hemodiálisis se hizo un análisis de bioimpedancia con los monitores BIVA y BIS inmediatamente antes de una sesión de diálisis. En 38 de ellos se repitió el estudio con el monitor BIVA al finalizar la misma sesión de diálisis. Resultados: Los datos de resistencia y ángulo de fase proporcionados por el monitor BIVA y por el monitor BIS a la frecuencia de 50 kHz son concordantes. En el caso de la resistencia, la variabilidad es de 1,3%, y el coeficiente de correlación intraclase, de 0,99. Para el ángulo de fase, la variabilidad es del 11,5%, y el coeficiente de  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;32(3): 389-395, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de concordancia entre la bioimpedancia vectorial y la espectroscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
