<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043007</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Brain metastases of endometrial carcinoma in a young woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of brain metastases preceding diagnosis of the primary tumor in a 43-year-old woman without risk factors for endometrial carcinoma. Histological examination and immunohistochemical studies revealed a poorly differentiated endometrial adenocarcinoma with highly vascular areas identified by factor VIII-positive cells. Although brain metastases have been described early in the course of the disease and in patients without suspected endometrial cancer, such cases are uncommon. In women of this age with bleeding disturbances, endometrial carcinoma is not usually suspected as the primary cause. The disturbance is normally treated with hormone therapy, which can delay diagnosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seco-Navedo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llaneza-Coto, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo-Onia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de metástasis cerebral de cáncer de endometrio precediendo al diagnóstico del tumor primario en una paciente de 43 años, sin factores de riesgo para cáncer de endometrio. Los estudios anatomopatológicos diagnosticaron un adenocarcinoma endometrial pobremente diferenciado, con importantes áreas vasculares demostradas mediante positividad para el factor VIII. Aunque se han descrito metástasis intracraneales en casos de estadios tempranos de la enfermedad o en mujeres sin sospecha de cáncer endometrial, su presentación es excepcional. Cuando encontramos sangrados irregulares a esa edad, no solemos sospechar la existencia de cáncer y es habitual que se intente regularlos con terapia hormonal, lo que puede retrasar el diagnóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(2): 82-84, feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043007</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis cerebral de cáncer de endometrio en paciente joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
