<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113694</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of anticoagulation measured using the Inratio® device in samples obtained fromthe arteriovenous fi stula compared to capillary samples</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Monitoring of patients treated with Sintrom® has evolved towards capillary blood testing as it is easier to draw blood, less painful, cheaper and immediate results are available. In each haemodialysis session we draw blood from an arteriovenous fistula, which provides a sample for monitoring treatment with Sintrom®, reducing the number of venous punctures without increasing the nursing workload. Objective To compare the INR results determined using the INRatio® method in capillary and arteriorvenous blood samples. Material and methods Seven patients with an arteriovenous fi stula and on Sintrom® anticoagulation were studied. Three samples were compared: one peripheral, analysed in the laboratory, and the other two using the INRATIO ® method for INR analysis in capillary blood. One of the samples was drawn according to the manufacturer&#146;s recommendations, and the other was drawn from the vascular access according to the unit&#146;s protocol. Results The mean INR determined in the capillary sample was 2.5 ±1; arteriovenous fistula 2.1 ±0.4 and laboratory 2.1 ±0.4. There were no significant statistical or clinical differences. Conclusion The use of the INRatio® method for determining capillary INR with vascular access samples would be appropriate in haemodialysis as it is equally reliable as the traditional methods. The use of INRATIO measurement device with samples drawn from the arteriovenous fistula presents benefi ts of facility of access to the sample, simplicity in determining and immediacy in obtaining results, convenience and an economic saving for the healthcare system(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arribas Cobo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Puerta, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz Santolaya, Alfredo José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Martín, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de Argote Cervera, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerrajero Calero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los controles a pacientes tratados con Sintrom® han evolucionado hacia métodos de determinación en sangre capilar por ser más fácil de extraer, menos cruento, más barato y tener resultados inmediatos. En cada sesión de hemodiálisis extraemos sangre de una fístula arteriovenosa lo que facilita una muestra para el control del tratamiento con Sintrom® disminuyendo el número de punciones venosas sin aumentar la carga de trabajo de enfermería. Objetivo Comparar los resultados de INR determinados con el método INRatio® en muestras sanguíneas capilares y arteriovenosa. Material y métodos Se estudiaron 7 pacientes anticoagulados con Sintrom ®, portadores de fístula arteriovenosa. Se compararon 3 muestras, una periférica, analizada en el laboratorio y otras 2 utilizando el método INRATIO® para análisis de INR en sangre capilar. Una de las muestras fue extraída según recomendaciones del fabricante, y otra extraída del acceso vascular según protocolo de la unidad. Resultados El INR medio determinado en la muestra capilar fue 2.5 ±1; Fístula arteriovenosa 2.1 ±0.4 y laboratorio 2.1 ±0.4. No existieron diferencias ni estadísticas ni clínicas significativas. Conclusión La utilización del método INRatio® de determinación de INR capilar con muestras del acceso vascular sería adecuado en hemodiálisis al ser igual de fiable que los métodos tradicionales. El uso del medidor INRATIO con muestra extraída de la fístula arteriovenosa presenta unos beneficios de facilidad de acceso a la muestra, sencillez en la determinación, inmediatez en los resultados, comodidad y un ahorro económico para el sistema sanitario(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;16(2): 99-103, abr.-jun.2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113694</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la anticoagulación medida con el dispositivo Inratio®, en muestras obtenidasde la fístula arteriovenosa frente a muestras capilares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
