<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137063</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An update of the management of antiplatelet and antithrombotic therapy for interventional technics in chronic pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Interventional pain physicians usually face situations were,  the patients that are going to be under an interventional procedure, are undergoing an antiplatelet or anticoagulant therapy.  Bleeding complications can be catastrophic when we talk about  deep blocks and interventions into the spinal canal. However,  the risk of thromboembolic events increases with the improper  discontinuation of antiplatelet and anticoagulant drugs in those  patients.  Nowadays, there are no algorithms or updated recommendations on the handling of those patients in the chronic pain  area. The goal of this article is to offer some recommendations  on how to use, in a safety way, those drugs depending on the  type of intervention and patient, with the objective of minimizing the risk of bleeding complications without increasing the  risk of thromboembolic events. To do this, the latest news on  the use of drugs which alters the hemostasis in regional anesthesia and other chronic pain technics had been reviewed, including different guides on the perioperative management (ASRA,  ESA, SEDAR, etc.). There is fair evidence that the risk of thromboembolic phenomenon increases on those patients whom discontinues their  antiplatelet therapy, and that this risk is even higher than the  risk of epidural hematomas on those patients whom continues  with their treatment, even though both risks are significant.  There is also good evidence of the incidence of spontaneous  epidural hematomas, associated or not to a traumatic puncture,  in patients with or without an antithrombotic therapy.  Those spontaneous epidural hematomas are more likely associated to favorable factors such as: Excessive manipulation,  the use of larger gauge needles, the use of catheters, procedures  into the cervical spinal canal, elderly patients, and vascular and  anatomical abnormalities of the patient. There is a less conservative tendency about intervals of discontinuation of antiplatelet drugs in high risk patients (3 days  for Aspirin®, 5 days for clopidogrel), while the use of heparin  and classic oral anticoagulants practically has not changed. Recently, new oral anticoagulants, not included in most  of these guides, have appeared (dabigatran, rivaroxaban and  apixaban) with a higher security profile than Sintrom®, usually  without the need of heparin bridging therapy after discontinuation of the drug. The inconvenience is that there is limited evidence about its perioperative use. That is why it &amp;#769;s suspension is  actually based on its strict pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics characteristics (2 days, being higher if there exists a decline  in renal function) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero Trujillano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendiola de la Osa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellejero Collado, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Insausti Valdivia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los especialistas en dolor crónico nos enfrentamos habitualmente a situaciones en las que los pacientes que van a ser sometidos a procedimientos intervencionistas están bajo tratamiento antiagregante o anticoagulante. Las complicaciones hemorrágicas pueden ser catastróficas cuando se trata de bloqueos profundos y técnicas dentro del canal espinal. Sin embargo, el riesgo de eventos tromboembólicos aumenta con la suspensión inadecuada de los fármacos antiagregantes y anticoagulantes en estos pacientes. A día de hoy no existen unos algoritmos o recomendaciones actualizadas para el manejo de estos pacientes en el área de dolor crónico. El objetivo de este documento es ofrecer unas recomendaciones de seguridad sobre el manejo de estos fármacos según el tipo de intervención y el tipo de paciente, con el objetivo de minimizar el riesgo de complicaciones hemorrágicas sin aumentar el riesgo de eventos tromboembólicos. Para ello, se han revisado las últimas publicaciones sobre el manejo fármacos que alteran la hemostasia en anestesia regional y otras técnicas de dolor crónico, incluyendo diferentes guías de manejo perioperatorio (ASRA, ESA, SEDAR...). Existe buena evidencia en el incremento del riesgo de eventos tromboembólicos en pacientes que suspenden la terapia antiagregante, y que este riesgo es mayor que el de la incidencia de hematomas epidurales en pacientes que continúan con el tratamiento, si bien ambos riesgos son significativos. Así mismo, existe buena evidencia de la incidencia de hematomas pidurales espontáneos asociados o no a punción traumática, en pacientes con o sin terapia antitrombótica. Estos hematomas epidurales espontáneos están asociados a factores favorecedores como la manipulación excesiva, el uso de agujas de mayor calibre, el uso de catéteres, los procedimientos sobre el canal cervical, la edad avanzada, y las anormalidades vasculares y anatómicas del paciente. Hay una tendencia menos conservadora hacia los intervalos de interrupción de los fármacos antiagregantes en pacientes de alto riesgo (Aspirina® 3 días, clopidogrel 5 días), si bien el manejo de heparinas y anticoagulantes orales clásicos prácticamente no ha cambiado. Recientemente han surgido nuevos anticoagulantes orales no contemplados en muchas de estas guías (dabigatran, rivaroxaban, apixaban) con mayor perfil de seguridad que el Sintrom®, habitualmente sin necesidad de terapia puente con heparinas tras la suspensión del fármaco. El inconveniente es que existe escasa documentación en la literatura sobre su manejo perioperatorio, por lo que su suspensión se basa actualmente en sus características farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas estrictas (2 días, siendo mayor si existe insuficiencia renal) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;22(3): 126-133, mayo-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de antiagregantes y anticoagulantes en procedimientos intervencionistas de dolor crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
