<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112184</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary vitamin K intake and stability of anticoagulation with coumarins; evidence derived from a clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Dietary vitamin K intake has been considered a major factor that influences stability of oral anticoagulation (OA) with coumarins. Few studies have evaluated the relationship between amounts of dietary vitamin K intake and stability of anticoagulation. Objective: To assess whether high dietary vitamin K intake is associated to stability of International Normalized Ratio (INR) of the prothrombin time. Methods: We performed a sub-analysis of a randomized clinical trial involving outpatients from the anticoagulation clinic of a university hospital. INR and vitamin K intake were prospectively collected at baseline, 15, 30, 60 and 90 days after randomization. Patients were considered with a stable anticoagulation when their INR coefficient of variation was less than 10%. Dietary vitamin K intake was assessed by a food frequency questionnair and a score of intake was derived. Results: We studied 132 patients on chronic OA (57 ± 13 years; 55% males); 23 patients (17%) were achieved stable anticoagulation. Stable and unstable patients had no significant differences in baseline characteristics. The dietary vitamin K score over the entire follow-up for stable patients was significantly lower than that for unstable patients (p = 0.012). Discussion: Our findings suggest that INR stability could be achieved with relatively low amounts of dietary vitamin K (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Assis, MCS de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza, GC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rohde, LE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuchinali, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabelo, ER</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El consumo dietético de vitamina K ha sido considerado un factor importante que influye en la estabilidad de la anticoagulación oral (AO) con cumarina. Pocos estudios han evaluado la relación entre el consumo dietético de vitamina K y la estabilidad de la anticoagulación. Objetivo: Evaluar la relación existente entre la alta ingesta de vitamina K y el mantenimiento de la estabilidade del la Razón Normalizada Internacional RNI. Métodos: Se realizó una subanálisis de un ensayo clínico aleatorizado con pacientes ambulatórios de la clínica de anticoagulación de un hospital universitario. Los datos acerca del RNI y la ingesta de vitamina K fueron recogidos prospectivamente al inicio del estudio, y en los días 15, 30, 60 y 90. Los pacientes fueron considerados estables cuando su coeficiente de variación del RNI fue menor de 10%. La evaluacion de la dieta y la ingesta de vitamina K se obtuvo mediante un cuestionario de frecuencia alimentaria y un sistema de puntuación fue creado para esto. Resultados: Se estudiaron 132 pacientes en tratamiento crónico (57 ± 13 años, el 55% masculino), 23 pacientes (17%) lograron anticoagulación estable. Con relación a las características basales, no hubo diferencias entre los sujetos con anticoagulación estable o inestable. La puntuación de la vitamina K de la dieta durante todo el seguimiento de los pacientes se mantuvo significativamente menor entre aquellos con RNI estable cuándo comparado con los inestables (p = 0,012). Discusión: Nuestros hallazgos sugieren que con cantidades relativamente bajas de vitamina K podremos obtener la estabilidad de RNI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 1987-1992, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo de vitamina K y la estabilidad de la anticoagulación con cumarínicos; evidencia derivada de ensayo clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15261^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15213^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3389^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33561^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
