<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148815</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention in reading processes in pupils with Specific Language Impairment (SLI)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Children with Specific Language Impairment (SLI) encounter significant difficulties in learning to read. The aim of this research was to determine the efficacy of an intervention program on reading processes (letter identification, lexical processes, syntactic processes and semantic processes) in children with SLI. Method: The sample consisted of a total of 34 pupils diagnosed with SLI and 34 children with typical language development. For the selection of the sample, the CELF-3 test, the Peabody test, the Hearing Association and Visual Association subtests of the ITPA and the K-BIT Intelligence test were used. The intervention program consisted of 144 sessions of 40 minutes each, in which oral language activities were combined with other activities related to the automation of basic reading processes and reading sentences and texts. Results: Significant gains were also made in the group of children with SLI versus controls in lexical, syntactic, and semantic reading processes.Conclusions: A combined program of both oral language and reading skills improves reading achievement in pupils with SLI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valle Hernández, Nayarit del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Rodríguez, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Santana, Gustavo M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Bermúdez, Laura de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">(TEL).Antecedentes: los niños con Trastorno Específico del Lenguaje (TEL) tienen importantes dificultades para el aprendizaje de la lectura. El objetivo de esta investigación ha sido comprobar la eficacia de un programa de intervención sobre los procesos lectores (identificación de letras, procesos léxicos, procesos gramaticales y procesos semánticos)  en niños con TEL. Método: la muestra estuvo compuesta por un total de 34 alumnos diagnosticados con TEL y 34 niños con un desarrollo típico del lenguaje. Para la selección de la muestra se utilizaron los tests CELF-3, Peabody,  las subpruebas de Asociación Auditiva y de Asociación Visual del ITPA y el Test de Inteligencia K-BIT. El programa de intervención constó de 144 sesiones, de 40 minutos de duración cada una, en el que se combinaron actividades de lenguaje oral con otras destinadas a la automatización de procesos lectores básicos y de lectura de frases y textos.Resultados: los niños con TEL obtuvieron ganancias significativas frente a los controles en los procesos lectores léxicos, sintácticos y semánticos.  Conclusiones: un programa combinado de lenguaje oral y lectura mejora el rendimiento lector en alumnado con TEL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);28(1): 40-46, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención en procesos lectores en alumnado con Trastorno Específico del Lenguaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7986^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7986^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
