<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103073</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ecais study: inadvertent cardiovascular adverse events in sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the incidence of cardiovascular adverse events in patients with sepsis in its various stages. Design: A longitudinal, descriptive, observational study was carried out. Setting: Intensive care units of two university hospitals in Bogotá (Colombia). Patients: A number of patients consecutively admitted to the adult ICU with a diagnosis of sepsis, and no evidence of previous ischemic myocardial injury. Interventions: Forty-eight hours of electrocardiographic record using Holter technology. Main variables: Ischemia, cardiac arrhythmia, heart rate variability. Results: A total of 100 patients were analyzed, 62% being staged as presenting septic shock. Three percent suffered ischemic events detected by Holter and unnoticed through conventional monitoring. Forty-six percent suffered an arrhythmic event detected by Holter, compared with only 6% as detected by conventional monitoring. Mortality was 40%. All patients showed loss of heart rate variability. Conclusion: In this study patients with sepsis showed a low incidence of cardiovascular ischemic events. In contrast, arrhythmic events showed a high incidence. Conventional monitoring failed to detect any of the ischemic events and most arrhythmic events. In this study, cardiovascular events generated by adrenergic discharge had no impact upon mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Torres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Durán, O. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Estrada, V. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Duque, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enciso Olivera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la incidencia de eventos cardiovasculares adversos en pacientes con diagnóstico de sepsis en sus diferentes estadios. Diseño: Estudio observacional, descriptivo, longitudinal. Ámbito: Unidades de cuidados intensivos de tipo mixto de dos hospitales universitarios en la ciudad de Bogotá. Participantes: Se incluyeron una serie de pacientes mayores de edad, que ingresan a UCI con diagnostico de sepsis, sin evidencia de lesión miocárdica isquémica previa. Intervenciones: Registros electrocardiográficos continuos de 12 derivaciones durante 48 horas con monitoría Holter Variables de interés: Isquemia, arritmia cardiaca, variabilidad de la frecuencia cardiaca. Resultados: Se analizaron 100 pacientes, 62% de los cuales se estadificó como choque séptico. El 3% presentó evento cardiovascular adverso de tipo isquémico detectado por Holter y desapercibido por monitoreo convencional. El 46% presentaron un evento de tipo arrítmico por Holter, comparado con solo un 6% detectado por monitoreo convencional. La mortalidad cruda fue de 40%. El 100% presentó pérdida de la variabilidad de la frecuencia cardiaca. Conclusión: La sepsis en esta experiencia mostró una baja incidencia de eventos cardiovasculares isquémicos. Los eventos arrítmicos, sin embargo, mostraron una incidencia alta. El monitoreo convencional falló en detectar la totalidad de los eventos isquémicos y en mayor proporción los eventos arrítmicos. En esta serie, los eventos cardiovasculares generados por descarga adrenérgica no impactan en la mortalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(5): 343-350, jun.-jul. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103073</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio ECAIS: eventos cardiovasculares adversos inadvertidos en sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29417^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
