<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144543</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of transanal endorrectal descent in Hirschprung&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To present our experience of patients with Hirschsprung disease (HD) operated by transanal endorrectal descent (TED). Methods: A retrospective study performed of TEDs. We correlate fundamentally the aganglionic segment length with: Complications, need for colostomy and surgical approach. Results: Between 2003 and 2012 we performed 73 TED (57 men), 78.6% diagnosed in the neonatal period. The aganglionic segment length evidenced in the enema was correlated with surgical findings in 68.9% of cases, being higher in the short forms than in the long segments (80.9 vs. 44%, P&lt;.001). Four patients required preoperative colostomy. The mean age of surgery was 6.3 months (4.5 to 33.7). Short forms represented 64.4% of cases. The abdominal approach was necessary in 10 patients, 9 of these were long/total colonic aganglionic segment. Postoperative enterocolitis presented in 10,9% (9 patients), with no relation with the length of aganglionic or the existence of residual dysplasia. Obstructions occurred in 19.2% of the long form or pancolonic forms. Currently, of the evaluable patients, 5 present constipationand 12 present occasional leakage. Conclusions: TED is the surgery of choice for patients with HD. The majority can be handled by preoperative «nursing» without colostomy. The diagnostic tests of choice are manometry with suction biopsy. No significant correlation was found between enterocolitis and length of aganglionic segment, although we observed a drastic reduction of postoperative enterocolitis, since the introduction of technical changes, such as the use of postoperative rectal tubes and the posterior section of the cuff muscles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moya, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustín Asensio, Juan Carlos de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Alonso, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valladares, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Criado, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de pacientes con enfermedad de Hirschsprung (EH) intervenidos mediante descenso endorrectal transanal (DET). Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los DET realizados. Correlacionamos, fundamentalmente, longitud del segmento agangliónico, con complicaciones, necesidad de colostomía y vía de abordaje. Resultados: Entre 2003 y 2012 hemos realizado 73 DET (57 varones), 78,6% diagnosticados en el periodo neonatal. La longitud agangliónica objetivada en el enema se correspondió con los hallazgos quirúrgicos en un 68,9% de los casos; esta correspondencia fue mayor en las formas cortas que en las largas o pancolónicas (80,9 vs. 44%; p &lt; 0,001). Cuatro pacientes precisaron colostomía preoperatoria. La edad media al descenso fue de 6,3 meses (rango 4,5-33,7). El 64,4% eran formas cortas. El abordaje abdominal fue necesario en 10 pacientes (13,6%), 9 de ellos aganglionismos largos o pancolónicos. El 10,9% (8 pacientes) ha presentado enterocolitis postoperatoria, sin relación con la longitud agangliónica ni con la existencia de displasia residual. La suboclusión por bridas se presentó en el 19,2% de las formas largas o pancolónicas. Actualmente, de los pacientes valorables, 5 tienen hábito estreñido y 12 presentan escapes ocasionales. Conclusiones: El DET es la cirugía de elección para pacientes con EH. La mayoría pueden manejarse con «nursing» preoperatorio, sin colostomía. Las pruebas diagnósticas de elección son la manometría y la biopsia rectal por succión. No hemos encontrado correlación entre la existencia de enterocolitis y la longitud del segmento agangliónico, aunque hemos observado una reducción drástica de las enterocolitis postoperatorias, desde la introducción de modificaciones técnicas, como la sonda rectal posquirúrgica y la sección posterior del manguito muscular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(9): 561-566, nov. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del descenso endorrectal transanal en la enfermedad de Hirschsprun</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4840^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23206^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
