<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129611</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the flexibility of international kickboxing wrestlers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study aims to assess the flexibility of the muscles of the trunk and lower limbs in different fighter&#146;s competitive kickboxing, which do not perform stretching exercises regularly. Optimal values in this quality are required, by their possible relation to muscle injury and athletic performance. The sample consists of 14 fighters (24.5 } 4.9 years old, 176.4 } 8.2 cm in height and 73.8 } 6.7 kg) of international level (n = 6) and national (n = 8). Was analyzed the mobility in the trunk joint through Sideways bending test, and the Schober and Ott test, in the hip joint tests were applied leg sideward Split, Split leg sideways, Hip abduction, Leg raise, Back saver sit and reach and Sit and reach, and the ankle joint goniometry was used for plantar and dorsal flexion of the foot. The results show higher values than those found in other sports. In the category analysis found significant differences between international and national competitors in the Hip abduction test (p &amp;#8804; 0.05) and dorsal flexion (p &amp;#8804; 0.01) of the non-dominant leg. No differences were observed between the dominant and non-dominant member in any of the groups studied, although international fighters is a greater balance between the values obtained in the test. International fighters participating in this study have better rates in the adductor muscles of the hip  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carretero, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sánchez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tiene como objetivo evaluar la flexibilidad de la musculatura de tronco y miembros inferiores, en luchadores de kickboxing de diferente nivel competitivo, que no realizan ejercicios de estiramiento de forma habitual. Unos valores óptimos en esta cualidad son necesarios, por su posible relación con la lesión muscular y el rendimiento deportivo. La muestra esta compuesta por 14 luchadores (24,5&#129;} 4,9 años de edad, 176,4&#129;} 8,2 cm de estatura y 73,8&#129;}6,7 kg de peso) de nivel internacional (n=6) y nacional (n=8). Se midieron los arcos de movilidad en la articulación del tronco a través del Test de flexión lateral de tronco, y los test de Schober y test de Ott; en la articulación de la cadera se aplicaron el Test de abducción máxima de cadera en bipedestación con rotación externa unilateral, Test de abducción bilateral máxima de cadera en bipedestación, Test de Abducción de cadera, Test de flexión de cadera en de cubito supino, Test &#147;Back saver sit and reach&#148; y Test &#147;sit and reach&#148;; y en la articulación del tobillo se empleó el test de flexión dorsal y plantar de tobillo. Los resultados muestran unos valores superiores a los encontrados en otras disciplinas deportivas. En el análisis por categorías se han encontrado diferencias significativas entre competidores de nivel internacional y nacional en el test de abducción de cadera (p&amp;#8804;0,05) y en la flexión dorsal (p&amp;#8804;0,01) del tobillo no dominante. No se han observado diferencias entre el miembro dominante y no dominante en ninguno de los grupos estudiados, si bien en los luchadores de nivel internacional se observa un mayor equilibrio entre los valores obtenidos en los test. Los luchadores de nivel internacional participantes en este estudio presentan mejores índices en la musculatura aductora de la cadera. Las técnicas de kickboxing demandan un buen nivel de flexibilidad por parte de los luchadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;31(160): 85-91, mar.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129611</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la flexibilidad de luchadores de kickboxing de nivel internacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52423^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32075^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9323^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
