<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138802</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute encephalitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute encephalitis can be due to many causes, although most are viral, and is a medical emergency. A significant percentage remains without a definitive diagnosis due to the large number of etiologic agents. The single most frequent cause of sporadic encephalitis around the world is herpes simplex virus type 1, although in certain locations diverse local agents should be considered such as West Nile virus or tick-borne encephalitis, among others. Patients with encephalitis require intense care measures with special emphasis on respiratory problems secondary to a depressed level of consciousness, seizures, and intracranial hypertension due to cerebral edema. Herpes encephalitis has an incidence of 4 cases per million inhabitants. Clinical presentation, together with electroencephalography, magnetic resonance imaging and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) findings are critical to establish a diagnosis. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in CSF is highly sensitive and specific (&gt; 95%), but the results can be negative during the first 3 days of the disease. The treatment of choice is currently acyclovir 10 mg/kg/8 h for 10-21 days. Whenever resistance is suspected, foscarnet is an alternative. The family of arboviruses represents another important etiologic group of encephalities. These are zoonotic diseases transmitted by mosquitoes or ticks and include alphaviruses, bunyaviruses (Toscana virus and others) and flaviviruses. The West Nile virus belongs to the latter group. There is no specific therapy and diagnosis is based on serology and PCR depending on the suspected virus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>&amp;#8232;García-Moncó, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La encefalitis aguda es una emergencia médica de etiología variada, aunque en su mayoría es viral. Un porcentaje elevado queda sin un diagnóstico etiológico específico debido al gran número de agentes causales. La causa más frecuente de encefalitis esporádica en todo el mundo es el virus del herpes simple tipo 1, aunque en determinadas localizaciones es importante considerar determinados agentes locales, como el virus del Nilo Occidental o la encefalitis transmitida por garrapata, entre otros. Los pacientes con encefalitis requieren cuidados generales, con especial énfasis en los problemas respiratorios derivados del deterioro del nivel de consciencia, las crisis epilépticas y la hipertensión intracraneal secundaria al edema cerebral. La encefalitis herpética tiene una incidencia de 4 casos por millón de habitantes. La presentación clínica junto al EEG, la RM y el análisis del LCR son claves en su diagnóstico. La PCR en el LCR es altamente sensible y específica (&gt; 95%), aunque puede ser negativa en los primeros 3 días de enfermedad. El tratamiento de elección en la actualidad es el aciclovir intravenoso, a una dosis de 10 mg/kg/8 h, durante 10-21 días. En casos de resistencia, el foscarnet es una alternativa. Los arbovirus constituyen otro importante grupo etiológico en las encefalitis. Son zoonosis transmitidas por mosquitos o garrapatas e incluyen los alfa-virus, los bunyavirus (el virus de la Toscana y otros) y los flavivirus. Entre estos últimos destaca el virus del Nilo Occidental. No hay tratamiento específico y el diagnóstico se basa en la serología o la PCR dependiendo del tipo de virus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(supl.1): 11-17, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalitis agudas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1107^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33209</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31410^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
