<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103752</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fabrication and in vitro evaluation of subgingival strips of calcium alginate for controlled delivery of ofloxacin and metronidazole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Subgingival strips of combined ofloxacin (OFX) and metronidazole (MET) were fabricated and evaluated in vitro using biodegradable calcium alginate. Methods: Strips of drug:polymer (10:90, 25:75, 50:50 and 75:25) were prepared using solvent casting method. A 10%w/v CaCl2 solution was used for gelation of the strips. Results: The thickness of strips were at par of recommended thickness (&lt;320 micrem). In vitro release of drugs followed a biphasic kinetics which was sufficient to maintain the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) to inhibit the growth of the microorganisms for 5 days. The rate of drug release was inversely proportional to polymer concentration in the formulations. The drug release was by diffusion in second phase of dissolution. Conclusions: The formulations OM1 and OM2 which contain 90 and 75%w/w of polymer could be employed for controlled delivery of combined OFX and MET for 5 days in subgingival infections. Calcium alginate, being a biodegradable is a good choice as drug retarding polymer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rao, Chandu B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prakash, Katakam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Awen, Bahlul Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kumari, Adiki S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Elaborar y evaluar tiras subgingivales combinadas compuestas por Ofloxacino y metronidazol in vitro con alginato de calcio biodegradable. Métodos: las tiras se prepararon utilizando el método de evaporación del disolvente. Se usó una concentración del 10% de CaCl2 para la gelificación.de las tiras. Resultados: el grosor de las tiras se encuentra dentro de las recomendaciones (&gt;320 microm). In vitro, la liberación de la droga siguió una cinética bifásica que fue suficiente para alcanzar la CMI e inhibir el crecimiento de microorganismos durante 5 días. La &#147;tasa de liberación de la droga&#148; es inversamente proporcional a la concentración de polímero de la formulación. La liberación de la &#147;droga&#148; fue por difusión y en segunda fase por disolución. Discusión: Las preparaciones OM1 y OM2 que contienen un 90 y un 75% de polímero respectivamente, podrían ser empleadas en liberación controlada durante cinco días en infecciones sublinguales. Siendo el alginato cálcico biodegradable una buena elección como polímero retardante(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;53(3): 26-33, jul.-sept. 2012. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración y evaluación in vitro de tiras subgingivales de alginato de calcio para la liberación controlada de ofloxacino y metronidazol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
