<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134206</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fundamental task of the medical inspectors of the National Institute of Social Security is the valuation of the work capacity of a worker when it suffers an illness that reduces or cancels the same, either temporary or permanent. Psyquiatric illness are the most difficult to assess due to the lack of objective evidence that guarantees the accuracy and intensity of the symptoms that tell patients. Why we conducted this formative work with teams of mental health of our province, to perform an assessment jointly with psychiatrists and guaranteeing greater reliability in our evaluation reports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alba Jurado, Matilde Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabuchola Moreno, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tarea fundamental de los médicos inspectores del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social es la valoración de la capacidad laboral de un trabajador cuando éste sufre una enfermedad que disminuye o anula la misma, de forma temporal o permanente. Las enfermedades psiquiátricas son las más difíciles de valorar debido a la inexistencia de pruebas objetivas que avalen la veracidad e intensidad de los síntomas que relatan los pacientes. Por ello hemos realizado este trabajo formativo con los Equipos de Salud Mental de nuestra provincia, para poder realizar una valoración conjunta con los psiquiatras y así garantizar una mayor fiabilidad en nuestros dictámenes evaluadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(supl.1): 243-250, 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa formativo interdisciplinar entre los Inspectores Médicos del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social y los Equipos de Salud Mental en Málaga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
