<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116144</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of perceived emotional intelligence and impulsivity in cannabis abuse in young</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze the role of perceived emotional intelligence (PEI) and impulsivity in cannabis abuse in young. One hundred and forty six university students voluntarily participated in this study and responded anonymously to questions about demographic aspects, alcohol and cannabis use together with the following scales: TMMS-24 of PEI, the Satisfaction With Life Scale (SWLS) and the impulsivity scale (IS). Cannabis abuse is mainly related to emotional attention, alcohol abuse and impulsivity, but not with life satisfaction. Also, interactive effects have been observed between emotional attention and impulsivity and these with alcohol abuse. These results should be taken into account when designing cannabis prevention and treatment programs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tomás Sabado, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limonero, Joaquín t</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Castro, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Romero, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar el papel de la inteligencia emocional percibida (IEP) y la impulsividad en el abuso de cánnabis en jóvenes universitarios. Ciento cuarenta y seis universitarios participaron voluntariamente en este estudio y respondieron de forma anónima a preguntas sobre datos demográficos, consumo de cánnabis y alcohol, y a las escalas TMMS-24 sobre IEP, SWLS de satisfacción con la vida y la escala de impulsividad (EI). El abuso de cánnabis se relaciona principalmente con la Atención emocional, el abuso de alcohol y la impulsividad, pero no con la satisfacción vital. Así mismo se observan efectos interactivos entre Atención emocional e impulsividad y éstas con el abuso de alcohol. Los resultados obtenidos se deberían tener en cuenta en el diseño de programas preventivos de consumo de cánnabis así como en los tratamientos de adicción a esta droga</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;19(2/3): 223-234, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la inteligencia emocional percibida y la impulsividad en el abuso de cánnabis en jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
