<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86654</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The genetics of human violence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In the last decade a great amount of progress has been made in the field of the neurobehavioural genetics of aggression and violence. Aim. To analyse and summarise the main genetic influences related with these behaviours in human beings. Development. The importance of genetic factors in the variation of aggressive behaviour in children, teenagers and adults is highlighted. The genetic and environmental origins of stability in the development of aggressive behaviour are then  discussed. The article concludes by reporting on several studies focused on the search for aggressiveness genes. Conclusions. Although considerable progress has been made in our understanding of the role played by genes in aggressive, violent and antisocial behaviour, as well as the interaction between genetic and environmental factors, today the exact mechanisms by which genetic factors contribute to these behaviours are still not fully understood. Genetic aspects probably influence biological factors, such as arousal, levels of hormones and neurotransmitters, among other  things, which in turn have an effect on behaviour. Analysing and understanding each of these parameters is essential to gain a better understanding of the biological mechanisms underlying aggressive or violent behaviour. Moreover, other environmental factors such as abuse and response to stress exert an important effect on the expression of specific genes  and, as a result, on people&#146;s aggressive behaviour (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rebollo Mesa, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polderman, Tinca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Albiol, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En la última década se ha producido un espectacular avance en el campo de la genética neurocomportamental de la agresión y la violencia. Objetivo. Analizar y resumir de forma integradora las principales influencias genéticas relacionadas con estas conductas en seres humanos. Desarrollo. Se expone la importancia de los factores genéticos en la variación de la conducta agresiva en niños, adolescentes y adultos. Tras ello, se discuten los orígenes genéticos y ambientales de la estabilidad en el desarrollo de la conducta agresiva. El trabajo finaliza con la exposición de algunos estudios focalizados en la búsqueda de los genes de la agresividad. Conclusiones. Aunque se ha avanzado considerablemente en el conocimiento de las contribuciones genéticas implicadas en la conducta agresiva, violenta y antisocial, así como en la interacción de los factores genéticos con los ambientales, en el momento actual no se conocen con exactitud los mecanismos exactos por los cuales los factores genéticos contribuyen a estas conductas. Probablemente, los aspectos genéticos influyen en los factores biológicos como el arousal, los niveles hormonales y los neurotransmisores, entre otros, que a su vez afectan al comportamiento. Analizar y comprender cada  uno de estos parámetros por separado es fundamental para mejorar nuestra comprensión de los mecanismos biológicos subyacentes a la conducta agresiva o violenta. Junto a ellos, otros factores ambientales como el maltrato y la respuesta ante el estrés tienen un efecto importante sobre la expresión de genes específicos y, consecuentemente, en la conducta agresiva de las personas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(9): 533-540, mayo 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genética de la violencia humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
