<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134317</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial activity of centaurea solstitialis and centaurea calcitrapa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Centaurea solstitialis and Centaurea calcitrapa (Asteraceae), commonly known as Abrepuño amarillo and Abrepuño colorado respectively, are weeds that grow in the Province of Pampea Argentina, the former of which being the most abundantly encountered species. Research carried out in other countries has demonstrated that the genus Centaurea possesses antimicrobial properties. The objective of this work was to ascertain the extent to which such a biological activity may be present in these species, found growing in this particular Argentinian Province. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration and Minimum Bactericide Concentration was evaluated by means of the dilution method, in broth of methanolic extracts of dry heads of both species. The results obtained, under the working conditions of this study, demonstrated that Centaurea calcitrapa, presents antimicrobial activity against four of the ten assayed strains: Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus agalactiae and Salmonella typhimurium, while Centaurea solstitialis shows antibacterial activity to a lesser extent, with inhibitory activity only being found against two strains: Streptococcus agalactiae and Staphylococcus aureus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riani, D. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Skliar, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Centaurea solstitialis y Centaurea calcitrapa (Asteraceae), son plantas conocidas vulgarmente como Abrepuño amarillo y Abrepuño colorado respectivamente. Son malezas que se desarrollan en la región pampeana, siendo la primera de ellas la más abundante. Investigaciones realizadas en otros países han demostrado que el género Centaurea posee propiedades antimicrobianas. El objetivo de este trabajo fue comprobar si esta actividad biológica se encuentra presente en las malezas que crecen en la provincia de La Pampa (Argentina). Se evaluó la Concentración Inhibitoria Mínima y la Concentración Bactericida Mínima mediante el método de dilución en caldo de extractos metanólicos de capítulos secos de ambas especies. Los resultados obtenidos demuestran que Centaurea calcitrapa, bajo nuestras condiciones de trabajo, presenta actividad antimicrobiana en cuatro de las diez cepas ensayadas (Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus agalactiae y Salmonella typhimurium), mientras que Centaurea solstitialis muestra menor actividad antibacteriana inhibiendo sólo a dos cepas (Streptococcus agalactiae y Staphylococcus aureus) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;45(4): 281-291, 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antimicrobiana de centaurea solstitialis y centaurea calcitrapa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d433^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
