<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165199</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exfoliative erythroderma and palmoplantar hyperkeratosis associated with Majocchi's granuloma by Trichophyton tonsurans in a patient with AIDS</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Dermatophytoses are skin superficial mycoses in which clinical manifestations are directly related to the virulence of the infecting microorganism or the host immunity. Case report. We describe a severe case of dermatophytosis associated with exfoliative erythroderma, substantial palmoplantar keratoderma, onychodystrophy affecting all nails, diffuse non-scarring alopecia and tissue fungal invasion by Trichophyton tonsurans, which led us to the diagnosis of AIDS. Direct examination and culture for fungi from skin scraping from two different sites were performed. Biopsy and histopathological exam were also performed on three different sites. Direct examination of the lesions&#146; scraping revealed septate hyaline hyphae and arthroconidia, identified as Trichophyton tonsurans by culture in glucose Sabouraud agar and Mycosel agar. A scalp biopsy revealed follicular fungal invasion and Majocchi's granuloma. Due to the severity of the presentation we requested an anti-HIV serology, which was positive. The patient was treated with itraconazole, 200mg/day, for 120 days, which promoted a complete regression of the lesions. Conclusions. Severe and atypical forms of dermatophytosis could lead to a diagnosis of AIDS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Imbeth, Maria Auxiliadora A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanziano, Andrea L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sá, Adriana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lyra, Marcelo R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muniz Álvarez, Bruna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuzzi, Tullia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Jeferson C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schubach, Armando O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Las dermatofitosis son micosis cutáneas superficiales cuyas manifestaciones clínicas están relacionadas directamente con la virulencia del microorganismo involucrado y la inmunidad del huésped. Caso clínico. Se describe un caso grave de dermatofitosis asociado con eritrodermia exfoliativa, con apreciable queratodermia palmoplantar, onicodistrofia de las 20uñas, alopecia no cicatricial difusa e invasión fúngica del tejido por Trichophyton tonsurans, lo cual permitió establecer el diagnóstico de sida. Se llevó a cabo exploración directa y cultivo de hongos de dos muestras tomadas por raspado en dos localizaciones distintas. También se llevaron a cabo una biopsia de piel y un estudio histopatológico de tres localizaciones. En la exploración directa del raspado de las lesiones se observaron hifas tabicadas hialinas y artroconidios; en el cultivo en agar Sabouraud con glucosa y agar Mycosel se aisló Trichophyton tonsurans. La biopsia de cuero cabelludo mostró una invasión fúngica folicular y la existencia de un granuloma de Majocchi. La gravedad del cuadro motivó la solicitud de la serología para el VIH, que fue positiva. Se trató al paciente con 200mg/día de itraconazol durante 120días, lo que llevó a la remisión completa de las lesiones. Conclusiones. Una dermatofitosis grave o atípica podría considerarse enfermedad reveladora de sida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;34(3): 185-188, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165199</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eritrodermia exfoliativa e hiperqueratosis palmoplantar asociada con granuloma de Majocchi por Trichophyton tonsurans en un paciente con sida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30914^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14649^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14649^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30940^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
