<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111687</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From inattentive-type attention deficit hyperactivity disorder to the restrictive type</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a very heterogeneous neurobiological condition. It is the most common neurodevelopmental disorder in the childhood population. Its prevalence is estimated to be 3-6% in school-age children. Aim. To review the characteristics of patients with inattentive subtype ADHD, including those who could be grouped in a more homogenous subtype which the DSM-5 proposes for classification as the restrictive subtype.  Development. The characteristic triad of symptoms consists of attention deficit, hyperactivity and impulsivity. The diagnostic criteria are defined in the DSM-IV-TR. For those with deterioration due to ADHD with no significant hyperactivity problems, this manual offers a confusing diagnostic label. Indeed, the neurobiological substrate underlying the diverse subtypes seems to be different in certain aspects, since the frontostriatal circuit appears to be more affected in combined ADHD, while the frontoparietal circuit is more compromised in the inattentive subtype. For these and other reasons, the DSM-5 will reformulate the different subtypes of ADHD and will probably include a new subgroup that will comprise those patients who satisfy at least six inattention criteria and fewer than two criteria for hyperactivity-impulsivity (restrictive ADHD). Conclusions. The definition of this subgroup could make it easier to detect some patients who have so far received Little attention from the point of view of both research and clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Fernández-Mayoralas, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Perrone, Ana Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Jaén, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) es una entidad neurobiológica marcadamente heterogénea. Es la alteración del neurodesarrollo más frecuente en la población infantil. Se estima que su prevalencia es del 3-6% en niños en edad escolar. Objetivo. Revisar las características de los pacientes con TDAH subtipo inatento, incluyendo aquellos agrupables en un subtipo más homogéneo que el DSM-5 propone clasificar como de tipo restrictivo. Desarrollo. La tríada sintomática característica la constituye el déficit de atención, la hiperactividad y la impulsividad. Los criterios diagnósticos se encuentran definidos en el DSM-IV-TR. Para aquellas personas con deterioros debidos a un TDAH  sin problemas significativos de hiperactividad, este manual da lugar a una etiqueta diagnóstica confusa. De hecho, el sustrato neurobiológico entre los diferentes subtipos parece ser diferente en ciertos aspectos, pues el circuito frontoestriatal parece estar más afectado en el TDAH combinado y el frontoparietal en el subtipo inatento. Por estos y otros motivos, el DSM-5 reformulará los diferentes subtipos de TDAH e incluirá probablemente un nuevo subgrupo en el que se incluirán aquellos pacientes que cumplan al menos seis criterios de inatención y menos de dos criterios de hiperactividad-impulsividad (TDAH restrictivo). Conclusiones. La definición de este subgrupo podría facilitar la detección de algunos pacientes que, hasta ahora, han recibido poca atención tanto desde el punto de vista de investigación como en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(supl.1): S77-S84, feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad: del tipo inatento al tipo restrictivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
