<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104943</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dental implant migrated into maxillary sinus:  a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Tooth loss in the maxillary posterior sites, in many cases involves a small amount of remaining bone which precludes placing dental implants. To solve this problem there are techniques such as sinus lifting, but although it solves the problem in many cases, it is not without its complications. The migration or displacement of dental implants to anatomical regions such as the maxillarysinus is a rare but possible complication. Objective: To present a clinical case of a dental implant that accidentally moved to the maxillary sinus, to describe the factors causing this phenomenon and establish guidelines for treatment of this type of case. Clinical case: Male patient, aged 32, who was given osseointegrated implants in the second quadrant, came to our service and through a radiology study we saw the image of a dental implant at the level of the maxillary sinus that was extracted using the intraoral approach. There were radiography controls monitoring progress for a year after the extraction of the implant. Conclusion: There are many factors that can explain the migration of a dental implant into the maxillary sinus, and the current approach must be to extract it well using either with intraoral approach or through nasal endoscopy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barona Dorado, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño Domingo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leco Berrocal, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cáliz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La pérdida dental en sectores posteriores del maxilar, implica en muchos casos una escasa cantidad de hueso remanente que imposibilita la colocación de implantes dentales. Para solucionar este problema existen técnicas como la elevación sinusal que si bien soluciona el problema en muchos casos, no está exenta de complicaciones. La migración o el desplazamiento de implantes dentales a regiones anatómicas como el seno maxilar, es una rara pero posible complicación. Objetivo: Presentar un caso clínico de un implante dental desplazado accidentalmente al seno maxilar, para describir los factores que justifican este fenómeno y establecer una pauta terapéutica para este tipo de casos. Caso clínico: Paciente varón de 32 años al que se le realizó la colocación de implantes osteoinegrados en el segundo cuadrante, acude a nuestro servicio y se le realiza un estudio radiológico en el que evidenciamos la imagen de un implante dental a nivel del seno maxilar que fue extraído mediante abordaje intraoral. Se realizaron controles radiográficos con un seguimiento de un año es de la extracción del implante. Conclusión: Existen múltiples factores que explican la migración de un implante dental al interior del seno maxilar, la actitud siempre debe ser la de extraerlo bien sea con abordaje intraoral o mediante endoscopio por vía nasal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);9(1): 41-44, ene.-abr. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implante dental migrado al seno maxilar: a propósitode un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33126</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
