<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129826</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fruit intake by school-age children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The recommended daily intake of fruit for school-age children is two to three servings. Objective. To describe the fruit intake by children between 3 and 14 years of age attending our primary clinic and to determine factors that could influence it. Methods. Cross-sectional study, using a single survey on fruit consumption the day before the visit. The following variables were collected: age, type and number of servings of fruit taken the day before the visit, at the following times: breakfast (home and school), lunch (home or school), snack, dinner, and other times in the day. We analyzed the relationship between the number of servings of fruit the children ate and the age, the area where they reside, and the educational level of their parents. Results. During the 2011-2012 school year a total of 778 children between 3 and 14 years (mean 7.27 years) were included in this study. Most children had one or two servings per day (median 1.89 servings/day); the highest intake was among 10-year-old children (2.2 servings/day) and the lowest was among 14-year-old adolescents (1.7 servings/day). Children residing outside the province of Barcelona and children whose mothers have a University degree ate more fruit servings. The three most commonly consumed fruits were bananas, apples, and pears. Conclusions. The children surveyed ate fewer than the 2-3 servings of fruit per day recommended in school-age children. The consumption of fruit at different times of the day and the diversification of the fruit offered should be encouraged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roger, Mariona</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilagrasa, Grisel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonjoch, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana, Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El consumo de fruta recomendado en la edad escolar es de dos a tres raciones al día. Objetivo. Conocer el consumo de fruta de los pacientes de 3 a 14 años visitados en nuestra consulta de atención primaria. Investigar algunos factores que podrían influir en su consumo. Mètode. Estudio observacional transversal mediante una encuesta única sobre el consumo de fruta del niño el día anterior a la visita. Descripción de frecuencias relativas (%) o medias (DE) de las siguientes variables: edad, número de raciones y tipo de fruta que comieron el día anterior de la visita en los siguientes momentos: desayuno (casa y colegio), comida (casa y/o colegio), merienda, cena y en otros momentos del día. Analizar la relación entre el número de raciones de fruta que come un niño en función de su edad, la población donde vive y el nivel de estudios de los padres. Resultados. Se analiza la ingestión de fruta durante el curso escolar 2011-2012 de 778 niños entre 3 y 14 años (mediana 7,27 años). La mayoría de niños consumieron entre una y dos raciones al día (1,89 raciones/día) con la excepción de los niños de 10 años (2,2) y los de 14 años (1,7). Los niños que viven fuera de la provincia de Barcelona y los hijos de madres universitarias fueron los que comieron más fruta. Las tres frutas preferentes son el plátano, la manzana y la pera. Conclusiones. El consumo de fruta recomendado en la edad escolar es de dos a tres raciones al día. La mayoría de niños encuestados comen menos (1,89 raciones/día), por lo que tenemos que seguir fomentando el consumo de fruta en diferentes momentos del día, así como conseguir diversificar los tipos de fruta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;74(3): 109-113, jul.-sept. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de fruta de los niños y niñas en edad escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5774^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5774^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5774^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
