<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98331</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Educational Psychologist in the United States and Australia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article we analyze the origins and the current situation of educational psychologists in two countries of great relevance for Psychology: the United States and Australia. In the first case, a review is conducted from the origins of school psychology, dating back to 1890 ? when the American Psychological Association (APA) was founded ? to the present day. The advance and development of educational psychology in this country has provided the elaboration of some very interesting proposals about professional preparation and accreditation of the educational psychologist, based on the establishment of their academic and professional competences. Given the great relevance of these proposals, we review the competences models proposed by the two main associations that represent these professionals: The American Psychological Association (APA) and the National Association of School Psychologists (NASP). With regard to Australia, we analyze the situation of the educational psychologist there, from the origins of this figure -dating back of the beginning of the twentieth century- up to their current situation. Important associations like the Australian Psychological Association and the Australian Guidance and Counsellor Association have played a very relevant role in the regulation of the professional preparation and functions of the educational psychologist. Finally, we outline some future trends that are likely to impact on the evolution of the educational psychologist in Australia. These issues share similarities with the situation of other countries reviewed in this special monographic edition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analizan los orígenes y la situación actual del psicólogo educativo en dos países de gran relevancia dentro de la Psicología como son Estados Unidos y Australia. En el primer caso, se hace una revisión desde el origen de la psicología escolar que data de 1890, fecha en la que se funda la Asociación Americana de Psicología (APA), hasta nuestros días. El avance y desarrollo de la psicología educativa en este país ha confluido en la elaboración de algunas propuestas muy interesantes de formación y acreditación del psicólogo educativo, basadas en el establecimiento de sus competencias académicas y profesionales. Dada su gran relevancia, se revisan en este artículo los modelos de competencias propuestos por las dos principales asociaciones que representan a este colectivo, como son la Asociación Nacional Americana de Psicólogos Escolares (NASP) y la Asociación Americana de Psicología (APA). En el segundo caso, se revisa la situación del psicólogo educativo en Australia, desde sus orígenes, que datan de comienzos del siglo XX, hasta su situación actual, en la que asociaciones importantes como la Asociación Australiana de Psicología y la Australian Guidance and Counsellor Association juegan un papel muy relevante en la regulación de la preparación necesaria y funciones del psicólogo educativo. Finalmente, se destacan algunas tendencias de futuro que marcarán de manera significativa la evolución de la psicología educativa en este país y que, como veremos a lo largo de este monográfico, comparten semejanzas con la situación de otros países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);17(1): 85-99, ene.-jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Psicólogo Educativo en EEUU y Australia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
