<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81388</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are parents present during invasive procedures? Assessment in 32 Spanish hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Parental participation in medical decisions involving their children is essential and family presence during invasive procedures (IP) is fundamental. Objectives: 1) To determine the frequency of parental presence during different IP in Spanish Paediatrics Emergency Departments (PED). 2) To assess the reasons for restricting parental presence. 3) To evaluate the agreement of health care professionals with regards to parental presence. Materials and methods: Descriptive multicentre study based on questionnaires sent to physicians in charge of different Spanish PED. Results: Thirty-two out of 43 questionnaires were replied. Family presence during IP is never allowed in 11 hospitals. In the rest, this varies depending on the type of IP: blood sampling (15 hospitals), wound suture (14), urethral catheterization (9), lumbar puncture (7), intubation (1) and cardiopulmonary resuscitation (1), with no significant differences between hospitals. The main arguments for restricting parental presence are parental anxiety (26/30) and a lower performance by health personnel (23/30). Occasional problems, such as nausea (22/28), have arisen due to family presence. The interviewed physicians in charge think that health care professionals&#146; agreement rates for parental presence decrease significantly with the increasing invasiveness of the procedure. Two hospitals have a working group and one a specific protocol to address parental presence. Conclusions: Parental presence during IP is limited in Spanish PED, due to parental anxiety and is detrimental to the success of the procedure. Physicians and nurses disagree with family presence, especially during the most invasive procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trenchs Sainz de la Maza, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamell Fullà, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corniero Alonso, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Cotanda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La participación de los padres en la toma de decisiones médicas sobre su hijo es esencial, siendo fundamental su presencia durante la realización de procedimientos invasivos (PI). Objetivos1) Estimar la frecuencia de la presencia familiar durante diferentes PI en los servicios de Urgencias Pediátricas (SUP) españoles; 2) estudiar los motivos por los que se restringe esta presencia; 3) conocer el grado de acuerdo del personal sanitario sobre esta. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo multicéntrico basado en encuestas dirigidas a responsables de SUP españoles. Resultados: Se envían 43 encuestas, respondiendo 32 hospitales. En 11 hospitales nunca se da opción a los padres de presenciar los PI. En el resto, los padres pueden presenciar la extracción sanguínea (en 15 hospitales), sutura de heridas (14), sondaje vesical (9), punción lumbar (7), intubación (1) y maniobras de reanimación (1), sin encontrarse diferencias entre hospitales. Para restringir la presencia familiar, los encuestados argumentan la ansiedad de los padres (26/30) y un peor rendimiento del personal (23/30). Ocasionalmente han surgido problemas derivados de la presencia familiar, siendo el más frecuente el mareo (22/28). Los responsables creen que el personal está poco o nada de acuerdo con la presencia familiar, especialmente cuanto más invasivo es el PI. Dos hospitales tienen un grupo de trabajo y uno un protocolo específico. Conclusión: La presencia familiar en nuestros SUP es escasa, probablemente por la ansiedad de los padres y el temor al peor rendimiento del personal. Los sanitarios están poco de acuerdo, especialmente durante las técnicas más invasivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);72(4): 243-249, abr. 2010. graf, mapa</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Están presentes los padres durante los procedimientos invasivos? Estudio en 32 hospitales de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37689^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
