<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119848</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urodynamic Assessment of Bladder and Urethral Sphincter Function Before and After Robot-assisted Radical Prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Affectation of the bladder after open prostatectomy is demonstrated. Decrease in bladder capacity and bladder compliance, detrusor hyper-or hypo-activity and voiding dysfunction are observed. We propose to investigate the effects of robotic surgery on bladder and sphincter function through the comparative study of preoperative and postoperative urodynamic values 3 months after prostatectomy. Material and methods: Prospective study of 32 consecutive patients undergoing robotic prostatectomy. They all underwent urodynamic study one month before the intervention and 3 months after the radical prostatectomy. Results: Twenty-five percent of patients undergoing robotic prostatectomy showed detrusor hyperactivity accompanied by a decrease in bladder compliance of 30.2 to 21.8 ml/cmH2O. Urethral profile showed diminished functional length of 67 to 44 mm and decreased maximum urethral pressure of 48.5 to 29.3 cmH2O. After robotic prostatectomy 21.8% of patients had detrusor hypoactivity, obstruction decreased between 28.1 and 12.5%. Conclusions: Decreased bladder compliance, detrusor hypo- or hyperactivity and obstruction improvement observed in the study of the flow pressure have been associated with sphincter involvement. It is part of the complex of lower urinary tract dysfunction that occurs after robotic prostatectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Galisteo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena-Gonzalez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machuca-Santacruz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Martinez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vozmediano-Chicharro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barnoiu, O. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Samaniego, J. M. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Está demostrada la existencia de una afectación vesical tras la prostatectomía abierta en relación con la disminución de la capacidad vesical y la acomodación, la hiperactividad o la hipoactividad y la disfunción de vaciado. Comparando el estudio urodinámico preoperatorio con el realizado a los 3 meses tras la prostatectomía, nos proponemos investigar el impacto de la cirugía robótica sobre la función vesical y la esfinteriana. Material y métodos: Hemos evaluado de forma prospectiva a 32 pacientes que de manera consecutiva han sido intervenidos de prostatectomía robótica. A todos estos pacientes se les ha realizado un estudio urodinámico un mes antes de la intervención y otro a los 3 meses tras la prostatectomía radical. Resultados: Hemos detectado una hiperactividad del detrusor en un 25% tras la prostatectomía robótica con una disminución de la acomodación vesical de 30,2 a 21,8 ml/cmH2O. En el perfil uretral hemos encontrado una disminución de la longitud funcional uretral de 67 a 44 mm y de la presión uretral máxima de 48,5 a 29,3 cmH2O. La hipoactividad se ha demostrado en el 21,8% de los pacientes y la obstrucción ha disminuido del 28,1 al 12,5% tras la prostatectomía robótica. Conclusiones: La disminución de la acomodación vesical, la hiperactividad o hipoactividad detrusoriana y la mejoría de la obstrucción en el estudio de presión-flujo se asocian a la afectación esfinteriana formando parte de un síndrome complejo de disfunción del tracto urinario inferior que aparece tras la prostatectomía robótica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(2): 78-83, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119848</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración urodinámica de la función vesical y esfinteriana antes y después de la prostatectomía radical asistida por robot</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
