<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135258</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional support in enterocutaneous fistulas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A high percentage of enterocutaneous fistulas are due to previous surgery; these entities are associated with high morbidity and mortality. The mortality rate is estimated to be between 5 and 20%. The treatment of enterocutaneous fistulas should aim firstly at stabilizing the patient, correcting any hidroelectrolitic disorders, controlling possible infections and fistula output, and starting nutritional support. The widespread use of somatostatin in continuous infusion, or its analogue octeotride, is controversial. Although data suggest a reduction in the fistula closure time, there is little evidence that this treatment increases the probability of spontaneous closure. Malnutrition is highly prevalent and starting nutritional support is essential. Whenever possible, the first choice should be enteral nutrition and, if output loss increases in high output fistulas, parenteral nutrition should be started (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Camps, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virgili Casas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fístulas enterocutáneas en un alto porcentaje son consecuencia de una cirugía y se asocian a una elevada morbimortalidad. La tasa de mortalidad se estima entre el 5 y el 20%. El tratamiento de las fístulas enterocutáneas debería ir dirigido en primer lugar a la estabilización del paciente, corrección del equilibrio hidroelectrolítico, control de la infección, del débito de la fístula y la instauración de soporte nutricional. El uso sistemático de somatostatina en infusión continua o su análogo octreotida es controvertido. Aunque los datos indican una reducción en el tiempo de cierre de la fístula, hay poca evidencia a favor de una mayor probabilidad de cierre espontáneo. La desnutrición tiene una alta prevalencia y la instauración de soporte nutricional es esencial como tratamiento de soporte. La nutrición enteral será de elección siempre que sea posible, y en caso de aumento de las pérdidas en las fístulas de alto débito, se debería instaurar nutrición parenteral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(supl.2): 48-53, ene. 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pauta nutricional en una fístula enterocutánea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22676^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22676^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31533^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31533^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31533^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
