<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116119</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Erectile Function After Cystectomy With Neurovascular Preservation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To study the utility of neurovascular preservation for postoperative erection in radical cystectomy. Materials and methods: Retrospective analysis of 44 cystectomies performed at our center between January 2006-December 2009 in men &lt; 65 years. In 11 cases a neurovascular preservation was done. We analyzed age, BMI, indication for surgery, urinary diversion, use of i-PDE5 or alprostadil, and daytime and nighttime continence. Erection Hardness Score (EHS) was used to assess erectile function. Results: Spontaneous postoperative erectile function in preservation group was 44,4% EHS 4, 33,3% EHS 3 and 22,3% EHS 1 (achieving EHS 3 or 4 with alprostadil). In the non preservation group, 4,5% achieved EHS 4 spontaneously. The other 95,5% had EHS 0 (4,5% achieved EHS 3 with tadalafil 20 mg and 9% with intracavernous injections). Variables age (P = 0.001) and nerve-sparing surgery (P &lt; 0.001) were related to postoperative erectile function recovery. In the multivariate analysis, nerve-sparing surgery remained statisticaly significant. Conclusions: The functional results in preserving cystectomy are promising. The preservation should be considered in young patients without erectile dysfunction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribal, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Márquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilaseca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estudiar la utilidad de la preservación neurovascular para la erección postoperatoria en la cistectomía radical. Materiales y métodos: Análisis retrospectivo de 44 cistectomias realizadas en nuestro centro entre enero de 2006 y diciembre de 2009 en hombres menores de 65 años. En 11 casos se hizo preservación neurovascular. Hemos analizado la edad, el índice de masa corporal, la indicación quirúrgica, la derivación urinaria, el uso de i-PDE5 o alprostadil, y la continencia diurna y nocturna. La erección se midió con el Erection Hardness Score (EHS). Resultados: La erección postoperatoria espontánea en el grupo con preservación fue del 44,4% EHS 4, del 33,3% EHS 3 y del 22,3% EHS 1 (alcanzaron EHS 3 o 4 con alprostadil). En el grupo sin preservación el 4,5% alcanzó EHS 4 espontáneamente. El otro 95,5% tenía EHS 0 (el 4,5% alcanzó EHS 3 con tadalafilo 20 mg y el 9% con inyecciones intracavernosas). Las variables edad (p = 0,001) y preservación neurovascular (p &lt; 0,001) se encontraron relacionadas con la erección postoperatoria. En el análisis multivariado la preservación mantuvo la significación estadística. Conclusiones: Los resultados funcionales con la preservación en la cistectomía son prometedores. La preservación debe ser considerada en pacientes jóvenes sin disfunción eréctil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(9): 554-559, oct. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función eréctil después de cistectomía con preservación neurovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
