<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130254</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Youth, alcohol and risk: a critical view from the socio-cultural theories</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work focuses its interest in the difficult relationships between health and social disciplines when facing a complex problem as alcohol consumption. The question is whether the scientific practice has the capacity to reduce risks, or on the contrary it is necessary to protect ourselves from the dangers which it produces. Social scientists complain about the limited use that medicine makes of the vast existing heritage about the cultural-based alcoholism. At the same time scientists criticize the inefficiency of biomedical approaches. In this article, we highlight the importance of a contextualized analysis about the alcohol consumption that takes into account the functions and consequences from the social structure that gives it collective and subjective significance. Current paradoxes in the social government of dependencies are manifested. Looking to the phenomenon of collective consumption of alcohol among young people, we suggest alternative approaches that incorporate the meanings and intervention capacity of the subjects themselves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios Ramírez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amezcua, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo centra su interés en las difíciles relaciones entre las disciplinas sanitarias y sociales ante un problema complejo como el consumo de alcohol. La cuestión es si la práctica científica tiene capacidad para disminuir los riesgos, o por el contrario es necesario protegerse de los peligros que ella misma produce. Los científicos sociales se quejan del poco uso que la medicina hace del gran acervo existente sobre el fenómeno del alcoholismo con base en la cultura, a la vez que critica la ineficacia de los abordajes biomédicos. Se resalta la importancia de un análisis contextualizado del consumo de alcohol que tenga en cuenta la función y las consecuencias a partir de la estructura social que le da significación colectiva y subjetiva. Se manifiestan las paradojas actuales en el gobierno de las dependencias. Y de cara al fenómeno del consumo colectivo de alcohol entre los jóvenes, se sugieren abordajes alternativos que incorporen los significados y la capacidad de intervención de los propios sujetos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(3): 149-152, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Jóvenes, alcohol y riesgo: una mirada crítica desde las teorías socio-culturales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d897^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
