<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058686</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Criteria for including vaccines in the immunization schedule of the Spanish Association of Pediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Vaccine Advisory Committee of the Spanish Association of Pediatrics analyzes and discusses the criteria followed when preparing their yearly Recommended Immunization Schedule for children and adolescents. The relative importance of each criterion in the final recommendation is assessed. Following a review of the current state of affairs of childhood immunization in Spain and of the crucial role played by pediatricians, some reflections are presented on the problems derived from the vaccines recommended by this Committee but not covered by the national health system. Suggestions are made for individual pediatricians who may need to establish specific priorities in the recommendation of these vaccines</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Comité Asesor de Vacunas de la Asociación Española de Pediatría</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Comité Asesor de Vacunas de la Asociación Española de Pediatría analiza y discute los criterios que siguen en la elaboración de su calendario vacunal recomendado cada año. Se argumenta la importancia relativa de cada uno de estos criterios en la recomendación final. Se analiza la situación actual de la vacunación infantil en España y el papel desempeñado por los pediatras. Se reflexiona sobre los problemas generados por las vacunas recomendadas por este comité y que no son financiadas por el sistema sanitario, y se orienta sobre la actitud a seguir por parte de los pediatras ante la eventual necesidad de establecer prioridades individualizadas en la recomendación de estas vacunas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(1): 58-62, ene. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios de inclusión de vacunas en el calendario de la Asociación Española de Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29429</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
