<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156889</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">RIT1: a novel gene associated with Noonan syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Noonan syndrome is the most frequent of the congenital group of malformation syndromes caused by germline mutations that encode components of the RAS/MAPK pathway, termed RASopathies, one of the most frequent congenital genetic disorders in the clinical practice. Recently RIT1 mutations have been reported in patients with Noonan syndrome. Case report. A 7 years-old girl with a clinical diagnosis of Noonan syndrome, and with a hypertrophic cardiomyopathy included in her clinical manifestations, where a de novo heterozygous, probably pathogenic, novel mutation in RIT1, c.295T&gt;C (p.Phe99Leu), has been identified. Conclusions. RIT1 shares homology with other RAS proteins and the expression of mutant alleles demonstrates a gain-offunction effect supporting a causative role in Noonan syndrome pathogenesis. Data suggest that the frequency of RIT1 mutations can be estimated as 3-5% in Noonan syndrome patients. These cases compared with Noonan patients harboring mutations in other genes are characterized by high frequency of prenatal abnormalities and hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, and lower frequencies of short stature and pectus abnormalities. We emphasize the importance of the novel identified genes in order to be included in the diagnostic panels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Torres, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Buitrago-Amigo, Jesús F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botet-Rodríguez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo-Carrera, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solo de Zaldívar-Tristancho, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Fernández, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Noonan es el más frecuente del grupo de los síndromes malformativos congénitos originados por mutaciones germinales en genes de la vía RAS/MAPK, denominados genéricamente RAS-opatías, uno de los grupos más comunes de alteraciones genéticas congénitas en la práctica clínica. Recientemente se han descrito mutaciones en el gen RIT1 en pacientes con síndrome de Noonan. Caso clínico. Niña de 7 años con diagnóstico clínico de síndrome de Noonan, que entre sus manifestaciones clínicas incluye miocardiopatía hipertrófica, en la que se ha identificado una mutación de novo en heterocigosis, en RIT1, c.295T&gt;C (p.Phe99Leu), no descrita previamente, probablemente causal. Conclusiones. RIT1 comparte homología con otras proteínas RAS y la expresión de alelos mutantes origina un efecto de ganancia de función que apoya su papel causal en el síndrome de Noonan. Podemos estimar actualmente que es responsable de un 3-5% de los casos del síndrome. Estos casos con síndrome de Noonan, respecto a los que presentan mutaciones en otros genes, se caracterizan por una mayor frecuencia de alteraciones prenatales, alta frecuencia de miocardiopatía hipertrófica y menor frecuencia de talla baja y deformidad torácica. Destaca la importancia de incorporar los nuevos genes identificados en los paneles diagnósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;63(8): 358-362, 16 oct., 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">RIT1: un nuevo gen causal del síndrome de Noonan</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9821^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9821^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24694^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24694^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
