<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105027</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sevillian teenagers&#146; labor: characteristics, diagnosis and procedure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe trends in teenage pregnancy rates, their obstetric characteristics, the diagnosis and procedures performed more frequently in pregnant women attended by the Andalusian Public Health System. Design type: Secondary analysis of the 2000-2008 data series. Unit of analysis: Exploiting the data referring to pregnancies in women aged between 14 and 19 years collected in the Minimum Basic Data Set (MBDS) of the Seville public hospitals for the years 2000 to 2008.Results: A 1.5% increase in the pregnancy rate among adolescent women can be observed in the period 2000 to 2008. The most frequent diagnoses in pregnant adolescents in Seville and the province are postterm pregnancies, prolonged second phase of the delivery, infections of the urinogenital tract, premature birth and anaemia, albeit in no greater figures than those described for mature mothers. The highest pregnancy rates among adolescents by post code correspond to the less well-off areas. The surgical-obstetric procedures practised most frequently on adolescents correspond to invasive procedures such as episiotomy and caesarean section. Conclusions: Despite the educational campaigns and strategies top revent adolescent pregnancy, it can be seen that not only has it not decreased, but it has in fact increased by 1.5% in the province of Seville in relation to the growth rate of the adolescent population. But it is also worth mentioning that teenage pregnancy and labor do not necessarily involve any added health hazard to the mother or gestation in the study population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Henríquez Valencia, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil García, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la evolución de las tasas de embarazo adolescente, sus características obstétricas, los diagnósticos y los procedimientos que se realizan con mayor frecuencia en las gestantes adolescentes atendidas en el Sistema Sanitario Público de Andalucía. Tipo de diseño: Análisis secundario de datos, serie 2000-2008.Unidad de análisis: Explotación de datos referentes a los embarazos de mujeres de 14-19 años de edad recogidos en el Conjunto Mínimo Básico de Datos (CMBD) de los hospitales públicos de Sevilla entre los años 2000 y 2008.Resultados: Se observa en este periodo un incremento de la tasa de embarazos de mujeres adolescentes (media del 1,5%). Los diagnósticos de las adolescentes gestantes más frecuentes en la provincia de Sevilla son el embarazo postérmino, la segunda fase prolongada del parto, la infección de las vías genitourinarias, el parto prematuro y la anemia, aunque en cifras similares a las descritas para madres adultas. Las mayores tasas de embarazo en adolescentes corresponden a las zonas desfavorecidas económicamente. Los procedimientos quirúrgicos-obstétricos practicados con mayor frecuencia a las adolescentes son la episiotomía y la cesárea. Conclusiones: A pesar de las campañas y estrategias educativas para prevenir el embarazo en adolescentes, observamos que, si tenemos en cuenta la evolución de la población, en la provincia de Sevilla ha aumentado un 1,5%. Asimismo, hay que destacar que el embarazo y el parto en adolescentes no representan un riesgo directo para la salud de la gestante en la población estudiada. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;13(1): 9-14, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El parto en las adolescentes sevillanas: características, diagnósticos y procedimientos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
