<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147755</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological secondary prevention after coronary artery bypass grafting surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Secondary prevention recommendations must be maintained indefinitely in patients with coronary artery disease. Pharmacological secondary prevention demonstrated a long-term benefit in morbidity and mortality after coronary artery bypass grafting surgery. In this paper we analyze the observance of clinical guidelines of pharmacological secondary prevention in patients submitted to coronary surgery. We performed a prospective observational study on 35 male patients submitted to elective coronary artery bypass grafting in Hospital Meixoeiro (Vigo). We recorded prescriptions on admission before surgery, on hospital discharge, and after a two years follow-up. There was a correct observance of pharmacological secondary prevention guidelines regarding antiplatelet drugs and beta-blockers, but with a decrease in prescription of angiotensinconverting enzyme inhibitors after surgery. The most important finding was an unjustified decrease in prescription of lipid-lowering agents on discharge, which was corrected on follow-up. Our results support the implementation of a pharmaceutical care program for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diz Gómez, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteva Lorenzo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Couñago, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilanova Vázquez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corujeira Rivera, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Requeijo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cardiopatía isquémica es una enfermedad crónica en la que se debe mantener la prevención secundaria de forma indefinida. Para un subgrupo de pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica, la revascularización coronaria constituye una opción terapéutica en la que se ha demostrado que una prevención secundaria farmacológica adecuada disminuye la morbilidad y la mortalidad a largo plazo. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar el cumplimiento de las guías clínicas de prevención secundaria farmacológica en una muestra de pacientes operados de revascularización coronaria. Se realizó un estudio prospectivo observacional sobre un grupo de 35 pacientes varones intervenidos de revascularización coronaria en el Hospital Meixoeiro (Vigo), analizando las prescripciones farmacológicas al ingreso para cirugía, al alta y tras un seguimiento medio de 2 años. Se comprobó un adecuado cumplimiento de la prevención secundaria farmacológica con antiagregantes y betabloqueadores, acompañado, sin embargo, de un descenso en la prescripción de inhibidores de la enzima conversora de la angiotensina (IECA) tras la cirugía. El dato más relevante fue una disminución no justificada en la prescripción de hipolipemiantes al alta del paciente, que se corrigió durante el seguimiento. Nuestros resultados apoyan la implantación de un programa específico de atención farmacéutica para estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;10(1): 14-21, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención secundaria farmacológica tras cirugía de revascularización coronaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54125^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
