<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166088</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of angiotensin receptor blockers in the treatment of chronic heart failure: What do the clinical practice guidelines say?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Substantial clinical trials investigating the nature and magnitude of the clinical benefits of angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs) for patients with heart failure exist for three scenarios. When used in adequate doses, these agents exert benefits similar in magnitude to those of ACE inhibitors and may be used as alternatives when ACE inhibitor-specific side effects such as cough or angioneurotic oedema have occurred or are feared. In patients with left ventricular (LV) systolic dysfunction and persistent or recurrent moderate to severe symptoms, addition of an ARB to an ACE inhibitor improves symptoms and reduces hospitalisation but uncertainty exists about whether they reduce mortality, whatever the cause. Patients with a clinical diagnosis of heart failure who have preserved LV systolic function have a lower rate of death or hospitalisation than patients with LV systolic dysfunction and a larger proportion of such events will be non-cardiovascular. ARBs reduce heart failure related hospitalisation in this group of patients but not mortality. ARBs also appear to reduce the incidence of diabetes in patients with heart failure, particularly in patients with preserved LV systolic function. European Society Guidelines on Chronic Heart Failure are consistent with these data. However, the classification system used is antiquated and should be reformed. The guidelines highlight the uncertainty about whether ARBs or aldosterone antagonists should be used as the next agent to add to ACE inhibitors and beta-blockers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cleland, John GF</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existen sustanciosos ensayos clínicos que investigan la naturaleza y la magnitud de los beneficios clínicos de los antagonistas de los receptores de la angiotensina (ARA-II) en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca en 3 escenarios. Usados en dosis adecuadas, estos fármacos ejercen beneficios similares en magnitud a los de los inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina (IECA) y pueden utilizarse como alternativa cuando los efectos secundarios específicos de los IECA, tales como la tos o el edema angioneurótico, se han presentado o se teme que aparezcan. En pacientes con disfunción sistólica del ventrículo izquierdo (VI) y síntomas de moderados a severos, persistentes o recurrentes, la adición de un ARA-II a un IECA mejora los síntomas y reduce la hospitalización, pero no existe la certeza de si reducen la mortalidad por cualquier causa. Los pacientes con diagnóstico clínico de insuficiencia cardiaca con fracción de eyección del VI preservada tienen una tasa menor de muerte o de hospitalización que los pacientes con disfunción sistólica del VI y, por tanto, la mayor proporción de tales eventos serán de causa no cardiovascular. Los ARA-II reducen la hospitalización relacionada con la insuficiencia cardiaca en este grupo de pacientes, pero no la mortalidad. Los ARA-II parecen también reducir la incidencia de diabetes en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca, sobre todo en pacientes con fracción de eyección preservada del VI. Las guías de la sociedad europea sobre insuficiencia cardiaca crónica son consistentes con estos datos. Sin embargo, el sistema de clasificación utilizado es anticuado y debería reformarse. Las guías ponen de relieve la incertidumbre sobre la utilización de los ARA-II o de los antagonistas de la aldosterona como el siguiente fármaco que se debe añadir a los IECA y a los bloqueadores beta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.C): 58c-72c, 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de los ARA-II en el tratamiento de la insuficiencia cardiaca: ¿qué dicen las guías de práctica clínica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54125^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
