<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046569</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiography without film. Actualization in Diagnostic for the image in Odontoestomatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The continous technological advances an the techniques incorporation not based in X rays have made that the classic concept of radiology changed suffering important modifications, accepting the most suitable the meaning of diagnostic by image. The application of informatics, with their spectacular results, allows to obtain radiographic images without film and the development of the TC or RM techniques. The informatics programs of surgical planning have proved their potential. The communication nets makes easy the transmission of facts talking about telediagnostic and the archive system permits the immediate access to the stored information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meniz García, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrigal Martínez-Pereda, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Aranegui, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Quiles Martínez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los continuos avances tecnológicos y la incorporación de técnicas no basadas en los rayos X han hecho que el concepto básico de la radiografía haya sufrido importantes modificaciones, aceptándose como más adecuada el término Diagnóstico por Imagen. La aplicación de la informática, con sus espectaculares resultados, permite obtener imágenes radiográficas sin película y el desarrollo de técnicas como la TC o la RM. Los programas informáticos de planificación quirúrgica han demostrado su potencial. Las redes de comunicación facilitan la transmisión de datos a distancia, pudiendo hablarse de telediagnóstico, y los sistemas de archivo permiten el acceso inmediato a la información almacenada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);3(1): 11-20, ene.-abr.  2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radiografía sin película. Actualización en Diagnóstico por la Imagen en Odontoestomatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14460^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
