<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051832</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scale for assessing perceptual anomalies. Validation of a Spanish version of the SIAPA scale in a sample of Cuban schizophrenic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Perceptual-attentional disorders other than hallucinations in schizophrenic patients have been studied little. In this work, the results of the Spanish version of the SIAPA scale to detect perceptual-attentional anomalies to real stimuli other than hallucinations in a sample of schizophrenic patients in a community study in Cuba are presented.        Methods. 329 subjects were studied: 129 schizophrenic patients and 200 controls. Patients were diagnosed by psychiatrists according to DSM-IV criteria. The SIAPA and PANSS scales were used for the study. Cronbach's alpha coefficient was determined to analyze internal consistency. Reliability, validity of current criterion and structural validity were measured. Comparisons between groups were made using the ANOVA.                Results. Schizophrenic patients had more perceptual anomalies than healthy controls. Auditory and visual perceptual anomalies were more frequent. The scale showed high internal consistency (Cronbach's alpha: 0.84). Using a PANSS scale cut-off score of 60, validity had a sensitivity of 56 % and specificity of 79 %. All modalities of SIAPA scales showed good kappa coefficients (0.72-0.85).                Conclusions. This scale showed similar internal validity and test-retest reliability to those reported in the English version. The results showed that this scale can differentiate the presence of perceptual anomalies in schizophrenic patients from healthy controls. Therefore, we suggest that the SIAPA scale may be useful for assessing perceptual anomalies in clinical researching for cognitive impairment evaluations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo, T. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrón Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Reyes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Quiñones, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de Villalvilla, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lomba, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las alteraciones perceptuales-atencionales diferentes de las alucinaciones en los pacientes esquizofrénicos han sido poco estudiadas. En este trabajo se presentan los resultados de la versión al español de la escala SIAPA para detectar anomalías perceptuales-atencionales a estímulos reales diferentes de las alucinaciones en una muestra de pacientes esquizofrénicos en un estudio comunitario en Cuba.        Métodos. Se estudiaron 329 sujetos: 129 esquizofrénicos y 200 controles. Para el diagnóstico se usaron los criterios diagnósticos del DSM IV. Para el estudio se aplicó la escala SIAPA y la escala PANSS. Se determinó el coeficiente alpha de Cronbach para analizar la consistencia interna. Se determinó la fiabilidad, la validez de criterio concurrente y la validez estructural. La comparación entre los grupos se realizó con el test de análisis de varianza ANOVA.                Resultados. Los pacientes presentaron más alteraciones perceptuales-atencionales diferentes de las alucinaciones que los sujetos normales, principalmente en las modalidades auditivas y visuales. La consistencia interna fue de 0,84. Se obtuvo una sensibilidad del 56 % y una especificidad del 79 %. Se obtuvo índices de fiabilidad (Kappa) adecuados (0,72-0,85) en las diferentes subescalas del SIAPA.                Conclusiones. En este estudio se obtuvieron valores de confiabilidad y validez de la escala similares a los obtenidos con la versión inglesa. Esta escala permite diferenciar la presencia de alteraciones perceptuales-atencionales diferentes de las alucinaciones en pacientes esquizofrénicos en comparación con la población general. Esta escala puede ser utilizada en investigaciones clínicas y epidemiológicas para la evaluación de alteraciones perceptuales-atencionales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(1): 15-19, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escala de evaluación de las anomalías preceptuales. Validación de la escala SIAPA al español en una muestra de pacientes esquizofrénicos cubanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10660^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10660^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
