<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102104</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To assess the quality of life, emotional state (anxiety and depression) and coping skills of a sample of lung cancer patients before the surgery. Methodology: 121 ambulatory patients  with non small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) were interviewed before the surgery. Patients filled the EORTC QILQ-C30 questionnaire, and  the EORTC-LC13 lung module, the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) and the Mental Adjustment to Cancer (MAC) Scale. Demographic and clinical data were also recorded. We compared the groups according to the gender and to the type of surgery  treatment. Result: The quality of life scores of the patients before the surgery were acceptable   72.5). On average patients had high levels of functioning and low levels of symptoms in both EORTC questionnaries (QLQ-C30 and  the lung cancer specific module LC13). Only pneumonectomy patients have limitations in some quality of life areas (role functioning, pain  in the chest and haemoptysis). Few differenceswere observed between the genders. Dyspnoea  was the main symptom related to low quality of life, depression, anxiety and some physical symptoms (fatigue and pain). 20.53% displayed high level of depressive symptoms and 32.15%  anxiety. The most prominents ways of coping used by lung cancer patients are fatalism (71.67%) and fighting spirit (70.49%).  Conclusions: Investigating the influence of psychological factors on the preoperative could be very useful for an early identification of psychological risk factors and bad adjustment to the illness and be able to plan a psychological intervention. Further investigations and longitudinal studies are needed especially to establish comparative among pre and post-operative moments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Quintana, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Trancho, Florentino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laserna, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jamal, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, M Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la calidad de vida, el estado emocional (ansiedad y depresión) y las estrategias de afrontamiento de pacientes con cáncer de pulmón antes de ser intervenidos  quirúrgicamente. Método: 121 pacientes ambulatorios con diagnóstico de cáncer de pulmón no microcítico (CPNMC) fueron entrevistados antes de la cirugía. Los cuestionarios empleados fueron el EORTC QLQ-C30 y el módulo específico de  pulmón LC13, la escala de Ansiedad y Depresión Hospitalaria (HAD) y el cuestionario de Ajuste mental al Cáncer (MAC). Datos demográficos y clínicos también fueron recogidos. Comparamos grupos en relación al sexo y al tipo de intervención quirúrgica.  Resultado: La calidad de vida global del paciente con cáncer de pulmón que va a ser intervenido fue aceptable (72,5). La mayoría de pacientes presentaron altos niveles de funcionamiento y bajos niveles de sintomatología ambos medidos por los cuestionarios EORTC  (QLQ-C30 y LC13). Sólo los neumonectomizados tuvieron más déficit en calidad de vida presentando peor funcionamiento de rol, más dolor en el pecho y más sangrado. Se encontraron diferencias en calidad de vida según la variable sexo. La disnea fue el principal síntoma que se asoció a déficit en calidad de vida, depresión y ansiedad, además de otros síntomas físicos (fatiga y dolor). El 20,53% presentó sintomatología depresiva y el 32,15% ansiosa. Las  estrategias de afrontamiento más utilizadas por los pacientes con cáncer de pulmón fueron fatalismo (71,67%) y espíritu de lucha (70,49%). Conclusiones: investigar la influencia de los factores emocionales en el pre-operatorio  puede ser útil para identificar los factores de riesgo y las dificultades en la adaptación a la enfermedad y así poder diseñar intervenciones  psicológicas. Futuras investigaciones y estudios longitudinales son necesarios para establecer comparaciones entre grupos (pre y post-operatorio) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(1): 95-112, jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la calidad de vida, estado emocional y estrategias de afrontamiento en pacientes con enfermedad neoplásica pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
