<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117042</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Underdiagnosis of peripheral arterial disease in patients with diabetes mellitus attending a hospital outpatient clinic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of undiagnosed peripheral arterial disease in patients with diabetes mellitus. Method: We conducted a cross-sectional study on 360 patients &gt; 50 years of age with diabetes mellitus, who were able to walk and be treated at our Department of Medicine. We excluded patients with severe oedema or swelling in the lower limbs, amputation or revascularization procedures, and those who were hemodynamically unstable or previously diagnosed with peripheral arterial disease. We evaluated the diagnostic performance of the Edinburgh questionnaire, and the absence of dorsalis pedis pulses. Peripheral arterial disease was defined by an ankle-brachial index measured by Doppler of less than 0.90. Results: The prevalence of peripheral arterial disease was 27% (95% CI: 22%-32%), distributed into 16% symptomatic peripheral arterial disease and 11% asymptomatic peripheral arterial disease. The prevalence of peripheral arterial disease in the three age strata, 50-60 years, 61-70 years, and over 70 years was 18%, 24% and 36%, respectively (P &lt; 0.001). There was no difference in the prevalence of peripheral arterial disease between men and women (28% vs. 25%, P = 0.083). The overall diagnostic yield of the Edinburgh questionnaire and the dorsalis pedis pulses examination had a sensitivity of 77% (95% CI: 68%-84%) and a specificity of 62% (95% CI: 59%-65%) Conclusions: Patients with diabetes mellitus treated at the hospital showed a high prevalence of undiagnosed peripheral arterial disease. The low diagnostic performance of the Edinburgh questionnaire and dorsalis pedis pulse examination justifies the implementation of the anklebrachial index routinely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ena, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argente, Carlos R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, Carlos E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez-Sanchez, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica no diagnosticada en pacientes con diabetes mellitus. Método: Estudio transversal en 360 pacientes con diabetes mellitus, mayores de 50 años de edad, con capacidad para deambular, que fueron atendidos en el departamento de Medicina de nuestro hospital. Se excluyeron pacientes con edema extremo o inflamación en miembros inferiores, presencia de amputación o revascularización o aquellos hemodinámicamente inestables o previamente diagnosticados de enfermedad arterial periférica. Evaluamos el rendimiento diagnóstico del cuestionario de Edimburgo y del examen de pulsos pedios. La presencia de enfermedad arterial periférica se definió por un índice tobillo-brazo medido por Doppler inferior a 0,90. Resultados: La prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica fue del 27% (IC95%: 22-32%), siendo en el 16% sintomática y en el 11% asintomática. En 3 grupos de edad considerados 50-60 años, 61-70 años y más de 70 años, la prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica fue del 18, 24 y 36%, respectivamente (p &lt; 0,001). No hubo diferencias en la prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica entre hombres y mujeres (28 vs. 25%; p = 0,083). El rendimiento diagnóstico conjunto del cuestionario de Edimburgo y la ausencia de algún pulso pedio tuvo una sensibilidad del 77% (IC95%: 68-84%) y una especificidad del 62% (IC95%: 59-65%). Conclusiones: Los pacientes con diabetes mellitus atendidos en el hospital muestran una elevada prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica no conocida. El bajo rendimiento del cuestionario de Edimburgo y de la exploración del pulso pedio justifican realizar rutinariamente el índice tobillo-brazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;29(6): 175-181, nov.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infradiagnóstico de enfermedad arterial periférica en pacientes con diabetes mellitus atendidos en consultas de segundo nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53218^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12109</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53672</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
