<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146459</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Position statement of the SEMI, SED, redGDPS, SEC, SEEDO, SEEN, SEMERGEN y SEMFYC</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity and excess weight are the main preventable causes of type 2 diabetes (DM2). When diagnosing type 2 diabetes, clinicians should establish the degree of obesity according to the body mass index (BMI) and, for patients with excess weight, measure the waist circumference. The proper treatment of DM2 requires a simultaneous approach to excess weight/obesity and the other cardiovascular risk factors, such as hypertension, dyslipidaemia and smoking. Nondrug interventions (e.g., diet and exercise) have proven benefits in preventing and treating patients with DM2 and excess weight/obesity and should follow an individual and multidisciplinary approach, with structured programs equipped with specific resources. Weight gain associated with antidiabetic treatment can hinder glycaemic control, compromise treatment adherence, worsen the vascular risk profile and limit the cardiovascular benefits of treatment. Therefore, it is significant to avoid weight gain, a measure that can be cost-effective. Antidiabetic drugs with benefits in body weight have also demonstrated their benefit in patients with BMIs &lt;30. In general, the treatment of patients with DM2 and obesity will depend both on the degree of obesity and the associated comorbidity. Clinical trials on DM2 intervention should consider combined objectives that include not only glycaemic control but also other variables such as the risk of hypoglycaemia and the effect of treatment on body weight (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Guisasola, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Simarro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ena Muñoz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanueva, FF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Domingo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caixas Pedrágos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Huelgas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Peralta, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artola Menendez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galve, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla Bravo, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazón Ramos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Beltrán, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monereo Megías, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Torre, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad y el sobrepeso constituyen la principal causa modificable de diabetes tipo 2 (DM2). En el momento del diagnóstico de la diabetes tipo 2 se debe establecer el grado de obesidad según el índice de masa corporal y, en los pacientes con sobrepeso, determinar el perímetro de la cintura. El adecuado tratamiento de la DM2 requiere un abordaje simultáneo del sobrepeso/obesidad y el resto de factores de riesgo cardiovascular, como la hipertensión, la dislipemia o el tabaquismo. Las intervenciones no farmacológicas (dieta, ejercicio) con beneficio demostrado en la prevención y tratamiento del paciente con DM2 y sobrepeso/obesidad deben seguir un enfoque individualizado y multidisciplinario, con programas estructurados dotados de recursos específicos. La ganancia de peso asociada al tratamiento antidiabético puede dificultar el control glucémico, comprometer la adherencia al tratamiento, empeorar el perfil de riesgo vascular de los pacientes y limitar los beneficios cardiovasculares del tratamiento. Por ello, es importante evitarla; una medida que resulta coste-efectiva. Los fármacos antidiabéticos con beneficios sobre el peso corporal también han demostrado su beneficio en pacientes con un índice de masa corporal&lt;30kg/m2. Globalmente, el tratamiento del paciente con DM2 y obesidad dependerá tanto del grado de obesidad como de la comorbilidad asociada. Los ensayos clínicos de intervención en DM2 deben contemplar objetivos combinados que incluyan no solo el control glucémico, sino otras variables como el riesgo de hipoglucemia y el efecto del tratamiento sobre el peso corporal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;215(9): 505-514, dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia un manejo integral del paciente con diabetes y obesidad. Posicionamiento de la SEMI, SED, redGDPS, SEC, SEEDO, SEEN, SEMERGEN y SEMFYC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
