<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053035</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of risk factors associated with surgical site infection in a urology department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Surgical site infections (SSIs) substantially increase morbidity and economic and social costs. The objective of this study was to analyze the risk factors associated with SSIs in urological surgery.                 Material and method: We performed a prospective study of 308 surgical patients. The risk factors studied were surgical urgency, patient preparation, preoperative hospital stay, antibiotic prophylaxis, degree of contamination during surgery, duration of the intervention, and patient health status. We were interested in the quality standards used in the incidence of SSIs.                 Results: The two factors most closely related to SSIs were the risk factors associated with the patient's health status with an (OR) of 3.16 and interventions lasting more than 90 minutes with an (OR) of 3.41. Surgery with an infection risk, potentially contaminated or dirty, showed a 2.2-fold increase in infections. The incidence of SSI was 2.27% (95% CI: 3.43-1.11) and was 1.72 in clean surgery. Among patients with indication for antibiotic prophylaxis, 95.2% received this therapy (95% CI: 97.8-92.6).                 Conclusions: The most important risk factors for SSIs in the present study were those composing the National Nosocomial Infections Surveillance (NNIS) system. Therefore, we advocate using this system because it is easy to implement, and because it would allow criteria to be standardized among hospitals and the quality of care to be determined</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canteras Jordana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Albacete, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botía Martinez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Zamora, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las infecciones de sitio quirúrgico (ISQ) originan un considerable aumento de la morbilidad y de los costes económicos y sociales. El objetivo de este estudio es el análisis de factores de riesgo asociados a la ISQ en cirugía urológica.                 Material y método: Es un estudio prospectivo que incluye a 308 pacientes intervenidos de cirugía mayor. Los factores de riesgo que estudiamos son urgencia de la cirugía, preparación del paciente, estancias prequirúrgicas, profilaxis antibiótica, el grado de contaminación de la cirugía, la duración de la intervención y el estado de salud del paciente. Nos interesamos por los estándares de calidad en la incidencia de las ISQ.                 Resultados: Los factores de riesgo que tienen en cuenta el estado de salud de los pacientes (odds ratio [OR] = 3,16) y la duración de la intervención superior a 90 min (OR = 3,41) son los factores que más se relacionan con las ISQ. La cirugía con riesgo de infección, potencialmente contaminada o sucia se infecta 2,2 veces más. La incidencia de la infección de sitio quirúrgico fue del 2,27% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 3,43-1,11) y en cirugía limpia, del 1,72%. Reciben profilaxis antibiótica en el 95,2% de las indicaciones (IC del 95%, 97,8-92,6).                 Conclusiones: Los factores de riesgo de ISQ que integran el sistema NNIS alcanzan en este estudio mayor significación; abogamos por la utilización de este sistema, por su fácil aplicación, que permitiría unificar criterios entre hospitales y conocer su nivel de calidad asistencial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(2): 89-93, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los factores de riesgo asociados a infección quirúrgica en un servicio de urología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
