<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60396</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safety and efficacy of oral tacrolimus in the treatment of paediatric inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In certain clinical situations, such as acute and severe episodes of ulcerative colitis (UC) or Crohn's Disease (CD), that do not respond to conventional intravenous steroid treatment, we need potent, fast-acting drugs to induce clinical remission and avoid surgery. Objectives: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of oral tacrolimus treatment of acute and severe UC or CD to induce their remission, and also to assess its efficacy in delaying or avoiding surgery. Material and methods: We present a retrospective study that included all patients under 18 years of age with acute and severe bouts of CD (colonic or ileocolonic location) or UC who were treated with oral tacrolimus at our institution from January 1998 to December 2007. Results: We included a total of 8 patients (4 males and 4 females), 6 presented with UC and 2 had CD. The mean age of our patients at the start of the treatment was 11.8 years (range 2.75&#150;16.58 y) and the mean time from diagnosis to the start of tacrolimus therapy was 4 months (range 1&#150;96m). An initial response was obtained in 50% of patients. Plasma trough levels of tacrolimus remained between 5&#150;11ng/ml. Six of the eight patients (75%) required surgery. In one patient with UC and in another with CD, surgery was avoided. In 2 of the 6 patients with UC, surgery was postponed beyond 6 months. Conclusions: Tacrolimus is useful in inducing clinical remission in patients with acute and severe bouts of UC or CD, and so can avoid or delay the surgery; it may also be used as a bridging agent until the new maintenance therapy with other immunosuppressants is effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas López, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barco Gálvez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicioso Recio, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Salinas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En determinadas situaciones clínicas, como es el caso de la colitis ulcerosa (CU) o de la enfermedad de Crohn (EC) graves, que no responden a tratamiento esteroideo intravenoso, es preciso disponer de alternativas terapéuticas a la cirugía. Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de tacrolimus oral en el tratamiento del brote grave de EC o CU para inducir la remisión y, asimismo, valorar su eficacia para evitar o diferir la intervención quirúrgica. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo que incluyó a todos los pacientes menores de 18 años afectados de EC o CU con brote grave tratados con tacrolimus oral en el período comprendido entre enero de 1998 y diciembre de 2007 en nuestro centro. Resultados: Se incluyó un total de 8 pacientes (4 varones): 6 con CU y 2 con EC. La edad mediana al inicio del tratamiento fue de 11,8 años (rango de 2,75 a 16,58), el tiempo de evolución fue de 4 meses (rango de 1 a 96) y la respuesta inicial se obtuvo en el 50% de los pacientes. Las concentraciones plasmáticas de tacrolimus se mantuvieron entre 5 y 11ng/ml. Un total de 6 de los 8 pacientes (75%) precisó intervención quirúrgica. En un paciente con CU y en otro con EC se evitó la cirugía. En 2 de los 6 pacientes afectados de CU se pudo posponer la intervención quirúrgica más allá de 6 meses. Conclusiones: Tacrolimus es útil en pacientes con brotes graves de CU y colitis de Crohn, modifica el curso de la enfermedad, evita o retrasa la intervención quirúrgica y permite preparar al paciente y a su familia ante la probable intervención quirúrgica. Puede emplearse como tratamiento puente en aquellos pacientes hasta que el nuevo tratamiento de mantenimiento sea efectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(6): 519-525, jun. 2009. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de tacrolimus oral para el tratamiento de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
