<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100370</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of postoperative pain in knee arthroplasty: single dose femoral nerve block versus continuous femoral block</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To compare the efficacy of a multimodal analgesia with 2 different techniques (femoral nerve block with a single dose and continuous femoral nerve block) in the control of pain, use of opioids, and secondary effects in patients subjected to total knee replacement. Material and methods. A prospective randomised study of patients subjected to knee replacement with subarachnoid anaesthesia. The postoperative analgesia consisted of tramadol, dexketoprofen and paracetamol, and one of the following techniques: Femoral nerve block with a single dose of 30mL of 0.5% ropivacaine, or that dose plus a continuous infusion via a femoral catheter of 0.375% ropivacaine 6ml/h for 48h. The demographic, anaesthetic and surgical variables were recorded, along with the pain intensity using a visual analogue scale, opioid use, and complications at 24 and 48h after surgery. Results. A total of 104 patients were included. There no differences in the demographic data between the groups. The pain intensity was lower in the group that had continuous femoral block, particularly at 48h, compared to the single-dose block, and with a lower use of rescue analgesia in the continuous femoral block. The incidence in secondary effects was similar, with a lower long-term sensory block being observed in the femoral block with a single dose. Conclusions. The use of peripheral nerve block is accepted practice for analgesia after knee replacement surgery. Continuous femoral block is a valid alternative, decreasing the use of rescue opiates and pain intensity (particularly at 48h) compared to isolated femoral block(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Castaño, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fayad Fayad, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Mesa, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Ruiz, V. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosío Carreño, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Alvárez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Comparar la eficacia de un régimen analgésico multimodal con 2 técnicas diferentes (bloqueo del nervio femoral con dosis única y bloqueo continuo del nervio femoral) en el control del dolor, consumo de opioides y efectos secundarios en pacientes intervenidos de artroplastia total de rodilla. Material y métodos. Estudio prospectivo aleatorizado, de pacientes intervenidos de prótesis de rodilla con anestesia subaracnoidea. La analgesia postoperatoria consistió en tramadol, dexketoprofeno y paracetamol, y una de las 2 técnicas siguientes: bloqueo del nervio femoral con dosis única de 30ml de ropivacaína 0,5% o la anterior dosis más perfusión continua por un catéter femoral de ropivacaína 0,375%, 6ml/h durante 48h. Se registraron las variables demográficas, anestésicas y quirúrgicas, intensidad del dolor según escala visual analógica, consumo de opiáceos y complicaciones a las 24 y 48h. Resultados. Se incluyeó a 104 pacientes. No hubo diferencias demográficas entre los grupos. La intensidad del dolor fue menor en el grupo en el que se realizó bloqueo femoral continuo, especialmente a las 48h, frente al bloqueo con dosis única, con menor consumo de analgesia de rescate en el bloqueo femoral continuo. La incidencia de efectos secundarios fue similar, observándose un menor bloqueo sensitivo de larga duración en el bloqueo femoral con dosis única. Conclusiones. El uso de los bloqueos nerviosos periféricos está aceptado para la analgesia postoperatoria de las artroplastias de las rodillas. El bloqueo femoral continuo es una alternativa válida disminuyendo el consumo de opiáceos de rescate y la intensidad del dolor (especialmente a las 48h) respecto al bloqueo femoral aislado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(4): 204-209, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del dolor postoperatorio en artroplastia de rodilla: bloqueo del nervio femoral con dosis única frente a bloqueo femoral continuo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5371^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
