<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046266</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The surgical habits of left-handed surgeons</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To question members of surgical, medical and nursing staff about their knowledge of the different        surgical habits of left-handed surgeons, the possible problems they may have as regards adaptation, and also about the        chances of complementarity that may be required when operating with a left-handed surgeon. Subjects and methods.        Between January and May 2003 a survey was conducted on 145 surgeons and 17 instrument nurses. The survey        consisted of 15 questions with multiple-choice answers. Responses were submitted to a descriptive analysis and the chi        squared test was use to determine whether there were statistically significant differences between the answers given by        the different groups. Results. The prevalence of left-handed and ambidextrous surgeons in the sample was the same        (6.2% versus 6.8%). 100% of the instrument nurses and 72% of the staff surgeons have assisted or acted as scrub nurses        with a left-handed surgeon. 93% of the respondents stated that left-handed surgeons operate in the same way as their        right-handed colleagues. 65% said that standard instruments are not as easy to use for left- and right-handers. 45% of        the respondents did not know that there are instruments specifically designed for left-handed users, although 80%        thought that they would improve their surgical capacity. The majority said that specific left-handed material was not        implemented due to the extra cost involved. Conclusions. The problems left-handed surgeons face are something that is        largely unknown and the possible advantages that could be gained by helping them are not taken into account. In        general respondents thought that implementing instruments designed for left-handed surgeons would be a valuable aid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Ferrer, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bofill Brosa, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armengol Carrasco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matas Docampo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Samsó, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Interrogar al personal quirúrgico, médico y de enfermería sobre su conocimiento de los distintos        hábitos quirúrgicos de los cirujanos zurdos, sus posibles problemas de adaptación, así como sobre las posibilidades de        complementariedad que puede suponer operar con un cirujano zurdo. Sujetos y métodos. Entre enero y mayo de 2003 se        encuestó a 145 médicos cirujanos y a 17 enfermeros instrumentistas. La encuesta se componía de 15 preguntas con respuestas        múltiples. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de las respuestas y se comprobó si existían diferencias estadísticamente        significativas entre las respuestas de los distintos grupos con el test de chi al cuadrado. Resultados. La muestra presenta        igual prevalencia de cirujanos zurdos y ambidextros (6,2% frente a 6,8%). El 100% de la enfermería instrumentista y el        72% de los cirujanos de staff han instrumentado o ayudado a un cirujano zurdo. El 93% de los encuestados opina que los        cirujanos zurdos operan igual que los diestros. El 65% opina que el instrumental estándar no es igualmente útil para diestros        y zurdos. El 45% de los encuestados desconoce la existencia de instrumental específico para zurdos, si bien el 80%        cree que mejoraría su capacidad quirúrgica. Es opinión mayoritaria que la implementación de material específico para        zurdos no se produce por problemas de costes. Conclusiones. Existe un desconocimiento notable de la problemática del        cirujano zurdo, y no se valoran las posibles ventajas que puede aportar su ayuda. La implementación de instrumental diseñado        para cirujanos zurdos sería, en opinión general, una ayuda valiosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(3): 231-238, mayo-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos quirúrgicos de los cirujanos zurdos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10054^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34964</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3240^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
