<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129222</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic urethrotomy: Indications and limitations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endoscopic urethrotomy is a simple, reproducible, highly widespread technique that enables an appropriate management of patients with urethral stenosis, if the indication is well established. Determinants of success of this procedure are stenosis length, site, number, degree of spongiofibrosis and previous treatments. The best results would be obtained in single, short bulbar stenoses with limited spongiofibrosis, in which it may be the first choice. Its main limitation is the fact that the procedure itself is a controlled intentional trauma the result of which depends on multiple variables, including the technique employed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miñana López, Bernardino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La uretrotomía endoscópica es una técnica sencilla, reproducible y altamente difundida que permite un manejo apropiado de pacientes con estenosis de uretra, si está bien indicada. Los determinantes del éxito de este procedimiento son la longitud de la estenosis, la localización, el número, el grado de espongiofibrosis y los tratamientos previos. Sus mejores resultados se obtendrían en las estenosis únicas bulbares, cortas, con escasa espongiofibrosis donde podría ser de primera elección. Su principal limitación radica en el hecho de tratarse en si misma de un traumatismo intencional controlado cuyo resultado depende de múltiples variables, incluida la técnica empleada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(1): 119-124, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uretrotomía endoscópica: indicaciones y limitaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31988^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
