<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115580</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction of the risk of complications related to central venous catheters: a proposal for improving patient safety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To adopt effective measures for reducing bacteremia related to central venous catheters (CVCs). Material and methods: A review was made of the insertion technique and required material, developing instructions and graphic support. The prevalence of CVC insertion was calculated. An analysis was made of all the yearly checklists between 2010 and 2012, along with the data drawn from an anonymous self-administered questionnaire, to assess knowledge of maintenance of central catheterization, and evaluating performance on the basis of the new instructions provided. «Safety instructions for the prevention of catheter-related bacteremia in hospitalized patients» were developed, an insertion kit was produced, and 58 physicians and 168 nurses were trained. A total of 687 patients were reviewed, of which 6.7% were seen to carry a CVC. Results: The checklist was found to be completed in 21.7% of the patients, and 39.4% required more than one catheterization attempt. Regarding care-related aspects, there were deficiencies in the registry of the dates on which the dressings and infusion systems were replaced. Conclusions: Maximum diffusion of the developed material was achieved. Reinforcement is required of those procedures in which a greater percentage of errors were detected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago Sáez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barberán Rodríguez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumayor Zarzuelo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alguacil Pau, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Implementar medidas eficaces para disminuir la bacteriemia relacionada con catéter venoso central. Material y método: Se revisó la técnica de inserción y el material necesario, elaborando instrucciones y material gráfico de ayuda. Calculamos la prevalencia de inserción de los catéteres venosos centrales (CVC). Se han analizado todas las listas de verificación realizadas entre 2010 y 2012 en un año y los datos de una encuesta autocumplimentada y anónima para valorar los conocimientos del mantenimiento de la vía central, evaluando el resultado conforme a las nuevas instrucciones. Se elaboró la «Instrucción de seguridad para la prevención de la bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter en pacientes hospitalizados», se organizó un kit de inserción y se formó a 58 médicos y 168 enfermeras. Se revisó a 687 pacientes, encontrando un 6,7% de portadores de un CVC. Resultados: El 21,7% de los pacientes tenían cumplimentada la lista de verificación y un 39,4% necesitó más de un intento. En cuanto a los cuidados, falló el registro de fechas de cambios de apósito y de sistemas de infusión. Conclusiones: Se ha conseguido una máxima difusión del material elaborado. Se deben reforzar aquellos procedimientos donde se han producido un mayor porcentaje de errores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(3): 182-187, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción del riesgo de complicaciones relacionadas con los catéteres venosos centrales: una propuesta para mejorar la seguridad del paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
