<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037562</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activity of an orthopaedics and traumatology ambulatory surgical unit in a third level hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVES: To determine the distribution  and characteristics of patients undergoing        ambulatory surgery in Traumatology in a third level hospital. METHODS: A descriptive study of 4451 outpatient surgical procedures, performed  between January 1993 and May 2004, was  undertaken, with a six months to one year follow-up. RESULTS: 80% (3565) of patients requiring  surgical procedures in our Unit were women. Mean age was 58.2 years. The most frequent   pathologies were: Hallux valgus 1608 (36%),  hammer toe procedures 964 (22%) and Carpal   Tunnel Release 642 (13%). 96% of the operations  were performed under local anesthesia and sedation. Postoperative pain was non-existent or mild in half of patients (48.73%). Post-operative  rate of complications was 2.5%, mainly scartissue problems (1.12%) and infection (0.9%). The unplanned hospital admission rate was 0.16%. The need for emergency care was 1.9%  and subjective satisfaction after 3 or 6 months  was "good" or "excellent" in 96.61% of the patients (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lobo Escolar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sicilia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joven Aliaga, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Determinar la distribución y  características de los pacientes intervenidos en        una Unidad de Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria de  Cirugía Ortopédica y Traumatología en un        Hospital de tercer nivel.  MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Muestra: N= 4451   pacientes. Estudio descriptivo de todos los  pacientes intervenidos desde el año 1993 hasta  el 2004 a los cuales se les ha hecho un seguimiento  entre seis meses y un año. RESULTADOS: El 80% (3565) de los pacientes   intervenidos en nuestra unidad fueron mujeres.  La media de edad fue de 58´2 años. Las patologías  más frecuentes fueron: Hallux valgus 1608  (36%), Dedo en martillo 964 (22%) y SDM túnel  carpiano 642 (13%). El 96% de las intervenciones  se realizaron bajo anestesia local y sedación. El dolor postoperatorio fue ausente o leve en la mitad de los casos (48´73%). La tasa de complicaciones   postoperatorias fue del 2´5%, predominando  los problemas de cicatrización (1´12%) y  la infección de herida (0´9%). La tasa de ingreso  fue del 0´16%. La necesidad de atención por el  Servicio de Urgencias fue de 1,9% y la satisfacción        subjetiva a los 3 o 6 meses de nuestros  pacientes fue de "contentos" o "muy contentos"  en el 96´61% de los casos (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;10(1): 20-23, mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037562</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad de una unidad ambulatoria de cirugía ortopédia y traumatología en un hospital terciario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19369^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23263^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23263^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
