<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94313</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Style of perception of parental relationship and coping in girls and teenagers with diagnosis of Turner&#146;s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The difficulty of women with diagnosing of Turner syndrome to interact with peers is a characteristic widely described in literature, is usually associated with low self-esteem, emotional immaturity and social anxiety. Under the assumption that girls and adolescents with this diagnosis may be exposed to models of compensatory parenting developing distinctive forms of social interaction, the aim of this paper is to characterize the perception of parenting styles and coping in situations of social interaction in this population. Materials and methods: This was applied Argentine Coping Questionnaire and the Argentine Scale of Perceived Relationship with Parents- mother version- a sample of six children and adolescents diagnosed with Turner syndrome. Results: The results indicate a strong tendency to perceive the relationship with their mothers as democratic, based on the acceptance and use of functional strategies: logical analysis, search of support and cognitive restructuring. These characteristics are similar to those reported to the Argentine population. One possible explanation for these results could be due to the particular psychosocial characteristics of the approached sample (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Marcela Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urquijo, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La dificultad de las mujeres con diagnóstico de Síndrome de Turner para interactuar con sus pares es una característica ampliamente descripta en la literatura que suele estar asociada con baja autoestima, inmadurez emocional y ansiedad social. Bajo el supuesto de que las niñas y adolescentes con este diagnóstico podrían estar expuestas a modelos de crianza compensatorios desarrollando formas de interacción social distintivas, el objetivo de este trabajo es caracterizar la percepción de los estilos parentales y las estrategias de afrontamiento ante situaciones de interacción social en esta población. Material y métodos: Para ello, se aplicó el Cuestionario Argentino de Afrontamiento y la Escala Argentina de Percepción de la Relación con los Padres- versión madre- a una muestra de seis niñas y adolescentes con diagnóstico de Síndrome de Turner. Los resultados indican una marcada tendencia a percibir la relación con sus madres como democrática, basada en la aceptación y el uso de estrategias de tipo funcional: análisis lógico, búsqueda de apoyo y reestructuración cognitiva; estas características son similares a las reportadas para la población argentina. Un explicación posible a dichos resultados podría deberse a las caracteristicas psicosociales partículares de la muestra abordada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 745-749, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de percepción de la relación parental y afrontamiento en niñas y adolescentes con diagnóstico de Síndrome de Turner</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14823^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
