<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151368</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance and affects in group problem-solving</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This experimental study compared college students' performance (individual vs. group) in a virtual game of bridge building for a train passage. We tested the superiority of group performance and power activation of affective states in the quality of task performance and conflict perception. The study (N =114) evaluated performance in groups (n = 60) and individuals (n = 54) by two criteria: an overall score(score and advancement in the game stages) and the problem-solving process. In both conditions, before and after the game, conflict perception was low, with positive affective states predominating. Groups performed better and reported greater use of problem-solving stages. There was no evidence of affective states as a mediator between experimental condition and the variables performance and conflict perception (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araújo-Simões, Ana Célia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedes-Gondim, Sonia Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio experimental comparó el desempeño de individuos y grupos en un juego virtual de construcción de puentes para el pasaje de un tren. Se puso a prueba la superioridad del desempeño grupal y el poder de activación de los estados afectivos en la calidad de la ejecución de la tarea y de la percepción de conflictos. El estudio (N = 114) evaluó el desempeño en la condición de grupo (n = 60)e individual (n = 54) mediante dos criterios: una puntuación general (puntuación y avance en las fases del juego) y un proceso de resolución de problemas. En ambas condiciones antes y después del juego, la percepción de conflictos fue baja, predominando los estados afectivos positivos. Los grupos presentaron mejor desempeño y relataron que había una mayor utilización de etapas en la resolución de problemas. No se encontró un papel mediador de los estados afectivos entre la condición experimental y el desempeño y la percepción de conflictos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);32(1): 47-54, ene.-abr. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desempeño y afectos en la solución de problemas en grupo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
