<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142223</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuity of care from the acute care hospital: results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the profile of patients treated by a Continuity of Care Manager in an acute-care center during the first six months of its activity, as well as the profile of patients treated and the resource allocation. Method: A prospective cross-sectional study was conducted on patients with complex care needs requiring continuity of care liaison, and who were attended by the Continuity of Care Nurse during the period from October 2013 to March 2014. Patient characteristics, their social environment and healthcare resource allocation were registered and analyzed. Results: A total of 1,034 cases of demand that corresponded to 907 patients (women 55.0%; age 80.57 ± 10.1; chronic 47.8%) were analyzed, of whom 12.2% were readmitted. In the multivariate model, it was observed that the variables associated with readmission were polypharmacy (OR: 1.86; CI: 1.2-2.9) and fall history prior to admission (OR: 0.586; CI: 0.36-2-88).Conclusions: Patients treated by a Continuity of Care Nurse are over 80 years, with comorbidities, geriatric syndromes, complex care, and of life needs, to whom an alternative solution to hospitalization is provided, thus preventing readmissions  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alsina-Ribas, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subirana-Casacuberta, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigoriol-Juvanteny, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solé-Casals, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oriol-Ruscalleda, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirveches-Pérez, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los casos atendidos por la gestora de continuidad de cuidados en un hospital de agudos durante los primeros 6 meses de su actividad, así como el perfil de los pacientes atendidos y la asignación de recursos. Método: Estudio descriptivo transversal prospectivo de pacientes con necesidades de atención compleja que requirieron de enlace de continuidad asistencial y fueron atendidos por la gestora de continuidad de cuidados, en un centro de agudos, durante los meses de octubre de 2013 a marzo de 2014. Se estudiaron las características de los pacientes, su entorno social y la asignación de los recursos asistenciales. Resultados: Se analizaron 1.034 casos de demanda que correspondieron a 907 pacientes (mujeres 55,0%; edad: 80,57 ± 10,1, crónicos 47,8%) de los cuales reingresaron el 12,2%. En el modelo multivariante se observó que las variables asociadas al reingreso eran la polifarmacia (OR: 1,86; IC: 1,2-2,9) y el historial de caídas previo al ingreso (OR: 0,586; IC: 0,36-2,88). Conclusiones: Los pacientes atendidos por la GCC son mayores de 80 años, con comorbilidades, síndromes geriátricos, necesidades de atención complejas y de final de vida, a los que se les asigna un recurso alternativo a la hospitalización que evita reingresos  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);25(4): 177-185, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La continuidad de cuidados desde el hospital de agudos: resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
