<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2244</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social capital as a determinant of public health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The concept of Social Capital (SC), originally described by Durkheim (1893), is composed of dimensions related to cohesion and trust between members of a social group, and considered by the Word Health Organization (WHO) as part of the social determinants of public health for the decrease of inequities and inequalities in health provision. Objective. To contribute to the dissemination of the concept of SC related to the social determinants of Public Health, in order to offer the reader in-depth content to observe the potential applications and practices in this field. Methodology. Literature search (Google Academics(TM), PubMed, Science direct(TM), Ebsco Host(TM)). Results. A total of 294 full-text publications were obtained, and those selected were the most influential sources on the evolution and application of the concept of Social Capital, socioeconomic development and health in the last decade. Conclusion. Although the current evidence shows that Social Capital is a determinant related to health, standards are still needed for its measurement. This could allow the concept to be measured, and facilitate its integration into the form of actions that exert positive influence and contribute to the implementation of institutional interventions planned for development and public health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo Vallejos, ND</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto. El concepto de capital social (CS) originalmente descrito por Durkheim en 1893 está compuesto por dimensiones relacionadas con la cohesión y la confianza entre los integrantes de un grupo social y es considerado por la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) como parte de los determinantes sociales de la salud pública para la disminución de las inequidades y desigualdades en salud. Objetivo. Contribuir a la difusión del concepto de CS relacionado con los determinantes sociales de la salud pública con el fin de ofrecer al lector elementos para visualizar las potenciales aplicaciones y prácticas en este campo. Metodología. Se realizó una búsqueda de la literatura (Google Academics(R), PubMed, Science direct(R) y Ebsco Host(R)). Resultados. Se obtuvieron 294 publicaciones de texto completo entre las que se seleccionaron las fuentes con mayor influencia sobre la evolución y aplicación del concepto de CS, desarrollo socioeconómico y salud pública en la última década. Conclusión. Aunque la evidencia actual permite afirmar que el CS es un determinante relacionado con la salud, aún es necesario disponer de estándares para su medición, lo que permitirá la instrumentalización y aplicación del concepto, y facilitará su integración en forma de acciones que ejerzan influencia positiva, y contribuyan a la implementación de intervenciones institucionales planificadas para el desarrollo y la salud pública (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(6): 342-346, nov.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El capital social como determinante de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
