<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129843</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rothia mucilaginosa Pneumonia in an Immunocompetent Patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rothia mucilaginosa is a gram-postive coccus that occurs as part of the normal flora of the oropharynx and upper respiratory tract. Lower respiratory tract infections caused by this organism are rare and usually occur in immunocompromised patients. This is the case of an immunocompetent 47-year-old woman with right upper lobe pneumonia in which R. mucilaginosa was isolated in sputum and bronchial aspirate. Infections caused by this agent in the last four years in our hospital were reviewed. The most common predisposing factor was COPD with bronchiectasis. R. mucilaginosa was identified as the causative agent for pneumonia in only two cases, of which one was our case and the other was a patient with lung cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora Molina, Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Serrano, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Carbonell, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Ricón, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sevila, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baeza Martínez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Rothia mucilaginosa es un coco grampositivo que forma parte de la flora normal de la orofaringe y del tracto respiratorio superior. Las infecciones del tracto respiratorio inferior por este germen son infrecuentes y se presentan habitualmente en pacientes  inmunocomprometidos. Presentamos una mujer de 47 a&#152;nos inmunocompetente con neumonía en lóbulo superior derecho en la que se aísla R. mucilaginosa en esputo y en broncoaspirado. Además se revisan las infecciones por este germen en los últimos cuatro años en nuestro hospital. En dicha revisión el factor predisponente más frecuente ha sido la EPOC con bronquiectasias, y en solo dos casos se ha identificado el germen como agente causante de neumonía, entre los que se encuentra nuestro caso y el de un paciente con una neoplasia pulmonar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;50(11): 493-495, nov. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía por Rothia mucilaginosa en paciente  inmunocompetente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30345^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
