<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145524</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Levels of obesity, metabolic profile, consumption of tabaco and blood pressure in sedentary youths</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: in Chile, the National Health Survey (ENS) conducted in 2009-2010 reported high prevalence of overweight, sedentary lifestyle, high cholesterol and metabolic syndrome in the population. Objective: to determine the prevalence in young sedentary obesity and consumption of tabaco and analyze their association with the metabolic profile, body fat percentage and blood pressure. Patients and Methods: 125 young sedentary, 26 men and 99 women, aged between 17 and 29 years old were evaluated. Body mass index (BMI), percent body fat (% fat), waist contour (CC), systolic and diastolic blood pressure, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol (HDL-C), LDL cholesterol (LDL-C), triglycerides: measurements were performed, glycemia and consumption of snuff. Results: HDL-C (p=0.000) and% MG (p=0.043) were higher in women. 37.6% of young people turned smoker. 35, 2% of the sample showed excessive malnutrition. Obese subjects had higher levels: waist contour (p=0.000) and% FM (p=0.000). When analyzing obesity DC, this showed significant differences in BMI,% fat, systolic and diastolic blood pressure. BMI presented positive association with CC,% fat, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL, systolic and diastolic blood pressure (p&lt;0.05). The CC presented association with MG%, triglycerides, systolic blood pressure and diastolic (p&lt;0.05). The MG% did not present association with other variables Conclusions: a high prevalence of malnutrition by excess consumption of tabaco in the study sample, while other variables are not high-risk categories, it is an opportune time to intervene and reverse these negative health trends now (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Hormazábal, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Floody, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caamaño Navarrete, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: en Chile, la Encuesta Nacional de Salud (ENS) realizada en 2009-2010 reportó una elevada prevalencia de exceso de peso, sedentarismo, colesterol elevado y síndrome metabólico en la población. Objetivo: determinar en jóvenes sedentarios la prevalencia de obesidad y consumo de tabaco, y analizar su asociación con el perfil metabólico, el porcentaje de masa grasa y la presión arterial. Pacientes y métodos: se evaluaron 125 jóvenes sedentarios, 26 hombres y 99 mujeres, entre 17 y 29 años de edad. Se realizaron mediciones de: índice de masa corporal (IMC), porcentaje de masa grasa (%MG), contorno de cintura (CC), presión arterial sistólica y diastólica, colesterol total, colesterol HDL (cHDL), colesterol LDL (cLDL), triglicéridos, glicemia y consumo de tabaco. Resultados: el cHDL (p=0,000) y el %MG (p=0,043) fueron superiores en las mujeres. El 37,6% de los jóvenes resultó ser fumador. El 35, 2 % de la muestra presentó malnutrición por exceso. Los sujetos obesos presentaron mayores niveles en: contorno de cintura (p=0,000) y %MG (p=0,000). Al analizar la obesidad por CC, esta presentó diferencias significativas en el IMC, %MG presión arterial sistólica y diastólica. El IMC presentó asociación positiva con el CC, %MG, colesterol total, triglicéridos, cLDL y presión arterial sistólica y diastólica (p&lt;0,05). El %MG no presentó asociación con las demás variables. Conclusiones: existe una elevada prevalencia de malnutrición por exceso y consumo de tabaco en la muestra de estudio, si bien las demás variables no presentan categorías de alto riesgo, es un momento oportuno para intervenir y revertir estas tendencias negativas para la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 2000-2006, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145524</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de obesidad, perfil metabólico, consumo de tabaco y presión arterial en jóvenes sedentarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
