<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158117</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A brief overview of English Primary Care in the last half century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Key hefts, the hard core of clinical profile, scientific nursing and nowadays of the English School of Primary Care in the last sixty years are revisited. We understand that the most profound intellectual influence has been to Archie Cochrane, among family physicians hard core components we include John Fry (1922-1994), David Metcalfe and Julian Tudor Hart. On the other hand, Lisbeth Hockey (1918-2004), PhD in Nursing, was responsible for several years of Nursing Research Unit at the University of Edinburgh. The internet sources of English nursing historical research are very noticeable. Finally, Trisha Greenhalgh, family physician, researcher and Professor at the University of Oxford, is launching the old English School of Primary Care towards the middle of the XXI century (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Francisco Montero, Carmen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabaldón-Rodríguez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Rubio, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Calvo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adrada Bautista, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Hernández, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo es hacer un breve repaso de las influencias, el núcleo duro de perfil clínico, la enfermería científica y el presente de la Escuela Inglesa de Atención Primaria durante los últimos sesenta años. Entendemos que la influencia intelectual más profunda fue la de Archie Cochrane. Entre los médicos de familia componentes del núcleo duro destacamos a John Fry (1922- 1994), David Metcalfe y Julian Tudor Hart. Por otra parte, Lisbeth Hockey (1918-2004), doctora en enfermería, fue la responsable durante varios años de la Unidad de Investigación en Cuidados de la Universidad de Edimburgo. Las fuentes de investigación historiográfica de la enfermería inglesa en internet son notables. Finalmente, Trisha Greenhalgh, médica de familia, investigadora y docente en la Universidad de Oxford, está lanzando a la vieja Escuela Inglesa de Atención Primaria hacia la mediana del siglo XXI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;90: 0-0, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Breve visión de los principales protagonistas de la Escuela Inglesa de Atención Primaria durante el último medio siglo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6228^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6228^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6228^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
