<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96507</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cricopharyngeal dysphagia in patient with chronic cervicalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Achalasia or cricopharyngeal dysphagia refers to the failure to open the upper esophageal sphincter (UES), mainly producing dysphagia to solids, regurgitations and/or aspirations. It is diagnosed by esophagogram, videofluoroscopy (VDF) and manometry. Treatment is mainly surgical. We report the case of a patient who came to the Locomotive System Unit, with complaints of chronic cervicalgia and difficulties in swallowing, which was initially associated to the presence of osteophytes observed in the esophagus X-ray. Due to the persistence of dysphagia, barium transit tests were carried out, ruling out our hypothesis. The diagnosis of cricopharyngeal spasms accompanied by diverticula was finally established. This study aims to show the importance for the rehabilitation medical specialist, trained in different disciplines such as phoniatry, to have a global vision of each patient, without imposing exploratory limitations in order to obtain relevant data in the diagnostic approach(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Romero, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Sarmiento, A. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Borrego, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lagares Alonso, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La acalasia o disfagia cricofaríngea se refiere al fracaso de apertura del esfínter esofágico superior (EES), que produce principalmente disfagia a sólidos, regurgitaciones y/o aspiraciones. Se diagnostica por esofagograma, videofluoroscopia (VDF) y manometría. El tratamiento mayoritariamente es quirúrgico. Se presenta a un paciente que acude a consultas de aparato locomotor aquejado de cervicalgia crónica y dificultad deglutoria, que inicialmente relacionamos con la presencia de osteofitos que improntan en el esófago en radiografía. Ante la persistencia de disfagia, se solicita tránsito de bario que descarta nuestra hipótesis y concluye con el diagnóstico de espasmo cricofaríngeo con presencia de divertículo. Se pretende evidenciar la importancia de que el médico rehabilitador, por su formación en diferentes disciplinas como la foniatría, deba tener una visión global del enfermo, sin límites exploratorios de cara a la obtención de datos relevantes para la orientación diagnóstica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);46(1): 64-67, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfagia cricofaríngea en paciente con cervicalgia crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53067^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53067^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53067^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8537^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23994^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53067^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
