<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166052</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Avascular necrosis of the femoral head in patients treated for leukaemia. Assessment of the need for a diagnostic protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the incidence of avascular necrosis of the hip in leukaemia patients treated in our hospital with high doses of corticosteroids in order to evaluate the necessity for an early detection protocol. Material and methods. Observational-descriptive and retrospective study from 2005 to 2016 of 253 patients diagnosed with paediatric leukaemia. Patients with musculoskeletal pathology were identified and patients with avascular necrosis were analysed. Results. A total of 26 patients (10%) had musculoskeletal symptoms. Three patients with avascular necrosis (1.2%) were analysed. One girl, 7 years old, was treated conservatively with traction - suspension and discharge. Two boys, an 11 and a 15.4 year-old,who developed graft-versus-host disease secondary to bone marrow transplantation, and whose treatment included high doses of corticosteroids, developed avascular necrosis of the hip. One was treated with bisphosphonates and forage and the other ended up with a total hip arthroplasty. Discussion. The occurrence of musculoskeletal symptoms during the treatment of leukaemia is different according to the bibliographic series (0.43 -12.6%). Some authors observe an increased risk in female patients between the ages of 10 and 17. A retrospective study reveals that there is a delay of 3.9 months in the diagnosis of CAP since the onset of pain. Other authors relate NAV to loading joints, age and high doses of corticosteroids. Conclusion. Based on the low incidence of avascular necrosis of the hip in our 14-year-old population treated for leukaemia, the creation of diagnostic protocols seems not to be necessary. However, close monitoring of patients with potential risk factors recognized in the literature, is advisable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salom Taverner, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Vives, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alguacil Pinela, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar la incidencia de necrosis avascular de cadera (NAVC) en pacientes con leucemia sometidos a altas dosis de corticoides tratados en nuestro hospital para evaluar si es necesaria la creación de un protocolo de detección precoz. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional-descriptivo y retrospectivo de 2005 a 2016 de 253 pacientes diagnosticados de leucemia en edad pediátrica. Se identificaron los pacientes con patología osteomuscular y se analizaron los pacientes con necrosis avascular. Resultados. Un total de 26 pacientes (10%) presentaron síntomas osteomusculares. Se analizaron 3 pacientes con NAVC (1,2%). Una niña, de 7 años, se trató de forma conservadora con tracción-suspensión y descarga. Dos niños de 11 y 15,4 años, que desarrollaron una enfermedad de injerto contra huésped secundaria al trasplante de médula ósea, cuyo tratamiento incluye altas dosis de corticoides, desarrollaron necrosis avascular de cadera. Uno se trató con bifosfonatos y forage y el otro terminó con una artroplastia total de sustitución. Discusión. La aparición de síntomas musculoesqueléticos durante el tratamiento de la leucemia es diferente según la serie bibliográfica (0,43-12,6%). Algunos autores observan un incremento del riesgo en pacientes de sexo femenino entre los 10 y 17 años. Un estudio retrospectivo observa que existe una demora de 3,9 meses en el diagnóstico de la NAVC desde el comienzo del dolor. Otros autores relacionan la NAV con las articulaciones de carga, la edad y las altas dosis de corticoides. Conclusión. Basado en la baja incidencia de NAVC en nuestra población de pacientes menores de 14 años tratados de leucemia, pensamos que no es rentable la creación de protocolos de diagnóstico. Sin embargo, sí que es recomendable la vigilancia estricta de los pacientes con factores de riesgo potenciales reconocidos en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(5): 331-338, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166052</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necrosis avascular de cabeza femoral en pacientes tratados de leucemia. Evaluación de la necesidad de un protocolo diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30672^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23872^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5376^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5376^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
