<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167580</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating disorders during the adolescence: personality characteristics associated with anorexia and bulimia nervosa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Previous studies provide relevant information about the relationship between personality and eating disorders (ED). The involvement of personality factors in the etiology and maintenance of ED indicates the need of emphasizing the study of the adolescent's personality when diagnosed of ED. Objectives: The aims of this study were to analyze the adolescent's personality profiles that differ significantly in anorexia nervosa (AN) and bulimia nervosa (BN), and to explore the most common profiles and their associations with those subtypes of eating disorders (ED). Methods: A total of 104 patients with AN and BN were studied by means of the Millon Adolescent Clinical Inventory (MACI). Results: The personality profiles that differ significantly in both AN and BN were submissive, egotistic, unruly, forceful, conforming, oppositional, self-demeaning and borderline. The most frequent profiles in AN were conforming (33.33%), egotistic (22.72%) and dramatizing (18.18%) while in the case of BN those profiles were unruly (18.42%), submissive (18.42%) and borderline (15.78%). We did not find any associations between the diagnostic subgroup (AN, BN) and the fact of having personality profiles that could become dysfunctional. Conclusions: Bearing in mind these results, it may be concluded that there are relevant differences between personality profiles associated with AN and BN during adolescence, so tailoring therapeutic interventions for this specific population would be important (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Laporta-Herrero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barajas-Iglesias, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santed-Germán, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui-Lobera, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: estudios previos aportan información relevante sobre la relación entre la personalidad y los trastornos de conducta alimentaria (TCA). La implicación de los factores de personalidad en la etiología y el mantenimiento de los TCA indica la necesidad de enfatizar el estudio de la personalidad del adolescente cuando se diagnostique un TCA. Objetivos: los objetivos del presente estudio fueron explorar los perfiles de personalidad más frecuentes asociados a la anorexia nerviosa (AN) y a la bulimia nerviosa (BN) en adolescentes y analizar aquellos perfiles de personalidad que diferencian de manera significativa a ambos subtipos de TCA. Métodos: un total de 104 pacientes con diagnóstico de AN y BN fueron estudiados mediante el Inventario Clínico para Adolescentes de Millon (MACI). Resultados: los perfiles de personalidad que difieren significativamente entre AN y BN fueron los perfiles sumiso, egocéntrico, rebelde, rudo, conformista, oposicionista, autopunitivo y tendencia límite. Los perfiles de personalidad más frecuentes en la AN fueron el conformista (33,33%), el egocéntrico (22,72%) y el histriónico (18,18%), mientras que en la BN los más prevalentes fueron el rebelde (18,42%), el sumiso (18,42%) y el límite (15,78%). No encontramos ninguna asociación entre el subgrupo diagnóstico (AN, BN) y el hecho de tener perfiles de personalidad que podrían llegar a ser disfuncionales. Conclusiones: existen diferencias relevantes entre los perfiles de personalidad asociados a la AN y la BN durante la adolescencia, por lo que sería importante adaptar las intervenciones terapéuticas para esta población específica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(5): 1178-1184, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos de la conducta alimentaria durante la adolescencia: perfiles de personalidad asociados a la anorexia y a la bulimia nerviosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51232^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
