<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93430</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occult anterior sacral meningocele</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The anterior sacral meningocele is a rare form of spinal dysraphism located in the presacral extraperitoneal space. It is generally asymptomatic and appears as a small pelvic mass. Case description. We present a case of a 10 year-old male that developes a bacteria meningitis because of a pararectal abscess that is connected with an anterior sacral meningocele. We successfully treated it using a posterior approach. Conclusion. The aim of the surgery is to repair the dural defect and to obliterate the communication between the thecal sac and the herniation defect. The posterior approach is the simplest and most effective surgical technique because the lower risk of neurologi­cal injury than the anterior approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa-Clara, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fructuoso, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Quesada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antuña-Ramos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alamar-Abril, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El meningocele sacro anterior es una rara forma de disrafismo espinal, localizado en el espacio presacro extraperitoneal. Generalmente es asintomático y suele presentarse como una pequeña masa pélvica. Caso clínico. Presentamos el caso de un niño de 10 años de edad que desarrolla una meningitis bacteriana consecuencia de un absceso pararectal que se comunica con una cavidad meningocélica sacra anterior. Recibe tratamiento quirúrgico realizándose con éxito un abor­daje posterior. Conclusión. La finalidad de la cirugía es reparar el defecto dural y obliterar la comunicación existente entre el saco tecal y el defecto herniario. El abordaje posterior es la técnica quirúrgica más efectiva puesto que tiene menor riesgo de daño neurológico que el abor­daje anterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);22(4): 342-346, ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningocele sacro anterior oculto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8758^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4448^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8335^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
