<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108603</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Twenty-five year history of the journal Psicothema</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: There is a growing interest in evaluating the contents of scientific Psychology journals and therefore, to mark the twenty-fifth anniversary of Psicothema, we aim to provide an insight into its historical evolution. The objective of this study was to carry out a bibliometric analysis of the articles published from 1989 to 2012, in order to provide information regarding different parameters related to production and quality. Method: The data analysed were the evolution of the articles throughout the analysed period, languages of publication, index of authorship, countries according to author affiliation, subject matter, the ten most cited articles, Top Ten journals in which Psicothema is most cited, and the evolution of the Impact Factor, amongst others. Results: A total of 2,163 articles were analysed, of which the majority (96.16%) are original articles, published in Spanish (80.07%) and with predominantly two authors (28.34%). The journal has published work by authors from 32 different countries according to their affiliation. Conclusions: The results support the multidisciplinary character of the journal and a positive and constant evolution towards the advance in Psychology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quevedo-Blasco, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: existe un creciente interés por evaluar los contenidos de las revistas científicas de Psicología, por ello, con motivo del veinticinco aniversario de Psicothema, se pretende conocer su evolución histórica. El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido realizar un análisis bibliométrico de los artículos publicados desde 1989 hasta 2012, con el fin de proporcionar información sobre diferentes parámetros relacionados con la producción y calidad de la misma. Método: los datos analizados han sido la evolución de los artículos a lo largo del período analizado, idiomas de publicación, índice de autoría, países en función de la filiación de los autores, las temáticas, los diez artículos más citados, Top Ten de las revistas en las que más se cita a Psicothema y evolución del Factor de Impacto, entre otros. Resultados: se analizaron un total de 2.163 artículos, de los cuales la mayoría (96,16%) son artículos originales, publicados en español (80,07%) y con una autoría predominante de dos autores (28,34%). La revista ha publicado trabajos de autores de 32 países diferentes atendiendo a la filiación de los mismos. Conclusiones: los resultados apoyan el carácter multidisciplinar de la revista y una evolución positiva y constante a favor del avance de la Psicología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(1): 93-99, ene.-mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Veinticinco años de historia de la revista Psicothema</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
