<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164929</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of uropathogenic bacteria and soluble factors produced by their metabolism on sperm quality: Escherichia coli and Enterococcus faecalis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Interactions between sperm and bacteria or soluble factors have a negative effect on semen quality and male fertility. The aim of this study was to determine the effect of 2 enteropathogenic bacteria (Escherichia coli [E. coli] and Enterococcus faecalis [E. faecalis]) and their soluble factors on sperm quality. Methodology: E. coli-sensitive and -resistant strains to ampicillin/sulbactam and piperacillin/tazobactam, E. faecalis-sensitive and -resistant strains to gentamicin and high level streptomycin and soluble factors produced by bacterial metabolism of each strain were incubated with semen samples from volunteers. Subsequently, motility was quantified by light microscopy and sperm function parameters (mitochondrial membrane potential, membrane integrity, reactive oxygen species, and chromatin integrity) by flow cytometry. Results: E. coli and E. faecalis strains and their soluble factors altered sperm motility and some of the sperm function parameters evaluated after 3h of incubation with human sperm but these changes were not statistically significant. Conclusion: Semen quality is affected by the interaction between E. coli and E. faecalis or their soluble factors. Therefore, there is a need to assess the impact of urogenital infections by these microorganisms on male fertility (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giraldo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puerta Suárez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadavid, ÁP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardona Maya, WD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Cháves, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galarzo Pardo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El contacto de los espermatozoides con algunas especies bacterianas y sus factores solubles tiene un efecto negativo en la calidad seminal, alterando la función reproductiva del hombre. El objetivo de este trabajo fue determinar el efecto de 2 bacterias enteropatógenas (Escherichia coli [E. coli] y Enterococcus faecalis [E. faecalis]) y sus factores solubles sobre la calidad espermática. Metodología: Las cepas bacterianas de E. coli sensible y resistente a ampicilina/sulbactam y piperacilina/tazobactam, las cepas de E. faecalis sensible y resistente a gentamicina y estreptomicina de alto nivel, además de los factores solubles producto del metabolismo bacteriano de cada cepa, se incubaron con las muestras de semen de voluntarios. Posteriormente, se cuantificó la movilidad por microscopia y los parámetros funcionales espermáticos (potencial de membrana mitocondrial, integridad de la membrana, detección de especies reactivas del oxígeno e índice de fragmentación del ADN) por citometría de flujo. Resultados: Las cepas de E. coli, E. faecalis y los factores solubles de su metabolismo alteran la movilidad espermática y algunos de los parámetros funcionales evaluados luego de 3 h de incubación con los espermatozoides humanos, sin que estos cambios sean estadísticamente significativos. Conclusión: La interacción de las bacterias E. coli y E. faecalis o los factores solubles producto de su metabolismo con los espermatozoides humanos alteran la calidad seminal, por lo que se debe evaluar el impacto de las infecciones urogenitales por estos microorganismos en la fertilidad masculina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(3): 106-112, jul.-sept. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164929</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de las bacterias uropatógenas y de los factores solubles de su metabolismo sobre la calidad espermática: Escherichia coli y Enterococcus faecalis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53463^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13043^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
