<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136214</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation to the hypo-hyperbaric environment in otorhinolaryngology. Phylogeny</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. With few exceptions, humans inhabit regions where the atmospheric pressure is more or less constant. Any brusque or gradual change in pressure will provoke alterations in the body. The present study aimed to evaluate physiological adaptation to these changes, as well as the phylogenetic adaptation of some animal  species that cohabit in different pressure ranges. Methods. We performed a review of physiological treatisesand present the main adaptations produced in the distinct  organisms and, specifically, in the area of otorhinolaryngology.  Results. Humans are not adapted to hypobaric-hyperbaric environments and suffer serious consequences when exposed to brusque changes in atmospheric pressure. The help of technology is required to be able to remain at high pressures (aquatic environment) and/or low pressures (aeronautic, mountain pressures) without complications. The large marine mammals, however, are highly adapted to hyperbaric aquatic environments. Modifications in the  middle and external ear have led to a sophisticated underwater communication mechanism. Conclusions. Humans cannot experience large pressure changes without sooner or later developing severe general repercussions. However, due to training, some privileged individuals have managed to reach underwater depths difficult to explain physiologically and to scale the peaks of the highest mountains. Marine mammals have managed to adapt by developing ingenious mechanisms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosal-Fraga, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan-Fernández, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La población humana, salvo excepciones, habita en regiones donde la presión atmosférica es más o menos constante. Cualquier cambio de presión brusca o paulatina provocará alteraciones en el organismo. El objetivo de este capítulo es valorar la adaptación fisiológica a estos cambios, así como la adaptación filogenética  de algunas especies animales que cohabitan en distintos rangos de presión. Métodos: Realizamos una revisión de tratados de fisiología y exponemos las principales modificaciones en los distintos organismos para su adaptación y, específicamente, en el área otorrinolaringológica. Resultados: El ser humano no está adaptado a medios hipobáricos-hiperbáricos y presenta graves consecuencias al exponerse a modificaciones bruscas de la presión atmosférica. Es necesaria la ayuda de la tecnología para poder permanecer a presiones altas (medio acuático) y/o bajas (aeronáutica, montañismo) sin complicaciones. Los grandes  mamíferos marinos, sin embargo, presentan una gran adaptación a los medios hiperbáricos acuáticos. Se aprecian modificaciones en el oído medio y externo que determinan un sofisticado mecanismo de comunicación bajo el agua. Conclusiones: El ser humano no soporta los cambios de presión importantes sin presentar, antes o después, graves repercusiones generales. Sin embargo, algunas personas privilegiadas, y gracias al entrenamiento, han conseguido llegar en el mar a profundidades difíciles de explicar fisiológicamente y conquistar las cumbres montañosas más altas. Los mamíferos marinos han conseguido adaptarse mediante el desarrollo de ingeniosos mecanismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.2): 11-17, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación al medio hipobárico-hiperbárico en la esfera otorrinolaringológica. Filogenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4305^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4305^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10214^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10216^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3678^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10216^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1281</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
