<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98665</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fatal rickets in the fetus and undiagnosed maternal celiac disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Celiac disease is a relatively frequent enteropathy associated with a wide range of clinical manifestations, due in part to malabsorption. In women, it has been associated with obstetric and gynecological alterations such as repeated miscarriages, intrauterine growth delay, premature delivery, and low birth weight. We present the case of a woman with undiagnosed celiac disease who gave birth to a stillborn foetus via normal delivery after 34 weeks of gestation. The foetus presented severe morphological alterations due to hypomineralization which were compatible with rickets.In the medical literature congenital rickets secondary to maternal celiac disease due to malabsorption is rare. We discuss the current knowledge on maternofoetal phospho-calcium metabolism and relate active celiac disease with severe hypocalcaemia during pregnancy and fatal rickets in the foetus. We recommend screening for celiac disease in pregnant women with signs of malabsorption or impaired fetal development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreres, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra-Buxeda, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veganzones, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Bel, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad celíaca es una enteropatía frecuente que se asocia a manifestaciones clínicas muy variadas en parte debidas a la malabsorción. En la mujer se ha asociado a alteraciones obstétricas y ginecológicas como abortos de repetición, retraso intrauterino de crecimiento, parto prematuro y bajo peso al nacer. Presentamos el caso de una mujer con enfermedad celíaca no diagnosticada y con un parto eutócico de feto muerto de 34 semanas de gestación con alteraciones morfológicas graves de hipomineralización compatibles con raquitismo. En la literatura médica el raquitismo congénito secundario a malabsorción por enfermedad celíaca de la madre es excepcional. Se comentan los conocimientos actuales sobre el metabolismo fosfocálcico materno-fetal. Relacionamos la celiaquía activa con la hipocalcemia severa durante la gestación y con el raquitismo fetal mortal. Se sugiere la necesidad de un cribado de dicha enfermedad en las gestantes con signos de malabsorción o anomalías en el desarrollo del feto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(10): 678-682, Dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Raquitismo fetal mortal y celiaquía materna no diagnosticada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5424^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38638^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7172^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12691^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
