<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136558</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non- PSA serum markers for the diagnosis of PCa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prostate cancer (PCa) is the most common male malignancy in our population. Over the past two decades, the prostate specific antigen (PSA) has been widely used for screening, diagnosis and monitoring of prostate cancer. Routine use of PSA has been continuing subject to controversy due to its limited specificity, which is derived from the fact that serum PSA levels are produced in a variety of non-neoplastic conditions. The shortcomings in sensitivity and specificity of PSA have promoted the search for new biomarkers to improve diagnostic performance. The ultimate goal is to get those diagnosing clinically significant prostate tumors and to individualize treatment in this disease. Among the biomarkers studied in prostate cancer we could found tissue biomarkers as well as serum or urine biomarkers. In this paper we proceed to review those serum biomarkers not related to PSA that have been published in the literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribal, María José1Hospital Clínic de Barcelona</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musquera, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciudin, Alexandru</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de próstata (CaP) es la neoplasia del varón más común en nuestra población. Durante las dos últimas décadas, el antígeno específico prostático (PSA) se ha utilizado ampliamente para el cribado, diagnóstico y seguimiento del CaP. El uso rutinario de PSA ha sido objeto de continua controversia debido a su limitada especificidad, que se deriva del hecho de que los niveles séricos de PSA elevados se producen en una variedad de condiciones no neoplásicas. Las carencias en sensibilidad y especificidad del PSA han promovido la búsqueda de nuevos biomarcadores para mejorar el rendimiento diagnóstico. El objetivo final es conseguir el diagnóstico de aquéllos tumores de próstata clínicamente significativos y poder individualizar el tratamiento en esta enfermedad. Dentro de los biomarcadores estudiados en cáncer de próstata encontramos biomarcadores tisulares, séricos y urinarios. En el siguiente trabajo procedemos a una revisión pormenorizada de aquellos marcadores séricos no relacionados con PSA que se han publicado en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(3): 229-239, abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136558</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores séricos no-PSA en el diagnóstico del CaP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23145</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22940^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9553^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9553^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
