<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117347</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Costs of temporary disability in Spain related to diabetes mellitus and its complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: To ascertain the socioeconomic impact of diabetes, it is essential to estimate overall costs, including both direct and indirect costs (premature retirements, working hours lost, or sick leaves). This study analyzed indirect costs for temporary disability(TD) due to diabetes and its complications in Spain in 2011 by assessing the related ICD-9 MCcodes. Material and method: For this purpose, the number of TD processes and their mean duration were recorded. The indirect costs associated to loss of working days were also estimated. Results: In 2011, diabetes and its complications were related to 2.567 TD processes, which resulted in the loss of 154.214 days. In terms of costs, this disease represented for Spanish public health administrations an expense of 3,297.095.3 D, with an estimated cost per patient (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Teófila Vicente-Herrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capdevila García, Luisa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terradillos García, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Iñiguez de la Torre, M. Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-González, Ángel Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivos: Para conocer el impacto socioeconómico de la diabetes es indispensable sable realizar el cálculo de los costes globales, de modo que se incluyan los gastos directos, pero también los indirectos (jubilaciones prematuras por enfermedad, pérdida de horas de trabajo o bajas laborales). El presente trabajo estudió los costes indirectos por incapacidad temporal (IT)derivados de la diabetes y sus complicaciones en España en el año 2011 mediante la evaluación &#152;de los códigos CIE-9 MC relacionados con esta patología. Material y método: Para ello, se registraron el número de procesos de IT y su duración media. Además, se estimó el coste asociado a la pérdida de días laborales. Resultados: La diabetes y sus complicaciones se relacionaron con 2.567 procesos de IT en 2011que dieron lugar a una pérdida de 154.214 días. Traducido en costes, esta enfermedad supuso para las administraciones públicas de salud en España un gasto de 3.297.095,3  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(8): 447-455, oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costes por incapacidad temporal en España derivados de la diabetes mellitus y sus complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
