<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141315</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of chronic diseases on life expectancy in the population of Catalonia, Spain, in 1994 and 200</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes the changes in the prevalence of selected chronic conditions and their impact on the life expectancy in the population of Catalonia. The chronic conditions selected are: hypertension, diabetes, stroke, heart diseases, chronic bronchitis, asthma, chronic allergies, musculoskeletal system diseases, and anxiety/depression. The prevalence of these diseases is estimated from data collected by the Health Survey of Catalonia in 1994 and 2006. The most frequently chronic conditions among the Catalan population are the musculoskeletal disorders, the high blood pressure and the depression and/or anxiety. By the analysis of the changes in the life expectancy free of chronic disorders, this study shows the impact of these disorders in the life expectancy. The burden of the chronic morbidity in our community, and its impact on the health systems, requires further studies to increase the knowledge of this phenomenon (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tresserras-Gaju, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mompart-Penina, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugulat-Guiteras, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Beneyto, Vicenç</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosas-Ruiz, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza los cambios en la prevalencia de determinados trastornos crónicos y estima su impacto en la esperanza de vida de la población de Cataluña. Los trastornos crónicos seleccionados son: hipertensión arterial, diabetes, ictus, enfermedades del corazón, bronquitis crónica, asma, alergias crónicas, enfermedades del aparato locomotor y ansiedad/depresión. La prevalencia de estos trastornos se estima a partir de los datos recogidos por la Encuesta de Salud de Cataluña en 1994 y 2006. Los trastornos crónicos más frecuentemente presentes en la población catalana son los del aparato locomotor, la hipertensión arterial y la depresión y/o ansiedad. Mediante el análisis de los cambios en la esperanza de vida libre de trastornos crónicos se profundiza en el impacto que estas patologías tienen en la esperanza de vida. La importancia de la morbilidad crónica en nuestra sociedad, así como su impacto en los sistemas de salud, requiere de nuevos estudios que profundicen en el conocimiento de este fenómeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(supl.2): 9-15, dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de los trastornos crónicos en la esperanza de vida de la población de Cataluña en 1994 y 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
