<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112106</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient's perception on their well-being during hospitalization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective was to know the patient´s opinion regarding the elements of the care they receive during hospitalization that are important to attain their well-being. Methodology: Exploratory qualitative study. The participants included 30 key informants who had been hospitalized in general surgery and were interviewed in their homes after they were discharged, using a semi-structured interview guide. Results: Technical and interpersonal care are essential factors to attain well-being during hospitalization. The infrastructures, services provided by other departments and meeting the patient´s expectations are also important elements. Conclusion: Hospitalized patients perceive wellness when they are treated properly and attended by trained personnel. It is important to consider the other issues that modulate the perception on well-being, which depend directly on the hospital environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Carreño, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almansa Martínez, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Monsiváis, María Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Interial Guzmán, M. Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la opinión de los pacientes acerca de los aspectos de la atención que reciben durante la hospitalización, que son importantes para lograr su bienestar. Metodología: Estudio cualitativo exploratorio. Los participantes fueron 30 informantes claves que estuvieron hospitalizados en cirugía general y fueron entrevistados en sus domicilios, posterior a su egreso, mediante una guía de entrevista semi-estructurada. Resultados: La atención técnica e interpersonal son esenciales para lograr el bienestar durante la hospitalización. Además es relevante la infraestructura, servicios otorgados por otros departamentos y cumplimiento de expectativas de los pacientes. Conclusión: Los pacientes hospitalizados perciben bienestar cuando reciben buen trato y son atendidos por personal competente. Es relevante la consideración de los otros aspectos que modulan la percepción del bienestar y dependen directamente del entorno hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(4): 185-189, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción del paciente acerca de su bienestar durante la hospitalización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
