<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159839</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">History prophylaxis against contagious diseases. Preventive measures described in Leviticus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chapters 13 and 14 of Leviticus focus on performance against leprosy, most feared throughout history that diseases like syphilis Black Death or disease. The aim of this paper is to analyze thoroughly the preventive measures of both sections from the biblical leprosy, its consequences and its impact throughout history. Method: Chapters 13 and 14 of Leviticus in three different versions of the Bible was discussed. Later, other studies and manuals communicable diseases were analyzed. Development: The findings highlight the utility of the above measures to control the spread of contagious diseases, quarantine appearing as the optimal solution to promote the welfare and health of the community at that time, and hygiene was considered a cornerstone in this area. Conclusions: The implementation of these interventions has produced notable benefits, especially in reducing mortality in both the Jewish population of the biblical period and subsequently other companies, highlighting some cities during the Black Death; and they have formed the pillars on which rests the current epidemiology and public health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Vázquez, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los capítulos 13 y 14 del libro de Levítico se centran en la actuación ante la lepra, enfermedad más temida a lo largo de la historia que enfermedades como la Peste Negra o la sífilis. El objetivo del presente artículo es analizar de forma exhaustiva las medidas preventivas de ambos capítulos frente a la lepra bíblica, sus consecuencias y su repercusión a lo largo de la historia. Método: Se examinaron los capítulos 13 y 14 del Levítico en tres versiones diferentes de la Biblia. Posteriormente se analizaron otros documentos de investigadores relacionadas con la temática y manuales de enfermedades transmisibles. Desarrollo del tema: Los hallazgos obtenidos destacan la utilidad de las medidas descritas para controlar la expansión de las enfermedades transmisibles, presentándose la cuarentena como la solución más óptima para promocionar el bienestar y la salud de la comunidad en aquel período, y la higiene era considerada un eje fundamental en este ámbito. Conclusiones: La aplicación de estas intervenciones ha producido beneficios notorios, especialmente en la reducción de la mortalidad, tanto en la población hebrea del período bíblico como en otras sociedades posteriormente, destacando algunas ciudades en durante la Peste Negra; y han instaurado pilares sobre las que descansa la epidemiología y salud pública actual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(46): 41-53, sept.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159839</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia de la profilaxis ante las enfermedades contagiosas. Medidas preventivas descritas en el Levítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27783^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
