<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73031</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflections on the role of the physician in in-hospital duties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The physician on-call is a fundamental support for modern in-patient care. The majority ofthe time during which a patient is in the hospital, he/she is under their care. There isalmost no information about its clinical aspects. These are greatly infl uenced by thepatient, his/her family, other patients and their relatives, catering services, some specialsituations, nursing personnel, and the doctor both as the main responsible person for thepatient and as the physician on-call. As the doctor on call, he/she should have a clear ideaof what the objectives are, achieve good management of the calls received, make thedifference corresponding decisions and help the work of the patient&#146;s responsible physician.It is necessary to analyze and adapt the amount of work that the physician on-call has(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Ahijado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Ramos, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Ruiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La guardia médica es un pilar fundamental en la asistencia hospitalaria moderna. La mayoríadel tiempo que un paciente permanece ingresado está bajo su cuidado. Prácticamenteno existe información sobre los aspectos clínicos de la misma. En ella tienen gran infl uenciael propio paciente, su familia, otros enfermos y sus acompañantes, hostelería, diversassituaciones especiales, personal de enfermería y el médico en su doble vertiente como responsabledel enfermo y como médico de guardia. Como responsable del enfermo el médicodebe tener en cuenta diversos aspectos sobre el control del mismo, la toma de decisionesy facilitar la labor de la guardia. Como médico de guardia debe tener claro cuáles son susobjetivos, lograr una buena gestión de las llamadas que recibe, tomar las decisiones que lecorresponden y facilitar la labor del médico responsable del enfermo. Asimismo, hay queanalizar y adecuar la carga de trabajo sobre el médico de guardia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;209(4): 185-188, abr.2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Refl exiones sobre el papel del médico en la guardia intrahospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33885^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33885^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33885^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33885^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33885^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11482</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
