<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158739</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiological diagnosis of medical device-associated infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of surgically implanted medical devices has increased greatly over the last few years. Despite surgical advances and improvements in the materials and design of devices, infection continues to be a major complication of their use. Device-associated infections are produced mainly during their implantation and, are caused by microorganisms that are part of the skin flora. Biofilm development on device surfaces is the most important factor to explain the pathophysiological aspects of infection. Microbiological diagnosis is difficult and can often only be achieved after removal of the device. Sonication of the removed device may be a useful tool, since this procedure dislodges and disaggregates biofilm bacteria from the device. Molecular techniques, especially PCR, applied to the tissues and material obtained after sonication have shown to have a high sensitivity and specificity for the diagnosis of cardiovascular device infections (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo León, Jose Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco-Álvarez de Luna, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marin Arriaza, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueto López, Marina de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El empleo de dispositivos biomédicos implantados quirúrgicamente se ha incrementado en los últimos años. A pesar de las mejoras en las técnicas quirúrgicas, en los materiales y el diseño de los dispositivos, la infección asociada continúa siendo una complicación relativamente frecuente y grave. La infección se produce generalmente durante la cirugía a partir de la microbiota cutánea del paciente. Cuando los microorganismos colonizan el dispositivo se desarrollan sobre su superficie formando una biocapa que es determinante en la patogenia de estas infecciones. El diagnóstico microbiológico es difícil y en muchas ocasiones solo se consigue tras la retirada del dispositivo. El cultivo tras sonicación puede ser una herramienta diagnóstica útil ya que consigue la desagregación de la biocapa. También, las técnicas moleculares, especialmente las basadas en PCR, aplicadas a tejidos y al material obtenido tras sonicación han demostrado alta sensibilidad y especificidad en el diagnóstico de infecciones asociadas a dispositivos intracardiacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;34(10): 655-660, dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico microbiológico de las infecciones asociadas a dispositivos biomédicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13907^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
