<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158602</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence, treatment satisfaction and quality of life in patients with breast cancer at the Hospital Universitario del Caribe. (Cartagena, Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the adherence, treatment satisfaction and quality of life of patients with breast cancer. Materials and methods: A descriptive, prospective, cross-sectional study, developed at the Hospital Universitario del Caribe, between August 2014 and April 2015. The sample consisted of 23 patients, diagnosed with breast cancer. Adherence, Treatment Satisfaction and quality of life were determined with the following instruments: Simplified Medication Adherence Questionnaire ( SMAQ ) , Dispensing Record (DR) , satisfaction test ESTAR of ARPAS Study adapted and WHOQOL BREF respectively. The ESTAR questionnaire was validated by experts using Cronbach&#146;s alpha. Results: 54.78 % of patients (according SMAQ) were no adherent to chemotherapy, satisfaction was 3.94 (range 0-6) . Quality of life was on average 3.2 (range 1-5), with values of 14.5% at level 1 and 7.14% at level 5 range . Most dimensions of QoL questionnaire bear a direct correlation with the overall level of satisfaction to treatment; casting a negative figure (-0.3207 ***) only in the dimension of satisfaction with treatment effectiveness. Conclusions: The quality of life was medium and low, adherence and treatment satisfaction the decreased treatment and an inverse correlation between quality of life and treatment satisfaction, probably because of undesirable adverse reactions are in declining quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marrugo Padilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Zambrano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paut Quiñonez, AE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diaz Mulford, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>viz Amador, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taron Dunoyer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar la adherencia, satisfacción al tratamiento y calidad de vida de pacientes con cáncer de mama. Materiales y métodos: Estudio descriptivo, prospectivo, trasversal, desarrollado en el Hospital Universitario del Caribe, entre agosto de 2014 y abril de 2015. La muestra fueron 23 pacientes, diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama. La adherencia, satisfacción al tratamiento y calidad de vida se determinaron con los instrumentos siguientes: Cuestionario simplified medication adherence questionnaire (SMAQ), registro de dispensación del hospital (RD), test de satisfacción ESTAR del Estudio ARPAS adaptado y el cuestionario WHOQOL BREF respectivamente. El cuestionario ESTAR fue validado por expertos y mediante alfa de Cronbach. Resultados: El 54,78% de las pacientes (según SMAQ), fueron no adherentes a quimioterápicos, la satisfacción fue de 3,94 (rango 0-6). La calidad de vida estuvo en un promedio de 3.2 (rango 1-5), con valores de 14,5% y 7,14% en el nivel 5 del rango. La mayoría de dimensiones del cuestionario de calidad de vida guardan una correlación directamente proporcional con el nivel total de satisfacción al tratamiento; arrojando un dato negativo (-0,3207) únicamente en la dimensión de satisfacción con la eficacia al tratamiento Conclusiones: La calidad de vida fue media y baja, la adherencia y satisfacción al tratamiento fueron bajas y se presentó una correlación inversa entre calidad de vida y la satisfacción al tratamiento, probablemente a causa de reacciones adversas indeseables que se constituyen en disminución de la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;18(6): 251-264, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158602</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia, satisfacción al tratamiento y calidad de vida de pacientes con cáncer de mama en el Hospital Universitario del Caribe. (Cartagena, Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
