<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158905</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nasogastric feeding tube located in the lung. SENSAR case of the trimester</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A clinical case is presented that was communicated to Spanish Notification System on Safety in Anaesthesia and Recovery (SENSAR). Using this communication and its analysis, a strategy is obtained in order to reduce the risks associated with the insertion of a nasogastric tube (NST) for enteral nutrition in adult patients in the post-surgical recovery unit. A description of the incident is presented, an analysis of its causes, and the measures that were introduced in order to avoid similar incidents in the future, as well as to promote a safety culture in the organisation. A description of associated incidents registered in SENSAR is also given. The aim of this work is to describe, analyse and introduce safety measures arising from incidents notified to SENSAR, associated with the insertion and checking of the nutrition NST in adult patients in the post-surgical recovery unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sistema Español de Notificación en Seguridad en Anestesia y Reanimación (SENSAR)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso clínico comunicado al Sistema Español de Notificación en Seguridad en Anestesia y Reanimación (SENSAR), y a consecuencia de esta comunicación y análisis se obtiene una estrategia para reducir riesgos asociados a la colocación y utilización de sonda nasogástrica (SNG) para nutrición enteral en pacientes adultos en la unidad de reanimación postoperatoria. Se describe el incidente, el análisis de sus causas, así como las medidas de mejora que se implementaron para evitar incidentes similares en el futuro y fomentar la cultura de seguridad en la organización. Se realiza también una descripción de los incidentes relacionados registrados en SENSAR. El objetivo del presente trabajo es describir, analizar e implementar líneas de seguridad derivadas de los incidentes notificados a SENSAR en relación con la colocación y la comprobación de SNG de nutrición en pacientes adultos de la unidad de reanimación postoperatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(1): e1-e5, ene. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158905</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sonda nasogástrica de nutrición enteral en localización pulmonar. Caso SENSAR del trimestre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12415^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7602^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
