<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117543</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">X-Linked juvenile retinoschisis history and present</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The linked juvenile retinoschisis X (XLRS) is a macular degeneration which can lead to vitreoretinal degeneration; presents recessive transmission pattern is almost exclusively men. It is often diagnosed at school age by decreased visual acuity or vitreous hemorrhage, abruptly. RS1 is the disease-associated gene, which encodes Retinosquina, a secreted protein from cells of the retina that binds to the surface of the photoreceptors and bipolar cells, helping to maintain the integrity of the retina. The characteristic features of the disease include, visual acuity reduction, radial grooves arising from the foveal retinoschisis, division of the peripheral and inner layers of the retina, given negative Electroretinograms a marked decrease in the b-wave. Today with spectral domain OCT is the most important diagnostic technique, which demonstrates the characteristic Retinoschisis macular area, beyond the radial pattern of the fundus. The treatment is based primarily on visual acuity improvement. The carbonic anhydrase inhibitors have been used with success in reducing the posterior pole retinoschisis. Recently, gene therapy has involved using nonviral vectors of solid lipid nanoparticles, for RJLX with promising results in the future. A literature review on the pathogenesis and options for diagnosis and current treatment XLRS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora Botia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Dangel, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboleda Hurtado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Retinosquisis Juvenil Ligada al cromosoma X (RJLX) es una degeneración macular que puede conducir a degeneración vitreorretiniana; presenta patrón de transmisión recesivo y es casi exclusivamente de hombres. Frecuentemente se diagnostica durante la edad escolar por disminución de agudeza visual o por hemorragia vítrea abrupta. RS1 es el gen asociado a la enfermedad, el cual codifica Retinosquina, una proteína secretada a partir de células de la retina que se une a la superficie de los fotorreceptores y células bipolares, contribuyendo a mantener la integridad de la retina. Los rasgos característicos de la  enfermedad incluyen, disminución de la agudeza visual, estrías radiales que surgen de la Retinosquisis foveal, división de las capas interna y periférica  de la retina, Electrorretinograma negativo dado por una disminución marcada de la onda b. En la actualidad la OCT con dominio espectral, es la técnica diagnostica más importante, la cual demuestra la Retinosquisis característica del área macular, mas allá del patrón radial del fondo de ojo. El tratamiento se basa principalmente en la mejoría de la agudeza visual. Los inhibidores de la anhidrasa carbónica han sido utilizados con éxito en la reducción de la Retinosquisis del polo posterior. Recientemente se ha involucrado la terapia génica mediante vectores no virales de nanopartículas sólidas lipidícas, para la RJLX, con resultados prometedores en un futuro. Realizamos una revisión bibliográfica sobre la patogenia y las opciones para el diagnostico y tratamiento actual de la RJLX (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(3): 173-176, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retinosquisis juvenile ligada al cromosoma X. Historia y actualidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31976^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37289^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
