<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61412</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health impact of compounds used in swimming pool water treatment: state of the question</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Swimming and the various aquatic activities performed in indoor swimming pools are not only practised by thousands of individuals daily but are also highly recommended for rehabilitation in patients with musculoskeletal processes to aid mobility and muscle activation; furthermore, these activities are also useful in patients with exercise-induced asthma and some other respiratory diseases, since the warm, moist air is less likely to provoke an attack. However, in the last decade, concern has arisen on whether direct contact with the compounds used in water disinfection could alter bronchial reactivity in swimming-pool users and could also be a triggering factor for asthma in predisposed children. The present review evaluates research articles on this subject and, especially, discussions on these articles, to create an objective view of the state of the question. In particular, the final aim is to provide recommendations based on the experience of these studies to stimulate swimming pool users to avoid contamination and preserve their health and that of their children, to train monitors and trainers in these matters and, lastly, to increase awareness among the managers of installations of the impact of disinfecting compounds on health(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Drobnica, Franchek</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La natación y las diversas actividades acuáticas realizadas en piscinas cubiertas, además de ser actividades deportivas practicadas por miles de individuos diariamente, son una herramienta de rehabilitación muy recomendada en pacientes con procesos limitantes del sistema musculoesquelético con el objeto de facilitar su movilización y su activación, y en pacientes con asma de esfuerzo y ciertas enfermedades respiratorias por su poca asmogenicidad al ser un ambiente cálido y húmedo. Sin embargo, en esta última década ha surgido la inquietud de si el contacto directo de los compuestos utilizados en la desinfección del agua pudiera no sólo ser un elemento importante en la alteración de la reactividad bronquial del usuario de la piscina, sino también ser un desencadenante de la aparición de asma en sujetos predispuestos en edad pediátrica. En la presente revisión se valoran los artículos de investigación y, sobre todo, las discusiones sobre ellos, con el objeto de crear una visión objetiva de dónde estamos hoy con respecto a este asunto. Pero sobre todo, el objetivo final es ofrecer recomendaciones basadas en la experiencia de esos estudios que estimulen al usuario de las piscinas a no contaminar y a preservar su salud y la de sus congéneres, a formar a los monitores y educadores de los practicantes en ese mismo sentido y, por último y no menos importante, a los responsables de la gestión de las instalaciones para concienciarlos de la importancia de su trabajo en el bien de los demás(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);44(161): 42-47, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto sobre la salud de los compuestos utilizados en el tratamiento del agua en las piscinas. Estado de la cuestión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32526</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51612^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15281^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
