<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68042</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relevant clinical role of the determination of insulin resistance degree in patients and in general population, has lead to the appearance of a great variety of methods. Among some of them based on fasting measures, there is the Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMA). This calculation is based on the relation between the fasting glycemia and insulin levels, evaluating the balance between the hepatic glucose production and the insulin secretion. Furthermore, this method is widely used in clinical practice. This fact gives the possibility to compare different studies. The HOMA method has an additional advantage since it is a good indicator of beta cell functionality (HOMA-B). This procedure presents good correlations with the euglycemic clamp, and with the intravenous glucose tolerance test (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tinahones, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fuentes, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Sánchez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El gran valor clínico que tiene la determinación del grado de resistencia a la insulina de los pacientes y de la población general ha hecho que proliferen gran cantidad de métodos. Entre los distintos métodos basados en medidas basales figura el Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMA). El cálculo se establece a partir de la relación entre la glucemia basal y los niveles de insulina, evaluando el balance entre la producción hepática de glucosa y la secreción de insulina. Es el método más usado y publicado. Esta sola razón le confiere un valor añadido, ya que permite la comparación entre los estudios que lo han utilizado. El método HOMA tiene una ventaja adicional, pues permite valorar la funcionalidad de la célula beta (HOMA-B). Este procedimiento presenta buenas correlaciones con el clamp euglucémico y con el test de tolerancia intravenosa a la glucosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;24(4): 291-295, jul.-ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68042</dc:identifier>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
