<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59468</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enteral feeding of critical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Artificial nutrition support forms part of thebasic care of critical patients. Enteral feeding has beenshown to be better than total parenteral nutrition atimproving morbidity (infectious complications) andreducing the length of hospital stays, number of days withmechanical ventilation, and costs. As with any othertreatment, enteral feeding has associated complicationsand side effects which should be understood and treatedin order to obtain the greatest benefit from it and reducepossible adverse effects. In this review, we attempt toprovide a practical summary of the use of enteral feedingin critical patients. We cover the management of the mostfrequent associated complications, based on new studiesand current scientific evidence. The review is intended toserve as a practice guide for the routine care of severely illpatients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Garrido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Garrido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Romero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El soporte nutricional artificial forma parte del cuidadobásico del paciente crítico. La nutrición enteral(NE) se ha mostrado superior a la nutrición parenteraltotal (NPT) en la mejoría de la morbilidad (complicacionesinfecciosas), y en la reducción de la estancia hospitalaria,días de ventilación mecánica y costes.Como cualquier otro tratamiento, la NE no está exentade complicaciones y efectos secundarios, que debemosconocer y tratar para obtener el máximo beneficio deésta y disminuir en lo posible los efectos adversos.En esta revisión intentamos resumir de manera prácticael uso de la NE en el paciente crítico, así como elmanejo de las complicaciones más frecuentes que podemosencontrar en relación con dicha nutrición en base alas nuevas publicaciones y la evidencia científica existente,de manera que pueda servir como Guía de actuaciónal profesional en la asistencia diaria al paciente gravementeenfermo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(1): 31-42, ene. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición enteral en el paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
