<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77337</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural therapy in the treatment of obesity (I): new directionsfor clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Behavioural therapy (BT) in obesity treatment helps individuals to develop skills to achieve healthier body weights. Instead of helping to decide what to change, it helps to identify how to change; lifestyle modification is essential for any treatment of obesity, be it dieting, medication, surgery, etc. Physicians often tend to be unwilling to use BT considering it time-consuming and skill-intensive. However, BT can be standardized and used more readily in clinical practice. Besides, new approaches have been developed which contribute to increase the success of the treatments, like non face-to-face techniques, or the new cognitive therapy. Setting: Classical knowledge on BT has been updated with recent publications and information on these new approaches, combined with our own experience in the clinical treatment of obesity. Results: Most research on BT has been conducted in university-based programs which, despite their importance, tell us little about its effectiveness in actual clinical practice. Future research might focus on determining how BT can be best applied in a real-world setting. Examples of new directions are increased maintenance periods, use of Internet, and new cognitive therapy. Besides, elucidating the genetic component in the prognosis of weight management -the nutrigenomic approach- could assist in the development of more effective and individually tailored therapeutic strategies; indeed, single nucleotide polymorphisms in candidate genes have been related with eating patterns. Conclusions: This review gives a renewed perspective of BT for obesity, offers key-pointers and describes specific ways in which medical professionals can promote and encourage self-care of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Heredia, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garaulet, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La terapia conductual (TC) en la obesidad busca desarrollar habilidades que promuevan un peso saludable. En lugar de qué cambiar, se trata de identificar cómo cambiar, pues modificar el estilo de vida es esencial para cualquier tratamiento de la obesidad, ya sea dietético, farmacológico, quirúrgico, etc. Los profesionales médicos suelen ser reacios a emplearla, considerando que exige tiempo y habilidades específicas. Sin embargo, la TC puede ser fácilmente estandarizada y aplicada en la práctica clínica, y nuevos enfoques y técnicas contribuyen a un mayor éxito del tratamiento. Ámbito: Se ha actualizado el conocimiento existente sobre TC, combinando información sobre los nuevos enfoques con nuestra propia experiencia en el tratamiento clínico de la obesidad. Resultados: Los estudios sobre TC provienen principalmente del ámbito académico y, aunque son importantes, dan poca información sobre la efectividad de la TC en la práctica clínica. Investigaciones futuras deberían determinar cómo la TC puede ser aplicada en un contexto clínico realista. Ejemplos de los nuevos enfoques son: el incremento del período de mantenimiento, el uso de internet, o la nueva terapia cognitiva. Asimismo, considerar el componente genético en la prognosis del control del peso corporal podría ayudar a desarrollar estrategias terapéuticas más efectivas y personalizadas; de hecho, ciertos polimorfismos génicos se han relacionado con la adopción de determinados patrones alimentarios. Conclusiones: Esta revisión presenta una perspectiva renovada de la TC para la obesidad, ofrece puntos clave y describe vías específicas por las que el profesional médico puede promover la participación activa de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(6): 629-639, nov.-dic. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77337</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de comportamiento en el tratamiento de la obesidad (I): Nuevas direcciones en la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
