<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164141</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmaceutical consultation: gemfibrozil poisoning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Forty-six-year-old patient diagnosed with depression, hyperthyroidism and hypertriglyceridemia. Over the last month and a half, she has had to go to the emergency service several times due to major diarrhea symptoms, nausea and malaise. The doctors diagnosed gastroenteritis, administered intravenous fluid with antiemetics and prescribed paracetamol 1 g every 8 hours. During the consultation, her husband asked to be given Trialmin® 600 mg, which had been «prescribed for [his wife&#146;s] thyroid» at a dose 6 pills per day. We detected a negative drug result stemming from a prescription error and the drug&#146;s indicated use for hypertriglyceridemia. We acted by explaining that Tirodril® is the drug that had been prescribed for hyperthyroidism, rather than Trialmin®, which is indicated for hypertriglyceridemia. The patient is directed to the emergency service with a written report for the doctor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acuña Elvira, Nerea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 46 años diagnosticada de depresión, hipertiroidismo e hipertrigliceridemia. En el último mes y medio ha tenido que acudir al servicio de urgencias del hospital en varias ocasiones por presentar cuadros diarreicos importantes acompañados de náuseas y malestar general. Los médicos le diagnosticaron gastroenteritis, administraron suero intravenoso con antieméticos y pautaron paracetamol 1g cada 8 horas. En la propia consulta, el marido solicita le dispensemos Trialmin® 600 mg, que su esposa «tiene prescrito para el tiroides» y del que toma 6 comprimidos diarios. Detectamos un resultado negativo de la medicación por error en la pauta e indicación del medicamento para la hipertrigliceridemia. Intervenimos explicándole que Tirodril® es el medicamento que le han prescrito para el hipertiroidismo y no Trialmin ®, que está indicado en hipertrigliceridemias. Se deriva al servicio de urgencias con un informe por escrito de la situación dirigido al médico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);9(2): 49-51, jun. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consulta farmacéutica: intoxicación por gemfibrozilo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23643^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23643^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
