<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102602</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of the rapid antigen technique in the diagnosis of Streptococcus pyogenes pharyngotonsillitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Streptococcus pyogenes is the most frequent bacterial cause of acute tonsillopharyngitis. The validity of the rapid antigen test was analysed for its diagnosis in a Paediatric Primary Care setting. The clinical profile with better diagnostic yield was also identified. The unnecessary use of antibiotics was quantified when the rapid antigen test or only the clinical diagnosis was used. The sensitivity of the assay to penicillin, erythromycin and clindamycin was also determined. Patients and methods: Cross-sectional study was conducted on children between 2 to 14 years with acute tonsillitis and/or pharyngitis seen in five Primary Care Centres, from January 2008to May 2010. After a clinical diagnosis, two swabs were taken for pharyngotonsillar smears: the first was used for a rapid antigen test, and the second one for a culture and a study of antibiotic sensitivity, with its analysis being blind to the rapid test result. A total sample of546 consecutive was envisaged and with consecutive sampling. Results: A total 192 patients were included. The prevalence of Streptococcus pyogenes was38.7% (95% CI: 31.4-45.7). Odynophagia and scarlatiniform rash were most likely with positive cultures, the Streptococcus pyogenes was sensitive to penicillin in 100%, to erythromycin in97.3% and to clindamycin in 86.3%. The specificity of the rapid antigen test was 91.5% and with a Negative Predictive Value of 91.5%. About half (49.2%) of those who would have receive antibiotics for clinical suspicion would have been treated unnecessarily, with this decreasing to at least in 29.5% when using the rapid antigen test. Conclusions: The rapid antigen test can lead to a better use of antibiotics. Its use in Paediatric Primary Health Care could be useful when, as when the result is negative, there would be no need to confirm by a culture, in those Health Centres with difficult access to laboratory(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Hurlé, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Rodríguez, P. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Bajo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Guirado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbesú Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicieza García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueras De Lorenzo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Streptococcus pyogenes es la causa bacteriana más importante de faringoamigdalitis aguda. Se analizó la validez de una prueba antigénica rápida para su diagnóstico, en consultas de atención primaria; asimismo se identificó el perfil clínico con mejor rendimiento diagnóstico, se cuantificó el uso innecesario de antibióticos cuando se utilizaba la prueba o solamente diagnóstico clínico y se determinó la sensibilidad microbiana a penicilina, eritromicina y clindamicina. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal a niños/as entre 2-14 años con amigdalitis y/o faringitis aguda atendidos en 5 consultas, desde enero de 2008 hasta mayo de 2010. Tras el diagnóstico clínico se realizó frotis faringoamigdalar con 2 hisopos: con el primero se realizó una prueba antigénica rápida y con el segundo cultivo y sensibilidad antibiótica, siendo su análisis ciego al resultado de la prueba. Se ha previsto una muestra de 546 personas y muestreo consecutivo. Resultados: Se incluyó a 192 pacientes. La prevalencia de Streptococcus pyogenes fue del 38,7%(IC del 95%: 31,4-45,7). La odinofagia y el exantema escarlatiniforme fueron más probables con cultivo positivo. En el 100% hubo sensibilidad a la penicilina, en el 97,3% a eritromicina y en el 86,3% a clindamicina. La especificidad de la prueba fue del 91,5% y el valor predictivo negativo del 91,5%. El 49,2% de quienes recibirían antibióticos por sospecha clínica serían tratados innecesariamente, disminuyendo al menos un 29,5% con la prueba. Conclusiones: La prueba permitió un uso más adecuado de antibióticos. Parece recomendable su uso en pediatría de atención primaria, sin necesidad de confirmación con cultivo cuando resulte negativa, en los centros con difícil acceso al laboratorio(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(3): 193-199, sept. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102602</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de una técnica antigénica rápida en el diagnóstico de faringoamigdalitis por Streptococcus pyogenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24356^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d947^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
