<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162173</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Increased serum renalase in peritoneal dialysis patients: Is it related to cardiovascular disease risk?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Renalase, with possible monoamine oxidase activity, is implicated in degradation of catecholamines; which suggests novel mechanisms of cardiovascular complications in patients with chronic kidney diseases. Epicardial adipose tissue (EAT) has been found to correlate with cardiovascular diseases (CVD) in dialysis patients. The present study aimed to evaluate the association of serum renalase levels with EAT thickness and other CVD risk factors in peritoneal dialysis (PD) patients. Methods: The study included 40 PD patients and 40 healthy controls. All subjects underwent blood pressure and anthropometric measurements. Serum renalase was assessed by using a commercially available assay. Transthoracic echocardiography was used to measure EAT thickness and left ventricular mass index (LVMI) in all subjects. Results: The median serum renalase level was significantly higher in the PD patients than in the control group [176.5 (100&#150;278.3) vs 122 (53.3&#150;170.0)ng/ml] (p=0.001). Renalase was positively correlated with C-reactive protein (r=0.705, p&lt;0.001) and negatively correlated with RRF (r=&amp;#8722;0.511, p=0.021). No correlation was observed between renalase and EAT thickness or LVMI. There was a strong correlation between EAT thickness and LVMI in both the PD patients and the controls (r=0.848, p&lt;0.001 and r=0.640, p&lt;0.001 respectively). Conclusions: This study indicates that renalase is associated with CRP and residual renal function but not with EAT thickness as CVD risk factors in PD patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Okyay, Gulay Ulusal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oguz, Ebru Gok</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akoglu, Hadim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cimen, Tolga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gursoy, Guner Karaveli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayli, M Deniz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merhametsiz, Ozgur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yildirim, Tolga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yeter, Ekrem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canbakan, Basol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La renalasa, posiblemente con actividad monoaminooxidasa, está implicada en la degradación de catecolaminas, lo que indica nuevos mecanismos de complicaciones cardiovasculares en pacientes con enfermedades renales crónicas. Se ha encontrado que el tejido adiposo epicárdico (TAE) se correlaciona con las enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV) en pacientes de diálisis. El presente estudio tuvo como objetivo evaluar la asociación de los niveles de renalasa sérica con el espesor del EAT y otros factores de riesgo de ECV en pacientes de diálisis peritoneal (DP). Métodos: El estudio incluyó a 40 pacientes de DP y a 40 controles sanos. Se tomaron la presión arterial y las medidas antropométricas de todos los individuos. Se evaluó la renalasa sérica mediante un ensayo disponible comercialmente. Se utilizó la ecocardiografía transtorácica para medir el espesor del TAE y el índice de masa ventricular izquierda (IMVI) en todos los individuos. Resultados: La mediana del nivel de renalasa sérica fue significativamente mayor en los pacientes de DP que en el grupo control (176,5 [100-278,3] frente a 122 [5,3-170,0] ng/ml) (p=0,001). La renalasa se correlacionó positivamente con la proteína C reactiva (r=0,705; p&lt;0,001) y negativamente con la FRR (r=-0,511, p=0,021). No se observó correlación entre la renalasa y el espesor del TAE ni el IMVI. Hubo una fuerte correlación entre el espesor del TAE y el IMVI tanto en los pacientes de DP como en los controles (r=0,848; p&lt;0,001 y r=0,640; p&lt;0,001, respectivamente). Conclusiones: Este estudio indica que la renalasa está asociada con la proteína C reactiva y la función renal residual, pero no con el espesor del TAE, como factores de riesgo de ECV en pacientes de DP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(2): 189-194, mar.-abr. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de renalasa sérica en pacientes de diálisis peritoneal: ¿está relacionado con el riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
