<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037118</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in selenium levels in epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. It has been suggested that antiepileptic drug therapies deplete total body selenium stores and failure    to give appropriate selenium supplementation, especially to patients receiving valproic acid during pregnancy may increase    the risk of neural tube defects or other free radical mediated damage. Selenium is essential for the synthesis of selenoproteins,    including glutathione peroxidase. Aims. To review the present state of knowledge about selenium behaviour in people with    epilepsy taking antiepileptic drugs and to develop guidelines for the appropriate use of selenium supplements. Development.    Databases such as Medline, Embase, Scisearch and Lilacs were consulted to have access to literature. A search in said    databases was performed in order to find articles published from January 1966 to August 2004. All articles published in    English and Spanish were considered. A manual review of the references present in each produced article was done in order    to identify the articles that the electronic search may have not found itself. The title and abstract of the potential articles were    analyzed before asking for the complete article. However, articles which seemed ambiguous were completely analyzed later to    establish their relevance. Conclusions. There is insufficient evidence to fully evaluate the effect of selenium supplementation.    The possible beneficial effects on pregnancy need to be evaluated in further studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Álvarez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Reyes, R. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, C. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se ha sugerido que los tratamientos anticonvulsionantes    disminuyen las reservas de selenio en el organismo    y que no administrar suplementos de selenio, especialmente a    las pacientes que reciben ácido valproico durante el embarazo,    puede aumentar el riesgo de desarrollar defectos del tubo neural u    otras alteraciones mediadas por radicales libres. El selenio es un    oligoelemento esencial para la síntesis de selenoproteínas, incluida    la glutatión peroxidasa. Objetivo. Realizar una revisión sistemática    de la literatura para poder presentar el estado del conocimiento    sobre el comportamiento del selenio en los pacientes con    epilepsia en tratamiento anticonvulsionante y desarrollar unas    recomendaciones para el uso adecuado de un suplemento de selenio.    Desarrollo. Se consultaron las bases de datos Medline, Embase,    Scisearch y Lilacs para acceder a la literatura, y se realizó una    búsqueda para localizar artículos publicados entre enero de 1966 y    agosto de 2004. Se tomaron todos los artículos publicados en    inglés y español. Se realizó una revisión manual de las referencias    presentadas en cada artículo con el fin de identificar los que no    identificó la búsqueda electrónica. El título y el resumen de los    artículos potencialmente útiles se analizaban antes de solicitar el    artículo completo. Sin embargo, los artículos en los que éstos eran    ambiguos para determinar su pertinencia también se analizaron en    su totalidad. Conclusiones. No hay suficientes evidencias para evaluar    el efecto de administrar un suplemento de selenio. El posible    beneficio durante el embarazo requiere estudios más profundos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(2): 111-116, ene. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037118</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteración de la concentración de selenio en la epilepsia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13027^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13027^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
