<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155199</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plasma homocysteine, Lp(a), and oxidative stress markers in peripheral macroangiopathy in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To study new risk factors for peripheral macroangiopathy (PM) in patients with diabetes, as oxidative stress (OS) and its interaction with classical risk factors: age, Lp(a), plasma homocysteine values and HbA1c. Subjects and methods: We studied 204 type2 diabetic (T2DM) patients, consecutive selected form a reference hospital and a secondary hospital form our Community (2009-2010). Design was a case (ABI&lt;0.89) control (ABI0.9-1.2) study. PM was defined using ankle brachial index (ABI). Thirty nine T2DM subjects presented ABI&gt;1.2 and were excluded. Clinical and biological parameters were determined using standard methods. Results: Comparing clinical and biological parameters obtained in both studied groups (T2DM+ABI&lt;0.9 vs T2DM+ABI0.9-1.2), we found statistical significant differences in age, evolution time of diabetes, Lp(a) and plasma homocysteine values. No differences were found in OS parameters: reduced glutathione, oxidized glutathione and maloldialdehide between studied groups. Plasma homocysteine values were an independent risk factor for the presence of PM and were related to evolution time of diabetes and reduced glutathione. Conclusions: We have confirmed that Lp(a) and independently plasma homocysteine values were related to PM in T2DM subjects. No association with PM and OS markers (GSH, GSSG and MDA) were found in T2DM with more than 10years of evolution time of their disease and high prevalence of chronic complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Folgado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Mendez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiro, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Hervás, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Real, Jose T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ascaso, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Buscar nuevos factores biológicos como el estrés oxidativo (EO) y su interacción con los clásicos, edad, HbA1c, Lp(a) y homocisteína plasmática asociados con la vasculopatía periférica (VP) del paciente con diabetes tipo2 (DMT2). Sujetos y métodos: Estudiamos 204 diabéticos tipo2 seleccionados de forma consecutiva de un hospital de referencia y un hospital comarcal de nuestra comunidad autónoma en el periodo comprendido entre enero de 2009 a mayo de 2010. Se trató de un estudio transversal de caso (ITB&lt;0,9)/control (ITB0,9-1,2). La VP fue definida por el índice tobillo-brazo (ITB). Se excluyeron 39 sujetos por presentar un ITB&gt;1,2. Los parámetros clinicobiológicos fueron medidos por procedimientos estandarizados. Resultados: Los sujetos fueron divididos en 2 grupos: con VP (ITB&gt;0,89) o sin VP (ITB0,9-1,2). Al comparar las variables clinicobiológicas entre ambos grupos encontramos diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la edad, el tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad, la Lp(a) y los valores plasmáticos de homocisteína. No encontramos diferencias en los parámetros de EO: glutatión reducido, glutatión oxidado y maloldialdehído entre grupos. La homocisteína plasmática fue un predictor independiente de la VP y se relacionó con los valores de glutatión reducido, la edad y el tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad. Conclusiones: Nuestro estudio confirmó que los valores elevados de Lp(a) y de forma independiente de homocisteína plasmática, se asocian con la presencia de VP definida por ITB en sujetos con DMT2. No encontramos que los marcadores de EO estudiados se asocien con VP en sujetos DMT2 con más de 10 años de evolución de su enfermedad y alta prevalencia de complicaciones crónicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(4): 188-194, ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155199</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Homocisteína plasmática, Lp(a) y marcadores de estrés oxidativo en la vasculopatía periférica del paciente con diabetes tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52270^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
