<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87056</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Navy Medical Corps (1728-1989)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Navy Medical Service was officially created by Juan Lacomba in 1728 in Cadiz. It was at its zenith in the Royal College of Surgery of the Navy until its suppression in 1836. In that year it started its independent period from the Faculty of Medical Sciences which later became the Faculty of Medicine of Cadiz. After its separation it suffered a loss of prestige that lasted until the last third of the 19th century, when it experienced a scientific recovery. The loss of the overseas colonies in 1898, the Second Republic and the Civil War were the bitterest and bloodiest moments of its history. Finally with the democratic transition at the end of the  seventies of the 20th century it experienced a new renaissance. In this last period the Naval Policlinic of Madrid, and the new naval hospitals in San Fernando, Cartagena and Ferrol were inaugurated. In 1989 it took a new turn with its integration by Royal Decree in the Defense Medical Service Corps. In this article we present a summary of its course, underlining its moments of glory and despair,  with the desire to pay to homage to the men who served along the 261 years of its existence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Cubillana de la Cruz, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Cuerpo de Sanidad de la Armada fue oficialmente instituido por Juan Lacomba en 1728 en la ciudad de Cádiz. Vivió su máximo esplendor dentro del Real Colegio de la Cirugía de la Armada hasta su supresión en 1836, momento en el que inició su andadura independiente de la Facultad de Ciencias Médicas, posterior Facultad de Medicina de Cádiz. Tras su segregación sufrió una fase de desprestigio que duró hasta el último tercio del siglo XIX, en el que resurgió científicamente. Las pérdidas de las colonias de Ultramar en 1898, la Segunda República y la Guerra Civil, marcaron los momentos más duros y sangrientos de su historia. Finalmente con la transición democrática en los finales de los años setenta del siglo XX, experimentó un nuevo renacimiento. En este último periodo se inauguraron la  Policlínica Naval de Madrid y los nuevos hospitales de Marina de San Fernando, Cartagena y Ferrol. En el año 1989 finalizó su singladura al ser integrado por Real Decreto en el Cuerpo Militar de Sanidad del Ministerio de Defensa. En este trabajo se intenta reflejar una síntesis de su trayectoria, resaltando sus momentos de gloria y de amargura, en un deseo de servir de homenaje a los hombres que le sirvieron a lo largo de los 261 años de su existencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;65(3): 188-203, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87056</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Cuerpo de Sanidad de La Armada (1728-1989)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
