<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76452</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimally invasive lateral approach in total hip replacement: A prospective randomized study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To compare the results of posterior correction using hybrid instrumentation and classical posterior release with those obtained with an extended posterior release. Material and methods: We carried out a retrospective cohort study of 46 patients diagnosed with adolescent idiopathic scoliosis (AIS). A posterior correction was carried out using hybrid instrumentation. In the first group, a standard posterior release (SPR) was performed, whereas in the second an extended release (EPR) was carried out, resecting all posterior ligaments and performing an extended bilateral facetectomy. The results of the measurements were compared using pre-op, post-op and 2-year-follow-up anteroposterior and lateral teleradiographs. Clinical results were evaluated using the SRS 22 questionnaire. Results: There were no differences as regards gender, age, curve type, instrumented levels, OR time or pre-op Cobb's angle (SPR: 60°±10°; EPR: 59°±8°) of the principal curve. In the extended release group the correction obtained was significantly greater at post-op (p&lt;0.001) and at 2 years (p&lt;0.05). Correction of the proximal and lumbar curve was similar in both groups, with no significant differences. Minor complications were similar in both groups, with no serious complications. Conclusion: Multiple-level posterior release improves correction of the principal curve on the coronal plane in patients with AIS, without an increase in the complications rate. The procedure also extends the arthrodesed area and facilitates introduction of the wires (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela-Gómez, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia-Mazón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela-Egocheaga, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sastre, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Suárez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Villán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar los resultados de la corrección por vía posterior con una construcción híbrida mediante el empleo de una liberación posterior clásica y la liberación posterior ampliada (LPA). Material y métodos: Efectuamos un estudio de cohortes retrospectivo con 46 pacientes diagnosticados de escoliosis idiopática del adolescente (EIA). Se realizó una corrección por vía posterior mediante el empleo de una instrumentación híbrida. En el primer grupo se realizó una liberación posterior estándar (LPE) y en el segundo se realizó una LPA, y se resecaron todos los ligamentos posteriores y se realizó una facetectomía amplia bilateral. Se compararon los resultados de las mediciones en telerradiografías anteroposteriores y laterales preoperatorias, postoperatorias y a los 2 años. Se valoraron los resultados clínicos mediante el cuestionario SRS 22. Resultados: No hubo diferencias en cuanto al sexo, edad, tipo de curva, niveles instrumentados, tiempo quirúrgico o Cobb preoperatorio (LPE: 60°±10°; LPA: 59°±8°) de la curva principal. En el grupo de LPA la corrección obtenida fue significativamente mayor en el postoperatorio (p&lt;0,001) y a los 2 años (p&lt;0,05). La corrección de la curva proximal y lumbar resultó similar en ambos grupos y no se encontraron diferencias significativas. Las complicaciones menores fueron similares en ambos grupos y no existieron complicaciones graves. Conclusión: La LPA a múltiples niveles mejora la corrección de la curva principal en el plano coronal en los pacientes con EIA, sin aumento de la incidencia de complicaciones, además de aumentar la superficie de artrodesis y facilitar la introducción del alambrado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(1): 27-33, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje lateral mínimamente invasivo en artroplastia total de cadera. Estudio prospectivo y aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
