<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132290</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoteliopathy by amantadine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report. A 42 year-old female with Parkinson disease treated with amantadine for three years who presented with bilateral corneal oedema. It was initially labelled as herpetic endothelitis without improvement with treatment. We lacked information on her treatment. After drug withdrawal the corneal oedema ?nally resolved. Nevertheless, the endothelial count remained low. Discussion. Amantadine affects corneal endothelium. It causes corneal oedema, usually reversible. Nevertheless, endothelial density remains low. An ophthalmologist examination should be performed before the initiation of treatment in order to establish a risk/bene?t ratio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesa Gutiérrez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico. Mujer de 42 años en tratamiento con amantadina durante 3 años por enfermedad de Parkinson, que presentó edema corneal bilateral. El caso se orientó como una endotelitis herpética que no mejoró tras el tratamiento. Se desconocía la medicación utilizada por la paciente. Tras la suspensión de la amantadina el edema corneal se resolvió aunque el recuento endotelial permaneció bajo. Discusión. La amantadina afecta al endotelio corneal. Origina un edema corneal normalmente reversible aunque la densidad endotelial permanece baja. Se hace conveniente la exploración oftalmológica antes de iniciar un tratamiento con amantadina para valorar el riesgo/ beneficio del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(4): 207-210, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endoteliopatía por amantadina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24587^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24587^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24587^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37775^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37775^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37775^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24587^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
