<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054205</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clavicle fracture in newborns: risk factors and associated morbidities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Clavicle fractures are caused by injury during the birth process. It is associated to childbirth with difficulty in the exit of shoulders and to multiple related biomedical factors. Objective: To evaluate risk factors and associated morbidities the clavicle facture in newborn of normal childbirth. Patients and method: Retropective study, type case control in the Hospital Herminda Martín, Chillán (Chile), January to June of 2004. The group study was constituted by 44 cases of newborn with clavicle fracture, the group control constituted itself in regard to 1:2, both corresponded to following vaginal childbirths to the case study (88 cases). Results: The incidence was of 4.1 percents, were statistically significant with the time of dilatation and expulsive in primiparas, weight and size of the newborns and presence of complications in the attention of the childbirth, shoulder dystocia (9.1 percents versus 2.3 percents), maternal uncontrol (6.8 percents versus 1.1 percents) and hand-dystocia (6.8 percents). Conclusions: Clavicle fracture in newborn is associated to factors of the normal labor and delivery</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urrutia, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oyarzún, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andaluz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriagada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fractura de clavícula es el traumatismo obstétrico óseo más frecuente en el recién nacido; se asocia a partos con distocia de hombros y a múltiples factores biomédicos relacionados. Objetivo: Analizar los factores de riesgo y morbilidad asociada con la fractura de clavícula en el recién nacido de parto normal. Pacientes y método: Estudio retrospectivo, tipo caso control, realizado en el Hospital Herminda Martín de Chillán (Chile), entre los meses de enero a junio de 2004. El grupo de estudio estuvo constituido por el total de recién nacidos con fractura de clavícula (44 casos), el grupo control se constituyó en razón de 1:2, que correspondió a los 2 partos vaginales siguientes al caso estudio (88 casos). Resultados: La incidencia fue del 4,1 por ciento; resultaron estadísticamente significativos con la presencia de fractura de clavícula el período de dilatación y expulsivo en primíparas, el peso y talla del recién nacido y la presencia de complicaciones durante el parto, como distocia de hombros (el 9,1 frente al 2,3 por ciento), el descontrol materno (el 6,8 frente al 1,1 por ciento) y laterocidencia de mano, que sólo se presentó en el grupo estudio (6,8 por ciento). Conclusiones: La fractura de clavícula en el recién nacido se asocia principalmente a factores del trabajo de parto y expulsivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(3): 121-126, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054205</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de clavícula en recién nacidos: factores de riesgo y morbilidad asociada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
