<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132292</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Corneal melts as the initial manifestation of sjögren syndrome secondary to rheumatoid arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rheumatoid arthritis(RA) is a common chronic inflammatory autoinmune disease, with unknown etiology. Approximately 11-31% of RA patients have secondary Sjögren´s syndrome. Ophthalmologic manifestations of these diseases can cause corneal scarring, ulceration, infection, and even perforation; thus, although the prognosis is good for most patients with Sjögren syndrome and ophthalmologic features, individuals with complications have much guarded prognosis. We report the case of a 65 years old woman with photophobia, pain, tearing and blurred vision in both eyes. Slit lamp exam showed an important corneal melting right eye, and corneal perforation left eye, which required amniotic membrane transplantation. The diagnosis was: Rheumatoid Arthritis and secondary Sjögren´s Syndrome. Azathioprine treatment was started in combination with oral steroids. Approximately 25% of patients have ocular involvement, and keratoconjunctivitis sicca is the most frequent ocular complication. Although the prognosis is good in most cases, an early diagnosis is necessary to avoid several complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabrillo Estévez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz González, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Galilea, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis reumatoide es una enfermedad sistémica inflamatoria crónica frecuente, de etiología desconocida. El síndrome de Sjögren puede ir asociado a dicha patología. El curso clínico de la artritis reumatoide a nivel ocular es muy variable y el diagnóstico temprano es determinante para prevenir graves complicaciones. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 64 años de edad que acudió al Servicio de Urgencias por presentar ojo rojo bilateral con fotofobia, lagrimeo continuo, dolor y disminución de la agudeza visual. En la exploración se objetivó importante adelgazamiento del estroma corneal en OD y perforación corneal OI, que requirió recubrimiento tectónico con membrana amniótica. Los análisis serológicos mostraron los siguientes resultados: Factor Reumatoide+, ANA+, ENA Anti-Ro/SSA+, ENA Anti-La/SSB+. La paciente fue diagnosticada de Artritis Reumatoide y Síndrome de Sjögren secundario. Desde entonces, sigue un tratamiento sistémico con corticoides y azatioprina. Aproximadamente, el 25% de los pacientes  desarrollan enfermedad oftalmológica, esencialmente queratoconjuntivitis seca (25%), epiescleritis, escleritis y queratitis. Estas manifestaciones son en general poco severas, pero hay un pequeño porcentaje de pacientes, como el caso que aquí presentamos, que sufren una inflamación ocular grave y que sin tratamiento inmunosupresor precozmente instaurado, pueden desarrollar úlceras corneales estériles, centrales o periféricas, que les puede llevar incluso a la perforación y destrucción del globo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(4): 214-216, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perforación corneal como primera manifestación de síndorme de Sjören secundario a artritis reumatoide</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53524^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24314^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53524^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24314^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24314^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53524^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24314^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
