<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136218</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alterations of the inner ear in diving and flying</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During diving, the inner ear can be affected by brusque pressure changes transmitted through the middle ear (barotrauma) or by the formation of nitrogen bubbles inside the inner ear (decompression sickness). Few cases have been described in aeronautics and are usually related to previous disease. Although infrequent, inner ear alterations can have serious sequelae. Rapid identification of the problem and early treatment are required to prevent hypacusis and/or residual tinnitus. Methods. We performed a literature review of the incidence, physiopathology, symptoms, treatment, prognosis and prevention of alternobaric vertigo, inner ear barotrauma, inner ear decompression sickness, and chronic dysbaric disorders of the inner ear. Results. The low incidence of these disorders, and their development in association with other, more important alterations, favors their underevaluation, and diagnosis is often delayed. Early treatment, including surgery, produces satisfactory results. Differential diagnosis between barotrauma and decompression sickness is essential. The sequelae may contraindicate resumption of diving or flying. Conclusions. Physicians treating these patients should be familiar both with subaquatic and hyperbaric medicine, as well as with otorhinolaryngology. Most cases are resolved by early medical and surgical treatment. The main sequelae are hypacusis and tinnitus. There is usually good central compensation of residual vestibular deficit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan-Fernández, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El oído interno, durante el buceo, puede verse afectado por cambios bruscos de presión que son transmitidos a través del oído medio (barotrauma) o bien por la formación de burbujas de nitrógeno en su interior (enfermedad descompresiva). En aeronáutica, los casos descritos son muy pocos y suelen estar relacionados con enfermedades previas. La afectación del oído interno, si bien es poco frecuente, puede provocar importantes secuelas. Se precisa una rápida identificación del problema y un tratamiento precoz para intentar evitar la hipoacusia y/o los acúfenos residuales. Métodos: Realizamos una revisión bibliográfica de la incidencia  de esta enfermedad, su fisiopatología, clínica, tratamiento, pronóstico y prevención. Resultados: Su baja incidencia y la posible aparición asociada con otras alteraciones más importantes favorecen su infravaloración con un diagnóstico que, la mayoría de veces, es tardío. El tratamiento precoz, incluida la cirugía,  tiene resultados satisfactorios. Es fundamental el diagnóstico diferencial entre barotrauma y enfermedad descompresiva. Las secuelas pueden contraindicar el reinicio de estas actividades. Conclusiones: El médico que trate a estos pacientes debe estar familiarizado tanto con la medicina subacuática e hiperbárica como con la otorrinolaringología. El tratamiento médico y quirúrgico precoz resuelve la mayoría de casos. La hipoacusia y los acúfenos son las principales secuelas. Habitualmente hay una buena compensación central del déficit vestibular residual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.2): 40-46, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades del oído interno en el buceo y la aviación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7935^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7935^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3678^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d341</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3678^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3678^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4307^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1491^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1491^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
