<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34742</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pharmacology of vestibular disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In recent years, significant advances have been made in the physiology and the pharmacology of vestibular disorders. It is now possible to elaborate an approximation of the mechanisms of action of the drugs used in the symptomatic treatment of vertigo. Development. These drugs usually have a number of different pharmacological actions and overlapping effects. They can modify the intensity of the symptoms (e.g. vestibular suppressants) or prevent recurrences (e.g. calcium blockers in the case of vestibular migraine). Most of the drugs used for the acute treatment of vertigo can have a negative effect on the central compensation mechanisms. Vestibular rehabilitation exercises and certain drugs can speed up compensation. Choice of medication and the method of administration depend on the severity of the clinical symptoms, the pattern of temporal evolution, the underlying vestibular disease, the associated clinical conditions and the profile of the collateral effects of the drugs utilised. Conclusions. Vestibular suppressants and antiemetic drugs are still the basis of the acute treatment of vertigo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Recientemente, se han realizado avances en la fisiología y la farmacología de las alteraciones vestibulares. Es posible ahora realizar una aproximación a los mecanismos de acción de los fármacos utilizados para el tratamiento sintomático del vértigo. Desarrollo. Estos medicamentos suelen tener múltiples acciones farmacológicas y superposición de efectos. Pueden modificar la intensidad de los síntomas (p. ej., los supresores vestibulares) o prevenir las recurrencias (p .ej., los bloqueadores del calcio en el caso de la migraña vestibular). La mayoría de los fármacos utilizados para el tratamiento agudo del vértigo pueden interferir negativamente con los mecanismos de la compensación central. Los ejercicios de rehabilitación vestibular y ciertos fármacos pueden acelerar la compensación. La elección del fármaco y la vía de administración depende de: la gravedad del cuadro clínico, el patrón de evolución temporal, la enfermedad vestibular subyacente, las patologías asociadas y el perfil de efectos colaterales de los fármacos empleados. Conclusión. Los supresores vestibulares y los antieméticos siguen siendo los pilares del tratamiento agudo del vértigo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(4): 381-387, ago. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacología de las alteraciones vestibulares</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Hain, TC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yacovino, DA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34742</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
