<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77048</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Big Five and Machiavellianism in Mexican Workers: a study of personality and manipulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to reveal the relationship between personality, Machiavellianism and other variables in a sample of 254 Mexican workers of private companies. The 5FM and the EMMMAQ were used as tools for measuring respectively personality and manipulation &#150;Machiavellianism. An analysis of variance and correlations were performed.The results showed significant personality differences between subjects with high and low scores in Machiavellianism. Important differences also appeared in demographic variables such as age, wage, seniority, education, and job and work preference. Finally, the paper emphasizes the importance of Machiavellianism for the study of personality and the organizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Olguín, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Saisó, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras Morales, Fabiola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe Prado, Jesús Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este estudio fue investigar la relación existente entre personalidad, maquiavelismo y otras variables en una muestra de 254 trabajadores mexicanos del sector privado. Se utilizaron los instrumentos 5FM y EMMMAQ, para medir personalidad y maquiavelismo respectivamente, se llevó a cabo análisis de varianza y correlaciones para el tratamiento estadístico. Se encontraron diferencias de personalidad entre los sujetos con alto y bajo maquiavelismo; además, variables demográficas como edad, sueldo, años de experiencia laboral, escolaridad, puesto y preferencia para trabajar mostraron relaciones relevantes. Las implicaciones del maquiavelismo en el estudio de la personalidad y las organizaciones son importantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);24(1): 61-79, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los Cinco Grandes y maquiavelismo en trabajadores mexicanos: un estudio de personalidad y manipulación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8429</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
