<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057207</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of basal cell carcinomas with positive margins</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A common problem in day-to-day practice is the approach to take following resection of basal cell carcinoma with positive margins. In such cases, it is important to decide whether we should take a wait-and-see approach or consider re-excision or radiotherapy. To make this decision, 4 key points need to be clarified: the significance of positive margins; whether positive margins are equivalent to tumor persistence; whether negative margins equate with complete excision; and the rate of recurrence in cases of re-excision compared in those in which a wait and see approach is taken. Having addressed each of these points, the approach will depend on the characteristics of the individual case. Based on the evidence presented, an aggressive approach involving re-excision would seem indicated in aggressive cases, whereas a flexible strategy combining observation, surgery, and radiotherapy (or other treatments) can be used in less aggressive cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ríos-Buceta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un problema habitual en la práctica diaria es la actitud que debemos adoptar tras la resección quirúrgica de un epitelioma basocelular con afectación de alguno de los bordes. Que tipo de actitud debemos adoptar en estos casos: ¿observar?, ¿reextirpar?, ¿radiar? Para responder, en el artículo se desgranan una serie de conceptos: cuál es el significado de bordes afectos; ¿es equivalente borde afecto a persistencia tumoral?; ¿es equivalente borde libre a extirpación tumoral completa?; cuál es el porcentaje de recidivas al comparar la reextirpación y la observación.         Después de aclarar cada una de las preguntas, la respuesta sobre qué actitud tomar depende de las características de cada caso. Con las evidencias que se presentan parece indicada una actitud agresiva de reintervención en los casos graves y una estrategia flexible que combine la observación, la cirugía y la radioterapia (u otros tratamientos) en los casos menos agresivos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;98(10): 679-687, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057207</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitud ante los epiteliomas basocelulares con bordes afectos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31275^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31275^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
