<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84269</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of scoliosis, hand dominance and handling loads in a male population of 6 to 12 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This research study evaluated the relationship between scoliosis and a set of variables related to age, motor skills (left-handed or right-handed) and the method of transporting school supplies (backpack or trolley) among a school-aged male population. The final selection of the sample - comprising 682 participants between 6 and 12 years old and residents in Granada (Spain) - was conducted by sampling in response to a natural composition of the groups. Several measurement instruments (such as Edinburgh Handedness Inventory, Adam's test and a questionnaire) were applied in order to collect the selected variables. The results indicated that 9.4% (n = 64) of the boys suffered from scoliosis, 10% (n= 73) were left-handed and 58.2% used a backpack for the transportation of school supplies. No statistically significant difference was found between the deviation of the spine and lateral dominance nor between the transportation of school supplies and deviation of the spine; however the results showed a connection between age and incidence of scoliosis (p= 0.03) as well as between age and the method of transporting school supplies (p= 0.00), mainly due to sociocultural habits. In conclusion, there is no connection between suffering scoliosis and left-handedness, nor between the method of transporting school supplies and the incidence of scoliosis. However, these results could vary at older ages and, therefore, programs aimed at teaching good ergonomic guidelines and preventing the pathology of the spine in schoolchildren and adults are highly encouraged in order to improve their quality of life(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sánchez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Cruzado y Barba, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajos Manzanares, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurita Ortega, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudió evaluó la relación entre la escoliosis y un conjunto de variables de tipo cronológico, motriz (zurdo o diestro) y de transporte de material escolar (mochila o trolley) en una población masculina en el ámbito educativo. La selección definitiva de la muestra, compuesta por 682 participantes, con edad comprendida entre 6&#150;12 años y pertenecientes a Granada (España) y alrededores se realizó por muestreo, atendiendo a una composición natural de los grupos. Se seleccionaron varios instrumentos de medición (Inventario de Lateralidad Manual de Edinburgh, test de Adams y cuestionario) para recoger las variables seleccionadas. Los resultados indicaron que el 9,4% (n=64) eran escolióticos, el 10 % (n=73) eran zurdos y el 58,2% empleaba la mochila como medio de transporte de material escolar. No se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre la desviación del raquis y las variables de tipo dominancia lateral y transporte de material escolar, no sucediendo lo mismo con la variable cronológica (p=0,03); del mismo modo, se encontró asociación entre la edad y el transporte de material (p=0,00), motivada por movimientos socioculturales (actitudes, costumbres, hábitos, etc.). Como principales conclusiones, cabe resaltar la nula relación entre la escoliosis y la dominancia lateral izquierda, así como el material con el que se transportan los utensilios escolares; sin embargo, no descartamos que en edades más avanzadas pueda invertirse esta situación, por lo que surge la necesidad de desarrollar programas de prevención de la patología del raquis en escolares y adultos, y aplicarles las pautas de ergonomía correctas enfocadas a incrementar la calidad de vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);45(168): 243-249, oct.-dic. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de escoliosis, dominancia manual lateral y transporte de material en una población masculina de 6&#150;12 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4351</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6956^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
