<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119179</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive diagnosis of fetal anemia: Multicentric nationwide input for a worldwide output</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To perform a nationwide multicentric validatation of the nomogram of fetal middle cerebral artery peak systolic velocity (MCA-PSV); previously constructed by us and to compare and contrast it with similar studies in the world for an effective output. Materials and methods: Fetal MCA-PSV was measured in normal 1015 pregnant women attending the antenatal ultrasound clinic at least once between 12 and 40 weeks of gestation (35 patients per week of gestation), at this institute and a nomogram was constructed. MCA-PSV in 30 patients each at 12, 24 and 36 weeks of gestation (GA) were measured at multiple centers [other institutes by different observers] in this nation. Their mean values were compared with the mean values mentioned in the nomogram prepared by us. Similarly the linear correlation diagrams as well as the regression equations of this large local study were compared with those from other worldwide published studies. Statistical analysis was done using the SPSS 12 software. Results: A nationwide comparison of the mean and standard deviation (SD) values of MCA-PSV at 12, 24 and 36 weeks of gestation calculated at 95% confidence interval, in our study with studies from different other centers, using ANOVA the calculated F value was far too high than the table value. So, null hypothesis that the nomogram previously prepared by us at this center can be comfortably followed at other centers in this nation is rejected. Comparative analysis of linear correlation between GA (weeks) and MCA-PSV (cm/s) in our study and other studies also displayed a disparity. Conclusions: A significant difference was found between local study and multicentric nation wide studies, as well as between local values and worldwide values. A multicentric nationwide input for a worldwide output thus enabled us not only to construct and compare normal local reference range of fetal MCA-PSV but also to validate it effectively and to realize its limitations. Hence it is time to say goodbye to the &#147;One Size Fits All Theory&#148; of fetal MCA-PSV and to welcome efforts to scientifically construct regional reference range all over the world (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ghanshyam Kachewar, Sushil</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: Realizar una validación nacional multicéntrica del nomograma de la velocidad sistólica máxima de la arteria cerebral media (MCA-PSV) que había sido previamente construida por los autores a fin de comparar y contrastar con estudios similares en el mundo para obtener unas conclusiones o resultados eficaces. Materiales y métodos: Entre las 12 y 40 semanas de gestación, se midió una vez, como mínimo, la MCA-PSV fetal en 1.015 mujeres embarazadas normales (35 pacientes por semana de gestación) que fueron atendidas en la clínica de ecografía prenatal de este instituto y elaboró un nomograma. Se seleccionaron 30 pacientes por cada edad de gestación (12, 24 y 36 semanas de gestación) en varios centros [otros institutos y con diferentes observadores] en esta nación. Los valores medios se compararon con los valores medios obtenidos en el nomograma elaborado por los autores. Asimismo, se compararon los diagramas de correlación lineales y las ecuaciones de regresión de este amplio estudio local con los de otros estudios publicados en el resto del mundo. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante el software SPSS 12. Resultados: La comparación a nivel nacional de la media y la desviación estándar (DE) de la MCA-PSV a los 12, 24 y 36 semanas de gestación, calculadas con un intervalo de confianza del 95%, entre nuestro estudio y otros estudios de diferentes centros de India, dio lugar a un valor F calculado mediante ANOVA mucho más alto que el valor de la tabla. Por lo tanto, se rechaza la hipótesis nula de que el nomograma previamente preparado por nosotros en este centro se pueda seguir cómodamente en otros centros de este país. El análisis comparativo de la correlación lineal entre la EG (en semanas) y la MCA-PSV (cm/seg.) en nuestro estudio y otros estudios también muestran disparidades. Conclusiones: Se encontró una diferencia significativa entre el estudio local y los otros estudios multicéntricos nacionales, así como entre los valores locales y los valores mundiales. Se trata de resultados de datos multicéntricos a nivel nacional para establecer valores mundiales, lo que nos permitió no sólo construir y comparar los valores de referencia locales de la MCA-PSV fetal normal, sino también validar de manera efectiva y conocer sus limitaciones. Por lo tanto, es el momento de decir adiós a la teoría de &#147;una misma talla para todos&#148; en cuanto a MCA-PSV fetal y dar la bienvenida a los esfuerzos por construir científicamente un rango de referencia regional en todo el mundo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);24(4): 141-147, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico no invasivo de la anemia fetal: Datos Multicéntricos Nacionales para unos resultados/conclusiones mundiales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34044^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
