<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166698</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary care in Belgium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Belgium is an attractive country to work in, not just for doctors but for all Spanish workers, due to it having the headquarters of European Union. The health job allure is double; on the one hand, the opportunity to find a decent job, and on the other, because it is possible to develop their professional abilities with patients of the same nationality in a health system with a different way of working. The Belgium health care system is based on security social models. Health care is financed by the government, social security contributions, and voluntary private health insurance. Primary care in Belgium is very different to that in Spain. Citizens may freely choose their doctor (general practitioner or specialist) increasing the lack of coordination between primary and specialized care. This leads to serious patient safety problems and loss of efficiency within the system. Belgium is a European country with room to improve preventive coverage. General practitioners are self-employed professionals with free choice of setting, and their salary is linked to their professional activity. Ambulatory care is subjected to co-payment, and this fact leads to great inequities on access to care. The statistics say that there is universal coverage but, in 2010, 14% of the population did not seek medical contact due to economic problems. It takes 3 years to become a General Practitioner and continuing medical education is compulsory to be revalidated. In general, Belgian and Spaniards living and working in Belgium are happy with the functioning of the health care system. However, as doctors, we should be aware that it is a health care system in which access is constrained for some people, and preventive coverage could be improved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sagrado, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Bélgica es un país atractivo laboralmente por ser sede de las instituciones europeas no solo para los médicos, sino para todos los españoles. El atractivo laboral sanitario es doble; por un lado, la oportunidad de encontrar un trabajo digno, y por otro, la de poder desarrollar las habilidades profesionales con pacientes de la misma nacionalidad en un sistema sanitario con un funcionamiento muy distinto. El sistema de salud belga pertenece al modelo de seguros sociales. Los servicios sanitarios están financiados por el estado, cuotas de seguridad social y seguros voluntarios privados. La atención primaria en Bélgica es muy diferente a la española. Los ciudadanos pueden elegir libremente el médico (generalista o especialista), lo que favorece la descoordinación entre atención primaria y especializada, genera graves problemas de seguridad para los pacientes y de pérdida de eficiencia para el sistema. Bélgica es uno de los países europeos con coberturas mejorables en actividades preventivas. Los médicos generalistas son profesionales liberales con autonomía de instalación y su salario está ligado a la actividad profesional. Las consultas médicas tienen copago y este hecho genera desigualdades importantes en el acceso a la atención. Las estadísticas hablan de una cobertura sanitaria universal, pero en el año 2010, el 14% de la población no acudió al médico por problemas económicos. El tiempo de formación para convertirse en especialista es de 3 años, y la formación médica continuada es uno de los requisitos fundamentales para obtener la revalidación del título. En general, los belgas y los españoles que viven y trabajan en Bélgica están contentos con el funcionamiento de su sistema sanitario. No obstante, los médicos debemos ser conscientes de que es un sistema donde el acceso todavía está limitado a una parte de la población y la cobertura de las actividades preventivas es mejorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(6): 445-449, sept. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La atención primaria en Bélgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
