<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82597</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polymalformative syndromes with expression in the central nervous system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the clinical aspects of polymalformatives syndromes with expression in the central nervous system detected in the neonatal period, and to investigate the associated maternal risk factors. Material and methods: Retrospective study, during the period of January 1976 to December 2005, carried out in the Pediatrics Department of the University Hospital of Guadalajara, Spain. All the newborns in our hospital with polymalformatives syndromes with expression in the central nervous system were included in the study. Results: During the study period 7 children were recorded with congenital defects of the central nervous system and a polymalformative syndrome. The most frequent anomalies were congenital hydrocephalus and neural tube defects. The risk factors found in the study were maternal infections during pregnancy, ionizing radiation, medications and consanguinity. Conclusions: The polymalformatives syndromes with expression in the central nervous system seem to have a multifactorial etiology, comprising both environmental and genetic components (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blázquez Arrabal, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdú Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Bustos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriola Pereda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Oguiza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigado Matamala, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar las características de los síndromes polimalformativos con expresión en el sistema nervioso central (SNC) detectados en el periodo neonatal, e investigar los factores de riesgo maternos asociados. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo, durante el periodo comprendido entre enero de 1976 y diciembre de 2005, realizado en el Servicio de Pediatría del Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara. Se incluyeron en el estudio todos los recién nacidos en nuestro hospital con síndromes polimalformativos con expresión en el SNC. Resultados: Durante el periodo de estudio, se recogieron siete casos de niños con malformaciones congénitas del SNC y síndrome polimalformativo. Las anomalías más frecuentes fueron la hidrocefalia congénita y los defectos del tubo neural. Los factores de riesgo encontrados fueron las infecciones durante la gestación, la radiación ionizante, la toma de algunos fármacos y la consanguinidad. Conclusiones: Los síndromes polimalformativos con expresión en el SNC tienen una etiología multifactorial, que comprende tanto factores ambientales como genéticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(6): 301-304, jun. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndromes polimalformativos con expresión en el sistema nervioso central</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9614^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
