<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129117</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement of food practices in a population with cardiovascular risk factors after a nutrition education program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To assess changes in clinical status and  nutrition pattern of a population of patients with cardiovascular risk (ATP III criteria) after a nutrition education program. Methods: Intervention study, pre-post test design, with no control group. Sample of 32 patients (87,5% women) with  cardiovascular risk; the average age was 57,43 years. Six week intervention with assessment undertaken through demographic and clinical data, food frequency   questionnaire, control of attendance and participation and evaluation test at baseline and after two and five months of intervention. Results: - A significant increase in the consumption of poultry  (p=0.043) and fat (p=0.013) and white fish (p=0.033) was observed. Patients who consumed more fruit tend to be  thinner in the first assessment (-0.461 p=0.008) and at the end of the study the consumption of fish was lower in  individuals with abdominal obesity (-0.417 p=0.034). In the post-test a decrease in the  ATP III cholesterol HDL criterion, from 37.6% to 12.5%,  (p=0.031) was observed. There was also a decrease in the proportion of people with metabolic syndrome from 68.8% to 31.3% (p=0.022). Conclusions: The Nutrition education program had a positive impact in food practices. After the intervention a decrease in cardiovascular risk factors was observed, as well as  people with diagnosis of metabolic syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lucha López, Ana Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tricás Moreno, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal Peracho, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucha López, María Orosia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estébanez de Miguel, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo García, César</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Conseguir la mejora en el estado clínico y  patrón alimentario de una población con riesgo cardiovascular (según ATP III) después de un Programa de educación nutricional (PEN). Métodos: Estudio de intervención antes-después de un solo grupo. Muestra de 32 pacientes (87,5% mujeres) y 57,43 años de edad media. La intervención (PEN) duró 6  semanas. La valoración recogió datos demográficos y clínicos, cuestionario de frecuencia de consumo de  alimentos, nivel de adherencia al programa y nivel de asimilación de conocimientos, al inicio, los dos y los cinco meses. Resultados: - Tras la intervención se produce un aumento en la carne de ave (p=0,043 ), de pescado blanco (p=0,033) y azul (p=0,013). - Los pacientes que consumen más fruta tienden a estar  más delgados al inicio (-0,461 p=0,008) y una mayor ingesta de pescado se correlaciona con menor obesidad abdominal al final (-0,417 p=0,034). - Se observa una disminución del criterio ATP III colesterol HDL del 37,6% al 12,5% (p=0,031). - Se registra una disminución en la proporción de personas con síndrome metabólico del 68,8% al 31,3% (p=0,022). Conclusiones: El PEN generó una mejora de la  alimentación, una disminución de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y el número de personas con síndrome  metabólico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(3): 156-162, jul.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la alimentación en una población con riesgo cardiovascular tras un programa de educación nutricional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5351^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5351^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
