<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146080</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enhancing quality in training programs: an application in the sport area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the field of education, specific or standard models of quality management are usually performed. Both alternatives have their advantages and disadvantages, but most educational organizations prefer to implement standard models which usually include some mismatches during their implementation. To address this situation, we propose an instrument that, when applied during the evaluation processes of these organizations, facilitates the specification and improvement of participation, usefulness and transparency. This creates a context that enhances the successful application of standard models. The instrument implementation is described in the needs assessment process of the Training Program Department in an Andalusian sports organization. Results are analyzed using key indicators before and after applying the instrument. Finally, potential advantages are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanduvete-Chaves, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chacón-Moscoso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el ámbito educativo, la gestión de la calidad suele llevarse a cabo mediante la aplicación de modelos específicos para este ámbito o bien mediante modelos estándares. Ambas alternativas tienen sus ventajas e inconvenientes; sin embargo, la mayoría de las organizaciones educativas prefieren implantar modelos estándares que suelen conllevar ciertos desajustes durante su implementación. Para hacer frente a esta situación, en este trabajo se propone un instrumento que, aplicado durante los procesos evaluativos de estas organizaciones, facilita la especificación y mejora de la participación, la utilidad y la transparencia, creando un contexto que favorezca la aplicación exitosa de los modelos estándares de gestión. Se describe su aplicación en la evaluación de necesidades llevada a cabo en el Departamento de Formación Continua de una organización andaluza dedicada al ámbito deportivo; se analizan los resultados mediante indicadores clave antes y después de aplicar el instrumento; y se valoran las ventajas obtenidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(60): 613-629, dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potenciar la calidad en formación continua: una aplicación en el ámbito deportivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
