<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106122</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of adherence to fluid restriction in kidney patients in haemodialysis: objective indicator and perceived compliance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Studies of adherence to fluid restriction show high variability in prevalence data, as different methods of measuring IWG (interdialysis weight gain) and cut-off criteria are used. Objectives: To describe the prevalence of adherence to fluid restriction using daily IWG (criterion: &amp;#8804;1Kg) and daily IWG adjusted for dry weight (DW) (cut-off point adjusted criterion: DW&lt;70kg, IWG=1kg/day; DW&gt;70kg and &amp;#8804;80kg, IWG=1.1kg/day; DW&gt;80kg and &amp;#8804;90kg, IWG=1.2kg/day; DW&gt;90kg, IWG=1.3kg/day) and to study the association between this objective indicator and adherence behaviour as reported by patient. Patients and method: Our study included a total of 146 patients with a mean age of 66 years (SD: 13.6 years; range: 25-88 years), 66% of which were male. Ours was a longitudinal study with one month of follow-up. We collected both sociodemographic and clinical variables and mean daily IWG. Patient-reported adherence behaviour was assessed through an interview by a trained staff member from outside the department who asked the following question: "In order to avoid complications between haemodialysis sessions: during the last month, how many days did you ingest less than 1 litre of fluid per day?" (0= no days; 10= every day). A score &amp;#8804;5 led to categorisation of patients as compliant with treatment. Statistical analysis included descriptive analysis, correlation test, chi-square and Crosstabs, ROC curve and logistic regression procedures. Results: Prevalence of "objective" adherence to fluid restriction was 61% (mean daily IWG&amp;#8804;1kg) and 73% (mean daily IWG adjusted for dry weight). Reported adherence (prevalence: 56.2%) was associated with IWG adjusted for  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Roig, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iborra-Moltó, Carmelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor-Mira, M. de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los estudios sobre adhesión a la restricción de líquidos muestran alta variabilidad en los datos de prevalencia debido a los distintos métodos de medida de la ganancia interdiálisis (GID) y los criterios de punto de corte utilizados. Objetivos: Describir la prevalencia de adhesión a la restricción hídrica según la GID diaria (criterio: &amp;#8804; 1 kg) y la GID diaria ajustada al peso seco (PS) (criterio: PS &lt; 70 kg, GID = 1 kg/día; PS &gt; 70 y &amp;#8804; 80 kg, GID = 1,1 kg/día; PS &gt; 80 y &amp;#8804; 90 kg, GID = 1,2 kg/día; PS &gt; 90 kg, GID = 1,3 kg/día); y estudiar la asociación entre este indicador objetivo y la conducta de adhesión referida por el paciente. Pacientes y métodos: 146 pacientes. Edad media: 66,1 años (desviación típica [DT]: 13,6; rango: 25-88); un 66,4% varones. Estudio longitudinal con un mes de seguimiento. Variables: sociodemográficas. Clínicas. GID diaria. Conducta de adhesión referida, evaluada mediante entrevista por personal entrenado ajeno al servicio, con la pregunta "Para evitar complicaciones entre las hemodiálisis: ¿Durante el último mes, ha tomado usted menos de un litro de líquidos al día? (0 = Ningún día; 10 = Todos los días)". Los pacientes fueron clasificados como cumplidores a partir de valores &amp;#8805; 5. Análisis estadístico: descriptivo, pruebas de correlación, &amp;#967;2 y procedimientos Crosstabs, curva ROC (receiver operating characteristics) y análisis de regresión logística. Resultados: La prevalencia de adhesión "objetiva" a la restricción de líquidos fue 61% (GID diaria media &amp;#8804; 1 kg) y 73% (GID diaria media ajustada al peso seco). La prevalencia de adhesión referida (56,2%) se asoció a la GID diaria media ajustada al peso seco (&amp;#967;2 = 31,34; p = 0,000). En los pacientes con adhesión objetiva ajustada al peso, la prevalencia (PR) de los que se declaran    (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;32(4): 477-485, jul.-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la adhesión a la restricción de líquidos en pacientes renales en hemodiálisis: indicador objetivo y adhesión percibida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
