<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79096</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fournier&#146;s gangrene. A battle won. Traditional cures versus a polyhexanide solution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article won the top place in the Third Prontosan® Scientific Prize in 2008. Fournier&#146;s Gangrene is a rare process having an unknown origin which affects soft tissue in the genital and perirectal area. The authors describe the case of a 61 year old patient suffering from this disease, the recommended treatment by the Nurses&#146; Consulting Office for Bed Sores, or Decubitus Ulcers, and Chronic Skin Ulcerations, and the patient&#146;s evolution. The medical team carried out a complete evaluation of this patient and his/her injury and took a sample to make a surface culture from. After this initial evaluation, the medical team&#146;s first recommendation was to apply treatment consisting of using polyhexanide combined with a calcic alginate dressing to control oozing; the objective of this treatment is to clean and decontaminate the wound and to provide the optimum conditions for a correct cicatrisation process in the least time possible. After 58 days undergoing treatment, the affected area did not show any sign nor symptom of infection and was practically finished with the cicatrisation process. The use of polyhexanide, in this case, proved to be the ideal therapeutic option to clean, decontaminate and maintain the conditions optimum for a correct cicatrisation of this wound(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorente Fernández, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cancio, M. Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdú Moresco, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Primer galardonado en el III Premio Científico Prontosan® 2008. La gangrena de Fournier es un proceso poco común de causa desconocida que afecta a los tejidos blandos de la región genital y perirrectal. Presentamos el caso de un paciente de 61 años afectado por dicha dolencia, el tratamiento recomendado por la Consulta de UPP y Heridas, y su evolución. Se realizó una valoración integral del paciente y de la herida y se tomó una muestra para un cultivo de superficie. Tras la valoración inicial se realizó una primera recomendación de tratamiento consistente en el uso de polihexanida combinado con un apósito de alginato cálcico para el control del exudado, con el objetivo de limpiar y descontaminar la herida y proporcionar las condiciones óptimas para un correcto proceso de cicatrización en el menor tiempo posible. Tras 58 días de evolución, la zona no presentaba ningún signo ni síntoma de infección y estaba prácticamente cicatrizada. El uso de polihexanida, en este caso, fue la opción terapéutica ideal para el lavado, descontaminación y mantenimiento de las condiciones óptimas para una correcta cicatrización de la herida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(11): 759-763, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gangrena de Fournier. Una batalla ganada. Curas tradicionales versus Solución de Polihexanida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d467^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
