<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168616</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social transformation in the europe in crisis. The gestation of social inequality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent decades, European countries have experienced, to varying degrees, adjustment processes of their social policies which, at the same time, should respond to the demands of disadvantaged groups in an increasingly adverse social context. Inevitably, social and health sciences have shown its concern about the way the shaping of these policies affects people who depend on external support and who are unable to manage their lives autonomously. We consider interesting to reflect on the effects and consequences of social transformations underway, supported by the results of a research, through a qualitative methodology based on in-depth interviews with key informants of social policy in four European countries (Germany, Spain, Finland and Sweden). The mail goal was to study the speeches of interviewees directly involved in these problems, social partners and experts who have a particular view of social problems. The results indicate new challenges for existing social welfare systems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sotomayor, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Domingo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merklen, Denis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las últimas décadas, los países europeos han experimentado, en diferentes grados, procesos de ajuste de sus políticas sociales que al mismo tiempo deben responder a las demandas de los colectivos desfavorecidos en un contexto social cada vez más adverso. De manera inevitable, las ciencias sociales y sanitarias, han evidenciado su inquietud por la forma en que la conformación de estas políticas afecta a individuos dependientes de ayudas externas e incapaces de gestionar sus vidas de forma autónoma. Creemos interesante reflexionar acerca de los efectos y consecuencias de las transformaciones sociales en curso, apoyados en los resultados de una investigación, a través de una metodología cualitativa basada en entrevistas en profundidad con informantes claves de la política social de cuatro países europeos (Alemania, España, Finlandia y Suecia). El objetivo ha sido estudiar los discursos de los entrevistados directamente implicados en estos problemas, agentes sociales y expertos que tienen una visión determinada de los problemas sociales. Los resultados apuntan a describir nuevos retos para los actuales sistemas de bienestar social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;26(3): 185-189, jul.-sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transformaciones sociales en la europa de la crisis. La gestación de la desigualdad social</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
