<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135177</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application procedure for accreditation of an ongoing medical training activity in  allergology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The continuing medical education (CME) is a fundamental tool for the health professional, a widely as umed concern for him and a commitment and duty for  the Administration. In Spain, and during last decades, CME has been a contant concern of various groups. but the first initiatives about accreditation did not emerge until the end of 80s An primordial advance was the development of the Health national System 's Commission on Continuing Education  of Healthcare Professions, dependent on the lnterterritorial Council, whose accreditation system started in 1998 through the use of the Sectorial Conference, planned in artieles 5 and 8 of Law of Legal Régime of public adrninitrations and the Common Adrninistrative Procedure, as the highest technical organ in that matter. From then, diverse autonomic commissions, no ali working nowadays, and the Spanish System in Accreditation of Continuing Medical Education (SEAFORMEC) have  been created. Although we have previously reported a guide, in this manuscript we describe and update the necessaries steps to request an accreditation for a Continuing Medica] Education activiry in allergology, explaining the different items  of the "official model of application", clarifying at whom  the application should be addressed, and outlining the essentials which are evaluated to get the accreditation, ali  with the aim to guarantee that the formative activity achieves the highest index of quality in order to get the objective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrandiz gomis, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallarés Neila, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negro Álvarez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Molina, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La formación médica continuada (FMC) constituye una herramienta fundamental para el profesional de Ja medicina. Constituye una preocupación ampliamente asumida por los profesionales sanitarios, al tiempo que un compromiso y una obligación de Ja administración. En España, durante los últimos decenios, la FMC ha sido preocupación constante de múltiples colectivos, sin embargo no ha sido hasta finales de los 80 cuando han surgido las primeras iniciativas de acreditación. Un paso trascendental lo constituyó la creación de la Comisión de Formación Continuada de las Profesiones Sanitarias del Sistema Nacional de Salud, dependiente del Consejo lntertenitorial, cuyo sistema de acreditación inició su singladura en 1998, mediante la utilización de la figura de Conferencia Sectorial, prevista en los artículos 5 y 8 de la Ley de Régimen Jurídico de las Administraciones Públicas y del Procedimiento Administrativo Común, como órgano técnico superior  en la materia. Desde entonces se han ido creando las diversas Comisiones Autonómicas existentes, no todas ellas actualmente en funcionamiento, y el Sistema Español de Acreditación de la Formación Médica Continuada (SEAFORMEC).  Aunque antes habíamos publicado una guía, en el pre ente manuscrito se actualizan y describen los pasos que deben darse para solicitar la acreditación de una  actividad de Formación Médica Continuada en Alergología a la vez que se explican los diferentes puntos del "modelo oficial de solicitud", se aclara a quién debe dirigirse la solicitud y se perfilan los fundamentos sobre los cuales se valoran la actividades a efectos de acreditación, con el fin de garantizar que la actividad formativa cumpla los más altos índices de calidad para conseguir los objetivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);19(3): 89-100, jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135177</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proceso para la solicitud de acreditación de una actividad de Formación Médica Continuada en Alergología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
