<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119431</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-concept and adaptation to illness in pediatric diabetic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Our objective is focused on studying self-concept and adaptation to the process of disease in diabetic pediatric patients. The assessment tools used were an ad-hoc self-report for the socio-demographic and illness variables, the questionnaire of self-concept Garley (CAG), and the questionnaire of adaptive response to the disease in diabetic patients. The sample consisted of 23 subjects evaluated at a single time of measurement, all of them children and adolescents aged between 8 and 16 years of age. The results show that about 50% of the children and adolescents with type I diabetes had a low self-concept in most of the studied dimensions, being especially significant that about 30% of the studied children have a very low self-concept. Moreover, most of the subjects presented a little adaptive behavior before their illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montoya Castilla, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado Gascó, Vicente Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao Cercós, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beniel Navarro, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Marín, Marián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcón Sáez, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es estudiar el autoconcepto y la adaptación a la enfermedad en pacientes pediátricos diabéticos. Como instrumentos de evaluación se utilizaron el registro ad-hoc para las variables sociodemográficas y de enfermedad, el cuestionario de Autoconcepto Garley (CAG) y cuestionario de respuesta adaptativa a la enfermedad en pacientes diabéticos. La muestra constó de 23 sujetos evaluados en un único momento de medida, todos ellos niños y adolescentes entre 8 y 16 años de edad. Los resultados muestran cómo aproximadamente el 50% de niños y adolescentes con diabetes tipo I presentan un autoconcepto bajo en la mayoría de las dimensiones estudiadas, destacando cómo cerca del 30% de los niños estudiados muestran un autoconcepto muy bajo. Por otro lado, la mayoría de los sujetos presentaron una conducta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;25(1): 57-65, mar. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119431</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El autoconcepto y la adaptación a la enfermedad en pacientes diabéticos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
