<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105583</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prática de atividade física entre idosos do Vale do Paraíba, São Paulo, Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">(Physical inactivity in the elderly often stems from socio-cultural constraints, rather than a disability. Thus this study aims to characterize the profile of seniors who participate in the Elderly Community Centre. Descriptive study, cross-sectional, exploratory, quantitative approach developed in the Social Centers for the Elderly in the Paraíba Valley. The study population was characterized by the predominance of women, average age 72 years, the ethnic self-declared white color, single mothers with incomplete primary education and specialized manual occupation. According to the data collected, we can see that physical activity changes to better the lives of the elderly, not only for the physical conditions, but mainly because it leads to the return or retention of their social activities, that support for welfare these emotional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araújo, C. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manucussi e Faro, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La inactividad física en las personas mayores a menudo se deriva de las limitaciones socio-culturales, en lugar de una discapacidad. Así, este estudio tiene como objetivo caracterizar el perfil de los adultos mayores que participan en el Centro de Convivencia de Ancianos (CCI). Estudio descriptivo, transversal, de carácter exploratorio, cuantitativo, desarrollado en los Centros Sociales para la Tercera Edad en el Valle del Paraíba. La población de estudio se caracterizó por el predominio de mujeres, con edad media de 72 años, de etnia autodeclarada blanca, madres solteras, con educación primaria incompleta y ocupación manual especializada. Según los datos recogidos, se observa que la actividad física mejora la vida de las personas mayores, no sólo por las condiciones físicas, sino sobre todo porque ocasiona la vuelta o el mantenimiento de sus actividades sociales, que son la base de su bienestar emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(28): 204-213, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La práctica de actividad física en personas mayores del Valle del Paraíba, São Paulo, Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3104</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
