<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057058</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality indicators in Capio group geriatric centers in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We present the geriatric center control panel used by Capio Spain as an instrument for managing the quality system.        Objectives: Stimulate qualitative improvements in a continuous and sustained manner in all Capio Spain geriatric centers. This necessitates the development of a system of management-by-process. Establish a barometer system which permits the assessment of quality-objective attainment along with internal and external comparability.         Material and methods: The Central Quality Core (CQC) has laid out a global control panel for geriatric centers consisting of basic indicators related to the processes identified in each area, all in accordance with their own Process Map. All indicators have corresponding description files detailing their content; these are made available to those with access to the quality portal located in the corporate intranet. Each center quality promotion group (QPC) is responsible for compiling the information regarding the indicators and forwarding it to the CQC on a quarterly basis; the CQC will then inform corporate management of its overall findings. Independently of the basic indicators, each process owner determines and defines the specific indicators that he/she finds suitable for the complete control of the process in question. When the preestablished alert levels are surpassed, the responsible quality groups (at both corporate and center levels) automatically contact each other.         Results: Each quarter, the CQC assesses the introduction of the basic indicators, with the goal that all Capio centers achieve 80% fulfilment by 2006. A description as to the indicators is provided regarding strategic processes, geriatric care, health care- and non-health care support.         Conclusions: The system used for monitoring indicators has proven to be valid and effective: it allows for the assessment of processes, inter-center comparison, the designing of improvement objectives and an unbiased analysis of their fulfilment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora Sánchez, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se presenta el cuadro de mandos de sociosanitario utilizado en el grupo Capio Sanidad como instrumento de gestión del sistema de calidad.        Objetivos: Impulsar la mejora cualitativa, de forma continuada y sostenida, en todos los centros sociosanitarios del grupo. Ello implica el desarrollo de una sistemática de gestión por procesos. Establecer una sistemática de medición que permita evaluar la consecución de los objetivos de calidad y la comparabilidad interna y externa.         Material y métodos: En el Núcleo Central de Calidad (NCC) se ha definido un cuadro de mandos integral para centros sociosanitarios, formado por indicadores básicos relacionados con los procesos identificados en cada ámbito, a partir de su propio mapa de procesos. Todos los indicadores disponen de fichas descriptivas de su contenido, que se hallan a disposición de las personas con acceso al portal de calidad en la intranet corporativa. Los grupos promotores de calidad (NPC) constituidos en cada centro se encargan de integrar la información de los indicadores y la envían trimestralmente al NCC, que aporta los resultados globales a la dirección corporativa. Con independencia de los indicadores básicos, cada propietario de proceso determina y define los indicadores específicos que considere adecuados para el control completo de su proceso. Cuando se superan los límites de alarma preestablecidos, automáticamente se ponen en contacto los grupos de calidad implicados (corporativo y de centro) para gestionar medidas de mejora inmediatas.         Resultados: El NCC evalúa trimestralmente la implantación de los indicadores básicos en los centros del grupo, siendo el objetivo para el año 2006 que se supere el 80%. Se describen los indicadores de los procesos estratégicos, de atención sociosanitaria, de soporte asistencial y de soporte no asistencial.         Conclusiones: El sistema de monitorización de indicadores utilizado se ha mostrado como un instrumento eficaz y válido, que permite la evaluación de procesos, la comparación entre centros, la fijación de objetivos de mejora y objetivar su logro</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);18(1): 24-29, ene.-mar.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores de calidad en los centros sociosanitarios del grupo Capio Sanidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22552^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
