<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153762</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seeding a Profession: The Intersection of the State, International Interests, and the Early Development of Brazilian Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">State and international entities can have profound effects on the development of a country&#146;s nursing profession. Through a global health governance lens, this paper explores the development of nursing in Brazil during the early twentieth century, and its intersections with national and international interests. Accordingly, we will show how state policies established an environment that fostered the institutionalization of nursing as a profession in Brazil and supported it as a means to increase the presence of females in nation building processes. The State focused on recruiting elite women for nursing, in part due to the Rockefeller Foundation&#146;s involvement in the country. Nurses who worked for Rockefeller came from well-educated classes within US society with specific ideas about who should be a nurse and the roles of nurses in a healthcare system. These women served as the primary vehicles for interacting with Brazilian health authorities responsible for health system development. Their early efforts did not, however, ensure a system capable of producing nursing human resources at a rate that, in present day Brazil, could meet the health needs of the country. Findings from this pa per offer new avenues for historians to explore the early roots of professional nursing through a global health governance lens, improve the understanding of the intersection between international politics and professionalization, and highlight how these factors may impact nursing human resources production in the long term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonini, Bárbara Barrionuevo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Squires, Allison</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Genival Fernandes de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oguisso, Taka</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Organizaciones estatales e internacionales pueden tener efectos profundos sobre el desarrollo de la profesión de enfermería de un país. A través de la óptica de la gobernación global de la salud, este documento analiza el desarrollo de la enfermería en Brasil en el inicio del siglo XX, y sus intersecciones con los intereses nacionales e internacionales. Por consecuencia, vamos enseñar como las políticas del Estado establecieron un ambiente que promocionó la institucionalización de la enfermería como profesión en Brasil, y la apoyó como medio para aumentar la presencia de las mujeres en los procesos de construcción de la nación. El Estado ha focalizado en el reclutamiento de mujeres de élite para la enfermería, en parte debido al envolvimiento de la Fundación Rockefeller en el país. Enfermeras que trabajaban para Rockefeller, también provenían de clases bien-educadas de la sociedad de los Estados Unidos, imbuidas de ideas específicas sobre quién debería ser una enfermera y su papel en un sistema de salud. Esas mujeres actuaron como vehículos primordiales en la interacción con autoridades brasileñas, responsables por el desarrollo del sistema de salud. Entretanto, sus esfuerzos iniciales no fueron suficientes para garantizar un sistema capaz de producir recursos humanos de enfermería con una tasa que, en los días de hoy, el Brasil podría satisfacer las necesidades de salud del país. Los hallados de este estudio ofrecen pistas sobre nuevos caminos para historiadores explotaren las primeras raíces de la enfermería profesional valiéndose de la lente de gobernanza global de la salud; mejoraren la comprensión de la intersección entre políticas internacionales y profesionalización; y aún destacaren, como eses factores pueden impactar la producción de recursos humanos de enfermería a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(44): 30-50, ene.-abr. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sembrando una profesión: la intersección entre el Estado, los intereses internacionales y el desarrollo precoz de la enfermería brasileña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6442^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28460^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53395^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13606^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12960^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
