<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99375</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preparation and characterization of an oily suspension for administration of omeprazole in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Develop an oral omeprazole suspension for use in the pediatric population. Methods: For the development of the formulation was used active ingredient in powder instead of pellets, which is usually used. By instability of the drug in acid medium, we developed a preparation of an oily character. Studies were conducted to characterize the oil vehicle, organoleptic characteristics, sedimentation volume and used the technique of differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) for studies of viscosity and drug-excipient compatibility. Results: The percentages in which the emulsified non formula were 1,54% and 4,1% surfactant agent. In the thermogram was observed that the peak melting temperature and enthalpy values of omeprazole were diminished by the presence of aspartame and also a change in the melting peak equal to 10ºC, indicating a possible interaction between omeprazole and aspartame. Conclusions: As far as the study did managed to stabilize all components of the formula, except the sweetener should be replaced by another similar power to reach the desired formula(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabasco Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón-Payer, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Corral, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Desarrollar una suspensión de omeprazol oral destinada a la población pediátrica. Métodos: Para el desarrollo de la formulación se empleó el principio activo en polvo en lugar de pellets, que es lo que habitualmente se utiliza. Por la inestabilidad del fármaco en medio ácido, se desarrolló una preparación de carácter oleoso. Se realizaron estudios para caracterizar el vehículo oleoso, características organolépticas, volumen de sedimentación y se utilizó la técnica de calorimetría diferencial de barrido (DSC) para los estudios de viscosidad y compatibilidad fármaco-excipientes. Resultados: Los porcentajes donde la fórmula no emulsionó fueron: 1,54% de viscosizante y 4,1% de tensioactivo. En el termograma se observó que la temperatura de fusión de pico y los valores de alfaHf entalpía de omeprazol se vieron disminuidos por la presencia de aspartamo y también un cambio en el pico de fusión igual a 10 °C, indicando una posible interacción entre omeprazol y aspartamo. Conclusiones: Hasta donde llegó el estudio se consiguió estabilizar todos los componentes de la fórmula, salvo el edulcorante que debe ser sustituido por otro de potencia similar para llegar a la fórmula deseada(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;53(2): 29-35[2], abr.-jun. 2012. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99375</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración y caracterización de una suspensión oleosa de omeprazol para su administración en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13916^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13930</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5177^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
