<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32472</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Rivermead Behavioural Memory Test (RBMT) in a sample of spanish population over 70 years old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Rivermead Behavioural Memory Test (RBMT) is a test for detecting everyday memory problems. Recently, a Spanish version of the RBMT has been published although without information about its reliability and validity, and without norms for the interpretation of the scores in Spanish populations. In order to correct this problem, studies with samples of Spanish children have been conducted. Nevertheless, there are no norms available for the elder population, a group of special importance given the high incidence of memory problems and complains usually associated to aging. The purpose of the present study was to validate the test and to obtain norms for the interpretation of the RBMT scores in the Spanish population over 70. Data about validity and reliability of the test are presented, along with the norms for the interpretation of scores in this age group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Test Conductual de Memoria de Rivermead (RBMT) es una prueba destinada a detectar problemas de memoria de la vida cotidiana. Recientemente, ha aparecido una versión en español del RBMT aunque sin información acerca de su fiabilidad, validez y sin normas sobre la interpretación de las puntuaciones con población española. Para subsanar este problema se han realizado estudios con muestras de niños españoles. Sin embargo, se carece de normas para la población anciana, un colectivo de especial importancia por ser donde se centra, el mayor número de quejas y déficits relacionados con el funcionamiento de la memoria. El presente trabajo tiene como finalidad la validación y obtención de normas de interpretación del RBMT con población española mayor de 70 años. Se presentan datos acerca de la validez y fiabilidad de la prueba, así como de las normas de interpretación para este colectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(2): 325-328, mayo 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión en español del Test Conductual de Memoria de Rivermead (RBMT) para población mayor de 70 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
