<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81476</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Different typologies of alcohol consumers in the practice of «botellon» in three Spanish cities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work, 6,009 youngsters (14-25 years old) who practice the «botellon» were interviewed in three cities of the Valencian Community. After a stratified sampling among college and noncollege students, a two-step cluster analysis was carried out for each sample with two aims: to identify different types of alcohol consumers in the practice of the «botellon» and to carry out a crossed validation of the results obtained. The variables included in the analysis were the following: gender, age group (university students: U; adolescent students: ES), performance of intensive episodes of consumption (yes/no), number of years practicing the «botellon» and grams of alcohol ingested. The results show the validity of the structure obtained for youngsters, revealing intensive episodes of alcohol consumption, as a four-group structure appeared in all three samples (male U, male ES, female U, female ES), in which men were always at the top of alcohol ingestion. Furthermore, ES consumed the same amount of alcohol as U, even though they had been consuming for less time. However, the youngsters who did not report intensive episodes of alcohol consumption showed some structure variability, with a tendency among women to match men&#146;s levels of alcohol consumption(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés Tomás, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín del Río, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Iñíguez, Consolación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espejo Tort, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se entrevistó a 6.009 jóvenes que practican botellón (14-25 años) en tres ciudades de la Comunidad Valenciana, realizando un muestreo estratificado de centros de Secundaria, Bachiller, CF y Universidad. Se efectuó un análisis de conglomerados en dos fases con cada muestra con dos objetivos: identificar tipologías de consumidores de alcohol en el botellón y realizar una validación cruzada de la solución obtenida. Las variables consideradas en los análisis fueron: sexo, grupo de edad (universitarios: U; estudiantes Secundaria: ES), realización o no de episodios intensivos de consumo, años practicando botellón y gramos de alcohol ingeridos. Los resultados muestran evidencia de validez de la estructura obtenida para los jóvenes que realizan episodios intensivos de consumo de alcohol, ya que aparece una estructura de cuatro grupos en las tres muestras (varones U, varones ES, mujeres U, mujeres ES), siendo siempre los varones quienes más consumen. Además, los ES consumen iguales cantidades de hol que los U, aunque llevan menos años consumiendo. Por su parte, entre los jóvenes que no realizan episodios intensivos de consumo de alcohol se observa cierta variabilidad en la estructura, siendo manifiesta la tendencia de las mujeres a igualar su consumo con el de los varones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(3): 363-368, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tipologías de consumidores de alcohol dentro de la práctica del botellón en tres ciudades españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
