<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84330</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cohesion and Cooperation in Sports Teams</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cohesion and cooperation are two psychological mechanisms of teams that are theoretically different and relatively independent. The intent of this study was to assess the levels of cohesion and cooperation and the relationships between them, as well as other variables, in a sample of 945 competitive football players between the ages of 12 and 18 years (M = 14.7, SD = 1.8). The results indicate that the factors of athletic cohesion behave almost as one single factor, which is the opposite of what happens with cooperation, and that there is a relationship between unconditional cooperation and cohesion. There is a significant difference between starting and bench players with regard to the conditional cooperation and overall cohesion, but there are no differences with regard to player's position nor with the years of practice. Finally, cohesion may be determined in part by cooperation, while the factor of cohesion of the acceptance of roles has been demonstrated to be relevant for both constructs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almeida, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lameiras, Joao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedilla, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Mas, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalonga, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cohesión y la cooperación son dos mecanismos psicológicos del equipo diferentes teóricamente, y relativamente independientes. En este trabajo se pretende estudiar, en una muestra de 945 jugadores de fútbol de competición, con edades comprendidas entre los 12 y los 18 años (media: 14.7 y dt: 1.8) los niveles de cohesión y de cooperación, y su relación entre sí, así como con otras variables. Los resultados indican que los factores de la cohesión deportiva se comportan casi como un factor único, al contrario de lo que ocurre con la cooperación, y que existe relación entre cooperación incondicionada y cohesión. Se ha hallado diferencia significativa entre los jugadores titulares y suplentes, respecto de la cooperación condicionada y de la cohesión global, pero no aparecen cambios con la posición de juego ni con los años de práctica. Finalmente, la cohesión puede ser determinada en parte por la cooperación, mientras que el factor de la cohesión de la aceptación de roles se demuestra relevante para ambos constructos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 232-238, ene.-abr. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cohesión y cooperación en equipos deportivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
