<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81211</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complete section of the external popliteal sciatic nerve during arthroscopic lateral meniscectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The aim of this paper is to present a case of external popliteal sciatic nerve injury, which is an unusual complication following knee arthroscopy. Clinical case: We present the case of a patient who suffered a complete rupture of the external popliteal sciatic nerve (EPSN), following arthroscopic lateral meniscectomy, which required the use of a nerve graft to facilitate recovery. Discussion: Nerve lesions following knee arthroscopy are rare. We have found no instances of complete nerve rupture accompanied by a break in neurologic continuity following meniscectomy. We have however found a few similar cases, which we report on in the paper. Conclusions: Although uncommon, injury to nerve structures is possible during knee arthroscopy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grau-Galtes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Ferrer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moranta-Mesquida, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas-Andreu, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez-López, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo:  Comunicar la lesión del nervio ciático poplíteo externo (CPE) como complicación inusual tras una artroscopia de rodilla. Caso clínico: Presentamos el caso clínico de un paciente que presenta una sección completa del nervio CPE, tras una meniscectomía externa por artroscopia, que precisó la realización de injerto nervioso para conseguir la recuperación. Discusión: Las lesiones neurológicas tras la artroscopia de rodilla son infrecuentes, no hemos encontrado un caso de sección completa con pérdida de continuidad neurológica tras una meniscectomía y existen casos publicados similares que son comentados. Conclusiones: Aunque infrecuente, es posible la lesión de estructuras nerviosas durante la práctica de una artroscopia de rodilla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(3): 183-185, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81211</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sección completa del ciático poplíteo externo durante una meniscectomía externa por artroscopia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12965^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
