<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166300</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical observation: A safe alternative to radiology in infants with mild traumatic brain injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The protocol for the management of mild cranioencephalic trauma in the emergency department was changed in July 2013. The principal innovation was the replacement of systematic X-ray in infants with clinical observation. The aims of this study were to determine whether there was, 1) a reduction in the ability to detect traumatic brain injury (TBI) in the initial visit to Emergency, and 2) a change in the number of requests for imaging tests and hospital admissions. Methodology: This was a retrospective, descriptive, observational study. Two periods were established for the study: Period 1 (1/11/2011-30/10/2012), prior to the implementing of the new protocol, and Period 2 (1/11/2013-30/10/2014), following its implementation. The study included visits to the emergency department by children&amp;#8804;2 years old for mild cranioencephalic trauma (Glasgow Scale modified for infants &amp;#8805; 14) of &amp;#8804; 24 hours onset. Results: A total of 1,543 cases were included, of which 807 were from Period 1 and 736 from Period 2. No significant differences were observed as regards sex, age, mechanism, or risk of TBI. More cranial fractures were detected in Period 1 than in Period 2 (4.3% vs 0.5%; P&lt;.001), without significant changes in the detection of TBI (0.4% vs 0.3%; P=1). However, there were more cranial X-rays (49.7% vs 2.7%; P&lt;.001) and more ultrasounds (2.1% vs 0.4%; P&lt;.001) carried out, and also fewer hospital admissions (8.3% vs 3.1%; P&lt;.001). There were no significant differences in the number of computerised tomography scans carried out (2% vs 3%; P=.203). Conclusions: The use of clinical observation as an alternative to cranial radiography leads to a reduction in the number of imaging tests and hospital admissions of infants with mild cranioencephalic trauma, without any reduction in the reliability of detecting TBI. This option helps to lower the exposure radiation by the patient, and is also a more rational use of hospital resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trenchs Sainz de la Maza, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maya Gallego, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuaresma González, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Santanach, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En julio 2013 se cambió el protocolo de manejo del traumatismo craneoencefálico leve en urgencias, siendo la principal novedad la sustitución sistemática de las radiografías craneales en lactantes por la observación clínica. Los objetivos son determinar si este cambio ha implicado: 1) una disminución en la capacidad de detección de lesiones intracraneales (LIC) en la visita inicial de urgencias y 2) cambios en la solicitud de pruebas de imagen e ingresos. Metodología: Estudio retrospectivo, descriptivo-observacional. Se establecen 2 periodos: periodo 1 (1/11/2011-30/10/2012), preimplantación nuevo protocolo, y periodo 2 (1/11/2013-30/10/2014), postimplantación. Se incluyen las consultas por traumatismo craneoencefálico leve a urgencias (escala Glasgow modificada para lactantes &amp;#8805; 14) de &amp;#8804; 24h de evolución de niños &amp;#8804; 2 años. Resultados: Se incluyen 1.543 casos, 807 del periodo 1 y 736 del periodo 2, sin observarse diferencias significativas en sexo, edad, mecanismo y riesgo de LIC. En el periodo 1 se diagnostican más fracturas craneales que en el periodo 2 (4,3 vs. 0,5%; p&lt;0,001) sin cambios significativos en la detección de LIC (0,4 vs. 0,3%; p=1). Asimismo, se realizan más radiografías de cráneo (49,7 vs. 2,7%; p&lt;0,001), más ecografías (2,1 vs. 0,4%; p&lt;0,001) e ingresan más casos (8,3% vs 3,1%; p&lt;0,001). No se hallan diferencias significativas en las tomografías computarizadas realizadas (2 vs. 3%; p=0,203). Conclusiones: La observación clínica como alternativa a la radiografía craneal permite reducir las pruebas de imagen y los ingresos en los lactantes con traumatismo craneoencefálico leve sin disminuir la fiabilidad diagnóstica de LIC. Esta opción permite la reducción de irradiación al paciente y un uso más racional de los recursos sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(3): 164-169, sept. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Observación clínica: una alternativa segura a la radiología en lactantes con traumatismo craneoencefálico leve</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23437^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
