<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-26621</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between quality of life and different models of home care among terminal cancer patients in an health area of Madrid, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This study assesses the effectiveness of the palliative home care for the purpose of ascertaining whether terminal cancer patients treated by Homecare Support Teams have a better quality of life than those treated by Primary Care Teams. Methods: A quasi-experimental prospective study conducted in Madrid Healthcare District 4 on patients referred from the hospital to Homecare Support Teams or to Primary Care Teams. The main study variable was the quality of life gauged using the Rotterdam Symptom Check List and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale. Statistical differences were evaluated by MANOVA, repeated measures ANOVA and Friedman test. Results: A total of 165 patients were treated by Homecare Support Teams and 56 by Primary Care Teams. The patients treated by the Homecare Support Teams showed better point scores on the overall scale (mean differece: 9.5; CI 95%; 2.3-16.67) and pain scale (mean difference: 6.4; CI 9%; 1.14-11.43) on the Rotterdam Symptom Check List during the first week of the study. The effect size was greater on the Homecare Support Team group. The prescription of drugs and the place of death were different between both groups. Conclusions: At the start of the study, the patients treated by Homecare Support Teams showed a better perception of the health condition than those treated by the Primary Care Teams. However, the great number of patients lost along the study makes it necessary be cautious when considering these results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En este trabajo se evalúa la efectividad de los cuidados paliativos a domicilio con el objetivo de determinar si los enfermos con cáncer terminal tratados por Equipos de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria presentan mejor calidad de vida que los tratados por Equipos de Atención Primaria. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo cuasi experimental realizado en el Área 4 del Insalud de Madrid con enfermos referidos desde el hospital a Equipos de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria o a Equipos de Atención Primaria. La variable estudiada fue la calidad de vida medida a través del Rotterdam Symptom Check List y el Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale. Para el análisis estadístico se utilizó MANOVA, ANOVA de medidas repetidas y el test de Friedman. Resultados: 165 enfermos fueron tratados por Equipos de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria y 56 por Equipos de Atención Primaria. Los primeros presentaron mejor puntuación en las escalas global (diferencia de medias: 9,5; IC 95 por ciento: 2,3-16,67) y dolor (diferencia de medias: 6,4; IC 9 por ciento: 1,14-11,43) del Rotterdam Symptom Check List en la primera semana del estudio. El tamaño del efecto fue mayor en el grupo Equipos de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria. La prescripción de fármacos y el lugar de la muerte fue diferente en ambos grupos. Conclusiones: Al principio del estudio los enfermos tratados por Equipos de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria presentaron una mejor percepción del estado de salud que los tratados por Equipos de Atención Primaria. No obstante, el importante número de pérdidas a lo largo del mismo hace que haya que mirar estos resultados con precaución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;77(5): 567-579, sept. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de la calidad de vida con diferentes modelos de atención domiciliaria en enfermos oncológicos terminales de un área sanitaria de madrid</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Agra Varela, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelayo Alvarez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán Rodea, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-26621</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
