<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130560</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Homosexualities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to study homosexualities, the author takes the freudian metapsychology as a starting point. He describes an evolutionary straight line: on the left side of the line, he places psychic ways of working related to a symbiosis or lack of differentiation from the primary object; on the right side of the line, he places neurotic ways of working organized by the depression. He draws attention on four paradigmatic points of the line in order to study them more deeply. He presents clinincal material related to two cases: the first one is about a woman with an important part of her psyche organized by te repression and thus, essentially neurotic; the other case history deals with a man with important problems to differentiate himself from a mamma-donna, who makes his debut with a late onset homosexuality. The author assesses controversial questions questions such as homparentality and the possible option for homosexual to become psychoanalysts. He criiticizes the tendency of each author to  homogenize the issu of all kinds of homosexualities depending on his ideological bias. He recommends the singular study of each individual case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artaloytia Usobiaga, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para referirse a las homosexualidades, el autor parte de una metapsicología freudiana. Define una línea evolutiva: en el extremo izquierdo, ubica funcionamientos relacionados con una simbiosis e indiferenciación con respecto al objeto primario; en el derecho, funcionamientos neuróticos estructurados en torno a la represión. Se centra en cuatro puntos paradigmáticos de la línea para estudiarlos más en profundidad. Presenta material clínico de dos casos: uno de una mujer con una parte importante de su psiquismo organizado en torno a la represión y por ello fundamentalmente neurótica; otro de un hombre con importantes dificultades para diferenciarse de una mamma-donna, que tardíamente debuta con un funcionamiento homosexual. Entra en cuestiones polémicas como la homoparentalidad y la posibilidad de que pueda haber psicoanalistas homosexuales, denunciando la tendencia a homogenizar el pensamiento sobre todas las homosexualidades según el sesgo ideológico de cada autor, y abogando por el estudio de la singularidad de cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(70): 61-104, sept.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130560</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Homosexualidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23910^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23910^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12515</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
