<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036729</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicenter study on the association between variables related to resuscitation and mortality in severe sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To establish the association between parameters indicative of delay and failure in the resuscitation and mortality in patients with severe sepsis, and to describe the pattern of use of vasoactive drugs in patients with septic shock. Design. Prospective cohorts study. Context. Seven polyvalent Intensive Care Units (ICU) in Spain. Patients and method. Patients with severe sepsis admitted consecutively in the participating UCIs over 1 month. Primary endpoints. Variables related to resuscitation interventions, persistence of a state of insufficient resuscitation, organs dysfunction, use of vasoactive drugs, and mortality in ICU were evaluated. Results. Global mortality was 40%. In comparison with patients who survive, those which die show greater SAPS II scoring (p = 0.02), greater number of organs with failure (p = 0.01), and lower GCS scores at admission (p = 0.001). Oliguria and hypotension lenght, as well as the period of vasopressor drugs administration were univariately related to prognosis. The more prevalent pattern of vasoactive drugs use was that of norepinephrine alone (60% of patients with hypotension) or that of norepinephrine in combination with dopamine with doses lower than 5 µg/kg/ min (32% of patients with hypotension). Conclusion. In severe sepsis not only indicative parameters of tissue hypoperfusion at admission are variables related to mortality, but also the lenght of tissue hypoperfusion and shock. These results support the concept that early application of resuscitation and therapeutic measures that avoid or diminish the lenght of tissue hypoperfusion can improve the prognosis of severe sepsis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Leyba, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raurich Puigdeval, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Balanza, J A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Juvé, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nin Vaeza, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baigorri González, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estimar la asociación entre parámetros indicativos de retraso y fracaso en la resucitación con la mortalidad en pacientes con sepsis grave, y describir el patrón de uso de fármacos vasoactivos en pacientes con shock séptico. Diseño. Estudio prospectivo de cohortes. Ámbito. Siete Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) polivalentes en España. Pacientes y método. Enfermos diagnosticados de sepsis grave ingresados de forma consecutiva en las UCI participantes durante un período de un mes. Variables de interés principales. Se recogieron variables relacionadas con intervenciones de resucitación, persistencia de un estado de resucitación insuficiente, disfunción de órganos, uso de fármacos vasoactivos y mortalidad en UCI. Resultados. La mortalidad global fue del 40%. En comparación con los enfermos que sobreviven, los que fallecen presentan mayor puntuación Simplified Acute Physiology Score II (SAPS II) (p = 0,02), mayor número de órganos disfuncionantes (p = 0,01), y menor escala de coma de Glasgow (GCS) en el momento del ingreso (p = 0,001). La duración de la oliguria y de la hipotensión, así como la duración de la necesidad de administración de fármacos presores, se relacionaron de forma univariante con el pronóstico. El patrón de uso de fármacos vasoactivos más prevalente fue noradrenalina sola (60% de los enfermos con hipotensión) o en combinación con dopamina a dosis inferiores a 5 µg/kg/min (32% de los enfermos con hipotensión).Conclusión. No sólo parámetros indicativos de hipoperfusión tisular presentes al ingreso, sino también la duración de la hipoperfusión tisular y del shock, son variables que se relacionan con la mortalidad en la sepsis grave. Estos resultados apoyan el concepto de que la resucitación y la aplicación de medidas terapéuticas de forma precoz que eviten o disminuyan la duración de la hipoperfusión tisular pueden mejorar el pronóstico de la sepsis grave</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(4): 212-218, mayo 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio multicéntrico sobre la asociación entre variables relacionadas con la resucitación y la mortalidad en la sepsis grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32030^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
