<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137649</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-5887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genetic counseling as eugenics procedure: a reflection related to bioethical principles and fundamental rights</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper aims to characterize the use of procedures of genetic counseling with eugenic discriminatory purposes as violation of fundamental principles and rights. Considering the need to address the bioethical principles and fundamental rights such as human dignity, non-discrimination and responsible parenthood. Through a deductive reasoning, we study the eugenics concepts, as well as the procedure of genetic counseling and bioethical principles and fundamental rights involved, seeking to demonstrate that the selection of genetic traits with non-therapeutic purposes is an affront to ethically responsible actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burg Conti, Paulo Henrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo busca caracterizar como violación de principios y derechos fundamentales la utilización del procedimiento de consejo genético con fines eugenésicos discriminatorios. Se considera la necesidad de atender a los principios bioéticos y derechos fundamentales, como la dignidad humana, la no discriminación y la paternidad responsable. A través de un raciocinio deductivo, se realiza un estudio conceptual de la eugenesia, así como del procedimiento de consejo genético y de los principios bioéticos y derechos fundamentales involucrados, tratando de demostrar que la selección de rasgos genéticos con fines no terapéuticos es una afrenta al actuar éticamente responsable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. bioét. derecho;(33): 44-56, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consejo genético como procedimiento eugenésico: una reflexión en relación con los principios bioéticos y los derechos fundamentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38873^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38400^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
