<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87567</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of overweight and obesity in adults in an urban health area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo estimate prevalence of overweight and obesity in adults and to identify those individuals at high cardiovascular risk (subjects with type 2 diabetes or hypertension) in whom a nurse intervention might be beneficial in terms of life-style changes and reduction in body weight.MethodA cross-sectional study on 2270 adults (18&#150;80 years-old) from an urban Primary Health Care Centre. Medical history, social and demographic data, physical examination and blood tests were collected.ResultsThe mean body mass index was 26.9±5.1kg/m2 and was found to be higher in men. Thirty-eight percent of subjects were overweight and 22% were obese. Although the prevalence of obesity was identical in both sexes, women had higher prevalences of type ii and iii obesity than men, but overweight was more frequent in men. Among those older than fifty years-old, 84% were overweight or obese. One-hundred and fifty-six (7%) subjects had type 2 diabetes and 707 (31%) had hypertension, and 111 (5%) subjects with both diabetes and hypertension. BMI was higher (P&lt;0.001) in patients who suffered from, hypertension (29.7±5.2), diabetes (28.5±4.6), and diabetes and hypertension (31.4±5.3), than in those who did not suffer from these diseases (25.4±4.3).ConclusionsObesity and overweight is highly prevalent in the population studied and is higher in patients with diabetes and hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrobianco-Cobo, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos-Cerezuela, Ildefonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poyatos-Ramos, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Huelgas, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Vera, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancera-Romero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán-Visquert,  Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Lagos, Juan Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEstimar la prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en adultos de un área de salud urbana e identificar a grupos de alto riesgo cardiovascular (diabéticos e hipertensos) que puedan beneficiarse de una intervención enfermera sobre modificación de estilos de vida para reducir el peso.MétodoEstudio transversal analítico realizado con una muestra aleatoria de 2.270 individuos obtenida a partir de la población adulta (18&#150;80 años) perteneciente a un centro de salud. A todos los participantes se les realizó una historia clínica (incluyendo datos sociodemográficos), una exploración física y determinaciones analíticas.ResultadosEl índice de masa corporal (IMC) medio se encontraba en el rango del sobrepeso (26,9±5,1kg/m2) y fue superior en varones. El 38% de la muestra tenía sobrepeso y el 22% obesidad. No se encontraron diferencias entre sexos en la prevalencia de obesidad, aunque las mujeres presentaron una mayor prevalencia de obesidad grados ii y iii. El sobrepeso fue más frecuente en los varones. La prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad aumenta con la edad. El 7% de la muestra (156 personas) presentaron diabetes, el 31% (707) tenían hipertensión arterial y en el 5% (111 personas) coincidían ambas patologías. El IMC fue significativamente mayor (p&lt;0,001) en los pacientes con diabetes e hipertensión (31,4±5,3), hipertensión (29,7±5,2) y diabetes (28,5±4,6) que en aquellos que no tenían estas patologías (25,4±4,3).ConclusionesEn nuestra población existe una alta prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad siendo más elevada en pacientes con diabetes e hipertensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(5): 286-291, sept.-oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en población adulta de un área de Salud Urbana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
