<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053341</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopically assisted fronto-orbitary correction in trigonocephaly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of multidisciplinar Units for Craneofacial  Surgery has led to a considerable decrease in morbidity even in the cases  of more complex craniofacial syndromes. The use of minimally invasive  techniques for the correction of some of these malformations  allows the surgeon to minimize the incidence of complications by means  of a decrease in the surgical time, blood salvage and shortening  of postoperative hospitalization in comparison to conventional craniofacial  techniques. Simple and milder craniosynostosis are best approached  by these techniques and render the best results. Different osteotomies resembling standard fronto-orbital remodelling besides simple  suturectomies and the use of postoperative cranial orthesis may improve  the final aesthetic appearence. In endoscopic treatment of trigonocephaly  the use of preauricular incisions achieves complete pterional resection,  lower lateral orbital osteotomies and successful precoronal frontal  osteotomies to obtain long lasting and satisfactory outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Recuero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hinojosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romance, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de equipos multidisciplinares en las Unidades de Cirugía Craneofacial ha permitido disminuir considerablemente la incidencia de morbimortalidad incluso en el caso de los síndromes craneofaciales más complejos. La posibilidad de ofertar técnicas mínimamente invasivas mediante osteotomías endoscópicamente asistidas para algunas de estas malformaciones permite disminuir el número de complicaciones, así como acortar el tiempo quirúrgico, las pérdidas hemáticas y la estancia hospitalaria postoperatoria respecto a las técnicas convencionales de cirugía craneofacial. Los resultados más satisfactorios se consiguen en las craneosinostosis simples o más leves. La realización de diversas osteotomías junto a la suturectomía simple imitando las técnicas de remodelación frontoorbitaria clásica y la aplicación postoperatoria de cascos de ortesis permiten mejorar la apariencia final de la deformidad. En el tratamiento endoscópico de la trigonocefalia la utilización de dos incisiones preauriculares permite una osteotomía orbitaria lateral más baja, la resección pterional completa y la realización de las osteotomías frontales en posición retrocoronal, con lo que es posible obtener un resultado más satisfactorio que tras la resección simple de la sutura metópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;20(1): 33-38, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Remodelación frontoorbitaria endoscópicamente asistida en la trigonocefalia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3409^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
