<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151391</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between vitamin D deficiency and visually evoked potentials in multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the possible relationship between serum 25-OH vitamin D levels and visually evoked potentials (VEP) in patients with multiple sclerosis (MS), residents in the south zone of Gran Canaria. Material and methods: The study included 49 patients with MS, on whom 25-OH-vitamin D was determined, along with VEP, and a neurological examination to determine incapacity. Clinical variables, such as a history of optic neuritis were recorded. Results: The mean value of 25-OH-vitamin D of the patients was 28.1 ± 9.5 ng/ml. The VEP latency was 119.1 ± 23.2 ms and the amplitude, 8.5 ± 4.4 &amp;#956;V. Patients with a higher 25-OH-vitamin D had a greater number of outbreaks in the year prior to the study (P=.049), and those with vitamin D deficiency and previous optic neuritis showed no reduction in the amplitude of the VEP (P=.006). Conclusion: Patients with vitamin D deficiency have lower clinical activity of the MS and show no axonal involvement in VEP after having suffered optic neuritis. These relationships, although statistically significant, do not seem clinically plausible, thus new studies are needed to try and confirm this possible relationship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sosa Henríquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Pérez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Méndez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la posible relación entre los niveles séricos de 25-OH-vitamina D y los potenciales evocados visuales (PEV) de los pacientes con esclerosis múltiple (EM) residentes en la zona sur de Gran Canaria. Material y métodos: Se incluyó a 49 pacientes con EM. Se les realizó determinación de 25-OH-vitamina D, PEV, exploración neurológica para determinar la discapacidad y se recogieron variables clínicas tales como el antecedente de neuritis óptica. Resultados: El valor medio de 25-OH-vitamina D de los pacientes fue de 28,1 ± 9,5 ng/ml, la latencia de los PEV fue de 119,1 ± 23,2 ms y la amplitud de 8,5 ± 4,4 &amp;#956;V. Los pacientes con niveles normales de 25-OH-vitamina D tuvieron mayor número de brotes en el año previo al estudio (p = 0,049) y aquellos con déficit de vitamina D y neuritis óptica previa no presentaron reducción de la amplitud de los PEV (p = 0,006). Conclusión: Los pacientes con déficit de vitamina D tienen menor actividad clínica de la EM y no presentan afectación axonal en PEV tras haber sufrido neuritis óptica. Estas asociaciones, aunque estadísticamente significativas, no parecen clínicamente plausibles, por lo que sería preciso realizar nuevos estudios que intentasen confirmar esta posible asociación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(5): 217-222, mayo 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre el déficit de vitamina D y los potenciales evocados visuales en la esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5171^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34242^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34242^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
