<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99746</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Invasive fungal infection in critically ill patient: role of micafungin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The invasive fungal infections (IFIs) have increased in critically ill patients in recent years and are a serious complication that determine the evolution and prognosis of critically ill patients, especially invasive candidiasis (IC) and candidemia. Fortunately, treatment options for these infections have increased and there is a large arsenal of antifungal agents. This review of the literature, using PubMed and Cochrane databases, assesses the situation of the IFIs in critically ill patients and discusses the role of micafungin in this context. The broader spectrum of this candin, which gets the antifungal effect with lower MICs and that translates into greater clinical efficacy with a lower rate of adverse effects and easier to use, with proven cost-effectiveness compared with other antifungal, position micafungin as a useful therapeutic option for the management of invasive candidiasis / candidemia in critically ill patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escudero López-Cepero, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Cabrera, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones fúngicas invasoras (IFI) han aumentado en los pacientes críticos (PC) en los últimos años y constituyen una complicación grave que condiciona la evolución y el pronóstico de estos pacientes, especialmente la candidiasis invasiva (CI) y la candidemia (CA). Afortunadamente existen más opciones terapéuticas y se dispone de un amplio arsenal de antifúngicos para optimizar el tratamiento de estas infecciones. En esta revisión de la literatura, utilizando las bases de PubMed y Cochrane, se evalúa la situación de las IFIs en el paciente crítico y se analiza el papel de micafungina en este contexto. El espectro más amplio de esta candina, y su efecto antifúngico con CMIs menores, que se traduce en gran eficacia clínica con una tasa menor de efectos adversos y de más fácil manejo, con coste-efectividad demostrada frente a otros antifúngicos, hacen de micafungina una opción terapéutica óptima para el manejo de la candidiasis invasiva/ candidemia en el paciente crítico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;25(1): 4-9, mar.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99746</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección fúngica en el paciente crítico: papel de micafungina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
