<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66034</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interdigital erythrasma: clinical, epidemiologic and microbiologic findings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Erythrasma is a superficial infection caused by Corynebacterium minutissimum and affects the major skin folds and the interdigital regions of the feet. It is characterized by erythematous, brown, scalypatches and maceration, and exhibits coral-red fluorescence under Wood light. Objective. The aim of this study was to determine the frequency of erythrasma in patients with interdigital lesions. Methods. An open, prospective, longitudinal, observational study was performed in a hospital in Mexico City between March and December, 2006. All patients with interdigital lesions were examined with a Wood lamp and direct examination was performed with 20 % potassium hydroxide. Cultures were done in Sabouraud dextrose agar and brain heart infusion agar, and smears were analyzed. General characteristics and concomitant diseases were recorded. Results. We examined 73 patients, of whom 24 (32.8%) were diagnosed with erythrasma based on coral-red fluorescence under Wood light and identification of corynebacteria by Gram staining. The disease was more common in women (83.33 %) and the mean age of the patients was 43.5 years. The main clinical findings were scaling and maceration, and the fourth interdigital web was the most commonly affected. Corynebacterium could not be isolated in any of the cases. Mycology was positive in 15 cases (62.5 %) and the following microorganisms were isolated: Candida (16.6 %), dermatophytes (12.5 %), and Trichosporon (4.1 %) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales-Trujillo, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El eritrasma es una infección superficial causada por Corynebacterium minutissimum, que afecta grandes pliegues y regiones interdigitales de los pies. Existe eritema, descamación, manchas color marrón y maceración; se presenta con fluorescencia rojo coral con luz de Wood. Objetivo. Determinar la frecuencia de eritrasma en pacientes con lesiones interdigitales. Métodos. Se realizó un estudio prospectivo, abierto, observacional y longitudinal en un hospital de la ciudad de México de marzo a diciembre de 2006. A todos los pacientes con lesiones interdigitales se les realizó luz de Wood, examen directo con hidróxido de potasio al 20 %, cultivo en agar dextrosa Sabouraud, frotis y cultivo en infusión cerebro-corazón. Se documentaron los datos generales y enfermedades concomitantes. Resultados. Examinamos 73 pacientes, 24 (32,8 %) presentaron eritrasma diagnosticado por la fluorescencia rojo coral y la identificación de la corinebacteria por tinción de Gram. Fue más frecuente en mujeres (83,33 %) y la edad promedio fue 43,5 años. Los principales datos clínicos fueron descamación y maceración y el cuarto pliegue fue el más afectado. En ningún caso se pudo aislar el microorganismo en el cultivo. El examen micológico fue positivo en 15 casos (62,5 %) y se aislaron: Candida (16,6 %), dermatofitos (12,5 %) y Trichosporon (4,1%). Conclusiones. El eritrasma interdigital es frecuente y puede confundirse fácilmente con tiña interdigital. Es persistente sin tratamiento adecuado. El diagnóstico es rápido y accesible con luz de Wood y el cultivo es difícil y no es indispensable para el diagnóstico. Debe considerarse la coexistencia de eritrasma con dermatofitos y Candida cuando afecta los pliegues inerdigitales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(6): 469-473, jul. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eritrasma interdigital: datos clínicos, epidemiológicos y microbiológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13433^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3370^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14132^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23483^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28027^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4981^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4981^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32684</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4981^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
