<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166432</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene&#150;environment interactions and cardiovascular risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this review were to examine the rationale for investigating the interaction between genes and the environment and to discuss recent studies into the interactions of genes and environmental modulators that are relevant to cardiovascular disease and its principle risk factors. Studies that have focused on smoking, alcohol and coffee consumption, and physical activity have all been observational studies and have involved relatively large samples. However, they tended to examine single genes and failed to take into account interactions with other genes or associated environmental factors. Both observational and interventional studies have been used to explore the interaction between genes and diet, with interventional studies being much smaller. Of the gene-diet interactions reported, two important highlights are, firstly, the confirmation that the apolipoprotein A-V gene (APOA5) is involved in triglyceride metabolism and is modulated by dietary factors and, secondly, the discovery that apolipoprotein A-II (APOA2) modulates food intake and the risk of obesity. The study of gene-environment interactions is an active and vital area of research. While the technical barriers to carrying out genetic studies are rapidly being overcome, studies are still hampered by the substantial difficulty of including comprehensive and reliable data on environmental factors. Progress in this area depends on involving large study populations across a range of geographical regions, as well as on employing a more comprehensive, standardized and precise approach to acquiring information about environmental factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ordovas, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta revisión se discuten las razones para analizar las interacciones entre genes y entorno, y los estudios recientes que examinan las interacciones entre genes y moduladores ambientales en relación con la enfermedad cardiovascular y sus factores de riesgo comunes. Los estudios que se han centrado en el tabaquismo, el alcohol, la actividad física y el café son todos ellos de tipo observacional y tienen unos tamaños muestrales relativamente grandes. Sin embargo, tienden a examinar un único gen y no abordan las interacciones con otros genes y con otros factores ambientales relacionados. El diseño de los estudios que han examinado las interacciones entre genes y dieta ha sido observacional o de intervención, éstos de tamaño mucho menor. Entre las interacciones descritas de los genes y la dieta, es importante resaltar la confirmación de que APOA5 es un gen importante que interviene en el metabolismo de los triglicéridos, que se armoniza por factores de la dieta, así como la identificación del APOA2 como modulador de la ingesta alimentaria y del riesgo de obesidad. El estudio de las interacciones entre genes y entorno es un campo activo en el que hay una gran necesidad de investigación. Los obstáculos técnicos para la realización de los estudios genéticos están siendo superados con rapidez. La inclusión de una información detallada y fiable sobre los factores ambientales constituye una dificultad importante para estas investigaciones. Los avances en este campo deberán incluir el uso de poblaciones más amplias y zonas geográficas múltiples, pero también el empleo de enfoques más precisos, estandarizados y exhaustivos, que permitan capturar la información sobre los factores ambientales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);9(supl.B): 39b-51b, 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166432</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones entre genes y entorno y factores de riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5937^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
