<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162980</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shared decision making from the perspective of the cancer patient: participatory roles and evaluation of the process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. In Spain there is no clear knowledge about the degree to which Shared Decision Making (SDM) is carried out in the normal practice of oncology. Our article analyses the preferred role and the perceived role of oncological patients and measures the SDM process from their perspective. Material and methods. Descriptive transversal study using a self-conducted questionnaire with patients with different types of cancer. To evaluate the role preferred and perceived by the patient we used The Control Preference Scales (CPS) and to measure SDM we used The nine-item Shared Decision Making Questionnaire (SDM-Q-9). Results. Out of the 132 patients surveyed, only 118 provided analysable data. No evidence was found that sex, age, educational level or type of tumour affected the preferred role or the perceived role. Only 59.3% was in agreement with the role exercised. All of those who preferred a passive role achieved this (21.2%), while out of those who wanted a shared role (78.8%), this was achieved by only 48.39% while the remaining 51.61% played a passive role. None preferred or played an active role. The set of patients evaluated the SDM process with a score of 41.07±5.94, on a scale of 0 to 100, with the highest score of 61.39 ± 13.24 reached by urological patients. Conclusions. Our study found no evidence that, from the point of view of the oncological patient, the SDM model is being implemented in practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Padilla Garrido, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado Correa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayo Calero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayo Lozano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. En España no existe un claro conocimiento sobre el grado en que la Toma de Decisiones Compartidas (TDC) es llevada a la práctica habitual en oncología. Nuestro trabajo analiza el rol preferido y el rol percibido de los pacientes oncológicos y mide el proceso de TDC desde su perspectiva. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal mediante cuestionario autoadministrado a pacientes con distintos tipos de cáncer. Para evaluar el rol preferido y percibido por el paciente utilizamos The Control Preference Scales (CPS) y para medir la TDC se utilizó The nine-item Shared Decision Making Questionnaire (SDM-Q-9). Resultados. De los 132 pacientes encuestados, solo 118 proporcionaron datos analizables. No se encontraron evidencias de que el sexo, edad, nivel educativo o tipo de tumor afectaran al rol preferido o al percibido. Solo el 59,3% estaba de acuerdo con el rol ejercido. Todos los que preferían un rol pasivo lo alcanzaban (21,2%), mientras que de los que deseaban uno compartido (78,8%), solo el 48,39% lo lograba y el 51,61% restante desempeñaba uno pasivo. Ninguno prefirió ni ejerció un rol activo. El conjunto de pacientes valoró el proceso de TDC con una puntuación de 41,07±5,94, en una escala de 0 a 100, alcanzando los pacientes urológicos una puntuación máxima de 61,39 ± 13,24. Conclusiones. Nuestro estudio no encuentra evidencias de que, desde el punto de vista del paciente oncológico, el modelo de TDC esté implementado en la práctica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;40(1): 25-33, ene.-abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162980</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La toma de decisiones compartidas desde la perspectiva del paciente oncológico: roles de participación y valoración del proceso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
