<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136623</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical usefulness of ultrasound-guided alcohol sclerosis in patients with breast fistulas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study the clinical usefulness of ultrasound-guided alcohol sclerosis as a treatment alternative to surgical intervention for breast fistulas. Material and methods. This was a retrospective study of data collected in a hospital breast unit over a three-year period (January 2011 through December 2013). The procedure consists of introducing a sclerosing solution into the lumen of the breast fistula under ultrasound guidance. All cases were reviewed by a multidisciplinary committee; patients were offered ultrasound-guided alcohol sclerosis as a first treatment option with surgical intervention as a rescue therapy for those with unsatisfactory outcomes. Results. Ten fistulas were treated in 9 women (median age, 33 y; interquartile range 18.5 y). Five patients (50%) attributed the clinical findings to recurrent mastitis, four (40%) to a previous surgical intervention, and one (10%) to lactation. Seven patients (78%) were smokers. The procedure was well tolerated: nine patients (90%) rated the pain as one or 2 (mild pain) on a visual analogue scale. There were no immediate complications. The response to treatment was considered excellent (absence of secretion and complete closure) in eight fistulas (80%). Conclusion. Ultrasound-guided alcohol sclerosis achieved excellent outcomes in 80% of cases and is a viable alternative to surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Marcos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana-Lopez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Silva, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar la utilidad clínica de la esclerosis con alcohol guiada con ecografía como tratamiento innovador y alternativo a la intervención quirúrgica de las fístulas de mama. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo basado en los datos recogidos en una Unidad de mama hospitalaria durante tres años (enero de 2011 - diciembre de 2013). El procedimiento consistió en introducir en la luz de la fístula mamaria una solución esclerosante guiada con ecografía. Todos los casos fueron revisados por un comité multidisciplinar, se planteó a las pacientes la esclerosis con alcohol guiada con ecografía como primera opción terapéutica, dejando la intervención quirúrgica para los casos con resultados desfavorables. Resultados. Se reunieron 10 fístulas en 9 mujeres. La mediana de edad fue de 33 años (rango intercuartílico 18,5 años). Cinco pacientes atribuyeron los datos clínicos a mastitis de repetición (50%), cuatro a una intervención quirúrgica previa (40%) y una a la lactancia (10%). Siete pacientes eran fumadoras (78%). El procedimiento se toleró bien, 9 pacientes (90%) puntuaron un valor de uno o 2 en la escala analógica visual del dolor (dolor leve). No hubo complicaciones inmediatas. La respuesta al tratamiento se consideró excelente (ausencia de secreción y cierre completo) en 8 fístulas (80%). Conclusión. La esclerosis con alcohol guiada con ecografía es una alternativa terapéutica a la quirúrgica que ha acabado con la curación del 80% de las fístulas tratadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);57(4): 321-325, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad clínica de la esclerosis con alcohol guiada con ecografía en pacientes con fístulas de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8584^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9743^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9743^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8584^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
