<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75056</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the use of antifungal management advisable in critical patients with positive isolation of Candida spp. from intraabdominal clinical samples?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnostic and therapeutic approaches to IFI have changed significantly inrecent years, fostered by the introduction of new diagnostic methods and newantifungal products. The diagnosis of invasive candidiasis (IC) involves bothclinical and laboratory parameters, but neither of these are specific and themajority of the yeast isolated showed only colonization but not true infection.This situation occurs in critical care setting specially when surgical drainages areused. A substantial number of patients become colonized with Candida spp. after abdominal surgery, but only a minority subsequently develops invasivecandidiasis. The clinical and microbiological diagnosis of Candida peritonitisremains problematic. It is still unclear which patients with may benefit fromantifungal treatment. Antifungal therapy can be suggested in critically illpatients with peritonitis where Candida is diagnosed based on perioperativelysampled peritoneal fluid. Since fungal infection is also a relatively commoncomplication of severe pancreatitis it seems reasonable that fungal prophylaxismay be an important component of management although actually there is noevidence to support this approach. However, the high mortality associatedwith IC is partly correlated to the difficulties of making an early diagnosis,thus, to improve earlier diagnosis and survival of IC, new nonculture-basedmicrobiological tools such as Candida albicans germ tube antibodies (CAGTA)and/or polymerase chain reaction (PCR) techniques for the detection offungal-specific DNA should be used in conjunction with recent published&#147;Candida score&#148; prediction rule. An algorithm based on this approach hasbeen provided to assess early treatment in surgical patients with yeastsisolated from intra-abdominal samples(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salavert, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pemán, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragoza, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aproximación diagnóstica y terapéutica a la infección fúngica invasiva (IFI)ha cambiado notablemente en los últimos años debido a la introducción denuevos métodos diagnósticos y a la aparición de nuevos fármacosantifúngicos. El diagnóstico de candidiasis invasiva (CI) está basado enparámetros clínicos y de laboratorio, aunque ninguno de ellos es específico.De hecho, incluso el aislamiento de levaduras en muchas ocasionescorresponde a simple colonización y no verdadera infección, en especial en elámbito de los cuidados críticos, y sobre todo cuando este aislamientoproviene de drenajes intraabdominales. Un gran número de pacientes secolonizan con Candida spp. después de una cirugía abdominal pero sólo unaminoría de estos desarrolla CI. El diagnóstico clínico y microbiológico de laperitonitis candidiásica sigue siendo controvertido, constituyendo todavía unreto el conocer que pacientes se podrían beneficiar de tratamiento antifúngico.En términos generales se recomienda tratar a aquellos pacientes críticos enlos que el aislamiento provenga de una muestra de líquido peritonealperioperatoria. Basados en el hecho de que la infección fúngica es unacomplicación frecuente de las pancreatitis agudas graves parecería lógicorealizar profilaxis antifúngica en estos enfermos; sin embargo, no existeevidencia hasta el momento para recomendar su uso. La alta mortalidad de laCI se asocia a la dificultad que supone realizar un diagnóstico precoz.Por tanto, para mejorar el pronóstico de estos enfermos sería muyaconsejable utilizar las nuevas herramientas que nos proporciona el laboratoriode microbiología como son la detección de anticuerpos antimicelio o la PCRfúngica, que deberían ser usadas en conjunción con el recién publicado&#147;Candida score&#148;...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(4): 203-207, 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75056</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Implica el aislamiento de Candida spp. en muestras intraabdominales de pacientes críticos la necesidad de tratamiento antifúngico?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10728^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d918^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
