<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-059020</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Achievement of therapeutic goals in patients with myocardial revascularization in Virgen Macarena&#146;s Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Myocardial revascularization is a well established therapeutic intervention in coronary disease. The aim of the present study was to asses the achievement of the therapeutic goals recommended by the Adult Treatment Panel (ATP) III in patients with high risk for cardiovascular disease. Material and methods. We have studied 131 patients with a previous aorto-coronary bypass. In order to evaluate their cardiovascular risk and their pharmacological treatment, we have followed the patients 3, 6 and 12 months after the intervention. In addition to the medical history, we measured blood pressure, waist circumference, weight, height, body mass index (BMI), smokers, non smokers, haematology test, biochemical and cardiovascular profile. To complete the cardiovascular study we determined cholesterol fractions. The serum samples were ultracentrifuged to separate lipoproteins, and measure the levels of apolipoproteins (Apo) A1 and B 100 and several markers of cardiovascular risk and inflammation such as lipoprotein (Lp) (a), ultra sensitive C reactive protein (CPR), fibrinogen and homocysteine. Results. The levels of lowdensity lipoprotein (LDL) decreased from 142 mg/dl to 108 mg/dl and Apo B levels from 101 mg/dl to 79 mg/dl. The therapeutic goals recommended by ATP III were achieved by 44% of patients, that is a cLDL &lt; 100 mg/dL. We observed changes in other risk factors in our population study. The number of overweight patients decreased from 42% to 12%, and obese patients from 27% to 10%. Those patients with a waist circumference greater than 102 cm decreased from 50% to 19.64% and 58% of the smokers gave it up. Conclusions. The patients showed a significant reduction in the major risk factors with no changes in the homocysteine and Lp (a) levels. After treatment with statins and/or statins- ezetimibe) 44% of the patients achieved the therapeutic goals suggested by ATP III. The combined treatment (statins + ezetimibe) seems to be more effective than therapy with statins only (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrobas, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oribe, Ana I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barco, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Holgado, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hijano, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia, Reyes de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabiani, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Jr, Juan Manuel de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Riejos, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La revascularización miocárdica es una intervención terapéutica perfectamente establecida en pacientes con enfermedad coronaria. El objetivo del presente estudio es el de comprobar el cumplimiento terapéutico de los objetivos marcados por el Adult Treatment Panel (ATP) III para una población de muy alto riesgo cardiovascular y la evolución de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Material y métodos. Se han estudiado un total de 131 pacientes intervenidos de bypass aortocoronario. Para la evaluación de su riesgo y posterior tratamiento, fueron atendidos a los 3, 6 y 12 meses tras la intervención. Independientemente de otros datos necesarios para la historia clínica, a todos se les determinó los valores de presión arterial, perímetro de cintura, peso, talla e índice de masa corporal, hábito tabáquico y hemograma, un perfil bioquímico y un perfil de riesgo cardiovascular que incluye, además de los habituales, una ultracentrifugación para la separación de las lipoproteínas, los valores de apolipoproteína (apo) A-I y B-100 y diversos marcadores de riesgo e inflamación como la lipoproteína(a) (Lp[a]), proteína C reactiva ultrasensible (PCR), el fibrinógeno y la homocisteína. Resultados. Los valores de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) descendieron desde 142 a 108 mg/dl y los de apo B desde 101 a 79 mg/dl. El 44% de los pacientes cumplió los objetivos marcados por el ATP III, es decir, cLDL  102 cm, presente en el 50% de los pacientes, descendió al 19,64%, y los fumadores, que abarcaban el 58% de los pacientes, abandonaron en su totalidad el hábito tabáquico. Conclusiones. Tras el tratamiento con estatinas y/o estatinas-ezetimiba y modificación de los hábitos de vida, los pacientes experimentan una reducción significativa de los principales factores de riesgo a excepción de la homocisteína y de la Lp(a); el 44% de los pacientes estudiados cumple los objetivos marcados por el ATP III. Por otro lado, el tratamiento combinado estatina-ezetimiba parece producir mayores beneficios que el tratamiento con estatinas en monoterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 1-7, ene. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-059020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de objetivos terapéuticos en pacientes con revascularización miocárdica en el Área Virgen Macarena de Sevilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
