<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104755</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparing the diets of elderly people living in different types of institution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study compares the diets administered to elderly persons living in 5 public and 10 private homes over a 15-day period. For each day of the study period, the following variables were recorded: the nutritional composition of the meals, the amount of each food type used and how it was cooked, the amounts of food types served to men and women, the number of meals prepared but not served and the number of meals served but not consumed by men and women. All the nutritional variables recorded were within recommended values such that the diets were well-balanced and sufficiently varied. All meals were also well accepted by the consumers and well-served. The quality of the different foods was good, although differences were observed in the use of fresh or frozen foods or how the food was prepared foods depending on the type of home. The modes of food preparation were generally not the most recommendable, since stews, fried food and sauces were significantly preferred to grilled, boiled or oven-cooked foods. Statistical analysis grouped the diets on a principal component plot as follows: those administered by public institutions in the area of predominating fibre and cholesterol, the diets of intermediate-cost homes in the zone of predominant fat and therefore greater number of kilocalories, while the meals supplied by intermediate to high cost homes grouped in the zone of high protein contents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tesedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tesedo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se lleva a cabo un estudio de las dietas suministradas en 5 residencias públicas y 10 residencias privadas de personas mayores durante un ciclo de 15 días. Se controla la composición nutricional de la ingesta para cada día del ciclo, la cantidad de cada alimento utilizado y la forma de cocinarlo, la cantidad de alimentos servidos a hombres y mujeres, la cantidad de alimentos preparados pero no servidos y la cantidad de alimentos servidos y no consumidos por hombres y mujeres. Todos los parámetros nutricionales obtenidos están dentro de los valores recomendados, por lo que el estudio indica que las dietas son equilibradas, la variabilidad de alimentos adecuada, el grado de aceptación bueno y el servicio correcto. La calidad de los alimentos es buena, si bien, según el tipo de residencia hay diferencias en la utilización de alimentos frescos o congelados y en las preparaciones. En todo caso las preparaciones no son habitualmente las más recomendadas, ya que se prefiere de forma muy significativa, los guisos, los fritos y las salsas frente a la plancha el hervido o el horno. El análisis estadístico mediante componentes principales agrupa las residencias públicas en la zona de predominio de la fibra y el colesterol, las privadas de coste medio en la zona de predominio de las grasas ypor tanto de mayor número de kilocalorías, mientras que las de coste medio alto se agrupan en la zona de las proteínas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;31(3): 35-44, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de las dietas suministradas en distintos tipos de residencias de la tercera edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
