<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81017</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the frequency food consumption that isfatty acid source w-3 (EPA and DHA) in Spanish pregnantwomen during the first trimester of the gestation.Materials and Methods: Descriptive study was conducted ineight hundred and eighty eight pregnant women in the firsttrimester of pregnancy coming from the Centers of Health ofeigtheen Spanish provinces were interviewed during period2003-2004. The doctors and/or matrons made an interviewthat included the socioeconomic data and a questionnaireof frequency of food consumption.Results: The average age was of 32.1 years (D.E.: 4.67) ina rank of 16 to 48 years. The cold-water fish was locatedfar distant of the first positions between the preferences ofthe pregnant women occupying the position number 21with a 4% and the seventh place between the foods thatless please with a 7%.Conclusions: In the population of pregnant womenstudied, the rich food ingestion in w-3, such as coldwaterfish. fish, less consume it of once to the monthmore of a 40% of the women. The cold-water fish isnot within foods preferred by the studied populationand occupies the seventh position between the foodsthat less please(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lluís Serra-Majem, Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Pérez, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ballart, Joan D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la frecuencia de consumo de alimentos queson fuente de ácidos grasos &amp;#969;-3 (EPA y DHA) en mujeres embarazadasespañolas durante el primer trimestre de la gestación.Material y Métodos: Estudio de campo, descriptivo, en 888mujeres embarazadas en el primer trimestre de gestaciónprocedentes de los Centros de Salud de 18 provinciasespañolas, durante el período 2003-2004. Los médicosy/o matronas realizaron una entrevista que incluía losdatos socio-económicos y un cuestionario de frecuencia deconsumo de alimentos.Resultados: La edad media fue de 32,1 años (D.E.: 4,67) enun rango de 16 a 48 años. El pescado azul quedó ubicadomuy distante de los primeros puestos entre las preferenciasde las mujeres embarazadas ocupando el puesto número21 con un 4% y el séptimo lugar entre los alimentos quemenos gustan con un 7%.Conclusión: En la población de embarazadas estudiada, laingesta de alimentos ricos en &amp;#969;-3, tales como los pescadosazules, lo consumen menos de una vez al mes más de un40% de las mujeres. El pescado azul no está dentro de losalimentos preferidos por la población estudiada y ocupa laséptima posición entre los alimentos que menos gustan(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;14(1): 42-48, ene.-mar.2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de alimentos ricos en ácidos grasos omega-3: Estudio en mujeres españolas durante el primer trimestre del embarazo (2002-2004)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
