<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161064</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coadministration of histamine H1 antagonist and oral anticoagulants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Indications for oral anticoagulation and antihistamine H1 antagonists therapies are increasingly. So, it is easy to find individuals who need both treatments. The unknowledgment about possible interferences of antihistamines over acenocumarin often makes to avoid them at the same time. A review on a population receiving anticoagulation on a Therapeutic Center allowed us to verify disorders secondary to the association of antihistamines into their therapeutic scheme. Loratadine, ebastine and cetirizine show similar records of interaction into acenocumarin pharmacokinetics, probably due to a liver enzymatic induction on the anticoagulant drug, producing a decrease on INR values in which anticoagulation is measured. This could make necessary to increase temporally acenocumarin dose. During coadministration no thromboembolic event nor bleeding were registered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Callejo, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Julián, EN</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velert Vila, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las indicaciones terapéuticas de los anticoagulantes orales y los antihistaminícos H1 son cada vez mayores. Por ello no resulta infrecuente encontrar individuos que precisan ambos tratamientos. El desconocimiento de las potenciales interacciones medicamentosas de los antagonistas de la histamina sobre el acenocumarol hace que a menudo se evite su asociación. La revisión de una población atendida en un Control de Terapéutica Anticoagulante nos ha permitido objetivar los trastornos originados por la introducción de algún antihistamínico en su esquema terapéutico. Loratadina, ebastina y cetirizina presentaron índices similares de interacción en el perfil farmacocinético del acenocumarol, probablemente por inducción enzimática hepática inactivadora del anticoagulante, lo que originó una disminución en los valores de INR con los que se mide el nivel de hipocoagulabilidad. Ello puede hacer necesario elevar temporalmente las dosis de acenocumarol. Durante el tratamiento sincrónico no se registró ningún evento tromboembólico ni hemorrágico en los pacientes seguidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;52(5): 442-445, jun. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empleo simultáneo de antihistamínicos H1 y anticoagulantes orales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6793^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
