<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81875</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantitative evaluation of SPECT with FP-CIT. Importance of the reference area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study is to compare several uptake indexes between specific and non-specific activity to determine the existence of degenerative Parkinsonism according to different reference areas. Material and methods. A total of 46 patients (23 men and 23 women), randomly selected from individuals referred to our center with a movement disorder, were included in the study. Mean age was 70.2±10.2 years (41&#150;87). The uptake indexes were obtained through the areas of interest (ROIs) located in the striate (specific uptake) and other reference ROIs located in areas with different concentrations of serotonin receptors: low-cerebellum, medium-occipital cortex and high-midbrain. Results. A high linear correlation was found between indexes having low and medium concentration of serotonin receptors. The ROC curve analysis shows an area under the curve of 0.874, 0.886 and 0.739 and regression coefficients of 5.41, 6.62 and 3.41, respectively for the striatum/cerebellum (E/C), striatum/occipital (E/O) and striatum midbrain (E/M) indexes. Optimal cutoff for E/O (1.35), index with the best behavior, provides a sensitivity of 0.84 and specificity of 0.89. Conclusion. The reference area selected may alter the predictive power of the different indexes to determine the existence of a degenerative Parkinsonism(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Hoyuela, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amrani Raissouni, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Lozano, S. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez del Valle Torres, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Viedma, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo del presente estudio es comparar diversos índices de captación entre actividad específica/inespecífica para determinar la existencia de parkinsonismo degenerativo teniendo en cuenta diferentes áreas de referencia. Material y métodos. Se incluyen a 46 pacientes (23 hombres y 23 mujeres) seleccionados de forma aleatoria de los sujetos remitidos a nuestro centro por presentar un trastorno del movimiento. La edad media de los mismos fue de 70,2±10,2 años (41&#150;87). Los índices de captación se realizan mediante ROI localizadas en estriados (captación específica) y otras de referencia situadas en zonas con baja concentración de receptores serotoninérgicos (cerebelo), media (corteza occipital) y alta (mesencéfalo). Resultado. Se aprecia una elevada correlación entre índices con baja y media concentración de receptores serotoninérgicos. El análisis mediante curvas ROC muestra un área bajo la curva de 0,874, 0,886 y 0,739 y unos coeficientes de regresión de 5,41, 6,62 y 3,41 respectivamente para los índices estriado/cerebelo (E/C), estriado/occipital (E/O) y estriado/mesencéfalo (E/M). El punto de corte óptimo para el estriado/occipital (1,35), índice con mejor comportamiento, aporta una sensibilidad de 0,84 y una especificidad de 0,89. Conclusión. El área de referencia seleccionada, puede alterar la capacidad predictiva de los distintos índices a la hora de determinar la existencia de un parkinsonismo degenerativo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;29(5): 246-250, sept.-oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración cuantitativa del SPECT con FP-CIT. Importancia del área de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34223^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
