<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108034</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological problems have been and continue to be pathologized, converted to psychopathology. This article gives a brief historical reference to this process and a critical analysis of its logical and epistemological inadequacies and an analysis of the problems posed to their understanding and solution. From the paradigms of psychology, its posible make a paradigm shift and offer an no psychopathological alternative that allows understand the significance of the problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Méndez, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa Cabanillas, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los problemas psicológicos han sido y siguen siendo patologizados, convertidos en psicopatología. El artículo hace una breve referencia histórica a este proceso y un análisis crítico de sus insuficiencias lógicas y epistemológicas y un análisis de los inconvenientes que plantea para su comprensión y solución. Desde los paradigmas de la psicología cabe hacer un cambio de paradigma y ofrecer una alternativa no psicopatológica que permita comprender el significado de los problemas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;33(3): 162-171, sept.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desvelar el secreto de los enigmas despatologizar la psicología clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1544^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14544</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
