<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85432</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interterritorial inequalities in compensation for occupational diseases in Spain from 1990&#150;2007</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo determine the reporting pattern and trends for occupational diseases by autonomous communities in Spain between 1990 and 2007.MethodsCases were obtained from the Ministry of Labor and Social Affairs, and the number of workers was obtained from the National Institute of Statistics. A principal components analysis was used to explain the data structure. Adjusted annual incidence rates were computed and relative risk is shown in maps.ResultsThe number of reported occupational diseases remained constant from 1990 to 2005 in all the autonomous communities, except for minor occupational diseases not leading to sick leave (accounting for 99% of the total), which increased. From 2006&#150;07, reported rates decreased to almost half: 17,061 cases in 2007 versus 30,030 in 2005. Both the increase and the decrease in incidence were observed in all autonomous communities, but with distinct values and slopes. As revealed by the principal components analysis, all the autonomous communities showed the same time pattern, except Asturias. Northern Spain showed the highest rates, which cannot be explained by factors such as age, sex, economic activity or occupation.ConclusionsThe social security system is not compensating the complex and chronic diseases that are prevalent today. Despite improvements in disease reporting from 1990&#150;2005, the decrease observed from 2006&#150;07 and, above all, the gap among autonomous communities show that provision is not working with equity, generating inequality and lack of cohesion and posing a challenge for the definition of efficient prevention policies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Gómez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañeda López, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoConocer el patrón de declaración y las tendencias por comunidades autónomas (CCAA) de las enfermedades profesionales en España en los años 1990 a 2007.MétodosLos casos se obtuvieron del Ministerio de Trabajo y Asuntos Sociales, y los trabajadores del Instituto Nacional de Estadística. Para explicar la estructura de los datos se utiliza el análisis de componentes principales. Se calculan las tasas de incidencia anuales ajustadas y se representa el riesgo relativo en mapas.ResultadosEl incremento en la declaración de las enfermedades profesionales es constante desde 1990 hasta 2005 en todas las CCAA, pero sólo aumentan los casos leves y sin baja, que sumaron el 99%. En 2006&#150;2007 la declaración desciende casi a la mitad: 17.061 casos en 2007 frente a 30.030 en 2005. Tanto el incremento como el descenso de la incidencia se observa en todas las CCAA, pero con valores y pendientes diferentes. El análisis de componentes principales muestra que Asturias presenta una evolución temporal diferente del resto de CCAA. Se observa un patrón en que destaca la elevada declaración en el norte del país, sin que factores tales como la edad, el sexo, la actividad económica y la ocupación expliquen las diferencias.ConclusionesEl sistema de seguridad social no está compensando enfermedades complejas y crónicas, prevalentes hoy día. A pesar de la mejora en la declaración de las enfermedades profesionales entre los años 1990 y 2005, el retroceso observado en 2006&#150;2007, y sobre todo la brecha entre CCAA, alertan de que la prestación no está funcionado con equidad, lo que genera desigualdad y falta de cohesión, y supone un reto para la definición de políticas de prevención ef(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(5): 373-379, sep. -oct. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85432</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualdades interterritoriales en la compensación de las enfermedades profesionales en España de 1990 a 2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30878^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
