<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152377</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The predictive ability of assertiveness in drug addicts relapse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to examine the effect of assertiveness and severity of drug addiction on the risk of relapse among drug addicts during a six months treatment. 90 Drug addicts completed the Research Interview on Addictive Behavior and the Rathus Assertiveness Schedule (RAS). The results showed that global assertiveness and Confrontation (a dimension of the RAS) are directly related to the risk of relapse, indicating that the higher the scores on these two variables the greater the risk of relapse. Other dimensions of the RAS (Defense of Rights and Personal Interests, Avoidance of Personal Confrontation, and Spontaneity) and the chronicity of drug use showed an inversed relationship to the risk of relapse, indicating that the higher the scores on those dimensions and on the chronicity of drug use the lower the risk of relapse. These results suggest caution when including assertion training for relapse prevention in drug addiction, and advise also caution when choosing the assessment instruments for assertiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Fernández, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda, Mª Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Isabel C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Torrecillas, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el efecto de la asertividad y de la gravedad del consumo de drogas en el riesgo de recaída (a los seis meses) en dos grupos (abstinencia vs. recaída) que han recibido tratamiento. Participaron 90 drogodependientes que rellenaron la &#147;Entrevista de investigación acerca del comportamiento adictivo&#148; y el &#147;Inventario de asertividad de Rathus&#148; (RAS). Encontramos que la asertividad global y la dimensión de Confrontación (del RAS) estaban directamente relacionadas con el riesgo de recaída, indicando que a mayores puntuaciones en asertividad y confrontación mayor es el riesgo de recaída. Otras dimensiones del RAS (Defensa de los derechos e intereses personales, Evitación de enfrentamientos personales y Espontaneidad), así como la cronicidad del consumo de drogas mostraron una relación inversa con el riesgo de recaída, indicando que a mayores puntuaciones en estas dimensiones de asertividad y mayor cronicidad de consumo menor riesgo de recaída. Estos resultados señalan la importancia de analizar qué entrenamiento asertivo realizamos para prevenir las recaídas en las drogodependencias y la elección de instrumentos de evaluación para la asertividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(3): 603-616, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La capacidad predictiva de la asertividad en las recaídas de los drogodependientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
