<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150802</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in patients with spinal cord injury and pressure ulcers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the prevalence of pressure ulcers in patients with spinal cord injuries and analyze their quality of life. Methods: A descriptive cross-sectional study conducted in a specialized institution for rehabilitation of patients with major disabilities. WHOQOL-bref (0 to 100; higher scores indicate better quality of life), and a profile form were used for data collection. Results: Of the 118 patients with spinal cord injuries admitted during the data collection, 58 (49.1%) had pressure ulcers. Among these, 40 answered the instruments. Analysis of the WHOQOLbref showed very low score for the Physical Domain (53.04), followed by the psychological (60.94) and environmental (63.52) domains. The social domain was the only one with a satisfactory score (70.21). Conclusion: A high prevalence of pressure ulcers among people with spinal cord injuries was observed. The evaluation of quality of life elucidates a significant dissatisfaction of the participants, especially regarding the physical domain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mota, Dalete</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, Milainy Barbosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar la prevalencia de úlceras por presión en portadores de traumatismos de la médula espinal y analizar su qcalidad de vida. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal realizado en una institución especializada en rehabilitación de personas con grandes incapacidades. Para colecta se aplicaron el WHOQOL-bref (0 a 100; cuanto mayor la puntuación, mejor calidad de vida) y cuestionario de caracterización sociodemográfica y clínica. Resultados: De los 118 portadores de traumatismos de la médula espinal ingresados en el periodo de colecta de datos, 58 (49,1%) presentaron úlceras por presión. De estos, 40 respondieron los instrumentos. El análisis del WHOQOL-bref evidenció puntuación muy baja en el Dominio físico (53,04), seguido de los dominios psicológico (60,94) y ambiental (63,52). El único dominio con puntuación satisfactoria fue el social (70,21). De modo general, estas puntuaciones son preocupantes. Conclusión: Se observó una elevada prevalencia de úlceraspor presión entre personas con traumatismos de la médula espinal. La evaluación de la calidad de vida revela una insatisfacción significativa de los participantes, principalmente respecto a los aspectos físicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(42): 13-21, abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en portadores de lesión medular con úlceras por presión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
