<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130166</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">QT interval heterogeneities induced through local epicardial warming/cooling. An experimental study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Abnormal QT interval durations and dispersions have been associated with increased risk of ventricular arrhythmias. The present study examines the possible arrhythmogenic effect of inducing QT interval variations through local epicardial cooling and warming. Methods. In 10 isolated rabbit hearts, the temperatures of epicardial regions of the left ventricle were modified in a stepwise manner (from 22 °C to 42 °C) with simultaneous electrogram recording in these regions and in others of the same ventricle. QT and activation-recovery intervals were determined during sinus rhythm, whereas conduction velocity and ventricular arrhythmia induction were determined during programmed stimulation. This multicenter retrospective study involved patients from the UMBRELLA national registry who underwent replacement due to defibrillator battery depletion. The incidence of ventricular arrhythmias was determined via remote monitoring. Risk factors for sustained ventricular arrhythmia after replacement were analyzed. Results. In the area modified from baseline temperature (37 °C), the QT (standard deviation) was prolonged with maximum hypothermia (195 [47] vs 149 [12] ms; P &lt; .05) and shortened with hyperthermia (143 [18] vs 152 [27] ms; P &lt; .05). The same behavior was displayed for the activation-recovery interval. The conduction velocity decreased with hypothermia and increased with hyperthermia. No changes were seen in the other unmodified area. Repetitive responses were seen in 5 experiments, but no relationship was found between their occurrence and hypothermia or hyperthermia (P &gt; .34). Conclusions. In the experimental model employed, local variations in the epicardial temperature modulate the QT interval, activation-recovery interval, and conduction velocity. Induction of heterogeneities did not promote ventricular arrhythmia occurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cebrián, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millet, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roses, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Such, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tormos, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorro, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberola, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarzoso, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guill, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Such-Miquel, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La duración anormal del intervalo QT o su dispersión se han asociado con un incremento en el riesgo de arritmias ventriculares. Se analiza el posible efecto arritmogénico de sus variaciones inducidas mediante enfriamiento y calentamiento local epicárdico. Métodos. En 10 corazones aislados de conejo, se modificó escalonadamente la temperatura de una región epicárdica del ventrículo izquierdo (22 a 42 °C), registrando simultáneamente los electrogramas en dicha zona y en otra del mismo ventrículo. En ritmo sinusal, se determinó el QT y el intervalo de recuperación de la activación y, mediante estimulación programada, la velocidad de conducción y la inducción de arritmias ventriculares. Resultados. En la zona modificada respecto al valor basal (37 °C), el QT se prolongó en hipotermia máxima (195 ± 47 frente a 149 ± 12 ms; p &lt; 0,05) y se acortó en hipertermia (143 ± 18 frente a 152 ± 27 ms; p &lt; 0,05). El intervalo de recuperación de la activación tuvo el mismo comportamiento. La velocidad de conducción disminuyó en hipotermia y aumentó en hipertermia. No hubo cambios en la otra zona. Se observaron respuestas repetitivas en cinco experimentos, pero no se encontró dependencia entre su aparición y las condiciones de hipotermia e hipertermia inducidas (p &gt; 0,34). Conclusiones. En el modelo experimental empleado, las variaciones locales de la temperatura epicárdica modulan el intervalo QT, el intervalo de recuperación de la activación y la velocidad de conducción. Las heterogeneidades inducidas no han favorecido la inducción de arritmias ventriculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(12): 993-998, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Heterogeneidades inducidas en el intervalo QT mediante enfriamiento/calentamiento epicárdico local. Estudio experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19558^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1151^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19558^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
