<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81964</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effect of unrealistic optimism in the intention of the use of the condom as method of prevention of non-wanted pregnancies and sexually transmitted diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Unrealistic optimism (UO) occurs when a person considers that his or her probability to go through an unpleasant or dangerous event is lower than that in others. It is a cognitive bias that can endanger the effectiveness of health care programmes. This article explores the existence of UO related to the use of the condom in situations of non-wanted pregnancies (NWP) and sexually transmitted diseases (STD). We have used a modified version of the questionnaire designed by Zakay (1996) and later adjusted by Fernández-Castro, Limonero, Rovira y Albaina (2002) (2002) in a sample of 292 college students with more than 20 years old (181 women and 111 men). Our results confirm the existence of the UO in the use of the condom, finding a greater bias in NWP&#146;s situations than in STD. Specifically, we found that study subjects believed they were less liable to go through a NWP if not using the condom (or if it tore) than other people. Regarding STD, they also believed that their probability of being infected without using the condom was lower than in others. Therefore, we found that men are more prone to UO than women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons-Salvador, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles Díaz, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Salazar, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El optimismo no realista (ONR) se produce cuando una persona estima que su probabilidad de ser víctima de un suceso desagradable o peligroso es menor que la de otros. Se trata de un sesgo cognitivo que puede comprometer la eficacia de los programas de promoción de la salud. Este artículo analiza la existencia del ONR en la intención de uso del condón como método de prevención de embarazos no deseados (END) y de enfermedades de transmisión sexual (ETS). Para ello, se ha utilizado una adaptación del cuestionario de Zakay (1996) y Fernández-Castro, Limonero, Rovira y Albaina (2002) en una muestra de 292 universitarios con más de 20 años (181 mujeres y 111 hombres). Nuestros resultados confirman la existencia del ONR en la intención del uso del condón, siendo mayor el sesgo ante las situaciones de END que ante las ETS. En concreto, los sujetos creen tener menos probabilidades que otros de sufrir un END tanto si no utilizan el condón como si, al utilizarlo, éste se rompe. También creen tener menos probabilidades que otros de contagiarse con una ETS cuando no usan el condón. El efecto del ONR es mayor en los hombres que en las mujeres  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;26(2): 310-317, jul.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El efecto del optimismo no realista en la intención de uso del condón como método de prevención de embarazos no deseados y de enfermedades de transmisión sexual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
