<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128353</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of stem cells from nucleus pulposus of cervical intervertebral disc and compared with bone marrow cells from the same patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the presence of mesenchymal cells in the nucleus pulposus (NP) of cervical discs and characterize them in comparison ot those obtained from the bone marrow of the same subjects. Patients and methods: We have performed a descriptive study with 14 patients requiring cervical fusion surgery. The presence of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) were analyzed in the NP from the disk and compared qualitatively with the bone marrow (BM) of the same patients. MSC were isolated and expanded for both NP and MO. We performed in vitro differentiation studies of mesenchymal cells from both sources, into osteogenic and adipogenic lines, and flow cytometric immunophenotyping. Results: We got differentiation towards both cell types, although adipocyte differentiation of disc-derived cells was decreased compared to those from BM. There were no differences in immunophenotypic markers. Cells from both sources have immunophenotypic markers characteristic of mesenchymal cells. Conclusion: The NP of degenerated cervical disc contains mesenchymal stem cells. These cells are quite similar to BM cells, with the exception of a diminished adipogenic differentiation capacity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Díaz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muntión, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pescador Hernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Guijo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la presencia de células mesenquimales en el núcleo pulposo de disco intervertebral cervical y caracterizarlas comparativamente con las obtenidas de médula ósea de los mismos sujetos. Pacientes y metodología: Hemos realizado un estudio descriptivo con 14 pacientes que precisaron cirugía de artrodesis cervical. Se analizó la presencia de células mesenquimales (CSM) en el núcleo pulposo (NP) del disco, comparándolas cualitativamente con las de médula ósea (MO) de los mismos pacientes. Se aislaron y expandieron CSM, tanto de NP como de MO. Se realizaron los estudios de diferenciación multilineal in vitro de las células mesenquimales de ambas fuentes, hacia osteoblasto y adipocito, y caracterización inmunofenotípica por citometría de flujo. Resultados: Las células de ambos orígenes se diferencian in vitro hacia ambos tipos celulares, si bien la diferenciación adipocítica de las células procedentes del disco fue menor que las procedentes de MO. Tampoco se han demostrado diferencias en los marcadores inmunofenotípicos. Las células de ambas fuentes poseen los marcadores inmunofenotípicos característicos de las células mesenquimales. Conclusión: El NP de disco vertebral cervical degenerado contiene células troncales mesenquimales. Estas células son similares a las células de MO, con la excepción de su capacidad disminuida de diferenciación adipogénica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);25(3): 127-135, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de células madre de núcleo pulposo de disco intervertebral cervical y comparación con células de médula ósea de los mismos pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
