<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044962</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Difficulty of epidural puncture for obstetric analgesia: risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Predicting technical difficulties in performingan epidural block can affect the anesthesiologist'schoice of technique or decisions about whoshould carry it out. Our aim was to determine patientcharacteristics associated with difficulty in performingan epidural block for obstetric analgesia.MATERIAL AND METHODS: We designed a prospectiveobservational study in 540 pregnant women who requestedepidural analgesia for obstetric labor. Patient characteristics(age, weight, height), anatomical features(body constitution, visible and/or palpable spinalapophyses, structural anomalies), technical features(number of attempts, repositioning of the needle), anesthesiologist'sexperience (resident or staff), block success,time taken to accomplish the procedure, and obstetricalvariables (parity, gestational age, cervical dilatation).RESULTS: The factor that best correlates with puncturedifficulty in the obstetric patient is the presence ofvisible or palpable spinal apophyses and palpation priorto carrying out the block. Factors like weight, body constitution,or anesthesiologist's experience seem to influencethe rate of success or failure of the epidural block forobstetric analgesia, although to a lesser degree.CONCLUSIONS: The most important factor for predictingsuccess of an epidural block for obstetric analgesia inour practice is the presence of palpable spinal apophyses</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palencia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La dificultad técnica prevista antes derealizar un bloqueo epidural, puede influir en las decisionesdel anestesiólogo en cuanto a qué técnica y quiéndebe realizarla. Nuestro objetivo es evaluar qué característicasde la paciente obstétrica influyen para predecirla dificultad técnica del bloqueo.MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Diseñamos un estudio observacionalprospectivo en 540 mujeres gestantes a términoque solicitaron analgesia epidural para trabajo de parto.Se registraron datos demográficos (edad, peso, talla),anatómicos (hábito corporal, apófisis espinosas visiblesy/o palpables, anomalías anatómicas), técnica (númerode intentos, re-direcciones de la aguja), experiencia delanestesiólogo (residente o adjunto), éxito del bloqueo,tiempo de realización del bloqueo y variables obstétricas(paridad, edad gestacional y dilatación cervical).RESULTADOS: El factor que mejor se correlaciona conla dificultad de la punción en la paciente obstétrica, es lapresencia de apófisis espinosas visibles y/o palpables a lainspección y palpación previa a la realización del bloqueo.Factores como el peso, hábito corporal o la experienciadel anestesiólogo, parecen influir a la hora depredecir el éxito o fracaso del bloqueo epidural paraanalgesia obstétrica, aunque en menor medidaCONCLUSIONES: En nuestra población obstétrica paraanalgesia de parto, el factor más importante para la predicciónde un bloqueo con éxito es el hecho de que lasapófisis espinosas sean palpables</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;53(3): 139-144, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044962</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a la dificultad de punción epidural en analgesia obstétrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10361</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
