<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128002</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consumption of energy drink on college</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the consumption of energy drinks in students of the University of La Laguna (Tenerife) and to evaluate the intake to caffeine derived from such beverages. Methods: An anonymous surveys of 307 college students (ages 18-30) from 18 faculties of ULL was conducted. Among the variables analyzed were: knowledge of the composition of these drinkd, consumption habits, and the combination with alcohol and drugs. A systematic bibliographic revision was done using the MEDLINE/Pub-Med, Scielo, Science Direct and Ebscohot databases. Results: 82.74% of university respondents have consumed, at least once in their life, such beverages, although only just over half the students know their composition (58.31%). Consumption of these energy drinks in university students is not frequent as 88.60% reported a non-weekly rate of consumption.Consumption rises in periods of examinations reaching a prevalence of consumption of 33.33%. also, 24.21% of students reported that they consume energy drinks at time of leisure. 30.29% and 2.28% of respondents reported mixing the beverages with alcohol and other drugs, respectively. Conclusions: Consumption of enerfy drinks is widespread in the university population. Although consumption is not regular, an increase of its consumption was detected during examination times because students seek their energizing and stimulating effects. Most od ULL´s students are unaware of the composition of energy drinks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas Gómez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravelo Abreu, Aarón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Carracedo, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Fernández, Ángel J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Armendáriz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hardisson de la Torre, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revert Gironés, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Gómez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos; Estudiar el consumo de bebidas energizantes  (Energy drinks) en alumnos de la Universidad de La Laguna (Tenerife) y evaluar la ingesta de cafeína derivada de su consumo. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal a través de una encuesta anónima a 307 estudiantes universitarios (18-30 años) pertenecientes a 18 facultades de la ULL. El conocimiento de la composición de las bebidas energetizantes, los hábitos de consumo, y la combinación con alcohol y drogas fueron algunos de los ítems analizados. Asimismo, se efectuó una revisión bibliografía sistemática sobre cafeína y bebidas energizantes, en las bases  de datos de MEDLINE/Pub-Med, Scielo, Science Direct, EBscohost. Resultados; 82.74% de los universitarios encuestados han probado como mínimo una vez en su vida este tipo de bebidas, aqunue sólo algo más de la mitad de los alumnos conoce su composición (58.31%). El consumo de estas bebidas energizantes en nuestra población universitaria no puede considerarse habitual ya que un 88.60% declara no consumir semanalmente. El consumo aumenta en los períodos de exámenes alcanzando una prevalencia de consumo del 33.33%. El 24.2% de los estudiantes manifiesta consumirlas en momentos de ocio. El 30.29% y el 2.28% de los encuestados afirmó mezclarlas con alcohol y otras drogas, respectivamente. Conclusiones: El consumo de bebidas energizantes están instaurado en la población universitaria. Aunque el consumo no es habitual se observa un incremento del consumo en época de exámenes ya que los estudiantes buscan los efectos energizantes y/o estimulantes. La mayoría de los universitario desconocen la composición de estas bebidas energizantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;19(4): 201-206, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de bebidas energizantes en universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
