<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157844</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of smoking habit on mobile genetic elements</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is known that smoking causes alterations in different parts of the body that entail appearance of cancer. The retrotransposons seem to be involved both at the onset and in the evolution of this disease. It has also been seen that they contribute to the fact that certain treatments against cancer, such as immunotherapy, stop being effective. In this work, we analyze how the mobile genetic elements are affected by the different compounds present in tobacco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Varela, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claros Díaz, MG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se sabe que el tabaco produce alteraciones en distintas partes del organismo que conllevan la aparición del cáncer. Los retrotransposones parecen estar implicados tanto en el inicio como en la evolución de esta enfermedad. Se ha visto que también contribuyen a que determinados tratamientos contra el cáncer, como la inmunoterapia, dejen de ser eficaces. En este trabajo analizamos cómo se ven afectados los elementos genéticos móviles por los distintos compuestos presentes en el tabaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;18(3): 155-164, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia del tabaquismo en los elementos genéticos móviles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10108^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8846^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32049^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29554^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8929</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32049^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33904^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
