<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129822</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascular complications after pelvic rami fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The case is presented of a 78 year-old patient who suffered a right ileo- and ischiopubic rami fracture after a casual fall. A few hours later, she presented with sudden abdominal pain and hypotension. Imaging test showed extraperitoneal hemorrhage with active bleeding and hemodynamic compromise. The progressive worsening, with anemia and hemodynamic instability, required her being sent to the reference hospital for selective embolization of the bleeding point. After embolization, the patient&amp;#769;s situation stabilized, and she was then able to sit down one week later. The fracture consolidated 3 months later. Although low-energy pelvic fractures by lateral compression do not usually present with complications, sometimes they require a strict control due to the potential risk of vascular injuries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lombardía, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz-Aparicio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Vaquero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 78 años que sufre fractura de ramas ilio e isquipubiana derechas tras caída casual. A las pocas horas presenta un cuadro de dolor abdominal brusco e hipotensión, siendo diagnosticada de hemorragia extraperitoneal con sangrado activo y repercusión hemodinámica. Ante el progresivo empeoramiento, con anemización e inestabilidad hemodinámica, es remitido al hospital de referencia, donde se realiza embolización selectiva del vaso sangrante. Tras la embolización, la paciente se estabiliza y permanece ingresada, comenzando sedestación una semana más tarde y con consolidación de las fracturas a los 3 meses. Las fracturas pélvicas de baja energía por compresión lateral suelen presentar escasas complicaciones, aunque precisan un control exhaustivo por el riesgo potencial de lesiones vasculares. Es estos casos suponen un riesgo vital, siendo la embolización selectiva del punto sangrante un método de control eficaz, que tampoco está exento de complicaciones graves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(6): 407-410, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicación vascular tras fractura de ramas pélvicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
