<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123948</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">46, XX (SRY +) male syndrome associated with Crohn disease. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To present the case of a patient showing male phenotype with testes and penis size slightly decreased, which was diagnosed with non-obstructive azoospermia. Review of the literature. Material and methods: Physical examination, hormonal profile, semen analysis, genital ultrasound scan, karyotype and cytogenetic microarray analysis (KaryoNIM). Results: Clinical examination showed a male phenotype with decreased size of testes  and penis and obesity. Hormonal determinations evidenced hypergonadotropic hypogonadism. The seminal study showed azoospermia and genital ultrasound a normal male genital tract. Karyotype 46,XX, normal woman, and the cytogenetic study showed the translocation of genetic material from chromosome Y to chromosome X, including the SRY gene. Testicular biopsy showed the presence of tubular hyalinization with mature Sertoli cells, absent germ line and pronounced hyperplasia of Leydig cells. Comments and conclusion: 46,XX male is a rare genetic condition of non-obstructive azoospermia. The association to autoimmune diseases needs to be clarified. Although sperm donation remains the only fertility treatment currently available multidisciplinary approach should be adopted in the management of 46,XX individuals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Raga, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastro, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monzó, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeu, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar el caso de un paciente de fenotipo masculino con testículos y pene de tamaño ligeramente disminuido diagnosticado de azoospermia no obstructiva. Revisión de la literatura. Material y métodos: Exploración física, perfil hormonal, espermiograma, ultrasonografía genital, cariotipo y análisis citogenético mediante microarrays KaryoNIM. Resultados: La exploración clínica mostró un fenotipo masculino con testes y pene disminuidos de tamaño y obesidad. Las determinaciones hormonales evidenciaron un hipogonadismo hipergonadotropo. El estudio seminal mostró una azoospermia y la ecografía genital un aparato genital masculino normal. El cariotipo fue 46,XX, normal de mujer, y el estudio citogenético mostró la traslocación de material genético del cromosoma Y al cromosoma X, incluyendo el gen SRY. La biopsia testicular evidenció la presencia de hialinización tubular con células de Sertoli maduras, sin línea germinal y acusada hiperplasia de células de Leydig. Comentarios y conclusión: El síndrome de varón con cariotipo 46,XX es una etiología inusual de azoospermia. Su asociación a patologías autoinmunes no está actualmente bien aclarada. Aunque la única opción disponible para tratar el problema reproductivo es el uso de semen de donante, el abordaje de estos pacientes debe ser multidisciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;31(2): 43-47, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de varón 46, XX (SRY +) asociado a Enfermedad de Crohn. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53978^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36332</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
