<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88859</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-Benefit Analysis of Amniotic Membrane Transplantation for Venous Ulcers of the Legs That Are Refractory to Conventional Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Standard compression therapy for venous ulcers of the legs does not promote healing. Although autografting accelerates tissue repair, it is difficult to use in patients with concomitant diseases or when multiple grafts are required. The amniotic membrane has been used as a covering material and promotes epithelialization, making it a good potential treatment option when autografts are not indicated. Objectives: To analyze the literature on the safety and efficacy of amniotic membrane grafting and compare the cost of currently available grafts (autografts, amniotic membrane grafts, and biocompatible skin substitutes) to promote tissue repair in venous ulcers. Material and methods: A systematic review of the literature on the use of amniotic membrane grafts for the treatment of venous ulcers was performed up to 2010. A cost-minimization analysis of direct healthcare costs was then performed (at 3 and 6 months). A sensitivity analysis was performed to confirm the stability of the results. Results: Only 1 study addressing safety and efficacy was identified. The cost-minimization analysis showed that autografts are always the least-expensive option (D 1053 compared with D 1825 for amniotic membrane grafts and D 5767 for biocompatible skin grafts). At 6 months, however, amniotic membrane grafts would have cost D 6765 less than the use of biocompatible skin substitutes. Conclusions: Despite having excellent therapeutic potential for the re-epithelialization of venous ulcers that do not respond to conventional treatment, amniotic membrane transplant remains an experimental therapy. Autograft is the most efficient treatment but amniotic membrane graft is less expensive than the use of biocompatible skin substitutes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alsina-Gibert, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedregosa-Fauste, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala-Blanco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Moreno, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampietro-Colom, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El tratamiento estándar compresivo de las úlceras venosas de extremidades inferiores no promueve la cicatrizacion. El autoinjerto es uno de los tratamientos que acelera la reparación tisular, sin embargo, su aplicación es difícil en pacientes pluripatológicos o cuando se requieren aplicaciones múltiples. La membrana amniótica se ha empleado como material de cobertura y como epitelizante, por lo que podría ser una buena opción terapéutica para cuando el autoinjerto no esté indicado. Objetivos: Analizar el estado de conocimiento científico sobre la seguridad y la eficacia de la membrana amniótica y comparar los costes de los injertos disponibles actualmente (autoinjertos, membrana amniótica y sustitutos cutáneos biocompatibles) para promover la reparación tisular de las úlceras venosas. Material y métodos: Se realizó una búsqueda y revisión sistemática de la literatura científica hasta marzo del 2010 sobre el uso de la membrana amniótica como tratamiento de las úlceras venosas. Asimismo, se realizó un análisis coste-minimización (horizonte temporal 3 y 6 meses). Se consideraron los costes directos sanitarios. Para comprobar la estabilidad de los resultados se llevó a cabo un análisis de sensibilidad. Resultados: Se identificó un único estudio sobre seguridad y eficacia. El análisis de costes mostró que el autoinjerto es siempre la opción más barata (1.053 D versus 1.825 D membrana amniótica, 5.767 D sustitutos cutáneos biocompatibles). A los 6 meses la membrana amniótica costaría 6.765 D menos que el uso de los sustitutos cutáneos biocompatibles. Conclusiones: El transplante de membrana amniótica para la reepitelización de úlceras venosas refractarias al tratamiento convencional es una opción terapéutica de gran potencial, pero aúnen estado experimental. El autoinjerto es el tratamiento más eficiente; pero la membrana amniótica es más económica que los sustitutos cutáneos biocompatibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(4): 284-288, mayo 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio coste-beneficio del trasplante de membrana amniótica para úlceras venosas de extremidades inferiores refractarias a tratamiento convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d665^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d665^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
