<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041359</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacotherapeutic follow-up of patients in community pharmacies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse pharmacist intervention (PI) resulting from the implementation of the Dáder Pharmacotherapeutic Follow-Up Program (PFU). Design. Descriptive study of the findings from the PFU program during the first year. Setting. Community pharmacists in area of the College of Pharmacists of the Province of Cordoba (Argentina). Participants. A total of 202 patients were included in the PFU, selected on the basis of the observed needs by each of the participating pharmacists. Principal measurements. From the resulting PI reports the sex and age were obtained and problems related to medication (PRM) were classified according to the Second Consensus of Granada. The method of resolving PRM, the number of medications used and the number of visits made to the pharmacy to resolve each of them. Results. 38 pharmacists participated and 108 patients were registered in the PI. The number of PI increased to 280, with 218 PRM resolved (77.9% effectiveness: 95% confidence interval [CI], 70.6-86.2). 25% of the PRM were resoled between the pharmacist and the patient and 75% required the participation of the doctor, the PI achieving an acceptance of 74.6% (95% CI, 67.8-82.6). Conclusions. A high percentage of resolving PRM was obtained, with a significant acceptance of the PI by the doctors, which demonstrates the feasibility of including community pharmacists in the medical team and the possibility that they could make a significant contribution in decreasing the morbility and mortality associated with medications by carrying out PFU activities</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sola, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Semería, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenllado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armando, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las intervenciones farmacéuticas (IF) resultantes de la aplicación del Programa Dáder de Seguimiento Farmacoterapéutico (SFT). Diseño. Estudio descriptivo de los hallazgos del programa de SFT durante el primer año. Emplazamiento. Farmacias comunitarias en el ámbito del Colegio de Farmacéuticos de la Provincia de Córdoba (Argentina). Participantes. Se incluyó a un total de 202 pacientes bajo SFT, cuya selección se basó en las necesidades observadas por cada uno de los farmacéuticos participantes. Mediciones principales. A partir del informe de las IF resultantes se consignaron el sexo y la edad de los pacientes y se clasificaron los problemas relacionados con los medicamentos (PRM) de acuerdo con el Segundo Consenso de Granada. Se registraron la modalidad de resolución de los PRM, el número de medicamentos utilizados y la cantidad de visitas a la farmacia necesarias para resolver cada uno de ellos. Resultados. Participaron 38 farmacéuticos y se registraron IF en 108 pacientes. La cantidad de IF ascendió a 280, con 218 PRM resueltos (efectividad del 77,9%; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 70,6-86,2). Un 25% de los PRM se resolvieron entre el farmacéutico y su paciente y un 75% requirieron la participación del médico, lográndose una aceptación de las IF del 74,6% (IC del 95%, 67,8-82,6). Conclusiones. Se obtuvo un elevado porcentaje de resolución de PRM, con una aceptación importante de las IF por parte de los médicos, lo que demuestra la factibilidad de insertar a los farmacéuticos comunitarios en el equipo de salud y la posibilidad de que éstos puedan efectuar una aportación significativa a la disminución de la morbilidad y mortalidad relacionadas con medicamentos por medio de la realización de actividades de SFT</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;36(3): 129-134, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041359</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento farmacoterapéutico de pacientes en farmacias comunitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
