<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64709</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vaginal microbiota, mainly comprised of Lactobacillus crispatus, L. jensenii and L. gasseri, protect the mucosa against the establishment of pathogenic microorganisms through three complementary mechanisms: a) specific adherence to the epithelium, which blocks colonization of pathogens, b) production of antimicrobial compounds, and c) co-aggregation with pathogens, which enhances their microbiocidal effect. Despite these mechanisms, vaginal microbiota are sometimes displaced by undesirable microorganisms, which is associated with the development of bacterial vaginosis, vaginitis due to Candida spp., trichomoniasis, and lower urinary tract infections. On rare occasions, lactobacilli cause disease, but exclusively in immunocompromised patients. The main conditions are bacteremia (about 50% of the cases) and endocarditis (30%). However, no genital pathology caused by lactobacilli has been reported. The mutualistic effect of lactobacilli suggests that instillation of these microorganisms might regenerate the vaginal ecosystem, thus eliminating the relapses associated with treatment of the infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Juan Evaristo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soberón, Nora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La microbiota vaginal, dominada por Lactobacillus crispatus, L. jensenii y L. gasseri, protege a la mucosa frente al establecimiento de microorganismos patógenos mediante tres mecanismos complementarios: a) la adherencia específica al epitelio, que bloquea su asentamiento, b) la producción de compuestos antimicrobianos y c) la coagregación con los patógenos, que potencia su efecto microbiocida. A pesar de ello, en ocasiones se ve desplazada por microorganismos indeseables, lo que se asocia con la aparición de vaginosis bacteriana, vaginitis por Candida spp., tricomoniasis e infecciones del tracto urinario inferior. Muy raramente, los lactobacilos causan patología, invariablemente en pacientes inmunodeprimidos. Los cuadros dominantes son bacteriemias (alrededor del 50% de los casos) y endocarditis (30%). Sin embargo, no se ha descrito patología genital por lactobacilos. El efecto mutualista de los lactobacilos sugiere que su instilación podría regenerar el ecosistema vaginal, eliminando las recidivas asociadas al tratamiento de la infección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(3): 160-167, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64709</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15023^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7954^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7954^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15025^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
