<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80961</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Basis: This article considers social participation as a key confrontation strategy that facilitates a person a person&#146;s adaptation to the retirement process. We distinguish, however, two types of social interaction that represent different styles of participation: associations and day centres. Following the "Transactional Model of Stress and Confrontation", developed by Lazarus and Folkman, our objective is to identify what variables defined in the study are associated with both forms of social participation. Method: We used a questionnaire that included the variables defined in this study to obtain the empirical information pursued. The sample used was composed of 348 retired people residing in Granada, of which 167 were members of associations and 181 were day centre users. Results: The logistic regression analysis applied shows that a high income, a high level of perceived social affective support, a high level of self-sufficiency and a low intensity in the evaluation of changes which occur in retirement are good predictors of associative participation. Conclusions: These results confirm the validity of the Transactional Model for establishing individual differences in the evaluation that people make of retirement, as well as in the resources they use to face this event (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Conde, M. del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En este trabajo consideramos la participación social como una estrategia de afrontamiento que facilita la adaptación de la persona cuando se jubila. Distinguimos, no obstante, dos espacios de actuación social que representan estilos diferentes de participación: el asociacionismo y los centros de día. Siguiendo el "Modelo Transaccional del Estrés y del Afrontamiento", desarrollado por Lazarus y Folkman, nuestro objetivo es identificar qué variables se asocian con estas dos formas de participación social. Método: Hemos empleado un cuestionario que incluye las variables definidas para obtener la información empírica perseguida. La muestra se compone de 167 miembros de asociaciones y 181 usuarios de centros de día, residentes en Granada. Resultados: El análisis de regresión logística aplicado pone de manifiesto que un alto nivel de ingresos, un elevado grado de apoyo social afectivo percibido, un alto nivel de autoeficacia y una baja intensidad en la valoración de los cambios sucedidos con la jubilación resultan buenos predictores de la participación asociativa. Conclusiones: Estos resultados confirman la validez del Modelo Transaccional para establecer diferencias en la valoración que las personas hacen de la jubilación así como en los recursos que suelen emplear para afrontar dicho acontecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;18(3): 113-118, jul.-sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80961</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recursos y estrategias para afrontar la jubilación. La participación social como opción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12594^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
