<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145096</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacoeconomic aspects of oral cytostatic agents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When validating oral chemotherapy, pharmacists should confirm the suitability and correctness of the prescription, applying the same safety standards as those used for parenteral cytostatic drugs. There are an increasing number of cancers for which orally administered drugs are available, which increases patient satisfaction as these drugs can be taken at home without the need to visit a hospital. As oral cytostatic treatments increase, so does the importance of ensuring optimal treatment compliance. The new oral cytostatic agents are less toxic, reduce indirect costs and imply less loss of time for patients and their families. However, the cost of these agents should be below a threshold acceptable for society. As an aid to decision making, pharmacoeconomic tools should be used (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poquet Jornet, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gasent Blesa, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera-Hueso, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peris Godoy, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la validación de la quimioterapia oral, el farmacéutico debe comprobar la idoneidad de la prescripción, así como la corrección de su contenido, aplicando los mismos estándares de seguridad para los citostáticos parenterales. Cada vez hay más cánceres que tienen disponibles tratamientos por vía oral, mejorando la satisfacción del paciente, ya que pueden tomarse en sus domicilios sin necesidad de visitar el hospital. A medida que se incrementen los tratamientos citostáticos por vía oral será mucho más importante asegurarse de que ese cumplimiento de los tratamientos sea lo más óptimo posible. Los nuevos citostáticos por vía oral son menos tóxicos, reducen los costes indirectos e implican una menor pérdida de tiempo para el paciente y sus cuidadores, pero sus costes deberían estar por debajo de un umbral aceptado por la sociedad. Para ayudar a esta toma de decisiones, deberemos emplear las herramientas que la farmacoeconomía pone en nuestras manos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;35(supl.2): 25-31, 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos farmacoeconómicos de los citostáticos orales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52851^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
