<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113441</identifier>
<setSpec>2013-6889</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To estimate the prevalence of use of drugs for the treatment of dementia during 2002-2011 period. Methods. Patients over 65 years old registered in the BIFAP database with at least one day of follow-up were selected. Patients with a diagnostic code «P70 Dementia» or with prescriptions of donepezil, rivastigmine, galantamine and mematin were indentified. In average 365 787 patients per year were analyzed. Results. Prevalence of dementia codification rose up from 2.97% to 4.17 %. Use of antidementia drugs increased from 0.86% to 2.40 % within the general population and from 23.13% al 41.12 % within patients with a diagnosis of dementia. The prevalence of combined therapy rose up from 1.69% in 2003 to 6.29 % in 2011. Donepezil was the most used drug. The use of rivastigmine and galantamine is more frequent within men over 75 years old with a diagnosis of dementia than women. After 85 years old, there is a decrease in the proportion of patients with dementia receiving drug treatment. Conclusions. BIFAP is a useful source of data in the study of medication use prevalence. There is an increase in the use of antidementia drugs, driven by an increase in the prevalence of the disease and in the proportion of patients receiving treatment. Some gender differences in the profile of pharmacological treatment of dementia were found and deserve further research(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonis Sanz, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil García, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Corominas, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abajo Iglesias, Francisco de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente García, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyos Alonso, María Canto de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estimar la prevalencia de uso de fármacos antidemencia en el período 2002-2011. Métodos. Se seleccionaron los pacientes registrados en la base de datos BIFAP de historias clínicas de atención primaria mayores de 65 años con al menos un día de seguimiento. Se identificaron los pacientes con un código CIAP «P70 Demencia» en su historia y aquellos que recibieron prescripciones de donepezilo, rivastigmina, galantamina y memantina. De promedio se analizaron 365 787 pacientes por año. Resultados. La prevalencia de registro de demencia aumentó de 2002 a 2011 del 2,97 % al 4,17 %. El uso de fármacos para la demencia aumentó del 0,86 % al 2,4 % en mayores de 65 años y del 23,13 % al 41,12 % en pacientes diagnosticados de demencia. La proporción de pacientes con demencia en terapia combinada aumentó del 1,69% en 2003 al 6,29 % en 2011. El donepezilo fue el fármaco más utilizado. En los varones con demencia a partir de los 75 años, la prevalencia de uso de rivastigmina y galantamina es mayor que en las mujeres. A partir de los 85 años, los pacientes con demencia reciben menos tratamiento farmacológico. Conclusiones. BIFAP es una fuente útil de datos en el estudio de prevalencia de uso de fármacos. Se observa un aumento en el uso de fármacos antidemencia, provocado por un aumento en la prevalencia de diagnóstico de la enfermedad así como de la proporción de pacientes diagnosticados que reciben esos tratamientos. Se detectaron algunas diferencias en el perfil de tratamiento farmacológico de la demencia según el sexo que merecen ser investigadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alzheimer (Barc., Internet);(54): 20-27, mayo-ago. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de uso de fármacos para el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Alzheimer y su evolución temporal: un estudio descriptivo con la base de datos de atención primaria BIFAP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
