<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80229</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Valuation of hydrophilic polymeric foam dressing Skinfoam's® behavior in the patients' treatment with vascular venous ulcers and pharmaceuticaleconomic analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Ulcers from vascular origin of the lower extremities are a healthproblem, with important socioeconomic and sanitary consequences, as well ashigh human and material resources consumption. The aim of the present studywas to assess the performance of the hydrophilic polymeric foam dressingSkinfoam® in the treatment of patients with vascular ulcer from venous aetiology,as well as to evaluate the costs of the sanitary activity of that treatment.Material and methods: Observational study of clinical cases, prospective andopen, carried out in patients from both sex and age higher than 18 years, presentingat least one vascular ulcer of venous aetiology capable of being treatedwith an hydrophilic polymeric dressing and giving their written informed consent.The endpoints assessed were the evolution of the wound characteristics duringtreatment, the data from dressing changes, the global assessment of dressingperformance, and the cost analyses, total, per day and per cm2. Study resultswere analysed with summary statistics, showing results in mean and standarddeviations, and in percentages. Results: 14 evaluable patients were included,with a mean age of 68.0 years, and a 64.3% were females. The 71.4% of thepatients presented type II venous vascular ulcer. Non adhesive foam dressingsSkinfoam® were applied to 92.9% of patients, being adhesive in the remaining7.1% of the cases. Ulcer healing was achieved by 85.7% of the patients within2 months in average; while the remaining 14.3% didn&#146;t achieve ulcer healing,and withdrawn the study. Global treatment assessment with foam dressingSkinfoam® was preponderantly of excellent or very good (78.6%). In the (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barahona, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roche, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las úlceras de origen vascular de las extremidades inferioresconstituyen un problema de salud, con importantes repercusiones socioeconómicasy sanitarias, así como conllevan un gran consumo de recursoshumanos y materiales. El objetivo del presente estudio fue valorarel comportamiento de los apósitos poliméricos hidrófilos de espumaSkinfoam® en el tratamiento de pacientes con úlcera vascular de etiologíavenosa, así como valorar los costes de la actividad sanitaria de dicho tratamiento.Material y métodos: Estudio observacional de series de casos clínicos,prospectivo y abierto, realizado en pacientes de ambos sexos y edadsuperior a los 18 años que presentaran, al menos, una úlcera vascular deetiología venosa susceptible de ser tratada con un apósito polimérico hidrófiloy que dieran su consentimiento informado por escrito. Las variablesanalizadas fueron la evolución de las características de la lesión duranteel tratamiento, los datos de los cambios de apósito, la valoraciónglobal del comportamiento del apósito, y el análisis de costes totales, pordía y por cm2. Los resultados del estudio se analizaron mediante una estadísticadescriptiva, expresando los resultados en medias y desviaciones estándar,y en porcentajes. Resultados: Se incluyeron 14 pacientes evaluables,con una edad media de 68 años y un 64,3% eran mujeres. El 71,4%de los pacientes presentaba úlcera vascular venosa de tipo II. Se aplicaronapósitos de espuma Skinfoam® no adhesivos en el 92,9% de los pacientes,siendo adhesivos en el 7,1% de casos  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(4): 181-187, dic. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del comportamiento de los apósitos de espuma polimérica Skinfoam® en el tratamiento de pacientes con úlceras vasculares venosas y análisis farmacoeconómico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9964</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
