<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108673</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phenomenological interviews with graduates from Psychiatric Institution: stories of experiences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article aims to describe my experience in a applying the method of Heideggerian research, in particular the phenomenological interviews with people with mental illness discharged from psychiatric institutions that are currently residents of Therapeutic Residential Services (SRTS). We interviewed nine residents of SRTs in Piauí. In this step several times to walk were striking as the strategy of rapprochement with the interviewees, the location of interviews and even stirring account of the subjects. This experience enabled me to identify what is necessary and important to establish empathy with the subjects, there is no formula for conducting the interview, but it is the researcher to identify the best strategy for obtaining the reports. So is that the empathetic experienced by me in getting the reports of respondents in essence residents through phenomenological interview was crucial to uncovering the meaning of the subjects lived in the daily life of these devices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vieira, Taiane Soares</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Claudete Ferreira de Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo pretende describir la experiencia en la aplicación del método de investigación de Heidegger, en particular las entrevistas fenomenológicas con las personas con enfermedad mental dados de alta en las instituciones psiquiátricas en las que se encuentran actualmente los residentes de la terapéutica de Servicios Residenciales (SRTS). Se entrevistaron a nueve residentes de la SRT en Piauí. Se repitió esta fase varias veces y los resultados fueron sorprendentes dado que incidió en la estrategia de acercamiento a los sujetos, el escenario de las entrevistas y en el nivel de agitación de los sujetos. Esta experiencia me permitió identificar lo que es necesario e importante para establecer empatía con los sujetos, no existe una fórmula para la realización de la entrevista, pero es el investigador el que debe identificar la mejor estrategia para la selección de los informantes. En conclusión, la empatía experimentada por el entrevistador al obtener los informes de los sujetos residentes mediante la entrevista fenomenológica resultó crucial para descubrir el significado de las vivencias de la vida cotidiana de estos sujetos en estas instituciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;15(31): 24-29, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrevistas fenomenológicas con egresados de una Institución psiquiátrica: Relatos de experiencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
