<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041455</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Colorectal cancer: lifestyle and dietary factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Colorectal cancer is the most common tumor in the developed countries, and the number of new cases annualy is aproximately equal for men and women. Several environmental factors can interact in all steps of carcinogenesis. Lately the balance between genetic predisposition and these factors, including nutritional components and lifestyle behaviors, determines individual susceptibility to develop colorectal cancer. The aim of this study is to revise the references about lifestyle include diet, physical exercise, tobacco smoking and use of alcohol, and the risk of colorectal cancer in databases published during 1994-2004.  Dietary factors: According to the reports high intake of red meat, and particularly of processed meat and positive energetic balance (high intake of total fat and carbohydrate) was associated with a moderate but significant increase in colorectal cancer risk. Convincing preventive factors include increase consumption of a wide variety of fruit and vegetable, particularly, dark-green leafy, cruciferous, a deep-yellow on tones, and fibre.  Lifestyle: Physical activity as a means for the primary prevention of colorectal cancer. There is a probable synergic effect among physical inactivity, high energy intake and obesity and incidence of colorectal cancer. A growing body of evidence supports that avoidance overweight and the use of tobacco and alcohol is recommended to prevent colorectal cancer.  Conclusion: Current data suggest that lifestyle modification including proper diet such as the ones rich in vegetable and poor in red meat and fat, regular physical activity and maintaining an appropriate body weight and avoiding the use of tobacco and alcohol may lead to reduce colorectal cancer risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corrêa Lima, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomes-da-Silva, MHG</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el cáncer colorrectal es el tumor más frecuente de los países desarrollados, y el número anual de casos nuevos es aproximadamente igual en hombres que en mujeres. Diversos factores ambientales pueden interactuar en todas las etapas de la carcinogénesis. Últimamente, el equilibrio entre la predisposición y estos factores, incluyendo los componentes nutricionales y los hábitos de vida, determina la susceptibilidad individual para el desarrollo de cáncer colorrectal. El objetivo de este estudio es revisar las referencias acerca de los hábitos de vida, incluyendo la dieta, el ejercicio físico, el tabaquismo y el consumo de alcohol, y el riesgo de cáncer colorrectal en las bases de datos publicadas durante 1994-2004.  Factores dietéticos: según los informes, la ingestión elevada de carne roja, y especialmente de carne procesada, y el balance energético positivo (ingestión elevada de hidratos de carbono y grasas totales) se asociaba con un aumento moderado pero significativo en el riesgo de cáncer colorrectal. Los factores preventivos convincentes incluyen el aumento de la ingestión de frutas y vegetales variados, particularmente los de hoja verde oscura, las crucíferas, los de tono amarillo oscuro y la fibra.  Hábitos de vida: la actividad física como medida de prevención primaria del cáncer colorrectal. Probablemente, exista un efecto sinérgico entre la inactividad física, el consumo elevado de energía y la obesidad, y la incidencia de cáncer colorrectal. Un cuerpo de evidencia cada vez mayor apoya la recomendación de evitar el sobrepeso y el consumo de tabaco y alcohol para prevenir el cáncer colorrectal.  Conclusión: los datos actuales sugieren que la modificación de los hábitos de vida, incluyendo una dieta adecuada, como las ricas en vegetales y bajas en carne roja y grasa, la actividad física habitual y el mantenimiento de un peso corporal adecuado, así como la evitación del consumo de tabaco y alcohol pueden reducir el riesgo de cáncer colorrectal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(4): 235-241, jul.-ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer colorrectal, hábitos de vida y factores dietéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
