<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18686</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variations in the application of medical techniques in primary health care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To describe the application of medical techniques (ATM) in Spain and to analyze the relationship with diverse characteristics related to general practitioners and the center of primary health. Design: Multicenter cross-sectional study. Setting: Three hundred nineteen general practitioners working in primary care centers in the restructured public sector of the Autonomous Communities of Andalusia, Basque Country and Catalonia in Spain. Main measurements: Structured and validated questionnaire comprising 100 items in four sections: general characteristics of the physician and health center, task profile, and job satisfaction. The questionnaire was sent by mail to the health center (Andalusia and Basque Country) or to the home (Catalonia). For the analysis an index variable was created from the answers to the questions on AMT. Results: The index variable of AMT obtained a mean value of 10.02 (SD = 4.55). Andalusia obtained the highest value (median: 11.11; SD: 4.33) of the three Autonomous Communities in the study (p = .012). AMT acquired significantly higher values when associated with: masculine sex (sample from the three autonomous communities; p = .046), rural environment, teamwork, availability of basic equipment, fewer patients, and reduced work load. Conclusions: Index of ATM in Spain is significantly different in the three Spanish communities under study. The quality of the sanitary services evaluated from the dimension of the ATM seems to be much related with demographic characteristics, the readiness in the consultations of scientific-technical stuff and the appropriate time for medical consultations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la aplicación de técnicas médicas (ATM) en tres comunidades autónomas españolas (Andalucía, Cataluña y País Vasco) y analizar sus relaciones con diversas características relacionadas con los médicos de atención primaria y el centro de salud. Diseño: Estudio multicéntrico, transversal. Emplazamiento: Un total de 319 médicos generales que trabajaban en los centros de atención primaria del sector público reformado en las comunidades de Andalucía, País Vasco y Cataluña. Mediciones principales: Cuestionario estructurado y validado de 100 preguntas en cuatro apartados: características generales del profesional y centro de trabajo, perfil de actividad y satisfacción laboral. Éste fue enviado por correo al centro de trabajo (Andalucía y Euskadi) o domicilio particular (Cataluña). Para el análisis se creó una variable índice a partir de las respuestas de las preguntas de ATM. Resultados: La variable índice de ATM obtuvo un valor medio (desviación estándar [DE]) de 10,02 (4,55) y Andalucía el valor más alto (media [DE]: 11,11 [4,33]) de las tres comunidades del estudio (p = 0,012). La variable índice ATM adquiere valores significativamente más altos en relación con: el sexo masculino (muestra de tres comunidades autónomas; p = 0,046), el ámbito rural, el trabajo en equipo, la disponibilidad de equipamiento básico, el número de pacientes más reducido y menor carga asistencial. Conclusiones: Los índices de ATM en España son significativamente distintos en las tres comunidades españolas estudiadas. La calidad de la asistencia sanitaria evaluada desde la dimensión de la ATM parece estar muy relacionada con características demográficas, la disponibilidad en las consultas del material científico-técnico y el tiempo adecuado de las visitas médicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;16(6): 497-504, nov.  -dic.  2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variaciones en la aplicación de técnicas médicas en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Sobrequés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiva, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unzueta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prados, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boerma, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolíbar, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18686</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
