<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70082</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare the pre-operative and post-operative clinical symptoms in patients diagnosed as having hyperparathyroidism and given surgical treatment, in order to prove the existence of statistically significant improvement. Material and method: We report here a retrospective study performed on 120 consecutive patients operated on following diagnosis of hyperparathyroidism between 1990 and 2003. Results: Nephrolithiasis, generalized bone pain and HBP were the most common clinical manifestations. Primary hyperparathyroidisms represented 76.7 %, while secondary ones were 20.8% and 2.5 % were tertiary. We carried out85 adenoma removals, 30 sub-total and 5 total parathyroidectomies. We only encountered one case of recurrent palsy and about 25 % of hypocalcemias (2 of them permanent). Osteoarticular pathology and nephrolithiasis suffered by our patients clearly improved after surgery (P&lt;0.01) after 2 years of follow-up. There was no significant improvement in HBP, digestive and psychiatric pathology or pruritus. Conclusions: The improvement in quality of life for most of the patients operated on for this condition amply justifies parathyroidectomy by an experienced otolaryngology team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pantoja Hernández, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas Ugena, Eladio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Palomino, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Santos, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Romero, Guillerma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Beneyto, Federico del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Carmona, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar los síntomas clínicos preoperatorios y postoperatorios en pacientes diagnosticados de hiperparatiroidismo y sometidos a tratamiento quirúrgico, para comprobar si se produce mejoría estadísticamente significativa. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo realizado sobre 120 pacientes consecutivos intervenidos con diagnóstico de hiperparatiroidismo entre 1990 y 2003. Resultados: La litiasis renal, los dolores óseos generalizados y la hipertensión fueron las manifestaciones clínicas más frecuentes. El 76,7 % eran hiperparatiroidismos primarios; el 20,8 %, secundarios y el 2,5 %, terciarios. Se practicaron 85 resecciones de adenoma, 30 paratiroidectomías subtotales y 5 paratiroidectomías totales. Sólo hemos constatado 1 caso de parálisis recurrencial y un 25 % de hipocalcemias (2 definitivas). Mejoraron significativamente tras la cirugía (p &lt; 0,01) la afección osteo articular y la litiasis renal que presentaban los pacientes tras 2 años de seguimiento. No mejoraron de forma significativa la hipertensión, las enfermedades digestivas y psiquiátricas y elprurito. Conclusiones: La mejoría en la calidad de vida de la mayoría de los pacientes operados por esta enfermedad justifica sobradamente la paratiroidectomía por un equipo otorrinolaringológico experimentado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;59(10): 485-488, dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70082</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10432^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7172^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
