<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133729</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The surgical experience of general surgery residents: An analysis of the applicability of the specialty program in General and Digestive Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Residents in our country have achieved a homogenous surgical training by following a structured residency program. This is due to the existence of specific training programs for each specialty. The current program, approved in 2007, has a detailed list of procedures that a surgeon should have performed in order to complete training. The aim of this study is to analyze the applicability of the program with regard to the number of procedures performed during the residency period. Material and methods A data collection form was designed that included the list of procedures from the program of the specialty; it was sent in April 2014 to all hospitals with accredited residency programs. In September 2014 the forms were analysed, and a general descriptive study was performed; a subanalysis according to the resident's sex and Autonomous region was also performed. The number of procedures performed according to the number of residents in the different centers was also analyzed. Results The survey was sent to 117 hospitals with accredited programs, which included 190 resident places. A total of 91 hospitals responded (53%). The training offered adapts in general to the specialty program. The total number of procedures performed in the different sub-areas, in laparoscopic and emergency surgery is correct or above the number recommended by the program, with the exception of esophageal-gastric and hepatobiliary surgery. The sub-analysis according to Autonomous region did not show any significant differences in the (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jover Navalon, Jose M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turrado Rodríguez, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Targarona Soler, Eduardo M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez Saiz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El entrenamiento quirúrgico siguiendo un periodo de residencia ha conseguido que los residentes en nuestro país posean una formación homogénea y satisfactoria para el desarrollo de su actividad profesional. Ello se debe a la existencia de planes de formación específicos para cada especialidad. El plan vigente promulgado en 2007 detallaba el número mínimo de intervenciones quirúrgicas y procedimientos que un cirujano debía haber efectuado para completar su periodo de formación. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer la aplicación del programa de la especialidad en cuanto al número de intervenciones practicadas durante el periodo de residencia. Material y métodos Se diseñó una hoja de recogida de datos que incluía la relación de intervenciones enunciada en el programa de la especialidad, que fue remitida en abril de 2014 a todos los hospitales que disponen de unidades acreditadas para la formación de residentes. En septiembre de 2014 se tabularon las respuestas remitidas y se efectuó un estudio estadístico descriptivo general, y un subanálisis en función del sexo del residente y de la comunidad autónoma. A la vez se analizó la actividad efectuada en función del número de residentes que existiera en cada unidad docente acreditada. Resultados La encuesta se remitió a los 117 hospitales con unidades acreditadas, que incluyen un total de 190 plazas ofertadas. De ellas se obtuvieron 91 respuestas (53%). La formación ofrecida se adapta en líneas generales a la propuesta por el plan (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(3): 152-158, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué operan los residentes españoles durante la residencia?: análisis de la aplicabilidad del programa de la especialidad de Cirugía General y Digestiva al finalizar el periodo de residencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17571^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
