<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128435</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the Military Health Service in the campaign of Morocco (1859-1860)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: In the Army and the Navy there was a lack of regulations and doctrine, sanitary material was inappropriate, non-homogeneous, outdated and, above all desperately scarce, sometimes even remaining from the previous Carlist wars; the chain of evacuation was capricious, at the mercy of the medical officer in charge, while the military doctor was a kind of civil servant subject to military jurisdiction when convenient, with no authority and extremely discredited, resented and handicapped, to that extent that young people no longer wanted to become military doctors. We intend to exhibit for the first time a series of circumstances that make this campaign a turning point for the Military Health Service. Results: we established the gradation of the sanitary formations and the chain of evacuation. The attention to casualties was exemplary: battalion aid stations were very close to the first line and almost always subjected to fire; however, all injuries were attended and all wounded soldiers ready for evacuation for the next treatment step during the very same day. The majority of the soldiers, who had participated in a battle and had been injured, were in the hospitals of Ceuta or the peninsula the next day or even the same night, most of them already having been operated and with their fractures reduced. For the first time The Spanish Military Health Service used a "scientific breakthrough" - chloroform anesthesia for surgery. The sanitary units, highly requested, were created. This was the first military campaign in which the soldiers were provided with tents for accommodations and for hospitals and the first campaign in which, embarrassing as it sounds, soldiers´ meals were including meat.  Discussion: We lack points of reference to discuss our results since this campaign has not been treated in depth, as for the Military Health Services. Therefore, we present them in the following pages, expecting possible critics and discrepancies, but also consents. As the only exception, we praise the use of anesthesia for the first time on the battlefield.  Conclusions: for The Military Health, the campaign of 1859-1860 represented: 1o. Use of the anesthesia for the first time in campaign. 2o. Records of the name, grade and destination of every participating military physician and of all causalities. 3o. "A before and an after" in regards to campaign. 4o. A beginning of health doctrine as we know it. 5o Creation of the first medical units. 6o. Preferred approach practiced by Spanish surgeons is conservative. 7o. There are no uniform criteria in articles of military history on the types of casualties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Sierra, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: En el Ejército y la Armada carecían de reglamentos y de doctrina, el material sanitario era inadecuado, no homogéneo, anticuado y, sobre todo, desesperantemente escaso, a veces el restante de las anteriores guerras carlistas; la cadena de evacuación era caprichosa, al albur del oficial médico de la formación sanitaria que evacuaba y el médico militar era una especie de funcionario civil sometido al fuero militar cuando convenía, sin ninguna autoridad y tremendamente desprestigiado, agraviado y perjudicado, hasta el punto de que los jóvenes ya no querían ser médicos militares. Pretendemos exponer por primera vez una serie de circunstancias que convierten esta campaña en un punto de inflexión para la Sanidad Militar.  Resultados: Se establece el escalonamiento de las formaciones sanitarias y la cadena de evacuación. La atención a las bajas fue ejemplar: los puestos de socorro de batallón estaban pegados a la primera línea y casi siempre sometidos a fuego, pero no anochecía sin que los heridos de la jornada hubieran sido atendidos en su totalidad y puestos en disposición de evacuación al siguiente escalón(1). La mayoría de los soldados que habían participado en una batalla y habían resultado heridos, estaban en los hospitales de Ceuta o de la península al día siguiente o incluso esa misma noche y gran parte de ellos llegaban ya operados y con sus fracturas reducidas. La Sanidad militar española utiliza por primera vez los "adelantos de la ciencia", fundamentalmente la anestesia por cloroformo en el teatro de operaciones. Se crearon las unidades sanitarias, tan solicitadas con anterioridad. Esta fue la primera campaña militar en la que los soldados contaban con tiendas de campaña para alojamientos y para hospitales y en la que, causa rubor contarlo, se presume de darles de comer carne por primera vez(2).  Discusión: Carecemos de puntos de referencia para discutir nuestros resultados, ya que esta campaña en lo referente a la Sanidad Militar, no ha sido tratada con profundidad. Por ello, los exponemos en las siguientes páginas esperando posibles críticas y discrepancias, o porque no, conformidades. Solo como excepción defendemos la utilización de la anestesia por primera vez en el campo de batalla.  Conclusiones: La campaña de 1859-1860 supuso para la Sanidad Militar:  1o. Utilización por vez primera de la anestesia en campaña. 2o. Se dan a conocer el nombre, grado y destino de todos los médicos militares participantes y sus bajas(3). 3o. Hay un antes y un después respecto a la campaña. 4o. Establecimiento de un principio de doctrina sanitaria. 5o. Creación de las primeras unidades sanitarias. 6o La actitud abstencionista de los cirujanos españoles se mantiene como práctica preferente. 7o No hay criterios uniformes en los artículos de historia militar sobre los tipos de baja (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;70(3): 157-173, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la Sanidad Militar en la campaña de Marruecos (1859-1860)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54373</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
