<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141803</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiologic surveillance on measles rubella and congenital rubella syndrome. Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To achieve the goal of eliminating measles and rubella two key strategies have been defined: sustain very low level of population susceptibility and strengthen surveillance system by rigorous case investigation and rapid control measures implementation. Surveillance of measles, rubella and CRS are included into the Spanish Surveillance System (RENAVE); surveillance is mandatory, passive, nationwide and case-based with laboratory information integrated. Information flows from sub national to national level (National Centre for Epidemiology) and then, to the WHO-Europe through ECDC. In the final phase of elimination, good surveillance and documented evidences are keys. Information on epidemiology of measles, rubella and CRS cases and outbreaks, pattern of importation, genotypes circulating and performance of measles and rubella surveillance are required at national and international level. Also all investigated and discarded measles or rubella cases should be reported. Currently the system faces some challenges gathering needed information for documenting the elimination. As long as the disease incidence declines, increases difficulties in identifying clinical measles and rubella because of non-specific prodromal signs and atypical cases. Differential diagnosis for fever and rash including measles and rubella should be performed in all clinical settings. Three clinical specimens must be collected to confirm or discard cases and to allow the virus characterization in order to know the pattern of importation of measles and rubella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masa Calles, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viarce Torres de Mier, María de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Perea, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para alcanzar la eliminación del sarampión y rubéola se precisa mantener un bajo nivel de susceptibilidad en la población y un sistema de vigilancia capaz de identificar a tiempo la circulación de los virus y de implantar medidas rápidas para controlar la transmisión. En España la vigilancia epidemiológica del sarampión, la rubéola y el síndrome de rubéola congénita está integrada en la Red Nacional de Vigilancia Epidemiológica, en la que participan todos los niveles del Sistema Nacional de Salud, incluidos los laboratorios. En el plano internacional, el Centro Nacional de Epidemiología suministra la información para documentar los progresos hacia la eliminación a OMS-Europa a través del ECDC. En la última fase de la eliminación la vigilancia está dirigida a documentar la ausencia de casos endémicos aportando evidencias sobre el origen de casos y brotes, patrones de importación de los virus y genotipos circulantes e indicadores de calidad de la vigilancia. Para demostrar que se ha interrumpido la trasmisión endémica no es suficiente con que no se confirmen casos, hay que aportar evidencias de que se identifican sospechas clínicas, se investigan en el laboratorio y se descartan. Aunque nuestro sistema de vigilancia cumple en general con los objetivos de calidad, actualmente tiene dificultades para detectar sospechas clínicas de sarampión o rubéola. La única manera de mejorar la sensibilidad en la identificación y captación de casos clínicos sería fortalecer la concienciación en el nivel asistencial promoviendo que en el diagnóstico diferencial de todo caso de fiebre y exantema que se presente en cualquier edad, se incluya el incluya el diagnóstico de laboratorio de sarampión y rubéola (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(4): 365-379, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141803</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigilancia epidemiológica en España del sarampión, la rubeola y el síndrome de rubéola congénita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12784^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50229</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19342^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
