<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103156</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between computational jobs and musculoskeletal symptoms in office workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: This found that frequent use of computers in administrative work shows an increase of musculoskeletal problems in people who use them. This study evaluated associations between computational jobs and presence of musculoskeletal symptoms, with special emphasis on physical elements that make up the design. Materials and Methods: Cross-sectional study on a population sample of 153 subjects administrative and frequent users of computers. Questionnaire was administered musculoskeletal symptoms and ergonomic assessment of jobs. Subsequently, we performed univariate and multivariate analysis. Results and Discussion: The proportion of jobs with inadequate ergonomic work surface was 62.7%, 53.6% keyboard, 90.8% and briefcases. The most important association between symptoms by body region was inappropriate ergonomically designed left shoulder / keyboard (p value: 0.04). We conclude that the study population has a high prevalence of musculoskeletal symptoms and ergonomic design is not the keyboard, desk and chair might be related to symptoms in upper extremities, thoracic and lumbar region respectively. It is suggested to study the use made of the jobs by the users as it could be influencing the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vanegas López, Jairo Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Poblete, Claudio Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Está comprobado que el uso frecuente de computadores en trabajos administrativos muestra un aumento de problemas musculoesqueléticos en las personas que los utilizan. Este estudio pretende determinar asociaciones entre puestos de trabajo computacional y presencia de síntomas musculoesqueléticos, con especial énfasis en elementos físicos que componen el diseño. Materiales y Métodos: Estudio transversal realizado sobre una muestra poblacional de 153 sujetos administrativos y usuarios frecuentes de computadores. Se administró cuestionario de síntomas musculoesqueléticos y una evaluación ergonómica de los puestos de trabajo. Posteriormente, se realizó análisis univariado y multivariados. Resultados y Discusión: La proporción de puestos de trabajo con diseño ergonómico inadecuado de la superficie de trabajo fue 62,7%, teclado 53,6%, y portadocumentos 90,8%. La asociación más importante entre los síntomas por región corporal con diseño ergonómico inadecuado fue hombro izquierdo/teclado (valor p: 0,04). Se concluye que la población estudiada tiene alta prevalencia de síntomas musculoesqueléticos y que el diseño no ergonómico del teclado, escritorio y silla podrían estar relacionados con síntomas en extremidades superiores, región dorsal y lumbar, respectivamente. Se sugiere estudiar el uso dado a los puestos de trabajo por parte de los usuarios, ya que podría estar influyendo en los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;58(227): 98-106, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre puesto de trabajo computacional y síntomas musculoesqueléticos en usuarios frecuentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22397</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
