<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165823</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Edoxaban: Pharmacodynamic and Pharmacokinetic Properties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Edoxaban is a potent, selective, direct, reversible inhibitor of coagulation factor Xa. Because of its mechanism of action, edoxaban prolongs the prothrombin time and the activated partial thromboplastin time and reduces anti-factor-Xa activity. In both in vitro and in vivo models, edoxaban is a more effective antithrombotic than fondaparinux. Given orally, the drug rapidly (i.e. in 1-2 hours) reaches its peak plasma concentration and achieves its maximum effect on various antithrombotic biomarkers (e.g. prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time and anti-factor-Xa activity). Edoxaban (15-150 mg once daily) has a linear pharmacokinetic profile. It is readily absorbed when given orally (the bioavailability is 62%), but, unlike other factor-Xa inhibitors, it exhibits only poor binding to plasma proteins and is not biotransformed via CYP3A4. It is eliminated by biliary and renal routes and has a half-life of 10-14 hours, which enables edoxaban to be administered once daily. Exposure to the drug is independent of age, sex and ethnicity, but increases as the patient&#146;s weight and renal function decrease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tamargo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El edoxabán es un inhibidor potente, directo, selectivo y reversible del factor Xa de la coagulación. Por su mecanismo de acción, prolonga los tiempos de protrombina y de tromboplastina parcial activada e inhibe la actividad anti-factor Xa. En modelos in vitro e in vivo, el edoxabán es más efectivo como antitrombótico que el fondaparinux. Por vía oral, alcanza rápidamente (1-2 h) concentraciones plasmáticas máximas y su efecto máximo en diversos biomarcadores antitrombóticos (tiempos de protrombina y de tromboplastina parcial activada, actividad anti-factor Xa). El edoxabán (15-150 mg una vez al día) presenta un perfil farmacocinético lineal. Se absorbe bien por vía oral (biodisponibilidad del 62%) pero, a diferencia de otros inhibidores del factor Xa, se une poco a proteínas plasmáticas y no se biotransforma a través del citocromo P3A4, se elimina por vía biliar y renal y tiene una semivida de 10-14 h, lo que permite su administración una vez al día. La exposición al edoxabán es independiente de la edad, el sexo o la raza, pero aumenta al disminuir el peso y la función renal del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);16(supl.A): 60a-66a, 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Edoxabán. Propiedades farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10505</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15261^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d651^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55662^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
