<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130612</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacology of the antifungals used in the treatment of aspergillosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The treatment of invasive aspergillosis requires the use of drugs that characteristically have complex pharmacokinetic properties, the knowledge of which is essential to achieve maximum efficacy with minimal risk to the patient. The lipid-based amphotericin B formulations vary significantly in their pharmacokinetic behaviour, with very high plasma concentrations of the liposomal form, probably related to the presence of cholesterol in their structure. Azoles have a variable absorption profile, particularly in the case of itraconazole and posaconazole, with the latter very dependent on multiple factors. This may also lead to variations in voriconazole, which requires considering the possibility of monitoring plasma concentrations. The aim of this article is to review some of the most relevant aspects of the pharmacology of the antifungals used in the prophylaxis and treatment of the Aspergillus infection. For this reason, it includes the most relevant features of some of the azoles normally prescribed in this infection (itraconazole, posaconazole and voriconazole) and the amphotericin B formulations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Azanza, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Guíu, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sádaba, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de la aspergilosis invasora exige la utilización de algunos fármacos que de forma característica presentan propiedades farmacocinéticas complejas, cuyo conocimiento es imprescindible para alcanzar la máxima eficacia con el mínimo riesgo para el paciente. Las formulaciones lipídicas de anfotericina B son muy distintas en su comportamiento farmacocinético, con concentraciones plasmáticas de la forma liposómica muy elevadas en probable relación con la presencia de colesterol en su estructura. Los azoles presentan un perfil de absorción variable, especialmente en el caso del itraconazol y del posaconazol, este último muy dependiente de múltiples factores. En el caso del voriconazol puede existir variabilidad a este respecto, lo que obliga a considerar la posibilidad de realizar una monitorización de las concentraciones plasmáticas. El objetivo de este artículo es revisar algunos de los aspectos más relevantes de la farmacología de los antifúngicos utilizados en la profilaxis y el tratamiento de la infección aspergilar. Por ello se incluirán los aspectos más relevantes de algunos de los azoles que suelen prescribirse en esta infección (itraconazol, posaconazol y voriconazol) y de las formulaciones de anfotericina B (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;31(4): 255-261, oct.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacología de los antifúngicos en el tratamiento de la aspergilosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31378^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
