<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68141</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a female patient suffering a peritonitis episode after subtotal gastrectomy due to gastric neoplasm in relation to lesser curvature necrosis extending to the anterior esophageal wall. This an uncommon and severe complication that made mandatory further aggressive surgery: transection of the abdominal esophagus, transection of the gastric stump, and cervical esophagostomy with creation of a jejunostomy with a needle catheter for feeding. This digestive tube access technique is generally used during major abdominal post-surgery until oral intake is reestablished. Our patient has been 187 days with this therapy since reconstruction of the GI tract was ruled out due to tumoral infiltration of the colon and tumor recurrence at the gastrohepatic omentum. To date, there has been no complication from permanence and/or long-term use of this technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Enríquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neira, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente que tras ser sometida a gastrectomía subtotal por neoplasia gástrica sufre una peritonitis en relación con necrosis de curvatura menor que se extiende a cara anterior de esófago. Esta es una complicación poco frecuente y grave que obligó a cirugía agresiva: transección de esófago abdominal, transección de muñón gástrico y esofagostomía cervical, con colocación de yeyunostomía con catéter de aguja para alimentación. Esta técnica de acceso a tubo digestivo es usada normalmente en el postoperatorio de cirugía mayor abdominal hasta que se reinicia ingesta oral. En nuestra paciente lleva un total de 187 días, dado que se descartó reconstrucción del tránsito digestivo por infiltración tumoral del colon y recidiva tumoral en la localización del epiplón gastrohepático. Hasta el momento no ha habido ninguna complicación derivada de su permanencia y/o uso a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(1): 75-76, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68141</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
