<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156511</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Using a musical metaphor as the clackloth, this paper studies the particularities of the analytical encounter that predetermine the particular form of analytical listening, which centres on listening to the latent, and is not only considered as the breakthrough of the repressed, but also of what is not present in manifest speech and which can appear through acts of the body or through disruptions and contradictions present in the discourse, all of which enable the analyst to listen in another key, through his own associative processes. The setting is considered to be a vital element because of its symbolizing function. Free association will be established progressively, in relation not only with the patient´s capacity for elaboration, but also, to a great extent, in accordance with the possibilities of the analyst´s listening. The analyst is frequently fascinated and paralyzed by the impact of the manfest content, and this makes listening of associative processes difficult. Within counter-transferential difficulties, the impact of traumatic anxiety and seduction-present in all analytical relations-is studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cid Sanz, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la metáfora musical como telón de fondo, el trabajo va recorriendo las particularidades del encuentro analítico que predetermina el modo particular de escucha analítica, centrado en la escucha de lo latente, no solamente considerado como retorno de lo reprimido, sino también de lo que no está presente en el discurso manifiesto, y que puede aparecer a través de los actos, del cuerpo o de las disrupciones y contradicciones presentes en el relato, lo que permite al analista escuchar en otra clave, a través de sus propios procesos asociativos. El encuadre se considera como un elemento indispensable por su función simbolizante. La libre asociación se irá instaurando progresivamente, en relación no solamente con las posibilidades elaborativas del paciente, sino también, en gran medida, según las posibilidades de escucha del analista, a amenudo fascinado y paralizado por el impacto del contenido manifiesto, que dificulta la escucha de los procesos asociativos. Entre las dificultados constratransferenciales, se revisan el impacto de la angustia traumática y la seducción, presentes en toda relación analítica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(43): 15-58, 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El arte del contrapunto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
