<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72909</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-8460</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paget's bone disease: usefulness of bisphosphonates as therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paget&#146;s disease of bone is characterized by the appearance and development of progressive skeletal deformation due to an accelerated rate of bone resorption coupled with osteoblastic activity of similar or equal intensity. This produces bone formation that is structurally disorganized. The parallel development of excessive bone remodelling requires the clinical use of anti-resorptive drugs, such as bisphosphonates. These drugs are very effective in the treatment of patients with Paget&#146;s disease because they are able to inhibit overly intense osteoclastic activity, and thus, decrease and regulate the bone turnover process. Unlike other drugs, bisphosphonates generally produce the total remission of symptoms, which means the normalization of biochemical parameters as well as improved bone histology. This paper reviews and discusses the symptoms of Paget&#146;s disease of bone so that it can be more effectively treated at healthcare facilities. We also discuss the latest diagnostic methods used as well as different treatments for this disease with a special focus on bisphosphonates, particularly, their chemical composition, usage, and benefits derived from administration(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Cordero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guisado Barrilao, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, p. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla López, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ferre, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Paget ósea constituye un cuadro clínico patológico caracterizado por la aparición y desarrollo de lesiones óseas dotadas de una acelerada actividad ósea resortiva y a la que se superpone un proceso de síntesis osteoblástica de igual o similar intensidad aunque de características desorganizadas. El desarrollo paralelo de un intenso remodelado óseo hace necesaria la utilización clínica de fármacos con capacidad antirresortiva, dentro de los cuales cabe destacar el grupo de los bifosfonatos, los cuales son de gran utilidad en estos pacientes si se considera su potencial capacidad para inhibir la intensa actividad osteoclástica y por tanto disminuir y regular el proceso de recambio óseo. A diferencia del tratamiento con otros fármacos, los bifosfonatos logran por lo general una remisión clínica completa del cuadro, circunstancia que se traduce en una normalización de los parámetros bioquímicos así como en una mejoría a nivel de las estructuras histológicas óseas. En el presente trabajo ofrecemos una revisión sobre las características clínicas del cuadro para su adecuado manejo en la clínica, así como una actualización sobre las diferentes alternativas en su diagnóstico y manejo terapéutico centrándonos de modo especial en la terapia con bifosfonatos, esto es, su estructura molecular así como sus principales indicaciones y beneficios derivados de su administración(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. enferm. metab. óseas (Ed. impr.);18(2): 34-38, abr.-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Paget ósea: utilidad de los bifosfonatos como terapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
