<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111397</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Refractory Chronic Cough: New Perspectives in Diagnosis and Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In patients with chronic cough, nearly 40% of the population does not experience definitive improvement of their cough despite correctly applying the anatomic diagnosis. In many of these patients with refractory cough, laryngeal symptoms are frequent. The region of the larynx/pharynx is configured as a bridge between the esophagus and the upper and lower respiratory tract. The association of reflux in patients with chronic cough and symptoms such as globus pharyngis, itchiness or the need to clear one's throat have recently been given attention due to the possibility of joint therapeutic intervention of the gastroesophageal reflux and larynx, both with new medications as well as with laryngeal rehabilitation therapies, with observed benefits in the disappearance of chronic cough in cases that had been previously labeled as refractory(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobeta, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wagner, Carolin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco, Adalberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los pacientes con tos crónica todavía existe una población cercana al 40% que no mejora definitivamente su tos a pesar de aplicar correctamente el diagnóstico anatómico al uso. En muchos de esos pacientes con tos refractaria los síntomas laríngeos son frecuentes. La zona de la laringe-faringe se configura como el puente entre el esófago y el tracto respiratorio superior e inferior. La asociación de reflujo en pacientes con tos crónica y síntomas como globo laríngeo, picor o la necesidad de aclarar la garganta han merecido atención recientemente por la posibilidad de intervención terapéutica conjunta sobre el reflujo gastroesofágico y la laringe, tanto con nuevas medicaciones como con terapias de rehabilitación laríngea, con beneficios objetivables en la desaparición de la tos crónica en casos que habían sido etiquetados previamente como refractarios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(4): 151-157, abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tos crónica refractaria. Nuevas perspectivas en diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31108^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53499^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12094^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53499^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53499^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53957^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
