<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123741</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Levosimendan for postoperative ventricular dysfunction following heart transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of postoperative ventricular dysfunction immediately after heart transplantation is a serious complication that leads to low-output syndrome and which necessitates circulatory support. It is one of the most common causes of early morbidity and mortality. We present our experience with 6 heart transplant patients who were treated with intravenous levosimendan, a calcium sensitizer with inodilator properties, after regular hemodynamic therapy with sympathomimetic amines failed to result in a satisfactory hemodynamic status. Use of this drug was well tolerated and brought about hemodynamic improvements that were sufficient to enable patients to be weaned from inotropic support with amines and which led to clinical recovery, with 5 of the 6 patients being discharged from the intensive care unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vela, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez De Viguri, Narciso Perales</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Tejedor, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Renes Carreño, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Regidor, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas López, Primitivo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corres Peiretti, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Rodríguez, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disfunción ventricular del injerto en el postoperatorio inmediato del paciente trasplantado cardiaco es una complicación grave, que cursa con un síndrome de bajo gasto cardiaco y necesidad de soporte circulatorio, y es una de las causas más frecuentes de morbimortalidad inicial. Presentamos la experiencia clínica con 6 pacientes trasplantados en los que, tras un manejo hemodinámico habitual con aminas simpaticomiméticas, no se consiguió una adecuada situación hemodinámica y se utilizó levosimendán intravenoso, un fármaco sensibilizador al calcio con propiedades inodilatadoras. El uso de este fármaco fue bien tolerado y favoreció una mejoría hemodinámica que facilitó la retirada del soporte inotrópico con aminas y la recuperación clínica (con alta de UCI de 5 de los 6 pacientes) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;61(5): 534-539, mayo 2008. mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123741</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de levosimendán en la disfunción ventricular postoperatoria del injerto en el trasplante cardiaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2347^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
