<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125800</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shame or the new pathologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The predominance of compulsive forms and narcissistic collapse in the prevailing pathologies is determined by failures in symbolization which correlate with a deficiency in the formation of the psychic instances &#150;ego, ego-ideal and superego. The spsychoanalytic task, be it interpretation, construction or resubjectification, will depend not only upon the psychopathological diagnosis, but upon our metapsychological understanding, which leads us to distinguish the place within the structure occupied by certain less symbolized currents of psychic life. Besed on the characters from the film Shame, the author reflects upon on moral masochism and melancholy as two privileged forms of expression of the overflowing of drives and its correlate, the deficiency in the structuration of the efo and the ideal instances (ego-ideal and superego) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amieba, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El predominio de formas compulsivas y colapsos narcisistas en las patologías actuales está determinado por fallos en la simbolización que tienen como correlato un déficit en la constitución de las instancias psíquicas &#150;Yo, Ideal del Yo, ySuperyo-. La tarea psicoanalítica, bien sea la interpretación, la construcción o la resubjetivación, va a depender no solo del diagnóstico psicopatológico sino de la comprensión metapsicológica que lleva a discriminar qué lugar ocupan en la estructura ciertas corrientes menos simbolizadas de la vida psíquica. Tomando como base los personajes de la película Shame, se hace una reflexión sobre el masoquismo moral y la melancolía como dos formas privilegiadas de expresión de los desbordes pulsionales y su correlato, el déficit en la estructuración del Yo y las instancias ideales (Ideal del Yo y Superyo (AU))</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(69): 307-325, mayo-ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Shame o las nuevas patologías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3223^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
