<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155985</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of embolisation in patients diagnosed with pelvic varices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Pelvic congestion syndrome (PCS), or pelvic varices (PV), is an entity suffered by millions of women worldwide, and its occurrence can reach up to 39%. Multiple factors contribute the pathophysiology of the PCS. Up to 15% of women between the ages of 20 and 50 years-old have varicose veins in the pelvis, although not all experience symptoms. The aim of this study was to determine the efficacy and safety of phlebography and embolisation of the PV as treatment for PCS. Material and methods: The study included 75 symptomatic women, who were enrolled from June 2014 to December 2015 after being referred from other centres with a diagnosis of PCS. Of these, 24 patients (aged 26-55 years with a mean of 37 years) were diagnosed with the presence of PV using transvaginal ultrasound. A venography was performed on this group to verify the diagnosis, and immediate embolisation was performed, if this was possible and required. The VAS score was measured to clinically determine the success of the procedure at 3, 6, 9, and 12 months of follow-up, correlating with prior to the procedure base. Transvaginal ultrasound was also performed at 6 months to determine the closure or rechannelling, as well as a phlebography at 12 months, with the same objective. These parameters were collected in a base template. Results: The presence of PV associated with PCS in our city, due to being a central institution of national reference, was 3.9% of the female population seen from June of 2014 to December 2015. All the 24 patients were symptomatic, with dyspareunia being one of the most referred to factors; 100%. All the study population presented with multiparity as risk factor, and only 37% of them showed varices in the lower limbs. When phlebography was performed the diagnosis was confirmed in only 83% (n=20) of patients referred due to PV observed in the transvaginal ultrasound. There were no complications during the follow-up of the procedure, 8.3% of patients had recurrence of symptoms at 9 months follow-up. A phlebography was performed and ectatic venous vessels dependent on the right internal iliac vein and gonadal right were embolised, respectively. There was no recurrence of symptoms in any of them after 12 months of follow-up. No differences were observed in the successful occlusion with the use of coils vs polidocanol. Conclusion: Phlebography is a specific test and with a low complication rate for the diagnosis of PV. Embolisation of pelvic varices using coils or polidocanol is an effective and safe method for the treatment of PCS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cisneros, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Imbaquingo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de congestión pélvica (SCP) o varices pélvicas (VP) es una entidad que pueden sufrir millones de mujeres en el mundo, y su ocurrencia puede llegar hasta un 39%. Son múltiples los factores que contribuyen la patofisiología del SCP. Hasta un 15% de las mujeres entre las edades de 20 a 50 años tienen venas varicosas en la pelvis, aunque no todas experimentan síntomas. Objetivo: Determinar la eficacia y seguridad de la flebografía y embolización de las VP como noxa del SCP. Material y métodos: Se incluyeron, desde junio de 2014 hasta diciembre de 2015, 75 mujeres sintomáticas remitidas de otros centros con diagnóstico de SCP; de ellas 24 pacientes (edades comprendidas entre 26 a 55 años con una media de 37 años) reportaron presencia de VP confirmadas con ultrasonido transvaginal (UST), posteriormente a este grupo se le realizó una flebografía control para ratificar dicho diagnóstico e inmediata embolización si así lo requerían. Se estableció el score escala analógica visual para determinar clínicamente el éxito del procedimiento con seguimiento a los 3, 6, 9 y 12 meses, correlacionando con el de base previo al procedimiento; además se realiza UST a los 6 meses para determinar el cierre o recanalización, y una flebografía control a los 12 meses con el mismo objetivo. Estos parámetros se recogieron en una plantilla base. Resultados: La presencia de VP asociada a SCP en nuestra ciudad, por ser nuestra institución centro de referencia nacional, constituyó un 3,9% de la población femenina recibida durante el año 2015. El 100% (n=24) de nuestras pacientes fue sintomática, donde la dispareunia era uno de los factores mayormente referido (100%); además el 100% de la población estudiada presentó como factor de riesgo la multiparidad y solo un 37% de ellas mostró varices en los miembros inferiores; cuando se realizó la flebografía control solamente en el 83% (n=20) de las pacientes referidas por US transvaginal con VP se confirmó el diagnóstico. Posteriormente al procedimiento no tuvimos complicaciones, el 8,3% de pacientes presentó recurrencia de síntomas a los 9 meses de seguimiento, se les realizó una flebografía control y se embolizó los vasos venosos ectásicos dependientes de la vena iliaca interna derecha y gonadal derecha, respectivamente. Al seguimiento a los 12 meses no tuvimos recurrencia de síntomas en ninguna de ellas. No tuvimos diferencias en el éxito de oclusión con el uso de coils vs polidocanol. Conclusión: La flebografía es un método específico y con baja tasa de complicaciones para el diagnóstico de VP. La embolización de VP con uso de coils o polidocanol representa un método eficaz y seguro como tratamiento del SCP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;68(5): 388-395, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de la embolización en pacientes con diagnóstico de varices pélvicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37257^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37257^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d292^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d292^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37257^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d292^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
