<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108787</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epicardial fat: a new tool for the assessment of cardiometabolic risk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scienti&amp;#64257;c and clinical interest in epicardial adipose tissue, the true visceral fat of the heart, is recent, but of great importance. Epicardial fat thickness can be directly detected and accurately measured with standard 2-dimensional transthoracic echocardiography, which has some advantages as an index of high cardiometabolic risk, including low cost, easy accessibility and good reproducibility. Epicardial fat is clinically correlated with left ventricular mass, atria dimensions, and diastolic function. Furthermore, the relation between epicardial adipose tissue and coronary atherosclerosis is present in patients with clinically manifest coronary artery disease, and based on the results of clinical studies it can be argued that epicardial adipose tissue may be involved in the process of atherosclerosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iacobellis, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Martínez, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El interés clínico y cientí&amp;#64257;co en el tejido adiposo epicárdico, la verdadera grasavisceral del corazón, es reciente, pero de gran relevancia. El espesor de la grasa epicárdica puede ser medido directamente mediante ecocardiografía transtorácica bidimensional estándar, teniendo algunas ventajas como índice de alto riesgo cardiometabólico, incluyendo bajo costo, fácil accesibilidad y buena reproducibilidad. La grasa epicárdica se correlaciona clínicamente con la masa del ventrículo izquierdo, las dimensiones auriculares, y la función diastólica. Además, la relación entre tejido adiposo epicárdico y aterosclerosis coronaria está presente en pacientes con enfermedad arterial coronaria mani&amp;#64257;esta, y basado en los estudios clínicos se puede argumentar que la grasa epicárdica puede estar envuelta en el proceso aterosclerótico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;28(2): 63-68, Mar. -Abr. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grasa epicárdica: una nueva herramienta para la evaluación del riesgo cardiometabólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10686^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31672^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
