<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77937</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wechsler inteligence scales in the Neuropsychoogical assessment of the child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes the role Wechsler´s Intelligence scales caryout in infantile neuropsychoogical assessment. We study their contribution inneuropsychological assessment when they are applied in an isolatd way, analyzing various indicators that can help to establish a neuropsycholgicla diagosis. The paper concludes underlining the need and imporance that these scales be applied in combination with neuropsychological batteries (Luria- DNI battery) and their interpretation rest on some of the most current heories of inelligence (Theory of the three levels and Theory of fluid and crystallized intelligence) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bausela Herreras, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Analizamos el papel que las escalas de inteligencia Wechsler, desempeñan en la evaluación neuropsicológica infantil. Se estudia su contribución cuando son aplicadas de forma aislada, analizando algunos indicadores que pueden ayudar a establecer un diagnóstico neuropsicológico. Se subraya la necesidad y la importancia de que sean aplicaas en combinación con baterías neuropsicológicas (batería Luria &#150; DNI) y que su nterpretación se apoye en algunas de las teorías más actuales de la inteligencia (Teorá de los tres estratos y Teoría de la inteligencia fluida y cristalizada) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(7): 85-90, ene.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las escala de inteligencia  Wechsler en la evaluación neuropsicológica infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
