<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150285</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Urban bus system: comparison between users and potential users evaluation models. The main objective of the actual investigation consist on the comparison of structure factors of two scales, which have been established to judge the opinions of the public about the bus as the most important means of urban transport. For this, a representative sample of the urban population of the Galician Autonomous Community was used. The psychometric analysis allows us to get to the conclusion that both scales have a similar scaling factor with acceptable psychometric characteristics. Moreover, there is a coincidence of opinion exposed by the regular and potential bus users, discovering that the latter used these stereotypes when formulating an opinion about the bus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez González, M Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seoane Pesqueira, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce Fernández, Constantino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo central de la presente investigación consistió en comparar la estructura factorial de dos escalas construidas para juzgar las actitudes y opiniones de las personas sobre el autobús, como principal sistema de transporte público urbano. Se utilizó una muestra representativa de la población urbana de la Comunidad Autónoma Gallega. El análisis psicométrico permite concluir que ambas escalas tienen una estructura factorial semejante, con cualidades psicométricas aceptables. Existe, además, una coincidencia en la opinión mostrada por usuarios habituales del sistema de autobuses y usuarios potenciales, descubriéndose que estos últimos utilizan estereotipos al formular juicios sobre el autobús (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 522-525, 2000. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de modelos de evaluación del servicio de autobús urbano para usuarios reales y potenciales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
