<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146568</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflections on consent of organ donation from deceased person; influence of judgment of European Court of Human Rights. Case Petrova v. Latvia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Agreeing to the removal of organs from deceased shows obvious differences from the technical-legal concept of informed consent; though some similarity might be found with those of obtaining consent by substitution, and in the case of minors or disabled, with the assumption of consent by proxy (consent by representation). The Spanish legislation, adopting the regime itself of the environment States belonging to the Council of Europe, has designed a system of presumed consent unless specifically stated otherwise; in which the work of the transplant coordination should be directed to determine whether the potential donor expressed in life such opposition; on the understanding that at no time be required a possible justification or weight whatsoever of the reasons for the refusal; and although the daily performance of transplant coordinators direct its action strategy to involve patients in the responsibility and significance of such an act of generosity. The JECHR of June 24, 2014 (case Petrova v Latvia), although showing full conformity with the regulations based on presumed consent contained in the Oviedo Convention of 4 April 1997 and its Additional Protocol Strasbourg 24 January 2002, has linked the so-called right to family life with the obligation of public authorities to provide the closest relatives with at least an opportunity to set out their views before an appropriate decision is adopted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Lainz, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prestación del consentimiento para la extracción de órganos de persona fallecida muestra evidentes diferencias frente al concepto técnico-jurídico de consentimiento informado; aunque podría encontrar cierta similitud con las exigencias propias de la obtención del llamado consentimiento por sustitución, y, en el supuesto de menores o incapaces, con el supuesto del consentimiento por representación. La legislación española, adoptando el régimen propio del entorno de los Estados pertenecientes al Consejo de Europa, ha diseñado un sistema de presunción de consentimiento salvo manifestación expresa en contrario; en el que la labor de la coordinación de trasplantes se debe dirigir a constatar si el potencial donante manifestó en vida tal oposición; en el bien entendido que no se requerirá en momento alguno una justificación o posible ponderación de los motivos de la negativa; y aunque la actuación cotidiana de las coordinaciones de trasplantes dirija su estrategia de actuación a involucrar a los pacientes en la responsabilidad y significado de tal acto de generosidad. La STEDH de 24 de junio de 2014 (caso Petrova v Lituania), sin perjuicio de mostrar su plena conformidad con los regímenes basados en el consentimiento presunto recogidos en el Convenio de Oviedo de 4 de abril de 1997 y su Protocolo Adicional de Estrasburgo de 24 de enero de 2002, ha relacionado con el llamado derecho a la vida familiar la obligación de los poderes públicos de favorecer que la opinión de éstos pueda al menos ser tenida en cuenta antes de adoptarse la oportuna decisión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;21(1/2): 19-23, ene.-jun. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones sobre el consentimiento de persona fallecida para la donación de órganos; la incidencia de la sentencia del Tribunal Europeo de Derechos Humanos del caso Petrova v. Letonia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14408^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37691</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14408^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
