<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98450</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical liability: professional liability vs. public health service liability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The medical liability is an inseparable phenomenon from the health care that today needs demands from the pragmatic approach and acceptance. Built-in mechanisms are necessary for the health system itself so it can give an adequate solution to difficult situations so that they can be assimilated by the professional and it also represents social requirements needed of an effective answer. The prosecution by criminal liability, in the best of the situations, could be solved promptly, but don´t provide prospective solutions at the problem. In the actual health care systems they tend to look for extrajudicial solutions, allowing a contextual approach that permits, in addition to compensation, actions to improve the system to increase safety and confidence patients and professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riva Moreno, C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríugez Hornillo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serratosa Sánchez-Ibargüen, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La responsabilidad médica es inseparable de la asistencia sanitaria que hoy en día exige planteamientos desde el pragmatismo y la aceptación. Se hacen necesarios mecanismos incorporados al propio sistema sanitario que den una adecuada solución a situaciones difícilmente asimilables por el profesional y que representan un requerimiento social necesitado de respuesta eficaz. La judicialización mediante la vía de la responsabilidad penal puede llegar a dar respuesta puntual en el mejor de los casos, pero no aporta soluciones prospectivas al problema. En los sistemas sanitarios actuales se tiende a la búsqueda de procedimientos extrajudiciales que, desde la despersonalización y la "desculpabilización", permitan un abordaje contextual que, además de indemnizar, plantee acciones de mejora del sistema aumentando la seguridad y confianza de pacientes y profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;17(2): 59-66, abr.-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Responsabilidad sanitaria: responsabilidad personal del médico vs. responsabilidad del sistema sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
