<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049380</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey of nursing roles in anesthesiology, postoperative recovery care and pain management in Catalonia, Spain: analysis of the current situation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To determine nursing functions in anesthesiology, postoperative recovery care, and pain management in Catalan hospitals and to analyze the roles of nurses in this specialty. METHODS: Development of a mail questionnaire sent to 70 public and private hospitals in Catalonia, to be filled in and returned separately by the nursing supervisor and by the anesthesiology department of each hospital. The survey included questions on whether tasks were or were not carried out by nurses. RESULTS: Responses were received from 31% of nursing supervisors and 45% of anesthesiology departments. Only 22% of the hospitals employed nursing staff with duties exclusively in the anesthesiology department. Nurses took on more responsibilities in major outpatient surgery services and postanesthetic recovery care units than in other areas. Significant discrepancies were found between answers given by nursing supervisors and those returned by anesthesiology departments regarding tasks of nurses in this specialty. Items with the greatest agreement were those related to maintenance of material. Those with the lowest agreement were related to drug management. CONCLUSIONS: Although responses came from only a third of the target population, the information obtained suggests a lack of definition in Spain of nursing tasks in the field of anesthesiology. This situation is different from that of most European countries and of the UnitedStates of America (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Conocer las funciones que asume la Enfermería en relación a la Anestesiología, Reanimación y Terapéutica del Dolor en hospitales catalanes y analizar el papel que puede jugar la enfermería en esta especialidad. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Elaboración de una encuesta que se remitió por correo a 70 centros públicos y privados de Cataluña para ser contestada y devuelta de forma separada por la dirección de Enfermería y de Anestesiología de cada centro. La encuesta incluyó preguntas relacionadas con tareas en las que se debía contestar si eran o no desempeñadas por la enfermería. RESULTADOS: La encuesta fue contestada por el 31% de las direcciones de Enfermería y el 45% de las de Anestesiología. Sólo un 22% de los centros disponían de personal de enfermería con tareas exclusivas en anestesia.La enfermería asumía más responsabilidades en las unida desde cirugía mayor ambulatoria y las unidades de recuperación postanestésica que en el resto de los ámbitos.Se observaron importantes discrepancias en las respuestas dadas por las direcciones de Enfermería y de Anestesiología sobre las tareas que realizaba la enfermería durante la anestesia. Las que había mayor coincidencia eran las relacionadas con el mantenimiento del material y las que menos las que implicaba manejo de fármacos. CONCLUSIONES: Aunque sólo respondieron un tercio de los encuestados, la información obtenida pone de manifiesto la indefinición en España de las tareas y funciones que realiza la Enfermería con relación a la Anestesiología, a diferencia de la mayoría de países europeos y Estados Unidos de América (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;53(6): 337-345, jun.-jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre las funciones de enfermería en Anestesiología, Reanimación y Tratamiento del Dolor en Cataluña. Análisis de la situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
