<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154483</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of risk factors for cardiovascular disease in Spanish university workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Cardiovascular diseases (CVD) are the leading cause of death worldwide, so the aim of this study is to analyze the risk factors of cardiovascular disease in workers at the University of Alicante (Alicante, Spain). Material and methods: Descriptive transversal study. Random sample (n = 124), 46.6% women and 53.4% men, aged between 25-68 years. On-line data collection by self-completed questionnaire. Variables: socio-demographic, self-referred weight and height, smoking habit, physical activity, daily consumption of olive oil, fruit-vegetables, butter-margarine-cream and weekly consumption of industrial baking and nuts. A descriptive analysis using SPSS 19.0 statistical package was performed. Results: 12% of women and 10.5% of men over 44 years were classified as obese. Otherwise, 32% and 23.7% of women and men respectively, do not practice any exercise routinely. Olive oil is consumed daily by all the sample studied. Conclusion: The studied eating habits are similar to those considered healthy Mediterranean dietary patterns. Daily olive oil consumption together with regular physical activity has an important role as protectors of CVD. The work environment studied has a positive influence in healthy habits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Moncada, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sospedra López, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado Sánchez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Norte Navarro, Aurora Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sanz, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sansano Perea, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: las enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV) son la principal causa de muerte mundial, por ello el objetivo de este estudio es analizar los factores de riesgo de ECV en los trabajadores de la Universidad de Alicante. Material y métodos: estudio transversal descriptivo. Muestra aleatoria (n = 124), 46,6% mujeres y 53,4% hombres, de edades entre 25-68 años. Recogida de datos mediante cuestionario online autocumplimentado. Variables: sociodemográficas, peso y talla autorreferidos, consumo de tabaco, actividad física, consumo diario de aceite de oliva, hortalizas-verduras, mantequilla-margarina-nata y consumo semanal de repostería comercial y frutos secos. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo con el paquete estadístico SPSS 19.0. Resultados: el 12% de mujeres y el 10,5% de los hombres mayores de 44 años presentan obesidad; además, el 32% de mujeres y el 23,7% de los hombres no realizan actividad física. Consume aceite de oliva a diario el total de la muestra a estudio. Conclusión: los hábitos alimentarios de los estudiados se asemejan a los patrones dietéticos mediterráneos considerados saludables. Destacar el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones de consumo de aceite de oliva y la realización de actividad física habitual como protectores de las ECV. El entorno laboral de la población estudiada favorece unos hábitos saludables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 644-648, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de factores de riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular en trabajadores universitarios españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55398</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
