<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048509</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Macroprolactin detection in the differential diagnosis of Hyperprolactinemia. Evaluation of a screening protocol for Macroprolactin detection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of macroprolactin should be considered in thedifferential diagnosis of hyperprolactinemia. Macroprolactinconsists of an G immunoglobulin molecule bound to a prolactinmolecule. In this form it is relatively resistant to degradationand rises to high levels serum prolactin. Almost, if not all, ofthe immunoassays detect macroprolactin but to varyingdegrees.In our hosptal we have used a polyethylene glycol precipitationprotocol to detect the presence of macroprolactinemiaamong patients with basal prolactin higher than 40 ng/mL. Wehave confirmed the presence of macroprolactinemia in the15,94% of them (IC95% 10,4 &#150; 23,3).Misdiagnosis in these patients may lead to inappropiateinvestigations and treatments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de macroprolactina debe tenerse en cuenta en eldiagnóstico diferencial de la hiperprolactinemia. La macroprolactinaestá constituida por una molécula de inmunoglobulina G unidaa la prolactina monomérica. En esta forma es relativamenteresistente a la degradación y eleva la concentración sérica deprolactina. Casi todos, si no todos, los inmunoensayos detectanla presencia de macroprolactina pero en diferente grado.En nuestro hospital hemos implantado un protocolo de precipitacióncon polietilengicol para detectar la presencia de macroprolactina,en todos los pacientes con valores de prolactina basalsuperiores a 40 ng/mL. Se ha detectado la presencia de macroprolactinemiaen el 15,94% de los casos analizados(IC 95% 10,4 &#150; 23,3).No diagnosticar esta situación clínica puede llevar a las pacientesa ser sometidas a pruebas y tratamientos innecesarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. diagn. biol;55(1): 22-25, ene.-mar. 2006. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de la presencia de Macroprolactina como parte integrante del diagnostico diferencial de la Hiperprolactinemia. Evaluación de la introducción de un protocolo para detectar la presencia de Macroprolactinemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11821^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
