<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96505</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of the Primary Care physicians on a Rehabilitation Service: are there differences between the healthcare centers with physical presence of a rehabilitation center and those that do not have it?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Physical medicine and rehabilitation should be considered within the biopsychosocial approach, providing a coherent view of the different health dimensions. In order to achieve this, it is essential to develop rehabilitation on the first care level. This study arose in order to know the opinion between the Primary Care Physicians (PCP) of 2 Healthcare Centers of area II of Zaragoza on the same rehabilitation service (RHBS), differences being observed between both, since one of the centers had a physical presence of the RHBS and the other did not. Materials and methods. A cross-sectional study was performed within an anonymous survey, evaluating 9 items, submitted to 244 medical specialists of the Healthcare Centers Fuentes Norte and San José Norte-Centro. Results. Participation: 72.7%, mostly in Fuentes Norte. Physical integration of the RHBS in the healthcare centers is essential for 94%. Current satisfaction with the RHBS is high in 37.5%. Grade of agreement with the treatments is very high and 50% in useful information always and 56%. On the contrary, delay time of the 1st visit is considered excessive and 97% in the follow-up of patients except about 478% the combined training with rehabilitation would be of interest for 97%. Conclusions. We found a consensus regarding excessive time of delay, interest in joint training and the need to have a consensus on referral and management criteria. On the contrary, there were large differences in other aspects, such as grade of agreement with the treatments and information received, greater satisfaction being much higher in the center with physical presence of the RHBS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morata Crespo, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escriche Ros, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La medicina física y rehabilitación ha de considerarse bajo un enfoque biopsicosocial, proporcionando una visión coherente de las diferentes dimensiones de salud; para conseguirlo es fundamental el desarrollo de la rehabilitación en el primer nivel asistencial. Este estudio nace con objeto de conocer la opinión entre los Médicos de Atención Primaria (MAP) de dos Centros de Salud (CS) del área II de Zaragoza sobre un mismo Servicio de Rehabilitación (SRHB), observando diferencias entre ambos, pues uno goza de presencia física del SRHB y otro no. Material y método. Estudio transversal por medio de encuesta anónima, valorando 9 ítems, presentada a 44 facultativos de los CS Fuentes Norte y San José Norte-Centro. Resultados. Participación: 72,7%, mayoritariamente del CS de Fuentes Norte. La integración física del SRHB en los Centro de Atención Primaria (CAP) resulta imprescindible para el 94%, la satisfacción actual con el SRHB es alto en el 37,5%, el grado de acuerdo con los tratamientos muy alto en el 50%, y la información útil siempre en el 56%. Por el contrario, el tiempo de demora de la primera consulta es considerado excesivo para el 97% y el seguimiento de pacientes aceptable para el 78%. La formación conjunta con rehabilitación resultaría de interés para el 97%. Conclusiones. Encontramos consenso en cuestiones como el tiempo excesivo de demora, el interés por la formación conjunta y la necesidad de consensuar criterios de derivación y manejo. Por el contrario, existen grandes diferencias en otros aspectos, tales como el grado de acuerdo con los tratamientos, y la información recibida, siendo el grado de satisfacción muy superior en el centro con presencia física del SRHB(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);46(1): 55-59, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96505</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opinión de los médicos de Atención Primaria de un Servicio de Rehabilitación: ¿existen diferencias entre los centros de salud con presencia física del SRHB y los que no?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
