<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050559</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraintestinal manifestations of Crohn's disease: prevalence and related factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: patients with inflammatory bowel disease maysuffer one or more extraintestinal manifestations during thecourse of their condition, these being more frequent in Crohn'sdisease. The aim of our study was to evaluate the prevalence ofextraintestinal manifestations in patients with Crohn's disease inour healthcare area, and to assess the relationship between itspresence and diverse clinical-evolutionary variables.Material and methods: extraintestinal manifestations in 157patients diagnosed with Crohn's disease in our center were retrospectivelystudied. The clinical-evolutionary characteristics of thispopulation were compared with respect to the presence or absenceof different extraintestinal manifestations.Results: seventy-two patients (46%) presented at least withone extraintestinal manifestation. Thirty-one percent were colitisrelatedmanifestations (22% rheumatologic, 13% muco-cutaneous,4% ophthalmologic), 11% cholelithiasis, 8% nephrolithiasis,3% thromboembolic illness, and other manifestations wereless frequent. Fourteen percent presented with more than one extraintestinalmanifestation. Rheumatologic and muco-cutaneousmanifestations were significantly more frequent in patients withdisease confined to the colon. Cholelithiasis was significantly associatedto those over 40 and also to males. Nephrolithiasis was alsosignificantly associated to those over 40, and thromboembolic illnesswas linked to females.Conclusions: forty-six percent of patients with Crohn's diseasepresented at least with one extraintestinal manifestation.Thirty-one percent presented with colitis-related manifestations,rheumatologic and muco-cutaneous manifestations being the mostfrequent, whereas hepatic manifestations were infrequent.Rheumatologic and muco-cutaneous manifestations were morefrequent in patients with disease confined to the colon</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Grueso, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carboles, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Rosas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Repiso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Merlo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcántara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Potenciano, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinalpueden sufrir a lo largo de su evolución una o más manifestacionesextraintestinales, siendo estas más frecuentes en la enfermedadde Crohn. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue valorar laprevalencia de las manifestaciones extraintestinales en los pacientescon enfermedad de Crohn en nuestro medio y la relación existenteentre su presencia y diversas variables clínico-evolutivas.Material y métodos: se recogieron de modo retrospectivolas manifestaciones extraintestinales de 157 pacientes diagnosticadosde enfermedad de Crohn en nuestro centro. Se compararonlas características clínico-evolutivas de esta población con respectoa la presencia o ausencia de las distintas manifestacionesextraintestinales.Resultados: setenta y dos pacientes (46%) presentaban almenos una manifestación extraintestinal. El 31% eran colíticas(22% articulares, 13% cutáneo-mucosas, 4% oculares), 11% colelitiasis,8% litiasis renal y 3% enfermedad tromboembólica. Otrasmanifestaciones presentaban una menor frecuencia. El 14% presentaronmás de una manifestación extraintestinal. Las manifestacionesarticulares y cutáneo-mucosas fueron significativamentemás frecuentes en la localización colónica. La colelitiasis se asociabasignificativamente con la edad mayor de 40 años y el sexomasculino. La litiasis renal se asociaba significativamente con laedad y la enfermedad tromboembólica con el sexo femenino.Conclusiones: el 46% de los pacientes con enfermedad deCrohn presentaron al menos una manifestación extraintestinal. El31% presentaban manifestaciones colíticas, siendo las articularesy cutáneo-mucosas las más frecuentes, mientras que las hepáticasfueron infrecuentes. Las manifestaciones articulares y cutáneomucosasfueron más frecuentes en la localización colónica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(7): 510-517, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones extraintestinales de la enfermedad de Crohn. Prevalencia y factores relacionados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
