<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137404</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurobiological correlates of object relations theory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This is an overview of present neurobiological understanding of early development that is relevant for the assumptions of contemporary psychoanalytic object relations theory. There are some major areas of neurobiological investigation that provide a neurobiological background and a foundation for the analysis of early development of internalized object relations. These areas of neurobiological development include the activation of affective systems, the differentiation of the self from others, the development of a theory of mind and of empathy, the evolution of self-structure, and the development of processes of metallization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kernberg, Otto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta es una revisión del actual conocimiento neurobiológico del desarrollo temprano en relación con la teoría psicoanalítica contemporánea de las relaciones objetales. La investigación neurobiológica provee una base para el análisis del desarrollo temprano de las relaciones de objetos internalizados. Las áreas relevantes de desarrollo neurobiológico incluyen la activación de sistemas afectivos, la diferenciación del self y de los otros, el desarrollo de una teoría de la mente y de la empatía, la evolución de la estructura del self y el desarrollo del proceso de mentalización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(24): 9-18, nov. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlatos neurobiológicos de la teoría de las relaciones de objeto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
