<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93890</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To study the possible association between gynecomastia  and breast cancer in men. Material and methods: A retrospective case-control study was designed. Male patients older than 14 years old with breast disorder undergoing surgery in our hospital between January 1996 and December 2009 were included. Two groups of patients were made, those with malignant disease and those with benign lesions. Results: The total number of cases analyzed was 49, 10 with pathological diagnosis of breast cancer and 39 of benign disease. A significant difference was found only for age at onset of gynecomastia and relative risk of breast cancer (p = 0.002). Conclusions: Although it was not possible to demonstrate that gynecomastia is a risk factor for breast cancer, it must be a differential diagnosis to be considered in patients with gynecomastia. According to our results, this suspicion should be higher with increasing patient age(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortea, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrig, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ramos, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivadulla, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daroca, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la posible relación entre la ginecomastia y el cáncer de mama en el varón. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo con revisión de los pacientes varones, mayores de 14 años, con ginecomastia intervenidos quirúrgicamente en nuestro hospital desde enero del año 1996 hasta diciembre de 2009. Para el análisis de los datos, los casos se dividieron en 2 grupos, atendiendo a la benignidad o malignidad en el estudio anatomopatológico. Resultados: El número total de casos analizados fue de 49, de los que 10 presentaron un diagnóstico anatomopatológico de cáncer de mama y 39 de patología benigna. Se ha encontrado una relación estadísticamente significativa entre la edad de presentación de la ginecomastia y el riesgo relativo de padecer cáncer de mama (p = 0,002). Conclusiones: Aunque no se ha podido demostrar que la ginecomastia sea un factor de riesgo para el cáncer de mama, este debe ser un diagnóstico diferencial a tener en cuenta en pacientes con ginecomastia. Según nuestros resultados, esta sospecha debería ser mayor cuanto mayor sea la edad del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);24(4): 141-145, 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ginecomastia y cáncer de mama en el varón. Estudio de 49 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53836^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6328^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32331^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32331^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32331^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53836^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6328^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32331^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6328^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53836^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
