<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91818</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Deep brain stimulation for refractory epilepsy: extrathalamic targets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Epilepsy is a neurological disorder that affects 1-2% of the population. The majority of epileptic patients achieve a good seizure control with the current available treatments. However, there is a subgroup of patients that remain severely disable despite the variety of anti-epileptic drugs, the possibility of surgery for resection of the epileptogenic foci in selected  patients, and vagal nerve stimulation; various lines of research are being carried out to look for new treatment alternatives.Deep brain stimulation (DBS) of the thalamus has emerged as a therapeutic alternative for patients who remain incapacitated; the efficacy of this new therapy is subject of several studies, and its effectiveness and safety has not been established yet. There are other targets for deep brain stimulation that may be useful for drug-resistant epilepsy. Experiments with animal models and preliminary human studies have shown encouraging results with DBS on cerebellum, subthalamic nucleus, substantia nigra, hippocampus and cerebral cortex, among others. The purpose of this review is to  revisit the studies that have been carried out on these brain nuclei, as targets for DBS for drug-resistant epilepsy. Studies  have shown varying degrees of effectiveness, and there is a need for controlled trials to draw any definite conclusions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, Cristina V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, Rafael G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete, Eduardo G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. La epilepsia es un trastorno neurológico que afecta a alrededor de un 1-2% de la población. Se han desarrollado diversas estrategias terapéuticas, útiles para el control de las crisis en la mayoría de los casos. A pesar del gran desarrollo de fármacos antiepilépticos, de la posibilidad de resección de los focos epileptógenos en pacientes seleccionados y de la estimulación vagal, existe un subgrupo de pacientes con mal control de sus crisis, para los que se están llevando a cabo  diversas líneas de investigación en busca de nuevas alternativas de tratamiento. La estimulación cerebral profunda del tálamo ha surgido como otra posibilidad terapéutica para pacientes que permanecen incapacitados; su utilidad es objeto de varios estudios, y aún no se ha establecido su eficacia y seguridad con suficiente evidencia científica. Existen otras dianas susceptibles de estimulación cerebral profunda como tratamiento para la epilepsia resistente. Los experimentos con modelos animales y estudios preliminares en humanos han mostrado resultados esperanzadores con estimulación cerebral profunda en el cerebelo, núcleo subtalámico, sustancia negra, hipocampo y corteza cerebral, entre otros. A continuación se muestran los estudios realizados en núcleos cerebrales extratalámicos que mostraron eficacia en la epilepsia farmacorresistente. Los estudios han mostrado distintos grados de efectividad, y es preciso realizar ensayos controlados para establecer conclusiones definitivas sobre su eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;53(3): 153-164, ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación cerebral profunda para la epilepsia resistente: dianas extratalámicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2460^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38807^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34057^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
