<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120274</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endocrinometabolic disorders in chronic obstructive pulmonary  disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is characterized by the presence of chronic airflow obstruction and associated endocrinometabolic disorders, which usually worsen the clinic and prognostic of the patients. Therefore, in-depth knowledge of these prevalent disorders in patients with COPD is relevant to develop preventive measures and early detection. PURPOSE: To analyze the prevalence of endocrinometabolic diseases that occur in COPD subjects and their related risk factors. METHODS: We carried out a bibliographic search of the bibliographic resources of the last 10 years, including PubMed, Scopus and Science Direct databases. Words used were: "endocrine metabolic disorders AND COPD", "endocrine disorders AND COPD" and "metabolic disorders AND COPD". The bibliographical analysis was made in two steps. During the first phase, we excluded those articles in which the title or their content did not correspond with the objective settled; during the second phase, we deleted all the references duplicated in both databases. Finally, 17 articles after full-text critical appraisal were maintained. RESULTS: After reviewing the articles, we found a significant relationship between diabetes mellitus, metabolic syndrome, obesity, osteoporosis, hypogonadism and COPD. Different authors have reported a higher prevalence of these comorbidities, influencing the development of COPD. CONCLUSIONS : Due to the high prevalence and association with COPD, these comorbidities have to be considered by the health professionals related to the COPD patients. Better understanding of the endocrinometabolic disorders related to COPD can influence the treatment and the outcome of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano-Capellaci, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenza-Demet, Gerald</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Sánchez, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera-Martos, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenza, Marie Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) se caracteriza por obstrucción crónica del flujo aéreo y se asocia frecuentemente a alteraciones endocrino-metabólicas que empeoran la situación clínica del paciente y su pronóstico. El conocimiento en profundidad de estas alteraciones en los pacientes con EPOC permite llevar a cabo medidas preventivas, detección temprana e intervenciones nutricionales adecuadas. Objetivos: Analizar la prevalencia de comorbilidades endocrino-metabólicas en pacientes con EPOC y los factores de riesgo que favorecen la aparición de dichas enfermedades. Métodos: Se desarrolló una estrategia de búsqueda exhaustiva de la literatura limitada a los últimos diez años, en las bases de datos PubMed, Scopus y ScienceDirect, usando las palabras clave &#147;endocrine metabolic disorders AND COPD&#148;, &#147;endocrine disorders AND COPD&#148; y &#147;metabolic disorders AND COPD&#148;. &#148;. En el análisis bibliográfico se excluyeron aquellos artículos cuyo título o contenido no se correspondía con el objetivo del presente estudio, así como los artículos duplicados en las bases de datos. Finalmente, tras una profunda lectura crítica, fueron seleccionados y analizados 17 artículos. Resultados: El análisis de los artículos ha mostrado una relación significativa entre la EPOC y la presencia de alteraciones endocrino-metabólicas tales como diabetes mellitus, síndrome metabólico, obesidad, osteoporosis e hipogonadismo. Los autores coinciden en la alta prevalencia de estas comorbilidades, que influyen de forma diferente en el desarrollo de la EPOC. Conclusiones: Debido a la alta prevalencia y asociación con la EPOC, estas comorbilidades han de ser tenidas en cuenta por el profesional sanitario, ya que pueden afectar su abordaje, intervención y resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(4): 1022-1030, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones endocrinometabólicas en la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
