<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17690</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac blockade after changing central venous catheter, on a guide, for total parenteral nutrition. Can it be avoided?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Catheterization of central veins is a routine process, especially in severely-ill patients. It is a technique associated with multiple potential complications, fortunately infrequent, depending on the skill with which it is performed.  Cardiac blockade is one of these infrequent complications with a high mortality. We describe a case in which suspicion, early diagnosis, and immediate manipulative treatment allowed a successful recovery of the patient.  In addition, the literature is reviewed and possible mechanisms involved in these episodes are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cateterización de venas centrales es un proceso rutinario, sobre todo en enfermos graves. Es una técnica en la que están descritas múltiples complicaciones, afortunadamente no muy frecuentes, y en relación con la pericia del que la realiza. El taponamiento cardíaco es una de estas infrecuentes complicaciones, con muy elevada mortalidad. Describimos un caso en el que por sospecha, diagnóstico precoz y tratamiento inmediato se siguió de éxito en las maniobras de recuperación del enfermo. Asimismo, se revisa la literatura y se analizan los posibles mecanismos de estos episodios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;18(1): 46-50, ene. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taponamiento cardíaco tras cambio de catéter venoso central, sobre guía, para nutrición parenteral total. ¿Lo podemos evitar?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Borregán, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Díaz de Lamadrid, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rico, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17690</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d34529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
