<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100756</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transient global amnesia after general anaesthesia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transient global amnesia is a neurological syndrome in which there is a sudden and brief inability to form new memories, as well as an intense retrograde amnesia. However, awareness, personal identity and attention remain intact. It is an uncommon condition seen after an anaesthetic procedure. There are several aetiopathogenic hypotheses (epileptic, migrainous or ischaemic origin) and triggering factors (pain, anxiety, temperature changes, exercise, Valsalva manoeuvres, diagnostic tests or certain drugs). We describe the case of a patient with a high level of pre-operative anxiety who suffered an episode of transient global amnesia after undergoing otolaryngology surgery. With an acute and continued amnesia after general anaesthesia, the first thing that must be done is to establish a suitable differencial diagnosis, which should include transient global amnesia, as this is mainly an exclusion diagnosis. Preoperative anxiety may be a triggering factor to take into account in this condition, with anxiolytic treatment prior to the surgery being important(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lablanca, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zannin, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galipienzo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olarra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarza, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La amnesia global transitoria es un síndrome neurológico en el que se produce una pérdida abrupta y pasajera de la capacidad para crear nuevos recuerdos, así como una amnesia retrógrada de intensidad variable, permaneciendo, sin embargo, preservadas la conciencia, la identidad personal y la atención. Se trata de una entidad poco frecuente tras un proceso anestésico. Existen distintas hipótesis etiopatogénicas (base epiléptica, migrañosa o isquémica) y desencadenantes (dolor, la ansiedad, los cambios de temperatura, el ejercicio, las maniobras de Valsalva, las pruebas diagnósticas o determinados medicamentos). Describimos el caso de una paciente con alto grado de ansiedad preoperatoria que sufrió un episodio de amnesia global transitoria tras una intervención quirúrgica otorrinolaringológica. Ante un episodio de amnesia aguda y mantenida tras una anestesia general debemos plantear, en primer lugar, un adecuado diagnóstico diferencial que incluya la amnesia global transitoria, puesto que, en la mayoría de los casos, se trata de un diagnóstico de exclusión. La ansiedad preoperatoria puede ser un desencadenante a tener en cuenta en esta entidad, siendo importante el tratamiento ansiolítico previo a la intervención(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(6): 335-338, jun.-jul. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amnesia global transitoria en el contexto de una anestesia general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d662^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d662^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d663^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d663^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27899^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d663^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
