<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153885</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of semen parameters in men attending at fertility centers in Perú and México</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To determine the seminal parameter most frequent in patients attending in the city of Chiclayo (27 m) and Mé- xico D.F (2240 m). Characterize and compare the sperm parameters of the patients attending in the two cities. Material and methods: Prospective study conducted at the Laboratory of Andrology &#147;In Vitro Gestar&#148; (Chiclayo &#150; Perú) (n=102 patients, Normozoospermic=56) and HISPAREP, Center for Assisted Reproduction, Spanish Hospital, Mexico D.F (n=115 patients, Normozoospermic=13), from October 2013 to August 2014. The semen samples were analyzed according to the criteria of WHO 2010. For determination of the median was used SPSS 22 software. Results: It was determined the sperm morphology (78.3%) and progressive motility (24.5%) were the semen parameters affected most frequent in México and Perú respectively. We determined significant differences (P=0.000) in the median in the parameters of concentration (106 /ml) (36.60 vs 76,50), progressive motility (%) (33.00 vs 49.20), normal morphology (%) (2.00 vs 5.00), vitality (%) (75.00 vs 85.00) in the total population of México and Perú, respectively. We determined significant differences in the median of the progressive motility (%) (44.00 vs 55.90 P=0.003) of the normozoospermic samples in the population of México and Perú, respectively. Conclusions: The main cause of male infertility differs from one population to another. It was shown that there significant difference in the semen parameters of the male attending in Chiclayo and México D.F. Among the patients was found significant differences in the progressive motility. We can attribute these differences due to geographical variations, altitude differences, endocrine, genetic, ethnic, lifestyle between the two countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salazar López Ortiz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Campos, Láyonal Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Miñano, Carlos Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuapio Padilla, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez Velasco, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar el parámetro espermático más frecuente en los pacientes atendidos en la ciudad de Chiclayo (27 msnm) y México D.F (2240 msnm). Caracterizar y comparar los parámetros espermáticos de los pacientes atendidos en las dos ciudades. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo realizado en el Laboratorio de Andrología de IN VITRO GESTAR, Chiclayo &#150; Perú (n=102 pacientes, Normozoospermicos =56) y HISPAREP, Centro de Reproducción Asistida, Hospital Español, México D.F (n=115 pacientes, Normozoospermicos=13), durante los meses de Octubre 2013 a Agosto 2014. Las muestras seminales fueron analizadas siguiendo los criterios de la OMS 2010. Para la determinación de la mediana (test no paramétrico) se utilizo el software SPSS 22. Resultados: Se determino que la morfología espermática (78,3 %) y la movilidad progresiva  (24,5 %) fueron los parámetros  seminales afectado más frecuentes en México y Perú respectivamente. Se encontraron diferencias significativas (P=0,000) en la mediana en los parámetros de concentración (106/ml) (36,60 vs 76,50), movilidad progresiva (%) (33,00 vs 49,20), morfología normal (%) (2,00 vs 5,00), vitalidad (%) (75,00 vs 85,00) en la población total de México y Perú respectivamente. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en la mediana de la movilidad progresiva (%) (44,00 vs 55,90 P=0,003) de la muestras normozoospermicas en la población de México y Perú respectivamente. Conclusiones: La causa principal de infertilidad masculina difiere de una población a otra. Se demostró que existen diferencias significativas en los parámetros seminales de los varones atendidos en Chiclayo y México D.F. Entre los pacientes normozoospermicos se encontró diferencias significativas en el parámetro de la movilidad progresiva. Podemos atribuir estas diferencias debido a las variaciones geográficas, diferencia de altitudes, endocrinas, genética, étnica, tipo de vida que existen entre ambos países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;33(2): 25-30, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de los parámetros seminales en varones atendidos en centros de fertilidad de Perú y México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13043^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9128^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37634^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13474^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13474^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
