<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128749</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening of polyphenolic compounds in Piper trioicum (Roxb. ) extracts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: Present study aims to reveal the polyphenol content in Piper trioicum (Roxb.) extracts. Materials and methods: In the present study, the phenolic content of the ethanol and water extracts of Piper trioicum (Roxb.) plants was determined by chromatography techniques like Thin layer chromatography, high performance thin layer Chromatography, high performance liquid chromatography and Gas chromatography with Mass spectrometric detection. Total phenol was determined by UV method. Results: All the results of analytical methods were compared with standard phenolic compounds. The ethanol extract contained maximum total phenolic content (2.323mg GAE/g) than the water extract. 13 compounds identified by chromatography techniques. The results suggested Arbutin, quercetin, caffeic acid, Ferulic acid, chlorogenic acid, Gallic acid and its derivatives may be present in ethanolic and water extracts of Piper trioicum. Conclusions: The water and ethanol could extract the highest concentration of polyphenols from the Piper trioicum (Roxb) plant; these extracts may have a good pharmacological potency due to the presence of polyphenols compounds (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>David, Banji</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Harani, Avasarala</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kumar, Dinakaran Sathis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veena, Mandarapu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El presente estudio tiene como objetivo revelar el contenido de polifenoles en extractos de Piper trioicum ( Roxb. ). Materiales y métodos: El contenido de fenoles totales en los extractos etanólicos y acuosos de Piper trioicum ( Roxb. ) se determinó mediante técnicas cromatografías, como la cromatografía en capa fina, cromatografía en capa fina de alto rendimiento, cromatografía líquida de alta resolución y cromatografía de gases con espectrometría de masas detección. El contenido de fenoles totales se determinó por el método UV. Resultados: Los resultados de los métodos de análisis se compararon con compuestos fenólicos estándar . Los extractos de etanol tienen un contenido mayor de fenoles totales ( 2.323mg GAE / g ) que los extracto acuosos. Se han identificado 13 compuestos por técnicas de cromatografía . Los resultados sugirieron que arbutina, quercetina, ácido caféico, ácido ferúlico, ácido clorogénico, ácido gálico y sus derivados puede estar presente en los extractos etanólicos y acuoso de Piper trioicum. Conclusiones: El agua y el etanol podrían extraer la mayor concentración de polifenoles de la planta Piper trioicum (Roxb); estos extractos pueden tener un buen potencial farmacológico debido a la presencia de compuestos fenolicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;55(3): 27-34[3], jul.-sept. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado de compuestos polifenólicos en extractos de Piper trioicum (Roxb. )</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37012^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10828^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37012^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10828^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10828^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
