<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141545</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of estimated glomerular filtration rate equations for dosing new oral anticoagulants in patients with atrial fibrillation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: New oral anticoagulants require dosing adjustment according to renal function. We aimed to determine discordance in hypothetical recommended dosing of these drugs using different estimated glomerular filtration rate equations in patients with atrial fibrillation. Methods:  Cross-sectional analysis of 910 patients with atrial fibrillation and an indication for oral anticoagulation. The glomerular filtration rate was estimated using the Cockcroft-Gault, Modification of Diet in Renal Disease and Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration equations. For dabigatran, rivaroxaban, and apixaban we identified dose discordance when there was disagreement in the recommended dose based on different equations. One-hundred samples from 54 patients with virologic breakthrough during entecavir, lamivudine or adefovir treatment and 21 samples from 21 nucleoside-naïve patients were tested by direct sequencing and an updated line probe assay (Innogenetics, HBV DR v.3) which incorporates probes that can detect mutations at 11 positions of the reverse transcriptase region of the HBV polymerase gene. Results: Among the overall population, relative to Cockcroft-Gault, discordance in dabigatran dosage was 11.4% for Modification of Diet in Renal Disease and 10% for Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration, discordance in rivaroxaban dosage was 10% for Modification of Diet in Renal Disease and 8.5% for the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration. The lowest discordance was observed for apixaban: 1.4% for Modification of Diet in Renal Disease and 1.5% for the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration. In patients with Cockcroft-Gault &lt; 60 mL/min or elderly patients, discordances in dabigatran and rivaroxaban dosages were higher, ranging from 13.2% to 30.4%. Discordance in apixaban dosage remained &lt; 5% in these patients. Conclusions:  Discordance in (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu-Cayuelas, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lip,  Gregory Y. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzano-Fernández, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orenes-Piñero, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los nuevos anticoagulantes orales requieren ajuste de la posología según la función renal. El objetivo de este estudio es determinar la discrepancia existente entre la hipotética posología recomendada de estos fármacos empleando diferentes ecuaciones de filtrado glomerular estimado en pacientes con fibrilación auricular. Métodos: Análisis transversal de 910 pacientes con fibrilación auricular e indicación de anticoagulación oral. Se estimó el filtrado glomerular con las ecuaciones de Cockcroft-Gault, Modification of Diet in Renal Disease y Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration. Para dabigatrán, rivaroxabán y apixabán, se identificaron discrepancias de la dosis cuando no coincidían con las dosis recomendadas según se usara una u otra ecuación. Resultados: En el conjunto de la población, respecto a la ecuación de Cockcroft-Gault, la discrepancia de la posología de dabigatrán fue del 11,4% con la ecuación Modification of Diet in Renal Disease y del 10 con la Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration; las discrepancias de la posología de rivaroxabán fueron del 10% y el 8,5% respectivamente. La menor discrepancia se observó con apixabán: el 1,4% con la primera y el 1,5% con la segunda. En los pacientes con un valor según la ecuación de Cockcroft-Gault &lt; 60 ml/min o en los pacientes ancianos, las discrepancias en las posologías de dabigatrán y rivaroxabán fueron superiores, entre el 13,2 y el 30,4%. La discrepancia en cuanto a la posología de apixabán se mantuvo en un valor &lt; 5% en estos pacientes. Conclusiones: La discrepancia en las posologías de los nuevos anticoagulantes orales empleando ecuaciones distintas es frecuente, sobre todo (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(6): 497-504, jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las ecuaciones de filtrado glomerular estimado para determinar la posología de los nuevos anticoagulantes orales para pacientes con fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
