<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163705</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serum potassium concentrations: Importance of normokalaemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abnormalities in potassium concentrations are associated with morbidity and mortality. In recent years it has been considered that small variations in serum potassium concentrations within normal intervals may also be associated with mortality. Strategies for achieving normokalaemia include dietary measures, limiting the use of potassium retaining drugs, and use of conventional cation exchange resins (calcium/sodium polystyrene sulfonate) and/or the new non-absorbed cation exchange polymer (patiromer) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Reyes, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las anomalías en las concentraciones de potasio se asocian con morbimortalidad. En los últimos años se está considerando que pequeñas variaciones en las concentraciones séricas de potasio dentro del intervalo de la normalidad también pueden asociarse con mortalidad. Las estrategias para conseguir la normopotasemia incluyen medidas dietéticas, limitar el uso de fármacos que retienen potasio y emplear resinas de intercambio catiónico clásicas (poliestireno sulfonato cálcico/sódico) o el nuevo polímero no absorbible de intercambio catiónico (patiromer) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(12): 562-565, jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163705</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones séricas de potasio: importancia de la normopotasemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30603^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7128^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7186^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11626^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2450^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
