<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164048</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of gestational vascular complications and thrombosis in women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The main objectives were to establish the prevalence of thrombophilia in pregnancy-related thrombosis and vascular placental complications and to evaluate the clinical management of these complications. Materials and methods: Multicenter, prospective and observational study. We analysed 4 patient cohorts: thrombosis, thrombosis prophylaxis, vascular placental complications, vascular placental complications prophylaxis. A total of 1032 episodes were registeredand 994 were included in the final analysis. Results: The distribution of the episodes was: 5.5% thrombosis, 30.2% thrombosis prophylaxis, 35.7% vascular placental complications and 24.9% vascular placental complications prophylaxis. Pregnancy loss was the most frequent complication registered. Thrombophilia studies were made in 82.6% patients in vascular placental complications cohort and in 70.2% of thrombosis patients. Positive results were obtained in 47% of patients in thrombosis group and in 21% of patients with vascular placental complications. In this group the most common defects found were high levels of FVIII, positive antiphospholipid antibodies and homocigosity for F12C46T polymorphism. Antithrombotic treatment was used in 85% of thrombosis prophylaxis episodes and in 77% of vascular placental complications prophylaxis episodes. Pharmacologic prophylaxis was not related with a better pregnancy outcome in vascular placental complications prophylaxis group. Conclusions: Thrombophilia studies were made to most patients in this registry. Results were different in patients with thrombosis and vascular placental complications. Most patients in vascular placental complications prophylaxis group with or without thrombophilia recieved LMWH +/- aspirin, but we did not find a benefit of these treatments. Further studies with more patients will be needed to confirm our findings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López de la Fuente, Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Ortiz, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Huerta, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Mallén, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Sáez, Edelmira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stevenazzi Rivas, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tàssies Penella, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas Caro, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguinaco Culebreras, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver Samper, Artur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Izal, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Fornés, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la prevalencia de trombofilia en trombosis gestacional y complicaciones vasulares gestacionales en nuestro entorno y el manejo de las mismas. Material y métodos: estudio prospectivo y observacional en el que se incluyeron cuatro cohortes: trombosis, profilaxis de trombosis, complicaciones vasulares gestacionales, profilaxis de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales. Se registraron 1.032 episodios, de los cuales se incluyeron 994 en el análisis final. Resultados: la distribución de episodios fue: 5,5% trombosis, 30,2% profilaxis de trombosis, 35,7% complicaciones vasulares gestacionales y 24,9% profilaxis de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales. Las pérdidas gestacionales fueron la complicación más frecuente. Se realizó estudio de trombofilia en 82,6% de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales y 70,2% de trombosis. Los resultados fueron positivos en el 47% de trombosis y en 21% de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales. Los defectos más comunes en complicaciones vasulares gestacionales fueron la elevación del factor VIII, la presencia de anticuerpos antifosfolípidos y la mutación F12C46T en homocigosis. Se empleó tratamiento antitrombótico en el 85% de profilaxis de trombosis y en el 77% de profilaxis de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales. La tromboprofilaxis de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales no se relacionó con una mejora en el resultado de la gestación. Conclusiones: se realizaron estudios de trombofilia a la mayoría de las pacientes, con resultados diferentes en trombosis y complicaciones vasulares gestacionales. Se empleó tromboprofilaxis en más del 70% de las pacientes. La profilaxis farmacológica de complicaciones vasulares gestacionales no aportó beneficio significativo. Serían necesarios estudios futuros para confirmar nuestros resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);60(2): 107-113, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de las complicaciones vasculares gestacionales y trombosis en la mujer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11689^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
