<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150441</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervicofacial necrotizing fasciitis: a rare disease with a high mortality requiring early debridement for survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. To review the clinical experience, management and outcome of cervicofacial necrotizing fasciitis (CFN) in patients treated in our institution. Methods. A retrospective review of patients with CFN from two large health care institutions completed over a 10-year period. Results. Five patients with complete data were identified. CNF was polymicrobial in 4 and monomicrobial in one patient and occurred as a result of odontogenic infection in 3, trauma in 1, and was idiopathic in one patient. All patients were treated with extensive debridement, broad spectrum antibiotics, and reconstruction with flaps. There was one death. Conclusions. Early diagnosis and rapid aggressive debridement are key elements for reducing mortality and optimizing the cosmetic and functional outcome in patients with CFN (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>McHenry, Christopher R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meneses Rivadeneira, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Alan Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito. Revisar la experiencia clínica, el manejo quirúrgico y los resultados del tratamiento de pacientes con fasceítis necrosante cervicofacial (FNC) en nuestras instituciones. Métodos. Un estudio retrospectivo de pacientes con FNC en un periodo de 10 años en 2 instituciones académicas. Resultados. Cinco pacientes con datos completos (clínicos, imágenes, cultivos microbiológicos, tratamiento y seguimiento) fueron identificados. La FNC resultó de una infección polimicrobiana en 4 pacientes y monomicrobiana en un paciente. La etiología de FNC fue odontogénica en 3 pacientes, postraumatismo en un paciente e idiopática en un paciente. Todos los pacientes fueron tratados con tratamiento quirúrgico (desbridamiento) agresivo temprano, antibióticos de amplio espectro y reconstrucción con diferentes tipos de colgajos. Se registró una mortalidad. Conclusiones. El diagnóstico temprano y un tratamiento quirúrgico agresivo son elementos clave en reducir la mortalidad y optimizar los resultados funcionales y cosméticos en los pacientes con FNC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(1): 23-28, ene.-mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fasceítis necrosante cervicofacial: una infección severa que requiere tratamiento quirúrgico temprano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21002^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
