<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18170</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Choice of social support sources among immigrants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Based on the social convoy model (Khan &amp; Antonucci, 1980), this study examines the choice of social support sources among immigrants through Manhein Interview (Veil, 1990). 150 well-fare facility recipients from Morocco and Philippines took part voluntarily. Log-linear analysis (SPSS.9) were employed to process data. The models obtained showed how nationality, family status and length of stay influenced participant&#146;s choices. Nevertheless, these direct effects were modulated by the types of demands. Generally, immigrants tended to chose kin and sometimes friends, particularly for psychological daily needs. Results from this study supported the application of the social convoy model to the analysis of immigrant&#146;s social support system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albar Marín, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, Manuel Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ramírez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir del modelo del convoy social (Khan y Antonucci, 1980), se analiza la elección de fuentes de apoyo entre inmigrantes con la Entrevista Manhein (Veiel, 1990). Participaron voluntariamente 150 marroquíes y filipinos potenciales usuarios de los Servicios Sociales de Marbella (Costa del Sol). Tras aplicar a los datos análisis log-lineales (SPSS 9), los modelos obtenidos muestran que: 1) la nacionalidad, etapa de asentamiento y situación familiar influyen en la elección de fuente de apoyo; y 2) la influencia directa de cada una de estas variables está modulada por la naturaleza de la demanda. Se observó que los inmigrantes prefieren el apoyo de vínculos familiares, pero destacan los amigos en demandas psicológicas cotidianas. Los resultados avalan el empleo del modelo del convoy en el análisis del apoyo social en inmigrantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 369-374, mayo 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La elección de fuentes de apoyo social entre inmigrantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37729^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
