<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155909</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sebaceous carcinoma of the breast</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sebaceous differentiation in the breast has occasionally been described associated with metaplastic carcinoma, adenoid cystic carcinoma, cylindroma, adenomyoepithelioma, and intraductal papilloma. Sebaceous carcinoma of the breast is defined in the WHO 2012 classification as a carcinoma with sebaceous differentiation in at least 50% of the cells, located in the breast tissue and unrelated to skin appendages. According to this definition, 14 cases have been reported to date in English (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Weil Lara, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diferenciación sebácea se ha descrito en la mama ocasionalmente asociada con el carcinoma metaplásico, el carcinoma adenoide quístico, el cilindroma, el adenomioepitelioma, y el papiloma intraductal. El carcinoma sebáceo de mama se define en la clasificación de la OMS 2012 como un carcinoma con diferenciación sebácea en al menos el 50% de las células, localizado en el tejido mamario y sin relación con anejos cutáneos. Acorde con esta definición, se han descrito 14 casos en la literatura de lengua inglesa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(4): 263-267, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma sebáceo de la mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8384^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31682^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
