<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75588</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary bilateral lipid Keratopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: Observational, case report study. A45-year-old woman complained of bilateral irritationand photophobia since childhood. Slit-lampexamination revealed yellow-whitish depositsinvolving the deep stroma of the peripheral half ofthe cornea in both eyes. The evolution was slowlyprogressive with a moderate impairment of hervisual acuity.Discussion: Lipid deposits adopt symmetric andbilateral configurations; the absence of corneal vascularizationand ocular pathology as well as anylipoprotein disorder support the diagnosis of primarylipid keratopathy. The slow progressing diseaseis also confirmed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Rebollo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes-Mollón, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Rico, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 45 años que desde la infanciarefería irritación ocular y fotofobia bilateral. Enla biomicroscopía se apreciaba en ambos ojos depósitosblanco-amarillentos en estroma profundo de laperiferia media corneana. La evolución de estosdepósitos fue lentamente progresiva sin repercusiónsignificativa sobre la agudeza visual.Discusión: La configuración bilateral y simétricade los depósitos lipídicos, la ausencia de vascularizacióncorneal y de patología ocular previa, asícomo la ausencia de enfermedad del metabolismolipídico asociada apoyan el diagnóstico de queratopatíalipídica primaria en nuestro caso. La evoluciónlentamente progresiva de la enfermedad quedatambién confirmada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(5): 263-266, mayo 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queratopatía lipoidea primaria bilateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
