<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15721</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacious psychological treatments for post-traumatic stress disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to offer a review of the psychological and pharmacological treatments that the research has shown as more effective to treat the post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Regarding the psychological treatments, the most rigorous studies have been carried out in the context of the cognitive-behavioral approaches. The empiric evidence suggests a bigger efficacy for the prolongued exposure (PE). The cognitive restructuring and the anxiety management training produces positive effects to alleviate the posttraumatic simptomatology too. More recent studies are dedicate to design treatment programs which integrate the several mentioned components. Also, it is noted the possible effectiveness of the hypnotherapy. On the other hand, different types of drugs have been used for the PTSD treatment. In spite of the beneficial effects that some drugs produce to alleviate the different symptoms, frequently have been registered collateral effects for nearly all of them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Báguena Puigcerver, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es el de ofrecer una revisión de los tratamientos psicológicos y farmacológicos que la investigación ha probado como más eficaces en el tratamiento del trastorno por estrés post-traumático (TEPT). Por lo que se refiere a los tratamientos psicológicos, los estudios más rigurosos se han llevado a cabo en el contexto de los acercamientos conductual-cognitivos. La evidencia empírica sugiere un mayor respaldo para la exposición prolongada (EP). También la reestructuración cognitiva y las técnicas para el manejo de la ansiedad dan lugar a efectos positivos a la hora de aliviar la sintomatología post-traumática. La investigación más reciente se dirige a la creación de programas de tratamiento que integran los distintos componentes mencionados. También, se anota la posible eficacia de la hipnoterapia. Por otra parte, se han utilizado diferentes tipos de fármacos para el tratamiento de TEPT. A pesar de los efectos beneficiosos que producen algunos de ellos para aliviar los diferentes síntomas, con frecuencia se han registrado efectos colaterales para casi todos ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(3): 479-492, ago. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamientos psicológicos eficaces para el estrés post-traumático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7167^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
