<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87537</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of molecular biology techniques in oral cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article summarizes the main techniques in the area of molecular biology that are available for the investigation of oral cancer and precancer. They have been classified depending on the biological material we expect to analyze, which can be DNA, RNA or proteins. The explanation for each technique includes a brief description of its basics, as well as some advantages, drawbacks and current use of the technique. Our aim is to throw light on the applications of these techniques, soon indispensable for most studies, in the early diagnosis, prognosis and individualized treatment of oral carcinoma. The most useful techniques for this objective are nowadays: gel electrophoresis, hybridation, microarray technology, biochips, PCR (conventional, quantitative or reverse transcriptase), Southern, Northern and Western blot studies, DNA sequenciation, cloning, immunohistochemistry, ELISA and flow citrometry. Some techniques that deserve a special mention due to their greater usefulness in the area of oral cancer are microarray technology, biochips and PCR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Durán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Trapero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo de revisión se propone exponer las principales técnicas de biología molecular disponibles actualmente para los investigadores, en el campo del cáncer y precáncer oral, clasificadas según el tipo de material biológico del que se disponga para iniciar la investigación. Éste puede ser ADN, ARN o proteínas. La explicación de cada técnica comprenderá una breve sistemática del proceso, así como sus ventajas, inconvenientes y estado de actividad actual. Todo ello con la finalidad de esclarecer las aplicaciones, pronto indispensables, de las técnicas más destacadas, en el diagnóstico precoz, pronóstico y tratamiento individualizado del carcinoma oral. Entre las técnicas más útiles en este proceso se encuentran: la electroforesis en gel, las técnicas de hibridación, la tecnología microarray, los biochips, la PCR convencional, la cuantitativa o la transcriptas a inversa, las técnicas de Southern, Northern y Western blot, la secuenciación de ADN, la clonación de genes, la inmunohistoquímica, el ensayo ELISA y lacitometría de flujo. Destacan en particular por su gran utilidad, la tecnología microarray, los biochips y la PCR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;26(4): 189-196, jul.-ago. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de las técnicas de biologíamolecular en oncología oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
