<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038549</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of personality traits in the choice of dialysis technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic Renal Insufficiency is accompanied by physical problems and a strong dose of anxiety. We believe that the personality traits and psychosocial support might influence in the choice of dialysis technique. Our objective is to evaluate how personality traits influence the choice of dialysis technique. In the Nephrology Service, since 1996 we have had a prospective register that gathers variables related to the choice of dialysis technique. In 2003, we performed a transversal study on all stable dialysis patients in our unit of the Character Traits, with the following questionnaires:&#149; Eysenk personality questionnaire (EPQ RS)&#149; Social adaptation scale (PSA)&#149; Confronting test (COPE) Thirty-nine patients were studied, of which 20 opted for haemodialysis and 19 for peritoneal dialysis. We found no differences with respect to the social lvariables nor in the personality test, only one statistically significant difference was found on the deadaptive scale of the COPE test. It was observed that the patients choosing PD showed a greater capacity to face problems, did not have better support and social adaptation or a less neurotic personality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mañé Buixo, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquina Parra, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuste Jiménez, Elios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Cabaña, Conchi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponz Clemente, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ocaña, Joan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Insuficiencia Renal Crónica se acompaña de problemas físicos y una fuerte dosis de ansiedad. Creemos que los rasgos de personalidad y el soporte psicosocial podrían influir en la elección de la técnica de diálisis. Nuestro objetivo es valorar como influyen los rasgos de personalidad en la elección de la técnica de diálisis. Desde 1996 disponemos, en el Servicio de Nefrología, de un registro prospectivo que recoge variables relacionadas con la elección de la técnica dediálisis. En el año 2003 realizamos un estudio transversal en todos los enfermos estables en diálisis de nuestro centro, sobre los Rasgos del Carácter, se administraron los cuestionarios:&#149; Cuestionario de personalidad de Eysenk (EPQ RS)&#149; Escala de adaptación social (PSA)&#149; Test de afrontamiento (COPE)Se han estudiado 39 pacientes de los cuales 20 optaron por hemodiálisis y 19 por diálisis peritoneal. No hemos hallado diferencias en cuanto a las variables sociales ni tampoco en el test de personalidad, solamente se ha hallado una diferencia estadísticamente significativa en la escala des-adaptativa del test de COPE. Se observa que los pacientes que eligen DP muestran una mayor capacidad para afrontar los problemas, no tenían mejor soporte y adaptación social, ni una personalidad menos neurótica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;8(1): 13-17, ene.-mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los rasgos de personalidad en la elección de la técnica de diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33932^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
