<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84292</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of adolescent and child psychiatric emergency in a pediatric emergency service of a general hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: For several years, there is an increase in visits due to psychiatric disorders in the pediatric emergency departments. Therefore the coordination between pediatric emergency department and mental health department is important to improve the care of pediatric patients with mental illness. Objectives: To analyze the characteristics of pediatric patients in the Pediatric Emergency Department in our hospital. Methodology: Transversal and descriptive study of the psychiatric emergencies treated in the Pediatric Emergency Department which required attention by psychiatry of the Corporació Sanitària Parc Taulí (Sabadell) (period 2006-2007). We analyzed social demographic variables, psychiatric diagnoses, as well as the need of treatment and final destination of the patient. Results: There were 104 psychiatric visits of 93,908 emergencies (0.1%), with a mean age of 12.37 years (range: 6-15).The main reasons for consultation were: worsening of their underlying disease (51%), different kinds of conduct alteration(31.7%) and suicide attempt (17.3%). Many of the cases showed associated factors or social dystocia: 68.2% had family history of psychiatric illness, a 39.4% alcohol or drugs abuse and 25.9% had a traumatic parent divorce. Only 26% of the cases needed drug treatment other than their usual treatment. The main diagnosis at discharge was, in 50% of the cases, unspecified conduct disorder or conversion disorders. A 64% of the patients were discharged, and 36% required admission. Conclusions: The pediatric psychiatric emergencies are complex and serious. There is an increase of these, which may be due to multiple causes. Some of the causes represent epidemiological trends and can be studied and foreseen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aldecoa, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartoli, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argemí, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde hace varios años, se ha producido un aumento en las visitas por patología psiquiátrica en los servicios de urgencias pediátricas. Por ello, es importante la coordinación entre los equipos de urgencias pediátricas y los de salud mental para mejorar la atención de los pacientes pediátricos con una enfermedad mental. Objetivos: Analizar las características de los pacientes pediátricos del servicio de urgencias psiquiátricas de nuestro hospital. Metodología: Estudio transversal descriptivo de las urgencias psiquiátricas atendidas en el Servicio de Urgencias de Pediatría que precisaron atención en el Servicio de Psiquiatría de la Corporació Sanitària «Parc Taulí» de Sabadell (periodo 2006-2007). Analizamos las variables sociodemográficas y los diagnósticos psiquiátricos, así como la necesidad de tratamiento y el destino final del paciente. Resultados: Se realizaron 104 visitas psiquiátricas de un total de 93.908 urgencias (0,1%), con una media de edad de los pacientes de 12,37 años (rango: 6-15). Los motivos de consulta principales fueron: empeoramiento de la enfermedad de base (51%), alteración de la conducta de diversos tipos (31,7%) e intento de suicidio (17,3%). Muchos de los casos presentaban factores asociados o distocia social: un 68,2% presentaba antecedentes de enfermedad familiar psiquiátrica, un 39,4% abuso de alcohol y/o drogas, y un 25,9% una separación traumática de los padres. Sólo un 26% de los casos precisaron una intervención farmacológica fuera de su tratamiento habitual. Los diagnósticos principales al alta fueron, en el 50% de los casos, trastornos de conducta no especificados y conversivos. Se dio de alta a su domicilio al 64% de los pacientes, y un 36% precisó ingreso hospitalario. Conclusiones: Las urgencias psiquiátricas pediátricas son complejas y graves. Últimamente se ha producido un aumento de ellas, lo que puede obedecer a múltiples causas, algunas de las cuales representan tendencias epidemiológicas que pueden estudiarse y preverse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(11): 547-553, dic. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y evolución de las urgencias psiquiátricas infantojuveniles en un servicio general de urgencias pediátricas hospitalarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
