<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164620</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Audiovisual Aids in nursing education: literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Audiovisual aids, as a teaching strategy, promote a change from the traditional educational system to an improved way of learning that integrates technological advances and resources to enhance education, this is why it is important to gather all the existent information about the topic, because we need to demonstrate and support its&#146; usage for the students development. Aim: Analyze the existent information about the impact that audiovisual aids have in the improvement or nursing teaching. Methodology: Systematic research in the Medina, CINAHL, EBSCO, SciELO, PubMed, LILACS and Cochrane databases. Using de PICo method and Health Science Descriptors (DeCS) in English, Spanish and Portuguese. Results: Seven experimental and quasi-experimental studies were selected, which showed that audiovisual aids helped in the improvement of declarative, contextual and attitudinal learning, nevertheless, they did not surpass the situated strategies such as simulations, authorized practices and interactive activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agama-Sarabia, Adiel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Islas-Ortega, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Felipe, Lizette</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Velázquez, María Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trejo-Niño, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De-la-Peña-León, Belinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Knopfler, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los recursos audiovisuales como estrategias de enseñanza fomentan el cambio de una educación tradicional hacia una que integra los cambios tecnológicos, la cual utiliza y dispone de los recursos para mejorar el aprendizaje, por lo que es necesario contar con la mejor evidencia disponible para apoyar su utilización en la formación de los estudiantes. Objetivo. Analizar la evidencia existente del impacto que tienen los recursos audiovisuales en el mejoramiento de la enseñanza en enfermería. Metodología. Búsqueda sistematizada en las bases de datos Medline, CINAHL, EBSCO, SciELO, ERIC, PubMed, LILACS y Cochrane. Utilizando el método PICo y Descriptores de Ciencias de la Salud (DeSC) en inglés, español y portugués. Resultados. Se seleccionaron 7 estudios experimentales y cuasi-experimentales dónde se observa que los recursos audiovisuales ayudan a mejorar el aprendizaje declarativo, contextual y actitudinal, sin embargo, no superan a las estrategias situadas como la simulación, práctica tutorizada y actividades interactivas. Conclusiones. La evidencia demuestra que el uso de los recursos audiovisuales desarrolla la empatía y favorece la expresión de la interioridad del alumno, sin embargo, por sí solos no superan a estrategias de aprendizaje constructivistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(47): 512-525, jul. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recursos audiovisuales en la educación en enfermería: revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1301^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1301^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
