<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123970</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medication error in a university hospital: perception and related factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The following research is a field, qualitative study performed with nursing workers in a surgical clinic of a university hospital in southern Brazil. It aimed at recognizing the perception of a nursing team on the medication errors and discussing the factors related to such event. A survey with open and closed question has been applied and the data were analyzed according to theme analysis. The results indicate that the workers associate medication error with multifactor causes and the as factors influencing the error, they cite unreadable handwriting, talking in the medication room, work overload, lack of attention, lack of identification in the patient, bed, medication, time, and via. Considering the data, it is vital that health organizations implement and use protocols related to the use of medicines and that it is a pact among the multiprofessional team in a way to assure patient safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zeitoune, Regina Gollner</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santi, Tiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tonel, Juliana Zancan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>da Silva, Rosângela Marion</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beck, Carmem Lúcia Colomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>do Reis, Daiane Aparecida Martins</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se trata de un estudio cualitativo, de campo, realizado con trabajadores de enfermería en clínicaquirúrgica de un hospital universitario del sur de Brasil. Tuvo como objetivo conocer la percepción del equipo de enfermería sobre errores de medicación y discutir los factores relacionados a ese evento. Se utilizó un cuestionario con preguntas abiertas y cerradas y los datos fueron chequeados según análisis temático Los resultados indican que los trabajadores asocian el error de medicación a causas multifactoriales y, como factores que influyen el error, citan la letra ilegible, charlas en la sala de medicación, sobrecarga de trabajo, falta de atención, falta de identificación del paciente, camilla, medicamento, hora y vía. A partir de los datos es imprescindible que las organizaciones de salud implementen y utilicen protocolos relacionados al uso de fármacos y que eso sea pactado entre el equipo multiprofesional de forma a asegurar la seguridad del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(35): 160-171, jul. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Error de medicación en un hospital universitario: percepción y factores relacionados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
