<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111487</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testicular tumour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A case of a testicular germ cell tumour arises, an unusual neoplasia characterized by the fact that it affects young people and having a great ability for differentiation. It involves a 37 year old male seeking medical care on feeling a painful growth in his right testicle after being hit by a ball. On examination, a hard, stony nodule can be felt in the right testicle, with deep layer adherence. On referral to urology, and after ultrasound confirmation of the growth, a radical orchiectomy is performed. The histopathological diagnosis is for classic seminoma with an intense sarcoid reaction, extending to the coverings of the testis, epididymis and to the proximal portion of the cord(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Andrés, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Puga, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedito Pérez de Inestrosa, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Larios, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de tumor de células germinales testiculares, neoplasia poco usual que se caracteriza por afectar a personas jóvenes y tener una gran capacidad de diferenciación. Se trata de un varón de 37 años que acude por palparse una tumoración dolorosa en testículo derecho tras recibir un balonazo. A la exploración, en el testículo derecho se palpa un nódulo de consistencia dura, pétrea, adherido a planos profundos. Una vez derivado a Urología y confirmada por ecografía la tumoración se le realiza una orquiectomía radical derecha. El diagnóstico anatomopatológico es de seminoma clásico con intensa reacción sarcoidea y extensión a las cubiertas testiculares, al epidídimo y a la parte proximal del cordón(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;5(3): 198-201, oct.2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor testicular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
