<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136229</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral treatments in multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of new disease-modifying drugs (DMD) in relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS), which share the common denominator of oral administration, considerably improves patient expectations in terms of effectiveness, tolerability and treatment adherence compared with currently available drugs. However, the common route of administration of these drugs does not mean that they are equivalent, since the heading of &#147;oral route&#148; encompasses drugs with distinct indications and mechanisms of action, as well as heterogeneous results in terms of efficacy and safety, allowing treatment to be personalized according to the each patient&#146; s characteristics. Currently, four oral DMD are available or in an advanced stage of clinical development: fingolimod, teriflunomide, dimethyl fumarate and laquinimod. In pivotal trials versus placebo, these molecules reduced the annualized rate of exacerbations versus placebo by 54%, 31%, 53% and 23%, respectively, the risk of progression of disability by 31%, 30%, 38% and 36%, and the number of active lesions showing contrast uptake on magnetic resonance imaging by 82%, 80%, 90% and 37%, respectively. Based on the risk/benefit ratio, fingolimod is indicated in patients with suboptimal response to initial DMD or in severe rapidly progressing RRMS, while the remaining drugs can be used as first-line options. Clinical experience with these treatments will provide new data on safety and effectiveness, which will be determinant when establishing therapeutic algorithms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carreón-Guarnizo, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eustasio Meca-Lallana, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Clares, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de nuevas opciones terapéuticas modificadoras del curso de la enfermedad (MCE) en esclerosis múltiple recurrente-remitente (EMRR), con el denominador común de la vía oral de administración, mejora considerablemente las expectativas de los pacientes en términos de efectividad, tolerancia y adherencia al tratamiento frente a los fármacos disponibles en la actualidad. Que estos fármacos compartan la vía de administración no implica que sean equivalentes entre sí, ya que bajo el epígrafe &#147;vía oral&#148; se engloban fármacos con diferentes indicaciones, distintos mecanismos de acción y resultados heterogéneos en cuanto a eficacia y seguridad, que permiten personalizar el tratamiento en función de las características individuales de cada paciente. En la actualidad hay 4 tratamientos MCE orales disponibles o en avanzado estado de desarrollo clínico: fingolimod, teriflunomida, dimetilfumarato y laquinimod. En los ensayos pivotales frente a placebo, estas moléculas redujeron la tasa anualizada de brotes frente a placebo en un 54, 31, 53 y 23%, respectivamente, el riesgo de progresión de la discapacidad en un 31, 30, 38 y 36%, y el número de lesiones activas captantes de contraste en resonancia magnética en un 82, 80, 90 y 37%, respectivamente. El balance riesgo/beneficio sienta la indicación de fingolimod en casos de respuesta subóptima al tratamiento MCE inicialmente instaurado o en formas de EMRR grave de rápida evolución, mientras que el resto de moléculas pueden utilizarse como primera opción de tratamiento. La experiencia clínica con estos tratamientos aportará nuevos datos de efectividad y seguridad, que serán determinantes a la hora de establecer nuevos algoritmos terapéuticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(supl.3): 23-29, dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamientos orales en esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34207^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13493^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
