<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051552</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Falls in the elderly in the community: prevalence, consequences, and associated factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To find the prevalence, characteristics, and consequences of falls in the elderly and related factors.                 Design. Cross-sectional, descriptive study using personal interviews.                 Setting. Three health districts in Cordoba city, Spain.                 Participants. A stratified sample of 362 people over 70.                 Main measurements. The assessment tools were the WHO questionnaire for the study of falls and the EuroQol-5D for the measurement of health-related quality of life. Uni-bivariate and multivariate analyses (P&lt;.05) were run.                 Results. The prevalence of falls was 31.78% (95% CI, 26.99%-36.6%); 12.98% of subjects had more than one fall in the previous year; 55.3% of falls happened at home; 71.8% of the falls had physical consequences, with 7.8% fractures; 44.7% of the elderly studied were scared of having a new fall, and 22% limited their mobility after the fall. In 30% of cases there was contact with the health system, and 3.3% needed hospital admission. The factors related to a greater risk of falls were: being older, being a woman, widowed, uneducated, with difficulties in moving both arms, suffering space disorientation, high drug consumption, and having worse perceived health status.                 Conclusions. Falls in the elderly living in the community are a frequent problem, with important physical, psychological and social consequences</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Francisco Varas-Fabra, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enciso Berge, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Martín, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Moral, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérula de Torres, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia de caídas en personas mayores así como sus características, consecuencias y factores asociados.                 Diseño. Estudio observacional, transversal, por entrevista personal.                 Emplazamiento. Tres zonas básicas de salud de Córdoba.                 Participantes. Se incluyó a 362 personas &amp;#8805; 70 años, residentes en la comunidad, elegidas por muestreo polietápico.                 Mediciones principales. Se realizó una valoración consistente en el estudio de las caídas con un cuestionario específico de la Organización Mundial de la Salud, y de la calidad de vida de los pacientes con el EuroQol-5D. Se realizó un análisis univariable, bivariable y multivariable (p &lt; 0,05).                 Resultados. La prevalencia de caídas es del 31,78% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 26,99-36,6%). Un 12,9% presentó más de una caída en el último año. El 55,3% ocurrió en el domicilio. El 71,8% sufrió lesiones físicas, con un 7,8% de fracturas. El 44,7% manifestó miedo a una nueva caída y el 22% limitó su movilidad desde la caída. El 30% contactó con el sistema sanitario, y un 3,3% precisó hospitalización. Los factores que se relacionaron con mayor riesgo de presentar caídas fueron: tener mayor edad, ser mujer, estar viudo/a, sin estudios, presentar dificultad para mover ambas extremidades superiores y orientarse en el espacio, consumir un mayor número de fármacos, y un peor estado de salud percibido.                 Conclusiones. Las caídas en los ancianos que viven en la comunidad son un problema frecuente, con importantes consecuencias físicas, psicológicas y sociales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(8): 450-455, nov.2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caídas en ancianos de la comunidad: prevalencia, consecuencias y factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
