<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055695</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of functionality and pain intensity before and after a transformial steroid injection in a preliminary sample of patients with lumbar radiculopathy due to a disk hernia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate the level of improvement in the functionality and pain intensity in a preliminary sample of patients with compressive lumbar radiculopathology due to disk hernia who received a transforaminal steroid injection (TSI) under fluoroscopic guidance. Material and Method From October to December 2006, patients experiencing back pain due to radiculopathy secondary to a lumbar disk  hernia were selected. These diagnoses had to have been corroborated clinically and by a magnetic resonance image. Furthermore, these were patients that responded poorly to conservative management. Pain intensity was evaluated by Visual Analog Scale Analogy (VAS) and the functionality by the Oswestry Questionnaire before the TSI and 7, 14 and 30 days thereafter in all of the patients included. Results Fourteen (14) patients were included; whereby twelve were women (87.5%) and two were men (14.3%). The average age was 62 ± 12.8. The VAS score prior to the  procedure averaged  74.0 ± 17.0. Significant differences were observed 7 days (VAS 4.64 ± DE 22.4); after 14 days (VAS 45.0 ± 17.0); and after 30 days (VAS 46.4 ± 25.9) after TSI with a p&lt; 0.05. This was not the case for functionality in which there were no significant differences in Oswestry Questionnaire for all of the patient&#146;s before-after comparisons of the aforementioned intervals. Conclusions The results obtained in this preliminary study suggested that ITE may effectively affect pain reduction at 7, 14 and 30 days; but, not so for the functionality index during the same intervals of the evaluated time</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guevara, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velázquez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medel, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar el grado de mejoría en el estado funcional e intensidad del dolor, en una muestra preliminar de pacientes con radiculopatía compresiva lumbar por hernia de disco a quienes se les realizó una inyección de esteroides por vía transforaminal (ITE) bajo guía fluoroscópica. Material y método Se seleccionaron prospectivamente en el periodo de Octubre a Diciembre del 2006, pacientes con dolor de espalda baja por radiculopatía secundaria a hernia de disco lumbar corroborado por clínica e imagen de resonancia magnética y que presentaran mala respuesta al manejo conservador. Se evaluó la intensidad de dolor por medio de la Escala Visual Análoga (EVA) y el índice de funcionalidad mediante el Cuestionario de Oswestry previo al ITE y posterior al mismo a los 7, 14 y 30 días en todos los pacientes incluidos. Resultados Se incluyeron a 14 pacientes; de ellos doce fueron mujeres (87.5%) y dos varones (14.3%); con una edad promedio de 62 ± 12.8 (40-84). La intensidad de dolor antes del procedimiento, según la EVA fue de 74.0 ± 17.0. Se observaron diferencias significativas en la intensidad del dolor a los 7 (EVA 46.4 ± 22.4), 14 (EVA 45.0 ± 17.0) y 30 (EVA 46.4 ± 25.9) días después del ITE (p &lt; 0.05), pero no así para el índice de discapacidad, en el que no hubo ninguna diferencia significativa para todas las comparaciones antes-después en los intervalos referidos. Conclusiones Los resultados obtenidos en el presente estudio preliminar sugieren que el ITE, podría ser efectivo para la disminución del dolor a los 7, 14 y 30 días, pero no así para el índice de funcionalidad en los mismos intervalos de tiempo evaluados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;14(3): 194-203, abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055695</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del impacto funcional e intensidad del dolor antes y después de la inyección de esteroides por vía transforaminal en una muestra preliminar de pacientes con radiculopatía lumbar por hernia de disco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
