<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61160</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latest developments in fungal lung infection in solid organ transplantation (SOT)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of invasive mycoses following solid organtransplant (SOT) ranges from 5 to 42% depending on theorgan transplanted. Despite the increasing impact of viralinfections in SOT, fungal infections still have a main rolein transplant recipients. In fact, they remain a commoncause of morbidity and mortality in the early and latepost-transplant periods. Aspergillus spp. and Candida spp.account for most IFI, but recent epidemiological andclinical studies suggest the emergence of mycelia fungiother than Aspergillus as well as resistant strains ofCandida in these patients. Due to the difficulty in making adefinitive diagnosis, the treatment is sometimes delayedor is not prescribed (post-mortem diagnosis). Serologicaland molecular detection of Aspergillus antigens or fungalDNA, in blood and/or BAL samples, may improve thediagnosis of pulmonary aspergillosis, but in SOT thesensitivity is variable and more studies are needed.Another pendent issue is antifungal prophylaxis in SOTrecipients; it is unknown which is the best agent or thetime duration, and in which receptors must be applied.Treatment combining AmB preparations, newer antifungaldrugs, early surgical resection of infected tissue anddiscontinuation or modulation of immunosuppressivetreatment can to be necessary in selected patients andin certain occasions, and all of them may improveprognosis of IFI. However, there are two main handicapsin the management of FI in transplant recipients: firstly,to establish an early diagnosis, secondly, delays inapplying early treatment with antifungal drugs.Development of new early diagnostic tools more preciseand well-designed multicenter evaluations of diagnosticmethods and therapeutic regimens available at presentare the important work in the next 3-5 years.This review highlights changing spectrumof invasive fungal infections, risk factors, antifungalprophylaxis, and treatment following SOT(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Tudela, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solé, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quindós, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pemán, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de nuevos métodos de diagnóstico precoz más precisos, y los estudios multicéntricos bien diseñados sobre los métodos diagnósticos y las pautas terapéuticas disponibles actualmente, son trabajos importantes a realizar durante los próximos 3-5 años. En la presente revisión se subrayan el espectro cambiante de las infecciones fúngicas invasivas, la profilaxis antifúngica y el tratamiento después del TOS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.3): 49-58, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Últimos avances en las infecciones micóticas pulmonares ocurridas en el trasplante de órganos sólidos (TOS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8349^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19278^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
