<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119537</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current global economic crisis has led us to ask how to generate competitive advantages with an impact on organizational effectiveness without jeopardizing the employees&#146; quality of life. The importance of the development of health and safety policies (Montero, Araque, &amp; Rey, 2009), among them, those relating to family-friendly policies promoting work-life balance (WLB) of employees (Leon &amp; Chinchilla, 2010; Urcelay, 2005) has been pointed out by various authors in our country. This article reviews the main Spanish and Latin American contributions on work-life balance (WLB) published in the last eight years, and presents the research work of ASH-PsicoSAO Group (University of Barcelona) related to this topic. The objective of our work is to contribute to both, the scientific and the occupations fields, with particular attention to the role of supervisor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romeo, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yepes-Baldó, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berger, Rita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actual situación de crisis económica mundial ha conllevado que nos preguntemos cómo generar ventajas competitivas que impacten en la efectividad organizacional sin que ello suponga poner en riesgo la calidad de vida de los empleados. Diversos autores en nuestro país señalan la importancia del desarrollo de políticas de salud y seguridad ocupacional (Montero, Araque, y Rey, 2009), y dentro de éstas, las relativas a políticas familiarmente responsables que favorezcan el work-life balance (WLB) de sus empleados (León y Chinchilla, 2010; Urcelay, 2005). Este artículo hace una revisión de las principales aportaciones españolas e hispanoamericanas sobre el WLB en los últimos ocho años, presentando el trabajo investigador del Grupo ASH-PsicoSAO (Universidad de Barcelona) en relación a este tema. El objetivo de nuestros trabajos es contribuir tanto en la esfera científica como en el ejercicio profesional, prestando especial atención al papel del supervisor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;35(1): 48-58, ene. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución española e iberoamericana al estudio del &#147;work life balance&#148;: claves para la intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
