<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122931</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">G_Clinic Questionnaire to assess job satisfaction in the clinical management units, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Job satisfaction of nurses is a determinant factor in the quality and organizational adaptation of clinical management models in the current socio-economic context. The aim of this study was to construct and validate a questionnaire to measure job satisfaction of nurses in the Clinical Management Units in the Andalusian Public Health System. Methods: Clinimetric and cross-sectional study with a sample of 314 nurses of two university hospitals from Seville. Nurses were surveyed in 2011, from March to June. We used the Font Roja questionnaire adapted to our study variables. We performed analyses of correlations, reliability and construct validity, using exploratory factor analysis (EFA) and confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) to test the a priori model. Results: The end questionnaire consists of 10 items, whose internal consistency was 0.75, with a percentage of variance explaining of 63.67%. CFA confirmed 4 dimensions (work environment, work relationships, motivation, and recognition): significant &amp;#967;2 (p &lt; .001); &amp;#967;2/gl = 2.013; GFI= 0.958, RMR = 0.055 y RMSEA = 0.057; AGFI = 0.927, NFI = 0.878, TLI = 0.902, CFI = 0.933 e IFI = 0.935; AIC = 132.486 y ECVI = 0.423. Conclusion: This new questionnaire (G_Clinic) improves clinimetric values of the Font Roja questionnaire, because it reduces the number of items, improves the reliability of the dimensions, increases the value of variance explained, and allows knowing job satisfaction of nurses in clinical managementt (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>gil García, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porcel Gálvez, Ana Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lara, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grao Cruces, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La satisfacción laboral de los profesionales de enfermería es un factor determinante en la calidad y adaptación organizativa de los modelos de gestión clínica en el actual contexto socioeconómico. El objetivo del estudio fue construir y validar un cuestionario para conocer el nivel de satisfacción laboral de los profesionales enfermeros en las Unidades de Gestión Clínica en el Sistema Sanitario Público Andaluz. Métodos: Estudio clinimétrico y transversal, tomando como muestra a 314 profesionales de enfermería pertenecientes a los Hospitales Universitarios Virgen del Rocío y Virgen Macarena de Sevilla. Las encuestas se realizaron en 2011, entre los meses de marzo a junio. Se utilizó como base el cuestionario Font Roja adaptado a las variables de nuestra investigación. Se realizó el análisis de correlaciones, fiabilidad, validez de constructo mediante Análisis Factorial Exploratorio (AFE) y Análisis Factorial Confirmatorio (AFC) para comprobar el modelo apriorístico. Resultados: Se construyó un cuestionario con 10 ítems, cuya consistencia interna es de 0,75 con un porcentaje explicativo de la varianza del 63,67%. El AFC corroboró 4 dimensiones (clima laboral, relaciones laborales, motivación y reconocimiento): &amp;#967;2 significativo (p&lt;,001); &amp;#967;2/gl=2,013; GFI=0,958, RMR=0,055 y RMSEA=0,057; AGFI=0,927, NFI=0,878, TLI=0,902, CFI=0,933 e IFI=0,935; AIC=132,486 y EC- VI=0,423. Conclusiones: Este nuevo cuestionario (G_Clinic) mejora los valores del cuestionario Font Roja, ya que disminuye el número de ítems, mejora la fiabilidad de cada una de las dimensiones, aumenta el valor de la varianza explicada y posibilita conoce  la satisfacción de los profesionales de enfermería en la gestión clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(3): 419-428, mayo-jun. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Construcción y Validación del cuestionario G-Clinic para medir la satisfacción laboral en profesionales de enfermería de las unidades de gestión clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53395^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
