<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052124</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transplant coordination and logistics of intra and extra-hospital cadaver donor tissue. &#147;The Pamplona Model&#148;. Sequence of tasks performed from 1992-2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Tissue and organ donations are the only option for    many patients. Cerebral death (CD) facilitates this approach. However,    hospitals that do not provide CD donors have to adapt in order to    obtain donors, referred to as tissue donors (TD), who have died from    cardiac arrest.    Objective. Is this paper it descripte the model for coordination    and donation of intra and extra-hospital TD in the Autonomous Community    of Navarra.    It creats a program for detection, donation and extractions called    the Pamplona Model, from 1992-2006.    Material and methods. In 1990, a transplant team was created    by an Intensive Medicine Physician of HVC, INML and SOS-Navarra. In    1996, VCH Transplant Coordination is defined as a reference centre    for the Tissue Transplant Programme in the Autonomous Community    of Navarra.    Results. Consensus protocols for &#147;intra and extra-hospital detection&#148;    of persons having died from cardiac arrest are developed:    &#150; Alerts from NHS-O hospitals, SOS-Navarra; judges and INML    forensic pathologists.    &#150; Criteria for selection, search and contacts with relatives.    &#150; Alert serology, extraction and transport teams.    &#150; Logistics and distribution of tissue.    &#150; Agreed incentives: Economic, administrative and relevant    regulations.    Conclusions. The Pamplona Model, with the Virgen Del Camino    hospital has made important contributions and is unique in the    world. Intra and extra-hospital coordination of cadaver donor from a    referred hospital, it is a scientific and organizational advance to have    in it counts for the creation of extraction and transplant tissues    teams</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Compains, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iturralde, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraví-Poma, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraví-Aznar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unzué, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teijeira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraví-Aznar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La donación de tejidos y órganos constituye la única    alternativa para muchos pacientes. La muerte cerebral (MC) facilita esta    actitud. Aquellos hospitales no-generadores de donantes con MC, tienen    que generar donantes a partir de fallecidos por parada cardiorrespiratoria,    llamados donantes de tejidos (DT).    En este trabajo se expone el modelo de coordinación y donación de    tejidos de DT intra y extra-hospitalarios en la Comunidad Foral de Navarra.    Se crea un Programa de detección, donación, extracción, denominado    Modelo Pamplona, desde 1992-2006.    Material y métodos. A partir de 1990 se organiza el Equipo de    Trasplantes formado por un médico de la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos    del hospital Virgen del Camino, Instituto Navarro de Medicina Legal    (INML) y SOS-Navarra. En 1996 la Coordinación de Trasplantes del HVC    es definido como centro de referencia para el Programa de Trasplantes    de Tejidos de la Comunidad de Navarra.    Resultados. Se desarrollan protocolos consensuados para la detección    intra y extrahospitalaria de los fallecidos en parada cardiorrespiratoria:    &#150; Alarma desde hospitales del SNS-O, SOS-Navarra, jueces y    forenses del INML.    &#150; Criterios de selección, búsqueda y contacto con familiares.    &#150; Aviso a equipos de serología, extracción y transporte.    &#150; Logística y reparto de los tejidos.    &#150; Incentivos pactados: económicos, administrativos y normativa    al respecto.    Conclusiones. El modelo Pamplona, desde el hospital Virgen del    Camino resulta positivo y es único en el mundo. La coordinación intra y    extrahospitalaria de trasplantes de donantes cadáver desde un hospital    de referencia, es un avance científico y organizativo a tener en cuenta para    la creación de equipos de extracción y trasplante de tejidos</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(supl.2): 45-62, mayo-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052124</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coordinación y logística del trasplante de tejidos de donantes de cadáver intra y extra-hospitalarios. &#147;Modelo Pamplona&#148;. Cadena de actuación 1992-2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1952</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10105^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33103^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14404^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
