<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158815</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Locally advanced breast cancer in elderly patient. Diagnosis and treatment: current controversies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast cancer in elderly patients occurs frequently. The incidence of locally advanced neoplasms is higher in this age group than in the younger population and is often underestimated and undertreated. We present the case of an octogenarian patient with this disease treated in our service. Simple mastectomy was made after finding the negativity of selective sentinel node biopsy. Hormone receptors were highly positive. Hormonal treatment was started and the patient is free of disease 6 months later. The aim of this study is to discuss aspects related to epidemiology, diagnosis and treatment of this entity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal Balaguera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Becerra, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García-Almenta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerquella Hernández, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camuñas Segovia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de mama en pacientes de edad avanzada se produce con frecuencia. La incidencia de los tumores localmente avanzados es mayor en este grupo de edad que en la población más joven. Generalmente es subestimada e infratratada. Presentamos el caso de una paciente octogenaria con esta patología tratada en nuestro servicio. Se realizó mastectomía simple tras constatar la negatividad de la biopsia selectiva del ganglio centinela. Los receptores hormonales fueron altamente positivos. Se indicó tratamiento hormonal coadyuvante. La paciente está libre de enfermedad 6 meses después. El propósito de este trabajo es el de discutir los aspectos relacionados con la epidemiología, diagnóstico y tratamiento de esta entidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;19(4): 157-163, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de mama localmente avanzado en la paciente anciana. Diagnóstico y tratamiento: controversias actuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
