<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71245</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Academic results of undergraduate students of the subject &#145;Structure and function of the human body&#146; in a Sports Sciences degree, are compared before and after the implementation of a contingency contract. Subjects and methods. A contingency contract was implemented during the academic year 2006-2007. Voluntary participants in the experience were able to obtain various benefits depending on their achievement of academic objectives. Results of this intervention on academic achievement were compared among participants and non-participants, as well as with the previous academic year. Results. 83% of the students participated voluntarily in the experience. Only 13% of them did not reach the minimum objectives to obtain any benefit. Taking together, academic results improved in the year of the intervention compared with the previous year. Over 74% of the participants in the experience passed the subject during the academic year 2006-2007. Similarly, subjective quality perception on the teaching of the subject significantly improved after the implementation of the contingency contract. Conclusions. Contingency contracts seem to be useful instruments to improve academic achievement of undergraduate students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aracil-Marco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallar-Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se describen los resultados académicos delos estudiantes de la asignatura &#145;Estructura y función del cuerpo humano&#146; impartida en Ciencias del Deporte tras firmar un contrato conductual, y se comparan con los del curso académico previo. Sujetos y métodos. Se estableció un contrato conductual por el que cada estudiante podía obtener beneficios académicos, ligados a la consecución de objetivos a lo largo del curso. Se analizó el efecto de esta intervención sobre los resultados académicos, así como sobre la satisfacción de los estudiantes con la asignatura. Resultados. El contrato conductual fue elegido por el 83% de los estudiantes. De ellos, sólo un 13% no alcanzó los objetivos mínimos. La tasa de éxito (estudiantes aprobados respecto a los presentados) aumentó del 42 al 68%, respecto al curso previo, obteniéndose además una mejora en las calificaciones. Más del 95% de los estudiantes que superaron la asignatura en el curso 2006-2007 había participado en el contrato, y de los participantes en el mismo el 74% superó la asignatura en el curso académico. Asimismo, el índice de calidad percibida por los estudiantes ascendió significativamente en casi un punto respecto al curso anterior. Conclusiones. Los contratos conductuales parecen herramientas pedagógicas útiles para mejorar el rendimiento académico y la calidad percibida de la docencia universitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 239-246, dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71245</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
