<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125076</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The challenge of electronic cigarettes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The electronic cigarette (e-cig) is a device with a conventional cigarette shape that releases a determined dose of nicotine vapour through an electronic heating process. The nicotine cartridges vary significantly in the amount of nicotine released, even within the same brand. Not all brands admit that they contain nicotine, but this is detected in the majority of units analysed. The e-cig usually contains a propellant, such as propylene glycol, which is a lung irritant. The short-term respiratory effect of the vapour of an e-cig is similar to that caused by the smoke of a cigarette, and is a cause of broncho-restriction. The majority of brands contain glycerine and at least one case of lipoid pneumonia has been detected due to this substance. Many brands contain traces of N-nitrosamines, heavy metals, and other products that are found in conventional cigarette smoke, but in a much higher proportion. There is currently no scientific evidence available that shows it is an effective device for quitting smoking, thus it should not be pro-actively recommended for this purpose, and may interfere with the use of demonstrated scientific evidence-based treatments for quitting smoking. It may have an undesirable effect on promoting the starting of smoking in adolescents or keeping adult smokers consuming nicotine and on gestural dependency. The toxicity of the vapour is not well known, but it is known that they are not innocuous, thus they should not be used in closed public spaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo Córdoba García, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cigarrillo electrónico (e-cig) es un dispositivo con forma de cigarrillo convencional que libera determinadas dosis de vapores de nicotina a través de un proceso de calentamiento electrónico. Los cartuchos de nicotina tienen mucha variabilidad en la cantidad de nicotina liberada, incluso dentro de la misma marca. No todas las marcas admiten que contienen nicotina, pero esta se detecta en la mayoría de unidades analizadas. El e-cig contiene habitualmente propelentes como el propilenglicol, que es un producto irritante pulmonar. El efecto respiratorio a corto plazo del vapor de un e-cig es similar al causado por el humo del cigarrillo y es causa de broncoconstricción. La mayoría de marcas contienen glicerina, y se ha detectado al menos un caso de neumonía lipoidea por esta sustancia. Muchas marcas contienen trazas de N-nitrosaminas, metales pesados y otros productos que se encuentran en el humo de los cigarrillos convencionales en mucha mayor proporción. Actualmente no se dispone de evidencia científica de que sea un dispositivo eficaz para dejar de fumar, por lo que no debe recomendarse de forma proactiva para este fin y puede interferir en el uso de tratamientos de evidencia científica demostrada para dejar de fumar. Puede tener un efecto indeseable al promover el inicio del consumo en adolescentes o retener a fumadores adultos en el consumo de nicotina y en la dependencia gestual. No se conoce bien la toxicidad de los vapores pero se sabe que no son inocuos, por lo que no deberían utilizarse en espacios públicos cerrados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(6): 307-312, jun.-jul. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125076</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El desafío de los cigarrillos electrónicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
