<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77978</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predominance of G9 rotavirus in Valencia and Castellón between 2005 and 2007</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Rotavirus is the leading cause of acute gastroenteritis in young children worldwide. Effective vaccines to prevent rotavirus infections are currently available, although their clinical use is still limited, and rotavirus still causes many episodes of infantile gastroenteritis, mainly during the winter seasons. Objective: To characterise G (VP7) and P (VP4) genotypes of rotaviruses causing acute gastroenteritis in children and to determine the prevalence of genotype G9 rotavirus in three public health areas in the provinces of Valencia and Castellon. Patients and methods: Five-hundred and forty-one stool samples were prospectively collected from infants and children with gastroenteritis in the period between October 2005 and September 2008. They were analysed for rotavirus by ELISA or by immunochromatography. G and P genotyping was performed by reverse transcription and PCR (RT-PCR). Results: G and P rotavirus genotypes were characterised in a total of 525 faecal samples (97%), resulting in a global predominance of strains G9P[8] (56.5%) and G1P[8] (29.9%). During the period of time studied, G9P[8] was the G/P combination most frequently detected during the rotavirus seasons 2005&#150;2006 and 2006&#150;2007, being present in 81.2% and 64.7% of the patients, respectively. However, during the 2007&#150;2008 season, G1P[8] strains were the most frequently found (68.8%), with a sharp decrease in G9P[8] strains to 7.2% of the samples. Conclusions: Rotavirus G9P[8] have spread rapidly and widely during the 2005&#150;2006 and 2006&#150;2007 seasons, replacing other previously dominant genotypes (G1, G4) in our geographic area. Its incidence has declined sharply in 2007&#150;2008, in which G1P[8] was again the predominating genotype (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Téllez Castillo, c. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Jiménez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montava Vilaplana, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buesa Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribes Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las infecciones por rotavirus son la causa más frecuente de gastroenteritis aguda en la infancia. Existen disponibles vacunas para su prevención, pero su uso todavía es limitado y estos virus continúan infectando a la población infantil, principalmente en los meses fríos del año. Objetivos: Caracterizar los genotipos G (VP7) y P (VP4) de rotavirus detectados en niños con gastroenteritis aguda y determinar la prevalencia de las cepas de rotavirus con genotipo G9 en 3 departamentos de Salud Pública de la Comunidad Valenciana. Pacientes y métodos: Se estudiaron de forma prospectiva 541 muestras de heces de niños con gastroenteritis desde octubre de 2005 a septiembre de 2008. Se analizó la presencia de rotavirus por métodos de ELISA o inmunocromatografía y se identificaron los genotipos G y P de las cepas de rotavirus mediante transcripción inversa y amplificación en cadena de la polimerasa. Resultados: Se caracterizaron los genotipos G y P en un total de 525 muestras (97%), y resultaron predominantes las cepas G9P[8] (56,5%) y G1P[8] (29,9%). Durante el período de tiempo estudiado, G9P[8] fue la combinación G/P más frecuente en las temporadas 2005&#150;2006 y 2006&#150;2007, y se encontró en el 81,2 y en el 64,7% de las muestras, respectivamente. Sin embargo, en la temporada 2007&#150;2008 fueron las cepas G1P[8] las más frecuentes (68,8%), y G9P[8] disminuyó a un 7,2%. Conclusiones: Las cepas de rotavirus G9P[8] se diseminaron rápida y ampliamente durante los períodos 2005&#150;2006 y 2006&#150;2007, y suplantaron a otros genotipos anteriormente predominantes (G1, G4) en nuestra área geográfica. Su incidencia descendió bruscamente en la temporada 2007&#150;2008, en la que las cepas G1P[8] resultaron ser nuevamente las que se detectaron más frecuentemente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);72(1): 49-54, ene. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77978</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predominio del genotipo G9 de rotavirus en Valencia y Castellón entre 2005 y 2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
