<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132918</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaginal balls: Therapeutic function</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Vaginal spheres are also known as Chinese balls, vaginal balls , love balls, geisha balls, Rin no tama, Ben Wa balls. Help strengthen the pelvic floor. These produce a microvibration to move the ball inside, favoring the pelvic floor muscles and increasing blood flow to the pelvic region. There are different areas of weight, torque indications pelvic floor should be tonic. Objective: To review the literature on the effectiveness of vaginal balls and increase knowledge of the professionals on this kind of proprioceptive therapy, which is effective for many women for its easy use. Methods: Literature search in databases: Cochrane, Medline, Gerion, SciELO, Take care, Reproductive Health Library WHO and Academic Google . Results: The vaginal balls are effective in the treatment of urinary and fecal incontinence and pelvic floor training. Urinary incontinence is a common and distressing problem, which may interfere in the work, social and sexual life. There is need for further trials to evaluate the methods and protocols of adequate training for the prevention of incontinence, prolapse and sexual dysfunction. Conclusion: It has been shown that vaginal are better than no active treatment in women with stress urinary incontinence and can be equally effective than pelvic floor muscle training and electrical stimulation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Karim Ruiz, Miriam Abdel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavilán Díaz, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Molina, Jesica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las esferas vaginales también son conocidas como bolas chinas, bolas vaginales, bolas del amor, bolas de geisha, Rin no tama, bolas Ben Wa. Ayudan a fortalecer el suelo pélvico. Estas producen una microvibración al moverse la bola del interior, favoreciendo la musculatura del suelo pélvico y aumentando el riego sanguíneo a nivel de la pelvis. Hay esferas de diferente peso, para su indicación el suelo pélvico debe estar tónico. Objetivo: Revisar la literatura sobre la efectividad de las esferas vaginales e incrementar los conocimientos de los profesionales sobre este tipo de tratamiento propioceptivo, que resulta eficaz para muchas mujeres por su fácil utilización. Metodología: Búsqueda bibliográfica en las bases de datos: Cochrane Plus, Medline, Gerion, Scielo, Cuiden, Biblioteca de Salud Reproductiva de la OMS y google académico. Resultados: Las esferas vaginales son eficaces en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria y fecal y para el entrenamiento del suelo pélvico. La incontinencia urinaria es un problema frecuente y molesto, que puede llegar a interferir en el trabajo, en la vida social y sexual. Hay necesidad de más ensayos para evaluar los métodos y protocolos de entrenamiento adecuados para la prevención de la incontinencia, del prolapso y de la disfunción sexual. Conclusión: Se ha evidenciado que las esferas vaginales son eficaces en el tratamiento de mujeres con incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo e igualmente efectivas, en el entrenamiento muscular del suelo pélvico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;18(40): 93-98, sept.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132918</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esferas vaginales: Función terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29576^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
