<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131114</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Dignity Therapy was designed to cope with suffering, psychosocial and existential distress among patients with advanced or terminal disease. This paper is a cuasi experimental study with sixteen cancer patients in advanced stages of the disease. The aim of the study is to apply, in our context, the Dignity Therapy as a proposal for intervention for the relief of suffering such patients, in order to assess whether there is pre and post intervention changes. The results of Wilcoxon&#146;s test, show statistically significant differences comparing the pre-intervention and the post-intervention for the variables Anxiety and Well-being. Nevertheless, statistically significant differences are not observed for the variables Depression and Serenity. The subjects agreed to participate voluntarily, and all the subjects felt satisfied after the application of the Dignity Therapy and noted that they found it useful enough or very useful. These results suggest that it is an appropriate therapeutic approach to these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Botella Mira, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Javaloyes Bernácer, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Díaz, Patricia N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meléndez López, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Dignity Therapy fue diseñada para hacer frente al sufrimiento, la angustia psicosocial y existencial entre los pacientes con enfermedad avanzada o terminal. El presente trabajo es un estudio cuasi experimental con dieciséis pacientes oncológicos en estado avanzado de la enfermedad. El objetivo del estudio fue aplicar, en nuestro contexto, la Dignity Therapy como propuesta de intervención para el alivio del sufrimiento a dichos pacientes, evaluando si existen cambios pre y post intervención. Tras obtener resultados mediante la prueba de Wilcoxon, se obtienen diferencias estadísticamente significativas comparando la pre-intervención y la post-intervención para las variables Ansiedad y Bienestar. Sin embargo, no se observa diferencias estadísticamente significativas para las variables Depresión y Serenidad. Los sujetos accedieron a participar de forma voluntaria y todos se sintieron satisfechos tras la aplicación de la Dignity Therapy, destacando que les había resultado bastante útil o muy útil. Estos resultados apuntan a que se trata de un acercamiento terapéutico apropiado con este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);11(2/3): 345-355, dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicaciónd e la Dignity therapy en pacientes oncológicos en situación avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
