<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109917</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of communication tool for patient safety (</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To validate a safety tool used in high-risk sectors (safety briefing) in intensive care medicine. Design: A prospective, observational and analytical study was carried out. Setting: Trauma and emergency intensive care unit in a tertiary hospital. Patients: Patients with severe trauma (Injury Severity Score ISS&gt;16). Intervention: Documentation of incidents related to patient safety (PS). Variables: Patients characteristics, state of the Unit, patient safety incidents, aspects of the tool (SP) and safety culture impact. Results: We included 441 patients (75.15% males, mean age 39.9±17.5 years), with blunt trauma in 89% and a 10.5% mortality rate. The tool was applied in 586 out of 798 possible shifts (73.4%), and documented 942 events (2.20 incidents per patient). The incidents were more frequently associated with medication (20.7%), devices (placement 4.03%, and maintenance 17.8%) and airway and mechanical ventilation (MV) (17.09%). A correlation was established between the occurrence of incidents and the characteristics of the patient (higher Injury Severity Score, presence of MV, and continuous renal replacement therapies) and the status of the Unit (more than 6 patients per shift out of 8 possible, and holiday period). The tool significantly influenced different aspects of the safety culture of the unit (communication frequency, number of events, punitive loss and active work in PS). Conclusions: Safety briefing is a tool for the documentation of incidents that is simple and easy to use, and is useful for implementing improvements and in influencing safety culture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Fernández, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fuentes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alted López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toral Vázquez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Aznárez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chico Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Izquierdo Riera, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Validar una herramienta de seguridad utilizada en sectores de alto riesgo (briefing de seguridad) en la medicina intensiva. Diseño: Estudio prospectivo, observacional y analítico. Ámbito: UCI de Trauma y Emergencias de un hospital terciario. Pacientes: Pacientes con trauma grave (Injury Severity Score-ISS&gt;16). Intervención: Recogida de incidentes, relacionados con la seguridad del paciente (SP). Variables: Características de la población, estado de la unidad, incidentes de SP, aspectos de la herramienta e impacto sobre la cultura de seguridad. Resultados: Se incluyeron 441 pacientes (edad media 39,9±17,5 años), 75,15% hombres, 89% con trauma cerrado y un 10,5% de mortalidad. La herramienta se aplicó en 586 turnos de 798 posibles (73,4%) y se recogieron 942 incidentes (2,20 incidentes por paciente). Los incidentes más frecuentes se relacionaron con la medicación (20,7%), los dispositivos (colocación 4,03% y mantenimiento 17,8%) y la vía aérea y la ventilación mecánica (VM) (17,09%). Se estableció una correlación entre la presencia de incidentes y las características del enfermo (mayor Injury Severity Score, presencia de VM y terapias de reemplazo renal continuo) y con el estado de la unidad (más de 6 pacientes por turno sobre 8 posibles y el periodo vacacional). La herramienta influyó en diferentes aspectos de la cultura de seguridad de la unidad de manera significativa (frecuencia de comunicación, número de eventos, pérdida de carácter punitivo y trabajo de manera activa en SP). Conclusiones: El briefing es una herramienta para la recogida de los incidentes, simple, fácil de usar, útil para implantar mejoras e influir en la cultura de seguridad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(7): 481-487, oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de una herramienta de comunicación para la seguridad del paciente (Briefing). Experiencia en una unidad de cuidados intensivos de trauma y emergencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
