<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056977</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of opportunities for health surveillance improvement in workers with occupational exposure to ergonomic risks through the AGREE instrument</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: to identify the opportunities for the improvement of    health surveillance tools in workers exposed to occupational    ergonomic risks.    Methods: AGREE instrument has been applied by three    multidisciplinary-evaluation teams for the evaluation of six    quality domains in the specific health surveillance protocols    edited by the Ministry of Health for monitoring workers    with an occupational exposition to Handling loads,    steering postures and repetitive movements.    Results: Scope and purpose, Clarity and presentation and    Editorial independence has been the strong points of the    protocols. Stakeholder involvement, Rigor of development    and Application represent the weak points of the evaluated    protocols.    Conclusions: The main opportunities in order to improve    these guidelines are linked with the procedures for identify    scientific evidence, the analysis of difficulties for the implementation    of recommendations and a more involvement    of potential users of the guide</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sanz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Blasco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ortíz de Salazar, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar las oportunidades para mejorar la vigilancia    de la salud de los trabajadores expuestos a riesgo    ergonómico.    Material y Métodos: Se aplica el Instrumento AGREE para    evaluar seis dimensiones de calidad teórica de los protocolos    de vigilancia sanitaria específica de trabajadores expuestos a    Manejo de cargas (MC), Posturas Forzadas (PF) y Movimientos    repetidos de miembro superior (MRMS), editados por el    Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo. La evaluación se realiza    por tres equipos multidisciplinares de evaluadores.    Resultados: Las dimensiones mejor valoradas fueron: Claridad    de la presentación, Objetivos y Alcance e Independencia    editorial. Mientras que las dimensiones de Participación de    los implicados, Rigor en la elaboración y Aplicabilidad recibe    puntaciones inferiores.    Conclusiones: Las principales oportunidades de mejora identificadas    en el proceso de evaluación están relacionadas con    los procedimientos de búsqueda de la evidencia, la discusión    sobre barreas potenciales a la hora de aplicar las recomendaciones    y una mayor implicación de los usuarios potenciales</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;18(3): 159-167, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las oportunidades de mejora de la vigilancia de la salud de los trabajadores con riesgo ergonómico en el lugar de trabajo mediante el instrumento AGREE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
