<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98807</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parental competences in psychosocial risk context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The analysis and evaluation of parental competences is a central task for the Social Services and specifically for those services targeted at families living in psychosocial risk circumstances. The evaluation of parental competence can be used, among others motives, to take support measures to the family or even to determine if it is necessary to displace the children from his/her home. Despite of its importance, it is an area of study under exploited that also plays a secondary role in the field of child protection. For this reason, it is important to clarify what is meant by parental competence, which are the parental competences considered as basic for the healthy and positive parenting of the children, as well as to have clear guidelines to profesionals for carrying out the assessment of these competences. The current article tries to give answers to the questions mentioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo López, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Casimiro, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Máiquez Chaves, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Quintana, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El análisis y la evaluación de las competencias parentales es una tarea central en los Servicios Sociales y concretamente en los Servicios especializados de atención a las familias en situación de riesgo psicosocial. Es imprescindible conocerlas y evaluarlas, entre otros motivos, para tomar medidas de apoyo a la unidad familiar o incluso para determinar si es necesario retirar a un menor de su familia. Paradójicamente, ésta ha sido un área de investigación poco explorada y ha ocupado también un lugar secundario en el campo de la protección de menores. Por ello, es importante clarificar qué se entiende por competencia parental, cuáles son las competencias parentales consideradas básicas para la educación saludable y positiva de los menores y poder contar con directrices claras para que los técnicos puedan llevar a cabo la evaluación de las mismas. El presente artículo pretende dar respuesta a estas cuestiones mencionadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;18(2): 113-120, mayo-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las competencias parentales en contextos de riesgo psicosocial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
