<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123755</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alcohol Consumption and the incidence of Hypertension in a Mediterranean Cohort: the SUN Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To assess prospectively the association between alcohol consumption, including alcoholic beverage preference and days of consumption per week, and the risk of hypertension in a Mediterranean cohort.Methods. We prospectively followed 9,963 Spanish men and women initially without hypertension. Self-reported and validated data on diet and hypertension diagnoses were collected.results. During follow-up (median [interquartile range], 4.2 [2.5-6.1] years), 554 incident cases of hypertension were identified over a total of 43,562 person-years. The hazard ratio for hypertension among those who consumed alcohol on &amp;#8805;5 days per week was 1.28 (95% confidence interval, 0.97-1.7) compared to abstainers. Among those who drank alcohol &amp;#8805;5 days per week, the hazard ratio for hypertension associated with consuming &amp;#8805;1 drink per day was 1.45 (95% confidence interval, 1.06-2) compared with abstainers. The consumption of beer or spirits, but not wine, was associated with an increased risk of hypertension. The hazard ratio associated with consuming &gt;0.5 drinks of beer or spirits per day was 1.53 (95% confidence interval, 1.18-1.99) compared with abstainers. In contrast, there was a nonsignificant inverse association between red wine intake and the risk of hypertension.Conclusions. In this Mediterranean population, the consumption of beer or spirits, but not wine, was associated with a higher risk of developing hypertension. However, the weekly pattern of alcohol consumption did not have a significant impact on the risk of hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bes-Rastrollo, Maira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beunza, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez-Córdoba, Jorge M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar prospectivamente la asociación entre el consumo de alcohol, incluidas la bebida alcohólica preferida y la frecuencia semanal de consumo, y el riesgo de hipertensión en una cohorte mediterránea. Métodos. Se siguió de manera prospectiva a 9.963 varones y mujeres españoles inicialmente libres de hipertensión. La información recogida sobre dieta y diagnóstico de hipertensión arterial fue la declarada por los pacientes y luego validada. Resultados. Durante el seguimiento (mediana [intervalo intercuartílico], 4,2 [2,5-6,1] años) se identificaron 554 casos incidentes de hipertensión entre 43.562 personasaño. La hazard ratio (HR) de hipertensión para un consumo de alcohol &amp;#8805; 5 días por semana fue 1,28 (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,97-1,70) comparados con abstemios. Entre consumidores de alcohol al menos 5 días por semana, la HR de hipertensión para consumos &amp;#8805; 1 copa al día fue 1,45 (IC del 95%, 1,06-2) comparados con los abstemios. El consumo de cerveza y licores, pero no de vino, se asoció con mayor riesgo de hipertensión. La HR para el consumo diario de más de 0,5 copas de cerveza y licores, en comparación con los no bebedores, fue 1,53 (IC del 95%, 1,18-1,99). En cambio, la asociación entre el consumo de vino tinto y el riesgo de hipertensión fue inversa pero no significativa. Conclusiones. En esta población mediterránea, el consumo de cerveza y licores, pero no de vino, se asoció con mayor riesgo de hipertensión. El patrón de consumo semanal de alcohol, sin embargo, no tuvo un impacto significativo en el riesgo de hipertensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(6): 633-641, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de alcohol e incidencia de hipertensión en una cohorte mediterránea: el estudio SUN</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1534</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
