<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125408</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical figures at the office of Endocrinology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some historical figures have suffered endocrine diseases. This review relates those whose diseases have been published in the scientific literature. It takes a biographical summary and describes the disease process in those considered most relevant by the nature of the disease or the importance of the figure in the Spanish and Latin American context: the Pharaoh Akhenaten, Maximinus I, Bodhidharma, Sancho I of Leon, William the Conqueror, Enrique IV of Castile, Henry VIII, Mary Tudor, Carlos II of Spain, Pio Pico, Pedro II of Brazil, Eisenhower and J. F. Kennedy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfaro-Martínez, José J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Algunos personajes históricos han sufrido enfermedades endocrinológicas. Esta revisión relaciona aquellos cuyas enfermedades han sido publicadas en la literatura cientí&amp;#64257;ca. Se realiza un breve apunte biográ&amp;#64257;co y se describe el proceso patológico en aquellos considerados más relevantes por la naturaleza de la enfermedad o la importancia del personaje en el ámbito español e iberoamericano: el faraón Akhenatón, Maximino I, Bodhidharma, Sancho I de León, Guillermo el Conquistador, Enrique IV de Castilla, Enrique VIII de Inglaterra, María Tudor, Carlos II de España, Pío Pico, Pedro II de Brasil, Eisenhower y J. F. Kennedy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(7): 382-388, ago.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personajes históricos en la consulta de Endocrinología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4786^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
