<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107394</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Painful shoulder is an entity that we find in our daily practice with relative frequency. With the introduction of ultrasound, opens a new field that we can explore, locate and exactly infiltrate the injured area. Ultrasound allows an exploration in the same act, as well as the ability to make a dynamic scanning. The shoulder is made up of 5 joint: true 3 (sternoclavicular, acromioclavicular and glenohumeral) and 2 known as false (subacromial and thoracic scapula). Wherever possible, we will try to puncture in plane, trying to display the full path of the needle and the tip of it. In the interventionism of the shoulder, this is quite easy to get since it&#146;s very superficial structures. It is highly unlikely any serious damage during the infiltration of the shoulder. Take special care of non piercing vascular structures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez Pareja, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez Pareja, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trinidad Martín-Arroyo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Morera, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hombro doloroso es una entidad que encontramos en nuestra práctica diaria con relativa frecuencia. Con la introducción de la ultrasonografía, se abre un campo novedoso ya que podemos explorar, localizar e infiltrar exactamente la zona lesionada. La ecografía permite una exploración en la misma consulta, así como la capacidad de realizar una exploración dinámica. El hombro se compone de 5 articulaciones: 3 verdaderas (esternoclavicular, acromioclavicular y glenohumeral) y 2 denominadas falsas (subacromial y escapulotorácica). Siempre que sea posible, intentaremos realizar la punción en plano, intentando visualizar el trayecto completo de la aguja y la punta de la misma. En el intervencionismo del hombro esto es bastante fácil de conseguir puesto que se trata de estructuras muy superficiales. Es muy poco probable que se produzcan daños graves durante la infiltración del hombro. Tendremos especial cuidado de no puncionar estructuras vasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;19(5): 264-272, sept.-oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107394</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio e intervencionismo ecoguiado de la articulación del hombro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54686^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
