<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144368</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heat Shock Proteins, L-Arginine, and Asymmetric Dimethylarginine Levels in Patients With Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Vascular endothelial inflammation and enhanced oxidative stress are important factors in the pathogenesis of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS). The aim of this study was to determine the levels of heat shock protein (HSP) 27, HSP70, HSP90, L-arginine, and asymmetric dimethylarginine (ADMA) in patients with OSAS and determine their relationship with cardiovascular (CV) risk factors. Material and methods: Forty patients with OSAS, comprising 26 with and 14 without traditional CV risk factors (obesity, hypercholesterolemia, diabetes, hypertension, and smoking), and 20 control subjects without OSAS were included. All patients underwent a full polysomnographic evaluation, and blood samples were obtained in the morning after the night the diagnostic study was performed. Results: No significant differences were found in serum HSP27 and HSP70 levels between the groups. HSP90 and ADMA levels increased significantly, whereas L-arginine levels decreased significantly in patients with OSAS, both with and without CV risk factors, compared with controls, but were not different among the subgroups. In all patients with OSAS, serum HSP70 levels were positively correlated with a percent time with saturation&lt;90% (r=.349, P=.027). Serum L-arginine levels were negatively correlated with desaturation number (r=&amp;#8722;.360, P=.022) and apnea-hypopnea index (r=&amp;#8722;.354, P=.025) and positively correlated with mean oxygen saturation (r=.328, P=.039). Conclusion: Serum levels of HSP90 and ADMA increased, whereas those of L-arginine decreased in patients with OSAS regardless of CV risk factors. These findings indicate the presence of oxidative stress and endothelial dysfunction in patients with OSAS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nedime Sökücü, Sinem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Özdemir, Cengiz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kaman, Dilara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>&amp;#304;n, Erdal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La inflamación del endotelio vascular y el aumento del estrés oxidativo son factores patogénicos importantes del síndrome de apnea obstructiva del sueño (SAOS). El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar las concentraciones de las proteínas de estrés (HSP) 27, HSP70 y HSP90, L-arginina y dimetilarginina simétrica (ADMA) en pacientes con SAOS y establecer su relación con factores de riesgo cardiovascular (CV). Material y métodos: En el estudio se incluyó a 40 pacientes con SAOS, 26 de los cuales presentaban factores de riesgo CV tradicionales (obesidad, hipercolesterolemia, diabetes, hipertensión y tabaquismo) y 14 no los presentaban, y 20 sujetos de control que no padecían SAOS. A todos los pacientes se les realizó una evaluación polisomnográfica completa y se extrajeron muestras de sangre en la mañana siguiente al estudio diagnóstico. Resultados: No se observaron diferencias significativas entre grupos en las concentraciones séricas de HSP27 y HSP70. En los pacientes con SAOS, con o sin factores de riesgo CV, se observaron aumentos significativos de las concentraciones de HSP90 y ADMA y disminuciones significativas de las concentraciones de L-arginina, en comparación con los sujetos de control, aunque no hubo diferencias entre los subgrupos. En todos los pacientes con SAOS, las concentraciones séricas de HSP70 se correlacionaron positivamente con porcentajes de tiempo con saturación &lt;90% (r=0,349; p=0,027). Las concentraciones séricas de L-arginina se correlacionaron negativamente con el número de desaturaciones (r=&amp;#8722;0,360; p=0,022) y el índice de apnea-hipopnea (r=&amp;#8722;0,354; p=0,025) y positivamente con la saturación de oxígeno media (r=0,328; p=0,039). Conclusión: Las concentraciones séricas de HSP90 y ADMA aumentaron y las de L-arginina disminuyeron en pacientes con SAOS, independientemente de los factores de riesgo CV que presentasen. Estos resultados indican la presencia de estrés oxidativo y disfunción endotelial en pacientes con SAOS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(11): 544-550, nov. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones de proteínas de estrés térmico, L-arginina y dimetilarginina asimétrica en pacientes con síndrome de apnea obstructiva del sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22891^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1123^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6510^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
