<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053360</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in management of depression in Spain from psychiatric and primary care physician point of view</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Given that depression is the most prevalent psychiatric disorder in our society, the current situation in pharmacotherapy of depression in Spain has been studied from the point of view of psychiatrists and general practitioners (GP).        Method. A total of 339 interviews were carried out with two groups of physician (238 primary care physicians and 101 psychiatrists) from different Spanish cities. Distribution, application and questionnaires collection were made throughout 2002.                Results. The diagnostic instruments most commonly used by more than 90 % of both medical groups to detect a depressive disorder in a consultation are the evaluation of symptoms and the interview with the patient. However the main diagnostic problem was «masking» of depression with other symptoms/disorders. Most GP (95 %) and psychiatrists (99 %) establish a pharmacological treatment in all their depressive patients. Both groups coincide in most community use of SSRI as drugs of first choice (93% from both samples). The pharmacological agents most used by the psychiatrist are the serotonine selective reputake inhibitors (SSRI) (98.3 %), followed by venlafaxine (84.4 %), anxiolytics (68.4 %), mirtazapine (58.9 %) and reboxetine (55.8 %). In the case of GP, the most commonly used pharmacological groups are SSRI (98.3 %) and anxiolytics (73.4 %). In primary care, the SSRI are considered the most effective antidepressant group. However, the tricyclic antidepressives (TCA) would be the most effective for the psychiatrists.                Conclusions. For psychiatrists and GP, the quality of care of depression in Spain is rated positively. However, there is a group of deficiencies and some aspects that need to be clearly improved, such as the time of consultations, coordination between GP and psychiatrists, waiting lists and available resources for mental health units</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Muñoz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Agueda, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álamo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Dado que la depresión constituye el trastorno psiquiátrico más prevalente en nuestra sociedad, se ha estudiado en qué situación se encuentra la asistencia sanitaria a la depresión en España merced a la opinión de los facultativos encargados de la misma, médicos psiquiatras y médicos de atención primaria (AP).        Método. Se realizaron 339 entrevistas estructuradas a dos muestras diferenciadas de médicos (238 médicos de AP y 101 psiquiatras) de diferentes ciudades de España. La distribución, aplicación y recogida de los cuestionarios se realizó a lo largo del año 2002.                Resultados. Los instrumentos diagnósticos utilizados por más del 90 % de médicos de ambos colectivos son la valoración de la sintomatología y la entrevista con el paciente, siendo el principal problema diagnóstico el enmascaramiento de la depresión con otra sintomatología. La mayoría de los médicos de AP (95 %) y de psiquiatras (99%) instauran un tratamiento farmacológico en todos sus pacientes depresivos. Ambos colectivos coinciden en la utilización mayoritaria de los inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación de serotonina (ISRS) como fármacos de primera elección (93% de ambas muestras). Los agentes farmacológicos más utilizados por el psiquiatra son los ISRS (98,3 %), seguidos de la venlafaxina (84,4 %), ansiolíticos (68,4 %), mirtazapina (58,9 %) y reboxetina (55,8 %). En AP los grupos farmacólogicos más empleados son los ISRS (98,3 %) y los ansiolíticos (73,4 %). Los ISRS son considerados el grupo antidepresivo más eficaz en AP y los antidepresivos tricíclicos para los psiquiatras.                Conclusiones. La valoración que hacen los médicos de la asistencia sanitaria actual al paciente deprimido es buena, aunque se ponen de manifiesto una serie de carencias y aspectos que necesitan ser claramente mejorados, tales como el tiempo de consulta, la coordinación entre AP y psiquiatría, las listas de espera y la dotación de medios a los centros de salud mental</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(2): 89-98, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos diferenciales del manejo de la depresión en España entre la atención psiquiátrica especializada y la atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30515^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
