<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166339</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute treatment of atrial fibrillation in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation is the most frequently encountered sustained arrhythmia in emergency departments. In Spain, it is becoming increasingly common. It is a serious condition that often affects elderly individuals who are at a high risk of stroke, who may have structural heart disease and associated comorbid conditions, and who usually present with acute symptoms associated with the arrhythmia. All of these factors have an important influence on treatment decisions. Since episodes of recent-onset atrial fibrillation are usually managed in the emergency department, it is vitally important that these departments implement appropriate treatment that increases the likelihood that sinus rhythm will be restored and that establishes prophylaxis for stroke as early as possible. This article contains a review of the methods of stroke prophylaxis used during the restoration of sinus rhythm, the aim of and strategies used for heart rate control, and the indications for, the factors influencing decisions on and the techniques used for restoring sinus rhythm, with particular emphasis on episodes of recent-onset atrial fibrillation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación auricular es la arritmia sostenida más prevalente en los servicios de urgencias, que en nuestro país presentan una elevada frecuentación. Es una enfermedad grave que afecta a pacientes de edad avanzada, con alto riesgo de tromboembolia, con cardiopatía estructural y comorbilidad asociada y que acuden por síntomas agudos relacionados con la arritmia. Todos ellos son datos decisivos para diseñar el tratamiento. Además, los episodios de reciente comienzo se manejan habitualmente en los servicios de urgencias, lo que explica la gran importancia de que en ellos se dé un manejo adecuado para incrementar las posibilidades de restauración del ritmo sinusal e instaurar una profilaxis precoz de la tromboembolia arterial. En esta revisión se analizan las estrategias de tromboprofilaxis durante la restauración del ritmo sinusal, los objetivos y las pautas del control de frecuencia y las indicaciones, los factores de decisión y las técnicas de restauración del ritmo sinusal, con especial énfasis en los episodios de reciente comienzo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);13(supl.C): 14c-20c, 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento agudo de la fibrilación auricular en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1151^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
