<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119026</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological treatment conciliation methodology in patients with multiple conditions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To carry out a bibliographic review in order to identify the different methodologies used along the reconciliation process of drug therapy applicable to polypathological patients. Design: We performed a literature review. Data sources: The bibliographic review (February 2012) included the following databases: Pubmed, EMBASE, CINAHL, PsycINFO and Spanish Medical Index (IME). The different methodologies, identified on those databases, to measure the conciliation process in polypathological patients, or otherwise elderly patients or polypharmacy, were studied. Study selection Two hundred and seventy three articles were retrieved, of which 25 were selected. Data extraction Specifically: the level of care, the sources of information, the use of registration forms, the established time, the medical professional in charge and the registered variables such as errors of reconciliation. Results: Most of studies selected when the patient was admitted into the hospital and after the hospital discharge of the patient. The main sources of information to be highlighted are: the interview and the medical history of the patient. An established time is not explicitly stated on most of them, nor the registration form is used. The main professional in charge is the clinical pharmacologist. Apart from the home medication, the habits of self-medication and phytotherapy are also identified. The common errors of reconciliation vary from the omission of drugs to different forms of interaction with other medicinal products (drugs interactions). Conclusions: There is a large heterogeneity of methodologies used for reconciliation. There is not any work done on the specific figure of the polypathological patient, which precisely requires a standardized methodology due to its complexity and its susceptibility to errors of reconciliation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfaro-Lara, Eva Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto-Martín, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galván-Banqueri, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Guerrero, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Coca, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Ramos, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar una revisión bibliográfica para identificar las diferentes metodologías empleadas en el proceso de conciliación de los tratamientos farmacológicos que sean aplicables a pacientes pluripatológicos. Diseño: Revisión sistemática. Fuentes de datos: Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica (febrero de 2012) en las bases de datos Pubmed, EMBASE, CINAHL, PsycINFO e Índice Médico Español de métodos de conciliación del tratamiento en pacientes pluripatológicos, o en su defecto, ancianos o polimedicados. Selección de estudios: Se recuperaron 273 artículos, de los que se seleccionaron 25. Extracción de datos: Se extrajo información relativa a la metodología empleada: nivel asistencial en el que se realiza, fuentes de información, uso de formulario, tiempo establecido, profesional responsable, información recogida y variables registradas como errores de conciliación. Resultados: La mayoría de estudios fueron al ingreso y al alta hospitalarios Como principales fuentes de información destacan la entrevista y la historia clínica. En la mayoría de trabajos no se especifica un tiempo preestablecido, ni se usa formulario, y el principal responsable es el farmacéutico clínico. Además de la medicación domiciliaria, los hábitos de automedicación y la fitoterapia también son registrados. Se recogen como errores de conciliación desde omisiones de fármacos hasta interacciones medicamentosas. Conclusiones: Existe gran heterogeneidad en la metodología empleada para la actividad de la conciliación. No existe ningún trabajo realizado específicamente en el paciente pluripatológico, que por su complejidad y susceptibilidad a errores de conciliación requiere una metodología estandarizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(2): 89-99, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología de conciliación del tratamiento farmacológico en pacientes pluripatológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
