<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120405</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Composition of breast milk of lactating adolescents in function of time of lactation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to evaluate the composition of breast milk of lactating adolescents in function of lactation time. Methods: We followed 51 lactating adolescents, between the 6th and 14th weeks postpartum (WPP). The determination of fat, protein and lactose in milk were conducted, respectively, by the methods of Lucas, Lowry and Perry &amp; Doan. Micronutrients were determined by atomic absorption spectrophotometry. Data was presented by the mean and standard error. ANOVA with repeated measures was used and Tukey as post test. It was accepted a significance level of 5%. Results: There was a significant reduction (P&lt;0.05) in protein content during the postpartum weeks studied (6th: 16.6 ± 1.1; 10th: 13.7 ± 1.0; 14th WPP: 12.3 ± 1.1 g/day). The lactose (6th: 60.2 ± 1.9; 10th: 60.4 ± 2.6; 14th WPP: 65.1 ± 4.0 g/day) and fat (6th: 41.6 ± 3.3; 10th: 36.2 ± 3.4; 14th WPP: 31.5 ± 9.0 g/day) concentration remained unaffected. The zinc concentration in the breast milk was lower than that is commonly found in literature (mean 1.16 mg/day). The copper, iron, calcium and phosphorus concentration was sufficient to meet the needs of the infants between 0 and 6 months old. Conclusion: The lactation period did not influence the concentration of micronutrients, lactose and lipids, but there is a reduction on protein of the breast milk. In spite of the reducing concentration of protein, it is sufficient to meet the needs of infants from 0 to 6 months old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereira, Kallyne Bolognini</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedruzzi, Liliana Magnago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sileira, Camila Barros da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azeredo, Vilma Blondet de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la composición de la leche materna de lactantes adolescentes en función del tiempo de la lactancia. Métodos: Se siguieron 51 adolescentes lactantes, entre la semana 6 y 14 después del parto (WPP). Se llevaron a cabo la determinación de grasa, proteína y lactosa de la leche, respectivamente, por los métodos de Lucas, Lowry y Perry &amp; Doan. Los micronutrientes se determinaron por espectrofotometría de absorción atómica. Los datos fueron presentados por la media y el error estándar. ANOVA con medidas repetidas se utilizó Tukey como prueba post. Se aceptó un nivel de significación del 5%. Resultados: Se observó una reducción significativa (P &lt;0,05) en el contenido de proteína en las semanas después del parto estudiados (sexto: 16,6 ± 1,1; 10 a: 13,7 ± 1,0; 14a SPP: 12,3 ± 1,1 g/day). La lactosa (sexto: 60,2 ± 1,9; 10o: 60,4 ± 2,6; 14 a SPP: 65,1 ± 4,0 g/day) y grasa (sexto: 41,6 ± 3,3; 10o: 36,2 ± 3,4; 14 a SPP: 31,5 ± 9,0 g/day) concentración no se vio afectado. La concentración de zinc en la leche materna fue menor que se encuentra comúnmente en la literatura (media de 1,16 mg / día). La concentración de cobre, hierro, calcio y fósforo es suficiente para satisfacer las necesidades de los niños entre 0 y 6 meses de edad. Conclusión: El período de lactancia no influyó en la concentración de micronutrientes, la lactosa y los lípidos, pero hay una reducción en la proteína de la leche materna. A pesar de la reducción de la concentración de proteína, que es suficiente para satisfacer las necesidades de los bebés de 0 a 6 meses de edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(6): 1971-1976, nov.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120405</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición de la leche de madres lactantes adolescentes en relación con el tiempo de lactancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
