<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74729</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of opioid analgesic use in a general university hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to analyze opioid analgesic use in the La Paz University Hospital in 2008 in order to identify patterns of use and consumption. To that end, data from inpatients were analyzed overall, as well as by hospitals and departments. We analyzed data on consumption in the previous 5 years and quantified the use of there maining active principles administered as analgesics in our hospital. Materials and methods: Following the Wold Health Organization&#146;s guidelines for studies on medication use in hospitals, data are shown as defined daily dose (DDD) per 100hospital stays. Data on drug use were obtained from the drug management program, Farma Tools (Dominion®), which is used by the Pharmacy Service at La Paz Hospital. Results: The overall value of opioid utilization in 2008 was 8.1 DDD per 100 hospital stays. The most widely used active principles were parenteral morphine and transdermal fentanyl. Together, these drugs represented 83% of total opioid consumption. Analysis by hospital revealed that the General and Traumatology Hospitals showed the highest opioiddrug consumption and followed the same utilization pattern as overall use. The services most representative of opioid consumption in inpatients were the Recovery Room in the General and Traumatology Hospitals, Critical Care, Oncology, Hematology and Palliative Care. In the last 5 years of the study, the overall use of these drugs increased by 20%, irrespective of the active principles involved. Analysis of analgesic intake at La Paz Hospital showed widespread use (104 DDD per 100 hospital stays). Opioids represented7.4% of total analgesic consumption, the most frequently used analgesics being acetaminophen and metamizol. Conclusions: The results of our study show an increasing trend in opioid consumption in this hospital...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz y Ramón, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Salcedo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Ambrosio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido realizar un estudio de utilización de analgésicos opiáceos en el Hospital Universitario La Paz (Madrid) en el año 2008 para conocer cómo se está utilizando este grupo de medicamentos y cuál es la tendencia del consumo. Para ello, se presentan los datos de uso de opiáceos en pacientes ingresados de forma global, por hospitales y por servicios clínicos. Se exponen los datos de consumo de los 5 últimos años y se ha cuantificado el uso del resto de principios activos empleados como analgésicos en nuestro hospital. Material y métodos: Haciendo uso de la metodología recomendada por la Organización Mundial de la Salud para los estudios de utilización de medicamentos en hospitales, presentamos nuestros datos en dosis diarias definidas (DDD) por 100 estancias. Los datos de consumo se han obtenido del programa de gestión de medicamentos del Servicio de Farmacia Farma Tools (Dominion®) Resultados: El valor global de utilización de opiáceos en 2008 ha sido de 8,1 DDD/100estancias. Los principios activos más consumidos han sido la morfina parenteral y el fentanilo transdérmico, y entre los 2 representan el 83% del consumo total de opiáceos. En el análisis por hospitales apreciamos que el Hospital General y el de Traumatología son los que presentan un mayor empleo de opiáceos y siguen el mismo patrón de utilización que el global. Los servicios más representativos del consumo de opiáceos han sido las reanimaciones del Hospital General y de Traumatología, los Servicios de Oncología, Cuidados paliativos y Hematología. En estos últimos 5 años se ha producido un incremento global del consumo de aproximadamente el 20%, viéndose implicados todos los principios activos. Con relación al consumo total de analgésicos, los datos reflejan una amplia utilización en el hospital (104 DDD/100 estancias)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(7): 373-380, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de utilización de analgésicos opiáceos en un hospital general universitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
