<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150577</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral Alitretinoin in the Treatment of Severe Refractory Chronic Hand Eczema in the Spanish National Health System: Description and Analysis of Current Clinical Practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Hand eczema affects nearly 10% of the population. The condition becomes severe and chronic in 5% to 7% of cases and is refractory to topical corticosteroids in 2% to 4%. This study aimed to describe the current use of oral alitretinoin in treating Spanish national health system patients with hand eczema that is refractory to potent topical corticosteroids. Materials and methods: Observational, descriptive, exploratory, cross-sectional study based on the retrospective analysis of records for patients with hand eczema treated with alitretinoin in the Spanish national health system. Results: We reviewed the records for 62 patients in 13 hospitals in 5 different administrative areas (autonomous communities) of Spain. Alitretinoin was usually used at a dosage of 30mg/d. In most cases the physician judged the clinical response to be satisfactory after a single cycle. The recorded adverse effects were foreseeable and of the type reported for systemic retinoids. The dermatologists agreed that the clinical benefits achieved with alitretinoin favored adherence to treatment and an early return to work. Conclusions: The results show that oral alitretinoin is being used according to established recommendations and that response is good, with few adverse effects. The dermatologists agreed that the benefits favored adherence and improved the patients&#146; health related quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urrutia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plazas, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roustan, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armengol, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizan, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El eczema de manos (ECM) afecta a cerca del 10% de la población, presentándose entre el 5 y el 7% de los casos como una enfermedad crónica grave y siendo refractario al tratamiento con corticoides tópicos entre el 2 y el 4% de las veces. El propósito del artículo es describir el uso de la alitretinoína oral en pacientes con ECM refractario a corticoides tópicos potentes en el ámbito sanitario público español. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo, exploratorio, transversal, basado en la revisión retrospectiva de historias clínicas de pacientes con ECM en tratamiento con alitretinoína en el ámbito sanitario público español. Resultados: Se revisaron 62 historias clínicas de pacientes de 13 centros distribuidos en 5 comunidades autónomas del territorio español. Alitretinoína se utilizó predominantemente a dosis de 30mg/día, principalmente en un único ciclo, tras el cual la mayoría de pacientes lograron una respuesta clínica satisfactoria según el juicio médico. Los eventos adversos fueron todos previsibles y en línea con los tratamientos sistémicos con retinoides. Los dermatólogos estuvieron de acuerdo en que los beneficios clínicos logrados con alitretinoína favorecían la adherencia al tratamiento y una reincorporación más rápida de los pacientes al trabajo. Conclusión: Los resultados muestran un uso de alitretinoína oral en línea con las recomendaciones establecidas así como la buena respuesta al tratamiento asociado y los pocos efectos adversos. Los dermatólogos coinciden que los beneficios alcanzados favorecen la adherencia al tratamiento y mejoran la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;107(2): 142-148, mar. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de la alitretinoína oral para el tratamiento del eczema crónico de manos grave y refractario al tratamiento en el sistema sanitario público español: descripción y análisis de la práctica clínica actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55657^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55657^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
