<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112083</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rituximab as rescue therapy in refractory esophageal lichen planus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Esophageal lichen planus (ELP) is a rare condition with unknown prevalence that can sometimes be underestimated due to the subtle and nonspecific findings of diagnostic workup. Oral lesions rarely extend to the esophageal mucosa, but when they do, the most frequent symptoms are dysphagia and odynophagia. There is often a significant delay in diagnosis and inadequate treatment. We report the case of a 59-year-old woman diagnosed with ELP, successfully treated with rituximab, a chimeric monoclonal antibody that depletes CD20+B cells. To our knowledge, this is only the second report of this treatment in ELP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vila Costas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arín Letamendía, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Clavijo García, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Gil, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almendral López, María Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goñi Esarte, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Pérez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El liquen plano esofágico (LPE) es una entidad poco frecuente cuya prevalencia se desconoce, que puede en ocasiones estar subestimada por los hallazgos sutiles e inespecíficos en las exploraciones realizadas. Las lesiones orales rara vez se extienden para afectar a la mucosa esofágica pero, cuando lo hacen, provocan disfagia y odinofagia. Esta infrecuente afectación del liquen plano conlleva un retraso en el diagnóstico y un tratamiento inadecuado. Se presenta el segundo caso (en nuestro conocimiento) de una paciente de 59 años con LPE, con buena respuesta al tratamiento con rituximab, un anticuerpo monoclonal quimérico dirigido específicamente contra la proteína CD20 presente en los linfocitos B (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;36(4): 264-267, abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rescate con rituximab en paciente con liquen plano esofágico refractario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8186^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
