<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048718</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis C serology: prevalence study in postmortem poblation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: to assess infection HCV prevalence in corpses where judicial necropsy was ordered by court, in Barcelona city. To compare results with those actually known in epidemiology and public health services. Material and Methods: retrospective, observational analitic study carried out in the department laboratory of Medico Legal Institute, in Catalunya (Spain). The sample was proceeding from 169 corpses where HCV analysis was solicitated by the forensic doctors, during 2004. Methods: analytical procedure followed was enzimoinmune essay to detect HIV antibodies, using AsXym analyzer (Abbott). Variables included were sex , age and cause of death. Cause of dead was divided in two groups: natural death and drugs relationated death. Results of the analysis were classified as HCV + and HCV- according to laboratory test specifications. Results: HCV prevalence was 10,8% in natural deaths group and 60% in drug relationated death group. Conclussions: HCV prevalence described is higher than reported in published studies, specially regarding to natural deaths group. Nowadays virus affecting to asymptomatic people is considered. Periodic HCV prevalence studies in general poblation must be carried out to provide dades to epidemiology and health public services</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carboné Coté, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: estudiar la prevalencia de la infección por VHC en una población cadáver de la ciudad de Barcelona a la que se le practica la necropsia judicial. Comparar los datos con los conocidos en epidemiología y salud pública. Diseño: estudio observacional analítico, retrospectivo llevado a cabo en el Laboratorio del Instituto de Medicina Legal de Cataluña, en 169 cadáveres en los que se solicitó la determinación de VHC por el médico forense, durante el año 2004. Metodología: análisis mediante técnica de enzimoinmunoensayo para detección de anticuerpos VHC en el analizador AsXym (Abbot). Variables principales: se incluyeron las variables edad, sexo y causa de muerte dividida en dos grupos, muerte natural y muerte por reacción adversa a drogas. La variable de respuesta fue hepatits C positivo o negativo. Resultados: la prevalencia del resultado positivo a la infección en el grupo de muertes naturales fue del 10,8%. En el grupo de muerte por reacción adversa a drogas fue del 60%. Conclusiones: La prevalencia encontrada es mayor que la descrita en la literatura especialmente en el grupo de muertes naturales. Se considera que el virus afecta a un número de población que se halla asintomática. La realización de estudios periódicos de prevalencia de esta infección tienen interés en epidemiología y salud pública</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(6): 260-263, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048718</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Serología hepatitis C: estudio de prevalencia en población post mortem</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32731^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
