<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129740</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spongiform encephalopathy: a conversive disorder?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prionpathies represent a group of neurodegenerative diseases of familiar, sporadic or acquired origin, heterogeneous symptoms and fatal outcome. The psychiatric symptoms can be present at the beginning and/or during the clinical evolution, with the presence or not of neurological disorders. Patients with these sympthoms are referred to psychiatric units, both at hospital level and as outpatients, to study a psychiatric disorder. In the described clinical case, the patient was admitted several times at emergency units, rated by neurologists and psychiatrists leading to different psychiatric disorders diagnoses. However spongiform encephalopathy was diagnosed only during the last month of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández- Miranda López, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado Rueda, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca García, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Gutiérrez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las prionpatías, constituyen un grupo de enfermedades neurodegenerativas con presentación familiar, esporádica o adquirida, con clínica heterogenea y resultado fatal. Los síntomas psiquiátricos pueden estar presentes al inicio y/o durante la evolución del cuadro, con la presencia o no de focalidad neurológica. Esta condición conlleva a que estos pacientes sean derivados a unidades de Psiquiatría tanto a nivel hospitalario como ambulatorio, para estudio de trastornos psiquiátricos. El caso clínico que nos ocupa el paciente fue atendido en varias ocasiones en las Urgencias Hospitalarias, evaluado por neurólogos y psiquiatras con diversos diagnósticos psiquiátricos. Sin embargo, la encefalopatía espongiforme sólo fue diagnosticada en el último mes de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(124): 785-789, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129740</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La encefalopatía espongiforme: ¿un trastorno conversivo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
