<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135696</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Topical antimicrobial angent in dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Topical antimicrobial agents are chemical substances that, directly applied to the skin, inhibit the growth or destroy any microorganism, either fungi, viruses or bacteria. Within this term, we generally refer to those that are active against the latter. They are divided into antiseptics and antibiotics. Antiseptics are directly applied to a living organism to eradicate the existing microorganism on the mucocutaneous surfaces, preventing their proliferation. Topical antibiotics are either produced by living organisms or manufactured through synthesis and are mainly used to fight infections. Topical antimicrobials represent an important option in the prophylaxis and treatment of primary and secondary superficial bacterial infections. Antibiotics for topical use have a lower incidence of systemic toxicity, secondary effects and development of resistance than parenteral antibiotics. The ideal topical antimicrobial must have a broad spectrum of activity, fast and prolonged antibacterial effect, bactericidal activity, easy diffusion through tissues and detritus, with minimal toxicity, very low or null incidence of irritation or allergy and sparse activity against normal skin flora. The approach of this article is the description of the classical and new antimicrobials that are, more important due to their wide use and proven efficacy. We review their pharmacological characteristics, spectrum of activity, possible secondary effects and interactions, as well as the combinations that improve their antimicrobial activity, main indications and possible development of resistance, all this properly documented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Porras-Luque, J I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antimicrobianos tópicos son sustancias químicas que, aplicadas directamente en la piel, inhiben el crecimiento o destruyen cualquier microorganismo, bien sean hongos, virus, o bacterias. Dentro de este término generalmente nos referimos a los que tienen actividad frente a estas últimas. Se dividen en antisépticos y antibióticos. Los antisépticos se aplican directamente sobre los organismos vivos, para eliminar los microorganismos existentes en las superficies cutáneo-mucosas previniendo la proliferación de los mismos. Los antibióticos tópicos son producidos por seres vivos o fabricados por síntesis y se utilizan principalmente para combatir las infecciones. Los antimicrobianos tópicos suponen una importante opción en la profilaxis y tratamiento de las infecciones bacterianas superficiales primarias y secundarias. Los antibióticos para uso tópico poseen una más baja incidencia de toxicidad sistémica, de efectos secundarios y de desarrollo de resistencias que los antibióticos de uso parenteral. El antimicrobiano tópico ideal debe poseer un amplio espectro de acción, efecto antibacteriano rápido y prolongado, ser bactericida, difundir con facilidad a través de tejidos y detritus, con una mínima toxicidad, muy baja o nula incidencia de irritación o alergia y escasa actividad frente a la flora comensal de la piel. El enfoque del presente artículo es la descripción de los antimicrobianos clásicos y novedosos, más importantes por su amplia utilización y demostrada eficacia. Se exponen en este trabajo sus características farmacológicas, su espectro de acción, sus posibles efectos secundarios e interacciones, así como las combinaciones que favorecen su actividad antimicrobiana, las principales indicaciones y la posible aparición de resistencias, todo ello debidamente documentado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;98(supl.1): 29-39, sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antimicrobianos tópicos en Dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30508^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30508^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
