<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163348</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The interface health and environment in dialogue with students: resignifying the sense of care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: know the meanings produced by students from dialogues of health care and the environment. Methodology: a qualitative study with 65 students of two schools of the Pelotas /RS /Brazil. The data were collected from September to August/2011/2012. The material analyzed in this paper was produced at the end of 18 workshops from essays and speeches written by focus groups. Results: it was observed that the process of participation at the workshops created a close liaison between health care encompassing the human relationship with the environment. The dynamic provided the motivation for adopting collective conscious, ethical attitudes, gesture of citizenship and ressignification of the values and symbology, including in these medicinal plants. Conclusion: the health and environmental issues can be optimized and experienced in an enjoyable way when worked interconnected with the individual&#146;s culture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, Márcia Vaz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceolin, Teila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceolin, Silvana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heck, Rita Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendieta, Marjoriê</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rossato Badke, Márcio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: discutir los significados producidos por escolares a partir de diálogos de cuidados de salud y el medio ambiente. Metodología: estudio cualitativo con 65 alumnos de escuelas del municipio de Pelotas/RS/ Brazil. La recogida de datos se llevo a efecto de septiembre/2011 a agosto/2012. El material analizado es resultado de 18 talleres de grupos focales. Resultados: se observó que el proceso de participación en los talleres provocó un estrecho enlace entre la atención de la salud que abarca la relación humana con el medio ambiente. La dinámica proporciono la motivación para la adopción de actitudes conscientes, colectivas, éticas, ciudadanas, de resignificación de los valores y simbología, incluidos en estas plantas medicinales. Conclusión: la salud y el medio ambiente pueden ser optimizados y vividos de forma agradable cuando son convenientemente trabajados de manera relacional con la cultura de los individuos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;21(47): 158-164, ene.-abr. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163348</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La interfaz salud y medio ambiente en el diálogo com estudiantes: ressignificando el sentido del cuidado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
