<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147885</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medicinal plant research conducted by medical students in Peru</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to determine the contribution in medicinal plant research conducted by medical students in Peru a bibliometric study was conducted, using as source of analysis the abstract books of the National Scientific Congress of medical students conducted in Peru during the years 2005 to 2011. Research in basic sciences which were aimed at the medicinal properties of plants were selected. As results, 17.4% (95/546) of the investigations were about medicinal plants, experimental model in vivo was 73.7%; mostly type used was the aqueous extract (29.5%), the alcohol-hidroalcohol (20.0%) and essential oil (12.6%); 21 reported possible medicinal utilities; 15.8% of all the investigations was published in a scientific journal. We conclude that there is interest in research on medicinal plants. We conclude that there is interest in the study of medicinal plants in undergraduate medical students. Support of schools for their development and communication of results through the publication is required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bendezú-Quispe, Guindo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camilo Torres-Romucho, Camilo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo-Hernández, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acevedo-Villar, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarco, J Jhonel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de determinar la contribución a la investigación sobre plantas medicinales por estudiantes de medicina en Perú se realizó un estudio bibliométrico, utilizando como fuente de análisis los libros de resúmenes de los Congresos Científicos Nacionales de estudiantes de Medicina realizados en Perú durante los años 2005 al 2011. Se seleccionaron las investigaciones en ciencias básicas que tuvieron como  objeto las propiedades medicinales de las plantas. El 17,4% (95/546) de las investigaciones fueren sobre plantas medicinales, el modelo de experimentación en e173,7% era in vivo; en su mayoría el tipo de extracto usado fue el acuoso (29,5%), el alcohólico y/o hidroalcohólico (20,0%) y el aceite esencial  (12,6%);se reportaron 21 posibles utilidades medicinales; e1 15,8% de las investigaciones fue  pub&amp;#64258;cada en alguna revista científica. Concluimos que existe interés hacia el estudio de plantas medicinales desde el pregrado médico, siendo necesario el apoyo de 103 centros educativos para su desarrollo y la comunicación de resultados a través de la publicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;15(2): 165-171, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación sobre plantas medicinales realizada por estudiantes de medicina en Perú</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24567^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24567^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24567^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
