<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121131</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reference values of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) version for parents in the Spanish population, 2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) is one of the most frequently used screening test for children and adolescents mental health (MH). In 2006,the Spanish National Health Survey included the child&#146;s MH section through the SDQ version for parents. Objective: To obtain reference values of the SDQ parents Spanish version for the 4-15 year-old population living in Spain during 2006-2007.Methodology: From the Spanish National HealthSurvey-2006, measurements of central tendency, dispersion and percentiles scores were calculated for the &#147;Total Difficulties Score&#148; (TDS-SDQ) Index and for the five dimensions of the questionnaire. Results: A sample made up of 6266 children, ages 4 to15 years, having national representativeness was obtained. Regarding the TDS-SDQ Index, scores were higher (worse MH) in boys than in girls (9.66 vs 9.04) and were higher in the younger age group in the total sample (9.90, 9.49 and8.73) and also in boys. Girls scored higher than boys on the emotional symptoms and prosocial dimensions, and the scores were higher in older age group for the total sample. Regarding behavior problems, the younger age group scored higher in the total sample (2.19, 1.87 and 1.76) and by sex. Boys scored higher than girls on hyperactivity (4.51 vs. 3.92) and scores were lower in older ages in total sample (4.71, 4.19 and 3.82) and by sex. Peer problems dimension has no statistically significant differences by sex or age. Conclusions: The population values shown are informative and extend the knowledge and interpretation of the SDQ results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando-Arizaleta, Lauro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriuso-Lapresa, Laura M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rajmil, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) -Cuestionario de Capacidades y Dificultades-, es uno de los test de cribado de salud mental (SM) infanto-juvenil empleado con más frecuencia. En 2006, la Encuesta Nacional de Salud de España (ENSE), introdujo el apartado de SM del menor a través de la versión para padres del SDQ. Objetivo: Obtener los valores de referencia de la versión española del cuestionario SDQ-padres para la población de 4a 15 años residente en España en los años 2006-2007.Metodología: A partir de la ENSE-2006, se calculan las medidas de tendencia central, dispersión y percentiles de las puntuaciones del Índice Total Difficulties Score (TDS-SDQ) y de las cinco dimensiones del cuestionario. Resultados: Muestra con representatividad nacional constituida por 6266 niños/as de 4 a 15 años. Para el Índice TDS-SDQ, los niños puntúan más elevado (peor SM) que las niñas (9,66 vs 9,04) y la puntuación disminuye al aumentarla edad en la muestra total (9,90, 9,49 y 8,73) y en los niños. En las dimensiones síntomas emocionales y conducta prosocial, las niñas puntúan más elevado que los niños y la puntuación aumenta con la edad. Para problemas de conducta, la puntuación es mayor en los más jóvenes en el conjunto de los entrevistados (2,19, 1,87 y 1,76) y desagregando por sexo. Para hiperactividad, los niños puntúan más que las niñas (4,51 vs 3,92) y la puntuación disminuye con la edad en el total de la muestra (4,71, 4,19 y 3,82) y por sexos. La dimensión problemas con compañeros no presenta diferencias estadísticamente significativas según sexo ni edad. Conclusiones: Los valores poblacionales presentados resultan informativos y amplían los conocimientos y la interpretación de los resultados del SDQ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;42(2): 43-48, mar.-abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia de la versión para padres del Cuestionario de Capacidades y Dificultades (SDQ) en población española, 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
