<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64576</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Congenital hyperinsulinism (CHI) is the most common cause of persistent hypoglycaemia in infancy. The differential diagnosis between focal and diffuse forms of CHI is of great importance when planning surgery. The aim of this article is to show the first case of focal CHI diagnosed in Spain using PET-CT imaging combined with genetic analysis. Methods: A 13 month child with CHI and normal conventional radiological investigations treated with diazoxide, diet control and feeding by gastrostomy is presented. Genetic analysis of ABCC8 and KCNJ11 genes and PET-TAC using 18F-fluoro-L-DOPA were performed. Results: A pathological mutation (G111R) in the paternal allele of ABCC8 was detected. PET-CT scanning using 18F-fluoro-L-DOPA showed a focus of high uptake in the body of the pancreas compatible with adenoma that was hystopathologically confirmed. After surgical resection the patient is asymptomatic without needing either pharmacological treatment or dietetic control. Conclusions: The combination of genetic analysis and 18F-fluoro-L-DOPA PET-TAC shows a great potential for the identification, location and guideline for surgery in CHI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Richter Echevarría, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carracedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino Casado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Marmiesse, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azcona San Julián, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbizu Lostao, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrastachu Zumarrán, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La distinción entre el hiperinsulinismo congénito (CHI) focal y difuso es esencial de cara al tratamiento y pronóstico de la enfermedad. El objetivo es presentar el primer caso de CHI focal diagnosticado en España combinando los estudios genético y PET-TC. Métodos: Paciente de 13 meses con CHI y pruebas de imagen convencionales normales, tratado con diazóxido, control dietético y alimentación por gastrostomía. Se analizó la secuencia de los genes ABCC8 y KCNJ11, y realizó una PET-TC con 18F-fluoro-L-DOPA. Resultados: Se detectó una mutación patogénica (G111R) en el alelo paterno de ABCC8. La PET-TC demostró un foco hipercaptante en el cuerpo del páncreas compatible con un adenoma confirmado histopatológicamente. Tras la cirugía el paciente continúa asintomático sin tratamiento farmacológico ni medidas dietéticas. Conclusiones: La combinación del análisis genético y la PET-TC con 18F-fluoro-L-DOPA muestra un gran potencial para la identificación, localización y guía de la cirugía del CHI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(5): 481-485, mayo 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64576</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23254^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5939^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5939^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5939^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23785^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
