<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157704</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8169</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical perspective of the platelet and its connection to thromboembolic disease and its treatment (past, present and future)</dc:title>
<dc:creator>García Rafanell, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">This article gives a historical review, from the middle of the last century to the present, of the importance of the platelet and its functional activity in thromboembolic disease. This review begins in the first half of the last century when this blood component was almost exclusively known for its role in primary haemostasis. However, in the nineteen-eighties and nineties, it becomes a key player in the formation of arterial thrombus. Currently and in the coming years it will be considered as an important factor, but just one more, in the formation and development of thrombotic processes. A review is done of the key events that have permitted this evolution and how this has enabled the discovery and development of platelet inhibitor drugs, in particular Trifusal, an anti-platelet agent obtained from research carried out by Uriach Laboratories. Due to this discovery, R&amp;d history at Uriach has been linked, for over four decades, to the historical evolution of both the platelet and thromboembolic disease</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. hist;36(3): 4-15, 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157704</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectiva histórica de la plaqueta y su conexión con la enfermedad tromboembólica y su tratamiento (pasado, presente y futuro)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1804^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38363^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38363^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1804</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4691^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1819^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1819^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4691^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
