<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113068</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of personality in satisfaction with life and sport</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study tested the relationships between personality, measured with the Neuroticism Extraversion Openness Personality Inventory-Revised (NEO-PI-R), satisfaction with life and satisfaction with sport, based on the five dimensions and on the thirty facets. Consistent with previous studies, satisfaction with life and satisfaction with sport were highly correlated. Stepwise regressions analysis showed that neuroticism and extraversion were the best predictors of life and sport satisfaction, bearing in mind that the other dimensions did not provide any prediction whatsoever. These results also indicated that a more precise facet-based assessment of personality significantly increased the prediction of satisfaction with life. The parametrical or graphical regression analysis LOESS revealed an interesting and different relationship between personality and satisfaction with life and sport</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baudin, Nicolas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanch, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aluja, Anton</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pierre Rolland, Jean</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio evaluó las relaciones entre la personalidad, medida por el &#147;Inventario de personalidad, neuroticismo, extraversión y apertura, revisado&#148; (Neuroticism Extraversion Openness Personality Inventory-Revised NEO-PI-R), satisfacción con la vida y la satisfacción con el deporte, basándose en las cinco dimensiones y las treinta facetas. Siendo consistentes con estudios previos, la satisfacción con la vida y la satisfacción con el deporte tuvieron una alta correlación. Un análisis de regresión por pasos sucesivos mostró que el neuroticismo y la extraversión eran los mejores predictores de la satisfacción con la vida y con el deporte, teniendo en cuenta que las otras dimensiones no aportaron ninguna predicción. Estos resultados también indicaron que una valoración más precisa de la personalidad, con base en las facetas, aumentó la predicción en la satisfacción con la vida. Un análisis de regresión gráfica o paramétrico LOESS mostró una relación interesante y diferente entre la personalidad y la satisfacción con la vida y con el deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(2): 333-345, mayo-ago. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/El papel de la personalidad en la satisfacción con la vida y el deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
