<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135483</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Esteem hearing implant by Envoy Medical</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Esteem hearing implant by Envoy Medical is a fully implantable system that uses piezoelectric transducers. This device uses the eardrum as the microphone. The mechanical signal is detected by a piezoelectric transducer at the head of the incus (the sensor) and converted to an electrical signal that is amplified, filtered, and converted back to a vibratory signal. The processed vibratory signal is then delivered by another piezoelectric transducer (the driver) to the stapes capitulum (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Algaba Guimerá, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolinaga Zubizarreta, Uxue</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altuna Mariezcurrena, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Esteem de Envoy Medical es un implante piezoeléctrico de oído medio totalmente integrado. No precisa micrófono, ya que emplea la fisiología normal del conducto auditivo y del tímpano para la recepción del sonido que, gracias a un primer transductor con funciones de sensor colocado en el yunque, convierte la señal mecánica en eléctrica, que se procesa y se reconvierte nuevamente en señal vibratoria gracias a un segundo transductor (el driver), que transmite la nueva señal al estribo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;59(supl.1): 33-34, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implante Esteem, de Envoy System</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6471^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54281^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4493^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13064^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19281^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
