<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133426</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric Cardiology and Fetal Echocardiography Unit: past, present and future of a prototype specialty of quality and high resolution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatric cardiology is the speciality that refers to the care of children with congenital or acquired disorders of the heart and vessels from conception through adolescent. Congenital heart defects are the most common pediatric congenital malformation, presenting an incidence of nearly 1% of all living RN. This fact, together with the advancement of technologies and years, associated with the appearance of ultrasound and high resolution techniques, has made the paediatric cardiology a major speciality, not only by the number of patients seen but al so by the significance of pathology that we see in our daily journal. In this article we review the history and current functioning of the section of paediatric cardiology and fetal echocardiography unit at University Hospital of Basurto, mainstay and prototype of high resolution consultations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Serrano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cardiología infantil es la especialidad pediátrica encargada de la asistencia integral al niño con enfermedad congénita o adquirida del sistema cardiovascular, abarcando desde la concepción a la adolescencia. Las cardiopatías congénitas constituyen la malformación congénita más frecuente en pediatría, presentando una incidencia cercana al 1% entre todos los RN vivos. Este hecho, junto al avance de las tecnologías y de los tiempos asociado a la aparición de ecógrafos y de técnicas de alta resolución, han hecho de la cardiología pediátrica una especialidad muy importante, no solo por el número de pacientes que atiende, sino también por la trascendencia de la patología que tratamos en nuestro quehacer diario. En este artículo repasaremos la historia y el funcionamiento actual de lo que es la sección de cardiología infantil y la unidad ecocardiografía fetal del Hospital Universitario de Basurto, pilares fundamentales y prototipos de consulta de alta resolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;70(6): 342-345, nov.-dic. 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidad de Cardiología Pediátrica y Ecocardiografía fetal: pasado, presente y futuro de una especialidad prototipo de calidad y de alta resolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
