<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79243</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The extracellular matrix: From the molecular mechanics to the tumoral microenvironment (part II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionThe extracellular matrix (ECM) is a three-dimensional network that envelopes all the organs, tissues and cells of the body. A biophysical filter that provides protection, nutrition and cell innervation, it is the site for the immune response, angiogenesis, fibrosis and tissue regeneration. It is also the transport medium for mechanical forces to the basal membrane through integrins that support the tensegrity system, activating cellular epigenetic mechanisms.Method and resultsThe review of the literature shows how the disruption of the ECM leads to a functional loss of nutrition, elimination, cell innervation, regenerative capacity and wound healing as well as alterations in mechanical transduction. This loss also disrupts the immune response to pathogens, tumour cells and toxins.Method and resultsThe second part of our revision of the ECM considers tumours as interconnected, functional tissues dependant on their microenvironment. The tumoural microenvironment, which is comprised of the ECM, stromal cells and the immune response, determines the morphology of the tumour and its classification as well as its clinical aggressivity, prognosis and response to treatment.ConclusionsBoth in physiological and pathological conditions, the reciprocal communication between the cells of the stroma and the parenchyma direct the genetic expression. The onocogenic capacity of the stroma depends not only on the fibroblasts associated with the tumour but also on the cellularity of the immune response and the alteration in the tensegrity model of the ECM. The epithelial-mesenchymal transition is the change which transforms a normal, or benign, cell into a malignant one. The &#147;pseudomesenchymal&#148; cytoskeleton provides the properties of migration, invasion and dissemination, and vice-versa: the malignant phenotype is reversible by correction of the key factors that create the tumoural microenvironment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvaro, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera-Salvá, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariñas-Guerrero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónLa matriz extracelular (MEC) representa una red tridimensional que engloba todos los órganos, tejidos y células del organismo. Constituye un filtro biofísico de protección, nutrición e inervación celular y el terreno para la respuesta inmune, angiogénesis, fibrosis y regeneración tisular. También representa el medio de transmisión de fuerzas mecánicas a la membrana basal, que a través de las integrinas soporta el sistema de tensegridad y activa los mecanismos epigenéticos celulares.Método y resultadosLa revisión de la literatura y actualización del tema muestran como la alteración de la MEC supone la pérdida de su función de filtro eficaz, nutrición, eliminación, denervación celular, pérdida de la capacidad de regeneración y cicatrización y alteración de la transmisión mecánica o mecanotransducción. También la pérdida del sustrato para una correcta respuesta inmune ante agentes infecciosos, tumorales y tóxicos.Método y resultadosEsta segunda parte de revisión de la MEC considera los tumores como tejidos funcionales conectados y dependientes del microambiente. El microambiente tumoral, constituido por la MEC, células del estroma y la propia respuesta inmune son determinantes de la morfología y clasificación tumoral, agresividad clínica, pronóstico y respuesta al tratamiento del tumor.ConclusiónTanto en condiciones fisiológicas como patológicas, la comunicación recíproca entre células del estroma y el parénquima dirige la expresión génica. La capacidad oncogénica del estroma procede tanto de los fibroblastos asociados al tumor como de la celularidad de la respuesta inmune y la alteración de la tensegridad por la MEC. La transición epitelio-mesenquimal es el cambio que transforma una célula normal o «benigna» en «maligna»...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(1): 24-32, ene.-mar.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La matriz extracelular: de la mecánica molecular al microambiente tumoral (parte II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5208^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5208^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34441^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34441^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24746^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24746^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
