<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88809</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of Fine Breathable Particles (PM2.5) as a Marker of Environmental Smoke in Catering Establishments in Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the levels of small breathable suspended particles (PM2.5) as atmospheric markersof environmental tobacco smoke in catering establishments in Zaragoza, Spain.Material and method: An observational study was conducted between October 2006 and April 2008 invarious catering establishments in Zaragoza. A SidePack Aerosol Monitor (AM510 model) was used tosample and record the levels of breathable suspended particles (PM2.5) indoors and outdoors, and thefollowing variables were collected: smoking policy (smoking allowed, completely banned, or partiallybanned with non-smoking sections, physically separated or not); percentage of smokers and presence ofcigarette ends, ashtrays or smokers in non-smoking sections.Results: A total of 111 venues were sampled. The level ofPM2.5 was eight times higher in smoking venuesthan in non-smoking ones and also higher than outdoors. The correlation between the level of particlesand percentage of smokers was 0.61 (P &lt; .01). In the non- smoking sections without physical separationthe level of particles was twice as much as outdoors and similar to physically separated smokers sections.Conclusion: Only a complete ban on smoking in all workplaces, including leisure venues, has been shownto have a positive effect on workers and customers health. The measurement of PM2.5 can be a simplemethod to assess the presence of environmental tobacco smoke(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Córdoba, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nebot, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nerín, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alayeto, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la contaminación por humo ambiental de tabaco mediante la medición de PM2.5 enuna muestra de locales de hostelería de la ciudad de Zaragoza, Espa&#152;na.Material y métodos: Estudio transversal observacional realizado entre octubre de 2006 y abril de 2008en locales de hostelería de Zaragoza. Para las mediciones de partículas PM2.5 se empleó un monitorSidePack Aerosol Monitor (modelo AM510). Se realizó una medición en el interior y otra en el exterior,y se recogieron las siguientes variables observacionales: se&#152;nalización sobre la permisividad de fumar;división (física o funcional) entre áreas de fumadores y no fumadores; porcentaje de personas que fumanrespecto al total; presencia de ceniceros, colillas o personas fumando en zonas y locales de no fumadores.Resultados: Se incluyeron 111 locales. La concentración de partículas fue casi 8 veces mayor en loslocales de fumador que en los de no fumadores y superior a la del exterior. La correlación encontradaentre concentración de partículas y porcentaje de fumadores fue de 0,61 (p &lt; 0,01). La concentración departículas en las zonas de no fumadores de los locales sin separación física (separación funcional) fue eldoble que en el exterior y similar a la de las zonas de fumadores cuando hay separaciones físicas.Conclusión: Las separaciones funcionales no protegen frente al humo de tabaco ambiental, sólo los lugarestotalmente libres de humo son eficaces para disminuir este riesgo. La medición de PM2.5 puede serun método sencillo para evaluar la existencia de humo ambiental de tabaco(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(4): 190-194, abr. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medición del nivel de partículas finas respirables (PM2.5) como marcador del humo ambiental del tabaco en locales de hostelería de Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25413^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25413^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
