<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120102</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-123X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The prevalence of MIH (Molar-Incisor-Hypomineralization) in the Area 2 children population of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To determine the prevalence of MIH (Molar- Incisor Hypomineralization) in the Area-2 in children population.  Method: The assignment was performed via a sequence of ramdom numbers applied to the list of paediatric dental treatment cards (1,914 children, of whom 789 lived in an urban area and 1.125 in a rural area), thereby revising 193 dental treatment cards, 79 belonging to children from urban areas and 114 to children from rural areas. The analyses were performed using version 6.04 of the EPIINFO version 6.04 (World Health Organization, Geneva Switzerland 2001) and CIA v 1,2 (Martin J. Gardner &amp; British Medical Journal 1992).  Results: The prevalence of MIH in our study was of 12,4% (8.1%-17.9%), corresponding to 24 children affected out of a total of 193 children checked. Conclusions: This prevalence level of 12,4% indicated that MIH is a common pathology in our environment. We found significant differences with respect to the children's year of birth, with a notable increase from 5.9% among those born in 1995 compared to 23.4% among those born in 1998 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puente Ruiz, Cristina de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Salvanés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comes Martínez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de MIH (hipomineralización de molares e incisivos) en una población infantil del Área 2.  Metodología: La asignación se hizo mediante una secuencia de números aleatorios que se aplicó al listado de cartillas odontopediátricas (sobre 1914 niños de los cuales 789 niños pertenecen a zona urbana y 1125 niños a zona rural) por lo que se revisaron 193 cartillas, 79 niños de niños de zona urbana y 114 de zona rural. Los análisis se realizaron con ayuda de los programas EPIINFO versión 6.04 (World Health Organization, Geneva Switzerland 2001) y CIA. y 1.2 (Martin J. Gardner &amp; British Medical Journal 1992).  Resultados: La prevalencia de MIH en nuestro estudio fue de un 12,4% (8,1-17,9%) lo que corresponde a 24 niños afectados de los 193 revisados.  Conclusiones: Esta prevalencia, 12,4%, indica que la MIH es una patología frecuente en nuestro ámbito. Encontramos diferencias significativas respecto al año de nacimiento con un incremento notable pasando de 5,9% en los nacidos en 1995 a 23,4% los nacidos en 1998 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>RCOE;12(3): 129-134, jul.-sept. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de Hipomineralización en primeros molares permanentes (MIH) en población infantil del Área 2 de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29774^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14461^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32880</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
