<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164789</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arthroscopic reconstruction for unstable scaphoid non-union</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the results of arthroscopic reconstruction for the treatment of unstable scaphoid non-union with cancellous bone autograft. Methods. 13 patients were treated with a mean age of 26 (18-45) years. The average time from injury until surgery was 14 (6-48) months. Preoperative and postoperative clinical and radiological parameters were evaluated. Mean follow-up was 16.8 (12-36) months. Results. Consolidation was achieved in all cases at 7 (4-10 weeks), no patient had complications or reoperations. Range of motion, pain, functional assessment (DASH questionnaire) and radiological measurements improved compared to preoperative measurements. The average range of flexion improved: flexion 71.9° (55°-80°) to 81.7° (55°-90°), extension 66.3° (30°-80°) to 84.4° (70° -90°), ulnar deviation 21.5 (10°-25°) to 25.5° (20°-45°) and radial deviation 11.9° (5°-25°) to 13.3° (10th-20th). Pain (VAS 0-10) improved from 6.8 (4-10) to 0.7 (0-3). DASH functional scale improved from 36 (12-78) to 8 (0-10). The Scapho-Lunate Angle improved from 67.7° (62°-88°) to 47° (32°-55°), and the Radio-Lunate Angle improved from 30.8° (10° -45°) to 4(0°-10°). Conclusion. Treatment of unstable scaphoid non-union with cancellous bone graft assisted by arthroscopy presents good clinical results with a short period of consolidation and recovery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nikolaev, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Jiménez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueredo-Ojeda, FA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Serrano, PJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil de Rozas-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar los resultados de la reconstrucción artroscópica para el tratamiento de la seudoartrosis de escafoides inestable con autoinjerto de hueso esponjoso. Método. Se trató a 13 pacientes con una edad media de 26 (18-45) años. El tiempo medio desde la fractura hasta la intervención fue de 14 (6-48) meses. Se evaluaron parámetros clínicos y radiológicos preoperatorios y postoperatorios. El seguimiento medio fue de 16,8 (12-36) meses. Resultados. La consolidación se obtuvo en todos los casos a las 7 (4-10 semanas), ningún paciente presentó complicaciones ni precisó nuevas reintervenciones. El arco de movilidad, la dolor, la valoración funcional (cuestionario DASH) y las mediciones radiológicas mejoraron respecto al preoperatorio. El rango de movimiento promedio de flexión mejoró de 71,9° (55°-80°) a 81,7° (55°-90°), extensión de 66,3° (30°-80°) a 84,4° (70°-90°), desviación ulnar 21,5° (10°-25°) a 25,5° (20°-45°) y desviación radial 11,9° (5°-25°) a 13,3° (10°-20°). El dolor (EVA 0-10) mejoró de 6,8 (4-10) a 0,7 (0-3). Y la escala funcional DASH mejoró de 36 (12-78) a 8 (0-10). El ángulo escafolunar mejoró de 67,7° (62°-88°) a 47° (32°-55°) y el ángulo radiolunar mejoró de 30,8° (10°-45°) a 4° (0°-10°). Conclusión. El tratamiento de seudoartrosis de escafoides inestables con injerto esponjoso asistido por artroscopia presenta buenos resultados clínicos, con un corto tiempo de consolidación y recuperación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(4): 216-223, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164789</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción artroscópica de la seudoartrosis inestable del escafoides carpiano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
