<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107596</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposals for improving the process of accreditation for specialized Healthcare training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After presenting the defining characteristics of the various manuals used in the external evaluation of the accreditation process for specialist training in our country, the article discusses a series of reflections on  various aspects that shaped the recent implementation of a new manual. Taking into account existing both in our country and international experience, the proposals are intended to provide ideas that will enrich the necessary process  of improving the system of accreditation, which foster a debate involving all actors and involved in the training system for specialization in Health Sciences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Muñoz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro Aguado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zancajo Castañares, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras exponer las características definitorias de los distintos manuales empleados en la evaluación externa del proceso de acreditación para la formación especializada  en nuestro país, el artículo plantea una serie de reflexiones sobre los diversos aspectos que confluyen en la reciente aplicación de un nuevo manual. Teniendo en cuenta la experiencia existente, tanto en nuestro país como en el ámbito internacional, las  propuestas pretenden aportar ideas que enriquezcan el necesario proceso de mejora del sistema de acreditación, al tiempo que propiciar un debate en que participen todos los actores implicados en el sistema de formación para la especialización en Ciencias de la  Salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(280): 19-23, dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107596</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuestas de mejora del proceso de acreditación para la formación especializada en Ciencias de la Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
