<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040422</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8241</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of different settings on the blood pressure values measured with automatic device</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The best possible information on the validity of the blood pressure (BP) measurement must be available in the nursing consultations, in the patients' home and in the pharmacies. This includes making readings of the BP with validated electronic instruments. The objectives of this study were to know the influence of the health care setting (medical consultation, nursing consultation and pharmacy) and non-sanitary one (home) in the BP values and their relationship with BP measured by out-patient monitoring. Material and methods. Cross-sectional and multicenter study that included hypertensive patients over 30 years treated with antihypertensive drugs and enrolled by consecutive sampling. BP measurement was done following standardized guidelines, on a single day, according to the following sequence: first in the patients' home (self-measurement), after, alternatively, in the medical and nursing consultation and finally in the pharmacy. In every case, a validated automatic electronic monitor was used. In a sample of non-selected patients, out-patient monitoring of the BP was done with validated instrument. Results. A total of 1,399 patients (50.4 % women), with mean age (SD) of 60.1 (9.7) years were included. The BP values obtained in the physician's consultation were significantly greater than those obtained in the nursing consultation, in the pharmacy and in the homes (p &lt; 0.01 in the three cases). The mean differences were more outstanding for the measurements done in the physician's consultation and at home, it being 2.79 (9.5) mmHg (p &lt; 0.001) for the systolic BP (SBP) and 0.88 (6,3) mmHg (p &lt; 0.001) for the diastolic BP (DBP). The smallest differences were observed between the pharmacy and home measurements, these being 0.69 (8.1) mmHg for the SBP (p = 0.007) and 0.15 (5.48) for the DBP (p = 0.370). The SBP obtained at home and the DBP obtained in the nursing consultation were related more closely with the daytime out-patient SBP and BBP. Discussion. The BP readings measured at home, nursing consultation and pharmacy are inferior to those recorded by the physicians and are well related with the out-patient monitoring. Our results indicate that the measurement of BP at home, nursing consultation and pharmacy minimize the white coat effect induced by the physician</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llisterri Caro, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Lima, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abellán Alemán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís Doménech, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Es necesario tener la mejor información posible sobre la validez de la medida de la presión arterial (PA) en las consultas de enfermería, en el domicilio de los pacientes y en las oficinas de farmacia, lo que incluye realizar lecturas de la PA con instrumentos electrónicos validados. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron conocer la influencia del ambiente sanitario (consulta médica, consulta enfermería y farmacia) y no sanitario (domicilio) en las cifras de PA y la relación de éstas con la PA determinada por monitorización ambulatoria. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal y multicéntrico que incluyó pacientes hipertensos mayores de 30 años tratados con fármacos antihipertensivos y reclutados mediante muestreo consecutivo. La medida de PA se realizó siguiendo normas estandarizadas, un solo día, atendiendo a la siguiente secuencia: primero, en el domicilio de los pacientes (automedida); después de manera alternativa, en la consulta médica y de enfermería, y finalmente, en la farmacia. En todos los casos se utilizó un monitor electrónico automático validado. En una muestra de pacientes no seleccionados se realizó monitorización ambulatoria de la PA con instrumento validado. Resultados. Se incluyeron 1.399 pacientes (50,4 % mujeres), con edad media (DE) de 60,1 (9,7) años. Los valores de PA obtenidos en las consultas de los médicos fueron significativamente superiores a los obtenidos en las consultas de enfermería, en las farmacias y en los domicilios (p &lt; 0,01 en los tres casos). Las diferencias medias fueron más acusadas para las determinaciones realizadas en consulta del médico y el domicilio, siendo de 2,79 (9,5) mmHg (p &lt; 0,001) para la PA sistólica (PAS) y de 0,88 (6,3) mmHg (p &lt; 0,001) para la PA diastólica (PAD). Las menores diferencias se observaron entre las medidas de farmacia y de domicilio, siendo de 0,69 (8,1) mmHg para la PAS (p = 0,007) y de 0,15 (5,48) para la PAD (p = 0,370). La PAS obtenida en domicilio y la PAD obtenida en consulta de enfermería se relacionaron más estrechamente con la PAS y la PAD ambulatoria diurna. Discusión. Las lecturas de PA medidas en domicilio, consultas de enfermería y oficinas de farmacia son inferiores a las registradas por los médicos y se relacionan bien con la monitorización ambulatoria. Nuestros resultados indican que la medida de PA en domicilio, consulta de enfermería y oficinas de farmacia minimiza el efecto de blanca inducido por el médico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertensión (Madr., Ed. impr.);22(6): 249-258, ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de distintos ambientes sobre los valores de la presión arterial medida con dispositivo automático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1328^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
