<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140472</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceptions and experiences of access to health services and their utilization among the immigrant population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify and describe the needs and problems of the immigrant population related to access and utilization of health services. Method: A descriptive, qualitative, phenomenological study was conducted using focus groups. The study area was the county of Campo de Gibraltar (Spain), which represents the gateway to Europe for immigration from Africa. The final sample size (51 immigrants from 11 countries) was determined by theoretical saturation. A narrative analysis was conducted with QSR NVivo9 software. Results: Immigrants&#146; discourse showed four categories of analysis: response to a health problem, system access, knowledge of social and health resources, and health literacy needs. Responses to health problems and the route of access to the health care system differed according to some sociodemographic characteristics (nationality/culture of origin, length of residence, and economic status). In general, immigrants primarily used emergency services, hampering health promotion and prevention. The health literacy needs identified concerned language proficiency and the functioning of the health system. Conclusions: There is a need to promote interventions to enhance health literacy among immigrants. These interventions should take into account diversity and length of residence, and should be based on an action-participation methodology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albar-Marín, M Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gutiérrez, Martina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ramírez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bas-Sarmiento, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar y describir las necesidades y los problemas percibidos por la población inmigrante en relación con el acceso y la utilización de los servicios de salud. Método: Estudio cualitativo descriptivo de orientación fenomenológica mediante grupos focales. El ámbito de estudio fue la comarca del Campo de Gibraltar, puerta de entrada a Europa para la inmigración procedente de África. La saturación teórica determinó el tamaño final de la muestra (51 inmigrantes de 11 nacionalidades). Se llevó a cabo un análisis narrativo del contenido con el software informático QSR NVivo9. Resultados: Los discursos muestran cuatro categorías de análisis: respuesta ante un problema de salud, acceso al sistema, conocimiento de recursos sociosanitarios y necesidades de alfabetización en salud. Las respuestas desplegadas ante los problemas de salud y la forma de acceder al sistema sanitario son distintas en función de algunas características sociodemográficas (nacionalidad/cultura de origen, tiempo de estancia y estatus económico). En general utilizan principalmente la asistencia sanitaria a demanda cuando presentan problemas de salud, y quedan relegados los servicios de promoción y prevención de la salud. Las necesidades de alfabetización en salud detectadas se relacionan sobre todo con el dominio del idioma y el funcionamiento del sistema sanitario. Conclusiones: Es necesario fomentar intervenciones destinadas a potenciar la alfabetización en salud de la población inmigrante, que atiendan a la diversidad, tengan en cuenta el tiempo de estancia y partan de una metodología de acción-participación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(4): 244-251, jul.-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción y experiencias en el acceso y el uso de los servicios sanitarios en población inmigrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33962</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53793</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
