<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128938</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative anesthetic management of 300 morbidly obese patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Laparoscopic bariatric surgery is a challenge for anesthesiologists because morbidly obese patients are at high risk and laparoscopy may complicate respiratory and hemodynamic management. The aim of this study was to analyze the perioperative anesthetic management of morbidly obese patients undergoing laparoscopic bariatric surgery. Material and methods: Prospective study of 300 consecutive patients diagnosed with morbid obesity and scheduled for laparoscopic bariatric surgery. Patients were positioned with a wedge cushion under the head and shoulders. A rapid sequence induction of anesthesia was carried out. A short-handled, articulated-blade McCoy laryngoscope was used for intubation; an intubation laryngeal mask airway (Fastrach) was on hand as a rescue device. Propofol and remifentanil were used for maintenance of anesthesia and morphine was administered at the end of surgery. Incentive spirometry was initiated in the postanesthetic recovery unit. Results: Eighty percent of the patients were women with a mean (SD) body mass index (kg/m2) of 46 (5). The first choice of direct laryngoscopic intubation was successful in 98.6% of cases. All patients were successfully intubated. Only 5 patients required intensive care. Postoperative complications (mainly respiratory problems, bleeding, and infections) were observed in 17%. No patient died. Conclusions: Perianesthetic management of morbidly obese patients who undergo laparoscopic surgery is safe. To minimize pulmonary complications, preoxygenation and rapid sequence induction should be performed correctly and incentive spirometry should be initiated in the immediate postoperative period. The McCoy laryngoscope ensures intubation in most cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pindado Martínez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro Cascante, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Adana, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariscal Flores, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Martín, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica supone un reto para el anestesiólogo, ya que el obeso mórbido es un paciente de alto riesgo y la laparoscopia puede dificultar el tratamiento ventilatorio y hemodinámico del paciente. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar el tratamiento perioperatorio anestésico de pacientes obesos mórbidos sometidos a cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de 300 pacientes consecutivos diagnosticados de obesidad mórbida, programados para cirugía bariátrica por laparoscopia. Los pacientes se posicionaron con almohadillado en cuña bajo cabeza y hombros. Se llevó a cabo una inducción anestésica de secuencia rápida. Para la intubación se utilizó un laringoscopio de mango corto y pala articulada (McCoy), utilizando de rescate la ILMA (intubation laryngeal mask airway) o Fastrach. El mantenimiento anestésico se realizó con propofol y remifentanilo, administrando cloruro mórfico al final de la cirugía. En la unidad de reanimación postanestésica se inició espirometría incentivada. Resultados: El 80% fueron mujeres, con un índice de masa corporal de 46 ± 5 Kg/m2. Se utilizó de primera elección laringoscopia directa para intubar en el 98,6% de los casos. Ningún paciente fue imposible de intubar. Sólo 5 pacientes precisaron cuidados intensivos. Hubo un 17% de complicaciones postoperatorias, destacando las respiratorias, hemorrágicas e infecciosas. No hubo ningún caso de mortalidad. Conclusión: El manejo perianestésico de pacientes con obesidad mórbida operados mediante abordaje laparoscópico es seguro. Para minimizar las complicaciones respiratorias, conviene: preoxigenar adecuadamente, realizar inducción de secuencia rápida y comenzar la espirometría incentivada en el postoperatorio inmediato. El laringoscopio de McCoy garantiza la intubación en la mayoría de los casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(4): 211-217, abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento anestésico perioperatorio de 300 pacientes con obesidad mórbida sometidos a cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica y breve revisión fisiopatológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12335^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11457^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11457^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
