<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109147</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chromosome 1p36 loss and COX-2 overexpression predict recurrence-free survival in completely removed meningioma grade I and II</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Long follow-up studies show that the 10-year regrowth rate for grade I (benign) and II (atypical) meningiomas rises up to 15---25% and 30---35%, respectively, despite aggressive surgery. We investigated completely removed meningiomas grade I and II (n = 135) to identify and compare prognostic markers for tumour recurrence. We determined the immunohistochemical expression of 30 biomarkers, cell death assay by in situ hybridisation (ApopDETEKTM) and loss of chromosome 1p36 by FISH. The univariate statistical analysis showed that WHO grade, high cellularity, nuclear atypia, loss of 1p36 (determined in 20 out of 107 valid cases), expression of COX-2 (9 positive cases and 126 negative cases), Cyclin A, Topoisomerase II  and MIB1/ki67 were associated with recurrence-free survival. The multivariate linkage analysis for the prognostic variables revealed that only 1p36 loss, expression of COX-2 and MIB1 were independent factors for predicting meningioma recurrence. The statistical analysis of COX-2 and 1p36 loss co-variation showed an antagonistic effect for both prognostic markers. Meningiomas with 1p36 loss showed significant increase of necrosis, nuclear atypia and increased expression of Cyclin E, PAKT, PDGF and p21. COX-2 overexpression was associated with increased VEGF, PDGF, HER2 and MDM2 expression. COX-2 inhibitors may be used as a putative chemopreventive treatment for meningioma recurrence in tumours with COX-2 over-expression(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zimman, Horacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos estudios con un largo periodo de seguimiento muestran que la tasa de recidiva para los meningiomas grado I (benignos) y II (atípicos) se sitúa entre el 15-25% y el 30-35% respectivamente, a pesar de una cirugía agresiva. Hemos investigado 135 meningiomas completamente resecados para identificar y comparar marcadores pronósticos de recurrencia tumoral. Hemos determinado la expresión inmunohistoquímica de 30 biomarcadores, la muerte celular por apoptosis mediante un ensayo de hibridación in situ (ApopDETEKTM) y las perdidas en el cromosoma 1p36 mediante FISH. El análisis estadístico univariante mostró que el grado tumoral de la OMS, la alta celularidad, la atipia nuclear, las pérdidas en el cromosoma 1p36 (determinadas en 20 de los 107 casos válidos) y la expresión de COX-2 (9 casos positivos y 126 negativos), Ciclina A, Topoisomerasa II  y MIB1/Ki67 se asociaron con el periodo libre de recurrencia. El análisis multivariante de estas variables pronósticas reveló que solamente las pérdidas en el cromosoma 1p36 y la expresión de COX-2 y MIB1 eran factores independientes para la predicción de recidiva tumoral. El análisis estadístico para la covariación de COX-2 y las perdidas en 1p36 mostraron un efecto antagonista para ambos marcadores. Los meningiomas con pérdidas en 1p36 mostraron un incremento significativo de la necrosis, la atipia nuclear y la expresión de Ciclina E, PAKT, PDGF y p21. La sobreexpresión de COX-2 se asocia a su vez con un aumento de la expresión de VEGF, PDGF, HER2 y MDM2. Los inhibidores selectivos de COX-2 podrían ser usados como un tratamiento quimiopreventivo putativo para evitar la recurrencia en aquellos meningiomas con sobreexpresión de COX-2(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;46(1): 14-25, ene.-mar.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109147</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pérdidas en el cromosoma 1p36 y la sobreexpresión de COX-2 predicen el intervalo libre de recurrencia en meningiomas completamente extirpados grados I y II</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2924^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2924^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
