<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053239</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The scientific study of the transcendental strengths from the positive psychology perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Within the framework of Positive Psychology there is a line of research focused on the virtues and strengths of human beings. Taking virtues and strengths as positive traits of personality, the Positive Psychology classifies them following a scheme similar to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM). With the aim of promoting research, this article reviews some of the studies that show the beneficial effects of a subset of strengths, the transcendental strengths &#150;i.e. spirituality, gratitude, hope, appreciation of beauty and excellence, and humor</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martí, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro del marco de la Psicología positiva existe una línea de investigación centrada en las virtudes y fortalezas del ser humano, entendidas como rasgos positivos de personalidad, que está elaborando una clasificación de ellas siguiendo un esquema similar al del Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM). En este artículo se exponen algunos de los estudios que muestran los efectos beneficiosos de un grupo concreto de estas fortalezas, las trascendentales (espiritualidad, gratitud, esperanza, apreciación de la belleza y excelencia, humor), con la intención de promover su investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;17(3): 245-258, 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El estudio científico de las fortalezas trascendentales desde la psicología positiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32693^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
