<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118488</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing students&#146; reflections on the death process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One&#146;s attitude toward and fear of death in the nursing field can determine the quality of care that a dying patient receives, which makes this topic an important one to consider and discuss. It is necessary for one to learn to perceive death as a natural process. Healthcare workers treat dying patients, interpreting the phenomenon of death as well as death itself through their own personal lens and breadth of understanding. Training in thanatology and palliative care is scarcely and irregularly included in regular academic curricula. The objective of this study is to analyze the contributions of 3rd-year nursing students on the subject of palliative care upon writing a reflective journal entry about an article that surrounds a nurse&#146;s view on the process of dying. Phenomenology was used as a methodological instrument which intended to inductively draw up a standardized explanation of the phenomenon of death through the students&#146; expressed thoughts on the matter. Relating to the attitudes that nurses that work with the terminally ill have towards death, the following facts stand out as impactful: lack of preparation, ineffective coping, and personal fears, values, and beliefs. Additionally, uneasiness associated with the use of life support and the care team&#146;s obstinate insistence on saving what cannot be saved is predominant. The results emphasize a very elevated level of the nurse&#146;s emotional involvement in caring for a dying patient. Specific preparation geared toward a better adaptation in working with terminal patients has been identified as a fundamental pillar for nurses in this line of work. Personal interest and emphasis on occupational excellence also stand out as influential factors. It is very important to analyze the problems regarding this &#147;environment of death&#148; and its impact on nursing students. Qualitative research in this field could be a useful tool in detecting worries and uncertainties surrounding this matter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Conty, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hanzeliková Pogrányivá, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conty Serrano, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Davila Sánchez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriga Martín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actitud y el miedo a la muerte en enfermería pueden condicionar la calidad de cuidados del paciente moribundo, por lo que es importante abordar este tema.  Es necesario aprender a percibir la muerte como algo natural. Los sanitarios tratan a los moribundos, interpretan el fenómeno de la muerte y la muerte misma bajo su óptica y entendimiento. La formación en tanatología y los cuidados paliativos se trata de forma escasa o al menos de forma irregular en los planes de estudio.  El objetivo del presente trabajo es analizar las aportaciones de los alumnos de tercero de enfermería en la asignatura cuidados paliativos a la hora de escribir una reflexión sobre un artículo que trata la visión de una enfermera del proceso de la muerte.  Se empleó la fenomenología como instrumento metodológico, con el que se pretendió elaborar inductivamente un marco explicativo del fenómeno estudiado a partir de las expresiones  de los estudiantes. En relación a la actitud hacia el trabajo con enfermos terminales y hacia la muerte se pueden resaltar los siguientes datos: escasa preparación, afrontamiento ineficaz, miedos, valores y creencias. Predomina la inquietud relacionada con el encarnizamiento terapéutico y con la actitud obstinada del equipo de salud por salvar lo insalvable.  Los resultados ponen de manifiesto un grado muy elevado de implicación emocional de la enfermera en el cuidado del paciente moribundo. Se considera como pilar fundamental una preparación específica para adaptarse mejor al trabajo con los pacientes terminales. Destaca el interés y la preocupación por la excelencia. Es muy importante el analizar los problemas en &#147;entorno de la muerte&#148; en los estudiantes de enfermería. La investigación cualitativa en este campo podría ser una de las herramientas útiles para detectar inquietudes y preocupaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(33): 133-156, ene. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones de los alumnos de Enfermería sobre el proceso de la muerte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
