<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113375</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fragile X Syndrome Treatment from early child attention in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Two male children with Fragile X Syndrome with full mutation received treatment at CADIT: the Children´s Center for Early Intervention and Development in Spain. The study´s main objective was to examine a comprehensive description of two FXS cases that serve to increase the knowledge about the syndrome characteristics and to recognize the importance of an individualized evaluation of children with this kind of syndrome, given the heterogeneity that exists within this syndrome; secondly, to evaluate the effectiveness of the work done in these centers, in particular in the language and cognitive areas, we discovered that although it is important to intervene in these areas, most of the needs are centered on the motor and autonomy áreas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Teruel, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles-Bello, María Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo examinó la respuesta al tratamiento de un programa de atención infantil temprana a través de un estudio de caso único en el que se realiza un seguimiento exhaustivo de los niveles iniciales y logros conseguidos por dos niños varones con SFX con mutación completa. El objetivo que se pretende es doble. Por una parte, realizar una descripción exhaustiva del SFX que sirva para aumentar el conocimiento sobre las características de este síndrome y, por otra, reconocer la importancia de una evaluación individualizada, dada la hetereogeneidad que existe dentro de este síndrome. Finalmente los resultados indican que aunque es evidente la necesidad de intervención en áreas tradicionales como la del lenguaje y cognitiva, el trabajo es igualmente relevante a nivel motor y de autonomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;24(1): 19-26, mar. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113375</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del Síndrome del cromosoma X frágil desde la atención infantil temprana en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
