<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154003</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vocal nodules in school age children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Vocal nodules are the most common organic and functional lesions among the paediatrics population, being the main cause of dysphonia during childhood. In Portugal, a few studies that describe the vocal parameters in school age children with this pathology were found. The objective of this paper is to analyse the perceptual and acoustic vocal parameters of school age children with vocal nodules and to compare them with a group of children without vocal nodules. Methodology. The perceptual and acoustic parameters of 5 children, of both genders, aged from 7 years and 2 months to 12 years and 10 months, where clinical diagnosis of vocal nodules were analysed. The following assessment instruments were used: software Praat, GRBASI scale, maximum phonation time and s/z coefficient. The obtained data was compared to children without vocal nodules. The Mann&#150;Whitney U test, with p &lt; .05 significance level, in SPSS Statistics, version 22.0 was used for statistical analysis. The results are presented as mean and standard deviations. Results. Statistically significant differences were registered between the group of vocal nodules vs. the group without vocal nodules, on the following parameters: fundamental frequency, shimmer, HNR, maximum phonation time for /a/ e /z/, s/z coefficient and GRBASI. On jitter and maximum phonation time for /s/ there were no statistically significant differences. Discussion and conclusions. This study underlines the importance of assessing the perceptual and acoustic parameters in children with vocal nodules (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coelho, Janete</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diogo Paiva, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los nódulos vocales son las lesiones orgánicas funcionales más comunes en la población pediátrica, la principal causa de disfonía en la infancia. En Portugal se encontraron pocos estudios que describan los parámetros vocales de los niños en edad escolar con esta patología. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar los parámetros acústico-perceptivos vocales de niños en edad escolar con nódulos vocales y compararlos con un grupo de niños sin nódulos vocales. Metodología. Se analizaron los parámetros acústico-perceptivos de 5 niños de ambos sexos, con edades entre 7 años y 2 meses y 12 años y 10 meses, con diagnóstico clínico de nódulos vocales. Se utilizaron los instrumentos de evaluación: software Praat, rango GRBASI, el tiempo máximo de fonación y el coeficiente s/z. Los datos obtenidos se compararon con los de los niños sin nódulos vocales. El análisis estadístico utilizando la prueba U de Mann&#150;Whitney, con nivel de significación de p &lt; .05, el SPSS Statistics, versión 22.0. Los resultados se presentan como medias y desviaciones estándar. Resultados. Hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre el grupo de nódulos vocales frente al grupo sin nódulos vocales en los parámetros: frecuencia fundamental, shimmer, HNR, tiempo máximo de fonación de /a/ y /z/, el coeficiente s/z y GRBASI. En jitter y tiempo máximo de fonación de /s/, no hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Discusión y conclusiones. Este trabajo subraya la importancia de la evaluación de los parámetros acústico-perceptivos en los niños con nódulos vocales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);36(3): 103-108, jul.-sept. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los nódulos vocales en niños en edad escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15228^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53079^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d168^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53079^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d165^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
