<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113887</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The diabetic patient develops sometimes associated pathologies, such as diabetic retinopathy, neuropathy, nephropathy, among others. In the field of urology scientific evidence about a possible link between diabetes mellitus and the formation of phimosis. Acquired Phimosis or adult, has been studied in diabetics from the perspective of local infection in the glans and / or foreskin, getting to provoke any degree of phimosis, even the peak known as amyotrophic foreskin. Among the most common infections are those caused by Candida albicans and Lichen, leading to develop balanitis or balanoposthitis. MATERIAL AND METHOD / OBJECTIVE: Cross-sectional study in the urology specialty center Migrants belonging to Hospital Ramón y Cajal on a sample of 95 patients with phimosis. The sample is collected over a period of time ranging from May to October 2011.OBJETIVE: To estimate the prevalence of acquired phimosis in diabetic patients, which does not develop infections that cause the development of this pathology at balanopreputial. DISCUSSION: There is evidence of phimosis prevalence in diabetics, but is controversial, and few publications. RESULTS: Of the 95 patients diagnosed with some form of phimosis, 11 had diabetes and no local infection acquired phimosis; calculated period prevalence of 11.57%.CONCLUSION: In the absence of local infection at the level of the penis, the diabetic patient can develop phimosis. Left open a path of research on causes that can affect the formation of acquired phimosis in diabetic patients, other than local infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Muñoz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: El paciente diabético desarrolla en ocasiones patologías asociadas, tales como retinopatía diabética, neuropatía, nefropatía, entre otras. En el campo de la urología existe evidencia científica acerca de una posible relación entre la diabetes mellitus y la formación de fimosis. La fimosis adquirida o del adulto se ha estudiado en los diabéticos desde la perspectiva de la infección local en el glande y/o prepucio, llegando a originar cualquier grado de fimosis, incluso el nivel máximo conocido como esclerosis de prepucio. Entre las infecciones más comunes están las ocasionadas por Candida albicans y liquen, llegando a desarrollar balanitis o balanopostitis. MATERIAL Y MÉTODO/OBJETIVO: Estudio transversal realizado en la consulta de urología del centro de especialidades. Emigrantes perteneciente al Hospital Ramón y Cajal sobre una muestra de 95 pacientes que presentan fimosis. La muestra se recoge durante un período de tiempo comprendido de mayo a octubre de 2011.OBJETIVO: Estimar la prevalencia de fimosis adquirida en pacientes diabéticos, que además no presenten infecciones que ocasionen el desarrollo de dicha patología a nivel balanoprepucial. DISCUSIÓN: Existe evidencia sobre prevalencia de fimosis en diabéticos, pero es controvertida, además las publicaciones escasas. RESULTADOS: De los 95 pacientes diagnosticados de algún tipo de fimosis, 11 presentaban diabetes y fimosis adquirida sin infección local; calculándose una prevalencia de periodo del 11,57%.CONCLUSIÓN: En ausencia de infección local, a nivel del pene, el paciente diabético puede desarrollar fimosis. Queda abierto un camino de investigación sobre causas que pueden afectar a la formación de fimosis adquirida en el paciente diabético, distinta a la infección local (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(123): 4-7, sept.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio piloto de prevalencia de la fimosis adquirida en pacientes diabéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10882^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
