<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60281</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of the loss in the genesis of depressive disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The role of loss has been carefully examined in the investigation of depression since it constitutes a central aspect of most of the life events that lead to depression. Methods. In the present study, a review was made of the different studies on the role of loss, focusing on its different aspects and different types, the association between loss and some mental diseases, loss and prognosis, relationship between hopelessness and loss, variations of the events of loss based on different factors, also considering loss in the childhood. Results. Loss constitutes a central role in the appearance of many depressive disorders. It can act as a provoking agent, a vulnerability factor or an agent that can modify the form, severity and course of a depressive disorder. Different factors such as the genetic one, gender or moment of life when the loss takes place, can modulate the influence of loss events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Livianos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En la investigación de la depresión, el papel de la pérdida ha sido examinado en detalle, puesto que constituye un aspecto central de la mayoría de los acontecimientos vitales que llevan a la depresión. Material y método. En el presente trabajo se realizó una revisión acerca de los estudios previos sobre la importancia de la pérdida centrándonos en diversos aspectos como sus diferentes tipos, la asociación con algunas enfermedades mentales, pérdida y pronóstico, relación entre desesperanza y pérdida, y variaciones de los acontecimientos de pérdida en función de diversos factores, considerando también la pérdida en la infancia. Resultados. La pérdida ejerce un papel clave en la aparición de muchos trastornos depresivos. Puede actuar como agente provocador, factor de vulnerabilidad o agente modificador de la forma, gravedad y curso de un cuadro depresivo. Diversos factores como el factor genético, el sexo o el momento de la vida en el que tiene lugar la pérdida pueden modular la influencia de los acontecimientos de pérdida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(3): 128-136, mayo-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60281</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la pérdida en la génesis de los trastornos depresivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
