<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97520</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using the Mobile Phone, Youth and Family: An Overview of the Brazilian Reality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract. The main objective of this article is to analyze the use of mobile phones in Brazil, under a psychosocial perspective, focusing on the role of young people and the family in disseminating such technology in the country. It presents and discusses previous investigation son the use of mobile phones by young people, describing its aims and consumption motivations. Young people are the Brazil&#146;s main consumer group of mobile phone in the country. The article provides an outlook of Brazilian youth and its participation in the country&#146;s Information Society. The repercussions of the use of such technology in family relationships are analyzed, including families with young people. The objective is to understand how parent and teenagers handle mobile phone&#146;s technology in their relationships in this phase of the life cycle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wagner, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verza, Fabiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Este artículo se propone analizar el panorama del teléfono móvil en Brasil, desde una perspectiva psicosocial, considerando hacia el rol de los jóvenes y de la familia en el proceso de difusión de dicha tecnología en el país. Se presentan y discuten investigaciones sobre la juventud y el uso del teléfono móvil, describiendo los objetivos y motivaciones para su consumo, considerando que éste es el mayor sector consumidor de móviles en el país. Se describe el panorama de la juventud brasileña en el contexto de la Sociedad de la Información en Brasil. Se analiza la repercusión del uso de esta tecnología en las relaciones familiares, en las familias con hijos jóvenes, con el fin de comprender cómo padres e hijos manejan en sus relaciones el teléfono móvil en esta fase del ciclo vital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;19(1): 57-71, mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del Teléfono Móvil, Juventud y Familia: Un Panorama de la Realidad Brasileña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35249</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
