<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114759</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To investigate bibliometric indicators of research output, or productivity, and impact of selected Spanish emergency physicians who engage in research and to describe the behaviour of these indicators for this group of researchers as a whole. Methods: Pilot study exploring indicators for a group of 24 emergency physicians who engage in research. The physicians were elected from among members of the editorial board and peer reviewers of the journal Emergencias. All had been publishing papers for at least 10 years and had authored at least 20 papers, including 5 in the last 3 years. The following information was collected for each author: publications in journals included in Science Citation Index Expanded; duration of career in medical research; number of publications as the output indicator; and number of cites, accumulated impact factor, and h-index as the impact indicators. These indicators were calculated for each year of the physicians&#146; research careers. The results, including change in the indicators over time, were analyzed for individuals and for the group as a whole by means of both linear and polynomial regression models. Results: The physicians had been engaged in research for a mean (SD) of 19 (7) years (range, 10-35 years). The associations between years of experience and the indicators of output and impact were not significant. Polynomial regression models fit the changes in these indicators over time better than linear models. Analyzed individually the R2values were always over 0.90 for all indicators in polynomial modelling; for the group as a whole, the h-index showed the best fit (R2 = 0.54). The h-index behaved differently for researchers with up to 20 years of experience (better fit,R2 = 0.71 as well as (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sánchez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado González, Nayade del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burnano, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo-Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar el comportamiento de distintos indicadores de producción y repercusión científicas en médicos investigadores españoles que trabajan en el ámbito de la medicina de urgencias y emergencias y definir un patrón global para el conjunto de ellos. Método: Estudio piloto exploratorio en 24 urgenciólogos. Criterios de inclusión: estar en el comité editorial o el panel de expertos de EMERGENCIAS, experiencia investigadora de al menos 10 años y tener 20 trabajos indexados en Science Citation Index Expanded, al menos 5 de ellos en los últimos 3 años. Para cada autor, se obtuvieron los años de experiencia, el número de trabajos publicados (indicador de producción) y el número de citas y el factor de impacto acumulado y el índice h (indicadores de repercusión).Estos indicadores se calcularon para cada año de experiencia de su trayectoria investigadora. Se contrastó esta experiencia y el valor alcanzado en estos indicadores y la evolución temporal de dichos indicadores, tanto individualmente como para todo el colectivo, mediante modelos de regresión lineal y polinomial. Resultados: La experiencia media investigadora fue de 19 ± 7 años (rango: 10-35). La relación entre la puntuación alcanzada por los investigadores en los indicadores evaluados y los años de experiencia no fue significativa. En cambio, la evolución temporal de estos indicadores se ajustó mejor a un modelo cuadrático que a uno lineal: individualmente, los valores de R2 fueron siempre superiores a 0,90 en todos los indicadores; globalmente, el mejor ajuste se produjo con el índice h (R2 = 0,54). En este último, se distinguía un comportamiento diferenciado para los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(4): 245-254, ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Producción y repercusión científica de un grupo de urgenciólogos españoles seleccionados por su trayectoria investigadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12529^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
