<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149831</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between renal function and renal volume in autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease: cross-sectional study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine in patients with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease the relationship between total renal volume (the sum of both kidneys, TRV) as measured by magnetic resonance and renal function; and its behaviour according to sex and the presence of arterial hypertension, hypercholesterolaemia and hyperglycemia. Method. Cross-sectional study including patients with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease who underwent periodic reviews at Nephrology external consultations at Hospital de las Nieves de Granada, and who underwent an magnetic resonance to estimate renal volume between January 2008 and March 2011. Results. We evaluated 67 patients (59.7% women, average age of 48±14.4 years) and found a significant positive association between TRV and serum creatinine or urea, which was reversed compared with estimated glomerular filtration by MDRD-4 and Cockcroft-Gault. Women showed an average serum creatinine level and a significantly lower TRV level compared with males. Subgroups affected by arterial hypertension and hyperuricemia presented average values for serum creatinine and urea, higher for TRV and lower for estimated glomerular filtration. The hypercholesterolaemia subgroup showed higher average values for urea and lower for estimated glomerular filtration, without detecting significant differences compared with TRV. Conclusion. The volume of polycystic kidneys measured by magnetic resonance is associated with renal function, and can be useful as a complementary study to monitor disease progression. The presence of arterial hypertension, hyperuricemia or hypercholesterolaemia is associated with a poorer renal function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteban de la Rosa, RJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Castillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrero, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Sánchez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila-Barranco, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Valverde, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Soto, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar en pacientes con poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante la relación entre el volumen renal total (suma de ambos riñones, VRT) medido con resonancia magnética y la función renal; y su comportamiento según el sexo y la presencia de hipertensión arterial, hipercolesterolemia e hiperuricemia. Método. Estudio transversal en el que se incluyen pacientes con poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante que realizan revisiones periódicas en las consultas externas de Nefrología del Hospital Virgen de las Nieves de Granada, a quienes entre enero de 2008 y marzo de 2011 se les realizó una resonancia magnética para estimar el volumen renal. Resultados. Se evaluaron 67 pacientes (59,7% mujeres, edad media 48±14,4 años). Encontramos asociación positiva significativa entre VRT y creatinina sérica o urea, que resultó inversa frente al filtrado glomerular estimado por MDRD-4 y Cockcroft-Gault. Las mujeres mostraron un nivel medio de creatinina sérica y VRT inferior respecto al varón de forma significativa. Los subgrupos afectos de hipertensión arterial e hiperuricemia mostraron valores medios de creatinina sérica, urea y VRT más altos y filtrados glomerulares estimados inferiores. El subgrupo con hipercolesterolemia mostró valores medios de urea más altos y filtrados glomerulares estimados inferiores sin detectarse diferencias significativas respecto al VRT. Conclusión. El volumen de los riñones poliquísticos medido por resonancia magnética se asocia con la función renal, y puede ser útil como estudio complementario para monitorizar la progresión de la enfermedad. La presencia de hipertensión arterial, hiperuricemia o hipercolesterolemia están asociados a una peor función renal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(2): 62-67, mar. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149831</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre función y volumen renal en la poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante: estudio transversal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37291^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37291^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
