<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038655</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Melanoma of the oral mucosa. Clinical cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of primary melanomas of the oral mucosa isuncommon. The aggressiveness of this entity and the absenceof any standardized treatment protocol make the prognostic unfortunate.The difficulty to obtain free surgical margins, the elevatedtendency to invade in depth and the early haematogenousmetastasis have been referred as features which may explain itsbad prognosis, even in comparison with cutaneous melanoma.However, no large clinical series exist and actually, clinical casesare the main source of information. Due to the absence ofany treatment modality which may substantially increase longtermsurvival, we suggest the use of resective surgery with widemargins and early diagnosis by means of biopsy for suspiciousmelanotic-pigmented lesions. In this work we present 2 newcases of primary melanoma of the oral mucosa, with a follow-upperiod of 72 and 12 months respectively, and we make a reviewof the literature in relation with this rare entity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naval Gías, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hyun Nam-Cha, Syong</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Guerra, Mario F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos, Pedro L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Campo, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre Pérez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de melanomas primarios de la mucosa oral esinfrecuente. La agresividad de esta entidad y la ausencia deprotocolos de tratamiento estandarizado, hacen que el pronósticosea infausto. Se han relacionado la dificultad de la resecciónquirúrgica con márgenes libres, la tendencia elevada a la invasiónen profundidad y las metástasis hematógenas tempranas,como consideraciones que justifican un peor pronóstico enrelación al melanoma cutáneo. Sin embargo, no existen seriesclínicas grandes, y las series de casos clínicos constituyen lafuente principal de información en el momento actual. Ante laausencia de modalidades de tratamiento que aumenten substancialmentela supervivencia a largo plazo, sugerimos el empleode cirugía de resección con márgenes amplios y el diagnósticoprecoz mediante la biopsia de lesiones pigmentadas melánicassospechosas. En el presente trabajo presentamos 2 nuevos casosde melanoma primario de mucosa oral, con un seguimiento de72 y 12 meses respectivamente, y realizamos una revisión dela literatura en relación con esta rara neoplasia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(3): 264-271, mayo-jul. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Melanoma de la mucosa oral. Casos clínicos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
