<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79543</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of phenomena after the death by the sanitary personnel in the hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to histories that count the sanitary personnel in the Virgen del Rocío Hospital (Seville), sometimes the welfare activity is interrupted by phenomenas, mainly in the context of the death of a patient, whom the physical laws do not give an explanation. These histories conform not only an own type of folklore, but that gets to condition the welfare work of some services, with a great emotional load of negative effects for the own personnel, being able to repel in the patient attention al. Groups of 30 members of different hospitable areas chose themselves, with and without welfare activity, by means of the system of open interview investigated themselves in their experiences in this field, from which we created a data bank, but without leaving of side the human answer. It is to say: we have considered qualitative and quantitative aspects in this study. With this information we have investigated in the real experiences of the sanitary personnel with these phenomena to value that personal he is more susceptible to suffer them and that measured of performance they are possible to be taken (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez López, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según las historias que cuentan el personal sanitario en el hospital Virgen del Rocío (Sevilla), a veces la actividad asistencial es interrumpida por fenómenos, sobre todo en el contexto de la muerte de un paciente, a los que las leyes físicas no dan una explicación. Estas historias conforman no sólo un tipo de folclore propio, sino que llega a condicionar la labor asistencial de algunos servicios, con una gran carga emocional de efectos negativos para el propio personal, pudiendo repercutir en la atención al paciente. Se escogieron 30 profesionales de diferentes áreas hospitalarias, con y sin actividad asistencial, mediante el sistema de entrevista abierta se indagó en sus experiencias en este campo, a partir de las cuales creamos un banco de datos, pero sin dejar de lado la respuesta humana. Es decir: hemos tenido en cuenta aspectos cualitativos y cuantitativos en este estudio. Con esta información hemos indagado en las experiencias reales del personal sanitario con estos fenómenos para valorar qué personal es más susceptible de padecerlos y qué medidas de actuación se pueden tomar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;17(2): 116-118, abr.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de fenómenos tras la muerte por el personal sanitario en el hospital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
