<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129588</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep quality in a sample of patients with nonspecific chronic low back pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of the present study was to describe sleep quality in patients with nonspecific chronic low back pain (CLBP) and its association with perceived pain, age, and/or gender. Material and methods: A total of 93 CLBP patients completed the Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) and a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for pain. Descriptive-correlational analyses and factor structure for the PSQI were calculated for these data. Results: Despite showing moderate-to-high mean scores on the VAS (mean = 6.31, SD = 2.10), pain perception, gender, and participants' age were not significantly related to global sleep quality. Overall sleep quality was described as «good» or «quite good» by 59.1% of the sample but as «quite bad» or «bad» by the remaining 40.9%. Factor analysis of the PSQI revealed six main factors that explained 67.56% of the variance (the first three accounted for 44.45% of the total variance). Conclusions: Globally, the quality of sleep in CLBP patients is satisfactory and is not related to perceived pain, age, or gender. However, almost a third of the sample (26.9%) reported impaired sleep maintenance (mainly women). Factor analysis revealed the suitability of the PSQI to study sleep quality in CLBP patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa-Requena, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biedermann-Villagra, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lusilla-Palacios, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barnola-Serra, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano-Tejedor, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El presente trabajo tiene por objetivo describir la calidad del sueño en pacientes con dolor lumbar crónico inespecífico (DLCI), así como la asociación de este con la percepción de dolor, la edad y/o el género. Material y métodos. Para ello, 93 pacientes con DLCI contestaron el Índice de Calidad del Sueño de Pittsburg (ICSP) y una escala visual análoga (EVA) de dolor. A partir de estos datos, se llevó a cabo un análisis descriptivo-correlacional y un análisis factorial exploratorio. Resultados. Pese a presentar puntuaciones medias moderadas-altas (M = 6,31, SD = 2,10) en la EVA, la percepción de dolor no guardaba relación estadísticamente significativa con la calidad global del sueño de la muestra de estudio. Tampoco lo hizo la edad o el género de los participantes. Aunque un 59,1% describió su calidad global del sueño como «buena» o «bastante buena», el 40,9% restante lo hizo como «bastante mala» o «mala». El análisis factorial reveló la existencia de 6 factores principales para el ICSP, que lograban explicar el 67,56% de la varianza (explicando los 3 primeros un 44,45% del total). Conclusiones. Globalmente, la calidad del sueño de pacientes con DLCI es satisfactoria y no guarda relación ni con el dolor percibido, ni con la edad o el género del participante. No obstante, casi un tercio de la muestra (26,9%) presentaba alteraciones de mantenimiento del sueño (principalmente, mujeres). El análisis factorial reveló la utilidad del ICSP como instrumento válido y aceptable para el estudio del sueño en pacientes con DLCI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(4): 219-225, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad del sueño en pacientes con lumbalgia crónica inespecífica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
