<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72775</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structured review of physical activity measurement with questionnaires and scales in older adults and the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To characterize the distinct questionnaires and scales used to measure physical activity, their conceptual frame works, psychometric properties and application norms. Method: The review included original articles that used questionnaires or scales to assess physical activity in older adults or the elderly. The CINAHL and MEDLINE data bases were consulted for they ears 1993 to 2007. The studies selected had to provide information on the use, development and psychometric properties of the instruments. Instruments used in the population aged more than 45 years old were included. Articles that assessed physical activity by direct estimation, complex methods, orphysical performance were excluded. Results: The search produced 166 references and 36 instruments were identified. Most of the studies quantified physical activity, and aminority assessed self-efficacy in physical activity performance and the stage of change. Half of the instruments were self-administered. The most frequently studied reliability was test-retest. Criterion validity was studied in14 instruments, and 11 of the se used atleast two alternative methods of measurement. Construct validity was assessedin 26 instruments. Responsive ness was evaluated in only three instruments(YPAS, CHAMP Sand Exercise Stage of Change)in addition to reliability and validity.          Conclusions: The Exercise Stage of Change questionnaire showed responsiveness and sufficient reliability to allow individual use. The 7 Day PAR questionnaire and the Modified Baecke Questionnaire (Spanish version), which evaluate physical activity, can be used on an individual basis, although the irresponsiveness has not be en studied. In general, the instruments analyzed do not assess mild intensity activities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabrero-García, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luz Muñoz-Mendoza, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Pina, J. Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guirao-Goris, Josep Adolf</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los diferentes cuestionarios y escalas que miden la actividad física, atendiendo a susdiferentes aspectos conceptuales, propiedades psicométricas y normas de aplicación.Método: La revisión incluyó artículos originales que utilizaban algún cuestionario para valorar la actividadfísica en los adultos mayores y ancianos. Se consultaron las bases de datos CINAHL y MEDLINE de 1993 a 2007. Los estudios seleccionados debían aportar información sobre uso, desarollo o propiedadespsicométricas de la medida. Se seleccionaron instrumentos utilizados en población mayor de 45 años. Seexcluyeron los que evaluaban actividad física mediante estimación directa, métodos complejos o medidas de desempeño físico.Resultados: La búsqueda produjo 166 referencias y se identificaron 36 instrumentos. La mayoríacuantificaba la actividad física, y minoritariamente la autoeficacia y el estado de cambio de conducta.Los instrumentos son autoadministrados en la mitad de los casos. La fiabilidad más evaluada fue test-retest. En 14 instrumentos se estudió la validez de criterio, 11 con al menos dos métodos alternativos demedición. La validez de constructo fue evaluada en 26 instrumentos. Sólo tres instrumentos muestran sensibilidad al cambio(YPAS, CHAMPS y Exercise Stage of Change) además de fiabilidad y validez.Conclusiones: El cuestionario Exercise Stage of Change, que mide la disposición al cambio, muestra sensibilidad al cambio y un índice de fiabilidad que permite su uso individual. Los cuestionarios 7 Day PAR y la versión española del Modified Baecke Questionnaire, que estiman la actividad física, pueden usarse con fines individuales aunque no se estudió la sensibilidad al cambio en ninguno. En general, los instrumentos analizados no valoran las actividades de intensidad ligera(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(4): e51-e67334, jul.-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión estructurada de los cuestionarios y escalas que miden la actividad física en los adultos mayores y ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
