<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138336</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The costs of a multiple sclerosis relapse in Catalonia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The objective of this study is to calculate direct, indirect and intangible costs of a relapse in multiple sclerosis (MS) in our cohort of patients. Methods: Data from patient questionnaires, hospital charts, Catalan Public Healthcare System tariffs and Catalan Statistics Institute. We employed a cost-of-illness method. The human capital approach was used to estimate indirect costs, and quality-of-life measurements were used to estimate intangible costs. Results: 148 MS patients monitored in our MS-Unit consecutively answered the questionnaire elaborated. We calculated 1,498.5-1,537.9 euros for direct costs (hospital admission and outpatient, respectively) and 1,530.6 euros for indirect costs. We estimated an average total cost of 3,048.8 euros per patient/relapse. We also calculated intangible costs, 539 euros per patient and relapse, which should be added to the previous figure. Conclusions: The total cost of a MS relapse in our population (3,048.8 euros) is lower than the cost reported in the literature. The economic impact of MS is due to its disabling progression rather than to relapses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Yelamos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Yelamos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbizu, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es calcular los costes directos, indirectos e intangibles de un brote de esclerosis múltiple (EM) en nuestra cohorte de pacientes. Métodos. Partimos de datos obtenidos de cuestionarios del paciente, historias clínicas, tarifas del Servicio Catalán de Salud e Instituto de Estadística de Cataluña. Realizamos un estudio del coste de la enfermedad con el método del capital humano para estimar los costes indirectos y medidas de calidad de vida para estimar los gastos intangibles. Resultados. Ciento cuarenta y ocho pacientes afectos de EM, controlados en nuestra unidad, que contestaron, consecutivamente, al cuestionario elaborado. Los costes directos resultan 1.498,5-1.537,9 euros (hospitalizado y ambulatorio, respectivamente) y los indirectos 1.530,6 euros. El coste medio total estimado es de 3.048,8 euros por paciente y brote. Los gastos intangibles a añadir al coste total resultan 539 euros por paciente y brote. Conclusiones. El coste total de un brote de EM estimado en nuestra población (3.048,8 euros) es menor que lo publicado anteriormente. El gran impacto económico de la EM vendrá dado fundamentalmente por la progresión de la discapacidad más que por los brotes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(7): 341-347, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuánto cuesta un brote de sclerosis multiple en Calauña?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
