<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14577</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of carbon dioxide concentration on the neurite outgrowth of mouse embryonic cortical neurons in vitro</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The carbon dioxide (CO2) concentration of the incubation medium in nerve cell culturing has always been a matter of debate and is usually adjusted in a somewhat empirical manner. In the many laboratory protocols and manuals published to date, the data concerning this aspect differ. The goal of this study was thus to follow up the neurite outgrowth of cortical neurons in dissociated primary cultures obtained from seventeen-day-old embryonic mouse brains incubated in 90% air and 10% CO2, and in 95% air and 5% CO2 respectively. We recorded the density and confluence of the neuronal distribution in vitro on the second, third and fifth day after establishing the cultures. Morphological evaluation to demonstrate viable cells was carried out by applying immunocytochemistry for microtubule-associated protein-2 due to its ubiquity in neurons. The results showed that neuronal survival, the rate of neurite outgrowth and the establishment of intercellular networks and synaptic contacts were more pronounced in cortical cultures raised in 10% CO2-containing incubation medium than in 5% CO2-containing incubation medium. From these results, it can be inferred that CO2 at a higher concentration plays a significant role in influencing the metabolic activities of embryonic cortical neurons in vitro, thus probably determining their synaptogenesis and viability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La concentración de dióxido de carbono (CO2) del medio de incubación en el cultivos de células nerviosas siempre ha sido debatible y normalmente es ajustada de una manera un tanto empírica. En los muchos protocolos y manuales de laboratorio que han sido publicados hasta la fecha, los datos relativos a este aspecto difieren. Por tanto, nuestro objetivo en el presente trabajo ha sido de llevar a cabo un seguimiento del crecimiento de neuritas de neuronas corticales in cultivos primarios disociados obtenidas de los cerebros de ratones embrionarios de 17 días de edad incubadas en 90 por ciento aire y 10 por ciento CO2 y en 95 por ciento aire y 5 por ciento CO2 respectivamente. Registramos la densidad y confluencia de la distribución neuronal in vitro en el segundo, tercer y quinto día después de establecer los cultivos. La evaluación morfológica encaminada a demostrar células viables fue llevada a cabo aplicando métodos inmunocitoquímicos para la proteína-2 asociada a los microtúbulos debido a su ubicuidad en las neuronas. Los resultados revelaron que la supervivencia neuronal, la velocidad de crecimiento de las neuritas así como el establecimiento de redes intercelulares y contactos sinápticos eran más pronunciados en los cultivos corticales derivados del medio que contenía una concentración de CO2 del 10 por ciento que con el que contenía 5 por ciento CO2. De estos resultados, se puede deducir que, a concentraciones mayores, el CO2 juega un papel significativo en influir en las actividades metabólicas de las neuronas corticales embrionarias in vitro, así probablemente determinando su sinaptogénesis y viabilidad. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;6(1): 9-11, mayo 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia de la concentración de dióxido de carbono en el crecimiento in vitro de neuritas de las neuronas corticales embrionarias del ratón</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Dandov, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14577</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2284</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2512^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29934^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
