<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165030</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomechanical analysis of cervical spine movement on removal of motorcycle helmets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To measure cervical spine movement during removal of a motorcycle helmet by health care professionals. Methods. Observational study using biomechanical inertial sensors to detect movement in the spinal column during removal of helmets. Results. Thirty-four emergency medicine specialists and nurses participated. The mean (SD) rotation was 1.14° (0.82°) to the left and 3.30° (1.69°) to the right (P&lt;.001). Mean flexion was 9.82° (7.46°) and mean extension was 6.23° (6.86°) (P&lt;.001). Mean lateral displacement was 5.73° (2.97°) to the left and 5.62° (8.22°) to the right (P=.678). The removal maneuvers took a mean of 70 seconds (4 seconds). Conclusion. Helmet removal was completed in an average of 70 seconds with flexion and rotation mainly toward the side where the professional supporting the head was positioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juguera Rodríguez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo Martín, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Ibáñez, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Ríos, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hontoria Hernández, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Martínez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Hernández, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el movimiento cervical durante la extracción de un casco realizada por profesionales sanitarios. Métodos. Estudio observacional mediante análisis biomecánico con sensores inerciales de los movimientos producidos en la columna durante la extracción de un casco. Resultados. La muestra final la componen 34 profesionales de servicios de urgencias y emergencias. La rotación fue de 1,14 (DE 0,82)° hacia el lado izquierdo y de 3,30 (1,69)° hacia el lado derecho (p &lt; 0,001). La flexoextensión fue de 9,82 (7,46)° para la flexión y de 6,23 (6,86)° para la extensión (p &lt; 0,001). La lateralización fue de 5,73 (2,97)° para el lado izquierdo y de 5,62 (8,22)° para el lado derecho (p = 0,678). El tiempo medio de realización de la extracción fue 70 (4) seg. Conclusión. La extracción del casco se realizó en 70 segundos con flexión y rotación hacia el lado donde se encuentra colocado el profesional que sujeta la cabeza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(4): 249-252, ago. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis biomecánico del movimiento cervical en la extracción del casco en motoristas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32050^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
