<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142577</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Observational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although there are many texts on the quality of epidemiological studies, little effort has been made to evaluate the publication of epidemiological studies and their results (the articles). Concern to improve the reporting of epidemiological studies prompted a working group to launch the STROBE (Strengthening the Reporting of observational studies in Epidemiology Statement). The STROBE checklist contains 22 items organized according to the Title and Abstract, Introduction, Methods, Results, and Discussion structure that can be used for the main epidemiological designs (cohort studies, case-control studies, and cross-sectional studies). It is a checklist to improve the reporting quality of epidemiological studies (generally original articles) and, therefore, to evaluate the quality of this type of publication and facilitate critical reading (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Esteve</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay numerosos textos sobre la calidad de los estudios epidemiológicos pero ha sido mucho menor el esfuerzo dedicado a valorar la calidad de la manera de publicar los estudios y resultados (los artículos) epidemiológicos. La preocupación por mejorar la comunicación de los estudios epidemiológicos llevó a un grupo de trabajo a configurar la Declaración STROBE (STrengthening the Reporting of OBservational studies in Epidemiology). La lista de comprobación STROBE contiene, para los 3 diseños epidemiológicos principales (estudios de cohortes, estudios de casos y controles, y estudios transversales), 22 puntos organizados según la estructura Título y Resumen, Introducción, Método, Resultados y Discusión. Se trata de una lista de comprobación para aumentar la calidad de la publicación de los informes de los estudios epidemiológicos (generalmente artículos originales) y, por ende, valorar la calidad o hacer una lectura crítica de este tipo de publicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(supl.1): 43-48, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudios epidemiológicos (STROBE)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12078^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54358^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28595</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
