<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046567</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bilateral lumbar perforator flap in reconstruction of a wide toracolumbar defect</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thoracolumbar defects have been treated by a variety of surgical methods. Primary closure, skin grafting, reverse latissimus dorsi musculocutaneous flap, transverse lumbosacral back flap, local randomly designed rotation, or transposition flaps may be indicated in occasional cases, but there is limited indication for their use in some cases with a wide lesion or when the surrounding tissues have been compromised by previous surgery or irradiation. Perforator flaps are specially indicated for ambulatory patients, in which large amounts of well-vascularized skin and subcutaneous tissue are transfered  easily based on one perforator vessel without sacrificing main vessels or muscles. The authors present a patient with a 17 cm wide defect in the midback region and exposed bone after excision of a squamous cell carcinoma, treated by two perforator flaps based on paralumbar arteries transposed ;;into the defect, in addition to a rotation latissimus dorsi musculocutaneous flap (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan Huelves, A de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sorando, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Rosás, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Duque, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la reconstrucción de los defectos toracolumbares se han empleado numerosas técnicas quirúrgicas. Ocasionalmente se puede utilizar el cierre directo, injertos de piel, colgajos de dorsal ancho volteado y lumbosacro transverso, colgajos de transposición o de rotación tipo random, pero están limitados cuando los tejidos circundantes están radiados o presentan cicatrices por cirugías previas. Igualmente, la extensión del defecto puede hacerlos inviables. Los colgajos de perforantes están especialmente indicados en pacientes con deambulación conservada, haciendo posible el aporte de una gran superficie de piel y tejido subcutáneo bien vascularizado, basado en los vasos perforantes y evitando así el sacrificio de vasos principales o músculos. Presentamos el caso de una paciente con un defecto en la espalda de 17 cm. De diámetro secundario ala resección de un tumor espinocelular con exposición de cuerpos vertebrales, tratado mediante la transposición de dos colgajos basados en las arterias perforantes lumbares asociados a un colgajo de rotación de dorsal ancho miocutáneo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;32(2): 141-144, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajo bilateral de perforantes lumbares para la reconstrucción de un severo defecto tóracolumbar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33365^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8336^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33267^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
