<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139101</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profiles of emotional intelligence and social behavior in Spanish adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work had two objectives. First, to identify different profiles of emotional intelligence (EI), and second, to verify the existence of significant statistical differences between the profiles identified in relation to social behavior. The participants were 1071 Spanish adolescents (50.2% girls), ranging in age from 14 to 17 years, who completed the Trait Meta-Mood Scale-24 (TMMS-24) and the Socialization Battery BAS-3. Cluster analysis identified four EI profiles: a group of adolescents with a low EI profile, a group with high scores in perception, a group with predominantly high emotional regulation, and a group of adolescents with high EI. The results also indicated statistically significant differences in the profiles in most of social behaviors. The students from the groups with high general EI scores and high scores in emotional regulation also show higher scores in several positive social behaviors. Findings are discussed in terms of their practical implications for Spanish adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gázquez, José J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fuentes, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inglés, Cándido J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Herrero, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo tuvo dos objetivos, por una parte, identificar diferentes perfiles de inteligencia emocional (IE)  y, por otra parte, comprobar si entre los perfiles identificados existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas respecto a la conducta social. Participaron 1.071 adolescentes españoles (50,2% chicas) españoles con edades de 14 a 17 años, a los que se les administró la 'Escala de inteligencia emocional percibida' (Trait Meta-Mood Scale-24, TMMS-24) y la 'Batería de socialización BAS-3'. El análisis de conglomerados identificó cuatro perfiles de IE: un grupo de adolescentes con un perfil de baja IE, un grupo con puntuaciones altas en percepción, un grupo con predominio de elevada regulación emocional y un último grupo de adolescentes con alta IE. Los resultados también indicaron diferencias  estadísticamente significativas entre los perfiles en los patrones de comportamiento social, destacando los estudiantes de los grupos con alta IE generalizada y alta puntuación en regulación emocional, los cuales muestran mayores puntuaciones en conductas sociales positivas. Los descubrimientos se discuten en términos de sus implicaciones prácticas con adolescentes españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(1): 141-160, ene.-abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139101</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfiles de inteligencia, emocional y conducta social en adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
