<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135597</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We report a retrospective review of the case series of Fournier&#146;s gangrene treated in our department from November 1996 to October 2004. METHODS/RESULTS: We studied nine male patients with ages between 21 and 85 years (mean 55 years). 66% of the patients had associated risk factors, and the underlying cause was identified in 56% of the cases. Mean hospital stay was 21 days and two of the patients died from the disease. CONCLUSIONS: Fournier&#146;s gangrene is an infection with a very fast evolution, producing necrotizing fascitis of the external genitalia and perineum. It has a high mortality rate, mainly if diagnosis and treatment are deferred. This last includes wide spectrum antibiotic coverage, surgical treatment with debridement and drainage, and, in many cases, a second surgical intervention for reconstructive plasties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Armada, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Juan de Laorden, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planelles Gómez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergés Prósper, Aleixandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Tortosa, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Lloret, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Presentamos una revisión de los casos de gangrena de Fournier tratados en nuestro servicio desde noviembre de 1996 hasta octubre de 2004. MÉTODO/RESULTADOS: Estudiamos nueve pacientes, todos varones, con edad comprendida entre 21 y 85 años (media 55). En el 66% tenían factores de riesgo y en el 56% de los casos se identificó la causa subyacente. Su estancia media fue de 21 días y destacamos que se produjeron dos defunciones. CONCLUSIÓN: La gangrena de Fournier es una infección de muy rápida evolución que cursa con fascitis necrotizante de los genitales externos y el periné. Tiene una alta mortalidad, sobre todo, si se demora su diag- nóstico y tratamiento. Éste se basa en una cobertura antibiótica agresiva de amplio espectro, en un tratamiento quirúrgico con desbridamiento y drenaje, y, en muchos casos, un segundo tiempo quirúrgico para las plastias correctoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(8): 767-771, oct. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gangrena de Fournier</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
