<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046902</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystic dystrophy of the duodenal wall. An underdiagnosed complication in aberrant pancreas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic dystrophy of the duodenal wall is an uncommon complication of aberrant pancreas characterized by increased duodenal wall thickness associated with intraparietal cystic lesions. We present the case of a male patient with cystic dystrophy of the duodenal wall, which posed major diagnostic problems due to the difficulty of distinguishing this entity from tumors of the head of the pancreas. Echoendoscopy was useful in establishing the definitive diagnosis, allowing puncture-evacuation of the intracystic contents with resolution of obstructive symptoms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Repiso, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vela, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Rodríguez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Frutos, Concha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carboles, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Chacón, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Grueso, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La distrofia quística duodenal es una rara complicación del páncreas aberrante, caracterizada por el aumento del grosor de la pared duodenal, asociado a la presencia de lesiones quísticas intraparietales. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con distrofia quística de la pared duodenal, ingresado por clínica relacionada con obstrucción duodenal, en el que se plantearon grandes problemas diagnósticos por la dificultad distinguirla de los tumores en la cabeza pancreática. La ecoendoscopia resultó de gran utilidad para establecer un diagnóstico definitivo, permitió la punción-evacuación del contenido intraquístico y así resolver el cuadro obstructivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;29(6): 345-348, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distrofia quística de la pared duodenal. Una complicación infradiagnosticada del páncreas aberrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4439^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4439^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
