<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154115</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variations in the diagnostic confirmation process between breast cancer mass screening units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse variations in the diagnostic confirmation process between screening units, variations in the outcome of each episode and the relationship between the use of the different diagnostic confirmation tests and the lesion detection rate. Method: Observational study of variability of the standardised use of diagnostic and lesion detection tests in 34 breast cancer mass screening units participating in early-detection programmes in three Spanish regions from 2002&#150;2011. Results: The diagnostic test variation ratio in percentiles 25&#150;75 ranged from 1.68 (further appointments) to 3.39 (fine-needle aspiration). The variation ratio in detection rates of benign lesions, ductal carcinoma in situ and invasive cancer were 2.79, 1.99 and 1.36, respectively. A positive relationship between rates of testing and detection rates was found with fine-needle aspiration-benign lesions (R2: 0.53), fine-needle aspiration-invasive carcinoma (R2: 0 28), core biopsy-benign lesions (R2: 0.64), core biopsy-ductal carcinoma in situ (R2: 0.61) and core biopsy-invasive carcinoma (R2: 0.48). Conclusions: Variation in the use of invasive tests between the breast cancer screening units participating in early-detection programmes was found to be significantly higher than variations in lesion detection. Units which conducted more fine-needle aspiration tests had higher benign lesion detection rates, while units that conducted more core biopsies detected more benign lesions and cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tardón, Adonina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torá-Rocamora, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Natal, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Somoano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar las variaciones en el proceso de confirmación diagnóstica entre unidades de cribado, las variaciones en los resultados de cada episodio y la relación entre las tasas de las diferentes pruebas de confirmación diagnóstica y las de detección de lesiones. Método: Estudio observacional de las variaciones de las tasas estandarizadas de pruebas diagnósticas y de detección de lesiones, en 34 unidades de cribado de los programas poblacionales de detección precoz de cáncer de mama, de tres comunidades autónomas, en el periodo de 2002 a 2011. Resultados: Las razones de variación entre los percentiles 25-75 en las tasas de realización de pruebas diagnósticas oscilaron entre 1,68 (recitaciones) y 3,39 (punción-aspiración con aguja fina). En las tasas de detección de lesiones benignas, carcinoma ductal in situ y cáncer invasivo fueron, respectivamente, 2,79, 1,99 y 1,36. Se encontró una relación positiva entre las tasas de realización de pruebas y las tasas de detección en punción-aspiración con aguja fina y lesiones benignas (R2: 0,53), punción-aspiración con aguja fina y carcinoma invasivo (R2: 0, 28), biopsias cerradas y lesiones benignas (R2: 0,64), biopsias cerradas y carcinoma ductal in situ (R2: 0,61), y biopsias cerradas y carcinoma invasivo (R2: 0,48). Conclusiones: Se observaron variaciones en la realización de pruebas invasivas entre las unidades de detección precoz de cáncer de mama de mayor magnitud que las de detección de lesiones. Las unidades con más pruebas de punción-aspiración con aguja fina tienen mayores tasas de detección de lesiones benignas, y las que realizan más biopsias cerradas detectan más lesiones benignas y cáncer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(4): 265-271, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variaciones en el proceso de confirmación diagnóstica entre unidades de cribado poblacional de cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
