<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116994</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of periodontal diseases on diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last few years, various studies have shown that diabetes is not only a risk factor for periodontal diseases, but also that periodontal diseases may affect glycaemic control, with the well known consequences in terms of diabetes complications. The aim of the present paper was to review the existing evidence on the impact of periodontal diseases on diabetes, its metabolic control, and its complications, as well as the implications of these findings. Periodontal diseases are infections, which trigger an immune inflammatory response in the periodontal tissues, responsible for a major proportion of the associated tissue destruction. The prevalence of periodontal diseases is high all over the world, which is confirmed in recent studies, both in Spain and Portugal. The importance of these diseases is based, not only on the local effects, such as tooth loss, but also on their systemic consequences. Among them, periodontal diseases have been shown to affect diabetes and its glycaemic control, due to (among other factors) the associated systemic inflammation. Different studies have shown that periodontitis is associated with a higher level of glycosylated haemoglobin, both in subjects with and without diabetes. Moreover, it has been suggested that periodontitis may increase the risk of diabetes onset, as well as a higher risk of diabetic complications for diabetes patients. Conversely, periodontal therapy may improve glycaemic control in type 2 diabetic patients and, eventually, decrease diabetes complications. The implications of these findings are numerous, affecting dentists, other health professionals and patients, among others (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Faria Almeida, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Alba, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Casanovas, Héctor J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera González, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha evidenciado en los últimos años no solo que la diabetes es un factor de riesgo para las enfermedades periodontales, sino que estas a su vez podrían afectar al control de la glucemia y las consecuencias de ello derivadas. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar la evidencia existente sobre la influencia de las enfermedades periodontales en la diabetes, su control metabólico y sus complicaciones, así como tratar de analizar las implicaciones de esos hallazgos. Las enfermedades periodontales son infecciones que inducen una respuesta inmunoinflamatoria en los tejidos periodontales, responsable en gran parte de la destrucción tisular asociada. Su prevalencia es alta en todo el mundo, lo que es confirmado por datos recientes tanto en España como en Portugal. Su importancia radica no solo en los efectos locales como la pérdida de dientes, sino también en sus efectos sistémicos. Entre ellos, las enfermedades periodontales pueden afectar a la diabetes y a su control glucémico, debido a los efectos a nivel de la inflamación sistémica. Diferentes estudios han señalado que la periodontitis se asocia a un nivel de hemoglobina glucosilada más elevado, tanto en pacientes con y sin diabetes. Incluso, se ha sugerido que la periodontitis puede asociarse a un riesgo aumentado de sufrir diabetes, además de un riesgo aumentado de sufrir ciertas complicaciones en pacientes diabéticos. Por otra parte, el tratamiento periodontal puede mejorar el control de la glucemia y, eventualmente, reducir la frecuencia de complicaciones. Las implicaciones de estas evidencias son múltiples y afectan a dentistas, personal médico y a pacientes, entre otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;29(5): 151-159, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de las enfermedades periodontales sobre la diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
