<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139308</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Currently there is a need for specific training and special dedication to pediatric urology (PU). Nevertheless, we lack of a continuous education program, which must be specific and multidisciplinary. Objectives: To create a complementary training program in PU with the following differential characteristics: 1) University postgraduate, 2) internationally accredited, 3) multidisciplinary, 4) theoretical and practical, 5) through virtual teaching, 6) with on-site support, 7) academically directed and mentored, 8) based on individual and group self learning, 9) with international faculty and alumni 10) objectively evaluable. Methods: We developed two original projects of virtual training courses with practices in PU, Master and Expert following the International University of Andalucía (UNIA) regulations and with the support of the Medical College of Malaga. The Master has a general content one year duration and will be repeated yearly. The Expert course has monographic character, half-year duration and will be repeated yearly with different topics. They are credited 60 and 30 ECTS credits respectively. The course has 3 parts well differentiated in objectives and development: 1. Virtual training 2. On-site hospital practices and, 3. Final work. The alumni answered a questionnaire to evaluate the master at the midpoint. RESULTS: The UNIA has considered viable and approved all 3 projects presented: I PU MASTER (2014- 2015), II PU MASTER (2015-2016) and Expert Course on pediatric incontinence (2015-2016) First PU MASTER data.- Registration applications: 60 alumni. Admitted alumni 40; mean age 37 years; 8 nationalities, 57% Spanish, 43% Foreigners. Specialities: Urology 14(35%), Pediatric Surgery 24 (60%), Pediatrics (Pediatric nephrology 1), General Medicine 1. Mid term Master evaluation by the alumni (0-100). Difficulty 60. Quality of the topics 92; complementary materials 90; faculty 90; UNIA virtual Campus 89. Conclusions: The demand of registrations demonstrates the need and interest of a pediatric Urology training program, through Master and Expert Courses. Vir tual Training, e-learning, within the Virtual Campus of the UNIA is viable. This self-learning model is being highly valued by the international alumni. We offer an interesting supplement for continuous education in PU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuente-Madero, José Luis de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caparrós-Cayuela, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguélez-Lago, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pereira, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Actualmente se ha hecho necesaria una formación específica y una especial dedicación a la Urología Pediátrica (UP). Sin embargo, falta un programa de formación continuada, que debe ser específico y multidisciplinar. Objetivo:  crear un programa de formación complementaria en UP con las siguientes características diferenciales: 1) universitario de postgrado, 2) con acreditación internacional, 3) multidisciplinar, 4) teórico y práctico, 5) mediante enseñanza virtual, 6) con apoyo presencial, 7) académicamente dirigido y tutelado, 8) basado en el auto aprendizaje individual y grupal, 9) internacional en profesorado y alumnado y 10) objetivamente evaluable. Método: Se han desarrollado dos proyectos originales de cursos de formación virtual con prácticas, en UP, Máster y Experto según normativa de la Universidad Internacional de Andalucía (UNIA) y con el apoyo de Colegio de Médicos de Málaga (COM). El Máster tiene carácter general con una duración de un curso académico y se repetirá cada año. El Experto tiene carácter monográfico, con duración de medio curso y se repetirá anualmente con diferentes argumentos. Están acreditados con 60 y 30 créditos ECTS respectivamente. El curso consta de 3 partes bien diferenciadas en desarrollo y objetivos: 1) enseñanza virtual, 2) prácticas presenciales hospitalarias y 3) trabajo final. A mitad del Máster el alumnado respondió al cuestionario para valoración del mismo. RESULTADOS: La UNIA ha considerado viables y ha aprobado los 3 proyectos presentados: I Máster UP (2014 &#150; 2015), II Máster UP (2015 &#150; 2016) y Experto en Incontinencia pediátrica (2015 &#150; 2016). Datos del I Máster UP.- Solicitud de matriculación: 60 alumnos. Alumnos admitidos 40; edad media 37 años; de 8 nacionalidades, españoles 57%, extranjeros 43%; especialidades de origen Urología 14 (35%), Cirugía Pediátrica 24 (60%), Pediatría: Nefrología Pediátrica 1, Medicina General 1. Valoración del alumnado a mitad de Máster: (0 &#150; 100). Dificultad 60; Calidad de los Temas 92; del material complementario 90; de los docentes 90; del Campus Virtual UNIA 89. Conclusiones: La solicitud de matriculaciones demuestra la necesidad y el interés de un programa de formación en UP, mediante cursos de Máster y Experto. La docencia virtual, e&#150;learning dentro del Campus Virtual de la UNIA, es viable. Este modelo de auto aprendizaje está siendo muy bien valorado por el alumnado internacional. Se oferta un complemento interesante en la formación continuada en UP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(6): 515-523, jul.-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139308</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Docencia virtual (e - learning) en Urología Pediátrica. Programa de cursos master y experto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33919^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
