<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98593</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe pediatric head injuries (I). Epidemiology, clinical manifestations and course</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the epidemiology, clinical manifestations and evolutive characteristics of pediatric patients with severe head injury (SHI).Material and method: A review was made of the patients admitted to the pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) with SHI between July 1983 and December 2009.Results: Of the 389 patients with head injuries admitted to the PICU during the study period,174 (45%) presented SHI. The mean age in this group was of 67±9 months, with a Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) of 5.5±1.8 and a PRISM score of 10.7±6.7. The most frequent etiology of SHI was traffic accidents (56%), though these have decreased significantly in the last decade(58.5%  vs  45.3%; P &lt; .001). Twenty-one percent of the patients required evacuation of the lesions detected by computed tomography (CT), and 39% presented severe diffuse encephalic injury(DEI). Seventy-nine percent of the patients in whom intracranial pressure (ICP) was monitored presented intracranial hypertension. Sequelae of clinical relevance were recorded in 59 patients(39%), and proved serious in 64% of the cases. The mortality rate in this patient series was 24.7%. Intracranial hypertension decreased significantly in the last decade (88% vs 54%; P &lt; .05), and clinical recovery has improved (23.3% vs 63.1%; P &lt; .001).Conclusions: a) The incidence of traffic accidents has decreased in the last decade in the studied population; b) patients with SHI in which ICP was monitored showed a high incidence of intracranial hypertension; c) morbidity-mortality among pediatric patients with SHI has decreased over the course of the study period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valerón Lemaur, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Álvarez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limiñana Cañal, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Bravo de Laguna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Quevedo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jorge, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morón Saén de Casas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Consuegra Llapurt, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características epidemiológicas, clínicas y evolutivas de los pacientes pediátricos con traumatismo craneoencefálico grave (TCEG).Material y método: Revisión de los pacientes ingresados en una unidad de medicina intensiva pediátrica (UMIP) con TCEG en el periodo comprendido entre julio de 1983 y diciembre de 2009.Resultados: De los 389 pacientes con traumatismo craneoencefálico (TCE) ingresados en nuestra unidad durante el periodo de estudio, presentaron TCEG 174 (45%). La media de edad de este grupo fue 67±9 meses, con una puntuación media en la escala de Glasgow (GCS) de 5,5±1,8 y una puntuación PRISM media de 10,7±6,7. La etiología más frecuente de los TCEG fueron los accidentes de tráfico (56%), aunque en la última década existe una disminución significativa de su incidencia (el 58,5 frente al 45,3%; p &lt; 0,001). Un 21% de los pacientes precisaron evacuación de la lesión objetivada en la TC, objetivándose en un 39% lesión encefálica difusa (LED) grave. Un 79% de los pacientes en los que se monitorizó la presión intracraneal (PIC) presentaron hipertensión intracraneal (HTC). Las secuelas de relevancia clínica se objetivaron en 59 pacientes(39%), siendo graves en el 64% de ellos. La mortalidad de la población estudiada fue de un 24,7%. La incidencia de HTC fue significativamente menor en la última década estudiada (el 88 frente al 54%; p &lt; 0,05), con una mejor recuperación clínica (el 23,3 frente al 63,1%; p &lt; 0,001).Conclusiones: a) La incidencia de los accidentes de tráfico disminuyó en la última década en la población estudiada; b) los pacientes con TCEG en los que se monitorizó la PIC presentaron una alta incidencia de HTC, y c) la morbimortalidad de los TCEG pediátricos disminuyó a lo largo del periodo de estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(6): 331-336, ago.-sept. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traumatismo craneoencefálico pediátrico grave (I). Epidemiología, clínica y evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6410</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
