<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058518</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute inferior myocardial infarction masking the J wave syndrome. Based on four observations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The J wave syndrome is characterized by a prominent J wave accompanied by ST-segment elevation in the absence of structural heart disease. It includes the benign early repolarization syndrome, the highly arrhythmogenic Brugada syndrome and idiopathic ventricular fibrillation. Although acute coronary syndromes are one of the leading causes of ST-segment deviation, no clinical reports that specifically describe the modulating effects of an ischemic injury current on the ECG manifestations of the J wave syndrome have been found. This report describes four cases of patients with acute inferior ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction who had J wave (or negative deplacement of the J point) and ST-segment depression in the right precordial leads. Later, these precordial ECG alterations disappeared and were progressively replaced by prominent J (R') waves and anterior ST-segment elevations, suggesting the presence of a J wave syndrome. In conclusion, the J wave syndrome may be obscured by an acute inferior myocardial infarction with concomitant ST-segment depression in the right precordial leads. In such circumstances, early detection of the J wave (or depressed J point) may be used as ECG marker of the early repolarization syndrome or Brugada syndrome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Carnicer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de la onda J está caracterizado por una onda J prominente acompañada de una elevación del segmento ST en ausencia de una enfermedad cardíaca estructural, e incluye el síndrome benigno de la repolarización precoz y los síndromes arritmogénicos de Brugada y de la fibrilación ventricular idiopática. Aunque los síndromes coronarios agudos son una de las principales causas de desviación del segmento ST, no existen casos clínicos que describan específicamente los efectos moduladores de una corriente de lesión isquémica sobre las manifestaciones electrocardiográficas del síndrome de la onda J. Este artículo describe 4 casos de pacientes con un infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación inferior del ST que tuvieron una onda J (o desplazamiento negativo del punto J) y depresión del segmento ST en las derivaciones precordiales derechas. Después, estas alteraciones precordiales del ECG desaparecieron y fueron progresivamente reemplazadas por ondas J (R') prominentes y elevaciones anteriores del segmento ST sugerentes de la presencia de un síndrome de la onda J. En conclusión, el síndrome de la onda J puede estar oculto por un infarto agudo de miocardio inferior con depresión simultánea del segmento ST en las derivaciones precordiales derechas. En estas circunstancias, la detección precoz de una onda J (o depresión del punto J) puede utilizarse como marcador electrocardiográfico del síndrome de Brugada o de la repolarización precoz</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(1): 48-53, ene. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infarto agudo de miocardio inferior enmascarando el síndrome de la onda J. A propósito de cuatro observaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
