<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101774</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the auditory cortex in the spatial information processing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Sound localization is a computational process accomplished along the auditory pathway. Once the acoustic  information received at each ear is analyzed independently (monaural cues) and comparatively (binaural cues), those  cues are integrated to generate a coherent spatial percept. Using adult ferrets trained by positive conditioning in a spatial  task, we aimed to study the role of the auditory cortex in the ability to localize sounds under both normal hearing and  monaurally occluded conditions, the latter of which requires a reinterpretation of the values of the localization cues.  Sound localization deficits were found after lesion or inactivation of the different auditory cortical regions, thereby  indicating their participation in spatial processing. The differential impairments found in the approach-to-target and in the  head movement responses reveal the complex relationship between cortex and midbrain which are putatively responsible   for the voluntary and reflexive aspects of localization behaviour respectively. Furthermore, every auditory cortical region  contributes to the adaptation process that follows monaural occlusion, indicating the key role that the auditory cortex  plays in experience-dependent plasticity. Also, the selective lesion of the descending projections from the auditory cortex to  the inferior colliculus by chromophore-targeted laser photolysis has revealed the essential function that descending   pathways play in learning-induced localization plasticity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Nodal, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo Lorenzana, Victoria M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. La localización del sonido es el resultado de un proceso computacional llevado a cabo a lo largo de la vía auditiva. La información acústica recibida por cada oído, una vez analizada independientemente (claves monoaurales o espectrales) y conjuntamente (claves binaurales), es integrada para generar una percepción espacial unificada. Hemos estudiado las propiedades espaciales de la corteza auditiva y su participación en fenómenos de plasticidad basados en la  adaptación a nuevas claves de localización en hurones adultos entrenados con condicionamiento positivo. La lesión e inactivación de las diferentes áreas corticales ha puesto de manifiesto no sólo su participación en la localización del sonido,  sino también la compleja interacción entre la corteza cerebral y el mesencéfalo, responsables, respectivamente, de los aspectos voluntarios y reflejos del comportamiento de localización. Todas las áreas auditivas corticales participan en  los procesos de adaptación ante nuevos valores en las claves de localización espacial que se producen ante la oclusión  temporal de un oído. Además, la eliminación selectiva de la proyección descendente desde la corteza al colículo inferior  ha revelado la importancia del control cortical sobre la información ascendente para su reinterpretación, necesaria para  la adaptación a diferentes condiciones ambientales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(2): 91-100, jul. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101774</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La corteza auditiva en el procesamiento de la información espacial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9665^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9308^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13409^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1308^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5398^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
