<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130793</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the clinical presentation of Pompe disease in infancy: two case reports and response to treatment with human recombinant enzyme</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pompe disease/glycogen storage disease type II is a congenital metabolic disorder. It is an autosomal recessive disease where there is a deficiency of acid &amp;#945;-glucosidase (GAA), an enzyme required for lysosomal glycogen degradation.  We describe two infantile onset cases with heterogeneous presentations.Case reports. The first case is a newborn with maintained bradycardia, a cardiologic study revealed severe biventricular hypertrophy. The second case is a 14 months old patient with motor delay and arreflexic hypotonia. Creatine kinase, lactate  dehydrogenase, glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase and glutamic-pyruvic transaminase were high. The electromyogram showed myopathic alteration and the muscle biopsy vacuolar myopathy with glycogen accumulation. In both of them, GAA activity was decreased and the genetic exam of the GAA gene revealed heterozygous mutations already described in Pompe disease. They started enzyme replacement therapy at 1 month old and 18 months old respectively, improving the cardiomyopathy hypertrophy, motor wise however less advance was seen. At the present time, the patients are 9 months and 5 years old respectively, the last one has a Gross Motor Function Measure (GMFM) III level. Conclusion. GAA is the only authorized option for Pompe disease treatment; the effects observed are similar to the ones described in the literature, with excellent outcome in the hypertrophic cardiomyopathy but less effective in the skeletal muscle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Antón, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Ramírez, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Medinilla, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berzosa López, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Pompe o glucogenosis tipo II es un error innato del metabolismo, de herencia autosómica recesiva, causado por un déficit de la enzima lisosomal &amp;#945;-glucosidasa ácida (GAA), que ocasiona un acúmulo multisistémico de glucógeno. Describimos dos casos de inicio temprano (infantil) con diferentes formas de presentación. Casos clínicos. El primer caso se trata de un neonato que presentó una bradicardia mantenida desde el nacimiento, lo que motivó el estudio cardiológico, en el que se evidenció una hipertrofia biventricular grave. El segundo caso se trata de un niño de 14 meses con retraso motor e hipotonía con arreflexia. En la analítica destacaban una creatincinasa, lactato deshidrogenasa, transaminasa glutámico oxalacética y transaminasa glutámico pirúvica elevadas. El electromiograma mostró  signos de afectación miopática, y la biopsia muscular, una miopatía vacuolar con depósito de glucógeno. En ambos, la actividad de la GAA estaba disminuida y el análisis genético del gen GAA evidenció que eran portadores heterocigotos de mutaciones descritas en la enfermedad de Pompe. Iniciaron tratamiento con enzima recombinante humana al mes y a los 18 meses de vida, respectivamente, con mejoría evidente de la miocardiopatía hipertrófica, aunque más limitada a nivel motor. En la actualidad tienen, respectivamente, 9 meses y 5 años, y este último presenta un nivel III de la escala GMFM (Gross Motor Function Measure). Conclusión. La GAA recombinante humana es la única opción terapéutica autorizada para estos pacientes. Los efectos que hemos observado son similares a los descritos en otros casos, con una excelente evolución de la miocardiopatía hipertrófica y un efecto variable sobre la musculatura esquelética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(11): 503-507, dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en la presentación clínica de la enfermedad de Pompe infantil: presentación de dos casos y respuesta al tratamiento con enzima recombinante humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d520^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54218^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53690^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
