<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59152</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlation between the molar potency of atracurium and its onset time and speed of action</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To study the correlation between thesubparalyzing dose of atracurium and its onset time andspeed of action.MATERIAL AND METHODS: Six groups of patients received0.36, 0.68, 0.98, 1.44, 1.77, or 2.06 times the median effectivedose of atracurium. The maximal effect, onset time, molarpotency (&amp;#956;M·kg&#150;1) and speed of action (relationship betweentime in seconds and percentage of maximum effect andbetween percentage of maximum effect and time) of eachdose were measured. The values were converted tologarithms and square roots to test for correlations. Theregression line provided the equation, coefficient ofdetermination (R2), and statistical significance.RESULTS: The correlation between the logarithms ofmolar potency and onset time was poor and not statisticallysignificant (R2 = 0.564, P = .138), whereas the correlationsbetween the logarithms of molar potency and speed ofaction (seg/%) (s/maximum % effect, R2 = 0.952; andmaximum % effect/s, R2 = 0.984) were strong andstatistically significant (P &lt; .0001) The regression formulaswere able to predict the onset time. The results were similarwhen the values were converted to their square roots.CONCLUSION: The onset time of a neuromuscularblocker is linked to its effect and its permeability is linkedto the size of its molecules or the molar potency, which isdose-dependent. In the case of atracurium, this correlationwas poor and not significant. This finding coincides withthose of other authors, who found that atracurium wasdistant from the regression line for equipotent quantitiesof different neuromuscular blockers. Substituting onsettime with speed of action, however, made it possible toestablish a strong and significant correlation. Our resultssuggest that the speed of action of atracurium depends onthe size of its molecule (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Steinberg,  D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Estudiar la correlación entre dosis subparalizantesde atracurio con el comienzo y velocidad.MATERIAL Y MÉTODO: Seis grupos de pacientes recibieron:0,36; 0,68; 0,98; 1,44; 1,77; ó 2,06 x DE50 de atracurio.Se determinaron el máximo efecto, tiempo para alcanzarlo(TC), las concentraciones molares (&amp;#956;M.Kg&#150;1) y velocidadde acción (VA) [relación entre tiempo y efecto (seg/%) oviceversa (%/seg))] de cada dosis. Para su correlación seconvirtieron en logaritmos o raíz cuadrada. De la línea deregresión se obtuvieron: la fórmula, R2 y significación estadística.RESULTADOS: La correlación entre los logaritmos de la&amp;#956;M.Kg&#150;1 y TC fue pobre y no significativa (R2 = 0,564; p =0,138), pero fue muy alta y significativa con la VA seg/%(R2 = 0,952; p &lt; 0,001) y VA %/seg (R2 = 0,984; p &lt; 0,001).Al resolver las fórmulas de regresión se pudo predecir elcomienzo. Cuando los valores se transforman en V2 losresultados fueron similares.CONCLUSIÓN: El TC de un bloqueante neuromuscularestá ligado a su efecto y la permeabilidad al tamaño de susmoléculas o &amp;#956;M.Kg&#150;1, la cual a su vez es función de la dosis.En el caso del atracurio, esta correlación resultó pobre yno significativa, hallazgo que coincide con el de otros autorescuando aseguran que el atracurio se aleja de la línea deregresión entre cantidades equipotenciales de varios bloqueantesneuromusculares. En cambio la sustitución deTC por VA permite establecer una buena y significativacorrelación. Los resultados sugieren la dependencia entrevelocidad del atracurio y el tamaño de su molécula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(6): 335-340, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación entre la concentración molar del atracurioy su tiempo de comienzo o velocidad de acción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9658^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19080^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38324</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
