<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129284</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New techniques to extract impacted partially covered metallic biliary stents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the problems affecting metallic biliary stents is the difficulty of removing them, especially after a period of months or if they have migrated. Several approaches have been used to remove both covered and uncovered stents, although with different degrees of effectiveness.We report two new approaches to removing partially covered stents that migrated proximally and that impacted in the papillary area and distal common bile duct. One stent was removed by papillectomy and the other by using duodenoscopy-guided controlled radial expansion balloon dilation. In both cases, the stents were removed without severe complications for the patient, leaving a good caliber in the stenosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Carrillo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Roldán,  Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Legaz Huidobro, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villafáñez García, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago González Carro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Manjavacas Muñoz, Natividad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Pérez, Gema de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Gutiérrez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ynfante Ferrús, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roncero García-Escribano, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los problemas que aparecen en las prótesis metálicas de vía biliar es su dificultad para retirarlas, sobre todo si han pasado meses o han migrado. Para eso se han usado varios métodos a fin de poder extraer las prótesis biliares metálicas, tanto las recubiertas como las no recubiertas, con diferente eficacia.Se describen 2 nuevas formas para poder extraer prótesis parcialmente recubiertas que presentan migración proximal y se han impactado en el área papilar y el colédoco distal. Una prótesis se extrajo mediante papilectomía y la otra con balón de dilatación con colangiografía retrógrada endoscópica; para esto, se usó un duodenoscopio. En ambos casos se pudieron retirar las prótesis sin complicaciones graves para los enfermos y con un buen resultado para el calibre final de la estenosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;32(7): 489-494, ago. -sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas técnicas para extraer prótesis biliares metálicas recubiertas impactadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15072</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
