<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82482</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Educational innovation on the practices for the subjects of community nursing. Mental health nursing and geriatric nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The new European space for higher education requires changes in education manners as well as execution. One of the main challenges is for the students to acquire competence in their professional life. For that purpose they require knowledge, but also skills and a proactive attitude towards learning. In this paper we tell the experience of the Virgen de las Nieves School of Nursing in Granada, with regards to the integration of the practices for the subjects of Community Nursing III, Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing, and Geriatric Nursing, which are taken in the third year of the Diplomatura en Enfermería degree. Said practices, which were previously being offered separately within different contexts, will be merged in the same program whose scope will be Primary Care. We believe that the experience has been very positive by looking both at the results and the satisfaction of the students and the professional lecturers. It has been achieved an increase in the number of community care practice hours, and students have managed to acquire more autonomy in their learning and to incorporate critical reasoning in their education. In the methodology used, they have been the main evaluators and protagonists in their learning process, seeking the implication of professionals and teaching tutors in this change.  The consensus on the objectives and methods, along with the obstacles which had to be overcome, constitutes one of the most interesting aspects of this experience(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heierle Valero, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garach Mirasol, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillamet Lloveras, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celma Vicente, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Caballero Gálvez, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El nuevo espacio europeo de educación superior exige cambios tanto en el fondo como en la forma de enseñar. Uno de los principales retos es que el alumnado adquiera competencias para su vida profesional. Para ello requiere, además de conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes proactivas para el aprendizaje.  En este artículo se explica la experiencia de la Escuela Universitaria de Enfermería (EUE) Virgen de las Nieves de Granada, a propósito de la integración de las prácticas de las asignaturas de Enfermería Comunitaria III, Enfermería Psiquiátrica y de Salud Mental y Enfermería Geriátrica, las cuales se cursan en tercer año de la Diplomatura de Enfermería. Dichas prácticas, que anteriormente se realizaban en distintos contextos de forma inconexa, se unen en un mismo programa que tiene como ámbito la atención primaria. Creemos que la experiencia ha sido muy positiva tanto por los resultados como por la satisfacción del alumnado y las profesionales docentes. Se ha conseguido incrementar el número de horas de prácticas extrahospitalarias, que el alumnado adquiriera mayor autonomía en su aprendizaje y que, además, incorporase el razonamiento crítico en su formación. Se ha utilizado una metodología donde han sido los principales evaluadores y dinamizadores de su proceso de aprendizaje, buscando la implicación de profesionales y tutores docentes en dicho cambio.  El consenso en los objetivos y en los métodos, así como las barreras que se han tenido que superar constituye una de las partes más interesantes de esta experiencia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(11): 771-776, nov. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82482</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Innovación docente en las prácticas de enfermería comunitaria, salud mental y geriatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
