<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81831</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">1st National Consensus Conference on maxillar sinus bone grafts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objectives of the first Spanish Consensus Conference on Sinus Bone Graft were trying to reach agreements points on the major controversies of this technique, and translate them in a summary document. Material and method: During the 17th and 18th of October of 2008 took place in Oviedo (Spain) the Conference, sponsored by the Spanish Society of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery. There, 50 national and international speakers reviewed in 6 workshops the major controversies of sinus bone grafts. Following the conferences, the moderators proposed the main conclusions of each workshop and opened a round of discussion where all attendees participated. Results: This document and its conclusions emanate from the presentations made by the speakers and the discussions and agreements of each workshop. Both have been approved after several corrections by all authors before being submitted for publication. They have also obtained the official scientific recognition of the Spanish Society of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery and should serve as a basis for future scientific studies and meetings. Conclusions: The main objective when we perform a sinus bone graft is vital bone formation in the maxillary sinus, to achieve long-term survival of the implants after prosthetic loading. To do this, the technique and sequence of treatment should aim to achieve predictable and stable results over time, although this involves a longer waiting time. The initial implant stability is the key factor for osseointegration and should be the main criterion to indicate simultaneous or delayed implants in the maxillary sinus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal, P. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Mauriño, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monje, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rituerto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Arranz, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rollón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Alfaro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arruti, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgueño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesdeoca, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Junquera, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forteza, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Díez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verrier, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Concejo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Granizo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baladrón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esnal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vega, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Birbe, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández San Román, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Lagunas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Infante, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lombardía, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garatea, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bustillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Conde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borja, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Recio, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz, V. M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejías, Q</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrat, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Recio, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caubet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rezola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueto, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Cedrún, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de la I Conferencia Española de Consenso sobre el Injerto Óseo Sinusal era intentar llegar a puntos de acuerdo sobre las principales controversias de esta técnica, aplicada de forma muy variada y con el empleo de materiales muy diversos, y conseguir plasmar los mismos en un documento resumen consensuado por todos los autores. Material y método: Durante los días 17 y 18 de octubre de 2008 se celebró en Oviedo la citada conferencia, auspiciada por la Sociedad Española de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial. En ella se dieron cita un total de 50 ponentes de reconocido prestigio nacional e internacional que repasaron en 6 mesas de trabajo las principales controversias sobre los injertos óseos sinusales. Tras las conferencias de los ponentes, los moderadores establecían las principales conclusiones de cada mesa y se abría un turno de debate donde participaban todos los asistentes. Resultado: Este documento y sus conclusiones emanan de las presentaciones realizadas por los ponentes y de las deliberaciones y acuerdos de cada mesa de trabajo. Ambos han sido aprobados tras varias correcciones por todos los autores antes de ser enviados para su publicación. Además, han obtenido el reconocimiento científico oficial de la Sociedad Española de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial y deben servir como base para futuros estudios y reuniones científicas. Conclusiones: El objetivo fundamental cuando se realiza un injerto óseo sinusal es la formación de hueso vital en el seno maxilar, para conseguir la supervivencia a largo plazo de los implantes tras su carga protésica. Para ello, la técnica y la secuencia de tratamiento deben orientarse a conseguir resultados predecibles y estables en el tiempo, aunque esto suponga un mayor tiempo de espera hasta la colocación de la prótesis. La estabilidad inicial del implante es el factor clave para la osteointegración y debe ser el principal criterio para indicar implantes simultáneos o diferidos en el seno maxilar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;32(2): 41-63, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81831</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">I Conferencia Nacional de Consenso sobre el Injerto Óseo del Seno Maxilar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8611^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8611^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33573^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8611^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8611^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8614^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
