<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80874</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atypical calcific tendinitis of the tendon of the gluteus maximus muscle with cortical bone abnormality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The calcifying tendinitis of the gluteus maximus is possible to being in association of erosion on the extern of the cortical of the femur at the insertion of the muscle. It is an unusual and self-limited pathology, but it is important to recognize the patron of the image features to avoid unnecessary diagnostic probes or actuations. We present a 36-year-old woman with a 4 months pain in the lateral side of her left hip and thigh. The radiographies showed a lytic lesion with calcifying matrix inside, while the CT showed external cortical erosion. The study was amplified to rule out malignity, performing chest radiography, mammography, hemogram, bioquimic and tumoral markers, which were normal, and isotope bone scan, that showed an area of increased activity in the proximal metaphysis. It was taken a conservative attitude, with progressive recovery until the resolution of the problem. The CT six months later demonstrated absence of calcifications and cortical erosion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artacho de Luna, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Fandiño, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Aristizábal, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonafont Vidal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tendinitis calcificante del músculo glúteo mayor se puede acompañar de erosión de la cortical del fémur a nivel de su inserción. Se trata de una patología infrecuente y autolimitada, pero es importante reconocer el patrón de las pruebas complementarias para evitar pruebas diagnósticas o actuaciones innecesarias. Presentamos a una mujer de 36 años con dolor en la cara lateral de la cadera y el muslo izquierdos de 4 meses de evolución. Las radiografías de fémur mostraban una lesión lítica con matriz calcificante en su interior, mientras que la TAC demostraba ruptura de la cortical externa. Se amplió el estudio para descartar malignidad, realizando radiografía de tórax, mamografía, hemograma, bioquímica y marcadores tumorales, que resultaron normales, y gammagrafía ósea, que mostró hipercaptación en la metáfisis proximal. Se adoptó una actitud conservadora con mejoría progresiva hasta la resolución del cuadro. La TAC realizada a los 6 meses mostró ausencia de calcificaciones y de erosión cortical(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(3): 271-274, jul.-sep.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendinitis calcificante atípica del tendón del músculo glúteo mayor con anormalidad ósea cortical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2147^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
