<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124226</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiorespiratory and metabolic responses to exercise performed on an air dissipation platform</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of the study was to analyze the effect of exercise performed on an air dissipation platform compared to the same exercise on the floor in a group of healthy women. Material and methods: In a quasi-experimental study 14 healthy women between 20 and 25 years performed exercises under two different conditions separated by one week, one was on an air dissipation platform and another on the floor. Respiratory exchange data were collected during the two tests using an open-circuit gas analyzer. Heart rate (HR) was recorded via telemetry. Capillary blood samples (5 &amp;#956;l) were taken every 10 minutes during the exercises using a portable lactate analyzer. The rated perceived exertion (RPE) was recorded every 10 minutes during the exercises using the Borg scale. Results: There were significant differences in mean HR variables (platform: 173.1 ± 13.6 bpm; floor: 166.7 ± 14.1 bpm; z = 1.9; P &lt; 0.05), average ventilation (VE) (platform: 58 ± 8.6 L/min; floor: 54.4 ± 12.4 L/min; z = 1.7; P &lt; 0.05), lactate in the 20th minute (platform: 6.9 ± 2.4 mmol/L; floor: 4.4 ± 1.9 mmol/L, z = 2.9; P &lt; 0.01), 30th minute (platform: 7.1 ± 2.6 mmol/L; floor: 5.0 ± 2.3 mmol/L; z = 2.4; P &lt; 0.01) and 40th (platform: 5.0 ± 1.9 mmol/L; floor: 3.6 ± 1,6 mmol/L; z = 1.9; P &lt; 0.05), with no significant differences in RPE throughout the test. Conclusions: The intensity of exercise on the air dissipation platform with the same session of exercises is greater than that performed on the floor, with similar values in the perceived exertion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Solano, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán Rubio, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rogríguez, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira Reis, Alessandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Subijana, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maté Muñoz, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnacho Castaño, Manuel Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del estudio fue analizar el efecto del ejercicio realizado sobre una plataforma de disipación de aire comparado con el mismo ejercicio en suelo en un grupo de mujeres sanas. Material y métodos: En un estudio cuasi-experimental 14 mujeres sanas de entre 20 y 25 años realizaron un mismo ejercicio en 2 condiciones diferentes separados entre sí por una semana; uno fue sobre una plataforma de disipación de aire y otro sobre el suelo. Durante las 2 pruebas se recolectaron los datos del intercambio respiratorio por un analizador de gases de circuito abierto. La frecuencia cardíaca (FC) fue registrada mediante telemetría. Muestras de sangre capilar (5 &amp;#956;l) fueron extraídas cada 10 min de ejercicio utilizando un analizador de lactato portátil. La percepción subjetiva del esfuerzo (RPE) fue registrada cada 10 min de ejercicio mediante la escala de Borg. Resultados: Hubo diferencias significativas en las variables de FC media (plataforma: 173,1 ± 13,6 lpm; suelo: 166,7 ± 14,1 lpm; z = 1,9; p &lt; 0,05), ventilación (VE) media (plataforma: 58 ± 8,6 l/min; suelo: 54,4 ± 12,4 l/min; z = 1,7; p &lt; 0,05), lactato en el minuto 20 (plataforma: 6,9 ± 2,4 mmol/l; suelo: 4,4 ± 1,9 mmol/l; z = 2,9; p &lt; 0,01), en el minuto 30 (plataforma 7,1 ± 2,6 mmol/l; suelo: 5,0 ± 2,3 mmol/l; z = 2,4; p &lt; 0,01) y en el minuto 40 (plataforma: 5,0 ± 1,9 mmol/l; suelo: 3,6 ± 1,6 mmol/l; z = 1,9; p &lt; 0,05), sin encontrar diferencias significativas en el RPE durante toda la prueba. Conclusiones: La intensidad del ejercicio realizado sobre la plataforma de disipación de aire ante una misma sesión de ejercicio es mayor que la realizada sobre el suelo, teniendo unos valores similares en la percepción de esfuerzo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);49(182): 53-58, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuestas cardiorrespiratorias y metabólicas al ejercicio realizado sobre una plataforma de disipación de aire</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
