<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148084</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dexamethasone intravitreal implant for treatment of persistent macular oedema in Birdshot retinochoroidopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: The case is reported of a 32 year-old man with a bilateral cystoid macular oedema and serous macular detachment due to birdshot retinochoroidopathy. An intravitreal implant of 0.7 mg dexamethasone (Ozurdex®, Allergan) was performed on both eyes, after a partial response of the macular oedema to oral and subtenon corticosteroids. Anatomical and visual improvements were observed and maintained after six months of follow up. Discussion: Intravitreal dexamethasone implant may be a good therapeutic option in patients with macular oedema due to Birdshot retinochoroidopathy, and who were refractory or had intolerance to previous therapies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rachwani Parshotam, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera de Zea, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Campos, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ben, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Presentamos el caso clínico de un paciente varón de 32 años de edad con edema macular quístico y desprendimiento seroso del neuroepitelio en ambos ojos secundario a una retinocoroidopatía de Birdshot. Tras la respuesta parcial del edema macular a corticoides orales y subtenonianos, se inició tratamiento mediante un implante intravítreo de 0,7 mg de dexametasona (Ozurdex®, Allergan) en ambos ojos, obteniéndose una mejoría anatómica y funcional que se mantuvo durante los 6 meses de seguimiento. Discusión: En pacientes con edema macular secundario a la enfermedad de Birdshot, bien por ineficacia, bien por intolerancia a terapias previas, los implantes intravítreos de dexametasona pueden ser una opción terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(3): 138-141, mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implante intravítreo de dexametasona como terapéutica del edema macular persistente en la retinocoroidopatía de Birdshot</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15224^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24564^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24564^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15224^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24564^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
