<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83457</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psoriatic Arthritis: What the Dermatologist Needs to Know, Part 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This review aims to cover all aspects related to the treatment of psoriatic arthritis and the evaluation of the response to treatment. We define the various evaluation methods currently used to assess response to treatment in patients with psoriatic arthritis and the complementary examination techniques used to ensure adequate follow-up. These tools enable both the dermatologist and the rheumatologist to carry out an ongoing evaluation of the clinical course, severity, and prognosis of the disease. The treatment lines proposed by the Group for Research and Assessment of Psoriasis and Psoriatic Arthritis and the Spanish Society of Rheumatology are discussed. Emerging strategies for treating this condition and improving prognosis are examined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrente-Segarra, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta revisión se pretenden abarcar todos los aspectos relacionados con el tratamiento de la artritis psoriásica así como la evaluación de la respuesta al tratamiento. Por este motivo, se definen los diferentes métodos de evaluación que se utilizan en la actualidad para valorar la respuesta al tratamiento de los pacientes con artritis psoriásica y las exploraciones complementarias que deben realizarse para el correcto seguimiento de estos pacientes. A través de estas herramientas, tanto el dermatólogo como el reumatólogo pueden evaluar la evolución, gravedad y pronóstico de la enfermedad en cada momento. En relación al tratamiento se exponen las líneas de tratamiento propuestas por la GRAPPA y la Sociedad Española de Reumatología (SER) y se introduce la aparición de nuevas terapias emergentes para el tratamiento de esta enfermedad y la mejora de su pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(9): 742-748, nov. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis psoriásica. Lo que el dermatólogo debe saber (Parte 2)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
