<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041157</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac tamponade as a presenting form of a tumor of unknown primary site: diagnostic test abuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">&#149; Purpose: We report the case of a woman with cancer of unknown primary site, presented with pericardialeffusion and cardiac tamponade. Necropsy showed a pericardium with poorly differentiated lungadenocarcinoma lesions.&#149; Material and Methods: We present a 60 year old woman who after the pertinent tests was diagnosed ofcardiac tamponade secondary to pericardial metastasis of cancer of unknown primary site.&#149; Results and conclusions: Cancer of unknown primary site is a very common problem in the oncologyclinical practice, that has been estimated between 5 and 10 % of all cancers, representing a common medicalproblem because of the difficult diagnosis and therapeutic management. The clinical manifestations depend onthe localization of the distant metastases, whose pattern differs from that of the metastatic localizations of thehomologous cancers of known primary site. The lack of results after an exhaustive search make further studiesunnecessary</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto de Prado, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, J del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceballos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocaña, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">&#149; Proposito: Presentamos el caso de un tumor de origen desconocido que debutó como derrame pericardiocon taponamiento cardiaco. El estudio necrópsico del pericardio resultó ser adenocarcinoma pobremente diferenciadode pulmón.&#149; Material y métodos: Mujer de 60 años que presento cuadro de taponamiento cardiaco secundario a underrame pericárdico metastásico de un tumor no filiado tras las pertinentes pruebas diagnósticas.&#149; Resultados y conclusiones: Los tumores de origen desconocido (TOD) son un problema relativamentefrecuente en la práctica clínica oncológica, estimándose su incidencia en un 5-10% de todos los enfermos concáncer1, presentando un problema de dificultad diagnóstica y manejo terapéutico. La forma de presentación clínicavaría dependiendo de la localización a distancia sin existir un patrón metastásico similar al de sus homólogoscon primario establecido. Así mismo la búsqueda exhaustiva del tumor primario suele ser la mayoría de lasveces improductiva y muy costosa</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;28(6): 293-296, jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taponamiento cardíaco como forma de presentación de un tumor de origen desconocido: abuso en las pruebas diagnósticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2349^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2349^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10681^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10681^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
