<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94079</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quotidian activities of mental health service users: A phenomenological study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study had the objective of understanding the quotidian activities of users of a Psychosocial Care Center. These services are strategic devices to consolidate the psychiatric reform and to promote psychosocial rehabilitation of people under psychological stress. It is a qualitative study, which follows the theoretical and methodological references from Alfred Schutz´s phenomenological sociology. The local of the study was a mental health service in Porto Alegre City, Rio Grande do Sul State, Brazil. Gathering of data was accomplished during the period from April to June, 2008, by phenomenological interview, with 13 users of the service. It was realized comprehensive data analysis, from which emerged a category about the performance of several activities in the quotidian of the users. With this study it is possible to understand that, with the service propitiated by the psychosocial services, the users are living in different social spaces and performing several activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nasi, Cíntia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schneider, Jacó Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo por objetivo comprender las actividades cotidianas de usuarios de un Centro de Atención Psicosocial. Esos servicios son dispositivos estratégicos en la consolidación de la reforma psiquiátrica y en la promoción y rehabilitación psicosocial. Se trata de un estudio cualitativo, con la utilización del referencial teórico-metodológico de Alfred Schutz. El sitio en que se llevó a cabo el estudio fue un servicio de salud mental en la ciudad de Porto Alegre, Brasil. La recolección de los datos ocurrió en el periodo de abril hasta junio de 2008, por medio de una entrevista fenomenológica, con 13 usuarios. Se realizó un análisis comprensivo de los testimonios, del cual surgió la categoría concreta que trata del desempeño de diversas actividades en el cotidiano de los usuarios. Con este estudio se pudo comprender que con la atención brindada en el modo psicosocial los usuarios circulan por distintos espacios y desarrollan diversas actividades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(4): 249-253, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividades cotidianas de usuarios de un servicio de salud mental: una investigación fenomenológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
