<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140082</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What's new in rectal cancer research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Clinical evidence has a more significant role in medical specialties than in surgery. Rectal cancer (CR) is no exception. This paper explores what CR-related subjects are being investigated at the present time in a quantitative and qualitative way and analyzes this information to know what possible answers clinical research could give us in the future. Methods: The data collection was carried out in April 2014 and was based on 3 sources: 2 institutional clinical trials registries &#151;American (clinicaltrials.gov) and European (EU Clinical Trials Register)&#151; and a survey given to members of the Asociación Española de Coloproctología (AECP). The obtained studies were exported to a database designed especially for this review, which included a number of descriptive elements that would allow the cataloging of the different studies. The AECP survey results were analyzed separately. Results: There are currently 216 clinical trials ongoing related to CR. Two-thirds are primarily conducted by oncologists. Nearly a third are surgical. The research focuses on improving preoperative treatment: new drugs, new schemes of chemo-radiotherapy (usually induction or consolidation schemes) or optimization of radiotherapy and its effects. Surgical clinical trials are related to robotics, laparoscopy, stoma, low colorectal anastomosis, distal CR and local treatment. Conclusion: Most of the current clinical trials ongoing on CR are analyzing aspects of chemo-radiotherapy and its effects. A third focus on purely surgical issues (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blesa Sierra, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Duarte, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Porcel, Orlando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidaña Márquez, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado Cobian, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Márquez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Gil, Francisco A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belda Lozano, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La evidencia clínica tiene más peso en las especialidades médicas que en las quirúrgicas. El cáncer de recto (CR) no es una excepción. En este artículo, nos hemos planteado explorar de forma cuantitativa y cualitativa, qué cuestiones y materias relacionadas con el CR están siendo investigadas en el momento actual y, posteriormente, analizar esta información para conocer qué respuestas podrá darnos la investigación clínica en el futuro.  Métodos: La obtención de datos se realizó en abril de 2014 y se basó en 3 fuentes: 2 registros institucionales de ensayos clínicos, &#151;el registro americano (clinicaltrials.gov) y el registro europeo (EU Clinical Trials Register) &#151; y una encuesta realizada a través de la Asociación Española de Coloproctología (AECP). Los estudios obtenidos fueron exportados a una base de datos diseñada especialmente para esta revisión, en la que se incluyeron además una serie de elementos descriptivos que permitieran la catalogación de los estudios. Los resultados de la encuesta AECP fueron analizados de forma separada. Resultados: Hay actualmente en marcha 216 estudios referidos al CR. Dos tercios son fundamentalmente oncológicos. Casi un tercio son quirúrgicos. Las líneas de investigación se centran en la mejora del tratamiento preoperatorio: nuevos fármacos, nuevos esquemas de quimiorradioterapia (generalmente de inducción o consolidación) u optimización de la radioterapia y sus efectos. Los ensayos clínicos quirúrgicos estudian aspectos relacionados con robótica, laparoscopia, estomas, anastomosis bajas, CR distal y tratamiento local.  Conclusiones: La mayoría de los estudios actuales sobre CR analizan aspectos relacionados con la quimiorradioterapia y sus efectos. Un tercio se centran en temas especialmente quirúrgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(6): 381-389, jun.-jul. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué se investiga en cáncer de recto?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52527^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54677^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
