<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047232</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A description of semantic memory performance in a sample of the antioquian  population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Available treatments for Alzheimer disease allow that early diagnosis become an important issue,because treatment only are useful during the earliest stage, especially during the mild cognitive impairment (MCI), when themost of the cognitive function is preserved. Aim. To observe the performance on a shortened version of a Semantic Cue RecallMemory Test (SCRMT) from a group of adult aged over 50 years old, living in Medellín city and with dementia of Alzheimertype (DAT). Subjects and methods. The sample was constituted by 30 patients with DAT, 30 with MCI, and 59 healthy controls,which were matched by socio economic strata and school achievement. The SCRMT was administered to the sample. For theanalyses two groups of age (50-69 and over 70 years) were conformed. Results. Comparisons statistically significant differencesbetween the groups (p &lt; 0.05). The scores were not significant affected by age. A combination of low scores with the presenceof intrusions on the free, immediate cue, and delay cue recalls suggested the diagnosis of DAT, which allow recommending acomplete neuropsychological assessment. Statistically significant differences were preserved when the groups were divided byage. The effect of the gender could not determine because the small size of the male sample. Conclusion. The shortened versionof the SCMRT would appear be useful for the DAT diagnosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Acevedo, D. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda, D. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboleda-Ramírez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara-Useche, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henao-Arboleda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La existencia de tratamientos para retardarla evolución de la demencia tipo Alzheimer (DTA) hace que ladetección temprana sea importante, ya que estos tratamientos sonefectivos si se inician cuando la mayoría de las funciones cognitivasaún están preservadas, o en la etapa de deterioro cognitivo leve(DCL). Objetivo. Observar la ejecución en la versión abreviada dela prueba de memoria semántica con clave (MSC), para el diagnósticode demencias de un grupo de adultos mayores de 50 añosdel área metropolitana de Medellín. Sujetos y métodos. La muestraestuvo formada por 30 pacientes con DTA, 30 con DCL y 59 controles;se emparejaron por estrato socioeconómico y escolaridad.Se les aplicó la prueba abreviada de MSC, y se formaron dos subgrupos:uno de 50 a 69 años, y otro de 70 años en adelante. Resultados.La comparación de las puntuaciones en la prueba entre lostres grupos arrojó diferencias estadísticamente significativas (p &lt;0,05). El desempeño no se modificó con la edad. La combinaciónde bajas puntuaciones con la presencia de intrusiones en la evocaciónlibre, diferida y con clave sugiere el diagnóstico de DTA, lo quejustificaría una evaluación neuropsicológica detallada. Al estratificarla muestra por edad las diferencias continuaron siendo significativas.El efecto del sexo no se pudo observar por el bajo númerode participantes de sexo masculino. Conclusión. La versión abreviadade la MSC parece ser útil para detectar sospechas de DTA</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(5): 272-276, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047232</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción del desempeño en memoria semántica en una muestra de la población antioqueña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
