<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111957</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic Nissen fundoplication surgery ambulatory: descriptive  observational study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: prospective evaluation of the feasibility of a programm of outpatient laparoscopic Nissen Fundoplication (OLNF) in patients undergoing antirre&amp;#64258;ux surgery for gastroesophageal re&amp;#64258;ux disease (GORD) at Institute of Gastrointestinal Surgery from the Quiron Hospital at Valencia. Methods: prospective observational study of 67 consecutive patients undergoing OLNF in intention to treat analysis. Main ambulatory surgical index, non planned admission, ambulatorization index, over-night stay requierements and demographics with GORD classi&amp;#64257;cation with REFA scale are reviewed. A comparative analysis of analgesic compsuntiom and daily activities recovery was performed comparing a paired group of patients undergoing ambulatory laparoscopic cholecystectomy (ALC) and those who underwent OLNF. Results: mean postoperative stay in outpatients was 5.65 ± 1.25 hours. Ambulatorization was achieved in 47.8% with a non planned admission index of 56.2%. Re-admissions were recorded in 3.1% and non scheduled visits reached 9.4%. The most frequent reason for admission was due to social reasons (55.6%), followed by inadecuated discharge time in 29.6%. Outpatients showed mean age and mean surgical time lower than admitted patients and also a more advanced GORD. In terms of pain, analgesic comsumption and daily activities recovery OLNF achieved better results than ALC. Conclussion: our results show that OLNF is a feasible procedure with long term results similar to traditional in hospital operations with a better result in terms of pain, analgesic compsumtion and recovery of daily activities in comparison with ALC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Espinosa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Vicente, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanahuja Santafé, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrau Giner, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planells Roig, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal Bertomeu, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Delgado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la factibilidad del desarrollo de un programa de fundoplicatura de Nissen laparoscópica ambulatoria (FNLA) en pacientes sometidos a cirugía antirre&amp;#64258;ujo por enfermedad por re&amp;#64258;ujo gastroesofágico (ERGE) en el Instituto de Cirugía y Aparato Digestivo de la Clínica Quirón de Valencia. Material y método: estudio descriptivo observacional de 67 pacientes consecutivos sometidos a FNLA analizados en intención de tratamiento. Se analizan los índices principales de cirugía mayor ambulatoria, ingresos no planeados, reingresos, tasa de ambulatorización, porcentaje de estancia over-night e in&amp;#64258;uencia de los factores demográ&amp;#64257;cos y clasi&amp;#64257;cación de la ERGE. Resultados: la estancia postoperatoria media en los pacientes ambulatorios fue de 5,65 ± 1,25 horas, el índice de ambulatorización fue de 47,8%, con un porcentaje de ingresos no planeados de 56,2%. La tasa de reingresos fue de 3,1%, con un porcentaje de consultas no plani&amp;#64257;cadas de 9,4%. La causa más frecuente de ingreso no esperado fue la social (55,6%) seguida de la hora de alta inadecuada (29,6%). Los pacientes ambulatorios presentaron edad media y duración de intervención signi&amp;#64257;cativamente inferior a los del grupo con ingreso, así como una ERGE más avanzada. Conclusiones: los resultados de nuestro estudio muestran que la FNLA es un procedimiento factible, seguro, con resultados a largo plazo similares a los obtenidos con hospitalización convencional y una mayor tolerancia para el paciente respecto a la CLA en términos de dolor, consumo de analgésicos y recuperación de las actividades diarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;17(4): 126-133, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fundoplicatura Nissen laparoscópica ambulatoria: estudio prospectivo observacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32242^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
