<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83966</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to bullying in adolescents in Barcelona (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesViolence and bullying in the school setting are a serious social and health problem that have created great alarm in the last few years. We aimed to describe bullying and factors related to this phenomenon in students in the city of Barcelona.MethodsWe performed a cross-sectional study of a representative sample of 2,727 students from 66 secondary schools in Barcelona. Bullying was defined as having been laughed at, hit or marginalized four or more times, or as having been the target of all three of these behaviors at least once, in the last 12 months. To analyze the associations among bullying and related factors including sociodemographic variables, attitudes and behaviors, we used bivariate and multivariate logistic regression.ResultsThe prevalence of bullying was 18.2%, 10.9% and 4.3% in boys and 14.4%, 8.5% and 4.5% in girls in the 8th, 10th and 12th grades, respectively. Factors associated with an increased likelihood of being bullied were negative mood states and violent behavior, while being older, alcohol consumption, cannabis use and going to bars and discos were negatively associated with being bullied.ConclusionsThis study confirms that bullying is a serious problem in our context and identifies certain factors, such as negative mood states and other risk behaviors. These factors should be further analyzed in longitudinal studies in order to design and implement appropriate prevention programs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcia Continente, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nebot Adell, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Giménez, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosLa violencia y el acoso escolar constituyen un problema social y de salud que ha generado una gran alarma en los últimos años. En este estudio se describe el acoso escolar y los factores relacionados en estudiantes de Barcelona.MétodosEstudio transversal de una muestra representativa de 2.727 estudiantes de 66 centros escolares de secundaria de Barcelona. Se definió «acoso escolar» como haber sido objeto de burla, golpeado o marginado cuatro o más veces, o al menos una vez en cada uno de los ítems, en los últimos 12 meses. Se realizó un análisis de regresión logística bivariado y multivariado para estudiar la relación entre el acoso y diversos factores, incluyendo variables sociodemográficas, actitudes y comportamientos.ResultadosLa prevalencia de acoso escolar fue del 18,2%, 10,9% y 4,3% en chicos, y del 14,4%, 8,5% y 4,5% en chicas de 2° y 4° de educación secundaria obligatoria y 2° de bachillerato o ciclos formativos de grado medio, respectivamente. Los factores que se asociaron con un incremento de la probabilidad de padecer acoso fueron el estado de ánimo negativo y la conducta violenta, mientras que tener mayor edad, el consumo de riesgo de alcohol, el consumo de cannabis e ir a bares y discotecas se asociaron negativamente.ConclusionesLos resultados confirman la relevancia del problema del acoso escolar en nuestro medio, y señalan diversos factores asociados, como el estado de ánimo negativo y varios comportamientos de riesgo, que deberían ser analizados con detalle en estudios longitudinales para diseñar e implementar programas preventivos apropiados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(2): 103-108, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con el acoso escolar (bullying) en los adolescentes de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
