<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045528</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endometriosis in a laparotomic scar after cesarean section: Report of two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Extrapelvic endometriosis in an abdominal wall surgical scar is a rare entity that is difficult to diagnose. However, it should be suspected in any woman of childbearing age complaining of a cyclic painful nodule in a scar from a previous obstetric or gynecologic procedure, after excluding other conditions such as incisional hernia, late abscess, or suture granuloma. Fine-needle aspiration biopsy provides an accurate preoperative diagnosis. Imaging studies such as ultrasound, computed tomography, or magnetic resonance imaging are non-specific, but may be helpful in identifying the exact anatomical location of the lesion and in excluding other surgical conditions. We present two cases of endometriosis in an abdominal wall scar that developed after cesarean section performed 7 years previously. In both patients, preoperative diagnosis, based on clinical suspicion in the first patient and aspiration cytology in the second, was correct. Wide local excision was curative in both patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>José A Carrasquer, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ángel L Custardoy, Ángel L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gambó, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujala, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalta, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La endometriosis extrapelviana, localizada en incisiones de la pared abdominal, es una entidad poco frecuente que puede plantear dificultades diagnósticas. No obstante, en la población femenina premenopáusica, la presencia de un nódulo cíclicamente doloroso y situado en el espesor de una cicatriz laparotómica, por anteriores procedimientos obstétricos o ginecológicos, debe resultar sospechoso de dicha complicación, una vez excluidos otros procesos más comunes como eventraciones, abscesos tardíos o granulomas por suturas. El diagnóstico de certeza preoperatorio puede hacerse mediante punción-aspiración con aguja fina del nódulo, mientras que la mayoría de pruebas de imagen sólo contribuyen a su localización anatómica y al cribado de hernia incisional. Presentamos 2 casos de endometriosis de pared abdominal desarrollados 7 años después de cesárea. En ambos se orientó el diagnóstico preoperatorio, por sospecha clínica en el primero y por examen citológico del aspirado en el segundo. La extirpación quirúrgica, con márgenes de resección suficientes, fue resolutiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(5): 313-315, mayo  2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis en la cicatriz de una cesárea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36499^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
