<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129474</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological performance and demographiccharacteristics in alcoholic patients in treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study compared the cognitive performance of alcoholics (AG) and participants from the general population (CG) without alcohol dependence. The sample consisted of 141 men, aged 18 and 59. Divided into two groups, 101 alcoholic patients without comorbidities, hospitalized for drug abuse treatment, and 40 healthy individuals from the general population, matched for age and socioeconomic status. The instruments assessed the sociodemographics data and economic classification, alcohol dependence, psychiatric comorbidities, cognitive performance, executive functions, memory and perception. The results showed that the AG group presented severe dependence on alcohol and 92.1% indicated having a family with problems associated with alcohol for only 41.5 % of the CG. At the moment of the evaluation, 59.4 % of the participants of the AG group were abstinent between 8 and 15 days, and the in CG, 43.9%, were more than 60 days alcohol free. The neuropsychological performance verified that there was a decline in cognitive functions in alcoholics&#146; participants, whereas the AG suggests psychomotor retardation. Thus, it can be inferred that alcohol greatly affects cognitive functions of people who depend on this substance. In addition, there was a greater number of family stories with prevalence of symptoms of anxiety and depression and nicotine addiction in alcoholic patients compared with the general population (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Rigoni, Maisa dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliz Duarte de Moraes, João Feliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quarti Irigaray, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrão, Ygor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Oliveira, Margareth da</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio comparó el desempeño cognitivo de sujetos alcohólicos (GA) y de participantes de la población general (GC) sin la dependencia del alcohol. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 141 hombres, con edad entre 18 y 59 años. Divididos en dos grupos, 101 pacientes alcohólicos sin comorbilidades, internados para el tratamiento de la dependencia química, y 40 sujetos de la población general sin dependencia, emparejados por edad y nivel socioeconómico. Los instrumentos utilizados evaluarán los datos socio-demográficos y la clasificación económica, la dependencia del alcohol, las comorbilidades psiquiátricas, el desempeño cognitivo, las funciones ejecutivas, la memoria y la percepción. Los resultados mostraron que el grupo dos GA denota dependencia grave en relación al alcohol y el 92,1% indican tener algún familiar con problemas asociados al alcohol; para el GC, el 41,5% afirmaron este dato. En el GA 59,4% estaban abstinentes entre 8 y 15 días, en la evaluación, y en el GC el 43,9%, lo estaban más de 60 días. En el desempeño neuropsicológico, fue verificado que había una disminución de las funciones cognitivas en los participantes alcohólicos, siendo que el GA sugiere un enlentecimiento psicomotor. Así, se puede inferir que el alcohol afecta en gran medida las funciones cognitivas de las personas que dependen de esta sustancia. Además, hubo un mayor número de historias familiares con prevalencia de síntomas de ansiedad y depresión y de adicción a la nicotina en pacientes alcohólicos en comparación con la población general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);26(3): 221-229, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desempeño neuropsicológico y características sociodemográficas en pacientes alcohólicos en tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d436^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
