<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90031</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement in health care quality for patients from the thoracic/chest pain unit in a regional hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The evaluation of an improvement cycle in patients suffering thoracic/chest pain in hospital emergencies, especially in those who could benefit from the early Bruce Treadmill Test. Material and methods. A multidisciplinary group care protocol was designed, which identified improvement opportunities and gave priority to the fact that «an early Bruce Treadmill Test was carried out on fewer occasions than recommended». Causes were analysed (Ishikawa diagram) and six quality criteria were defined. These criteria were evaluated in a random sample of 30 patients out of the total of 180 who used the ergometer at the Hospital in the first six months of 2007, as well as questionnaire for the doctors. Corrective measures were introduced: circulation, accessibility through intranet and explicit information for new employees (doctors). The second evaluation was carried out during the first six-months of 2008 using another random sample of 30 patients from a total of 120. Results. In the first evaluation, the classification of the risk according to the protocol was very low (100% non-compliance) and patients whose admission to the Chest Pain Unit was recommended and an early Bruce Treadmill Test (74% criteria failure) were referred to cardiology clinics. After implementation of the corrective measures, we obtain a general improvement in all the criteria, but very significant from the previous ones, with non-compliances being reduced to 17% in classification and to the 23% in referrals. Conclusions. The structured cycle has helped resolve the priority problem in the short-term. The adopted measures have mainly been organisational, dependent on the professionals involved, and at a very low cost. Simple but organised methodological approaches should be taken into account before the incorporation of higher cost technologies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellano Ortega, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rus Mansilla, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero de Castilla, R. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortez Quiroga, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayona Gómez, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duran Torralba, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar un ciclo de mejora en pacientes con dolor torácico en urgencias hospitalarias, especialmente los que se benefician de la realización de test de isquemia precoz en nuestro entorno. Material y métodos. Se diseñó un protocolo de atención por grupo multidisciplinario que identifica oportunidades de mejora y prioriza abordar que «la realización de test de isquemia de forma precoz era menor que lo recomendado». Se analizan las causas (diagrama de Ishikawa) y se definen seis criterios de calidad. Se evaluaron estos en una muestra aleatoria de 30 pacientes del total a los que se realizó ergometría en el hospital en el primer semestre de 2007 (n=180) y con encuesta a facultativos. Se introdujeron medidas correctivas: difusión, accesibilidad en intranet, información explícita a nuevos facultativos. La segunda evaluación se realizó durante el primer semestre de 2008 en otra muestra similar de 30 pacientes (n=120). Resultados. En la primera evaluación la clasificación de riesgo según protocolo fue muy baja (incumplimiento del 100%) y se derivaba a consultas de cardiología a pacientes subsidiarios de ingreso en la unidad de dolor torácico y test de isquemia precoz (incumplimiento del criterio del 74%). Tras medidas correctivas, se obtiene una mejora general, pero muy significativa en los anteriores, reduciendo incumplimientos al 17% en clasificación y el 23% en derivaciones. Conclusiones. El ciclo estructurado ha facilitado la solución del problema priorizado en un plazo corto. Las medidas adoptadas han sido fundamentalmente organizativas, dependientes de los profesionales y con coste muy bajo. Enfoques sencillos pero con metodología ordenada deben valorarse antes de la incorporación de tecnologías de mayor coste(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(4): 242-250, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la calidad asistencial a los pacientes de la unidad de dolor torácico de un hospital comarcal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30118^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
