<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038853</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of 107 Spanish Healthcare Registries and Evaluation of the Utilization Thereof</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The information concerning the currently- existinghealthcare registries in our country is not readily accessible, is scarceand some are not well-known, possibly being underused in comparisonto their many potential uses. This study is aimed at evaluating thecharacteristics of the Spanish Healthcare registries and the utilizationthereof, especially in Healthcare technology assessment.Methods: Descriptive, cross-sectional study of the SpanishHealthcare registries within the 1997-2002 period. These registrieswere identified by means of a bibliographic databases search and byway of a survey of Scientific Societies and Central and AutonomicHealthcare Administration. Another bibliographic databases searchwas conducted of the publications which use data from the healthcareregistries included and have been evaluated by applying the scientificevidence quality criteria.Results: A total of 107 healthcare registries were identified,most of which of local or regional coverage (71%), preferably wereunder Autonomic government authority (64.5%). The areas showingthe largest number of registries identified were those related to deathstatistics (16.8%) and cancer (15.9%). A total of 298 publicationswere retrieved which analyze data produced by the registries identified,most of which are devoted to the study of the frequency and distributionof the events recorded (58.1%) and less frequently to theconducting of healthcare technology assessment studies (24.4%).Conclusions: The critical evaluation of the publications made itpossible to identify some elements related to the analysis methodologyand design which would heighten the quality of the healthcaretechnology assessment. Healthcare registries in Spain have developedrecently and to differing degrees. Important areas without anyrecords and improvement elements related to the use of healthcareregistries for healthcare technology assessment were detected. Itwould be advisable to avail of a register of registries which wouldprovide relevant, up-dated information thereon</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gol Freixa, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Imaz Iglesia, Iñaki </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aibar Remón, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez López, Luis Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Enríquez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La información sobre los registros sanitarios existentesen nuestro país es poco accesible y escasa y algunos son pococonocidos, pudiendo estar infrautilizados en relación con sus múltiplesusos potenciales. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar las característicasde los Registros Sanitarios españoles y su utilización, especialmenteen Evaluación de Tecnologías Sanitarias.Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal de los Registros Sanitariosespañoles entre 1997 y 2002. La identificación de los registros serealizó a través de búsqueda bibliográfica y mediante encuesta a SociedadesCientíficas y Administración sanitaria central y autonómica. Seha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica específica de las publicacionesque utilizan datos de los registros sanitarios incluidos y se han evaluadoaplicando los criterios de calidad de la evidencia científica.Resultados: Se han identificado 107 registros sanitarios, preferentementede cobertura local o regional (71%) y dependientes en sumayoría de la Administración autonómica (64,5%). Las áreas conmayor número de registros identificados corresponden a la mortalidad(16,8%) y al cáncer (15,9%). Se han recuperado 298 publicacionesque analizan datos producidos por los registros identificados, delas que la mayoría se dedican al estudio de la frecuencia y distribuciónde los eventos registrados (58,1%) y con menor frecuencia a la realizaciónde estudios de evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias (24,4%).Conclusiones: La evaluación crítica de las publicaciones ha permitidoidentificar algunos elementos relacionados con el diseño y lametodología de análisis que incrementarían la calidad de los estudiosde evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias.Los registros sanitarios enEspaña han tenido un desarrollo desigual y reciente. Se han detectadoáreas relevantes sin registros y elementos de mejora relacionadoscon la utilización de los registros sanitarios para estudios de evaluaciónde tecnologías sanitarias. Sería recomendable contar con unregistro de registros que proporcionara información relevante yactualizada sobre los mismos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(1): 17-34, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038853</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de 107 registros sanitarios españoles y valoración de su utilización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
