<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155933</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivation and incentives at work in nursing management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From the hypothesis that the exclusive use of monetary incentives may undermine intrinsic motivation of health professionals, causing the opposite effect to that intended, this paper analyzes the factors that are associated with intrinsic motivation of professionals responsible for nursing management. To this end, we designed a questionnaire on Work Motivation in Nursing Management based on Intrinsic Motivation Inventory (IMI), which was distributed at the National Conference of Supervisors of Nursing (Bilbao, 2010). After analyzing the results, we obtained a motivational profile that can guide health managers in the redesign of a system of incentives that, aligned with professional values, influence the efficient performance of health workers, and to invest in a new type of capital that we call 'motivational capital'(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabasés Hita, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Laraña, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Errea Rodríguez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez Iriarte, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir de la hipótesis de que la utilización exclusiva de incentivos monetarios puede minar la motivación intrínseca de los profesionales sanitarios y producir el efecto contrario al perseguido, este trabajo analiza los factores que se asocian con la motivación intrínseca de los profesionales responsables de gestión en enfermería. Para ello, se elaboró un cuestionario sobre Motivación en el Trabajo de Gestión en Enfermería basado en el Intrinsic Motivation Inventory (IMI), que se distribuyó en las Jornadas Nacionales de Supervisoras de Enfermería (Bilbao, 2010). Tras el análisis de los resultados, se obtiene un perfil motivacional que puede orientar a los gestores sanitarios en el rediseño de un sistema de incentivos que, alineado con los valores profesionales, influya en el comportamiento eficiente de los agentes sanitarios, y a invertir en un nuevo tipo de capital que denominamos 'capital motivaciona'(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(9): 579-586, sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incentivos y motivación en el trabajo de gestión en enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4725^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9903</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
