<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129735</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological and emocional distress in immigrant homeless</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most research on social exclusion has focused on psychopathology and some other variables had been little studied. The article explores the relationship between psychological and emotional distress with sociodemographic variables, acculturative stress, social support, substance abuse , stressful life events and changes of identity in a sample of 107 homeless migrants. This has been made interviews and self-reports exploring the relationships between variables using various techniques of data analysis. The results show the importance of material resources in psychological wellbeing, and the high influence of stressful life events experienced by the person, the social support, and other variables related to the experience of social exclusion such as dehumanization, lack of control over their own lives and changes in the identity. All of which leads us to reflect on how psychology and psychiatry approaches the study of social problems, giving too much emphasis to psychopathologi (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Lashayas, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de la investigación en torno a la exclusión social se ha centrado en psicopatología y poco se han estudiado otras variables. El artículo muestra las relaciones entre el sufrimiento psicológico y malestar emocional con variables sociodemográficas, estrés aculturativo, apoyo social, abusos de sustancias, sucesos vitales estresantes y cambios en la identidad en una muestra de 107 personas migrantes sin hogar. Para ello se han realizado entrevistas en profundidad y autoinformes analizando las relaciones entre las variables mediante diversas técnicas de análisis de datos. Los resultados muestran la importancia de los recursos materiales en el bienestar psicológico, así como la alta influencia de los sucesos vitales estresantes sufridos por la persona, el apoyo social recibido y otras variables vinculadas con la experiencia de exclusión social como la deshumanización, la falta de control sobre la propia vida y los cambios identitarios. Todo ello nos debe llevar a reflexionar sobre la manera que desde la psicología y psiquiatrías nos acercamos al estudio de los problemas sociales, dando un excesivo énfasis al diagnóstico psicopatológico en perjuicio de otras variables importantes como las citadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(124): 711-723, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sufrimiento psicológico y malestar emocional en las personas migrantes sin hogar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55089^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19640^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19640^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
