<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128391</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human dignity revisited</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since World War II, human dignity has made its way into many constitutions, bills of rights and international treaties. As its roots can be traced easily back to the Judeo-Christian tradition, and, later on, tothe influential Kantian vision, dignity cannot be deemed an entirely new concept. For the same token, it cannot be said that dignity has been entirely alien to the legal realm till 1945. On the other hand, the latestphilosophical and anthropological trends, as well as the politicisation of the human being, along with  some recent advances in biotechnologies, help to explain its growing presence in the legal world. However, these authors suggest that writing down dignity in legal texts does not fully settle its meaning &#151;not even if such texts are constitutions&#151; and the fact remains that its presence in the judicial reasoning does not always imply being the ratio decidendi, as the study of some relevant judicial decisions shows (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereira Menaut, Antonio Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Sáez, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De la Segunda Guerra Mundial en adelante, la dignidad humana es recogida en muchas constituciones, declaraciones de derechos y tratados internacionales. Esto no significa que sea un concepto nuevo, pues su significado puede rastrearse sin dificultad en la tradición judeo-cristiana y, mucho más tarde, en la influyente comprensión kantiana; y tampoco significa que no haya tenido relación con el Derecho antes de 1945. Por otro lado, las nuevas tendencias filosóficas y antropológicas así como la politización del hombre, junto con los avances de la técnica, explican su presencia cada vez mayor en el Derecho. Sin embargo, la inclusión de la dignidad en los textos jurídicos no es capaz de agotar su significado &#151;ni aunque los textos sean los constitucionales&#151;, y el hecho de que los jueces la aleguen no significa que la empleen realmente como criterio para su decisión, como puede verse al estudiar algunas sentencias relevantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;25(84): 231-242, mayo-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">De nuevo sobre la dignidad humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6960</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3268</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
