<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131667</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital nasal obstruction due to pyriform aperture stenosis. A case series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nasal obstruction in neonates is a potentially fatal condition due to their exclusive nasal breathing. The main cause is inflammatory or infectious rhinitis. Congenital, neoplastic,  traumatic or iatrogenic causes are less frequent. Choanal atresia is the most common congenital nasal anomaly. A less common etiology of congenital nasal obstruction is pyriform aperture stenosis. Suspicion might arise in any newborn with varying degrees of stridor and respiratory distress, associated with the difficulty of passing a probe through anterior nares. Diagnosis should be confirmed by a computed tomography of the craniofacial massif. The therapeutic approach will depend on the severity of symptoms. We describe our experience with 5 patients with this condition, treated surgically using a sub-labial approach, and followed by nasal stenting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Demarchi, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boccio, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Razetti, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuestas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>José, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obstrucción de las fosas nasales en el neonato es un cuadro potencialmente fatalpor su respiración nasal obligada. La causa principal es inflamatoria o infecciosa, y con menor  frecuencia puede ser de origen congénito, neoplásico, traumático o iatrogénico. La atresia de coanas es la anomalía congénita nasal más común. Una etiología menos frecuente de obstrucción nasal congénita es la estenosis de la apertura piriforme. Debe pensarse en esta última en todo recién nacido con cornaje y dificultad respiratoria de grado variable, asociado a la dificultad de pasar una sonda a través de la región anterior de las fosas nasales. El diagnóstico se confirma por tomografía computarizada del macizo craneofacial. La conducta terapéutica dependerá de la gravedad de los síntomas. Describimos nuestra experiencia con 5 pacientes que presentaban esta afección, tratados quirúrgicamente mediante abordaje sublabial y colocación de tutor nasal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e44-e47, ene. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obstrucción nasal congénita por estenosis de la apertura piriforme. Serie de casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23484^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23484^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
