<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141516</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Total dystrophic onychomycosis in both feet by Tricophyton rubrum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Onychomycosis is an uncommon condition in children. When it appears, it usually affects toenails, mainly the first and fifth toenails, and occasionally it is associated to tinea pedis. We report a case of total dystrophic onychomycosis by Tricophyton rubrum in both feet in a male patient seven years old, with favorable outcome after systemic and topical treatment. The interest of this case report lies in the low prevalence of onychomycosis at this age, as well as in an uncommon (total dystrophic) clinical presentation. Fungal isolation is sometimes challenging, but the culture proved positive in this case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellares González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Alonso, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Deyros, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las onicomicosis son una patología infrecuente en la edad pediátrica. De presentarse, suelen afectar a las uñas de los pies, principalmente a las uñas del primer y quinto dedo, y ocasionalmente se asocia a una tinea pedis. Presentamos un caso de onicomicosis distrófica total por Tricophyton rubrum en ambos pies en un paciente varón de siete años, con evolución favorable tras tratamiento sistémico y tópico. El interés del caso radica en la baja prevalencia de las onicomicosis en esta franja etaria, así como una presentación clínica (distrófica total) poco frecuente. El aislamiento de las levaduras es, en ocasiones, dificultoso, pero en este caso el cultivo resultó positivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;17(67): 251-253, jul.-sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Onicomicosis distrófica total en ambos pies por Tricophyton rubrum</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9453^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9453^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9451^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31378^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9451^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
