<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121795</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The moderating role of professional self-efficacy in situations of workplace bullying and self-perceived health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Self-efficacy is a personal competence stressors acts against in-creasing or decreasing the psychological discomfort they may generate, meanwhile workplace bullying or mobbing is one of the psychosocial work environment factors more damaging to the health of workers. Using as a framework the theoretical JD-R, this paper's main objective is to analyze the moderating role of professional self-efficacy between workplace bullying and perceived health status in a multi-occupational sample of 772 workers (379 men and 383 women). An anonymous questionnaire to workers was administered in active-duty after analyzing the data provided by the scale of workplace mobbing NAQ, Questionnaire GHQ-12 for the evaluation of the health and professional self-efficacy of the MBI. The result highlights the moderating role of self-efficacy on health in workplace bullying situations. To these work results of and its possible implication in the organizations are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meseguer, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Izquierdo, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La autoeficacia es una competencia personal que actúa frente a los estresores incrementando o disminuyendo el malestar psicológico que estos pueden generar; por su parte el acoso psicológico o mobbing es uno de los factores psicosociales del medio laboral más dañinos para la salud de los trabajadores. Utilizando como marco de referencia el modelo teórico de demandas-recursos (JD-R model), este trabajo tiene como objetivo principal analizar el papel moderador de la autoeficacia profesional entre el acoso laboral y la salud autopercibida en una muestra multiocupacional de 772 trabajadores (379 hombres y 383 mujeres). Se administró un protocolo que contenía la escala NAQ para la medida del acoso laboral, el cuestionario de salud GHQ-12 y la subescala de autoeficacia profesional del MBI. Como resultado destaca el papel moderador de la autoeficacia sobre la salud en situaciones de acoso psicológico. Se discuten los resultados de este trabajo, las limitaciones y sus posibles implicaciones en las organizaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(2): 573-578, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel moderador de la autoeficacia profesional entre situaciones de acoso laboral y la salud en una muestra multiocupacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
