<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042987</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiple sclerosis in Peru. A clinical-epidemiological description of a series of patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In Peru up to recent years multiple sclerosis (MS) was considered a very rare disorder. Aim. To report clinical, epidemiological and ancillary test results of an MS cases series. Patients and methods. Description of a retrospective cohort of 55 patients studied in HNCH and a private neurological center in Lima between 1993-2004. Clinical records, laboratory and MRI tests were reviewed with Mc Donald&#146;s criteria. Results. There were 55 cases (36 women). Mean age was        forty. 65% were born in Lima, 27% have foreign ancestor up to third generation. 42 cases were definite MS and 13 possible MS. The most frequent form of MS was RRMS (49.1%). Early symptoms were optic neuritis, motor and sensitive complaints; in the follow up cerebelar symptoms, increase of motor compromise and sphincteric disturbance were showed. Brain and        spine MRI were positive in 27 cases and 17 cases respectively. VEP were abnormal in 53% of cases, just one case had cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) compatible with MS. Mode of EDSS was 6.5. Immunomodulators were used in 30% of cases. Survival at 10 and 20 years of disease were 87% and 45% respectively. Conclusion. Our study shows than optic neuritis is an important        early symptom and CSF study is commonly negative in patients with MS. Survival is shorter than other reports. Other features resembled previous international reports. To have foreign ancestors could be a risk factor for MS in this group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vizcarra-Escobar, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tipismana-Barbarán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cava-Prado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En Perú, hasta hace algunos años se consideraba        que la esclerosis múltiple (EM) era una condición inusual.        Objetivo. Descripción clínica, epidemiológica, de laboratorio        y control clínico de una serie de casos. Pacientes y métodos.        Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de un grupo de pacientes con        diagnóstico propuesto de EM atendidos en el Hospital Nacional        Cayetano Heredia y en un centro neurológico privado, entre 1993 y        2004, cuyos registros e información paraclínica se revisaron con        criterios de McDonald. Resultados. Se incluyeron 55 casos (36 mujeres).        El promedio de edad fue de 40 años; 27% tuvo ascendencia        extranjera hasta la tercera generación. 42 casos fueron EM definida        y 13 EM posible. La forma más frecuente de EM fue esclerosis        múltiple remitente recurrente (49,1%). Los síntomas de inicio fueron        neuritis óptica, afección motora y sensitiva; en el curso de la        enfermedad aparecieron síntomas cerebelosos, acentuación de los        motores y afectación de esfínteres. Se encontraron lesiones en resonancia        magnética en la mitad, y un tercio de los estudios de encéfalo        y médula, respectivamente. Sólo un líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR)        fue compatible con EM. La discapacidad evaluada por EDSS (Expanded        Disability Status Scale) tuvo una moda de 6,5. El 30% recibió        terapia inmunomoduladora. Las supervivencias a 10 y 25 años        fueron 87 y 45%, respectivamente. Conclusión. Nuestra serie muestra        características clinicoepidemiológicas similares a la literatura        mundial, a excepción de los marcadores en LCR, inicio más frecuente        con neuritis óptica y menor supervivencia. La ascendencia        extranjera podría ser un factor de riesgo para EM en este grupo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(10): 591-595, nov. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esclerosis múltiple en Perú. Descripción clinicoepidemiológica de una serie de pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
