<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164126</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Investigation on the endemic characteristics of Metorchis orientalis in Huainan area, China</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the endemic characteristics of Metorchis orientalis (M. orientalis) in the Huainan area, Anhui province, China. Methods: The first-intermediate host, second-intermediate host and reservoir hosts were collected, and the endemic characteristics of M. orientalis were examined through field investigation and artificial infection. Results: Investigation was completed in 89 domestic ducks, 156 domestic chicken, 41 domestic geese, 20 domestic cats and 19 dogs. The infection rate of M. orientalis was 18.0% (16/89) in ducks, 12.2% (19/156) in chicken, 9. 8% (4/41) in geese, 5.0% (1/20) in cats and 5.3% (1/19) in dogs. Sixty-seven cercariae of M. orientalis were identified in 1,000 Parafossarulus striatulus, with a natural infection rate of 6.7%, and 19 cercariae occurred in 300 Pseudorasbora parva, with a natural infection rate of 6.33%. The activity of the cercariae of M. orientalis was associated with light intensity and temperature. The full life cycle of M. orientalis ranged from 120 to 140 days; it occurred approximately in 89 days in snails, 28 days in fish and 20 days in ducks. Conclusion: M. orientalis is prevalent in the Huainan area, and it may complete its life cycle in Parafossarulus striatulus, Pseudorasbora parva and natively raised ducks</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Entao, Sun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuxia, Zhu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xiaodong, Zhan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hua, Wu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaopin, Li</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: investigar las características endémicas del Metorchis orientalis (M. orientalis) en el área de Huainan, en la provincia de Anhui, China. Métodos: fueron recogidos el primer huésped intermediario, el segundo huésped intermediario y el reservorio, y se examinaron las características endémicas del M. orientalis a través de investigación de campo e infección artificial. Resultados: la investigación se llevó a cabo en 89 patos domésticos, 156 gallinas domésticas, 41 gansos domésticos, 20 perros y 19 gatos domésticos. La tasa de infección del M. orientalis fue del 18,0% (16/89) en patos, 12,2% (19/156) en pollos, 9,8% (4/41) en gansos, 5,0% (1/20) en gatos y 5,3% (1/19) en perros. Sesenta y siete cercarias de M. orientalis fueron identificadas en 1.000 Parafossarulus striatulus, con una tasa de infección natural del 6,7%, y 19 en 300 Pseudorasbora parva, con una tasa de infección natural del 6,33%. La actividad de las cercarias de M. orientalis se asoció con la intensidad de la luz y la temperatura. El ciclo de vida completo del M. orientalis osciló entre 120 y 140 días, y se produjo aproximadamente en 89 días en caracoles, 28 días en peces y 20 días en patos. Conclusión: el M. orientalis es prevalente en el área de Huainan, y puede completar su ciclo de vida en Parafossarulus striatulus, Pseudorasbora parva y patos autóctonos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(3): 675-679, mayo-jun. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación sobre las características endémicas de Metorchis orientalis en Huainan, China</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10462^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1739^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33154^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33154^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1739^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10462^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
