<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120138</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What is personalistic bioethics?. An analysys of its specificity and its theoretical foundations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article try to analyze why, although personalistic bioethics is expanding, there are so few theoretical studies on its characteristics and identity, and concludes it is due to a problem of lack of specificity. Personalistic bioethicists rely either on movements or institutions that have a weak theoretical foundation or in the realist philosophy taken in a very broad sense, which generates a problem of internal inconsistency due to its great diversity. To solve this problem the author proposes: 1) be aware of the existence of this theoretical problem; 2) solve it through the use of personalistic philosophy understood as a particular philosophical school of the XX century. In this sense, the author proposes: 1) a detailed description of personalistic philosophy; 2) states that a particular version, the modern ontological personalism, developed from an anthropological point of view by Wojtyla, from a bioethical point of view by Sgreccia and from the theory of personalism by Burgos is the best choice to put the foundations of personalistic bioethics. The author concludes exposing the contributions and limits of this theory for personalistic bioethics, and the steps that should be followed to promote it and develop it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgos Velasco, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo se plantea porqué, a pesar de que la bioética personalista está en expansión, existan tan pocos trabajos teóricos sobre sus características e identidad, y concluye que se debe a un problema de falta de especificidad. Los bioéticos personalistas se apoyan o bien en movimientos o instituciones que tienen una base teórica débil o bien en la filosofía realista tomada en un sentido muy amplio, lo que genera un problema de inconsistencia interna debido a su gran diversidad. Para solventar este problema el autor propone: 1) ser consciente de la existencia de este problema de fundamentación; 2) resolverlo mediante el recurso a la filosofía personalista entendida como escuela filosófica concreta del siglo XX. En este sentido, el autor propone: 1) una descripción detallada de la filosofía personalista y, 2) postula que una versión concreta, el personalismo ontológico moderno, desarrollado desde un punto de vista antropológico por Wojtyla, bioético por Sgreccia y de teoría del personalismo por Burgos es la mejor opción para fundar la bioética personalista. Por último, concluye exponiendo las aportaciones y los límites que esta concreta teoría personalista tiene para la bioética personalista, así como los pasos que deberían seguirse para potenciarla y desarrollarla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;24(80): 17-30, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120138</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué es la bioética personalista?. Un análisis de su especificidad y de sus fundamentos teóricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36364</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
