<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72912</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Memory impairment in a sample of patients with chronic pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is relatively common that patients suffering fromchronic pain complain about memory loss and concentrationproblems. Traditionally, this fact has been connected withthe medication aimed at the management of pain, with thedepressed mood and with pain itself.AimsTo know whether the subjective complaints of memoryloss about which these patients complain can be found in theirperformance in neuropsychological tasks. Secondly, to studywhether there is any difference in such tasks between patientssuffering from chronic pain with depressed mood and thosewithout depressive symptomatology. Finally, to analyze ifthere is a relationship between the severity of the depressivesymptomatology and the performance in neuropsychologicaltasks that assess memory and attention.MethodIn order to fulfil the previous aims, we have carried out atransversal observational study. In this study, 21 patients withchronic pain and subjective complaints of memory loss referredby the Pain Unit of the &#147;Río Hortega&#148; University Hospitaltook part.ResultsOnly those patients suffering from chronic pain and depressedmood performed badly in neuropsychological tasks,especifically in the ones that assess memory in which attentionplays a major role. Finally, the data obtained in our studyrevealed that the more severe the depressive disorder was, themore the performance of the patients in the neuropsychologicaltasks got worse.DiscussionSubjective complaints of memory loss that these patientsstate seem to be related to the depressed mood from whichmany of them suffer. Memory impairment can be explained,at least partially, by the attentional deficit they suffer from(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Santos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Nieto, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Ladrón de Cegama, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEs relativamente frecuente que los pacientes con dolor crónicose quejen de problemas de memoria y concentración. Históricamente,este hecho se ha relacionado con la medicación dirigida al control del dolor, con el estado de ánimo y con elhecho de padecer dolor crónico.ObjetivosConocer si las quejas subjetivas de pérdida de memoria querefieren los pacientes se objetivan en su ejecución en pruebasneuropsicológicas. En segundo lugar, estudiar si hay algunadiferencia en el rendimiento en dichas pruebas entre pacientescon dolor crónico que presentan sintomatología depresivaasociada y aquellos que no presentan dicha sintomatología.Por último, analizar si existe alguna relación entre la intensidaddel episodio depresivo que padece el paciente con dolorcrónico y el rendimiento en pruebas neuropsicológicas queevalúan atención y memoria.MétodoSe trata de un estudio observacional transversal en el que participaronpacientes derivados por la Unidad de Dolor del HospitalUniversitario &#147;Del Río Hortega&#148; con problemas de dolorcrónico y queja subjetiva de pérdida de memoria.ConclusionesÚnicamente los pacientes con dolor crónico y depresión asociadatuvieron un rendimiento deficitario en pruebas neuropsicológicas,especialmente en tareas que evalúan memoria enlas que la atención juega un papel importante. Por último, losdatos de nuestro estudio revelan que a medida que la intensidaddel episodio depresivo que padece el paciente aumenta,el rendimiento del paciente en dichas pruebas empeora.DiscusiónLas quejas subjetivas de pérdida de memoria que refieren estospacientes parecen guardar relación con el estado de ánimodepresivo que muchos de ellos presentan. Las alteracionesmnésicas parecen explicarse, al menos en parte, por el déficitatencional que padecen(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(1): 5-12, ene.-feb. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit de memoria en una muestra de pacientes con dolor crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
