<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108167</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse effects of sasonal flu vaccine and new influenza a (H1N1) vaccine in health care workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To assess and compare adverse effects of Seasonal Influenza Vaccine (SIV) and new Influenza A(H1N1)Vaccine (AIV) in health care workers. Methods. Multicenter cross-sectional study in health care workers from acute care hospitals, primary health care centers, social centers, mental health centers and a geriatric hospital participating in the 2009 vaccination campaign. Self-administered questionnaires were sent to all workers vaccinated with SIV and/or AIV. Results. 527 valid questionnaires were collected out of 1123 sent to SIV vaccinated workers (46.9%), and 241 out of 461 sent to AIV vaccinated workers (52.5%). Participant workers include 527 vaccinated only with SIV, 117 first vaccinated with SIV and later with AIV (SIV+AIV), and 125 vaccinated only with AIV. Overall, 18.4% (95% CI 15.1-21.7) of workers vaccinated only with SIV reported adverse effects, as compared to 45.3% (95% CI 36.3-54.3) reporting adverse effects to AIV in the SIV+AIV group and 46.4% (95% CI 37.7-55.1) of workers vaccinated only with AIV. In all participants the most common adverse effect was a local reaction. Women were more reactive to both SIV and AIV than men. In all age groups SIV vaccination alone caused fewer reactions than either AIV only or the combination of SIV+AIV, with the exception of workers below 29 years of age. Conclusions. AIV was associated with more reactions than SIV, with no differences observed in relation to administration sequence. There were differences by sex and age, but reactions always occurred more commonly with AIV(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benito Carreras, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Besora Cunillera, Arnau</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Soto, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras Valls, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde Lozano, Judith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inglés Torruella, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Valorar y comparar los efectos indeseados de la vacuna de la gripe estacional (VGE) y vacuna de la gripe AH1N1 (VGA) en trabajadores sanitarios. Métodos. Estudio transversal multicéntrico en trabajadores sanitarios de hospitales de agudos, centros de asistencia primaria, centros sociosanitarios, centros de salud mental y un hospital geriátrico participantes en la campaña de vacunación antigripal del 2009. Se enviaron encuestas autocumplimentadas a todos los vacunados con VGE y/o VGA. Resultados. De los 1123 vacunados con VGE se obtienen 527 encuestas válidas (46,9%) y de 461 vacunados con VGA se obtienen 242 encuestas (52,5%). De los trabajadores participantes 527 estaban vacunados sólo con VGE, 117 vacunados previamente con VGE y después VGA (VGE+VGA) y 125 sólo vacunados sólo con VGA. El 18,4% (IC 95% 15,1-21,7) del grupo VGE presentaron algún efecto adverso a la vacuna VGE; en el grupo VGE+VGA el 45,3% (IC 95% 36,3-54,3) presentó una reacción adversa al recibir la VGA, y en el grupo VGA fue el  46,4% (IC 95% 37,7-55,1). En todos los participantes el problema más frecuente fue una reacción local. Las mujeres presentan mayor reacción a VGA y VGE que los hombres. Para todas las edades la VGE es menos reactógena que VGA y que la combinación de ambas vacunas, con la excepción de los trabajadores menores de 29 años. Conclusiones. La VGA es más reactógena que la VGE, sin diferencias por orden de administración. Se observan variaciones por sexo y edad, pero siempre con mayor reactogenicidad para la VGA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);16(1): 11-16, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108167</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacciones adversas de la vacuna de la gripe estacional y la vacuna de la gripe A H1N1 en personal sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
