<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103561</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aplasia of the posterior arches of the atlas: a presenation of 2 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Aplasia of the posterior arches of the atlas is an uncommon condition caused by a defect in their closure. It is usually associated with different syndromes. Case report. We present 2 asymptomatic patients with aplasia of C1 posterior bodies. Conclusions. Further studies are required on these lesions in order to take possible protection measures against trauma, and the selection between conservative or surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yáñez Calvo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano Romero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quinteiro Antolín, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La aplasia de los cuerpos posteriores del atlas es una afección poco frecuente, causada por un defecto en el cierre de los mismos. Habitualmente se asocia a diferentes síndromes. Casos clínicos. Presentamos 2 casos clínicos de pacientes asintomáticos con aplasia de los cuerpos posteriores del atlas. Conclusiones. Es necesario estudiar más a fondo este tipo de lesiones de cara a valorar la posibilidad de tomar medidas de protección ante traumatismos y escoger entre el tratamiento conservador y el quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(5): 381-384, sept.-oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplasia de los arcos posteriores del atlas: a propósito de 2 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1277^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1880^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1277^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
