<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116186</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Angiomatoid fibrous histiocytoma. A case report and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Angiomatoid fibrous histiocytoma is a mesenchymal neoplasm of intermediate grade malignancy which is most commonly found in the extremities of children and young adults. Its histogenesis is uncertain and its morphology is unusual as it is a circumscribed lesion with spindle cells, peripheral lymphoplasmacytic infiltrate, blood-filled cystic cavities and frequent desmin expression. We report a new case and review the literature, paying special attention to genetic developments, differentiation, morphology, immunohistochemistry and differential diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura-Sánchez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Carrasco, Carmen-Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Carrasco, Carmen Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-Severín, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El histiocitoma fibroso angiomatoide es una neoplasia mesenquimal de malignidad intermedia e histogénesis incierta que se da frecuentemente en las extremidades de niños o adultos jóvenes. Su morfología es peculiar, y está constituida como una lesión circunscrita de células fusiformes, infiltrado linfoplasmocitario periférico, cavidades quísticas rellenas de sangre y frecuente expresión de desmina. Nosotros presentamos un nuevo caso y revisamos la literatura, en particular con respecto a acontecimientos genéticos, de diferenciación, morfológicos, inmunohistoquímicos y de diagnóstico diferencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;46(4): 264-268, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116186</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitoma fibroso angiomatoide  Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31565^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3913^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
