<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90971</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnitude and characteristics of residual lipid risk in patients with a history of coronary revascularization: The ICP-Bypass study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Residual lipid risk has been defined as the excess of cardiovascular events observed in patients with adequate control of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol and has been mainly attributed to high-density lipoprotein cholesterol and triglycerides. The aim of our study was to describe the clinical features and the magnitude and characteristics associated with residual lipid risk in patients with a history of coronary revascularization. Methods. Multicenter, observational, cross-sectional study of patients with a history of coronary revascularization. Residual lipid risk was defined as the presence of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;40 mg/dL and/or triglycerides &gt;150 mg/dL in patients with low-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;100 mg/dL. Results. We included 2292 patients with a mean age of 65.5 (12.4) years; 94.1% were receiving no statin therapy and 4.8% no lipid therapy. Statin-only therapy (74%) was the most common strategy, followed by combination with ezetimibe (17%). The prevalence of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;40 mg/dL was 35.8%, hypertriglyceridemia 38.9%, and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol &gt;100 mg/dL 44.9%; the residual lipid risk group included 29.9% of all patients. This patient group had a similar clinical profile except for slightly lower mean age, higher incidence of diabetes, and higher proportion of men. Multivariate analysis identified positive associations of diabetes and male sex with residual lipid risk; current smoking, male sex, and fibrate therapy were associated with high-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;40 mg/dL; current smoking, abdominal obesity, and fibrate therapy were associated with hypertriglyceridemia. Conclusions. In daily clinical practice, almost one-third of patients with a history of coronary revascularization have low-density lipoprotein cholesterol &lt;100 mg/dL plus low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol and/or hypertriglyceridemia, a concept known as residual lipid risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cordero, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitale, Gustavo C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Timón, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Juanatey, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazón, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. El riesgo residual lipídico se define como el exceso de complicaciones cardiovasculares en pacientes con buen control del colesterol unido a liproteínas de baja densidad y se atribuye fundamentalmente al colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad y los triglicéridos. El objetivo del estudio fue describir la magnitud y las características asociadas al riesgo residual lipídico en pacientes con antecedentes de revascularización coronaria. Métodos. Estudio multicéntrico, transversal y observacional. Se definió riesgo residual lipídico por la presencia de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad &lt; 40mg/dl y/o triglicéridos &gt; 150mg/dl en pacientes con colesterol unido a liproteínas de baja densidad &lt; 100mg/dl. Resultados. Se incluyó a 2.292 pacientes, con una media de edad de 65,5±12,4 años. El 94,1% estaba en tratamiento con estatinas y el 4,8% no recibía ningún tratamiento hipolipemiante; el tratamiento únicamente con estatinas (74%) fue la estrategia más común, seguida de la combinación con ezetimiba (17%). La prevalencia de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad &lt; 40mg/dl fue del 35,8%; la de hipertrigliceridemia, del 38,9%, y la de colesterol unido a liproteínas de baja densidad &gt; 100mg/dl, 44,9%. El 29,9% de los pacientes constituyeron el colectivo de riesgo residual lipídico. Estos pacientes presentaron un perfil clínico similar, salvo por una media de edad ligeramente inferior, más diabetes y sexo masculino. El análisis multivariable identificó asociación positiva de la diabetes y el sexo masculino con riesgo residual lipídico; diabetes, tabaquismo activo, sexo masculino y el tratamiento con fibratos se asociaron al colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad &lt; 40mg/dl; y diabetes, tabaquismo, obesidad abdominal y el tratamiento con fibratos, a la hipertrigliceridemia. Conclusiones. Casi una tercera parte de los pacientes con antecedentes de revascularización coronaria presentan colesterol unido a liproteínas de baja densidad &lt; 100mg/dl y colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad bajo y/o triglicéridos elevados en la práctica clínica diaria, el denominado riesgo residual lipídico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(10): 862-868, oct. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Magnitud y características del riesgo residual lipídico en pacientes con antecedentes de revascularización coronaria: estudio ICP- Bypass</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51243^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8249^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
