<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98105</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uveitis diagnosis characterization at a referral centre in the area of Barcelona, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To describe the uveitis pattern in our geographic area. Recent demographic, environmental and scientific changes can determine uveitis pattern changes, which we aim to investigate. Patients and methods: A cross-sectional study between 1st January 2009 and 30th June 2010 was done. All uveitis patients visited at our institution were included. Anatomical (IUSG &amp; SUN) and aetiological patterns (by &#147;tailored&#148; tests), age, sex, origin and laterality were analyzed. Results from first visits and controls were compared statistically, by chi-square and ANOVA tests. Results:From 416 patients included, 150 (36%) were anterior uveitis, 128 (31%) posterior, 101 (24%) panuveitis and 37 (9%) intermediate uveitis (IU). Fifty-six percent (236) were bilateral, mean age was 46 years (6-87) and 58% were women. Fourteen percent (58) were from non-Spanish origin. By aetiology, 20% were unclassifiable, 31% infectious, 26% associated with systemic immune diseases and 23% were ocular specific syndromes. Among classified causes, herpes virus (11%), Toxoplasma (8%), Behçet (8%) and tuberculosis (6%) were the most common. IU were diagnosed more frequently at first time in foreign patients (P=.018); they affected younger patients (P=.008), were more chronic (P=.003) and unclassifiable (P=.024). Conclusion: In our area, 80% of uveitis can be correctly classified. IU have an increased frequency among foreigners, and they use to be unclassifiable and chronic. Tuberculosis (6%) and Birdshot chorio-retinopathy (4%) must be kept in mind as uveitis causes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pelegrín Colás, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesquida Febrer, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorenç Bellés, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa Garriga, Gerard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Torrente, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martínez, Julià</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Keller, Johannes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adán Civera, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Segura, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Conocer el patrón uveítico de nuestra área geográfica. Los recientes cambios demográficos, ecológicos y científicos pueden determinar cambios epidemiológicos en las uveítis, que nos hemos propuesto investigar. Pacientes y método: Corte transversal desde el 1-01-2009 al 30-06-2010. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes atendidos por uveítis en nuestro centro. Se analizaron el tipo anatómico (IUSG &amp; SUN), la etiología (tests «a medida»), la edad, el sexo, la procedencia y la lateralidad. Los resultados entre las «primeras visitas» y los controles fueron comparados estadísticamente mediante los tests de ANOVA y ji al cuadrado. Resultados: De 416 pacientes incluídos, 150 (36%) fueron uveítis anteriores, 128 (31%) posteriores, 101 (24%) panuveítis y 37 (9%) uveítis intermedias (UI). Un 56% (236) fueron bilaterales, la edad media fue de 46 años (extremos 6-87) y un 58% fueron mujeres. El 14% (58) fueron pacientes extranjeros. Por etiología, un 20% fueron inclasificables, un 31% infecciosas, un 26% asociadas a enfermedades sistémicas y un 23% oculares específicas. Entre las causas conocidas, la herpética (11%), Toxoplasma (8%), Behçet (8%) y tuberculosis (6%) fueron las más frecuentes. Las UI afectaron significativamente por primera vez a más extranjeros (p=0,018), afectaron a pacientes más jóvenes (p=0,008) y fueron más frecuentemente crónicas (p=0,003) e inclasificables (p=0,024). Conclusión: En nuestro medio, un 80% de las uveítis pueden ser correctamente clasificadas. Las UI han incrementado su frecuencia en población extranjera, suelen ser inclasificables y crónicas. La tuberculosis (6%) y la enfermedad de Birdshot (4%) deben ser tenidas en cuenta como causa de uveítis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);138(7): 277-282, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de las uveítis diagnosticadas en un centro de referencia del área de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53529^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31856^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27878^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24826^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
