<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115879</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Topical vs subconjunctival application of regenerative factor-rich plasma for chemical eye burns: a comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We assess the efficacy of subconjunctival and topical application of regenerative factor-rich plasma (RFRP) for chemical eye burns. Fifteen eyes with chemical burns in 15 patients distributed in 3 groups were treated. One group received routine care (control group), another received routine care plus topical RFRP application, and another received routine care plus subconjunctival RFRP application. Clinical course and time until definitive cure. Were analyzed times until a definitive cure and corneal and conjunctival epithelization in the groups receiving RFRP application (either topical or subconjunctival) were shorter than the times in the control group. We conclude that RFRP application, whether topical or subconjunctival, is an effective, uncomplicated, and economical treatment for eye burns from caustic chemicals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez de Aracena, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudio de la aplicación subconjuntival y tópica de plasma rico en factores regeneradores(PRFR) en pacientes con quemaduras oculares por productos químicos. Se analizaron15 ojos de 15 pacientes con quemaduras químicas oculares. Se dividieron en tres grupos: uno de control con tratamiento médico clásico; otro con tratamiento médico clásico y tópico de PRFR y un tercero, con tratamiento médico clásico e infiltración subconjuntivalde PRFR. Se estudió la evolución clínica de las lesiones y tiempo hasta su curación final. En los grupos con PRFR tópico y subconjuntival hubo un acortamiento de los días de curación frente al grupo control, que fueron significativos para las variables tiempo de curación final, epitelización de córnea y conjuntiva. Podemos considerarla aplicación tópica y subconjuntival de RFRP como un tratamiento eficaz, sencillo y económico en el tratamiento de las causticaciones de la superficie ocular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(5): 393-396, oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las quemaduras oculares por productosquímicos mediante aplicación tópica y subconjuntival deplasma rico en factores regeneradores. Estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28014^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
