<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144106</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary antioxidants for chronic periodontitis prevention and its treatment. A review on current evidences from animal and human studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. Given the relationship between chronic periodontitis and high levels of oxidative stress, this review aims to clarify what role can played the dietary intake of different antioxidants in maintaining a healthy periodontium and in reducing chronic periodontitis risk, as well as possible use of dietary therapies based on them for this disease treatment. Methods. The database of the National Library of Medicine, Washington, DC (MEDLINE PubMed) was used and all the studies in animals and humans are on the subject of interest in English writing online available from inception of the database until May 2015 were collected.  Results. Antioxidants analyzed in this regard include vitamin C, vitamin A, carotenoids and some polyphenols, and coenzyme Q; as well as minerals iron, copper and zinc that are constituents of antioxidant enzymes. Still, there is a paucity of studies with few human studies, mostly observational. Among the various antioxidants, vitamin E and polyphenols seem to have more evidence for its beneficial effect, but in general the studies are insufficient to rule out or establish what antioxidants are useful and which are not. Conclusions. Overall, the data presented indicate that dietary antioxidants are beneficial for periodontal health, at least under certain circumstances. However more studies are needed to establish the relationship between chronic periodontitis and each specific anti-oxidant and to design useful dietary interventions for this disease management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bullón, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela López, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiles, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Battino, Maurizio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Dada la relación existente entre periodontitis crónica y altos niveles de estrés oxidativo, esta revisión pretende clarificar qué papel puede desempeñar la ingesta de los diferentes antioxidantes de la dieta en el mantenimiento de un periodonto saludable y en la reducción del riesgo de padecer periodontitis crónica, así como el posible uso de terapias dietéticas basadas en estos para el tratamiento de dicha enfermedad.  Métodos. Se utilizó la base de datos de la National Library of Medicine, Washington, DC (MEDLINE: PubMed) y todos los estudios en animales y humanos tratando el tema de interés escritos en inglés disponibles online desde la creación de la base de datos hasta Mayo de 2015 fueron recopilados.  Resultados. Los antioxidantes analizados a este respecto incluyen a la vitamina C, la vitamina A, algunos carotenoides y polifenoles, y el coenzima Q; así como los minerales, hierro, cobre y zinc que forman parte de enzimas antioxidantes. Aun así hay una escasez generalizada de estudios con pocos estudios en humanos, la mayoría de tipo observacional. Entre los diferentes antioxidantes, la vitamina E y los polifenoles parecen ser los que más evidencias a favor de su efecto beneficioso suman, pero en general los estudios son insuficientes para descartar o establecer qué antioxidantes son útiles y cuáles no.  Conclusiones. En general, los datos presentados indicarían que los antioxidantes de la dieta resultan beneficiosos para la salud periodontal, al menos bajo ciertas circunstancias. Sin embargo se necesitan más estudios para establecer la relación entre la periodontitis crónica y cada antioxidante concreto así como para diseñar intervenciones dietéticas útiles en la gestión de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;56(3): 131-140, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antioxidantes dietéticos para la prevención de la periodontitis crónica y su tratamiento: una revisión de las evidencias actuales procedentes de estudios en animales y humanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30577</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53078^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2379^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29135^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3321^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53078^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10188</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1212^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6030^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15427^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29572^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15202^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32967^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53078^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
