<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92819</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diversity of Legionella pneumophila in cooling towers: coculture kinetics and virulence studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Legionella pneumophila (L. pneumophila) was isolated from three cooling towers involved inthree community outbreaks of Legionnaires&amp;#711;&amp;#305; disease. Each cooling tower had two different chromosomalDNA subtypes. However, only one matched identically to the clinical strains. To try to understand whyonly one of the environmental strains caused clinical cases we investigated the intrinsic virulence ofthese strains.Methods: We selected six strains of L. pneumophila sg.1: two strains (A1 and B1) from cooling tower1, two strains (A2 and B2) from tower 2 and two strains (A3 and B3) from tower 3. One of the twosubtypes (A) exhibited the same chromosomal DNA subtype as the strains isolated from the patientsin each outbreak and the other exhibited a different subtype. The replication within macrophages, thepresence of lipopolysaccharide epitope recognized by MAb 3/1 and the growth kinetics in BCYE brothwere investigated. Isolates were typed by pulsed field electrophoresis. Results: The A strains did not have a higher virulence level, but were able to grow and survive better thanstrains B in BCYE broth.Conclusions: These results suggest that the strains better adapted to the environment will manage todisplace the others and will be able to spread and infect humans. The adaptation to the environmentalconditions could play an important role in the pathogenesis of the strains (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabria, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Núñez, Marian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ragull, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro-Botet, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónLegionella pneumophila (L. pneumophila) fue aislada en tres torres de refrigeración implicadas en tres brotes de legionelosis comunitaria. En cada una de ellas se encontraron cepas con dos subtipos diferentes de ADN cromosómico. Sin embargo, sólo uno de ellos era idéntico al de las cepas clínicas. Para intentar entender porque solo una de las cepas ambientales produjo los casos clínicos investigamos la virulencia intrínseca de estas cepas.MétodosSe seleccionaron 6 cepas de L. pneumophila sg.1: dos cepas (A1 y B1) procedentes de la torre de refrigeración 1, dos cepas (A2 y B2) de la torre 2 y dos cepas (A3 y B3) de la torre 3. Las cepas A presentaban un perfil de ADN cromosómico idéntico a la cepa clínica aislada en los individuos afectados en cada uno de los brotes de legionelosis. La cepa B presentaba un perfil cromosómico diferente. Se realizaron ensayos de replicación en macrófagos, se determinó la presencia del epítopo reconocido por MAb 3/1 y se estudió la cinética de crecimiento en medio BCYE. Las cepas se tipificaron mediante electroforesis en campo pulsante.ResultadosLas cepas A no presentaron mayor grado de virulencia, sin embargo, fueron capaces de crecer y sobrevivir mejor que las cepas B en medio BCYE.ConclusionesEstos resultados sugieren que las cepas mejor adaptadas al medio conseguirán desplazar a las demás y serán capaces de propagarse e infectar a los humanos. La adaptación a las condiciones ambientales podría desempeñar un papel importante en la patogenia de cada cepa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(5): 334-338, mayo 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diversidad de subtipos de Legionella pneumophila en torres de refrigeración: estudios de cinética de crecimiento y virulencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30016^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19226^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30016^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12456^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
