<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134035</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The modified Brussels scale as a predictor of mortality in the Intensive Care Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose To compare discrimination and calibration of the modified Brussels score with the Simplified Acute Physiology Score version 3 (SAPS-3) in predicting mortality. Design A prospective cohort study was carried out. Setting The Respiratory Intensive Care Unit (RICU) of Mexico General Hospital. Patients A total of 251 patients out of 285 admissions to the RICU in 2012 were included. The mean age was 48.4±17.1 years, and 132 of the patients were men (52.8%). Interventions None. Variables of interest Demographic data, SAPS-3 score upon admission and the modified Brussels score on the day 1 of stay in the RICU. Results On day 1, the modified Brussels and SAPS-3 scores were 4.7±3.8 and 54.7±17.8, respectively. Areas under the ROC curve for the modified Brussels score on day 1 and the SAPS-3 were 0.837±0.025 (95% CI 0.787-0.887) and 0.813±0.027 (95% CI 0.761-0.865), respectively. Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit values were 5,885 (P=.660) and 4,026 (P=.855), respectively. Conclusions The modified Brussels score on day 1 offers excellent discrimination and calibration in predicting mortality in the RICU, comparable to that of the SAPS-3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo-Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Velázquez, L. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Riveros, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Comparar la discriminación y calibración de la escala modificada de Bruselas con el sistema Simplified Acute Physiology Score version 3 (SAPS-3) como predictor de mortalidad. Diseño Cohorte prospectiva. Ámbito Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Respiratorios (UCIR) del Hospital General de México. Pacientes De 285 ingresos en la UCIR en 2012, se incluyeron 251 pacientes, con una edad media de 48,4±17,1 años; de ellos, 132 fueron hombres (52,8%).Intervenciones Ninguna. Variables de interés Demográficas, SAPS-3 y escala modificada de Bruselas del primer día de estancia en UCIR. Resultados El valor de la escala de Bruselas modificada del día 1 fue 4,7±3,8, y de SAPS-3, 54,7±17,8. El área ROC para la escala de Bruselas modificada del día 1 fue 0,837±0,025 (IC 95% 0,787 a 0,887), y para SAPS-3, de 0,813±0,027 (IC 95% 0,761 a 0,865), con prueba de bondad de ajuste de Hosmer-Lemeshow de 5.885 (p=0,660) y 4.026 (p=0,855), respectivamente. Conclusiones La escala modificada de Bruselas en el día 1 tiene una discriminación y calibración excelentes para predecir la mortalidad de los pacientes en la UCIR, comparables a las del modelo SAPS-3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(1): 20-25, ene.-feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La escala modificada de Bruselas como predictor de mortalidad en la Unidad de Terapia Intensiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
