<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154497</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Summary of evidence-based nutritional recommendations of the Clinical Practice Guideline for the management of patients with Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To announce the Human Nutrition and Dietetics (NHyD) recommendations of the Clinical Practice Guideline in the management of Parkinson&#146;s disease in the Spanish National health system, and promoting its dissemination and implementation in practice. To point out the implication of NHyD professionals in the quoted guideline was the secondary objective. Material and methods: The following items were carried out according to the Methodological Manual for Clinical Practice Guidelines Preparation in the Spanish National health system: formulating the clinical questions, systematic search for each question in databases (PubMed/ Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library, CRD, LILACS, IBECS and ClinicalTrials), definition of eligibility criteria, studies were selected by at least two researchers, critical reading of the literature was made using evidence summary tables, and corresponding recommendations were established. Results: 14 questions directly related with Parkinson&#146;s disease and NHyD were proposed; only 3 of which could be finally included. It was formulated a question related to speech therapy for Parkinson&#146;s disease patients with swallowing disorders. Human Nutrition and Dietetics professionals got involved in this treatment. Only 2 of the 642 articles were included to answer the corresponding questions. According to evidence found, 11 recommendations were proposed with the active involvement of Human Nutrition and Dietetics. Conclusions: Multidisciplinary healthcare professionals&#146; implication improves the final result of the guideline and the health care results in patients. It is necessary that Human Nutrition and Dietetics healthcare professionals get involved in this kind of initiatives, based on the best evidence available, and they should be a member of multidisciplinary work teams (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Rodríguez, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos Pérez-Surio, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baladia, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: dar a conocer las recomendaciones relacionadas con la Nutrición Humana y Dietética (NHyD) de la Guía de Práctica Clínica para el manejo de la enfermedad de Parkinson del Sistema Nacional de Salud (GPC-EP/SNS) y favorecer su difusión e implementación en la práctica. El objetivo secundario es presentar la implicación de los profesionales de la NHyD en la elaboración de la guía. Material y métodos: siguiendo el Manual Metodológico de Elaboración de Guías de Práctica Clínica en el Sistema Nacional de Salud, se formularon las preguntas clínicas, se realizó una búsqueda sistemática para cada pregunta en bases de datos (PubMed/Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library, CRD, LILACS, IBECS y ClinicalTrials), se definieron los criterios de elegibilidad, al menos dos investigadores seleccionaron los estudios, se realizó lectura crítica de la literatura se resumió en tablas de síntesis de evidencia y se establecieron las recomendaciones. Resultados: se propusieron 14 preguntas relacionadas directamente con NHyD-Parkinson, de las cuales solamente 3 pudieron incluirse. Se formuló una pregunta relacionada con la terapia de logopedia aplicada en personas con EP que presentan problemas de deglución, tratamiento donde se imbrican los profesionales de la NHyD. De 642 artículos localizados, únicamente 2 pudieron ser incluidos para contestar las correspondientes preguntas. De las evidencias halladas, se derivaron 11 recomendaciones directa o indirectamente relacionados con la NHyD. Conclusiones: la implicación de profesionales sanitarios en equipos multidisciplinares mejora el resultado final de las guías y la atención sanitaria de los pacientes. Es necesario que los profesionales sanitarios de la NHyD (los/las dietistas-nutricionistas) se impliquen en iniciativas basadas en la mejor evidencia científica disponible y que formen parte de los equipos de trabajo multidisciplinares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 749-760, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sumario de recomendaciones nutricionales basadas en la evidencia de la Guía de Práctica Clínica para el manejo de pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
