<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63744</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Analytic studies make it possible to study and verify causal hypotheses and clinical studies, specifically contribute the greatest level of evidence in the verification of these hypothesis. A randomized clinical trial (RCT) is a planned experiment in which two or more preventive, curative or rehabilitating interventions, assigned in an individualized and random way to a group of patients to study the effect of these interventions in man, are compared. To do so, a series of methodological aspects must be taken into account, such as the choice of the subject sample based on adequate screening criteria, random allotment of the subjects to the different intervention groups, choice of the control group, masking or blinding of some or all the subjects participating in the study and description of losses and drop-outs for correct analysis of the data. The characteristics of the type of study, conducted in humans, imply the need for the fulfillment of some ethical and legal requirements that protect the participants, reason why it is essential to obtain an informed consent and favorable report from the Ethics Committee for its conduction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, J. L. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seoane, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lurueña-Segovia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Moreno, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios analíticos permiten estudiar y verificar hipótesis causales, y los ensayos clínicos, en particular, aportan el mayor nivel de evidencia en la comprobación de estas hipótesis. Un ensayo clínico aleatorio (ECA) es un experimento planificado en el que, de forma prospectiva, se comparan dos o más intervenciones preventivas, curativas o rehabilitadoras, que son asignadas de forma individualizada y aleatoria a un grupo de pacientes para estudiar el efecto de estas intervenciones en el hombre. Para su realización es necesario tener en cuenta una serie de aspectos metodológicos, como la elección de la muestra de sujetos a partir de unos adecuados criterios de selección, asignación aleatoria de los sujetos a los diferentes grupos de intervención, elección del grupo control, enmascaramiento o cegamiento de algunos o todos los sujetos que intervienen en el estudio, y descripción de pérdidas y abandonos para un correcto análisis de los datos. Las características de este tipo de estudios, realizados sobre humanos, implican la necesidad del cumplimiento de unos requisitos éticos y legales que protejan a los participantes, motivo por el cual es imprescindible la obtención de un consentimiento informado, así como el informe favorable de un Comité Ético de Investigación Clínica para su realización</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(6): 296-304, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63744</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
