<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134222</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Animal Models of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Animal models of disease have always been welcomed by the scientific community because they provide an approach to the investigation of certain aspects of the disease in question. Animal models of COPD cannot reproduce the heterogeneity of the disease and usually only manage to represent the disease in its milder stages. Moreover, airflow obstruction, the variable that determines patient diagnosis, not always taken into account in the models. For this reason, models have focused on the development of emphysema, easily detectable by lung morphometry, and have disregarded other components of the disease, such as airway injury or associated vascular changes. Continuous, long-term exposure to cigarette smoke is considered the main risk factor for this disease,  justifying the fact that the cigarette smoke exposure model is the most widely used. Some variations on this basic model, related to exposure time,the association of other inducers or inhibitors, exacerbations or the use oftransgenic animals to facilitate the identification of pathogenic pathways have been developed. Some variations or heterogeneity of this disease, then, can be reproduced and models can be designed for resolving researchers&#146; questions on disease identification or treatment responses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peces-Barba, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Rial, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón-Martínez, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de modelos animales de una enfermedad ha sido siempre bien acogido por la comunidad científica porque permite realizar una aproximación a la investigación de determinados aspectos de la misma. Los modelos animales de la EPOC no pueden llegar a reproducir la heterogeneidad de esta enfermedad y generalmente solo llegan a representar los estadios más leves de la misma. Además, la obstrucción al flujo aéreo, variable que determina el diagnóstico en un paciente, no siempre se tiene en cuenta en los modelos. Por este motivo, los modelos se han centrado en el desarrollo de enfisema, fácilmente detectable por morfometría pulmonar, sin prestar atención a otros componentes de la enfermedad, como la lesión de las vías aéreas o las alteraciones vasculares asociadas. La exposición continua y prolongada al humo de tabaco se considera el principal factor de riesgo de esta enfermedad, lo que justifica que sea el modelo de exposición al humo de tabaco el más ampliamente utilizado. Sobre esta base de modelo podemos encontrar algunas variantes relacionadas con el tiempo de exposición, la asociación de otros inductores o inhibidores, las exacerbaciones o el uso de animales transgénicos que facilitan la identificación de las vías patogénicas. Es posible, por tanto, reproducir algunas variantes o heterogeneidades de esta enfermedad y diseñar uno u otro modelo que sea capaz de responder a una u otra pregunta de investigación, dirigida bien a una identificación patogénica y/o bien a una respuesta terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(3): 121-127, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos animales de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37359^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12093</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37357^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
