<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117632</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper deals with the emerging synthetic biology, its challenges and risks, and tries to desing a model for the governance and regulation of the field. The model is called of &#147;prudent vigilance&#148; (inspired by the report about synthetic biology, drafted by the U.S Presidential Commission on Bioethics, 2010), and it entails (a) an ongoing and periodically revised process of assessment and management of all the risks and concerns, and (b) the adoption of policies- taken of proportionality (among benefits and risks), on a reasonable balancing between different interests and rights at stake, and are oriented by a constitutional frame, which is represented by the protection of fundamental human rights emerging in the field of synthetic biology (right to life, right to health, dignity, freedom of scientific research, right to environment). After the theoretical explanation of the model, its operability is &#147;checked&#148;, by considering its application with reference to only one specific risk brought up by synthetic biology- biosecurity risk, i. e the risk of bioterrorism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colussi, Ilaria Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se adentra en la emergente biología sintética, sus retos y riesgos y trata de diseñar un modelo para la gobernanza y regulación de esta materia. El modelo se denomina &#147;prudent vigilance&#148; (inspirado en el informe acerca de la biología sintética, elaborado por la Comisión Presidencial de Bioética de EE.UU. en 2010), e implica (a) un proceso permanente y periódicamente revisado de evaluación y gestión de todos los riesgos y preocupaciones, y (b) la adopción de políticas &#150; llevadas a cabo a través de mecanismos de &#147;hard law&#148; y &#147;soft law&#148; que se basan ene le principio de proporcionalidad (entre beneficios y riesgos), en un equilibrio razonable entre los diferentes intereses y derechos en el juego, y orientadas hacia un marco constitucional, que está representado por la protección de los derechos humanos fundamentales que surgen en el campo de la biología sintética (derecho a la vida, derecho a la salud, dignidad, libertad de investigación científica, derecho al medio ambiente). Después de la explicación teórica de dicho modelo, su operatividad está &#147;probada&#148;, al considerar su aplicación con referencia a un solo riesgo específico planteado por la biología sintética: riesgo de bioseguridad, es decir, el riesgo de bioterrorismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(38): 185-214, ene.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Synthetic biology between challenges and risks: Suggestions for a model of governance and regulatory framework, based on fundamental rights</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54357^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35431</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
