<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82858</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological treatment in the pregnant woman: drugs contraindicated during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As primary care doctors treat pregnant women and those of fertile age, they must decide which treatments they should follow. Therefore, they have to confront the difficult situation of assessing the risks that different alternative treatments may have on embryo/foetal development. An assessment that is not straightforward as established general guidelines may not be applicable. For example, one drug may be used in some pregnant women but may not be appropriate in others. This implies that the decision on treatments given during pregnancy requires an individualised assessment in each woman. On the other hand, identifying the effects of different drugs on human embryo and foetal development is very difficult, and is also mainly based on observational epidemiological studies. This makes it even more difficult as in many cases these publications are not easy to understand, making it difficult to apply in clinical practice. This has led to introducing Telephone Information Services on Teratogenics in many countries, which are answered by experts in the assessment of risks for the embryo and foetus, as well as on the processes of prenatal development. However, we know that there are drugs that do not seem to affect this development and can be used during pregnancy if required. Similarly, others are also known to be used in pregnant women or those planning a pregnancy are totally contraindicated. For this reason, women who take these have to follow strict guidelines to prevent becoming pregnant. This article provides a general view on treatments for pregnant women or those planning a pregnancy, together with their potential effects, as well as a list of those drugs that may be considered safe to use during pregnancy, and those that are contraindicated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pinilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Frías, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los médicos de atención primaria atienden a las mujeres embarazadas y en edad reproductiva, por lo que han de decidir sobre el tratamiento que deben seguir. Para ello, han de enfrentarse a la difícil situación de evaluar el riesgo que las diferentes alternativas terapéuticas pueden suponer para el desarrollo embrionario/fetal. Una evaluación que no es sencilla porque no se pueden establecer normas de aplicación general. De hecho, un mismo medicamento puede ser utilizado en algunas mujeres embarazadas y no ser adecuado en otras. Esto implica que la decisión sobre el tratamiento que se debe aplicar durante el embarazo requiera una evaluación individualizada en cada mujer. Por otra parte, la identificación del efecto de los diferentes medicamentos sobre el desarrollo embrionario y fetal humano es muy difícil y, además, está generalmente basada en estudios epidemiológicos observacionales. Esto supone una dificultad añadida porque en muchos casos este tipo de publicaciones no resultan fáciles de entender, lo que dificulta su traslación a la práctica clínica. Esto dio lugar en muchos países a la organización de servicios de información telefónica sobre teratógenos, atendidos por expertos tanto en evaluación de los riesgos para el embrión y feto, como sobre los procesos del desarrollo prenatal. No obstante, sabemos que hay fármacos que no parecen alterar el desarrollo y que pueden utilizarse durante el embarazo si se necesitan, otros que sí conllevan riesgo pero tienen que utilizarse para controlar la enfermedad materna y, por último se conocen otros cuya utilización en mujeres embarazadas o que planean estarlo está contraindicada. Estos últimos en mujeres en edad reproductiva han de utilizarse siguiendo unas estrictas normas para prevención de embarazos. En este artículo se ofrece una visión general sobre los tratamientos en mujeres embarazadas o que pueden estarlo, junto con sus potenciales efectos y se ofrece la lista de aquellos fármacos que se consideran seguros de utilizar durante la gestación y los que están contraindicados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(10): 579-585, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento farmacológico de la mujer embarazada: fármacos contraindicados durante la gestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14101^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
