<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109670</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Kill the Killers: Natural Killer cells therapy against paediatric refractory solid tumours</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Refractory solid tumours lead children deaths. To change this statement, new treatments should be developed. Natural Killer cells constitute the first line of defence against tumour cells. We propose a new strategy for antitumor cell therapy in children with refractory solid malignancies: IL-15 stimulated NK cells. Patients and methods: 22 paediatric patients suffering refractory solid tumours participate in this study. We compare NK cell subsets and K562 cytotoxicity in patients and sex-age pair&#146;s healthy controls. We use multiparametric flow and time-resolved fluorescent, respectively. In immunocompromised mice we developed an aggressive human metastatic neuroblastoma model and IL-15 stimulated NK cells rescue. Results: Patients had higher NK bright cells subset and lower NK cytotoxicity than healthy controls. IL-15 stimulated NK cells improved NK cell cytotoxicity in vitro and decreased tu-mour burden in vivo. Conclusions: IL-15 stimulated NK cells may constitute a new cell therapy tool for paediatric refractory tumours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Casanova, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuñez Martín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Génesis Martín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valentín Quiroga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el momento actual, los tumores sólidos refractarios al tratamiento convencional constituyen la principal causa de muerte en la edad pediátrica. Por tanto, es necesario desarrollar y consolidar nuevos tratamientos. Las células Natural Killer (NK) constituyen la primera línea de defensa del sistema inmune frente al desarrollo de células tumorales. Planteamos una nueva estrategia de terapia celular antitumoral en niños con cánceres refractarios, inmunoterapia con células NK estimuladas con interleucina 15 (IL-15). Pacientes y Métodos: En 22 pacientes pediátricos con tumores sólidos refractarios y en controles sanos determinamos mediante citometría de flujo multiparamétrica y fluorescencia resuelta en el tiempo, el fenotipo y la actividad citotóxica de las células NK, respectivamente. En ratones inmunodeficientes desarrollamos un modelo de neuroblastoma metastático muy agresivo y terapia de rescate con células Natural Killer estimuladas con IL-15. Resultados: Los pacientes pediátricos con cáncer refractario tienen un mayor porcentaje de células NK bright y una menor actividad citotóxica. La estimulación con IL-15 mejora la citotoxicidad in vitro y disminuye la carga tumoral in vivo. Conclusiones: Las células NK estimuladas con IL-15 constituyen una prometedora estrategia antitumoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;68(3): 141-146, jul.-sept. 2012. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Kill the Killers: terapia con células Natural Killer en pacientes pediátricos con cáncer refractario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3622^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33079^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
