<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119623</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysing bullying in Spanish Schools</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we try to settle down the principal points for analysing bullying in Spanish Schools (Primary and Secondary Schools), using the same instrument, the Bull-S questionnaire, very well validated and used in different Countries and Contexts. This study presents data from the development of bullying from 1990 to 2006, in Spanish Schools, in terms of level of incidence. Also included the analysis of the personal characteristics of those involved pupils, sociometric aspects, and situational points like, frequency, ways and places where bullying takes place and the self-report of the importance and incidence in security perceived by the whole class-group. All these aspects can contribute to the knowledge of the prevalence and diffusion of bullying (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, Fuensanta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio pretende sentar las bases del análisis de la situación de bullying en España a partir del empleo de un mismo instrumento el test Bull-S, ampliamente validado y utilizado en diferentes países y contextos. Se presentan los datos de la evolución del fenómeno bullying desde 1990-2006 en los centros educativos españoles (Educación Primaria y Secundaria) en términos de niveles de incidencia. Se incluye el análisis de las características personales de  los implicados, aspectos sociométricos y situacionales como, frecuencia, formas y lugares donde ocurre, así como una valoración de la importancia y nivel de seguridad percibida en el grupo-aula donde se produce. Estos elementos permitirán explicar su prevalencia y extensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);9(3): 383-394, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bullying: análisis de la situación en las aulas españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
