<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32461</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics and treatment of treatment-resistant obsessive disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes the clinical profile referring obsessive patients without manifiest compulsions as a subtype of treatment-resistant obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD), with poor response to effective treatment approaches (cognitive-behavioral therapy and pharmacotherapy). There are no clear criteria when defining the concept of treatment refractory patients. A number of factors such as partial response to pharmacotherapy of frist choice (clomipramine and fluvoxamine) and to observe a small reduction in the symptomps with intensive trials of exposure and response prevention therapy (of at least the 65%) are considered posible causes of treatment-resistant disorder. The neutralization of obsessive thoughts is considered as a key element associated to obsessive disorder wich determines the refractoriness to the treatment. Revising the therapies used with resistant obsessive disorder we find three prevailing approaches: behavioural therapy, cognitive therapy and medical therapy. It is suggested that future clinical research should focus on this refractory group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Bayón, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo presenta el perfil clínico del trastorno obsesivo resistente a las intervenciones terapéuticas de primera elección (cognitivo-conductuales y farmacológicas). No existen criterios claros en la definición del concepto de resistencia al tratamiento para los pacientes obsesivos. Para considerar a un paciente como resistente se pueden considerar los siguientes criterios: el paciente ha recibido un mínimo de dos ensayos de tratamiento con fármacos de primera elección (clomipramina o fluvoxamina), haber pasado por un programa de exposición y prevención de respuesta y observar una reducción de los síntomas de menos del 65 por ciento (medido en frecuencia de obsesiones, duración, malestar asociado, interferencia y control percibido sobre las obsesiones). Se consideran las neutralizaciones como un elemento clave que determina la refractariedad al tratamiento y que están asociadas especialmente al trastorno obsesivo puro. Existen tres enfoques predominantes para el tratamiento de estos pacientes: terapia conductual, terapia cognitiva y terapia médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(2): 241-247, mayo 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y tratamiento del trastorno obsesivo resistente al tramiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
