<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046329</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the quality of services in Spain and Paraguay, and its impact on customers satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examined gender differences in the analysis of customer quuality of    different sociocultural contexts and their repercussion in the perception of the satisfaction    of the received service. The study was based on a survey of 1008 Spanish clients    and 176 Paraguayans customers that go to different services. The results of an empirical    study support the hypothesis that, in spite of the cultural divergences, similarities exist    in the perception of the quality and in the analysis of customer satisfaction. Concretely,    this paper provides importants information for services to use in the improvement of    the quality and, also, seek to increase the levels of customer satisfaction. In the same    way, the data show the decisive paper of the expectations in the service quality and    customers satisfaction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador Ferrer, Carmen María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio examina las diferencias en el análisis de calidad de los clientes de distintos    contextos socioculturales y su repercusión en la percepción de la satisfacción del    servicio recibido. El trabajo está basado en 1008 clientes españoles y 176 paraguayos que    acuden a distintos servicios. Los resultados obtenidos apoyan la hipótesis de que, pese    a las divergencias culturales, existen similitudes en la percepción de la calidad y en el    análisis de la satisfacción de los clientes. Concretamente, esta investigación proporciona    información importante para los distintos servicios que depositen su interés en la mejora    de la calidad y, también, pretendan incrementar los niveles de satisfacción de los clientes.    Del mismo modo, los datos muestran el decisivo papel que desempeñan las expectativas    de los clientes en el análisis de la calidad del servicio y en sus niveles de satisfacción</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;23(1): 71-82, 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046329</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la calidad de servicios en España y Paraguay y su impacto en la satisfacción de los usuarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
