<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92161</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New perspectives in the treatment of Multiple Sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A best knowledge of etiopathogeny and prognosis of Multiple Sclerosis is allowing the development of new and more effective therapies. Current therapies are divided into three groups: treatments for the acute relapses, disease-modifying therapy and symptomatic treatment. There are six approved drugs available in Spain, also there are two oral new drugs (Cladribina and Fingolimod) and others designed for  improving the quality of life of these patients (Frampidina and Sativex) waiting to be approved and some others in different stages of clinical trials that will offer encouraging perspectives in a near future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olmedilla González, M N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Vela, F T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El conocimiento de la etiopatogenia y el pronóstico de la Esclerosis Múltiple (EM) ha permitido desarrollar tratamientos nuevos y más eficaces. Las terapias actuales pueden dividirse en tres grandes grupos: los tratamientos del brote agudo, los modificadores del curso de la enfermedad y el tratamiento sintomático. Actualmente hay seis fármacos aprobados para el tratamiento de la EM en España, dos nuevos  fármacos orales (Cladribina y Fingolimod) y otros destinados a mejorar la calidad de vida de los pacientes (Fampridina y Sativex) están pendientes de aprobación y varios en distintas fases de estudios clínicos que ofrecen perspectivas muy esperanzadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(2): 108-114, abr.-jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas perspectivas en el tratamiento de la Esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29455^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29469^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24613^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
