<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113927</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eosinophilic ulcer tongue: a diagnostic challenge controversial pathogenesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eosinophilic ulcer, also know as traumatic ulcerative granuloma with stromal eosinophilia, is a rare and benign ulcerative lesion of oral mucosa that has a persistent progression, often requiring a differential clinical diagnosis. The diagnosis is only established from histopathological studies, which frequently show morphological features that may be suggestive of a lymphoproliferative process, resulting in a controversial pathogenesis that is still not clarified today. We report the clinical and pathological observations of an eosinophilic ulcer affecting a woman 76 year-old woman. A biopsy was performed twice on a 2.5 cm diameter ulcer affecting the lingual edge. After a clinical follow-up of 5 months, a self-limiting course with the production of a scar was verified. She has currently been scheduled for an extended 24-month clinical follow-up. The morphological and immunohistochemical features found in the biopsy study are presented, and the pathogenesis hypothesis of this uncommon ulcerative lesion is discussed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Sempere, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera-Sirera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero Ruíz de la Hermosa, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delhom-Valero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La úlcera eosinofílica, también conocida como granuloma ulcerativo traumático con eosinofilia estromal, es una infrecuente y benigna lesión ulcerativa de la mucosa oral que presenta una evolución persistente, planteando a menudo diferentes diagnósticos clínicos diferenciales. Su diagnóstico se establece solo a partir del estudio histopatológico, si bien su morfología presenta a menudo características que pueden sugerir al patólogo la existencia de un proceso linfoproliferativo, traduciendo una patogénesis lesional controvertida todavía no bien aclarada. Comunicamos una observación clínico-patológica de úlcera eosinofílica afectando a una mujer de 76 años de edad. La lesión, de 2,5 cm de diámetro, afectaba al borde lateral lingual, siendo biopsiada en dos ocasiones, presentando tras un seguimiento clínico de 5 meses una evolución cicatricial, programándose actualmente un seguimiento clínico prologando de 24 meses. Se presentan las características morfológicas e inmunohistoquímicas del estudio biópsico, discutiendo las hipótesis patogéneticas que esta infrecuente lesión ulcerativa plantea(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;35(3): 128-132, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlcera eosinofílica lingual: un reto diagnóstico de patogénesis controvertida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28001^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53957^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28001^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53957^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
