<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126155</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Normative data for 148 Spanish emotional words in terms of attributions of humanity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Research on outgroup infrahumanization is based on the subtle and not deliberate distinction of secondary emotions, an exclusively human emotion, and primary emotions, which are shared by animals and human beings. According to prior studies, people attribute more secondary emotions to the ingroup than to the outgroup which they deny or restrict the ability to experience them. This study presents normative measures for 148 emotional words viewed by Spanish people in seven dimensions related to humanity assessments. Two factors were revealed by the principal components analysis (PCA). The first component was loaded on dimensions that differentiate the emotions depending on the cognitive demands (cognition, moral quality and duration) whereas the second one was loaded on their expressive profile (visibility, age at which they are acquired, universality and causal locus). These dimensions were analyzed in relation to desirability, familiarity and explicit humanity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leyens, Jacques Phillipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pérez, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño-Mateo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancor-Rodríguez, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demoulin, Stephanie</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las investigaciones sobre la infrahumanización del exogrupo se apoyan en la distinción sutil y no deliberada que existe entre los sentimientos, una emoción exclusivamente humana, y las emociones, que son compartidas por animales y humanos. De acuerdo con esos estudios, las personas atribuyen más sentimientos al endogrupo que al exogrupo al que niegan o restringen la capacidad para experimentarlos. Este estudio presenta los datos normativos relativos a 148 términos afectivos en siete dimensiones relacionadas con las evaluaciones de humanidad. El Análisis de Componentes Principales calculado sobre las respuestas dio lugar a dos factores. El primero agrupó las dimensiones que diferencian los términos afectivos en función de las demandas cognitivas requeridas (cognición, naturaleza moral y duración), mientras que el segundo las diferenció en función de su perfil expresivo (visibilidad, edad a la que se adquiere, universalidad y foco causal). Estas dimensiones se analizaron en relación a la valencia, la familiaridad y la humanidad explicita (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(3): 1137-1145, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Datos normativos de 148 términos afectivos en dimensiones relacionadas con la atribución de humanidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6960</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15334^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d533</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
