<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101901</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relation between maximum expiratory volume in one section, BODE index and quality of life perceived by the chronic obstructive pulmonary disease patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To measure the correlation between perceived quality of life and two objective severity parameters: forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) and body mass, airflow obstruction, dyspnea and exercise capacity (BODE) index. Material and methods: Observational descriptive cross-sectional study involving 40 Chronic Obstruction Pulmonary Disease (COPD) patients. They were classified using the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) classification system into moderate or severe. The Saint George Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) was carried out by interview and the BODE value was analyzed after measurement of the parameters included in it. Anthropometry and demography data were also collected. Results: A study including 40 patients, 38 of them men 38 (95%), with mean age 76.15 ± 5.82 was performed. The means obtained for the subjective variable of the SGRQ was 33.58 ± 18.14. Regarding the data obtained for the objective variables, the FEV1 had a mean of 49.05 ± 15.731, and the BODE index showed 2.33 ± 1.8. The parameters making it up were: 6-minute exercise test 440 ± 87.9, mean MRC score: 1.4 ± 0.6, and body mass index (BMI) 28.16 ± 4.4. According to the values obtained, we observed the existence of a correlation between SGRO and the BODE index and between the activity, and subscale of the SGRO and BODE index. Conclusions: The BODE index are weakly correlative with the results of the SGRO combined. High index BODE negatively affects the perceived quality of life of moderate/severe COPD patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Astals Bota, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortes Genescá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biendicho Palau, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Puñet, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol Salud, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Sancho, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la correlación existente entre la calidad de vida percibida por los pacientes y dos parámetros objetivos de gravedad: a) la gravedad de la obstrucción por el volumen espiratorio máximo en el primer segundo (FEV1), y b) el índice BODE (Body Mass Index, Airflow Obstruction, Dyspnea and Exercice Capacity). Material y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo de corte transversal, realizado en 40 pacientes diagnosticados de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y clasificados según la escala GOLD (Global initiative for chronic obstructive lung disease) en moderados o graves, a los que se entrevistó mediante el cuestionario respiratorio de St. George (SGRQ). Se calculó el índice BODE, previa medición de los parámetros que lo componen. También se recogieron datos antropométricos y demográficos de los pacientes. Resultados: De los 40 pacientes del estudio, 38 eran varones (95%), con una edad media ± desviación estándar (DE) de 76,15 ± 5,82 años. Las medias ± DE obtenidas en referencia a la variable subjetiva del cuestionario SGRQ fueron de 33,58 ± 18,14. En referencia a los datos conseguidos de las variables objetivas, obtuvimos del FEV1 una media ± DE de 49,05 ± 15,731, y del índice BODE de 2,33 ± 1,8 y de sus parámetros integrantes: test de los 6 minutos, 440 ± 87,9; escala Medical Research Council, 1,4 ± 0,6; índice de masa corporal, 28,16 ± 4,4. Según los valores obtenidos observamos la existencia de correlación entre SGRQ y el índice BODE, al igual que entre la actividad, como subescala de la SGRQ y el índice BODE. Conclusiones: El resultado del índice BODE se correlaciona débilmente con los resultados de la SGRQ de forma conjunta, por lo que un elevado índice BODE afecta negativamente a la calidad de vida de los pacientes con EPOC moderados o graves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;14(4): 112-116, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el volumen espiratorio máximo en un segundo, el índice BODE y la calidad de vida percibida por el paciente de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27741^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
