<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054630</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mediastinal lipoblastoma with intramedullary extension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Lipoblastomatous lesions are mesenchymal tumors of fetal-embryonal fat that are classified into two    types: a superficial, well-defined mass (lipoblastoma) or an infiltrative lesion (lipoblastomatosis). Case report. An unique case    of mediastinal lipoblastoma in a 27-month-old boy with spinal epidural extension from C7-D9, clinically manifested as a    progressive painful. Conclusion. The treatment of choice is the complete excision, with high risk of recurrence, suggesting a    periodical clinical evaluation with neuroimaging studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa-Clara, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Quesada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las lesiones lipoblastomatosas son tumores mesenquimales grasos fetoembrionarios que se clasifican    en dos tipos, uno superficial como masa bien definida (lipoblastoma) y otro infiltrativo (lipoblastomatosis). Caso clínico.    Caso único de lipoblastoma mediastínico en un niño de 27 meses de edad con una extensión epidural intramedular desde C7    a D9, clínicamente manifestado por un dolor progresivo. Conclusión. El tratamiento de elección es el quirúrgico, aunque el    porcentaje de recidivas es alto, por lo que se aconseja control seriado con resonancia magnética para el diagnóstico precoz    de éstas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(12): 745-746, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054630</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lipoblastoma mediastínico con extensión intramedular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8647^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8647^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
