<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137609</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicenter evaluation of materials for the quality control of the serum indexes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hemolysis, turbidity and the presence of high concentrations of bilirubin are the most frequent sources of interference in the clinical laboratory. Many analyzers incorporate detection systems for these interferents called &#147;serum indexes&#148; of hemolysis, icterus and lipidemia. The accuracy of such indexes is usually not verified by the difficulty in obtaining appropriate reference materials. In this work we show the results of an interlaboratory study of hemolysis, icterus and lipidemia indexes using reference materials containing known concentrations of these interfering substances. Material and methods. Ten clinical laboratories from different centres have participated in the study using 7 different analyzers. The reference materials for the serum indexes contained known concentrations of bilirubin, hemoglobin (hemolysate) and triglycerides (Intralipid). Results. All instruments provided acceptable results for the icterus and hemolysis index. Among the analyzers providing quantitative values, low results were found in one of the analyzers for materials containing Intralipid. The analyzers expressing the result as an interval provided correct results for materials with low turbidity but a low result for the material with the highest turbidity. Conclusions. The reference materials used have proved to be useful to verify the serum indexes for hemolysis, icterus and lipidemia in analyzers. The results obtained in different instruments generally agree among them and with the assigned values. The most important differences between analyzers were found in the lipidemia index (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Biosca, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alsina, M Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrat, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesinos, Merce</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarz, Merce</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llovet, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gella, F Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hemólisis, la turbidez y la presencia de concentraciones elevadas de bilirrubina son las fuentes de interferencia más frecuentes en el laboratorio clínico. Muchos analizadores incorporan sistemas de detección de estos interferentes denominados «índices séricos» de hemólisis, ictericia y lipidemia. El grado de veracidad de los índices no suele ser verificado por la dificultad en conseguir materiales de referencia adecuados. En este trabajo se presentan los resultados de un estudio interlaboratorios de los índices hemólisis, ictericia y lipidemia empleando materiales de referencia con concentraciones conocidas de los interferentes. Material y métodos. En el estudio han participado los laboratorios clínicos de 10 centros con 7 analizadores distintos. Los materiales de referencia de índices séricos contenían concentraciones conocidas de bilirrubina, hemoglobina (hemolisado) y triglicéridos (Intralipid). Resultados. Todos los instrumentos proporcionaron resultados aceptables para el índice de ictericia y de hemólisis. Entre los analizadores que dan valores cuantitativos se encontraron resultados bajos en uno de los analizadores para los materiales que contenían Intralipid. Los analizadores que expresan el resultado en forma de un intervalo proporcionaron resultados correctos para los materiales con turbidez menor y bajos para el material con turbidez mayor. Conclusiones. Los materiales de referencia utilizados han demostrado su utilidad para verificar los índices séricos de ictericia, hemólisis y lipidemia en los analizadores. Generalmente los índices proporcionados por los instrumentos concuerdan entre sí y con los valores asignados. Las diferencias más importantes entre analizadores se encuentran en el índice de lipidemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;8(2): 61-66, abr.-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137609</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación multicéntrica de materiales para el control de calidad de los índices séricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54202^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7734^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8245^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
