<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73496</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palpebral edema: A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ocular symptoms such as irritation with sensation of sand, blurry vision on reading for prolonged periods, tearing or palpebral edema are frequent reasons for a visit to primary health care. We present the case of a woman with a background of thyroid disease in situation of euthyroidism who presented this ocular symptom and after a series of diagnostic errors, was labeled as having thyroid infiltrative ophthalmopathy. She initiated treatment with steroids. We want to stress that we should consider infiltrative ophthalmopathy in patients who have had a background of thyroid disease, generally hyperthyroidism, because delay in the diagnosis and initiation of treatment could bear severe consequences such as blindness or permanent diplopia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boix Cisneros, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Corduente, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sebastián Checa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Oviedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los síntomas oculares tales como irritación con sensación de arenilla, visión borrosa al leer tiempos prolongados, lagrimeo o edema palpebral son motivos frecuentes de consulta en Atención Primaria. Presentamos el caso de una mujer con antecedentes de patología tiroidea en situación de eutiroidismo, que presentaba esta sintomatología ocular, y que tras una serie de errores diagnósticos se etiquetó de oftalmopatía infiltrativa tiroidea, iniciándose tratamiento con esteroides. Queremos destacar que debemos pensar en la oftalmopatía infiltrativa en pacientes que han tenido antecedentes de patología tiroidea, generalmente hipertiroidismo, debido a que el retraso en el diagnóstico y en la instauración del tratamiento puede conllevar consecuencias graves como ceguera o diplopía permanente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(7): 364-365, ago. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Edema palpebral. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5242^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5242^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
