<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046116</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Digital acrometastasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cutaneous metastases are infrequent and in some cases represent the first manifestation of an unknown neoplasm. Acrally located metastases are particularly rare, and the prognosis is very poor, with a survival time of only a few months. Although the clinical presentation varies, they are generally confused with an infectious or inflammatory process, which delays diagnosis. When they are located on the fingers, the most frequent cause is lung carcinoma, while those located on the toes are usually due to tumors in the genitourinary tract. The histology of the metastasis is similar to that of the primary tumor, although less differentiated. In most acrometastases, first the bone and then the skin are affected. Treatment is palliative. We present the case of a patient with a metastasis on the big toe as an initial sign of a previously unknown lung tumor</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortina, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Arpa, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Vázquez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Caminero, Prado</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las metástasis cutáneas son poco frecuentes y en algunos casos representan la primera manifestación de una neoplasia no conocida. Las metástasis de localización acral son particularmente raras y el pronóstico es muy malo, con una supervivencia de pocos meses. Aunque la clínica es variable, generalmente se confunden con un proceso infeccioso o inflamatorio, retrasándose el diagnóstico. Cuando se localizan en los dedos de la mano la causa más frecuente es el carcinoma de pulmón, mientras que las localizadas en los dedos de los pies suelen deberse a tumores del tracto genitourinario. La histología de la metástasis es similar al primario aunque más indiferenciada. En la mayoría de las metástasis acrales se afecta primero el hueso y secundariamente la piel. El tratamiento es paliativo. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con una metástasis en el primer dedo del pie como signo inicial de un tumor pulmonar no conocido previamente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;97(5): 334-336, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis digital acral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9128</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23483^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23483^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
