<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86241</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatrics, Down&#146;s syndrome and allergic disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Allergic diseases have a genetic basis (atopy), meaning that inheritance is a determining factor in the development of these processes. Respiratory pathologies are the most common, although reactions to foods and drugs also occur. The most common clinical manifestations occur in the skin and digestive tract, and generalised reactions (anaphylaxis) can often occur that can be severe or even fatal. The increase in respiratory pathologies in recent years has been linked to a reduction in infectious diseases in developed countries. The activity of Th1/Th2 lymphocytes has become imbalanced, leaning towards the Th2 that are responsible for producing antibodies against allergens (&#147;hygiene hypothesis&#148;). In spite of this, children with trisomy 21, with the wide gamut of altered genes responsible for many of the processes associated with this syndrome, rarely suffer from allergic diseases. This is reflected in the small number of publications on this field. In contrast, immune response to pathogens is constantly affected (greater incidence of infections requiring the production of specific antibodies produced by Th1 lymphocyte activity) along with other processes (auto-immune, leukaemia) related to patient immunity, and this could be the cause of the reduced possibility for allergic reactions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades alérgicas tienen una base genética (atopia), por lo que la herencia es determinante para presentar estos procesos, en los que la enfermedad respiratoria es predominante, aunque no faltan las reacciones frente a alimentos o medicamentos, cuyas manifestaciones clínicas más comunes tienen lugar en la piel y el aparato digestivo, con reacciones generales en no pocas ocasiones (anafilaxia) que pueden ser graves, incluso mortales. El aumento de la afección respiratoria en los últimos años se ha relacionado con la disminución de las enfermedades infecciosas en los países desarrollados, con un desequilibrio en la actuación de los linfocitos Th1/Th2, inclinada hacia los Th2, encargados de la producción de anticuerpos frente a alérgenos (&#147;hipótesis higiénica&#148;). A pesar de esto, en los niños con trisomía 21, con gran alteración de genes encargados de otros muchos de los procesos asociados a la entidad, en pocas ocasiones presentan enfermedades de causa alérgica, como refleja la escasez de publicaciones que se ocupen de este tema. Por el contrario, la afectación de la respuesta inmunitaria frente a patógenos (mayor incidencia de infecciones con necesidad de producción de anticuerpos específicos a cargo de los linfocitos Th1) y otros procesos (autoinmunes, leucemia) relacionados con la inmunidad, se mantienen de forma constante, lo cual puede ser la causa de la menor posibilidad de reacciones alérgicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);15(1): 8-13, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86241</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pediatría, síndrome de Down y patología alérgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14715^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14715^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14715^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
