<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110882</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The successful free throw in basketball: how it influences the minute of the game, the  scoreboard and be home or visitor team</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze the released free throws in a sample of 56basketball games category ACB. There has been the number of pitches and the percentage of hits in each minute of play. In addition, it also took into account the marker location at the time of launch and the condition of acting as the home team or visitor team. No significant differences were found between local teams and visitors teams in relation to the free throw attempts. In terms of percentages of correct answers, there is minimal difference in favor of the teams playing at home. We discuss these findings and make practical proposals for the training side of the free kick (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Gutiérrez,  Carlos J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Torres,  Manuel G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar los tiros libres lanzados en una muestra de 56 partidos de baloncesto de categoría ACB. Se ha registrado el número de lanzamientos y el porcentaje de aciertos en cada minuto de juego. Además, también se ha tenido en cuenta la situación del marcador en el momento de lanzar y la condición de actuar como equipo local o visitante. No se han encontrado diferencias significativas entre los equipos locales y los visitantes, en relación a los tiros libres intentados. En cuanto a los porcentajes de aciertos, existe una mínima diferencia favorable a los equipos que juegan como locales. Se comentan estos resultados y se hacen propuestas prácticas de cara al entrenamiento del tiro libre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;12(2): 25-38, jul.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110882</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El acierto en el tiro libre en baloncesto: cómo influye el minuto de partido, el estado del marcador y ser equipo local o visitante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
