<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151852</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subjective memory complaints, perceived stress and coping strategies in young adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Subjective memory complaints are becoming more and more frequent among young adults. There are currently no studies in the literature that analyse the relation among memory complaints, perceived stress and coping strategies as a whole in young adults. Aim. To determine the contribution made by perceived stress and diff erent coping strategies on subjective memory complaints in healthy young adults. Subjects and methods. The sample consisted of 299 university students, of whom 71.6% were women, with a mean age of 22.54 ± 4.73 years. The variable &#145;memory complaints&#146; was measured with the memory failures questionnaire; the variable &#145;perceived stress&#146; was measured with the perceived stress scale, and the variables referring to coping strategies were measured using the coping strategies inventory. Results. The variables that made a higher contribution to the variance of the memory complaints are, fi rst, perceived stress and positive problem-focused coping strategies, and, second, negative coping strategies focused on the emotion and on the problem. The positive emotion-focused coping strategies do not make any contribution. Conclusion. Again we fi nd evidence of the infl uence of stress on memory processes. The use of positive problem-focused coping strategies, such as cognitive restructuring and problem-solving, can be benefi cial to lessen the presence of memory complaints. Further research on this matter is warranted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Amorós, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Rodríguez, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer Porcar, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirete Fructuoso, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las quejas subjetivas de memoria son cada vez más frecuentes entre los adultos jóvenes. En la actualidad, no existe bibliografía que analice la relación entre las quejas de memoria, el estrés percibido y las estrategias de afrontamiento de forma conjunta en adultos jóvenes. Objetivo. Determinar la contribución del estrés percibido y diferentes estrategias de afrontamiento sobre las quejas subjetivas de memoria en adultos jóvenes sanos. Sujetos y métodos. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 299 universitarios, el 71,6% mujeres, con una edad media de 22,54 ± 4,73 años. La variable &#145;quejas de memoria&#146; se midió con el cuestionario de fallos de memoria; la variable &#145;estrés percibido&#146;, con la escala de estrés percibido, y las variables referidas a estrategias de afrontamiento, con el inventario de estrategias de afrontamiento. Resultados. Las variables que presentan una mayor aportación a la varianza de las quejas de memoria son, en primer lugar, estrés percibido y estrategias de afrontamiento positivas centradas en el problema, y, en segundo lugar, estrategias de afrontamiento negativas centradas en la emoción y en el problema. Las estrategias de afrontamiento positivas centradas en la emoción presentan una aportación nula. Conclusión. Una vez más se evidencia la infl uencia del estrés sobre los procesos de memoria. El empleo de estrategias de afrontamiento positivas centradas en el problema, como la reestructuración cognitiva y la resolución de problemas, puede resultar benefi cioso para atenuar la presencia de quejas de memoria, y es necesario realizar una mayor investigación al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(8): 344-350, 16 abr., 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quejas subjetivas de memoria, estrés percibido y estrategias de afrontamiento en adultos jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
