<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101771</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardioembolic stroke in atrial fibrillation and new anticoagulation criteria: a therapeutic dare</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To evaluate in patients with known AF and cardioembolic stroke, the indication of oral anticoagulation under previous  risk embolism according to the CHADS2 scale and new classification CHA2-DS2-VASc, assessing the risk of bleeding with  HAS-BLED scale.  Patients and methods. We included 164 patients with atrial fibrillation and cardioembolic stroke, 87 of them with known AF.  It was recorded previous anticoagulant treatment and criteria for prior anticoagulation taking into account CHADS2 scales  and CHA2-DS2-VASc, including hemorrhagic risk scale HAS-BLED. In anticoagulated patients INR level was recorded in   acute stroke phase.  Results. There were no significant differences in baseline patients characteristics according to previous anticoagulation,  except higher percentage of previous stroke in anticoagulated patients (47%). 41.3% were anticoagulated with known AF  prior to stroke. From 52 non-anticoagulated patients, 61.5% met criteria for anticoagulation prior to stroke as CHADS2.  Using CHA2-DS2-VASc, this percentage increased to 94.2% (p &lt;0.001). 78.8% of non-anticoagulated had a low risk of  bleeding according to the scale HAS-BLED. In anticoagulated patients, 67.6% had suboptimal INR at the time of stroke.  Conclusion. In our study, we found low compliance scales of thromboembolic risk stratification in patients with AF for an   optimal treatment strategy. It should be increased its use for primary prevention of stroke and optimization of anticoagulant therapy in patients with AF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moniche Álvares, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ortega, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Hernández, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Marcos, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La fibrilación auricular (FA) aumenta por cinco el riesgo de ictus. El nuevo esquema de estratificación de  riesgo para instauración de anticoagulación oral CHA2-DS2-VASc obtiene mejores resultados en la estratificación del riesgo de ictus frente a la previa escala CHADS2.  Objetivo. Evaluar en pacientes con FA conocida e ictus cardioembólico la indicación de anticoagulación oral conforme al  riesgo previo embolígeno según la escala CHADS2 y la nueva clasificación CHA2-DS2-VASc, valorando el riesgo hemorrá- gico con la escala HAS-BLED.  Pacientes y métodos. Se incluyeron 164 pacientes con FA e ictus cardioembólico, 87 de los cuales tenían FA conocida. Se  registró tratamiento precedente anticoagulante y criterios de anticoagulación previos según las escalas CHADS2 y CHA2- DS2-VASc, incluyendo la escala de riesgo hemorrágico HAS-BLED. En anticoagulados se registró un nivel de índice internacional normalizado (INR) en fase aguda del ictus.  Resultados. No hubo diferencias significativas en características basales según anticogulación previa, excepto mayor porcentaje de ictus en anticogulados (47%). El 41,3% con FA conocida estaba anticoagulado antes del ictus. De los 52 pacientes  no anticoagulados, el 61,5% tenía criterios de anticoagulación previos al ictus según la CHADS2. Usando la CHA2-DS2-  VASc, dicho porcentaje aumentó al 94,2% (p &lt; 0,001). El 78,8% de los no anticoagulados presentaba bajo riesgo de sangrado según la escala HAS-BLED. En pacientes anticoagulados, el 67,6% presentaba INR infraterapéutico en el momento  del ictus.  Conclusión. En nuestro medio, detectamos bajo cumplimiento de escalas de estratificación de riesgo tromboembólico en  pacientes con FA para una estrategia óptima de tratamiento. Es preciso su mayor uso para la prevención primaria del ictus  y la optimización del tratamiento anticoagulante en pacientes con FA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(2): 74-80, jul. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ictus cardioembólico por fibrilación auricular y nuevos criterios de anticoagulación: un reto terapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15213^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
