<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119509</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interactive technologies for learning in physiotherapy: Electronic response devices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the satisfaction of students and teachers regarding the use of classroom electronic response system to support the lecture. Material and methods: A descriptive study including all the students enrolled during the 2010- 11 course in the &amp;#64257;rst year subject of General Procedures in Physiotherapy I at the University of Murcia was made. The students participated voluntarily in two sessions of sessions of training assessment using the electronic multiple choice classroom response system. Each session included 25 questions which were conducted at two different times of the semester. After the &amp;#64257;nal evaluation, both students who had participated and teachers involved &amp;#64257;lled out an anonymous questionnaire to assess the use of this tool. Results: Of the 97 students enrolled, 82.5% and 88.7% participated in the &amp;#64257;rst and second session, respectively. At least 70% of the questions asked in both sessions were answered correctly by 92% of participants. The questionnaire showed a high level of satisfaction among both students and teachers. The students rated this tools with an average score of 4.57 points (over5 points), highlighting the active, motivating and participatory character of this activity. The teachers emphasize the possibility of obtaining real and immediate feedback that helps clarify and go deeper into the approach to key aspects of the practice and the profession that may not have been suf&amp;#64257;ciently covered during the lecture. Conclusions: The classroom response system is an effective teaching tool to increase motivation in the classroom (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Carrasco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la satisfacción de los estudiantes y del profesorado respecto al uso de los mandos electrónicos de respuesta como apoyo a la lección magistral. Material y método Es un estudio descriptivo integrado por todos los estudiantes matriculados en el curso 2010-11 en la asignatura de Procedimientos Generales en Fisioterapia I de la Universidad de Murcia. Los estudiantes participaron voluntariamente en 2 sesiones de evaluación formativa utilizando los mandos electrónicos de respuesta múltiple. Cada sesión incluyó 25 cuestiones y se realizaron en 2 momentos distintos del cuatrimestre. Tras la evaluación final de la asignatura, tanto los estudiantes que habían participado, como los profesores involucrados, cumplimentaron un cuestionario anónimo para evaluar el uso de esta herramienta. Resultados De los 97 estudiantes matriculados, el 82,5% y el 88,7% participaron en la primera y segunda sesión de evaluación, respectivamente. El 92% de los participantes contestó correctamente, al menos, al 70% de las cuestiones planteadas en ambas sesiones. El cuestionario de valoración manifiesta un nivel de satisfacción muy elevado entre los estudiantes y el profesorado. Los estudiantes valoraron esta herramienta con una puntuación media de 4,57 puntos (sobre 5 puntos), destacando su carácter activo, motivador y participativo. El profesorado destaca la posibilidad de obtener un feedback real e inmediato que permite aclarar y profundizar en aspectos clave para el abordaje de la práctica que pudieran no haber quedado suficientemente cubiertos durante la lección magistral. Conclusiones El sistema de mandos electrónicos de respuesta supone una herramienta didáctica eficaz para incrementar la motivación en el aula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(1): 12-18, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tecnologías interactivas para el aprendizaje en fisioterapia: los mandos electrónicos de respuesta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
