<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157179</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Some features of lung cancer have changed in recent decades. The objective is to find out the features of lung cancer diagnosed at our center.  Methods: Cases diagnosed between 02/18/2008 y 02/18/2013 are analysed. Cases not citohistologically confirmed are excluded.  Results: 307 cases were diagnosed during the study period, 244 (79.5%) men and 63 (20.5%) women, with a mean age of 65.37 years (DE ± 11.27). Mean age was 66,73 ± 10,53 years among men and 60.14 ± 12.6 among women (p= 0.0001). Among men 97% were smokers or former smokers, versus 63% of women. The most frequent way of presentation was a radiological finding in an asymptomatic patient. Adenocarcinoma was the most frequent histology among men and women, with a total of 117 (38.1%) cases, followed by squamous cell carcinoma with 77 (25.1%) cases and small cell carcinoma with 58 (18.9%). More than 65% of patients with non-small cell carcinoma presented at diagnosis with a locally advanced (22,5%) or disseminated disease (43%). The percentage of patients with advanced disease was higher among adenocarcinoma (71%) compared to squamous cell carcinoma (51%, p= 0.004).  Conclusions: Lung cancer diagnosed at our center is characterized by a mean age near 65 years, a high percentage of women, a higher mean age in the group of women, adenocarcinoma as the most frequent histology among men and women and a higher percentage of patients with advanced disease among adenocarcinomas in comparison to squamous cell carcinomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Zabaleta, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Ortega, GM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Prieto, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdugo Cartas, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo-Moreno-Arrones, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro Zulueta, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Algunas características del cáncer de pulmón han cambiado en las décadas recientes. El objetivo es conocer las características del cáncer de pulmón diagnosticado en nuestro centro.  Métodos: Se analizan los casos diagnosticados entre 18/02/2008 y 18/02/2013. Se excluyen los no confirmados citohistológicamente.  Resultados: En el periodo referido se diagnosticaron 307 casos, 244 (79,5%) varones y 63 (20,5%) mujeres, con una edad media de 65,37 años (DE ± 11,27). La edad media de los varones fue 66,73 ± 10,53 años y 60,14 ± 12,6 la de las mujeres (p= 0,0001). El 97% de los varones fumaba o había fumado, frente al 63% de las mujeres. La forma de presentación más frecuente fue la alteración radiológica en un paciente asintomático. El adenocarcinoma fue la estirpe tumoral más frecuente en varones y mujeres, con 117 (38,1%) casos en total, seguido del carcinoma epidermoide con 77 (25,1%) casos, y del carcinoma de célula pequeña con 58 (18,9%). Más del 65% de los pacientes con carcinoma de célula no pequeña presentaban al diagnóstico una enfermedad localmente avanzada (22,5%) o diseminada (43%). El porcentaje de enfermedad avanzada fue  superior en el adenocarcinoma (71%) comparando con el carcinoma epidermoide (51%, p= 0,004). Conclusiones: El cáncer de pulmón diagnosticado en nuestro centro se caracteriza por una edad media cercana a los 65 años, un porcentaje alto de mujeres, una edad media significativamente menor en el grupo de mujeres, predominio del adenocarcinoma tanto en varones como en mujeres y un porcentaje significativamente mayor de pacientes con enfermedad avanzada entre los adenocarcinomas en comparación con los carcinomas epidermoides (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;19(3): 83-87, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de una serie de pacientes con cáncer de pulmón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53059^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
