<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043359</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thrombolysis in cardiac arrest</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Both acute myocardial infarction and pulmonary thromboembolism are responsible for a great number of cardiac arrests. Both present high rates of mortality. Thrombolysis has proved to be an effective treatment for acute myocardial infarction and pulmonary thromboembolism with shock. It would be worth considering whether thrombolysis could be effective and safe during or after cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR). Unfortunately, too few clinical studies presenting sufficient scientific data exist in order to respond adequately to this question. However, most studies they show that thrombolysis applied during and after CPR is a therapeutic option that is not associated with greater risk of serious hemorrhaging and could possibly have beneficial effects. On the other hand, experimental data exists which show that thrombolytics can attenuate neurological damage produced after CPR. Nevertheless, clinical trials would be necessary in order to adequately establish the effectiveness and safety of thrombolysis in patients who require CPR</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morante Valle, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Rivera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rucabado Aguilar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Bailén, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tanto el infarto agudo de miocardio como el tromboembolismo pulmonar son responsables de un gran número de paradas cardiorrespiratorias, presentando éstos una altísima mortalidad. La trombolisis se ha mostrado eficiente como tratamiento del infarto agudo de miocardio y del tromboembolismo pulmonar que cursa con shock. Se podría plantear si la trombolisis es eficaz y segura durante o tras las maniobras de reanimación cardiopulmonar. Desgraciadamente, existen muy pocos estudios clínicos con un nivel suficiente de evidencia científica para responder satisfactoriamente a esta pregunta. No obstante, la mayoría de los estudios muestran que la trombolisis aplicada durante y tras la reanimación cardiopulmonar es una opción terapéutica que no se asocia con un mayor riesgo de complicaciones hemorrágicas graves y que podría tener un posible efecto beneficioso. Por otra parte, existen datos experimentales que muestran que los trombolíticos pueden atenuar el daño neurológico producido tras la reanimación cardiopulmonar. Sin embargo, para establecer de manera adecuada cuál es la eficacia y la seguridad de la trombolisis en los pacientes que requieren reanimación cardiopulmonar sería necesario realizar un ensayo clínico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(2): 62-67, mar. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043359</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombolisis en la parada cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
