<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25884</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The assessment of communicative development in the early years: Adaptation of the MacArthur scales to Galician</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The MacArthur Communicative Development Inventories are a valid and reliable instrument for assessing young children&#146;s communicative and linguistic development. The present paper offers data coming from the adaptation of the MacArthur scales to Galician and their application to a sample of 722 Galician-speaking children between 8 and 30 months of age. Means and standard deviations scores for the different parts of the scale are offered. An analysis of the results obtained is carried out. An initial analysis is offered of the type of vocabulary used at different points in development. Finally data on reliability of the scales are given (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Soto, Xosé Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pereira, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los inventarios del desarrollo comunicativo MacArthur constituyen un instrumento válido y fiable para la evaluación del desarrollo comunicativo y lingüístico de los niños pequeños. Este artículo proporciona datos que provienen de la adaptación de las escalas MacArthur al gallego y su aplicación a una muestra de 722 niños gallegoparlantes entre 8 y 30 meses de edad. Se proporcionan las puntuaciones medias y desviaciones típicas para las diferentes partes de la escala. También se lleva a cabo un análisis de los resultados obtenidos y un análisis preliminar del tipo de vocabulario empleado en diferentes puntos del desarrollo. Finalmente, se proporcionan datos sobre la fiabilidad de las escalas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(3): 352-361, ago. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25884</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico del desarrollo comunicativo en la primera infancia:adaptación de las escalas MacArthur al gallego</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9819^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
