<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-1387</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Auditory training with wide-band white noise: effects on the verbal discrimination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The auditory training with wide-band white noise is a methodology for the qualitative recovery of the hearing loss in people suffering from sensorineural hearing loss. It is based on the application of a wide-band white modified noise. In a prospective study, we have assessed the modifications of the verbal reception threshold URV), the maximum discrimination (Dmax), and the discrimination coefficient (Kd) in a sample of 48 patients, who have followed a program of 15 auditory training with wide-band white noise sessions. The average improvements of the verbal discrimination variables expressed in percentage are 4.23% for the URV, a 9.04% for the kd, a 17.87% for the Dmax, and 4.32%, 10.05%, 13.04% for the binaural URV, Kd and Dmax respectively. From our results, it can be deduced that the auditory training with wide-band white noise improves the verbal discrimination measures. Not only it allows to reach the verbal reception threshold at a lower intensity, but also it moves the discrimination line towards the left. Furthermore, it increases the maximum discrimination both in binaural measurements and in those which consider all the ears (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El entrenamiento auditivo con ruido blanco de banda ancha es una metodología para la recuperación cualitativa de la pérdida auditiva en personas con hipoacusia neurosensorial, basado en la aplicación de un ruido blanco de banda ancha modificado. Hemos valorado en un estudio prospectivo las modificaciones del umbral de recepción verbal (URV), la discriminación máxima (Dmax), y el coeficiente de discriminación (Kd) en una muestra de 48 pacientes que han seguido un programa de 15 sesiones de entrenamiento auditivo con ruido blanco de banda ancha. Las mejorías medias de las variables de discriminación verbal expresadas en porcentaje son 4,23 por ciento para el URV, 9,04 por ciento para el Kd, 17,87 por ciento para la Dmax, y 4,32 por ciento, 10,05 por ciento, 13,04 por ciento para URV, Kd, y Dmax binaurales respectivamente. De nuestros resultados se concluye que el entrenamiento auditivo con ruido blanco de banda ancha mejora las medidas de discriminación verbal: permite que se alcance el umbral de recepción verbal a menor intensidad, desplaza hacia la izquierda la curva de discriminación, y aumenta la discriminación máxima, tanto en las mediciones binaurales como en las que consideran todos los oídos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;52(3): 178-190, abr. 2001. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento auditivo con ruido blanco de banda ancha: efectos sobre la discriminación verbal (II)</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Morejón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Ugidos, LJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallés Varela, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iparraguirre Bolinaga, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Knaster del Olmo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-1387</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d168^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9808</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
