<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053003</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the amygdala in facial emotion recognition in schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To provide an update on knowledge of the functions of the amygdala in healthy individuals and schizophrenics, with special emphasis on the process of facial emotion recognition. Development: The amygdala plays a key role in danger evaluation, including possible external aggressions, novelty in general and especially external stimuli that could pose a threat to survival. Consequently, the amygdala is activated in healthy individuals during facial emotion recognition, acting as a warning sign activator. Patients with schizophrenia have severe emotional difficulties and consequently the amygdala has long been considered a critical structure in investigation of this disorder. To date, structural alterations have been found in the amygdalae of schizophrenic patients, while the findings of functional neuroimaging tests have been much more contradictory, including hypo-, hyper- and normal activation, suggesting overall dysfunction. Conclusions: The results obtained to date could be due to a deficiency in the amygdalar habituation mechanism in patients with schizophrenia or to the heterogeneity of the disorder. Studies with more homogeneous samples should be performed and different study models are proposed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lomeña Caballero, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Egea,  Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo Arroyo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parellada Rodon, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mané Santacana, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Actualizar los conocimientos sobre las funciones de la amígdala en los sujetos sanos y en pacientes con esquizofrenia, centrándonos especialmente en el proceso del reconocimiento facial emocional. Desarrollo: Se considera que la amígdala protagoniza el papel de líder en la evaluación del peligro, atendiendo a las posibles agresiones provenientes del exterior, a la novedad en general y especialmente a los estímulos externos que pueden ser considerados como ambiguos para la supervivencia. Por este motivo se activa en sujetos sanos durante el reconocimiento facial de las emociones, y actúa como activador de la señal de alerta. Los pacientes con esquizofrenia presentan serias dificultades emocionales, por lo que se ha considerado a la amígdala desde hace tiempo como una estructura crucial en el estudio de la esquizofrenia. Hasta la fecha, se han encontrado alteraciones estructurales en la amígdala de los pacientes esquizofrénicos, mientras que los hallazgos realizados mediante neuroimagen funcional son mucho más dispares, e incluyen hipoactivación, hiperactivación o normoactivación, lo que indicaría disfunción global. Conclusiones: Los resultados obtenidos hasta la fecha pueden ser consecuencia de un déficit en el mecanismo de habituación amigdalar en los pacientes con esquizofrenia o por la propia heterogeneidad del trastorno. Se sugiere que se deberían realizar trabajos con muestras más homogéneas y se proponen diferentes modelos de estudio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);14(1): 31-39, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la amígdala en el reconocimiento facial de las emociones en la esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d693^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10557^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
