<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88318</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical diagnosis and physical examination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In children, medical history and meticulous examination are essential to the diagnosis andfuture treatment of all the alterations contributing to sleep breathing disorders. Examination ofthe oropharynx aids assessment of hypertrophy of the palatine tonsils, while fiberopticendoscopy assists in the diagnosis of adenoid hypertrophy. Among radiological examinations,only cephalometry has proved to be useful in the study of the facial skeleton. Lateral radiographyof the nasopharynx to study adenoid vegetations has been surpassed by fi beroptic endoscopy interms of diagnostic performance. All examinations facilitate an etiological and topographicaldiagnosis of patients with sleep breathing disorders. The diagnosis of respiratory problems thataffect children&#146;s dentofacial development can begin at a very early age, since early detection isessential to preventing the effects of these alterations on orofacial morphology and function.This article reviews the basic and additional dental examinations that should be conducted inchildren with upper airway obstruction and a medical history of sleep breathing disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ademà, Joan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubert Adelantado, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matiñó Soler, eusebi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellet Dalmau, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico y futuro tratamiento de todas las alteraciones que contribuyen a provocar trastornosrespiratorios del sueño (TRS) en la edad infantil. La exploración de la orofaringe permitela valoración de la hipertrofi a de las amígdalas palatinas y la fi broendoscopia el diagnóstico dela hipertrofi a adenoidea. De las exploraciones radiológicas, únicamente la cefalometría se hamostrado útil para el estudio del esqueleto facial. La radiografía lateral de cavum para estudiode las vegetaciones adenoideas ha sido superada por la fi broendoscopia en cuanto a rentabilidaddiagnóstica. Todas las exploraciones permiten el diagnóstico etiológico y topográfi co delpaciente con TRS. Desde edades muy precoces, se puede iniciar el diagnóstico de problemasrespiratorios que afectan al desarrollo dentofacial del niño, siendo clave su precoz detecciónpara prevenir sus efectos sobre la morfología y la función orofacial. En este capítulo, se revisanlas exploraciones básicas y complementarias odontológicas que deben llevarse a cabo en losniños con obstrucción de la vía aérea superior y clínica de TRS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;61(supl.1): 40-44, dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico clínico y exploración física</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9251^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
