<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127160</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Promoting Cardiovascular Health Worldwide: Strategies, Challenges, and Opportunities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death in the world, affecting not only industrialized but, above all, low- and middle-income countries, where it has overtaken infectious diseases as the first cause of death and its impact threatens social and economic development. The increased prevalence of cardiovascular disease in recent years together with projected mortality for the coming decades constitute an irrefutable argument for the urgent implementation of well-planned interventions to control the pandemic of cardiovascular diseases, especially in the more economically deprived countries. The combination of behavioral, social, environmental, and biological factors, and others related to health care systems, that contribute to the development of cardiovascular diseases requires a multi-sector strategy that promotes a healthy lifestyle, reduces cardiovascular risk factors, and cuts mortality and morbidity through quality health care services. These proposals should be guided by leaders in the scientific community, government, civil society, private sector, and local communities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narula, Jagat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares son la primera causa de muerte en el mundo, y afectan no solo a países industrializados, sino sobre todo a países de ingresos medios-bajos, donde han superado a las enfermedades infecciosas como primera causa de muerte y su impacto amenaza al desarrollo social y económico de estas regiones. El aumento en la prevalencia de las enfermedades cardiovasculares de los últimos años, junto con las proyecciones de mortalidad para las próximas décadas, supone un argumento irrefutable acerca del carácter urgente de implementar intervenciones bien planificadas para controlar la pandemia de enfermedades cardiovasculares, especialmente en los países económicamente más deprimidos. La combinación de factores de comportamiento, sociales, medioambientales, biológicos y relacionados con sistemas de salud que contribuyen al desarrollo de la enfermedades cardiovasculares requiere una estrategia multisectorial que promueva estilos de vida saludables, reduzca los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y disminuya la mortalidad y la morbilidad a través de servicios sanitarios de calidad. Dichas propuestas deben ser dirigidas por líderes de la comunidad científica, el gobierno, la sociedad civil, el sector privado y las comunidades locales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(9): 724-730, sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Promoción de la salud cardiovascular global: estrategias, retos y oportunidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
