<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156659</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care plans for chronic kidney disease patients in hemodialysis: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD) is considered a current public health problem worldwide due to its prevalence and growing incidence in the population, its relative importance in the health burden of our country, its permanent chronic behavior, its lethal potential and its impact on the patient, family and nations. Therefore requires a comprehensive care based on good clinical practice based on evidence. Method: A systematic scientific literature review of the articles published between 2004 and 2014, done in Spanish, Portuguese and English, and available in full text. A thorough search for original works in databases such as Cuiden Plus, CINAHL, SciELO, Lilacs, PubMed, and Nursing Ovid. A critical assessment of the scientific quality of the studies, applying the CASPe research grids, and the STROBE checklist. Findings: The themes that came out as a result of the articles analysis were: Perspective on Nursing models and theories for caring patients in hemodialysis; Common nursing language and nursing care process; Nursing diagnosis for the patient in hemodialysis; Education for the patient in hemodialysis; Self-care for the patient in hemodialysis; Family&#146;s important role when caring for a patient; Patient satisfaction as a quality objective. Conclusions: Nursing models, theories and taxonomy allow a broader, deeper and comprehensive view of nursing that eases the path to excellence in patient care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Duque Castaño, Germán Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tovar Cortes, David Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ángel Ángel, Zahira Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad renal crónica es considerada actualmente un problema de salud pública en el ámbito mundial por su prevalencia e incidencia creciente en la población, su importancia relativa en la carga de enfermedad del país, su comportamiento crónico o permanente, su potencial letal, y su impacto en el paciente, su familia y los sistemas sanitarios. Por lo tanto requiere una atención integral fundamentada en buenas prácticas clínicas basadas en la evidencia. Método: Revisión sistemática de la literatura científica de artículos publicados entre 2004 a 2014, en idioma español, portugués e inglés, y accesibles a texto completo. Búsqueda exhaustiva y reproducible de trabajos originales en las bases de datos Cuiden Plus, CINAHL, SciELO, Lilacs, PubMed, y Nursing Ovid. Valoración crítica de la calidad científica de los estudios aplicando las parrillas de investigación de CASPe, y la lista de chequeo STROBE. Resultados: Los temas que surgieron del análisis de los artículos fueron: Perspectiva sobre modelos y teorías de enfermería en el cuidado del paciente en hemodiálisis, lenguaje común enfermero, diagnósticos de enfermería en el paciente en hemodiálisis, educación y autocuidado del paciente en hemodiálisis, importancia de la familia en el cuidado del paciente, satisfacción del paciente como objetivo de calidad. Conclusiones: Los modelos, teorías y taxonomía permiten una visión más amplia, profunda y abarcadora de la enfermería que viabiliza el camino a la excelencia en la atención al paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;19(3): 202-2013, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156659</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados de enfermería en el paciente con enfermedad renal crónica en hemodiálisis: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
