<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91861</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales-21 (Dass-21) in Spainish college students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of the present study was to examine the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Depression Anxiety StressSCales, in its 21-item version (DASS-21), in a simple of Spanish college students. The sample was composed of 759 participants (532 females), with a mean age of 19.63 years (SD=2.03). Results showed that the levels of internal consistency for the subscales of the DASS-21 ranged from 0.73 to 0.81. With respect to the internal structure of the DASS-21, the confirmatory factor analysis indicated that the three-factor model, composed by the Depression, Anxiety and Stress factors, was the one with the best fit indices in comparison to the remaining competent models. No item in the DASS.-21 presented differences in functioning due to gender of participants. Likewise, statistically significant differences were found due to gender between mean scores in the Stress subscale. Consistent with previous literature, the DASS-21 seems to be a useful and brief assessment instrument, of depression, anxiety and stress in nonclinical populations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Pedrero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lemos Giráldez, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paino, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El principal propósito del presente trabajo fue examinar las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española de la Escala de Depresión, Ansiedad y Estrés en su versión de 21 ítems (DASS-21) en una muestra de universitarios españoles. La muestra la formaron 759 participantes (532 mujeres), con una edad media de 10,63 años (DT=2,03). Los resultados mostraron que los niveles de consistencia interna para la subescalas de la DASS-21 oscilaron entre 0,73 y 0,81. La obtención de evidencias de estructura interna de la DASS-21 oscilaron entre 0,73 y 0,81. La obtención de evidencias de estructura interna de las DASS-21 mediante análisis factorial confirmatorio, indicó que el modelo tridimensional concretado en las dimensiones Depresión, Ansiedad y Estrés fue el que mejores índices de ajuste mostró en comparación con el resto de modelos alternativos. Ningún ítem de la DASS-21 mostró funcionamiento diferencial en función del sexo de los participantes. Asimismo, se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en función del sexo entre las puntuaciones medias de la subescala Estrés. En convergencia con la literatura previa, la DASS-21 parece ser un instrumento de medida útil, breve, de rápida administración y con adecuadas propiedades psicométricas para la valoración de la depresión, la ansiedad y el estrés en población no clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;16(2/3): 215-226, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91861</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades Psicométricas de la depression anxiety and stress scales-21 (Dass-21) en universitarios españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
