<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110895</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Single port video-assisted transumbilical appendectomy. What have we gained and what have we lost after 754 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Single-port transumbilical laparoscopically assisted appendectomy (TULAA) has become the preferred method of treating appendicitis in our Department. At first, it was reserved for non complicated cases, and gradually for the rest of them. We have gained experience, and it is time to share it, evaluate the results and raise into new possibilities. Material and Methods. We performed a retrospective statistical analysis of undergone changes over the last years, referring to aspects such as surgical indications, and postoperative complications, hospital stays and re-admissions. Results. From September 2003 to January 2012, a total of 1,022appendectomies were performed. Eight hundred and forty-one children underwent TULAA, 89.65% were completed with no problems. In 179patients, open appendectomy was initially chosen. In those cases, the reasons were complicated appendicitis, obesity or surgeon&#146;s preference(43 in the first year and just 3 in the last one). Ninety seven patients had postoperative complications of any kind, fifteen were readmitted to the hospital and 3 were reoperated because of intestinal obstruction. Medical cost savings were estimated around 750.000 &#128;.Conclusions. We think that TULAA is a simple and easy learning procedure, which does not result in any increase in complications, inexpensive and beneficial for patients. However, along these years, our surgical staff may have lost skills and training opportunities in conventional laparoscopic surgery. So although TULAA is still our preferred method in appendicectomy, selected cases will undergo laparoscopic appendectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Caballero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pisón Chacón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Temprano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goñi Orayen, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La técnica de elección para la apendicectomía en nuestro servicio es la videoasistida transumbilical por puerto único(AVT). Inicialmente reservada para casos no complicados y paulatinamente en todos. Hemos adquirido gran experiencia y ha llegado el momento de compartirla, evaluar los resultados y plantearnos otras posibilidades. Material y métodos. Trabajo retrospectivo y descriptivo en el que se valoran, mediante análisis estadístico, los cambios sufridos a lo largo de los años de AVT en aspectos como mejoras técnicas, indicaciones, complicaciones, estancias y reingresos. Resultados. Desde septiembre de 2003 hemos realizado 1.022 apendicectomías (61% varones). En 841 casos iniciamos abordaje umbilical, completándose sin problemas en el 89,65%. En 179 pacientes el cirujano optó por una laparotomía directa por apendicitis complicada, obesidado preferencia personal (43 en el primer año y solo 3 en 2011). Noventa y siete enfermos tuvieron complicaciones, de los cuales 15 reingresaron para tratamiento médico y 3 fueron reintervenidos. El ahorro frente a la laparoscopia se estima en 750.000 &#128;.Discusión. La AVT es una técnica sencilla, fácil de aprender, sin complicaciones añadidas, barata y beneficiosa para los pacientes. Sin embargo, al limitarnos a ella hemos perdido oportunidades y habilidades laparoscópicas. Conclusiones. La AVT sigue siendo nuestra preferencia en la apendicectomía, pero cada vez más pacientes seleccionados serán sometidos a laparoscopia convencional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;25(4): 197-200, oct.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110895</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apendicectomía videoasistida transumbilical por puerto único. Qué hemos ganado y qué hemosperdido después de 754 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14871^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
