<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154270</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prostate cáncer recurrence after focal therapy: treatment options</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Focal therapy is a novel treatment option in localised prostate cancer with or without a visible lesion on MRI. Treatment for low to intermediate risk prostate cancer with focal therapy has demonstrated good short to medium term outcomes with fewer undesirable genitourinary side effects. This has made focal therapy more appealing to men who find the implications of radical treatment unacceptable or are unable to tolerate active surveillance. In this paper we review the literature for treatment options in prostate cancer recurrence post focal therapy. We also cover the different definitions of failure agreed upon in previous consensus meetings, as well as their implications on future management focal therapy patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Shah, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arya, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ahmed, HU</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hamid, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillaumier, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia focal es una opción nueva de tratamiento en cáncer de próstata localizado con o sin lesión visible en la RMN. El tratamiento con terapia focal para el cáncer de próstata de riesgo bajo e intermedio ha demostrado buenos resultados a corto y medio plazo don menos efectos secundarios genitourinarios indeseables. Esto ha hecho la terapia focal más atractiva para varones que encuentran inaceptables las implicaciones del tratamiento radical o no son capaces de tolerar la vigilancia activa. En este artículo revisamos la literatura sobre las opciones de tratamiento en cáncer de próstata recurrente después de terapia focal. También cubrimos las diferentes definiciones de fracaso salidas del acuerdo en reuniones de consenso previas, así como sus implicaciones en el manejo futuro de pacientes de terapia focal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;69(6): 375-383, jul.-ago. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recurrencia del cáncer de próstata después de Terapia Focal: opciones de tratamiento de rescate</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29830^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29830^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29830^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
