<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81726</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inverted urothelial papilloma: Our clinical experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study of inverted urothelial papilloma in our area. Methods: A study was conducted of inverted urothelial papillomas diagnosed at our center from January 1994 to December 2007. This was a retrospective and prospective study with a descriptive statistical analysis: urological history, reason for consultation, diagnostic methods, tumor focality, follow-up method, prognosis, and recurrence. SPSS software version 13 was used for statistical analysis. Results: Fourteen inverted papillomas were diagnosed in the study period in patients with a median age of 59 years. The presenting complaint was hematuria in 7 patients (50%), followed by low back pain in 2 patients (14.28%), and irritative syndrome in 1 patient (7.14%). The tumor was incidentally diagnosed in 4 patients (28.5%). A single relapse/recurrence occurred in a low-grade tumor during the follow-up period. Conclusions: Prognosis, recurrence, and malignant potential of this tumor are unclear, and controversy exists in the literature on this subject. Thus, although we think this is a benign tumor, we advise follow-up as if it were a low-grade urothelial tumor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López García Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Hidalgo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buendía González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolufer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oladre, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampietro Crespo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bethancourt, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudio de los papilomas invertidos uroteliales en nuestra área. Material y métodos: Realizamos un estudio de los papilomas invertidos uroteliales diagnosticados en nuestro centro entre enero de 1994 y diciembre de 2007. Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo y prospectivo con análisis estadístico descriptivo: antecedentes urológicos, motivo de consulta, método diagnóstico, focalidad tumoral, método de seguimiento, pronóstico y recurrencia. Se realizó un estudio estadístico con el software SPSS versión 13. Resultados: En el período de estudio se han diagnosticado 14 papilomas invertidos, con una mediana de 59 años. El motivo de consulta fue hematuria en 7 enfermos (50%), seguido de dolor lumbar en 2 enfermos (14,28%) y de síndrome irritativo en 1 enfermo (7,14%), fue diagnosticado en 4 enfermos (28,5%) de manera incidental. Durante el período de seguimiento sólo se produjo una recidiva/recurrencia en un tumor de bajo grado. Conclusiones: El pronóstico, la recurrencia y el potencial de malignización de este tumor no están claros, existiendo controversias en la literatura médica mundial, hecho por el cual aunque desde nuestro punto de vista su naturaleza es benigna, aconsejamos un seguimiento como si se tratase de un tumor urotelial de bajo grado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(4): 386-389, abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papiloma invertido urotelial: nuestra experiencia clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31219^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32875^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
