<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054165</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sydenham&#146;s chorea: report of a case treated with carbamazepine with excellent clinical response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sydenham's chorea is the most common cause of acquired chorea in childhood. This disorder is secondary to an autoimmune response against basal ganglia in the brain, induced by prior streptococcal infection. Chorea is a major criterion for the diagnosis of rheumatic fever and can also be the presenting feature of the disease. The incidence of rheumatic fever has been markedly decreased by improved socioeconomic conditions and increased antibiotic prescription. In the last two decades, however, this disease has reappeared and should be taken into account in the evaluation of children with movement disorders.         Chorea is characterized by acute exacerbations that can cause substantial functional impairment and may warrant drug treatment. Carbamazepine has proven to be both efficacious and safe in the treatment of this condition.         We present a case of rheumatic chorea, in which carbamazepine therapy produced excellent clinical response</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabacas García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Ruiz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayol Canals, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Arévalo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La corea de Sydenham es la causa más frecuente de corea adquirida en el niño. Se presenta por la existencia de una respuesta autoinmunitaria contra los núcleos de la base del cerebro, inducida tras una infección estreptocócica. La corea es uno de los criterios mayores de diagnóstico de fiebre reumática y puede ser la forma de presentación de esta entidad. La mejoría de las condiciones socioeconómicas y el tratamiento antibiótico han condicionado un descenso importante de la incidencia de fiebre reumática. En los últimos 20 años se ha producido un repunte de la enfermedad, que se ha de tener en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial de los trastornos del movimiento en la edad pediátrica.         La corea evoluciona generalmente de forma subaguda con episodios de exacerbación que generan una importante repercusión funcional planteando la necesidad de un tratamiento farmacológico. Una de las posibilidades terapéuticas es la carbamazepina que se ha mostrado eficaz y segura en el tratamiento de esta entidad.         Presentamos un caso de corea reumática que se trató con carbamazepina con una excelente respuesta clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(1): 80-83, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Corea de Sydenham: presentación de un caso tratado con carbamazepina con excelente respuesta clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2869^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12624^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12624^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12624^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2869^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
