<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050354</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Annual rhythm of urinary excretion of lipoperoxidation products</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: many biological features are linked to daily, annual, or seasonal rhythms. One of these features could be the production and urinary excretion of lipoperoxidation products (TBARS), which are modified by crenotherapy with different mineromedicinal waters. The objective of the present article was to analyse whether urinary excretion of TBARS depends on the time of the year in which it is determined. Material and methods: urinary samples were obtained from 230 volunteers from the Social Thermalism Program of the Institute for the Elderly and Social Services (Instituto de Mayores y Servicios Sociales [IMSERSO]). There were 115 men and 115 women (aged 52-81years) who where assigned to two different spas at six different times of the year: 110 were assigned to the first spa and 120 to the second. TBARS concentration was determined on arrival at the spa by means of spectrophotometry; a clinical history was also taken, including blood pressure measurement. Results: the mean total TBARS excretion on arrival was 0.418 ± 0.025 nmol/mg of creatinine for the population from the first spa and 0.368 ± 0.01 nmol/mg of creatinine for the second. One of the reasons why these values differed between the two populations was that they were determined in different months of the year, showing a maximum excretion in July and a minimum in November. Conclusion: this study shows that excretion rates of lipid peroxidation products follows an annual rhythm</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramón, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Torres, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo de Santos, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca Giralde, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, Encarnaciónc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: existen numerosos rasgos biológicos ligados a ritmos diarios, anuales o estacionales. Uno de estos rasgos podría ser la producción y eliminación urinaria de productos de lipoperoxidación (sustancias reactivas al ácido tiobarbitúrico [TBARS]) eliminados por orina que son modificados por la crenoterapia con diferentes aguas mineromedicinales. El objetivo del presente artículo es analizar si la eliminación urinaria de TBARS depende de la época del año en que se determina. Material y métodos: se han obtenido muestras de orina de 230 voluntarios del Programa de Termalismo Social del IMSERSO (edad 52-81 años), 115 varones y 115 mujeres que se adscribieron a 2 balnearios diferentes en 6 épocas distintas del año: 110 al primero y 120 al segundo. A la llegada al balneario se determinó la concentración de TBARS mediante espectrofotometría; paralelamente se realizó a los pacientes historia clínica que incluyó registros de la presión arterial. Resultados: la media de eliminación total de TBARS a la llegada al balneario en la población del primero fue de 0,418 ± 0,025 nmol/mg de creatinina; en la segunda fue de 0,368 ± 0,01 nmol/mg de creatinina. Una de las posibles razones de los diferentes valores de ambas poblaciones, con un máximo de excreción urinaria en julio y un mínimo en noviembre, fue el hecho de que las determinaciones se realizaron en diferentes meses del año en ambas poblaciones. Conclusión: este estudio muestra que las tasas de eliminación de productos de lipoperoxidación siguen un ritmo anual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);41(5): 285-288, sep. 2006. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La eliminación urinaria de productos de lipoperoxidación depende de un ritmo biológico anual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30480^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29755^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
