<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055954</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of sleep disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sleep disorders encompass pathology of very    diverse origin with clinical expressions as varied as    insomnia, hypersomnia, breathing disorders, complex    motor disorders, etc. Some of these processes can be    diagnosed clinically, while for the evaluation, diagnosis    and treatment of others a battery of tests are required    that are carried out in a sleep laboratory. Given the    complexity and the cost of these tests, their indication    must be based on a suitable evaluation and clinical    exploration of the subject. Besides establishing the    pertinence of the indication of the study, such    evaluation must establish the type of test to be carried    out. We review the different diagnostic tests available    in the sleep units: polysomnography, respiratory    poligraphy, multiple sleep latency test, maintenance of    wakefulness test, Osler test, video- EEG for sleep and    actigraphy. We comment on basic aspects of these,    both theoretical and practical</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Gurtubay, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de sueño engloban patología de    muy diverso origen con manifestaciones clínicas tan    variadas como insomnio, hipersomnia, trastornos respiratorios,    trastornos motores complejos, etc., Algunos    de estos procesos son de diagnóstico clínico, mientras    que otros precisan para su evaluación, diagnóstico    y tratamiento de una batería de pruebas que se realizan    en un laboratorio de sueño. Dado la complejidad y    el coste de estas pruebas, la indicación de las mismas    debe apoyarse en una adecuada evaluación y exploración    clínica del sujeto. Además de establecer la pertinencia    de la indicación del estudio, dicha evaluación    establecerá el tipo de prueba a realizar. Se revisan las    diferentes pruebas diagnósticas disponibles en las unidades    de sueño: polisomnografía, poligrafía respiratoria,    test de latencias múltiples, test de mantenimiento    de la vigilancia, test de Osler, el vídeo EEG de sueño y    la actigrafía. Se comentan aspectos básicos, teóricos y    prácticos de las mismas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;30(supl.1): 37-51, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055954</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudios diagnósticos en patología del sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15145^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
