<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054529</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene therapy for Parkinson's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Parkinson's disease is a chronic and progressive disorder whose treatment does not prevent middle term appearance of invalidating motor and psychic complications. Gene therapy techniques which are increasingly applied in the field of neurodegenerative diseases are added to the possibility of treatment of this disease. Among the existing modalities, the in vivo strategies that use potent viral vectors are those which have obtained the best results in the different existing models of the disease. This article aims to review the information regarding the use of these latter techniques, the therapeutic trials that have been conducted and the advantages and disadvantages that the use of the different vectors have</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Barreiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gallego, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Parkinson es un trastorno crónico y progresivo cuyo tratamiento no impide a medio plazo la aparición de complicaciones motoras y psíquicas invalidantes. Las técnicas de terapia génica de aplicación cada vez mayor en el campo de las enfermedades neurodegenerativas se suman a las posibilidades de tratamiento de esta patología. Entre las modalidades existentes, las estrategias in vivo que emplean potentes vectores virales son las que mejores resultados han obtenido en los distintos modelos existentes de la enfermedad. Este artículo pretende revisar la información referente al empleo de estas últimas técnicas, los ensayos terapéuticos que se han llevado a cabo y las ventajas e inconvenientes que tiene la utilización de los diferentes vectores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;22(1): 27-38, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia génica en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5955</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
