<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102243</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SOD1-N196 mutation in a family with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: N19S mutation is produced by substitution in the 139 position of SOD1 and was described by Mayeux in a patient with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS). He suggested that it did not have a causal effect as it was found in asymptomatic and sporadic cases. Other authors in later articles did not agree. Material and methods: We describe a family with 4 members with ALS patients and attempt to find the carrier of the N19S mutation of the propositus. Molecular studies were performed on 15 members of the family of a different order. Results: The ALS cases were found in the maternal line of the propositus. The presence of the mutation was detected in 3 people, the other two were asymptomatic. One of patients with ALS in the family, who died  previously, did not have the mutation. Two of the sons of this case and another of the other case did not show it. On the other hand, N19S mutation was only present in paternal branch of the propositus, where there were no cases. Conclusion: The described family supports the hypothesis by Mayeux and against that mutation N19S has pathological consequences, since mutation is only in the family line where there are no cases with ALS. In consequence, although the described case is included as a familiar form, it cannot be attributed to the mutation, and its relationship with N19S should be considered as casual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valencia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Redondo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, P. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La N19S es una mutación por la sustitución en la posición 139 de la SOD1 y fue descrita por Mayeux et al, donde los autores sugirieron que no tenía un efecto causal al hallarse casos asintomáticos y esporádicos pero autores posteriores han sugerido lo contrario. Material y métodos: Se describe una familia con 4 pacientes con ELA en los que en el caso propósito es portador de la mutación N19S. Se realiza un estudio molecular en 15 personas de la familia de diferente orden. Resultados: La enfermedad se halla en la línea materna del primer caso. Se detecta la presencia de la mutación en tres personas, el primer y dos asintomáticos. Uno de los pacientes afectos de ELA de la familia que murió previamente, no presentaba la mutación. Dos de los hijos del tercer caso y otro del cuarto caso tampoco la mostraron. Contrariamente, la mutación está presente en la rama paterna del primer caso, que es asintomática. Conclusión: La familia descrita apoya la hipótesis de Mayeux et al y va en contra que la mutación N19S tenga connotaciones patológicas, ya que la mutación se encuentra en la línea familiar no afecta de la enfermedad y no está en la línea con enfermos de ELA. En consecuencia, aunque el caso descrito es una forma familiar no puede ser atribuido a la mutación y su relación debe ser considerada como casual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(1): 11-15, ene.-feb. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mutación SOD1-N19S en una familia de esclerosis lateral amiotrófica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33413^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53723^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
