<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106072</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abortion in immigrant women: the perspective of the social and health professionals who deal with the demand in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The high fertility rate of immigrant women resident in Spain raises the question of studying how many elective abortions they have, the circumstances behind the pregnancy which they decide to interrupt, their reasons for having the abortion and the obstacles encountered. In-depth interviews of the professionals &#150;both of social services and health care&#150; who deal with the demand for elective abortions at different stages in the process were carried out in Madrid. For women from other countries, elective abortion is closely associated with their situation as immigrants: from the failure of birth control to the impossibility of caring for the baby. The most relevant problems are the opening hours of birth control services, the bureaucratisation of health care provision and the lack of transparency regarding financial criteria in a framework of legal restrictions and insufficient public resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llácer Gil de Ramales, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Blanco,  M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazarrasa Alvear, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Martín,  C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La elevada fecundidad del importante contingente de mujeres inmigrantes residentes en España plantea el interés de explorar su contribución a la Interrupción Voluntaria del Embarazo (IVE), las circunstancias del embarazo que se interrumpe, las razones para hacerlo y las barreras que encuentran hasta realizarlo. Para ello se ha hecho en Madrid una encuesta en profundidad a profesionales que atienden la demanda de IVE en distintos puntos del circuito sociosanitario. En mujeres de otros países la IVE está muy asociada a su situación de inmigrantes: desde el fallo en la anticoncepción que conduce al embarazo hasta la imposibilidad de asumir el cuidado de la criatura. Destacan la inadecuación horaria de las consultas de anticoncepción, la burocratización del itinerario asistencial y la falta de transparencia de los criterios de financiación en un marco normativo restrictivo de escasos recursos públicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(55): 13-17, oct.-dic. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El aborto en las mujeres inmigrantes. Una perspectiva desde los profesionales sociosanitarios que atienden la demanda en Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3287^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20210^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
