<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043037</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimal residual disease in acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a new concept of complete remission</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Early response to induction treatment is one of the most important prognostic factors in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). Cytological remission is currently achieved in 95-98 % of these patients, although a significant proportion will later relapse. More sensitive techniques are required to measure residual leukemia and establish a new definition of complete remission.                 Objective: To identify minimal residual disease (MRD) by immunological techniques and define its prognostic impact in children with ALL.                 Methods: MRD was studied by flow cytometry in 53 children diagnosed in our department between June 1999 and April 2003 and treated using the Pethema protocols. All the children achieved complete cytological remission (&lt; 5 %) with the induction treatment and had at least one useful phenotype for follow-up: 11 % were T phenotype, one was biphenotypic and the remainder were B cell leukemias. Bone marrow samples were analyzed post-induction, post-consolidation, after 6 and 11 months of maintenance treatment, at the end of treatment, and 3 months later. The positivity threshold was set at 0.01 % and the sensitivity of the technique was 1 x 10­4-1 x 10­5.                 Results: A total of 199 samples were analyzed. Thirty-seven percent of the post-induction and 20 % of the post-consolidation samples analyzed were MRD-positive. Elimination was slower in patients with a T phenotype and in high-risk patients according to the traditional classification. After a median follow-up of 26 months, event free survival (EFS) in the group as a whole was 92 %. The EFS rate in the patients who were MRD-positive post-induction was 79 %. None of the patients who were MRD-negative post-induction has developed recurrence.                 Conclusion: Study of MRD is essential and should be included in all current treatment protocols for children with ALL. Its usefulness derives from the prognostic impact of the response to induction treatment. Continued sequential monitoring may predict recurrence before the onset of clinical or hematologic manifestations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacio García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez de Toledo Codina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida Vilá, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solsona Riera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Aramburu, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La respuesta precoz al tratamiento de inducción es uno de los factores pronósticos más importantes en niños afectados de leucemia linfoblástica aguda (LLA). Actualmente se consigue la remisión citológica en el 95-98 % de estos pacientes; sin embargo, un porcentaje importante recaerá posteriormente. Es preciso utilizar técnicas más sensibles para medir la leucemia residual y establecer un nuevo concepto de remisión completa.                Objetivo: Identificar por técnicas inmunológicas la enfermedad mínima residual (EMR) y conocer su impacto pronóstico en niños afectados de LLA.                 Métodos: Estudiamos la EMR por citometría de flujo en 53 niños diagnosticados en nuestro servicio desde junio de 1999 hasta abril de 2003 y tratados según protocolos del grupo Pethema. Todos habían conseguido la remisión citológica (&lt; 5 %) con el tratamiento de inducción y tenían al menos un fenotipo útil para seguimiento. El 11 % eran de fenotipo T, 1 bifenotípica y el resto eran leucemias tipo B. Se analizaron muestras de médula ósea postinducción, posconsolidación, a 6 y 11 meses de mantenimiento, al final del tratamiento y 3 meses después. Se colocó el umbral de positividad en 0,01 %, siendo la sensibilidad de la técnica de 1 x 10­4-1 x 10­5.                 Resultados: Se analizaron un total de 199 muestras. El 37 % de las muestras analizadas postinducción y el 20 % posconsolidación eran EMR1. La eliminación fue más lenta en los pacientes de fenotipo T y en los de alto riesgo según la clasificación tradicional. Con una mediana de seguimiento de 26 meses, la supervivencia libre de enfermedad (SLE) del grupo completo fue del 92 %. Los pacientes con una EMR1 postinducción tuvieron una tasa de SLE del 79 %. Ningún paciente con EMR-postinducción ha presentado recidiva.                 Conclusión: El estudio de la EMR es imprescindible y debe estar incluida en todos los protocolos de tratamiento actuales para niños con LLA. Su utilidad radica en el impacto pronóstico de la respuesta al tratamiento de inducción. La monitorización secuencial posterior puede predecir recaídas antes de que aparezcan manifestaciones clínicas o hematológicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(5): 390-395, nov. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043037</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leucemia mínima residual: nuevo concepto de remisión completa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52571^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32119^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
