<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19999</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral activation during Stroop's test in a case of early focal brain injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) offers an important advantage over other functional neuroimaging techniques used with children because of its harmlessness. Previous studies conducted with adults with alexia suggested two ways the brain can reorganise reading after a brain injury affecting the left hemisphere, one contralateral and the other ipsilateral. Case report. We describe a study carried out using fMRI of a 10-year-old girl with an injury to the left hemisphere caused by a fishing harpoon when she was 6 years old. As a result of the accident the girl presented a right hemiparesia. The girl&#146;s parents and teachers also reported difficulties in the acquisition of reading-writing and arithmetic, as well as a certain degree of attentional deficit. An fMRI exploration was performed while the girl was doing the Stroop test. The structural MR images showed left hemisphere cortical lesions in the orbital and angular gyrus regions, in addition to the caudate and putamen nuclei, and in the inferior longitudinal bundle. The fRMI revealed a strong overactivation of the right dorsolateral frontal cortex, in the evaluation of interference, and activations of the right angular and bilateral supramarginal gyri, in the evaluation of word reading. Conclusion. The functional study suggests the existence of a reorganisation of reading that is both intra- and interhemispheric (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La resonancia magnética funcional (RMf) presenta una gran ventaja frente a otras técnicas en estudios de neuroimagen funcional con niños debido a su inocuidad. Estudios previos de adultos con alexia sugieren dos vías de reorganización cerebral de la lectura tras una lesión cerebral del hemisferio izquierdo, una contralateral y la otra ipsilateral. Caso clínico. Describimos un estudio mediante RMf de una niña de 10 años con una lesión del hemisferio izquierdo causada por un arpón de pesca, lesión ocurrida a los 6 años de edad. Como consecuencia del accidente la niña presenta hemiparesia derecha. Los padres y profesores informaron también de dificultades en la adquisición de la lectoescritura y el cálculo, así como cierto déficit atencional. Se realizó una exploración mediante RMf mientras la niña ejecutaba la prueba de Stroop. Las imágenes de RM estructural demostraron lesiones corticales del hemisferio izquierdo en la región orbital y el giro angular, así como en los núcleos caudado y putamen y en el fascículo longitudinal inferior. La RMf reveló una fuerte sobreactivación del córtex frontal dorsolateral derecho, en la evaluación de la interferencia, y activaciones del giro angular derecho y supramarginal bilateral, en la evaluación de la lectura de palabras. Conclusión. El estudio funcional sugiere la existencia de una reorganización intra e interhemisférica de la lectura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(4): 343-346, feb. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Activación cerebral durante el test de Stroop en un caso de lesión cerebral focal temprana</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Navarro, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Hernández, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bargalló, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Ruiz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lage, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caldú Ferrús, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Pineda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falcón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19999</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d1956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
