<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135063</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Whey and soy protein supplements changes body composition in patients with Crohn&#146;s disease undergoing azathioprine and anti-TNF-alpha therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Crohn&#146;s disease (CD) is a chronic transmural inflammation of the gastrointestinal tract of unknown cause. Malnutrition associated with active CD has been reduced although obesity has increased. Dietary strategies such as those with high-protein have been proposed to reduce body fat. This study compares the effects of two supplements on the nutritional status of CD patients. Materials and Methods: 68 CD patients were randomized in two groups: whey protein group (WP) and soy protein group (SP). Using bioimpedance analysis, anthropometry and albumin and pre-albumin dosages the nutritional status was measured before starting the intervention and after 8 and 16 weeks. The disease activity was determined by Crohn&#146;s Disease Activity Index and serum C-reactive protein dosage and dietary intake by 24h dietary recalls. Results: Forty-one patients concluded the study and both supplements changed body composition similarly. Triceps skin fold thickness (p&lt; 0.001) and body fat percentage (p=0.001) decreased, whereas mid-arm muscle circumference (p=0.004), corrected arm muscle area (p=0.005) and body lean percentage (p=0.001) increased. Conclusions: For Crohn&#146;s disease patients undergoing anti TNF-alpha and azatioprine therapies, supplementation with whey and soy proteins changes body composition through reduction of body fat and thus contributes to control inflammation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morcillo, André Moreno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wu, Chao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sgarbieri, Valdemiro Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilela, Maria Marluce dos Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oya, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Severino, Silvana Dalge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado, Júlia Figueiredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coy, Cláudio Saddy Rodrigues</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad de Crohn (EC) es un trastorno inflamatorio crónico transmural del tracto gastrointestinal de carácter desconocida. La desnutrición asociada con EC activa se ha reducido a pesar de la obesidad que ha aumentado. Se han propuesto estrategias dietéticas, como aquellos con alto contenido de proteínas para reducir la grasa corporal. Este estudio compara los efectos de dos suplementos sobre el estado nutricional de los pacientes con EC. Materiales y Métodos: Fueron randomizados en dos grupos 68 pacientes con EC: el grupo de proteína de suero y el grupo de proteína de soya. Se utilizó el análisis de bioimpedancia eléctrica, la antropometría y dosificaciones de albúmina y prealbúmina del estado nutricional midiéndose antes de comenzar la intervención y después de 8 y 16 semanas. La actividad de la enfermedad se determinó por Índice de Actividad de Enfermedad de Crohn (CDAI), dosificación en suero de la proteína C reactiva y la ingesta dietética por recordatorio de 24h. Resultados: Cuarenta y un pacientes concluyeron el estudio y ambos suplementos cambiaron la composición corporal de manera similar. El espesor del pliegue cutáneo del tríceps (p &lt;0,001) y el porcentaje de grasa corporal (p = 0,001) se redujeron, mientras que la circunferencia muscular braquial (p = 0,004), el área muscular del brazo corregida (p = 0,005) y el porcentaje corporal magra (p = 0,001) han aumentado. Conclusiones: En los pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn sometidos con anti-TNF-alfa y terapias azatioprina, la suplementación con proteínas de suero de leche y de soya cambia la composición corporal a través de la reducción de la grasa corporal y por lo tanto contribuye para controlar la inflamación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(4): 1603-1610, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Suplementos de proteína de suero y soya cambia la composición corporal en los pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn sometidos con azatioprina y anti-TNF-alfa terapias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1394^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23132^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33047^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
