<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113830</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The answer is in nature: "micronutrients: the vitamins, therapeutic agents in wounds"</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The nutritional state exercises a supreme power on over the processes of the life of the Human Being, but, &#147;what clinical evidence do we have of the implication of vitamins, in the process of cure of the injuries, at present? Can they serve the purpose of natural instruments in prevention and treatment of the wounds?&#148; After having numerous bibliographic searches in the main biomedical databases, it has been obtained as to result few studies dedicated to investigate in this matter, with design precarious methodological and controversial findings. The more studied vitamins have been the A, C, E and D, the least studied the complex B and the K. It is investigated equally in mixed supplementation as in the exclusive input of a vitamin. In the injuries the more worked pattern has been the chronic wounds and in short the pressure ulcers, besides, the research works orientate them principally to interventions in secondary prevention, leaving cracks in the investigation with wounds of another etiology and interventions in primary prevention. Now, with the data that we have, it is safe to say that vitamins are therapeutic cheap and efficacious instruments in prevention and treatment of the wound , although requires to more studies and with better quality methodological that backs it. We do not have to quit on and keep on deepening and perfecting the existing gaps in this matter". Making what's evident, scientist&#148;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrera Castro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estado nutricional ejerce un poder supremo sobre todos los procesos de la vida del ser humano, pero, ¿qué evidencia clínica actual tenemos del la implicación de las vitaminas, en el proceso de curación de las heridas?, ¿Se pueden usar como instrumentos naturales en la prevención y tratamiento de las heridas? Tras realizar numerosas búsquedas bibliográficas en las principales bases biomédicas, se ha obtenido como resultado pocos estudios dedicados a investigar en esta materia, con diseño metodológico precario y hallazgos controvertidos. Las vitaminas más estudiadas han sido la A, C, E y D, las menos estudiadas el complejo B y la K. Se investiga por igual en suplementación mixta como en el aporte exclusivo de una vitamina. En las heridas, el patrón mas trabajado ha sido las heridas crónicas y en concreto las UPP, además, los trabajos de investigación los orientan principalmente a intervenciones en prevención secundaria, dejando grietas en la investigación con heridas de otra etiología e intervenciones en prevención primaria. Actualmente, con los datos que disponemos, se puede afirmar con cierta seguridad que las vitaminas son instrumentos terapéuticos baratos y eficaces en la prevención y tratamiento de la herida, aunque se precisa más estudios y con mejor calidad metodológica que lo respalde. No debemos desistir y seguir profundizando y perfeccionando las lagunas existentes en esta materia. "Haciendo lo evidente, científico&#148;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(31): 273-289, jul. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">En la naturaleza está la respuesta: &#147;Micronutrientes: las vitaminas, agentes terapéuticos en las heridas&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15217^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15217^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16538^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16540^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16540^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16540^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
