<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163875</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient safety culture in Family practice residents of Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the views held by Family practice (FP) residents on the different dimensions of patient safety, in order to identify potential areas for improvement. Design: A cross-sectional study. Location: Seven FP of Galicia teaching units. Participants: 182 FP residents who completed the Medical Office Survey on Patient Safety Culture questionnaire. Measurements: The Medical Office Survey on Patient Safety Culture questionnaire was chosen because it is translated, validated, and adapted to the Spanish model of Primary Care. The results were grouped into 12 composites assessed by the mentioned questionnaire. The study variables were the socio-demographic dimensions of the questionnaire, as well as occupational/professional variables: age, gender, year of residence, and teaching unit of FP of Galicia. Results: The «Organisational learning» and «Teamwork» items were considered strong areas. However, the «Patient safety and quality issues&#148;, «Information exchange with other settings», and «Work pressure and pace» items were considered areas with significant potential for improvement. First-year residents obtained the best results and the fourth-year ones the worst. Conclusions: The results may indicate the need to include basic knowledge on patient safety in the teaching process of FP residents in order to increase and consolidate the fragile patient safety culture described in this study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bugarín González, Rosendo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calvo, María Sol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portela Romero, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la percepción que tienen los médicos residentes de Medicina Familiar y Comunitaria (MFyC) sobre las diferentes dimensiones de la seguridad del paciente para identificar posibles áreas de mejora. Diseño: Estudio transversal descriptivo por encuesta.Emplazamiento: Las 7 unidades docentes de MFyC de Galicia. Participantes: Se incluyó a 182 médicos residentes de MFyC que contestaron el cuestionario Medical Office Survey on Patient Safety Culture. Mediciones: Se eligió el cuestionario Medical Office Survey on Patient Safety Culture porque está traducido, validado y adaptado al modelo de atención primaria español. Los resultados se agruparon en las 12 dimensiones que evalúa dicho cuestionario. Las variables del estudio fueron las dimensiones del cuestionario y las variables sociodemográficas/laborales de los profesionales: edad, sexo, año de residencia y unidades docentes de MFyC. Resultados: Las dimensiones «Aprendizaje organizacional» y «Trabajo en equipo» se consideraron áreas fuertes. En cambio, las dimensiones «Aspectos relacionados con la seguridad del paciente y la calidad», «Intercambio de información con otros dispositivos asistenciales» y «Ritmo y carga de trabajo» se consideraron áreas con un importante potencial de mejora. Los residentes de primer año obtuvieron los mejores resultados y los de cuarto, los peores. Conclusiones: Los resultados nos indican posiblemente la necesidad de incluir durante el proceso docente conocimientos básicos entre los profesionales en formación con el objetivo de incrementar y consolidar la frágil cultura de seguridad del paciente que se describe en este estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(6): 343-350, jun.-jul. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cultura de seguridad del paciente en los médicos internos residentes de Medicina Familiar y Comunitaria de Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
