<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111702</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimization of the medical treatment for acromegaly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Somatostatin analogues are the cornerstone in the first-line and adjuvant (postsurgical) therapy in patients with acromegaly. These drugs highly effectively decrease serum concentrations of growth hormone (GH) and insulin-like growth factor type I (IGF-I), as well as pituitary adenoma size. However, in approximately one third of patients response to these agents is unsatisfactory. The optimization of the medical therapy for acromegaly can be accomplished by modifying the dose or the interval of administration of somatostatin analogues or by combining other pharmacological agents. Increasing the dose or frequency of administration is followed by an additional decrease in GH and IGF-I levels in a  significant percentage of patients. These changes are not accompanied by a relevant increase in the number or severity of adverse events. Combined treatment with somatostatin analogues and pegvisomant has been shown to significantly reduce serum IGF-I levels in patients with inadequate control of disease activity. The  ddition of cabergoline to somatostatin analogue therapy is accompanied by a further decrease in IGF-I levels that is independent of serum prolactin concentrations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los análogos de somatostatina son los agentes más ampliamente utilizados en el tratamiento primario y adyuvante (posquirúrgico) de los pacientes con acromegalia. Disminuyen con gran eficacia las concentraciones de hormona del crecimiento (growth hormone, GH) y del factor de crecimiento  insulinoide tipo I (insulin-like growth factor type I, IGF-I) y reducen el volumen del adenoma hipofisario. Sin embargo, en aproximadamente un tercio de los pacientes la respuesta a estos agentes no es satisfactoria. La optimización del tratamiento me´ dico de la acromegalia puede llevarse a cabo modificando la dosis o el intervalo de administración de los análogos de somatostatina, o bien mediante la combinación con otros agentes farmacológicos. El incremento de la dosis o la frecuencia de administración se acompañan de una reducción ulterior de las concentraciones de GH e IGF-I en una proporción no desdeñable de pacientes. Estas modificaciones no se acompañan de un incremento relevante en el número o gravedad de los efectos   dversos. El tratamiento combinado de análogos de somatostatina con pegvisomant ha mostrado reducir significativamente las concentraciones de IGF-I en casos de control inadecuado de la actividad de la enfermedad. La adición de cabergolina al tratamiento con análogos de somatostatina induce una ulterior reducción de los valores de IGF-I que es independiente de los valores séricos de prolactina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);140(8): 360-365, abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimización del tratamiento médico de la acromegalia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d284^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22676^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51846^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50471^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
