<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83916</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of infected pseudoarthrosis treated with bone transport guided by a tibiotalocalcaneal arthrodesis intramedullary nail</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The effectiveness of the treatment of the infected nonunions by radical resección and bone transport is guaranteed by Literature. Progressively, these techniques have been developed to avoid complications and to assure the results. We presented a clinical case in which the affectation of all the distal end of the tibia has been solved by the combination of the bone transport with the endomedular specific nailing for fusion of the ankle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Vegas, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forriol, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Oliva, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldomar, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La eficacia del tratamiento de las pseudoartrosis infectadas mediante resección radical y transporte óseo está avalada por la literatura. Progresivamente estas técnicas se han ido desarrollando para evitar complicaciones y asegurar los resultados. Presentamos un caso clínico en el que la afectación de todo el extremo metafisodiafisario distal de la tibia se ha resuelto mediante la combinación del transporte óseo con el enclavado endomedular específico para artrodesis de tobillo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);20(1): 49-53, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de pseudoartrosis infectada de tibia mediante transporte óseo guiado por clavo endomedular de artrodesis de tobillo. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10191^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10191^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
