<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27826</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A neuropsychological study of huntington's disease in families in antioquia, colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Various neuropsychological studies have been conducted to determine the cognitive functioning of patients with Huntington&#146;s disease and their results have shown that the pattern of cognitive decline is thought to be typical of a frontal-subcortical dementia. Objectives. To determine if significant differences exist between the cognitive performances of a group diagnosed with Huntington&#146;s disease and a group of healthy, at-risk relatives on a series of neuropsychological tests, and to examine the extent to which the Huntington group&#146;s cognitive performance profile corresponds to frontal-subcortical damage as reported in other studies. Patients and methods. The sample was comprised of a group of 18 subjects with a clinical diagnosis of initial stage Huntington&#146;s disease and a group of 15 healthy relatives at-risk for Huntington&#146;s disease. A battery of tests (the CERAD) and additional neuropsychological tests were administered to all subjects. Results. Compared to the at-risk group, the Huntington&#146;s disease group scored significantly lower on 85.41% of the tests. Conclusions. The neuropsychological tests utilized in this study were useful to discriminate between diagnosed and at-risk groups. The Huntington&#146;s disease group&#146;s global neuropsychological profile was similar to that of a frontal-subcortical dementia in which the predominant features include executive functioning deficits, memory problems, visuo-constructive alterations, attention deficits, verbal fluency problems and naming deficits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Diferentes estudios neuropsicológicos han tenido como objetivo conocer el funcionamiento cognitivo de pacientes con la enfermedad de Huntington (EH). Se ha encontrado que el patrón de deterioro cognitivo se considera como prototipo de una demencia frontosubcortical. Objetivos. Identificar si existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre el rendimiento cognitivo de un grupo de pacientes con EH y un grupo de sujetos sanos en riesgo (SR) en los diferentes test administrados, y determinar si el perfil de funcionamiento cognitivo del grupo de EH corresponde al de una afectación frontosubcortical. Pacientes y métodos. La muestra se componía de un grupo de 18 sujetos con diagnóstico clínico de EH en estadio inicial y un grupo de 15 familiares SR. A ambos grupos de sujetos se les administró la batería del CERAD y varios test neuropsicológicos adicionales. Resultados. El grupo de pacientes con EH presentó puntuaciones más bajas (estadísticamente significativas) en el 85,41 por ciento de las pruebas neuropsicológicas utilizadas, en comparación con el grupo de SR. Conclusiones. El rendimiento cognitivo medido a través de una exploración neuropsicológica ha sido útil para discriminar entre ambos grupos. El perfil neuropsicológico global del grupo de EH fue similar al de una demencia frontosubcortical, en la que predominaron los déficit de funciones ejecutivas, problemas nemónicos, alteraciones visuoconstructivas, déficit de atención, reducción de la fluidez verbal y problemas de denominación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(1): 7-13, jul. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio neuropsicológico de la enfermedad de Huntington en familias de Antioquia, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Moreno, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Dorado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango Lasprilla, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27826</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
