<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155201</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascular risk in endocrine diseases other than diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endocrinological diseases directly affect the cardiovascular system. The deleterious effects on cardiovascular function can be direct, and linked to the increase or reduction of circulating hormones. Equally, the adverse effects may be indirect; for example following the rise in blood pressure, increase or redistribution of lean mass, or increased plasma lipoproteins. The best health care and the increasing availability of biochemical tests lead to the diagnosis of many endocrine diseases before the onset of clinical signs. This review will focus on presenting evidence of cardiovascular functional or structural impairment in cases of primary hyperparathyroidism, Cushing's syndrome, and hypothyroidism in their sub-clinical forms, as well as the reversibility of complications after appropriate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antequera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuende, José I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto López-Guerrero, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivielso, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades endocrinológicas afectan directamente al sistema cardiocirculatorio. Los efectos deletéreos sobre la función cardiovascular pueden ser directos y ligados al incremento o reducción de las hormonas circulantes. Igualmente, los efectos nocivos pueden ser indirectos, por ejemplo los que siguen a la elevación de la presión arterial, el incremento o redistribución de la masa grasa o la elevación de las lipoproteínas plasmáticas. La mejor asistencia sanitaria y la disponibilidad cada vez mayor de pruebas bioquímicas hacen que muchas enfermedades endocrinológicas se diagnostiquen antes de la aparición de la clínica. Esta revisión se va a centrar en mostrar evidencias de alteración funcional o estructural cardiovasculares para casos de hiperparatiroidismo primario, síndrome de Cushing e hipotiroidismo, en sus formas subclínicas, y la reversibilidad de sus complicaciones tras tratamiento adecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(4): 197-201, ago. 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155201</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo vascular en enfermedades endocrinológicas distintas a la diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50516^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3500^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
