<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127651</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence-based practice. Psychometric properties of a questionnaire its measurement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The questionnaire developed in the U.S by Jette et al. is used as a screening to olto estimate the attitudes, beliefs, knowledge and behaviors toward evidence-based practice(EBP). This instrument was adapted and validated in the Spanish language by Guerra et al., but lacking validity studies in the Hispanic population. This research has aimed to estimate the psychometric properties as a way to obtain evidence on the validity of the instruments for the use proposed. Method: The sample was made up of 1,064 Physiotherapists in Colombia who completed the on-line version of the questionnaire. Its reliability and reproducibility were estimated with Cronbach&#146;s alpha procedure, the test-retest with Lin&#146; correlation coefficient and Cohen&#146;s kappaindex, respectively. An exploratory factor analysis was used to analyze the factorial structure. Results: The questionnaire has shown global high internal consistency, moderate temporal stability, acceptable reproducibility, and construct validity appropriate. Exploratory factorial analysis identified two factors that account for 37.953% of the variance. Conclusions: The results obtained in this study support the use of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Correa-Bautista, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Rodríguez, D. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Vélez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Cardona, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ruiz, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flórez-López, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo El cuestionario desarrollado en EE. UU. por Jette et al. se emplea como herramienta para estimar las actitudes, las creencias, los conocimientos y los comportamientos hacia la práctica basada en la evidencia (PBE). Este instrumento fue adaptado y validado en lengua española por Guerra et al., pero carece de estudios de validez en población hispana. El objetivo de esta investigación fue estimar las propiedades psicométricas, como forma de obtener evidencias de validez del instrumento para el uso propuesto. Método La muestra se compone de 1.064 fisioterapeutas de Colombia y que completaron la versión on-line del cuestionario. La fiabilidad y la reproducibilidad fueron estimadas mediante el procedimiento alfa de Cronbach, prueba-reprueba con el coeficiente de correlación intra-clase de Lin y el índice de kappa de Cohen, respectivamente. Se aplicó un análisis factorial exploratorio para analizar la estructura factorial. Resultados El cuestionario ha mostrado a nivel global alta consistencia (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(5): 207-216, sept.-oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Práctica basada en evidencia. Propiedades psicométricas de un cuestionario para su medición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
