<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105939</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost analysis of 3 candins in the treatment of invasive candidiasis in adult non-neutropaenic patients in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the cost of 3 candins (anidulafungin, caspofungin and micafungin) inthe treatment of adult non-neutropaenic patients with invasive candidiasis (IC) in a Spanish hospital pharmacy setting. Methods: The overall cost impact was evaluated by varying the percentage dosage required of each candin in different possible scenarios. The prices (in euros) for each presentation wereobtained from the Drug Catalogue (in August 2010). Only drug purchase costs were considered. The results are expressed as total cost for each of the 3 candins. Results: The cost per episode (14 days) of anidulafungin was constant at D 5400 per patient. The cost of caspofungin varied from D 4281 to D 7991, depending on patient weight and liverdysfunction. The cost of micafungin varied from D 6000 (100 mg/day) to D 9000 (when increasing the dose due to inadequate response). Based on a hypothetic cohort of 100 patients with IC, the total cost of anidulafungin treatment would be D 540 000, for caspofungin it would be D 631 459,and for micafungin it would be D 632 998, depending on any dose adjustment required. Conclusion: Patients treated with anidulafungin did not require dose adjustment, unlike those treated with caspofungin or micafungin. The use of anidulafungin is a cost-saving treatment for adult non-neutropaenic patients with IC, which would result in better control of the Spanish pharmacy budget (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrueta, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vargas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar el coste de tres candinas (anidulafungina, caspofungina, y micafungina) en el tratamiento de pacientes adultos no neutropénicos con candidiasis invasora (CI), desde la perspectiva de la Farmacia Hospitalaria en España. Métodos Para evaluar el impacto global en los costes, se han considerado diferentes escenarios posibles modificando el porcentaje de ajuste de dosis requerido con cada candina. Los precios de cada presentación (&#128;, agosto 2010), se han obtenido del Catálogo de Medicamentos. Únicamente se han considerado los costes de adquisición del fármaco. Los resultados se expresan como coste total para cada una de las tres candinas. Resultados El coste por episodio (14días de tratamiento) de anidulafungina por paciente se mantiene constante en 5.400&#128;. El coste de casponfungina varía de 4.281&#128; a 7.991&#128;, dependiendo del peso del paciente y la disfunción hepática. El coste de micafungina osciló entre 6.000&#128; (100mg/día) y 9.000&#128; (aumento de dosis por respuesta inadecuada al tratamiento). El coste total de tratar a una hipotética cohorte de 100 pacientes con CI con anidulafungina sería de 540.000&#128;, mientras que con caspofungina y micafungina sería de 631.459&#128; y 632.998&#128;, respectivamente, dependiendo del ajuste de dosis requerido. Conclusión Los pacientes tratados con anidulafungina no requieren ajuste de la dosis, a diferencia de caspofungina y micafungina. El empleo de anidulafungina en el tratamiento de la CI en pacientes adultos no neutropénicos es una opción que conlleva un ahorro de costes, lo que permite un mejor control del presupuesto desde la perspectiva de la Farmacia Hospitalaria en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;36(4): 207-215, jul. -ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105939</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de costes de tres candinas en el tratamiento de la candidiasis invasora en pacientes adultos no neutropénicos en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
