<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053777</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of muscarinic receptor antagonists in the treatment of men with lower urinary tract symptoms secondary to BPH</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Use of antimuscarinic agents in male patients with lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) secondary    to benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) and with symptoms of overactive bladder (OAB) has become    increasingly relevant over the last few years. Prescription of these drugs is in conflict with a long-established    concept learnt in Medical School: antimuscarinics are contraindicated in patients with BPH.    Several factors, however, have placed this issue under constant review. The description of OAB syndrome    and the scientific research carried out over recent years have provided epidemiological and pathophysiological    data worthwhile reviewing, most importantly in order to understand why a review of    such a solidly established concept has been raised. This paper reviews the prevalence of OAB in men    with BPH, the role of urodynamics to evaluate men with OAB and the existing evidence on the effect    antimuscarinics have in terms of efficacy and safety on male patients with detrusor obstruction and    overactivity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kaplan, Steven A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de antimuscarínicos en pacientes varones con síntomas del tracto urinario inferior (STUI)    por hiperplasia benigna de próstata (HBP) con síntomas de vejiga hiperactiva (VH) es un tema que está    adquiriendo relevancia en los últimos años. Indicar estas drogas choca directamente contra un concepto    estudiado en la facultad: los antimuscarínicos están contraindicados en pacientes con HBP. Sin    embargo, diversos factores han conducido a que este tema esté en constante revisión. La creación del    síndrome de VH y toda la investigación científica llevada a cabo durante los últimos años han aportado    datos epidemiológicos y fisiopatológicos que merecen la pena repasar. Sobre todo, para poder    entender el porqué se ha planteado la revisión de este concepto solidamente establecido desde hace    muchos años. En este trabajo se realiza una revisión de la prevalencia de la VH en varones con HBP,    del papel de la urodinámica en la evaluación de varones con VH y de la evidencia existente sobre el    efecto que los antimuscarínicos tienen en cuanto a eficacia y seguridad en los pacientes varones con    obstrucción e hiperactividad del detrusor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(2): 86-91, feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los antagonistas de los receptores muscarínicos en el tratamiento de los varones con síntomas del tracto urinario inferior secundarios a HBP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1773^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32129^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
