<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151951</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with delays in seeking medical attention in patients with ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Prompt coronary reperfusion is crucial in patients with ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. The aim of this study was to determine factors associated with a delay in seeking medical attention after the onset of symptoms in patients with this condition. Methods: Prospective cohort study in consecutive patients with ST segment elevation infarction. Multiple logistic regression analysis was used to identify factors independently associated with a longer delay in requesting medical help. Results: In total, 444 consecutive patients were included (mean age, 63 years; 76% men, 20% with diabetes). Median total ischemia time was 225 (160-317) minutes; median delay in seeking medical attention was 110 (51-190) minutes. Older patients (age &gt; 75 years; odds ratio = 11.6), women (odds ratio = 3.4), individuals with diabetes (odds ratio = 2.3), and those requesting medical care from home (odds ratio = 2.2) showed the longest delays in seeking medical attention. Lengthy delay was associated with higher in-hospital mortality (9.8% vs 2.7%; P &lt; .005) and 1-year mortality (7.3% vs 2.9%; P &lt; .05) than when attention was promptly solicited. Conclusions: Elderly patients, women, and diabetic individuals with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction show longer delays in seeking medical attention for their condition. Delays in seeking medical attention are associated with greater in-hospital and 1-year mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfonso,  Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle, Maurice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastante, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordo, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedicto, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salamanca, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo, Jorge-Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Río</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La rapidez en la instauración de la reperfusión coronaria es crucial para los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo con elevación del segmento ST. El objetivo del estudio es determinar los factores asociados al retraso en la demanda de atención médica desde el inicio de los síntomas. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio de cohortes prospectivo de pacientes consecutivos con infarto y elevación del ST. Se utilizó un modelo de regresión logística múltiple para identificar los factores asociados de manera independiente con mayor retraso en la petición de asistencia sanitaria. Resultados: Se incluyó a 444 pacientes consecutivos (media de edad, 63 años; el 76% varones, el 20% diabéticos). La mediana del tiempo total de isquemia fue de 225 (160-317) min; la mediana del retraso en la demanda de atención médica, 110 (51-190) min. Los pacientes más ancianos (edad &gt; 75 años; odds ratio = 11,6), las mujeres (odds ratio = 3,4), los diabéticos (odds ratio = 2,3) y los que solicitaron asistencia desde su propio domicilio (odds ratio = 2,2) son los que más tardaron en pedir atención. El mayor retraso en la demanda de atención médica se asoció a una mayor mortalidad durante el ingreso hospitalario (el 9,8 frente al 2,7%; p &lt; 0,005) y al año (el 7,3 frente al 2,9%; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: Los pacientes ancianos, las mujeres y los diabéticos con infarto de miocardio y elevación del ST presentan mayor retraso en la demanda de atención médica. El retraso en la demanda de atención médica se asocia con mayor mortalidad durante el ingreso y al año (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;69(3): 279-285, mar. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados al retraso en la demanda de atención médica en pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo con elevación del segmento ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53672^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55032^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
