<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76413</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of the disability in Spain for autonomous communities: the paper of the individual factors and the geographical environment in the variability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The prevalence of disability shows a highgeographical variability and the identification of factors that couldexplain these variations can be usuful to the heath and socialwelfare planning. Here the analysis of disability variations amongautonomous regions in Spain is made taking into accountindividual and geographical setting factors together.Methods: Data come from the Spanish Disability,Impairment and Health Status survey of 1999 and from Inebaseboth of the National Institute for Statistics. The prevalence ofdisability crude and adjusted by age was calculated for eachautonomous region. Individual factors related to disability areidentified by means of a logistic regression. The analysisaccounting for both, individual and geographical setting factorswas performed by means of a logistic regression of two levels.Results: Disability prevalence showed a maximum differenceof 5.75 points among regions. In a logistic regression the region ofresidence was statistically significant (OR: 3.35 in the highestrated region related to the lowest) beside several individual factors:age (OR 40-64= 1,78 OR 65-79= 1,87 and OR &gt;79= 3,34), sex(OR women= 0,66), working status (OR unemployment=2,25 ORhousewife/student=1,39 y OR other=2,03), health status (ORregular= 1,69 OR bad/very bad= 2,05) and chronic diseases (OR1-3=1,56 OR 4-6=1,82 OR &gt;6=2,59). Individual factors accountedfor a very few variance at the two levels regression model(s=0,261) and none of the regional variables improved the model.Conclusions: Individual factors do not explain enough theobserved disability variations among the regions and none factorrelated to the geographical setting has been identified asstatistically significant(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clot-Razquin, Guillem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz-Ramos, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Fernández, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gispert Magarolas, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March Llanes, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas Ramírez, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets Bou, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La prevalencia de discapacidad en la poblacióngeneral presenta una gran variabilidad geográfica, de manera queidentificar aquellos factores que pudieran explicarla será importantepara la planificación de políticas sociales. En este trabajo se analizala variabilidad de la discapacidad por comunidades autónomasdesde una doble vertiente, los factores individuales y del entorno.Métodos: Los datos proceden principalmente de la Encuestade Discapacidad, Deficiencias y Estado de Salud de 1999 y delInebase, ambas del Instituto Nacional de Estadística (INE). Secalculó la prevalencia de discapacidad simple y ajustada por edadde las CCAA. Se analizan los factores individuales asociados a ladiscapacidad mediante una regresión logística y los factores individualesy de la comunidad autónoma conjuntamente con unaregresión logística de dos niveles.Resultados: La prevalencia de discapacidad muestra una diferenciamáxima de 5,75 puntos entre las comunidades autónomas.En la regresión logística la comunidad de residencia fue estadísticamentesignificativa (OR: 3,35 en la de mayor prevalencia respectoa la de menor) junto con otras variables individuales: edad (ORde 40-64= 1,78 OR de 65-79= 1,87 y OR de &gt;79= 3,34), sexo (ORmujer= 0,66), situación laboral (OR sin trabajo=2,25 OR amascasa/estudiante=1,39 y OR otros=2,03), estado de salud (OR regular=1,69 OR malo/muy malo= 2,05) y enfermedades crónicas (OR1-3=1,56 OR4-6=1,82 OR&gt;6=2,59). En la regresión de dos niveleslas variables individuales explican poca varianza (s=0,261) y ningunade las variables relativas a las CCAA mejora el modelo.Conclusiones: Las características individuales no explicansuficientemente la variabilidad de la discapacidad entre CCAA yno se han identificado variables del entorno que sean significativas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(6): 821-834, nov.-dic.2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la discapacidad en España por Comunidades Autónomas: el papel de los factores individuales y del entorno geográfico en su variabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29817</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
