<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128182</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Registry of nursing professional activity in the Digital Clinical Record: an experience in Menorca</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incorporation of information and communication technologies (ICT) in the healthcare setting has provided applications which make easier the access to information on individual health both to users and professionals.In the Hospital General Matéu Orfila in Menorca (Balearic Islands), the process of computerizing the digital clinical records started back in 2007, and multiple difficulties were detected for the use of the application, thus generating a loss of confidence in information systems. Faced with this situation, the objective established was the preparation of an electronic working tool which might allow to satisfy the registry of the nursing professional role. The purpose of this article is to describe the process of preparation and implementation of a work setting for the Nursing team, incorporated in the digital clinical record of the Hospital Matéu Orfila in Menorca, resulting in the availability of an agile, intuitive, reliable and high-scope working tool, which incorporates those relevant activities for all nursing functions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cases Sanchis, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Torres, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incorporación de las tecnologías de la información y la comunicación (TIC) en el ámbito sanitario ha dotado en los últimos años a usuarios y profesionales de aplicaciones que facilitan a ambos colectivos el acceso a información sobre la salud individual.En el Hospital General Mateu Orfila de Menorca (Islas Baleares) el proceso de informatización de la historia clínica digital comenzó en 2007, detectándose múltiples dificultades para el manejo de la aplicación y generando pérdida de confianza en los sistemas de información. Ante esta situación, se marcó como objetivo la elaboración de una herramienta de trabajo electrónica que permitiese satisfacer el registro del rol profesional enfermero.El propósito de este artículo es describir el proceso de elaboración y la implantación de un entorno de trabajo para el equipo de Enfermería, integrado en la historia clínica digital del Hospital Mateu Orfila de Menorca, con el que se ha conseguido disponer de una herramienta de trabajo ágil, intuitiva, fiable y de gran alcance, que integra actividades relevantes para todas las funciones enfermeras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(8): 62-68, oct. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro de la actividad profesional enfermera en la historia clínica digital: experiencia en Menorca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
