<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101039</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depressive symptoms, perceived emotional intelligence and ways of coping among pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this research is toa nalyze the relationship between PEI levels (perceived emotional intelligence), ways of coping and depressive symptoms during pregnancy. For this purpose, we used the Trait Meta-Mood Scale-24 which evaluates perceived emotional intelligence (Salovey, Mayer, Goldman, Turvey &amp; Palafai, 1995), the Ways of Coping Scale (Ruiz, Hernández &amp; Hernández, 2004), and adapted version of Edimburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (Cox, Holden &amp; Sagovsky, 1987) in 668 emotional attention increases depressive symptoms, desiderative thoughts, resignation and self-blame. Increasing emotional Clarity and Repair reduces depressive symptoms and enables the use of more adaptative ways of coping during pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Jiménez, Beatriz Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Acosta, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la relación entre los niveles de IEP, afrontamiento y síntomas depresivos durante el embarazo. Para ello se utilizó la escala Trait Meta-Mood Scale-24 que evalúa la Inteligencia Emocional Percibida (Salovey, Mayer, Goldman, Turvey &amp; Palafai, 1995), la escala de formas de Afrontamiento (Ruiz, Hernández &amp; Hernández, 2004), y una versión adaptada de la Escala de Depresión Posnatal de Edimburgo (Cox, Holden &amp; Sagovsky, 1987) en 668 mujeres embarazadas. Los resultados muestran que cuando se presta excesiva atención a las emociones se incrementa la sintomatología depresiva, pensamientos desiderativos, resignación y autoculpa. Al aumentar la Claridad y Reparación emocional disminuye la sintomatología depresiva y se emplean formas de afrontamiento adaptativas durante el embarazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;17(2/3): 255-264, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas depresivos, inteligencia emocional percibida y formas de afrontamiento en mujeres embarazadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
