<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21216</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of smoking and alcohol consumption on mortality in the population of Barcelona [Spain]: 1983-1998</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the mortality attributable to smoking and alcohol consumption in the city of Barcelona from 1983 to 1998. Methods: All deaths among residents of the city of Barcelona from 1983 to 1998 were included. Population data were obtained from the city inhabitants register. The mortality attributable to smoking and alcohol consumption was calculated by population attributable fractions using relative risks from previous studies in the US population. Results: In 1998, 2,205 deaths were attributable to smoking, representing 13.8% of all deaths among the population aged 35 years or older and a decrease of 9.6% compared with deaths in 1983. From 1983 to 1998 there was an increase in smoking-attributable adjusted mortality rates for lung cancer (155.84/100,000 inhabitants in men and 9.39/100,000 in women in 1998) and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) (95.89/100,000 in men and 11.29/ 100,000 in women in 1998). In 1998, deaths attributed to alcohol consumption accounted for 4.3% of total mortality, representing a reduction of 26% since 1983. Among men, the primary cause of alcohol-attributable mortality was liver cirrhosis (17.1%), although its relative importance decreased (accounting for 17.1% of alcohol-attributable mortality in 1998 compared with 24.3% in 1983). Conclusions: The mortality attributable to smoking and alcohol consumption decreased in the city of Barcelona during the study period. Smoking-attributable mortality from lung cancer and COPD increased in both sexes. Alcohol consumption-attributable mortality from liver cirrhosis decreased in men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la mortalidad atribuible al tabaquismo y al consumo excesivo de alcohol, así como su evolución, en la ciudad de Barcelona entre 1983 y 1998.Métodos: Se incluyen todas las defunciones de las personas residentes en Barcelona desde 1983 a 1998. Los datos poblacionales se han obtenido de los Padrones de Habitantes.La mortalidad atribuible al tabaquismo y al consumo de alcohol se obtiene calculando las Fracciones Atribuibles Poblacionales a partir de los riesgos relativos de estudios previos en la población de los EE.UU.Resultados: En 1998 se produjeron 2.205 muertes atribuibles al hábito tabáquico, lo que representó el 13,8 por ciento de la mortalidad en la población de 35 años o más, y una reducción del 9,6 por ciento respecto a 1983. Durante el período 19831998 aumentó, en varones y mujeres, la mortalidad por cáncer de pulmón atribuible al tabaquismo (155,84/100.000 y 9,39/100.000 habitantes en 1998, respectivamente) y la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) (95,82 y 11,29/100.000 habitantes en 1998). La mortalidad por consumo de alcohol en 1998 representó el 4,3 por ciento de la mortalidad total, reduciéndose en un 26 por ciento desde 1983. La cirrosis hepática siguió siendo la primera causa de muerte atribuible al consumo de alcohol en varones en 1998, aunque su importancia relativa disminuyó (17,1 por ciento de la mortalidad atribuible al consumo de alcohol en 1998, 24,3 por ciento en 1983).Conclusiones: La mortalidad atribuible al hábito tabáquico y al consumo excesivo de alcohol ha descendido en la ciudad de Barcelona durante el período de estudio. Asimismo, se ha incrementado la importancia relativa de la mortalidad atribuible al tabaquismo para el cáncer de pulmón y la EPOC en ambos sexos, mientras que se ha reducido la proporción de mortalidad atribuible al consumo excesivo de alcohol para las cirrosis hepáticas en el caso de los varones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;17(2): 108-115, mar.  -abr.  2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del tabaquismo y del consumo excesivo de alcoholen la mortalidad de la población de la ciudad de Barcelona:1983-1998</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Borrell, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nebot, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasarín, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jané, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21216</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
