<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99702</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraction of a vascular catheter´s fragment from superior mesenteric artery in an extreme preterm infant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Central venous catheters are used routinely in the newborn intensive care units. These devices are reliable, but not free of potential complications. Its rupture is an example, and, being exceptional, when it happens it produces doubts about its correct management. Clinic case. We report the case of a broken percutaneous central venous catheter, accidentally inserted at humeral artery, and the subsequent migration of a fragment to superior mesenteric artery in a premature infant of 26 weeks of gestational age. After evaluating different treatment options, it was decided to perform an interventional catheterization to retrieve it. The foreign body was removed from femoral artery, without any complications associated with the procedure. Comment. It is, to our knowledge, the first reported example of the usefulness of interventional catheterization in the recovery of foreign bodies located in systemic arterial territory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roguera, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muchart, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocaña, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcázar, Ricardo del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coroleu, Wifredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los catéteres venosos centrales se utilizan de forma rutinaria en las unidades de cuidados intensivos neonatales. Son dispositivos seguros, pero no están libres de potenciales complicaciones. Su rotura es un ejemplo, y, al ser un hecho excepcional, cuando acontece puede producir dudas sobre su correcto abordaje. Caso clínico. Se expone el caso de una rotura de catéter venoso central percutáneo, accidentalmente insertado a nivel de arteria humeral, y la migración posterior de un fragmento hasta arteria mesentérica superior en un recién nacido pretérmino de 26 semanas de edad gestacional. Después de valorar diferentes opciones terapéuticas, se decide realizar un cateterismo intervencionista para su recuperación. De esta forma, se consigue la extracción del cuerpo extraño desde arteria femoral, sin ninguna complicación asociada al procedimiento. Comentario. Es, según nuestro conocimiento, el primer caso descrito de la utilidad del cateterismo intervencionista en la recuperación de cuerpos extraños situados en territorio arterial sistémico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;71(4): 146-148, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Extracción de un fragmento de catéter vascular en arteria mesentérica superior en un prematuro extremo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
