<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153856</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Groove pancreatitis vs. pancreatic adenocarcinoma: A review of 8 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Groove pancreatitis (PS) is an uncommon clinical situation and radiologically it can mimic carcinoma of the periampullary area. The aim of this paper is to study a series of 8 patients who underwent surgery with preoperative diagnosis of pancreatic head mass and subsequent pathological diagnosis of PS. Methods: In our series, 6 were men and 2 women, with an average age of 51,9 years. Before surgery, all patients had epigastric abdominal pain requiring analgesia at high doses. The preoperative analytical CEA and Ca 19.9 were normal in all patients. Imaging studies showed intrapancreatic solid lesions in 6 of the 8 patients, and in the remaining 2 one papillary mass of 5 and 6 cm, respectively, that caused stenosis in the duodenal luz. EUS neoplastic cells were negative in all patients. Results: The immediate postoperative evolution was satisfactory, there are no complications. In our series, no patients have died. The long-term follow-up, in 7 of the 8 patients, has been excellent with disappearance of abdominal pain and improvement of nutritional status. The remaining patient had frequent recurrent episodes of acute pancreatitis, and at 60 months, presented a pseudocyst that has required a Roux-en-Y cystojejunostomy. Conclusions: PS must be included in the differential diagnosis of pancreatic lesions, which may include carcinoma of the periampullary area and other causes of chronic pancreatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claver Valderas, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Bueno, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Moral, Jesús de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Zárate, Wilfredo Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster Quiñonero, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Ruiz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Salmerón, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La pancreatitis del surco (PS) es una entidad poco frecuente que clínica y radiológicamente puede simular un carcinoma del área periampular. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar una serie de 8 pacientes que fueron intervenidos quirúrgicamente con el diagnóstico preoperatorio de masa en cabeza pancreática, con un diagnóstico anatomopatológico definitivo de PS. Metodos: En nuestra serie, 6 eran hombres y 2 mujeres y tenían una edad media de 51,9 años. Previamente a la cirugía, todos los pacientes presentaban dolor abdominal en epigastrio que requería analgesia a altas dosis. En la analítica preoperatoria, el CEA y el Ca 19.9 fueron normales en todos los pacientes. Los estudios de imagen mostraron lesiones sólidas intrapancreáticas en 6 de los 8 pacientes, y en los 2 restantes una masa mamelonada de 5 y 6 cm, respectivamente, que estenosaba la luz duodenal. La ecoendoscopia fue negativa para células neoplásicas en todos los pacientes. Resultados: La evolución durante el postoperatorio inmediato fue satisfactoria, sin complicaciones. En nuestra serie, no ha fallecido ningún paciente. La evolución a largo plazo, en 7 de los 8 pacientes, ha sido excelente, con desaparición del dolor abdominal y mejoría del estado nutricional. El caso restante ha tenido frecuentes episodios de pancreatitis aguda recidivante y, a los 60 meses, ha presentado un seudoquiste que ha precisado una quistoyeyunostomía en Y de Roux. Conclusiones: La PS debe incluirse en el diagnóstico diferencial de lesiones pancreáticas, que pueden incluir carcinoma del área periampular y otras causas de pancreatitis crónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);94(6): 346-352, jun.-jul. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pancreatitis del surco versus adenocarcinoma de páncreas: a propósito de 8 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35312^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35312^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
