<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154069</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The qualitative evidence and the care of patients in Peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Nursing care as a relationship between a subject of care and professional ability to do so requires that the latter understand the experiences that the disease and the treatments generate in the person. Objective: To establish the qualitative relationship between the qualitative evidence available in scientific literature published between 1997-2014, related to nursing care in patients with peritoneal dialysis nurses taxonomies. Material and methods: Qualitative study in which with prior authorization from the ethics and research committees, systematic review of qualitative studies was conducted in three stages: 1. Search databases: PubMed, Embase, CUIDEN, CINAHL, Dialnet, Scielo Virtual Library Health and Web of Science. 2. Assessment of methodological quality conducted by independent peers using the Critical Appraisal Skills Programme, in Spanish; 3. Summary of qualitative evidence, which is interrelated with the taxonomies Nursing Diagnoses: Definitions and classification, and Nursing Intervention Classification. Results: The research paper is based on 19 studies that, using the voice of research subjects reported by the authors and approved with the defining characteristics, allowed the formulation of diagnoses and the determination of the necessary nursing interventions framed in the 13 domains established by the Nursing Diagnoses: definitions and classification. Some of the results and conclusions themselves are qualitative evidence of the care required by people on peritoneal dialysis. Discussion and conclusions: Peritoneal dialysis interferes in all domains, which goes beyond the subject, affecting their family and environment. Generally it requires lifelong support to achieve adhesion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Algarra, Ana Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Parra, Kimberly Julieth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque Salazar, Nathaly</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La atención de enfermería como relación entre un sujeto de cuidado y un profesional con capacidad para hacerlo requiere que éste último comprenda las vivencias que la enfermedad y los tratamientos generan en la persona. Objetivo: Establecer interrelación entre las evidencias cualitativas disponibles en la literatura científica cualitativa publicada entre 1997-2014 respecto al cuidado de enfermería a pacientes en Diálisis Peritoneal con las taxonomías enfermeras. Material y Métodos: Estudio cualitativo en el cuál, previa autorización del comité de ética e investigación, se realizó revisión sistemática de estudios cualitativos en tres etapas: 1. Búsqueda en las bases de datos: PubMed, Embase, CUIDEN, CINAHL, Dialnet, Scielo, Biblioteca Virtual en Salud y Web of Science. 2. Evaluación de calidad metodológica por pares independientes utilizando el Critical Appraisal Skills Programme, en español; 3. Síntesis de evidencias cualitativas, que se interrelacionaron con las taxonomías Nursing Diagnoses: definitions and classification, y Nursing Intervention Classification. Resultados: Se incluyeron 19 estudios que permitieron, desde la voz de los sujetos de investigación reportadas por los autores y homologadas con las características definitorias, formular diagnósticos y determinar intervenciones de enfermería enmarcadas en los 13 dominios establecidos por la Nursing Diagnoses: definitions and classification. Algunos resultados y conclusiones en sí mismos son evidencias cualitativas del cuidado que requieren las personas en diálisis peritoneal. Discusión y conclusiones: La diálisis peritoneal interfiere en todos los dominios, afectando al sujeto, su familia y su entorno. En general requiere de educación y apoyo permanente para lograr adherencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;19(2): 154-163, abr.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154069</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evidencia cualitativa y el cuidado del paciente en diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
