<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043920</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cluster headache: its diagnosis, pathophysiology and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cluster headache (CH) is the most frequent subtype of trigeminal headache with autonomic symptoms(THAS); yet, despite its characteristic clinical profile it remains poorly understood and badly controlled. Aims. To identify thecorrect diagnostic criteria of CH and the respective differential diagnoses, as well as to gain an understanding of thepathophysiology of CH, its treatment and prognosis by means of a review of the literature. Development and conclusions. CHis a condition that is characterised by the presence of sharp, or extremely sharp, unilateral pain that is short-lasting andusually located in the retroocular and/or temporal region; it is also accompanied by ipsilateral autonomic symptoms (mainlyconjunctival injection). CH can be differentiated from other THAS by the frequency with which it appears and the amount oftime the pain lasts (the average is less than five attacks a day lasting from 30 minutes to 3 hours), as well as the response totreatment. A number of neuronal pathways are involved in the pathophysiology of CH. It has been suggested that theactivation of the trigeminovascular and the parasympathetic systems, together with the dysfunction of the cranial sympatheticsystem, are involved in this condition. Moreover, there is evidence to support the role of functional and structural alterationsin the hypothalamus. Treatment of CH is based on the proper pharmacological implementation of abortive, transitional andprophylactic therapies. Surgical interventions are recommended in patients with strictly unilateral pain in the ophthalmicdivision of the trigeminal nerve who are resistant to multiple therapies, and/or offer a poor response and/or contraindicationsto pharmacological treatment. Factors related to genetics, brain functioning or the environment, as well as the way thesymptoms present (episodic or chronic), determine the prognosis of CH</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Volcy-Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La cefalea en racimos (CR) es el subtipo decefalea trigeminal con síntomas autonómicos (CTA) más frecuente;sin embargo, a pesar de su característico perfil clínico continúasiendo pobremente reconocida y mal controlada. Objetivos. Aprendera identificar los correctos criterios diagnósticos de la CR y losdiagnósticos diferenciales respectivos; comprender la fisiopatologíade la CR, su tratamiento y pronóstico mediante la revisión de la literatura. Desarrollo y conclusiones. La CR es una entidad caracterizadapor la presencia de dolor agudo o extremadamente agudo,unilateral, de corta duración, generalmente de ubicación retrooculary/o temporal, acompañada de síntomas autonómicos ipsilaterales(principalmente inyección conjuntival). La CR se puede diferenciarde otras CTA por la frecuencia de presentación y duración deldolor (promedio de menos de cinco crisis por día de más de 30 minutosa 3 horas), así como por la respuesta a los tratamientos. Lafisiopatología de la CR involucra múltiples vías neuronales. Se sugierela activación del sistema trigéminovascular y del sistemaparasimpático, y disfunción del sistema simpático craneal. Por otrolado, hay evidencias de alteración funcional y estructural en el hipotálamo.El tratamiento de la CR se basa en la correcta implementaciónfarmacológica de terapias abortiva, de transición y profiláctica.Los procedimientos quirúrgicos se recomiendan en pacientescon dolor estrictamente unilateral en la división oftálmica del nerviotrigémino refractarios a múltiples terapias, y/o con mala respuestay/o contraindicaciones al tratamiento farmacológico. Factoresgenéticos, de funcionamiento cerebral, medioambientales, aligual que la forma de presentación (episódica o crónica), determinanel pronóstico de la CR</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(2): 114-121, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cefalea en racimos: diagnóstico, fisiopatología y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3054^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3054^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
