<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040952</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-2273</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phytochemical products with estrogen and/or antioxidant activity. Expectatives for peri-postmenopausal woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When reaching the menopause, the adapting process includes trying to improve a woman's quality of life by selecting the appropriate diet compositíon. An idea ofthis ideal diet can be inferred from the improved perception of quaIity of life that eastem women have compared to westem women during this stage. The increased consumption of products containing phytoestrogens in eastem countries has recentIy sparked an interest in their functional properties both in the nutritíon and clinical setting. Although so far there is no proven link between the intake of the phytoestrogen; isoflavones and lignanes and anti-aging effects, clinical trials aimed at fmding a cause-effect relationship are presentIy underway. This calls for prudence in the intake of supplements based on different types of phytoestrogens given that, although we are dealing with vegetable products that are easily absorbed and metabolized, we cannot assume that they will be innocuous at any ingested dose</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrocal Sertucha, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La menopausia requiere una adaptación de la mujer para mejorar su calidad de vida que incluye la composición de la dieta. Una aproximación al tipo de dieta deseable procede de la mejor percepción de calidad de vida que tienen las mujeres orientales frente a las occidentales en esta etapa. El incremento en el consumo de productos con fitoestrógenos ha potenciado las expectativas sobre sus propiedades funcionales, tanto en el ámbito clínico como en el dietético. Aunque todavía no existe una relación científicamente probada entre los fitoestrógenos: isoflavonas y lignanos y el envejecimiento, se progresa en optimizar los ensayos clínicos que conduzcan a la relación causa-efecto. La prudencia se impone en la ingesta de suplementos a base de diferentes clases de fitoestrógenos, ya que aunque se trata de productos de origen vegetal que son absorbidos y metabolizados por el organismo humano, no supone que sean inocuos independientemente de la dosis ingerida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cienc. ginecol;9(6): 329-336, nov.-dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fitoquímicos con actividad estrogénica y/o antioxidante. Expectativas para la mujer en la etapa peri-posmenopausica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31157^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7696^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31157^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11272</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11272^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
