<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62137</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Distal percutaneous osteotomy in the treatment of lesser ray metatarsalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The purpose of this study is to evaluate the results of distal osteotomy of lesser metatarsals carried out through a percutaneous technique. Materials and methodsForty-four feet in 37 patients were reviewed, which the same surgeon had subjected to 110 percutaneous osteotomies between November 2002 and July 2006. Metatarsalgias of general or traumatic origin were excluded from the study. All patients were assessed functionally (by means of the AOFAS [American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society] Lesser Metatarsophalangeal-Interphalangeal Scale) and radiographically. ResultsAfter a mean 15-month¿ follow-up, a satisfactory functional result was obtained in 93.2% of cases (41 feet), with a mean final score of 91 (range: 65¿100) on the AOFAS scale. The condition recurred in 5 patients, and 2 developed transfer metratarsalgia (these required an osteotomy of the affected metatarsals). Mobility of the metatarsophalangeal (MTP) joint was not significantly disturbed in any of the cases and 7 patients developed a ¿floating toe¿ deformity. Radiologically a mean shortening of 2.9mm was observed. There were 3 cases of delayed healing, but eventually healing was achieved by all patients. ConclusionsPercutaneous osteotomy affords satisfactory clinical and cosmetic results and leads to no problems in terms of healing or MTP joint stiffness. These results indicate that it is an effective and safe surgical technique that can be recommended for lesser ray metatarsalgia, whether in association with other forefoot procedures or not(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lajara Marco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Gilabert, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Herrera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar los resultados de la osteotomía distal de los metatarsianos menores realizada mediante técnica percutánea. Material y método: Se revisaron retrospectivamente 44 pies de 37 sujetos en los que un mismo cirujano había practicado 110 osteotomías percutáneas desde noviembre de 2002 hasta julio de 2006; se excluyeron previamente las metatarsalgias de origen general o de origen traumático. Todos los sujetos se valoraron radiográfica y funcionalmente (mediante la escala para metatarsianos menores e interfalángicas de la American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society [AOFAS]). ResultadosTras un seguimiento medio de 15 meses, se obtuvo un resultado funcional satisfactorio en el 93,2% de los casos (41 pies) y se alcanzó una puntuación final media de 91 puntos (rango de 65 a 100) en la escala de la AOFAS. En 5 sujetos se apreció recidiva de la enfermedad y en 2 sujetos se apreció metatarsalgia de transferencia (que precisaron osteotomía de los metatarsianos afectados). La movilidad de la articulación metatarsofalángica (MTF) no se vio afectada de forma significativa en ningún caso, aunque en 7 casos se observó deformidad en «dedo flotante». Radiológicamente, se apreció un acortamiento promedio de 2,9mm. Hubo 3 casos de retardo de consolidación, pero finalmente se consiguió en todos los sujetos. Conclusiones: La osteotomía percutánea obtiene buenos resultados clínicos y estéticos sin presentar problemas de consolidación o rigidez de la MTF. Estos resultados permiten afirmar que es una técnica quirúrgica efectiva, segura y recomendable para las metatarsalgias de los radios menores asociada o no a otras cirugías del antepié (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);53(3): 192-197, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La osteotomía distal percutánea en el tratamiento de la metatarsalgia de los radios menores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2515^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37272^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37272^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
