<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045039</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early mobilisation of patients with acute deep vein thrombosis does not increase the risk of a symptomatic pulmonary embolism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM. To evaluate if early mobilization in patients with acute lower limbs deep vein thrombosis (DVT) increases the incidence of symptomatic pulmonary embolism (PE). To evaluate determining factors of PE, like location of the thrombus and /or time of clinical evolution. PATIENTS AND METHODS. Prospective randomised clinical trial. Carried on in two university hospitals, from January 2002 to December 2003. 146 patients with acute lower limbs DVT where included, 68 female and 78 male, with a mean age of 60.7 years. The inclusion criteria were: less that 15 days of initial symptoms, life expectancy greater than one year, no life threatening clinical condition, inform written consent. These patients were randomized into two groups. Group A: 67 patients (45.9%) hospital treatment with a 5 days bed rest. Group B: 79 patients (54.1%) home care with early walking and compressive bandage. Primary end point was the presence of symptomatic PE during the first ten days of treatment. The relationships between time of clinical evolution, location of thrombus and symptomatic PE were also analyzed. The statistical analysis was made using the chi-square o Fisher exact test, homogeneity basal and multivariate analysis. RESULTS. Four cases of symptomatic PE were detected (2.7%), two in each group. There was no significant difference concerning the occurrence of new PE between the two groups (p = 0.33). Also no difference was detected according to time of evolution (p = 0.45) and location of thrombus (p = 0.37). Multivariate analysis did not show any significant difference between groups. CONCLUSION. Seemingly location of thrombus and elapse time of symptoms did not increase the incidence of symptomatic PE</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Piqueras Gómez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Villegas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Mestre, Francesc Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cairols Castellote, Marc Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonell Pascual, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapiedra Mur, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Principal: evaluar la influencia de la deambulación precoz en pacientes con trombosis venosa profunda (TVP) aguda sobre la incidencia de tromboembolismo pulmonar (TEP) sintomático; secundario: valorar si la localización del trombo y/o el tiempo de evolución influyen en la aparición del TEP sintomático. Pacientes y métodos. Ensayo clínico de observación realizado en dos centros, en el período 2002-2003, con asignación aleatoria 1:1 según sobres cerrados. Se diagnosticaron 650 pacientes con TVP, de los cuales sólo se incluyeron 146, 68 mujeres y 78 hombres (edad media: 60,7 años; rango: 18-83 años). Criterios de inclusión: TVP inferior a 15 días de evolución, consentimiento informado, esperanza de vida mayor de un año y condición clínica sin riesgo vital. Ambos grupos se trataron con heparinas de bajo peso molecular, seguido de anticoagulación oral según protocolo. Grupo A: 67 pacientes, cinco días de reposo. Grupo B: 79 casos, deambulación precoz con contención elástica. Se compararon ambos grupos según el tiempo de evolución y la localización de la trombosis. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante un estudio descriptivo; se utilizó la prueba de chi al cuadrado o el estadístico exacto de Fisher y análisis multivariante. Resultados. Cuatro casos de TEP sintomático (2,7%), sin diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los dos grupos (p = 0,33). Tampoco hubo diferencias en relación con el tiempo de evolución (p = 0,45) ni localización del trombo (p = 0,37). El análisis multivariante no detectó ninguna variable con significación estadística. Conclusión. Parece ser que la localización del trombo y el tiempo de evolución no influyen en la incidencia de TEP sintomático</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(2): 127-135, mar.-abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La movilización precoz en pacientes con trombosis venosa profunda aguda no aumenta el riesgo de embolismo pulmonar sintomático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
