<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105554</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcomes in patients with Achilles tendon rupture surgically managed with conventional technique vs patients treated with minimally invasive technique. Two-year outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare two surgical techniques for solving Achilles tendon rupture in young recreational athletes. Patients and methods: Study performed in 25 patients undergoing surgery: 18 with conventional technique, with a central Kessler stitch, and seven cases treated with mini-open technique, with double Kessler stitch lateral and medial to the tendon. Results: Of the 18 patients operated with conventional technique, one had wound dehiscence and another wound infection. No complications were seen in the seven patients operated with a minimally invasive technique. This technique reduced surgical time and return to work and activities of daily living was significantly faster. The percentage of wound adhesions and dehiscences also decreased owing to the smaller surface exposed. Conclusions: Minimally invasive surgery in Achilles tendon rupture provides a faster recovery and return to work and sports in a shorter time; it also reduces surgical times (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paton, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar dos técnicas quirúrgicas para la resolución de la rotura del tendón de Aquiles en pacientes jóvenes deportistas ocasionales. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de 25 pacientes intervenidos quirúrgicamente: 18 con técnica convencional, con un punto de Kessler central, y siete casos tratados con técnica mini-open, con doble punto de Kessler lateral y medial al tendón. Resultados: Entre los 18 pacientes operados con técnica convencional, uno presentó dehiscencia de la herida y otro infección de la herida. Entre los siete pacientes operados con técnica mínimamente invasiva no se observaron complicaciones. Con esta técnica se redujo el tiempo quirúrgico, y la reincorporación laboral y a las actividades cotidianas fue significativamente más rápida. El porcentaje de adherencias y dehiscencias de la herida también se redujo por la menor superficie expuesta. Conclusiones: La cirugía mínimamente invasiva en la rotura del tendón de Aquiles ofrece una recuperación más rápida e inserción laboral y deportiva en menor tiempo; también reduce los tiempos quirúrgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(3): 172-175, jul.-sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105554</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados en pacientes con rotura del tendón de Aquiles tratados quirúrgicamente con técnica convencional frente a pacientes tratados con técnica mínimamente invasiva. Evolución a dos años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d134^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
