<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052662</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiopathology of articular stiffness: preventive bases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article takes a look at the scientific basis of articular stiffness throughout a bibliographic review of the physiopathology and its repercussions in physical therapy. Lack of movement and joint stress lead to articular stiffness. If the origin of the restriction is unknown, recurrence of the problem may occur. The causes knowledge and histological changes let us apply appropriate techniques to get better results. Methodology: bibliographic review of classic works and specific Databases. Results: articular stiffness is the consequence of lack of movement and joint stress deprivation. Stress deprivation alters the morphologic, biochemical and biomechanical characteristics of tissues. Proliferation of connective tissue and collagen disorganization appear as a result of immobilization. Stiffness prevention is based in minimizing dangerous effects of immobilization and goes through a complete physical therapy treatment, initiated during immobilization phase. Preventive measures are edema's treatment, active and passive mobilization, isometrics, early beginning of the treatment and Passive Continuous Motion (combined with physical therapy)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montull, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monterde, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es realizar una revisión bibliográfica de la fisiopatología de la rigidez articular y de sus repercusiones en el enfoque preventivo de la fisioterapia. La falta de movimiento y de tensiones aplicadas sobre las articulaciones da como resultado rigidez articular. El desconocimiento del origen de la rigidez puede llevar consigo una recurrencia del problema. El conocimiento de las causas y sus cambios histológicos permitirá aplicar las técnicas más oportunas obteniendo mejores resultados. Método: Revisión bibliográfica de textos clásicos y Bases de Datos específicas. Resultados: La rigidez articular se da como resultado de la falta de movimiento y de fuerzas aplicadas sobre las articulaciones. La falta de estrés altera las características morfológicas, bioquímicas y biomecánicas de los tejidos. La inmovilización produce proliferación del tejido conectivo y desorganización del colágeno de los distintos tejidos. La prevención de la rigidez se basa en minimizar los efectos nocivos de la inmovilización y pasa por un completo tratamiento de fisioterapia, iniciado en fase de inmovilización. Las medidas preventivas se resumen en medidas antiedema, movilización pasiva y activa, isométricos, inicio temprano del tratamiento y Movilización Pasiva Continua combinada con fisioterapia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(2): 90-98, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiopatología de la rigidez articular: bases para su prevención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
