<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163934</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethyl chloride aerosol spray for local anesthesia before arterial puncture: randomized placebo-controlled trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To compare the efficacy of an ethyl chloride aerosol spray to a placebo spray applied in the emergency department to the skin to reduce pain from arterial puncture for blood gas analysis. Material and methods. Single-blind, randomized placebo-controlled trial in an emergency department of Hospital de Basurto in Bilbao, Spain. We included 126 patients for whom arterial blood gas analysis had been ordered. They were randomly assigned to receive application of the experimental ethyl chloride spray (n=66) or a placebo aerosol spray of a solution of alcohol in water (n=60). The assigned spray was applied just before arterial puncture. The main outcome variable was pain intensity reported on an 11-point numeric rating scale. Results. The median (interquartile range) pain level was 2 (1-5) in the experimental arm and 2 (1-4.5) in the placebo arm (P=.72). Conclusion. Topical application of an ethyl chloride spray did not reduce pain caused by arterial puncture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros-Peña, Sendoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Aedo, Irrintzi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo-De la Hoz, Gorka</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar la eficacia del cloruro de etilo en aerosol aplicado sobre la piel frente a placebo para disminuir el dolor provocado por una punción arterial durante la realización de una gasometría en el servicio de urgencias (SU). Método. Ensayo clínico aleatorizado, simple ciego y controlado con placebo realizado en el SU del Hospital de Basurto (Bilbao, España). Se incluyeron 126 pacientes a los que se les había solicitado una gasometría arterial, asignándoles al azar al grupo de tratamiento tópico experimental con cloruro de etilo en aerosol (n = 66) o al grupo control con mezcla hidroalcohólica en aerosol (n = 60), ambos administrados inmediatamente antes de la punción arterial. La variable de resultado principal fue la intensidad del dolor autopercibido por el paciente medida por la escala NRS-11. Resultados. El dolor percibido por el paciente tuvo una mediana (rango intercuartílico) de 2 (1-5) en el grupo tratado con cloruro de etilo y de 2 (1-4,5) en el grupo placebo (p = 0,72). Conclusiones. La aplicación de cloruro de etilo tópico no reduce el dolor por punción arterial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(3): 161-166, jun. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163934</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del cloruro de etilo en aerosol como anestésico local previo a la punción arterial: ensayo clínico aleatorizado controlado con placebo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5110^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1811^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
