<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042974</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastric food bezoar as a complication of bariatric surgery. Case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last few years bariatric surgery has become an excellent therapeutic alternative for the treatment of morbid obesity. Food bezoar as a cause for obstruction seems to be a very infrequent postoperative complication. It has only been published as anecdotal case reports. We describe a female patient with morbid obesity (weight, 131 kg; body mass index, 45) who underwent laparoscopic bariatric surgery (subtotal 95% gastrectomy with gastroyeyunoanastomosis in Roux-Y) obtaining a significant weight reduction (51 kg) in the next few months post surgery. She developed a food bezoar in the gastric remnant as a late complication of surgery (13 months after bariatric surgery) and presented as a gastric outlet acute obstruction with persistent vomiting and satiety. The diagnosis and treatment was performed through an upper GI endoscopy. It is important to consider this complication in patients with persisting vomiting after this kind of surgery. In the near future we will probably have a significant amount of patients operated due to morbid obesity and we may see this kind of complication more frequently</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zapata, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdova, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años la cirugía bariátrica se ha consolidado como una opción terapéutica eficaz en el tratamiento de la obesidad mórbida. El bezoar como causa de obstrucción en el remanente gástrico parece ser una complicación muy infrecuente de morbilidad postoperatoria en estos pacientes, pues en la bibliografía internacional sólo se citan casos anecdóticos. Se presenta el caso de una paciente con obesidad mórbida (peso, 131 kg; índice de masa corporal, 45) sometida a cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica (gastrectomía subtotal del 95% y gastroyeyunoanastomosis en Y de Roux), que logró reducir 51 kg de peso en los meses siguientes a la intervención quirúrgica. Trece meses más tarde presentó un bezoar en el remanente gástrico que se manifestó clínicamente como una obstrucción aguda «gástrica» con vómitos precoces de repetición e intensa saciedad. El diagnóstico y el tratamiento se realizaron mediante endoscopia digestiva alta. Es importante tener en cuenta esta complicación en pacientes que presentan vómitos tras esta cirugía. Próximamente, probablemente habrá un importante número de pacientes operados por obesidad mórbida en Chile y es posible que veamos esta complicación con mayor frecuencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;29(2): 77-80, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bezoar gástrico como complicación de la cirugía de obesidad mórbida. Caso clínico y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1654^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30720^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
