<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89514</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of early arthritis units that may be associated with better referral efficiency: survey of SERAP units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify characteristics of early arthritis units, that may be associated with better referral eficiency. Methods. A national survey of the 36 early arthritis units (EAU) in Spanish Rheumatology Units in 2004 (SERAP project). Survey collected information about general practitioners (GP) educational program to improve knowledge and practical skills of early arthritis, networking and feed-back system and referral efficiency. EAU were classified in two groups according to 25 and 50% of inappropriate referral process, respectively. Results. Thirty four of the 36 (94%) EAU, answered the survey. GP were trained in only 1 medical meeting in the primary care clinic, with one or more rheumatologists responsible of GP education. Fourteen of the 34 EAU (42.4%) regularly interacted with GP and only 20 (39.4%) contacted the GP who were responsible for the wrong referral process. Median lag time for referral to the Rheumatology out-patient clinic, was 73 days (15-365 days). The percentage of wrongly referred patients was between 0 and 80% (38% ± 21). Only 10 EAU (27.8%) referred patients appropriately according to the most strict criteria (25% of inappropriate referral) and 27 EAU (75%), according to 50% of inappropriate referral criteria. Conclusions. Only two aspects of the EAU implementation strategy were associated with better referral efficiency: 1) interaction with the GP responsible of the inappropriate referral process and 2) a lower median lag time for referral to the Rheumatology out-patient clinic(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villaverde, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Descalzo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar las características de una unidad de artritis precoz (UAP) que se asocian con una mejor eficiencia de la derivación desde atención primaria. Métodos. Encuesta a 36 UAP creadas en centros hospitalarios de toda España en el año 2004, mediante el programa SERAP. Las preguntas de la encuesta recogían detalles del proceso formativo de los médicos de atención primaria (MAP), del sistema de feedback, liderazgo y derivación. Se consideró que una UAP era tanto más eficiente, cuanto menor fuera el número de pacientes mal derivados. Para el análisis se utilizaron dos dinteles de derivación errónea: 25 y 50%. Resultados. Treinta y cuatro UAP (94%) participaron en la encuesta. La mayoría (62%) realizó la formación de los médicos en una sesión por centro de atención primaria. Catorce de las 34 UAP (42,4%) informaron regularmente del estado del proyecto a sus MAP y sólo 20 (39,4%), contactaron con los MAP que estaban derivando mal a los pacientes. El tiempo de espera medio para una primera consulta en Reumatología fue de 73 días (15-365 días). El porcentaje de pacientes mal derivados osciló entre el 0 y el 80% (38% ± 21). Sólo 10 UAP (27,8%) tenían una derivación aceptable, según el dintel más estricto (25% de derivación errónea). Hasta 27 UAP (75%) cumplían criterios de derivación aceptable si se establecía el dintel en el 50%. Conclusiones. Sólo dos aspectos de la estrategia adoptada por las UAP estaban asociados con la eficiencia en la derivación: 1) el hecho de que se contactara con los MAP que no estaban derivando bien y 2) una menor lista de espera en la consulta general de Reumatología(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);7(4): 236-240, jul.-ago.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de una unidad de artritis precoz que mejoran la eficiencia de la derivación: encuesta a las unidades SERAP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
