<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164461</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cultural adaptation to Spanish and assessment of an Adolescent Peer Relationships Tool for detecting school bullying: Preliminary study of the psychometric properties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: School bullying is a growing problem. The current study is aimed at culturally adapting and assessing the psychometric properties of a brief scale to measure bullying. Material and methods: A cross-cultural adaptation of the brief scale &#151;Adolescent Peer Relations Instrument-Bullying (APRI)&#151; was performed using the translation and back-translation technique. The Spanish version of APRI questionnaire was administered to a sample of 1,428 schoolchildren aged 12-14years in the region of Mar Menor in Murcia (Spain). Exploratory factor analysis, with oblique rotation, was used to assess the validity of the internal structure, the Cronbach's alpha to analyse their consistency, and the Kruskal-Wallis test to check their ability to discriminate between subjects with varying degrees of bullying according to Kidscreen-52 scale of social acceptability.  Results: Two factors were identified in the adapted version of APRI (physical victimisation and verbal/social victimisation), similar to those in the original scale. The questionnaire has high internal consistency (Cronbach's alpha=0.94) and discrimination capacity (P&lt;01), with significant effect sizes between degrees of bullying. Conclusions: The internal structure of the APRI Spanish version is similar to the original, and its scores confirm high reliability and construct validity. Further studies need to be performed with broader age ranges and confirmatory analysis techniques, to ratify the equivalence of the adapted version with the original version (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cózar Fernandez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heredia Calzado, Jose M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Russo de Leon, Jessica Roxanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón-Cánovas, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos y objetivos: El acoso escolar es un problema de magnitud creciente para el que existen escasos instrumentos breves validados al español. El objetivo de este estudio es adaptar y validar una escala breve de medición del bullying. Material y métodos: Se realizó una adaptación transcultural, mediante la técnica de traducción-retrotraducción, de la escala Adolescent Peer Relations Instrument-Bullying (APRI). La versión adaptada al español del cuestionario APRI se administró a una muestra de 1.428 escolares de entre 12-14años de la comarca del Mar Menor de Murcia (España). Se utilizó el análisis factorial exploratorio, con rotación oblicua, para evaluar la validez de la estructura interna, el alfa de Cronbach para analizar su consistencia y el test de Kruskal-Wallis para comprobar su capacidad de discriminación entre sujetos con distintos grados de bullying según la escala Kidscreen-52 de aceptabilidad social. Resultados: En la versión adaptada del APRI se identificaron 2 factores (victimización física y victimización verbal/social) similares a los de la escala original. El cuestionario tiene una elevada consistencia interna (alfa de Cronbach=0,94) y capacidad de discriminación (p&lt;0,01), con tamaños de efecto considerables entre los distintos grupos de grado de bullying. Conclusiones: La estructura interna de versión en español del APRI es análoga a la original, y sus puntuaciones confirman una elevada fiabilidad y validez de constructo. Serán necesarios estudios posteriores, con rangos de edad más amplios y técnicas de análisis confirmatorio, para ratificar la equivalencia de la versión adaptada con la original (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(1): 9-17, jul. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación cultural al español y baremación del Adolescent Peer Relations Instrument (APRI) para la detección de la victimización por acoso escolar: Estudio preliminar de las propiedades psicométricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
