<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77893</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Etiologic possibilities for the development of rheumatic diseases through environmental mechanisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Living beings and the environment that supports them have a mutual interdependence and therefore any event that occurs within an ecosystem affects all parts. The influence that the environment has on subjects that may develop an illness has been amply recognized. For some autoimmune diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), the possibility of its development under ultraviolet light and prolonged exposure to sunlight has been recognized. Microorganisms may activate other illnesses such as reactive arthritis. Substances such as alfalfa are also able to unleash disease activity. Laboratory workers who manipulate sera of patients with autoimmune rheumatic disorders develop antibodies to the sera that they are working with. It is thus that environmental sciences and focused research allow the development of a new approach to the study of possible pathogenic mechanisms in the appearance of certain rheumatic disorders. This article reviews the main existing evidence and proposes certain hypotheses derived from it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yáñez-Santos, Jorge A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañuelos-Ramírez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cedillo-Ramírez, María L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los seres vivos y el medio que los sostiene tienen una interdependencia obligada; cualquier evento ocurrido dentro de un ecosistema afecta a todas sus fracciones. El enfoque del proceso salud-enfermedad reconoce las influencias del medio ambiente. Para enfermedades autoinmunitarias como el lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) o generalizado se ha reconocido la posibilidad de que se produzca por luz ultravioleta y exposición al sol de manera prolongada. Los agentes microbianos pueden generar otras enfermedades como las artritis reactivas. Sustancias como la alfalfa son capaces de causar alguna enfermedad y los trabajadores de laboratorio que manipulan sueros de pacientes con enfermedades reumáticas autoinmunitarias se tornan positivos a los anticuerpos que están trabajando. Es así que las ciencias ambientales y el enfoque laboral permiten un nuevo abordaje para el estudio de los posibles mecanismos patogénicos en la aparición de algunas enfermedades reumáticas. Este artículo revisa las principales evidencias existentes y plantea algunas hipótesis generadas a partir de esa misma revisión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);3(5): 226-229, sept.-oct. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posibilidades etiológicas para el desarrollo de enfermedades reumáticas por mecanismos ambientales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
