<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77794</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome and ageing: Cognitive impairment and structural alterations of the central nervous system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The metabolic syndrome is a cluster of vascular risk factors, including: hypertension, insulin resistance,low levels of high density lipoproteins, high levels of triglycerides and obesity. Nowadays the prevalence of the syndrome inthe developmental societies increases and it is related to aging. Aim. To review the relation of metabolic syndrome to thecognitive impairment and cerebrovascular alterations during the aging. Development. The syndrome involves higher risk ofvascular pathologies and recently has been related to the pathological aging, including cognitive impairment and structuraldamage in the central nervous system. Specifically the studies about metabolic syndrome have described a profile of highergeneral cognitive impairment and higher risk of dementia, as well as concrete neuropsychological deficits probably related towhite matter alterations. The independent effects of vascular risk factors in cognition have been studied before as well as theirinfluences in structural integrity of the brain. Conclusion. Nowadays further research is necessary to know if the metabolicsyndrome effects on cognition and brain are greater than the sum of the effect of his components. In the future the knowledgeabout the cognitive and structural damage due to the syndrome could be useful to design prevention programs and promote thehealthy aging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jurado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome metabólico (SdMet) es un conjunto de factores de riesgo vascular que incluye: hipertensión,resistencia a la insulina, bajos niveles de lipoproteínas de alta densidad, altos niveles de triglicéridos y obesidad. En laactualidad, la prevalencia del síndrome en las sociedades desarrolladas aumenta y se relaciona con el envejecimiento. Objetivo.Revisar la relación del SdMet con el déficit cognitivo y las alteraciones cerebrovasculares durante el envejecimiento. Desarrollo.El SdMet implica un mayor riesgo de enfermedades vasculares y, recientemente, se ha relacionado con el envejecimientopatológico, incluido el deterioro cognitivo y los daños estructurales en el sistema nervioso central. Específicamente,los estudios sobre el SdMet han descrito un perfil de mayor deterioro cognitivo general y riesgo de demencia, así como déficitneuropsicológico concreto, probablemente relacionado con la alteración de la sustancia blanca. Los efectos independientesde los factores de riesgo vascular en la cognición se han estudiado anteriormente, así como su influencia en la integridadestructural del cerebro. Conclusión. Hoy en día se precisa más investigación para conocer si el efecto del SdMet en la cognicióny el cerebro es mayor que la suma de los efectos de sus componentes. En el futuro, el conocimiento sobre los daños cognitivosy estructurales debidos al síndrome podría ser útil para diseñar programas de prevención y promover el envejecimientosaludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(8): 417-424, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome metabólico y envejecimiento: déficit cognitivo y alteraciones estructurales del sistema nervioso central</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
