<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121173</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abdominal ultrasound and medical education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ultrasound is a very versatile diagnostic modality that permits real-time visualization of multiple internal organs. It is of invaluable help for the physical examination of the patients. Aim. To assess if ultrasound can be incorporated into medical education and if the students can perform a basic abdominal ultrasound examination without the necessity of a long period of training. Methodology. Twelve medical students were trained in basic abdominal ultrasound during a 15-hour training program including a 5-hour theoretical and practical course and supervised practice in 20 selected patients. Subsequently, we conducted an evaluation test that assessed the ability of students to obtain the ultrasound views and to detect various pathologies in five different patients. Results. The students were able to correctly identify the abdominal views more than 90% of the times. This percentage was only lower (80%) in the right subcostal view to locate the gallbladder. The accuracy or global efficiency of the ultrasound for the diagnosis of relevant pathological findings of the patients was greater than 90% (91.1% gallstones, abdominal aortic aneurysm 100%; splenomegaly 98.3%, ascites 100%; dilated inferior vena cava 100%; acute urinary retention 100%). Conclusion. The ultrasound may be a feasible learning tool in medical education. Ultrasound can help students to the improve the physical examination (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Macho, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez Lobato, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Casasola Sánchez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Santos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villena Garrido, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Rojo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubo Romano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La ecografía es una técnica muy versátil, que permite en tiempo real visualizar múltiples órganos internos y es de inestimable ayuda para la exploración física de los pacientes. Objetivo. Evaluar si la ecografía puede incorporarse en la enseñanza de la medicina y si los alumnos pueden realizar una exploración ecográfica abdominal básica sin un largo periodo de formación. Metodología. Doce estudiantes de medicina recibieron formación en ecografía abdominal básica durante un programa formativo de 15h de duración, que incluía un curso teórico-práctico de 5h y prácticas supervisadas en 20 pacientes seleccionados. Posteriormente realizamos una prueba de evaluación objetiva en la que valoramos la capacidad de los alumnos para obtener los planos ecográficos y detectar diversas enfermedades en 5 pacientes distintos. Resultados. Los estudiantes fueron capaces de identificar correctamente los planos abdominales en más del 90% de las ocasiones. Solo en el corte subcostal derecho para localizar la vesícula este porcentaje fue inferior (80%). La precisión o eficiencia global de la ecografía para el diagnóstico de los hallazgos patológicos relevantes de los enfermos fue superior al 90% (colelitiasis 91,1%; aneurisma de aorta abdominal 100%; esplenomegalia 98,3%; ascitis 100%; vena cava inferior dilatada 100%, y retención aguda de orina 100%). Conclusión. La ecografía puede ser una herramienta formativa en la enseñanza de la medicina y puede ayudar a los alumnos a mejorar la exploración física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(3): 131-136, abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ecografía clínica abdominal y educación médica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29144^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15084^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
