<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14258</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of antibiotic resistance in fecal flora before transrectal ultrasound-guided prostate biopsy and the clinical impact of targeted antibiotic prophylaxis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: In this study, we aimed to evaluate ciprofloxacin resistance and the presence of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase producing organisms (ESBLs) in the population of patients with indication to undergo prostate biopsy. Our additional aim was to compare the targeted antibiotic prophylaxis and sepsis rates after transrectal ultrasound guided prostate biopsy in patients who received routine ciprofloxacin prophylaxis and to evaluate the predictive factors of antibiotic resistance. Methods: Between September 2012 and January 2014, 300 patients were randomized to two groups. The first group (Group 1, n=156) received routine ciprofloxacin prophylaxis and the second group (Group 2, n=144) received a targeted prophylactic antibiotic regime that was adequate for rectal swab culture results. Rectal swab cultures were collected two weeks before the procedure. After the procedure, patients were followed for one month and told to return to the hospital if they developed a fever (&gt;38°C), shivering, dysuria or fatigue. Results: In Group 1, four patients (2.6%) returned to our clinic with signs of sepsis; no patient in Group 2 returned to our clinic (p= 0.124). When the rectal swab culture results of Group 2 were evaluated, there were ESBLs in 18 patients (12.5%), quinolone resistance in 26 patients (18%), and both ESBLs and quinolone resistance in 15 patients (10.4%). There were no statistically significant differences between antibiotic resistance and urologic operations, urinary tract infections, prior catheterization history, the presence of a catheter during prostate biopsy and antibiotic usage history due to a high PSA level. Conclusion: In our study, the rates of ESBL presence and ciprofloxacin resistance in rectal flora were not negligible. However, by obtaining rectal swab cultures prior to performing transrectal prostate biopsies and using targeted prophylaxis before prostate biopsy, the sepsis rates were reduced; however, this effect was statistically insignificant. Additional studies with a larger patient population could help to evaluate the targeted prophylaxis procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asif, Yildirim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrin, Tanidir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turhan, Caskurlu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haluk, Vahapoglu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gokhan, Atis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulent, Erol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenk, Gurbuz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meftun, Culpan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozgur, Arikan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Onur, Danacioglu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hulya, Caskurlu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En este estudio buscamos evaluar las resistencias a ciprofloxacino y la presencia de organismos productores de BLEE (Beta lactamasa de espectro extendido) en la población de pacientes con indicación de biopsia prostática. Otro objetivo adicional es la evaluación de la profilaxis antibiótica dirigida y las tasas de sepsis después de la biopsia de próstata guiada por ecografía transrectal comparando con los pacientes que recibieron profilaxis de rutina con ciprofloxacino y evaluar los factores predictivos de resistencia antibiótica. Métodos: Entre septiembre de 2012 y enero de 2014, 300 pacientes fueron asignados aleatoriamente a dos grupos. El primer grupo (Grupo 1, n=156) recibió profilaxis rutinaria con ciprofloxacino y el segundo grupo (Grupo 2, n=144) recibió un régimen de profilaxis antibiótica dirigida adecuado a los resultados del cultivo de muestras rectales. Las muestras rectales fueron obtenidas dos semanas antes del procedimiento. Después del procedimiento, los pacientes fueron seguidos durante un mes y se les dijo que volvieran al hospital si tenían fiebre (&gt;38º), escalofríos, disuria o fatiga. Resultados. En el grupo 1, cuatro pacientes (2,6%) volvieron a nuestra consulta con signos de sepsis; ningún paciente del grupo 2 volvió (p=0,124). Cuando se evaluaron los resultados de cultivo rectal del Grupo 2, había BLEEs en 18 pacientes (12,5%), resistencia a quinolona en 26 pacientes (18%), y la combinación de ambos en 15 pacientes (10,4%). No había diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre resistencia antibiótica y operaciones urológicas, infección urinaria, historia de sonda vesical previa, presencia de sonda en el momento de la biopsia e historia de toma de antibióticos por PSA elevado. Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio, las tasas de presencia de BLEE y resistencia a ciprofloxacino en la flora rectal no eran despreciables. Sin embargo, mediante la obtención de cultivos de muestras rectales y la utilización de profilaxis dirigida antes de la realización de la biopsia prostática transrectal se redujeron las tasas de sepsis; sin embargo, este efecto no fue estadísticamente significativo. Estudios adicionales con poblaciones de pacientes más grandes podrían ayudar a evaluar el procedimiento con profilaxis dirigida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(10): 852-858, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de resistencias a antibióticos en la flora fecal antes de la biopsia de próstata guiada por ecografía transrectal y el impacto clínico de la profilaxis antibiótica dirigida</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
