<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75571</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7548</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary steroid profile after the completion of concentric and concentric/eccentric trials with the same total workload</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High intensity strength training causes changes in steroid hormone concentrations.This could be altered by the muscular contraction type: eccentric or concentric.The aim of this study was to compare the effect of the completion of a short concentric(CON) and concentric/eccentric (CON/ECC) trial on the urinary steroidprofile, both with the same total work. 18 males performed the trials on an isokineticdynamometer (BIODEX III) exercising quadriceps muscles, right and left, on differentdays. Trial 1(CON): 4x10 Concentric knee extension + relax knee flexion,speed 60&amp;#186;/second; rest 90 seconds between each series and 4 minutes between each legexercise. Trial 2(CON/ECC): 4x5 concentric knee extension + Eccentric knee flexionunder similar conditions. Urine samples were taken before the exercise and onehour after finishing it. Androsterone, Etiocholanolone, DHEA, Androstenedione,Testosterone, Epitestosterone, Dehydrotestosterone, Estrone, B-Estradiol, Tetrahydrocortisone,Tetrahydrocortisol, Cortisone and Cortisol (free, glucoconjugated andsulfoconjugated) urinary values were determined using gas chromatography/massspectrometry techniques. No significant differences were noted in Total Work andAverage Peak Torque, although Maximum Peak Torque in the CON/ECC trial washigher than in the CON trial. These results demonstrate no changes in the steroidprofile before and after trials, or when comparing CON to CON/ECC trials. Thedata suggest that eccentric contractions do not cause hormonal changes different tothe ones produced by concentric contractions, when they are performed in strengthshort trials with the same total workload(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olcina, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mu&amp;#241;oz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maynar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timon, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomas-Carus, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raimundo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tampoco se observó ningún cambio en el perfil esteroideo urinario entre antes y después de las sesiones de ejercicio, o comparando las sesiones CON/EXC con la CON. Por tanto, los datos sugieren que las contracciones excéntricas no producen alteraciones hormonales diferentes a las producidas por las contracciones concéntricas, cuando se trata de sesiones de ejercicio de fuerza de corta duración con similar carga de trabajo total(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J Physiol Biochem;65(2): 105-112, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75571</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil esteroideo urinario tras la realización de una sesión de ejercicio concéntrico y otra concéntrico/excéntrico con similar carga de trabajo total</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7696</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33414</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23571^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
