<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142461</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Weight loss and metabolic outcomes 12 months after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in a population of Southeastern Brazil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: previous outcome research in bariatric surgery has to document positive changes in co-morbidities associated with obesity. Objective: the study aimed report a description of the impact of bariatric surgery on weight loss and on the resolution of diseases associated with obesity in patients followed up for 12 months in the public health service of São Paulo/Brazil. Methods: the study was conducted on the data for 598 selected patients with grade III obesity subjected to Rouxen-Y gastric bypass evaluated postoperatively and 6 and 12 months after surgery. Anthropometric, demographic and biochemical data and personal history were determined at each time point. Serum glucose, total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, HDL cholesterol and triglycerides were determined in the biochemical evaluation. Data were analyzed statistically by the Chi-square test, by ANOVA followed by the Bonferroni post-test and by the Student t-test for independent data, significance set at p&lt;0.05. Results: weight loss of 45.5±13.7kg (33.5%) was observed during the first year after surgery. Serum glucose, total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol were reduced during the first six months after surgery and the values were maintained up to 12 months, whereas weight and triglycerides were reduced throughout the study period. A reduced prevalence of diabetes mellitus and dyslipidemia was observed after surgery (p0.001). Conclusions: Roux-en-Y gastric bypass is an important procedure for weight loss and control of comorbidities such as diabetes and dyslipidemia at least during the first postoperative year (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sivieri, Thiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Bruno AP de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Annunciato, Danielle R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicoletti, Carolina F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcatto, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinhel, Marcela AS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cássia Paixão Chaves, Raoana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tabajara Parreiras, Luciana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa Nonino, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgado, Luiza MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luz, Gabriela RL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Junior, Wilson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza, Dorotéia RS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vulcano, Vinicius MC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la investigación de los resultados previa en cirugía bariátrica tiene que documentar los cambios positivos en las comorbilidades asociadas a la obesidad. Objetivo: el objetivo del estudio fue informar de una descripción de los efectos de la cirugía bariátrica sobre la pérdida de peso y en la resolución de enfermedades asociadas con la obesidad en pacientes seguidos durante 12 meses en el servicio de salud pública de São Paulo/Brasil. Métodos: el estudio se realizó con los datos de 598 pacientes seleccionados con obesidad grado III sometidos a bypass gástrico en Y de Roux evaluados antes y 6 y 12 meses después de la cirugía. En cada momento se determinaron la antropometría, los datos demográficos y bioquímicos y la historia personal. La glucosa sérica, el colesterol total, el colesterol LDL, el colesterol HDL y los triglicéridos fueron determinados en la evaluación bioquímica. Los datos fueron analizados estadísticamente por el test de Chi-cuadrado, por ANOVA seguido por el post-test de Bonferroni y por la prueba t de Student para datos independientes; significación fijada en p&lt;0,05. Resultados: se observó pérdida de peso de 45,5±13,7 kg (33,5%) durante el primer año después de la cirugía. Glucosa sérica, colesterol total y colesterol LDL se redujeron durante los primeros seis meses después de la cirugía y los valores se mantuvieron hasta los 12 meses, mientras que el peso y los triglicéridos se redujeron en todo el período de estudio. Se observó una prevalencia reducida de diabetes mellitus y dislipidemia después de la cirugía (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: el bypass gástrico en Y de Roux es un procedimiento importante para la pérdida de peso y el control de las comorbilidades como la diabetes y la dislipidemia, al menos durante el primer año postoperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1017-1021, sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La pérdida de peso y los resultados metabólicos después de 12 meses de bypass gástrico en Y de Roux en una población del sureste de Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22830^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
