<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143830</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The &#147;x&#148; of dyslipemias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with cholestatic diseases can present secondary hypercholesterolemia, as a result of the accumulation of lipoprotein X (Lp-X); an abnormal LDL form, considered as the biochemical parameter more sensitive and specific for the diagnosis of cholestasis intra or extrahepatic cholestasis. The aim of this clinical comunication is to illustrate this association. A 54-year-old male with severe cholestatic liver disease wich in turn presents a progressive total cholesterol rise and LDL with presence of lipoprotein X. Total and LDL cholesterol were down to normal, also coinciding with the improvement of cholestatic liver disease conferring cardiovascular protection pattern (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Ares, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navea Aguilera, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montaño, July Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guijarro de Armas, M Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Piñero, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Viveros, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con colestasis hepática pueden presentar hipercolesterolemia secundaria, como consecuencia de la acumulación de la lipoproteína X (Lp-X); una forma anómala de LDL, considerada como el parámetro bioquímico más sensible y específico para el diagnóstico de colestasis intra o extrahepática. El objetivo de esta comunicación clínica es ilustrar esta asociación. Se trata de un varón de 54 años con hepatopatía colestásica severa que a su vez presenta una elevación progresiva de colesterol total y LDL con presencia de lipoproteína X. El colesterol total y LDL, descendieron progresivamente hasta normalizarse, coincidiendo con la mejoría de la función hepática, confiriendo un patrón de protección cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(4): 953-955, abr. 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La X de las dislipemias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2830^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1676^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8247^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
