<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68423</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: a healthy sex education promotes both the individual health and the construction of an integral behaviour model which contributes to personal balance, communicative skills, pleasure and a good development of affectivity. The problem of teenagers&#146; sexuality is not that they are active sexually, but that they have neither a preparation nor an orientation in order to responsible sex behaviour. The study&#146;s aim was to describe the information that Valencia&#146; secondary obligatory education adolescents have with regard to: contraceptive methods, sexually transmitted diseases (STD), abortion and teenager&#146;s self-opinion. Material and methods: descriptive, transversal and observational study. Population: fifteen to eighteen-year-old adolescent students of three secondary education institutes. The information was obtained by an ad hoc anonymous survey. Results: the surveys of 67 adolescents (43.3% boys and 56.7% girls) are studied. The study shows a lack (30%) with regard to contraceptive methods. Eighty eight percent of the population agrees on abortion. There is a low consciousness with regard to seriousness and importance of STD. Couple relations are described as absorbent (25%). Moreover, adolescents&#146; opinion of the opposite sex is not too bad or negative by almost 50% of adolescents. Conclusion: an integral sex education is needed both from educational systems and family, in order to a suitable adolescent sexual health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colombo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Munitis, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: una educación sexual sana es aquella que fomenta tanto la salud del individuo como la construcción de un modelo de comportamiento integral que aporte equilibrio personal, habilidades comunicativas, placer y un buen desarrollo de la afectividad. El problema de la sexualidad en los adolescentes no es que estos sean sexualmente activos, sino que no cuentan con una preparación y orientación para una conducta sexual responsable. El objetivo del estudio fue describir la información que tienen los adolescentes valencianos de enseñanza secundaria obligatoria sobre sexualidad, en relación a: métodos anticonceptivos, enfermedades de transmisión sexual (ETS), aborto y autoconcepto del adolescente. Material y métodos: estudio observacional descriptivo transversal. Población: adolescentes de 15-18 años estudiantes de tres institutos de enseñanza secundaria valencianos. La información fue obtenida a través de una encuesta anónima ad hoc. Resultados: se estudian las encuestas de 67 alumnos (43,3% chicos y 56,7% chicas) de una edad media de 16,3 años. El estudio revela un desconocimiento de un 30% en relación a los métodos anticonceptivos, un criterio favorable al aborto en un 88% de los casos y una baja concienciación respecto a la gravedad e importancia de las ETS. Las relaciones de pareja son valoradas como absorbentes en un 25% de los casos y la visión del sexo opuesto es considerada por estos adolescentes como regular o negativa en casi un 50% de los casos. Conclusiones: del estudio se deduce la necesidad de una educación integral para la sexualidad tanto desde los sistemas educativos como de la familia, en pro de una adecuada salud sexual del adolescente, fuente de realización personal del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;10(39): 433-442, jul.-sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68423</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3182^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
