<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153121</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of the professional training specific competences of the physiotherapist</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. The present study covers the perception of the physical therapist unique knowledge and competence among the allied health care professionals. Subjects and methods. A total of 102 professionals participated related to the work of a therapist answering the questionnaire that covered all areas of specific skills and scope necessary at time of graduation. A non-experimental transversal cross co relational study was used to interview the volunteer&#146;s subjects who gave their personal opinion. Results and conclusions. The outcome indicated there are agreement among allied health care professional about the importance of the competence of the physical therapist although they advise of some differences in the emphasis according from their specific area of work. Those who work closely to a therapist developed a higher importance to the scope of the physical therapist as a clinician. Beside common areas of conflict such as health administration were least appreciated by other allied health care workers who normally are employed in this area. The results are reviewed to apply them in the adjustments for future curriculum in physical therapy schools (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada-Goic, Claudia A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Elgueta, Alejandra M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La presente investigación se interesó en conocer la percepción que profesionales del equipo de salud tienen sobre las competencias de formación del cinesiólogo. Sujetos y métodos. Un total de 102 participantes de profesiones afines a la cinesiología contestaron el instrumento que contenía el total de las competencias específicas propuestas para el perfil de egreso. Mediante un diseño no experimental transversal correlacional, los participantes voluntarios opinaron individualmente sobre la cuestión. Resultados y conclusiones. Los resultados indican que existe acuerdo sobre la relevancia de las competencias del perfil, aunque hay algunas diferencias de énfasis según la profesión. Aquellos profesionales que desarrollan labores vinculadas directamente con el trabajo del cinesiólogo otorgaron una mayor importancia a las competencias del área clínica. Además, áreas históricas de conflicto como la gestión y administración fueron menos valoradas por profesionales que suelen ejercer estos roles. Se discuten los resultados en torno a sus posibles aplicaciones para la actualización de los perfiles de egreso profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);19(3): 125-135, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción sobre las competencias específicas de formación profesional del cinesiólogo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6432^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32705^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
