<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69138</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Combining efforts and achieving the maximum degree of quality and safety in the care provided is the responsibility of healthcare professionals. We proposed to assess the perception of clinical safety in peritoneal dialysis perceived by the patient and to determine the importance of communication-information provided by healthcare personnel. Descriptive transversal study, encompassing all patients on peritoneal dialysis, distributing a survey seeking their opinion on clinical safety. 38 surveys were analysed (response rate 100%). 60.5% were men and 39.5% women. Average age 59.1 ±12 years and average time on the dialysis technique 24.4 ±19.7 months. 71% of the patients stated that they were very concerned about suffering a medical error. 100% of the patients who had suffered an undesired effect as a result of the care or medication administered stated that they were very worried about medical errors. On analysing the questions relating to information communication between healthcare personnel and the patient, 81% indicated that the effects and precautions of the treatment had been explained to them in detail, and 84.2% responded that they had been able to discuss their doubts and concerns with the nurse and doctor in sufficient privacy. However, those patients who detected a deficit in the information-communication in any of these aspects mentioned that they were very concerned about suffering from a medical error. Clinical safety arouses interest and concern among patients. The lack of information-communication is related to greater concern about suffering from a medical error (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochando García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Martínez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paniagua, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royuela García, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Meca, M. Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunar esfuerzos y conseguir el máximo grado de calidad y seguridad en la atención prestada es una responsabilidad de los profesionales sanitarios. Nos propusimos evaluar la percepción de la seguridad clínica en diálisis peritoneal percibida por el paciente y determinar la importancia que tiene la comunicación-información del personal sanitario. Estudio descriptivo y transversal, a todos los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal, administrando una encuesta de opinión sobre seguridad clínica. Se analizaron 38 encuestas (tasa respuesta 100 %). El 60.5% eran hombres y el 39.5% mujeres. Edad media 59,1±12 años y tiempo medio en técnica 24.4 ±19.7 meses. El 71 % de los pacientes manifestó que les preocupaba mucho sufrir un error médico. El 100 % de los pacientes que habían sufrido un efecto indeseado como consecuencia de la asistencia o de la medicación administrada, manifestaron estar muy preocupados por sufrir un error médico. Al analizar las preguntas relacionadas con la información- comunicación entre el personal sanitario y el paciente, el 81% manifestaron que les habían explicado, con detalle, los efectos y precauciones del tratamiento y el 84,2% respondió que habían podido consultar sus dudas y preocupaciones a la enfermera y al médico con la suficiente intimidad. Sin embargo, aquellos pacientes que detectaron un déficit en la información-comunicación en alguno de estos aspectos, comentaron estar muy preocupados por poder sufrir un error médico. La seguridad clínica suscita interés y preocupación entre los pacientes. La falta de información comunicación se relaciona con una mayor preocupación de sufrir un error médico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;11(3): 190-195, jul.-sept. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69138</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
