<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137257</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Could aggressive fibromatosis be considered whitin the spectrum of gstrointestinal stromal tumors?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Desmoid tumors appear as a result of fibroblastic proliferation without histological signs of malignancy but locally aggressive. Fibromatosis have been described after removing a gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST). We present a case of a resected gastric GIST and eigthteen months after surgery, a exploratory laparotomy was performed suspecting recurrence and after definitive histological findings, the diagnosis was aggressive intra-abdominal fibromatosis. Clinical-oncological assessment of fibromatosis is discussed as a form of GIST local recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Velasco, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yagüe, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Moreno, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballestero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornejo, M A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores desmoides aparecen como resultado de la proliferación fibroblástica, sin signos histológicos de malignidad pero localmente muy agresivos. Se han descrito casos de fibromatosis tras extirpación de GIST. Presentamos el caso de un GIST gástrico operado, que a los 18 meses se realiza laparotomía exploradora por sospecha de recurrencia y tras hallazgos histológicos definitivos, se diagnostica de fibromatosis intra-abdominal agresiva. Se discute la valoración clínico-oncológica de la fibromatosis como forma de recurrencia local del GIST (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;18(1): 38-42, 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Podría englobarse la fibromatosis agresiva dentro del espectro de los tumores del estroma gastrointestinal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31469^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10723^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31470^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31470^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31470^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31470^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31469^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10723^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31469^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37549^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
