<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118712</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Celiac disease and alcohol use disorders: Increased length of hospital stay, overexpenditures and attributable mortality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: alcohol use disorders are associated with a greater incidence of certain comorbidities in patients with celiac disease. Currently there is no available information about the impact that these disorders may have on length of hospital stays, overexpenditures during hospital stays, and excess mortality in these patients. Methods: a case-control study was conducted with a selection of patients 18 years and older hospitalized during 2008-2010 in 87 hospitals in Spain. Estimations of excess length of stays, costs, and attributable mortality were calculated using a multivariate analysis of covariance, which included age, gender, hospital group, alcohol use disorders, tobacco related disease and 30 other comorbidities. Results: patients who had both celiac disease and alcohol use disorders had an increased length of hospital stay, an average of 3.1 days longer in women, and 1.7 days longer in men. Excess costs per stay ranged from 838.7 euros in female patients, to 389.1 euros in male patients. Excess attributable mortality was 15.1 % in women, 12.2 % in men. Conclusions: apart from a gluten-free diet and other medical measures, the prevention of alcohol abuse is indicated in these patients. Patients hospitalized who present these disorders should receive specialized attention after leaving the hospital. Early detection and treatment should be used to prevent the appearance of organic lesions and should not be solely focused on male patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sharp, Brett</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gili, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Béjar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: los trastornos por consumo de alcohol se han asociado a una mayor incidencia de ciertas comorbilidades entre los pacientes con enfermedad celiaca. En la actualidad no disponemos de información sobre si estos trastornos tienen un impacto en la prolongación de las estancias hospitalarias, mayores costes por estancia y un exceso de mortalidad entre estos pacientes. Métodos: Se hizo un estudio de casos y controles a partir de una muestra de pacientes de 18 o más años de edad hospitalizados durante 2008-2010 en 87 hospitales de España. Las estimaciones de prolongación de estancias, exceso de costes y mortalidad atribuible se calcularon mediante un modelo de análisis multivariante de la covarianza que incluyó edad, género, grupo hospitalario, trastornos por alcohol, trastornos por tabaco y 30 comorbilidades. Resultados: los pacientes de enfermedad celiaca con trastornos por alcohol presentaron una prolongación de estancias de 3,1 días en las mujeres y de 1,7 días en los varones, un exceso de costes por estancia de 838,7 euros en las mujeres y de 389,1 euros en los varones, y un exceso de mortalidad atribuible de 15,1 % en las mujeres y de 12,2 % en los varones. Conclusiones: además de una dieta sin gluten y otras medidas asistenciales, en estos pacientes está indicada la prevención del abuso de alcohol, y los hospitalizados que presentan estos trastornos deberían recibir asistencia especializada tras el alta hospitalaria. La detección e intervención precoz debería intentar prevenir el desarrollo de lesiones orgánicas y no centrarse exclusivamente en varones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(9): 537-543, oct. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad celiaca y trastornos por consumo de alcohol: prolongación de estancias, exceso de costes y mortalidad atribuible</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
