<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037947</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consistency of clinical practice with the scientific evidence in the management of childhood asthma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is substantial inconsistency between the evidence available on the management of childhood asthma and its application in practice. Objective: To evaluate the degree of appropriateness of current management of childhood asthma. Material and methods We performed a structured review of the articles published on appropriateness in the recent biomedical literature (last 5 years). Methodological analysis and qualitative synthesis were performed. Results: Twenty-three articles were identified that reflected the following problems: insufficient documentation on trigger factors, evolution of pulmonary function and symptoms, inadequate guidelines on the treatment of exacerbations, inadequate use of inhaler devices, insufficient use of anti-inflammatory drugs, unjustified heterogeneity in the selection of anti-inflammatory drugs, lack of correlation between severity and level of treatment, lack of written guidelines on customized self-management, unjustified use of antibiotics, and lack of pulmonary function testing devices. Conclusions: The management of childhood asthma should be reviewed since a large number of decisions made in clinical practice are not always based on valid scientific evidence</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Sangrador, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe una importante discordancia entre la evidencia disponible sobre el manejo del asma en la infancia y su grado de aplicación en la práctica clínica real. Objetivo Valorar el grado de idoneidad de la práctica pediátrica en el manejo del asma. Material y métodos: Revisión bibliográfica estructurada de los trabajos sobre adecuación publicados en la literatura biomédica actualizada (últimos 5 años). Análisis metodológico y síntesis cualitativa. Resultados:  Se han identificado 23 artículos que reflejan los siguientes problemas: insuficiente documentación escrita sobre factores desencadenantes y sobre medición y evolución de síntomas y función pulmonar, pautas inadecuadas de tratamiento de crisis de reagudización, empleo de dispositivos de administración de medicación inhalada inadecuados, insuficiente empleo de fármacos antiinflamatorios de control, heterogeneidad injustificada en la elección de antiinflamatorio de control, falta de correlación entre grado de afectación y nivel de tratamiento, carencia de pautas escritas de actuación personalizada, uso injustificado de antibióticos y falta de implantación de dispositivos de control de la función pulmonar. Conclusiones: El manejo del asma en la infancia debe ser revisado, ya que una parte importante de las decisiones de la práctica clínica no siempre se sustenta en una evidencia científica válida</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);62(3): 237-247, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de la práctica clínica a la evidencia científica en el manejo del asma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33209</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
