<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14661</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficiency estimation model based on the Experimental Program for Parents: A Generalizability Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a growing concern on the estimation of both efficacy and efficiency of parenting intervention programs. The present study is aimed at showing the efficiency estimation model based on the Experiential Program for Parents (Máiquez, Rodrigo, Capote y Vermaes, 2000). This Program was developed in three different community centers placed on Tenerife island, which were dedicated to primary and secondary prevention. The Program is made up of 4 Modules to be treated in 12 meetings. In all these meeting parents and the assistent-mediator were observed to have a follow-up of the process of knowledge building within the group. Generalizability theory allowed us to prove the reliability of the design structure used in order to generalize the results. We found that a improvement of the Program application is possible, on the one hand, by increasing moderately the number of categories and, on the other hand, by diminishing the number of observations and registers. In this sense, we reduce Program costs concerning assistant staff while keeping the information level about the progress observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo López, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Chaves, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Villaseñor, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vermaes, Ignace P. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada día se hace más necesaria la evaluación tanto de la eficacia como de la eficiencia de los programas de intervención familiar. El objetivo de este estudio es presentar el modelo de evaluación de la eficiencia seguido con el Programa Experimental para Padres (Máiquez, Rodrigo, Capote y Vermaes, 2000). Este programa se desarrolló en tres centros comunitarios de la isla de Tenerife, destinados a prevención primaria y secundaria. El Programa consta de 4 Módulos repartidos en un total de 12 reuniones. En cada una de ellas se realizaban observaciones al grupo de padres y al guía-mediador, llevando así un seguimiento de proceso. La teoría de la generalizabilidad nos permite comprobar la validez de la estructura del diseño que hemos utilizado para poder generalizar los resultados. Encontramos que se puede mejorar la aplicabilidad del programa incrementando moderadamente el número de categorías y disminuyendo el número de observaciones y registros. De esta forma se reduce el coste del programa en personal observador sin perder información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(4): 533-542, nov. 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la eficiencia en la intervención familiar: generalizabilidad y optimización del Programa Experiencial para Padres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
