<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142643</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of procalcitonin and C-reactive protein for predicting bacteremia in urinary tract infections in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of this study was to analyze and compare the capacity of procalcitonin (PCT), C-reactive protein (CRP), lactate and leukocytes to predict the presence of bacteremia in patients with urinary tract infections (UTIs). Methods: Observational, retro-prospective analytical study of adult patients (&amp;#8805;15 years) diagnosed with UTI in an emergency department from August 2012 to January 2013. Results: The study included 328 patients diagnosed with UTI, with a mean age of 52 ± 22 years, 74% of whom were women. Of these, 43 (13.1%) had bacteremia. For predicting bacteremia, PCT achieved the largest area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC-AUC) at .993 (95% CI .987-1; P &lt; .001). A cutoff &amp;#8805; 1.16 ng/mL achieves a sensitivity of 100%, a specificity of 97%, a positive predictive value of 84% and a negative predictive value of 100%. Lactate achieved an ROC-AUC of .844, and CRP achieved only .534. The mean values when comparing PCT levels in patients with UTIs with and without bacteremia were 8.08 ± 16.37 and .34 ± .37 ng/mL, respectively (P &lt; .001). Conclusions: For patients with UTIs in the emergency department, PCT achieves considerable diagnostic performance for suspecting bacteremia, a performance greater than that of lactate, CRP and leukocytes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heredero-Gálvez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Martín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Guerrero, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso-Manso, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizcano-Lizcano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julián-Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del estudio fue analizar y comparar la capacidad de la procalcitonina (PCT), proteína C reactiva (PCR), lactato y leucocitos para predecir la existencia de bacteriemia en los pacientes con infección del tracto urinario (ITU). Métodos: Estudio observacional, retroprospectivo y analítico de pacientes adultos (&amp;#8805; 15 años) diagnosticados de ITU en un servicio de urgencias desde agosto de 2012 hasta enero de 2013. Resultados: Se incluyeron 328 casos diagnosticados de ITU con una edad media de 52 ± 22 años, el 74% mujeres. De ellos 43 (13,1%) con bacteriemia. Para predecir bacteriemia la PCT obtiene la mayor área bajo la curva ROC (ABC-ROC), de 0,993 (IC 95%: 0,987-1, p &lt; 0,001) y con un punto de corte &amp;#8805; 1,16 ng/ml se consigue una sensibilidad del 100%, especificidad del 97%, un valor predictivo positivo de 84% y un valor predictivo negativo del 100%. El lactato consigue un ABC-ROC de 0,844 y la PCR solo de 0,534. Los valores medios al comparar la PCT en pacientes con ITU con/sin bacteriemia fueron 8,08 ± 16,37 vs 0,34 ± 0,37 ng/ml, p &lt; 0,001. Conclusiones: En los pacientes con ITU en el servicio de urgencias la PCT consigue un gran rendimiento diagnóstico para sospechar bacteriemia, mayor que el lactato, la PCR y los leucocitos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(8): 502-510, oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la procalcitonina y proteína C reactiva para predecir bacteriemia en las infecciones del tracto urinario en el servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24549^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24549^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24549</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22311^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
