<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161635</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinicopathologic variants of mycosis fungoides</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mycosis fungoides (MF) is the most common primary cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. The clinical course of the disease is typically characterized by progression from a nonspecific phase of erythematous macules to the appearance of plaques and ultimately, in some patients, tumors. However, numerous clinical and histopathologic variants of MF with specific therapeutic and prognostic implications have been described in recent decades. Clarification of the differential diagnosis can be frustrated by the wide range of clinical manifestations and histopathologic patterns of cutaneous infiltration, particularly in the early phases of the disease. In this paper, we review the main clinical, histopathologic, and immunohistochemical characteristics of the variants of MF described in the literature in order to facilitate early diagnosis of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina-Ruiz, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-González, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La micosis fungoide (MF) es el linfoma primario cutáneo de células T más frecuente. La evolución clínica clásica de la enfermedad se caracteriza por la progresión desde una fase inespecífica de máculas eritematosas a la aparición de placas y, finalmente, tumores en algunos pacientes. Sin embargo, a lo largo de las últimas décadas se han descrito numerosas variantes de MF, tanto desde el punto de vista clínico como histopatológico, con implicaciones terapéuticas y pronósticas específicas. El diagnóstico diferencial se ve dificultado así ante el amplio abanico de manifestaciones clínicas y patrones histopatológicos de infiltración cutánea, especialmente en fases precoces de la enfermedad. Este artículo revisa las principales características clínicas, histopatológicas e inmunohistoquímicas que definen las distintas variantes de MF descritas en la literatura con el objetivo de facilitar el diagnóstico temprano de MF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;108(3): 192-208, abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161635</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variantes clínico-patológicas de micosis fungoide</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29031^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
