<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82806</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of rebleeding from peptic ulcer in patients treated with proton pump inhibitors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The aim of this study is to assess the prevalence of peptic ulcer rebleeding by comparing patients who received omeprazole versus pantoprazole i.v. as well as to study the costs of each treatment.Patients and methods: Retrospective and observational study. Information was gathered on sex and age of the patients, the diagnosis of upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGB) according to the classification of Forrest, the type of proton pump inhibitor (PPI) i.v. used and the treatment regimen, presence or absence of rebleeding, mortality and data on health costs through a pharmacoeconomic cost-effectiveness analysis. Results: We included 807 patients, 490 of whom (60.7%) received pantoprazole and 317 (39.3%) omeprazole. There was no difference between the average age of both groups, 61.2 years vs 62.3, p=0.544; sex, 71% men vs 68.6%, P=.78; the percentage of patients within Forrest I was 35.1% vs 42%, P=.05, in grade II was 50.2% vs 40.4%, P=.006 and in grade III was 14.7% vs 17.7%, P=.259. The number of vials per day of treatment was significantly lower in the pantoprazole group from the third to fifth day, with no differences in the first two days and the sixth. There was rebleeding in 8.2% of patients treated with pantoprazole and 11.7% with omeprazole, P=.098. 2.2% of patients treated with pantoprazole died vs 2.6% treated with omeprazole, P=.086. The expected cost of a patient treated with pantoprazole was 2188.25&#128; vs 3279.02&#128; with omeprazole, P&lt;.001. Conclusions: While the results of the administration of omeprazole vs pantoprazole i.v. in patients with UGB are similar, the latter turns out to have a better cost-effectiveness profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iborra, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saperas, Esteba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de Sousa, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es la evaluación de la prevalencia de resangrado por úlcera péptica comparando pacientes que habían recibido omeprazol frente a pantoprazol por vía intravenosa y estudiar los costes derivados de cada tratamiento. Pacientes y métodos: estudio observacional y retrospectivo. Se recogió información sobre el sexo y la edad de los pacientes, el diagnóstico de la hemorragia digestiva alta (HDA) según la clasificación de Forrest, el tipo de inhibidor de la bomba de protones (IBP) utilizado por vía intravenosa y la pauta de tratamiento, presencia o no de resangrado, mortalidad y datos referentes a los costes sanitarios mediante un modelo farmacoeconómico de coste-efectividad. Resultados: Se incluyó a 807 pacientes, 490 de los cuales (60,7%) recibieron pantoprazol y 317 (39,3%) omeprazol. No hubo diferencias entre la edad media de ambos grupos (61,2 frente a 62,3 años, p=0,544), sexo (el 71% de varones frente al 68,6% de mujeres; p=0,78), porcentaje de enfermos dentro del grado I de Forrest (el 35,1 frente al 42%; p=0,05), en el grado II (el 50,2 frente al 40,4%; p=0,006) y en el grado III (el 14,7 frente al 17,7%; p=0,259). El número de viales por día de tratamiento por vía intravenosa fue significativamente inferior en el grupo de pantoprazol desde el tercer al quinto día, sin diferencias en los dos primeros días y a partir del sexto. Hubo resangrado en el 8,2% de los pacientes tratados con pantoprazol y en el 11,7% de los tratados con omeprazol (p=0,098). Falleció el 2,2% de los pacientes tratados con pantoprazol frente al 2,6% de los tratados con omeprazol (p=0,086). El coste esperado de un paciente tratado con pantoprazol es de 2.188,25&#128; mientras que con omeprazol es de 3.279,02&#128; (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: Si bien los resultados de la administración de omeprazol frente a pantoprazol por vía intravenosa en pacientes con HDA ulcerosa son similares, este último resulta tener mejor perfil de coste-efectividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);134(13): 577-582, mayo 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de nueva hemorragia por úlcera péptica en pacientes tratados con inhibidores de la bomba de protones por vía intravenosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52172^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10633^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27743^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6446^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27743^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27743^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52172^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10633^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
