<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110984</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Identify mental health problems and distress in cancer patients; recognise the obstacles to their detection and the lack of specific psychological care for patients who need it; and determine the pathways that are being developed to address them. A true understanding of these problems would facilitate the design, implementation and improvement of health-care resources for oncologic patients. Methods: Literature review of the investigations on the subject from the last decades. Results: During their illness, cancer patients show a high prevalence of psychopathological disorders, anxiety symptoms, depression and distress, related to several medical, physical, psychological and social factors. To discover the protective and predictive factors of worsening, data analysis does not indicate the real punctual prevalence of these disorders and symptoms -mainly due to the different investigation methods used-, neither does it show the evolution during the illness and afterwards. Several barriers make psychological assessment of cancer patients difficult, this leads to a lack of specific and specialised attention when needed, a clinic worsening of these patients and difficulty in adhesion to  medical treatments. Training in communication tools for sanitary professionals and the development of distress and mental disorder detection tools, according to the clinic reality of the patients, are the solutions preferred in this last decade, though with irregular results.  Conclusions: In order to offer cancer patients a specific psychological attention when needed, mental health problems and distress detection tools need to keep improving. A real knowledge of these problems will result in the design of specialised psycho-oncological and  clinic psychological assistance programmes. To guarantee access and coordination with the psychologist in medical teams is essential (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los problemas de salud mental y de malestar psíquico de los pacientes con cáncer, las barreras que pueden incidir en su escasa detección y en la falta de atención psicológica específica a los pacientes que la precisan, así como las vías que clínicos e investigadores están desarrollando para solventarlas. Un conocimiento real de estos problemas facilitaría el diseño, implementación o mejora de los recursos asistenciales, para el paciente oncológico. Método: Revisión bibliográfica de las investigaciones sobre el tema en las últimas décadas. Resultados: Los pacientes con cáncer presentan elevada prevalencia de trastornos psicopatológicos y síntomas de ansiedad, depresión y malestar emocional (distress), en distintos momentos de la enfermedad, relacionados con diversos factores médicos, físicos, psicológicos y sociales. Los datos no permiten concluir sobre la prevalencia real puntual de dichos trastornos y síntomas, debido a las diferentes metodologías de investigación, y menos aun sobre su evolución durante la enfermedad, y en momentos posteriores a la misma, para conocer los posibles factores predictivos de empeoramiento  o protección. Diversas barreras dificultan una adecuada evaluación psicológica a los pacientes con cáncer, lo que conlleva una falta de atención específica y especializada cuando se precisa, un empeoramiento clínico de esos pacientes, y dificultades de adherencia a los tratamientos médicos. Las vías de solución favorecidas  en la última década son la formación a los profesionales sanitarios en herramientas de comunicación y el desarrollo de herramientas de detección de trastornos mentales y malestar emocional adecuadas a la realidad clínica de los pacientes, con resultados dispares.  Conclusiones: Es preciso seguir mejorando los sistemas de detección de problemas de salud mental y de malestar emocional en pacientes oncológicos, para darles la atención  psicológica específica cuando se precise. Un conocimiento real de estos problemas favorecerá el diseño de programas asistenciales especializados en psicooncología y psicología clínica. Es necesaria la coordinación y accesibilidad del psicólogo en los equipos médicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(2/3): 233-257, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110984</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Salud Mental y malestar emocional en pacientes con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
