<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142925</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pros and cons of prophylactic circumcision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The management of phimosis in children is still controversial. Objective. To review the literature regarding phimosis in order to determine whether prophylactic circumcision is indicated. Methods. Bibliographical research using informatic databases (TRIP, Cochrane, PUBMED). Results and conclusion. Our review of the literature indicates that, in order the establish the value of prophylactic circumcision, it would be necessary to evaluate the overall impact (morbidity and cost-effectivity studies) of circumcision in the incidence of urinary tract infections and its repercussion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fargas, Arnau</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñallonga, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El manejo de la fimosis pediátrica sigue siendo un tema a debate. Objectivo. Revisar la literatura sobre fimosis para determinar si la circuncisión preventiva es o no es necesaria. Método. Búsqueda bibliográfica a partir de bases de datos informáticas (TRIP, Cochrane, PUBMED). Resultados y Conclusión. La revisión de la literatura indica que es necesario conocer el impacto global (morbilidad + estudios coste-efectividad) de la circuncisión sobre las infecciones de orina y sus repercusiones, para poder establecer con seguridad la necesidad o no de circuncidar preventivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;64(3): 125-131, mayo-jun. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Circuncidar preventivamente o no. Pros y contras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2970^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10882^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10882^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52002^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
