<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159714</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adapting the GOLD/GesEPOC guidelines in patients with COPD within the scope of Neumosur</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The objective of our study is to learn the implementation of the GOLD and Ges EPOC guidelines among patients with COPD at Pneumology departments in the regions of Andalusia and Extremadura (Spain) to assess variability and possible determining factors. Method: EPOCONSUL is a study that audits the clinical histories of patients who have been diagnosed with COPD. An observational study in 62 centers in Spain is carried out. Data has been extracted from centers within the scope of NEUMOSUR (Pneumology Departments in Andalusia and Extremadura) for analysis. The degree to which the GOLD and GesEPOC guidelines are implemented were analyzed, as well as variability in the various degrees of the disease and clinical phenotypes. Results: The clinical histories of 926 patients were analyzed. 32.8% were classified according to GOLD guidelines. Of these patients, 36.2% were classified as grade A, 9.9% as grade B, 22.3% as grade C and 31.6% as grade D. 49.5% of the cases were classified following GesEPOC criteria. 44.5% were classified as non-acute phenotype, 14.9% as mixed phenotype COPD-asthma, 15.7% as acute phenotype with a predominance of emphysema and 24.9% as acute phenotype with a predominance of chronic bronchitis. Conclusions: Within the scope of NEUMOSUR medical practices, there is a majority use of GesEPOC guidelines over GOLD guidelines. The most frequent degrees are those of low risk and barely symptomatic (A) followed by high risk and very symptomatic (D). The phenotype seen most frequently at practices is the non-acute type (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcázar, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, FL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Gil, FL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domenech, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Campos, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnedillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, JD</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de nuestro estudio es conocer la implantación de las guías GOLD y GesEPOC en pacientes EPOC en las consultas de Neumología de Andalucía y Extremadura, para evaluar su variabilidad y los posibles factores determinantes. Métodos: EPOCONSUL es un estudio en el que se realiza una auditoría de historias clínicas de pacientes con diagnóstico de EPOC. Se hace un estudio observacional en 62 centros de España. Se han extraído los datos de los centros del ámbito de NEUMOSUR para su análisis. Se analiza el grado de implantación de las guías GOLD y GesEPOC, así como la variabilidad en los distintos grados de enfermedad y fenotipos clínicos. Resultados: Se ha analizado la historia clínica de 926 pacientes. El 32,8% estaban clasificados siguiendo la guía GOLD. De estos pacientes, el 36,2% estaban clasificados como grado A, 9,9% grado B, 22,3% grado C y el 31,6% como grado D. El 49,5% estaban clasificados siguiendo los criterios de GesEPOC. El 44,5% eran clasificados como fenotipo no agudizador, 14,9% fenotipo mixto EPOC-asma, 15,7% fenotipo agudizador con predomino de enfisema y 24,9% fenotipo agudizador con predominio de bronquitis crónica. Conclusiones: En las consultas de neumología del ámbito de NEUMOSUR hay un mayor uso de los criterios de la guía GesEPOC que de la guía GOLD. Los grados más frecuentes son los de bajo riesgo y poco sintomáticos (A) seguidos de los de alto riesgo y muy sintomáticos (D). El fenotipo que con mayor frecuencia se atiende en la consulta es el no agudizado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;28(5): 248-254, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de guías GOLD/gesEPOC en pacientes EPOC del ámbito Neumosur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52959^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
