<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112266</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enterocutaneous fistulas and Crohn's disease: clinical characteristics and response to treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the low prevalence of enterocutaneous fistulas (ECF) in patients with Crohn&#146;s disease (CD) justifies the scarcity of studies that analyze the effect of medical treatment and the need for surgery in these patients. The objective of this study was to evaluate the clinical characteristics of patients with CD who have ECF and the response to different treatments. Material and methods: patients with CD who presented ECF fistula between 1970 and 2009 in three tertiary centers in Spain were analyzed retrospectively for their clinical characteristics, response to treatment as well as the correlation between the response to biological therapies for ECF and perianal disease. The inflammatory activity of the disease was measured using the Harvey-Bradshaw index. The definitions of partial or complete response were based on the treating physician&#146;s judgment. Results: twenty six patients were included (18 women); in more than half of cases (67%), anti-TNF treatment improved fistula drainage. Postoperative fistulas responded better to anti-TNF treatment than did spontaneous fistulas (80 versus 57%). One hundred percent and 60% of spontaneous and postoperative fistulas closed after surgery, respectively. Conclusions: although the majority of patients required surgery as the ultimate treatment, anti-TNF drugs improved fistula output in an acceptable percentage of patients who were treated. Therefore, this may be a treatment strategy prior to surgery in a select group of patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Senent, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro-de Acosta, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la baja prevalencia de las fístulas enterocutáneas (FEC) en los pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn (EC) justifica la escasez de estudios que analicen el efecto del tratamiento médico y la necesidad de cirugía en estos pacientes. El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido evaluar las características clínicas de los pacientes con EC que presentan FEC y la repuesta a los distintos tratamientos. Material y métodos: se analizaron retrospectivamente los pacientes con EC que presentaron FEC desde 1970 a 2009 en tres centros terciarios de España analizando las características clínicas de los pacientes, las respuestas a los tratamientos así como la correlación entre la respuesta a terapias biológicas de la FEC y enfermedad perianal. La actividad inflamatoria de la enfermedad se midió mediante el índice de Harvey-Bradshaw. Las definiciones de respuesta parcial o completa se establecieron a juicio del médico responsable. Resultados: se incluyeron 26 pacientes (18 mujeres), en más de la mitad de los casos (67%) el tratamiento con anti-TNF mejoró el drenaje de la fístula. Las fístulas post-quirúrgicas respondieron mejor al tratamiento con anti-TNF que las fístulas espontáneas (80 vs. 57%). Se obtuvo un 100% y un 60% de cierre en fístulas espontáneas y post-quirúrgicas tras cirugía, respectivamente. Conclusiones: aunque la mayoría de los pacientes requirieron cirugía como tratamiento definitivo, los fármacos anti-TNF mejoraron el débito de la fístula en un porcentaje aceptable de los pacientes tratados, por lo que en un grupo seleccionado podría considerarse una estrategia de tratamiento previo a cirugía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(1): 3-6, ene. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístulas enterocutáneas en la enfermedad de Crohn: características clínicas y respuesta al tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28910^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31092^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
