<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161412</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paget's disease of bone: approach to its historical origins</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paget's disease of bone is the second most common bone disease after osteoporosis. It is characterized by focal regions of highly exaggerated bone remodeling, with abnormalities in all phases of the remodeling process. This study aims to investigate the hypothesis of a possible British origin of Paget's disease of bone by studying the worldwide geographic distribution of cases identified in ancient skeletons excavated from archaeological sites. The methodology consists in reviewing cases of Paget's disease of bone described in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menéadez-Bueyes, Luis R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Fernández, María del Carmer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad ósea de Paget es la segunda enfermedad ósea más común después de la osteoporosis. Se caracteriza por la aparición de regiones focales que presentan una remodelación ósea muy exagerada, con anormalidades en todas las fases del proceso. Este estudio tiene como objetivo investigar la hipótesis del posible origen británico de esta enfermedad estudiando su distribución geográfica mundial en esqueletos antiguos excavados en yacimientos arqueológicos. La metodología utilizada consiste en una revisión de la literatura que presenta diagnóstico de la enfermedad ósea de Paget (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);13(2): 66-72, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, mapa</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad ósea de Paget: aproximación a sus orígenes históricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10351^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10351^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
