<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165327</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Work accidents reported to a social security hospital in Piura-Perú, 2010-2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the social and occupational characteristics of the occupational injuries reported to a Social Security hospital in Piura. Methods: A cross-sectional analytical study of a database of occupational injuries reported to "José Cayetano Heredia" Hospital in Piura, Peru, between 2010 and 2012 was performed. Characteristics of workers including job position, type of injury and repercussion were examined. The variable &#145;immediate referral to a medical facility of the Social Security System&#146; was used as dependent variable, considering as category of interest whether the first destination after an occupational injury was any outpatient clinic or medical facility. The non-adjusted (RP) and adjusted prevalence rates (aPR) were calculated with generalized lineal models, using the binomial family and log link function. Results: a total of 2251 occupational injuries were notified, with 59% (1317) of workers that went home as first destination after being injured. Most accidents occurred between 10 am and 12 pm. In the multivariate analysis, the blue collar workers and the accidents did not go immediately to the medical facility after the event in 24% (IC95%: 19-33%) and 36% (IC95%: 12-35%), respectively. However, injuries that were caused by physical agents had a rate of 25% (IC95%: 1-55%) of immediate referral to an outpatient clinic. Conclusion: according to the analyzed data, a high frequency of not-immediate report of occupational injuries to the hospital was found. This has to be taken into account by the authorities to improve this situation, which goes against the law (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mejia, Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiñones-Laveriano, Dante M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bazán Ruiz, Susy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valadares-Garrido, Danae</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomero, Raul</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar factores asociados a la referencia inmediata a un hospital de la seguridad social luego de un accidente laboral. Métodos: Estudio transversal analítico de los datos de accidentes laborales atendidos en el Hospital III "José Cayetano Heredia" - Piura, entre los años 2010-2012. Se evaluó las características del trabajador, de su puesto de trabajo, del accidente y su repercusión. Se usó la variable referencia inmediata a la institución de salud como dependiente, considerando como categoría de interés si se acudió a un establecimiento de salud como primer lugar post accidente de trabajo. Se calcularon las razones de prevalencia crudas (RPc) y ajustadas (RPa) con los modelos lineales generalizados, usando la familia binomial y la función de enlace log. Resultados: Se notificaron 2251 accidentes de trabajo en los tres años, siendo el domicilio de los trabajadores el primer lugar a donde acudió el 59% (1317), entre las 10 am-12 m fue el período del día con más accidentes. En el análisis multivariado, los operarios y los accidentes que generaron heridas no acudieron inmediatamente al hospital post accidente en 24% (IC95%: 19-33%) y 36% (IC95%: 12-35%), respectivamente. En cambio, aquellos accidentes que fueron causados por agentes físicos tuvieron un 25% (IC95%: 1-55%) más referencia inmediata al hospital. Conclusión: Según los datos analizados, se encontró una elevada frecuencia de no reporte inmediato a la institución hospitalaria de accidentes laborales, esto debe ser tomado en cuenta por las autoridades responsables para mejorar la situación que va contra la ley (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;26(2): 92-99, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidentes laborales reportados a un hospital de la seguridad social en Piura-Perú, 2010-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7512^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13327^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
