<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105067</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Earlobe reconstruction with modified bilobed flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Earlobe absence may be due to congenital, oncologic or traumatic causes. This deformity sometimes constitutes an obvious facial deformity that warrants surgical correction. There are several techniques for reconstructing the earlobe, however, most of them require more than a on estage operation, may leave scars on the cheek or the pre auricular or postauricular regions and sometimes require complementary skin grafts. It is difficult to reconstruct the natural and three-dimensional structure of the earlobe. In our practice we use a new type of local flap, with transposition and rotation techniques, based in a bilobed shape flap design (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fidalgo Rodríguez, F. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ausencia de lóbulo auricular puede deberse a causas congénitas, oncológicas o traumáticas. Esta deformidad con frecuencia constituye una alteración estética facial que precisa de corrección quirúrgica. Se han descrito muchas técnicas para la reconstrucción del lóbulo auricular, sin embargo, algunas requieren varios tiempos quirúrgicos, dejan cicatrices en las regiones adyacentes o incluso pueden requerir injertos cutáneos complementarios. Además es complicado reconstruir la estructura tridimensional del lóbulo. En nuestra práctica, empleamos una nueva variante de colgajo bilobulado para este tipo de reconstrucción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;38(1): 41-47, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105067</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción del lóbulo auricular con colgajo bilobulado modificado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52522^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13249^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52522^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
