<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94066</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transitional care programs for patients with rheumatic diseases: review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transitional care programs are developed to facilitate the passage of a young patient with a chronic disease to an adult clinic where he needs to learn how to get involved in his own care. Various models have been proposed to address this transition in a multidisciplinary process. This review will address, in an updated format, various aspects of the transition units. With this objective in mind, we developed a narrative overview of the available information in the literature on transition units (TU) in rheumatic diseases. The most relevant information is presented in different stages: description and recommendations for the management of the adolescent patient, guidelines and information on programs at TU, and a description of aspects that should be part of a TU. Although several transition programs have been described, we do not have enough information to know what the ideal one would be like. More research is needed in this field, focusing on variables such as quality of life, satisfaction, activity and chronic damage(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castrejón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las unidades de transición se encargan de facilitar el cambio de un paciente joven con una patología crónica a una consulta de adultos. Se han propuesto diversos modelos de transición que abordan este proceso de una forma multidisciplinar. En esta revisión se abordarán de una manera actualizada los distintos aspectos de las unidades de transición. Con este objetivo se ha realizado una revisión narrativa de los artículos disponibles en la literatura médica sobre unidades de transición (UT) en patología reumática. La información más relevante se presenta en distintos puntos: descripción y recomendaciones en el manejo del paciente adolescente, información sobre guías y programas de UT, y una descripción de aspectos que deberían ser parte de una UT. Aunque hay descritos varios programas de transición, no disponemos de suficiente información para saber cuál es el programa ideal. Es necesaria más investigación en este campo, haciendo hincapié en variables como calidad de vida, grado de satisfacción, actividad y daño crónico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(1): 20-26, ene.-feb.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94066</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidades de transición para pacientes con patología reumática: revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33209</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33156</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
