<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89360</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Open Fetal Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Many congenital defects can now be detected before birth. Some of these malformations have predictable postnatal consequences and could be eligible for some form of prenatal treatment. Breaching the uterus by open surgery or even by fetoscopy can cause maternal morbidity and preterm labour but these approaches may be the only opportunities for prenatal treatment in some cases. The purpose of the present work was to review the current results and indications of open fetal surgery procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Encinas, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Muchas malformaciones fetales de consecuencias postnatales predecibles pueden ser diagnosticadas prenatalmente. El abordaje de la cavidad uterina se lleva a cabo, generalmente, mediante técnicas fetoscópicas; sin embargo, existe un grupo particular de malformaciones que solo pueden ser tratadas prenatalmente mediante cirugía fetal abierta. Nuestro objetivo en este estudio ha sido revisar las indicaciones y resultados actuales de estos procedimientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(4): 292-296, jul.-ago. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tratamiento prenatal de las malformaciones congénitas mediante cirugía fetal abierta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4702^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38806^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5432^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
