<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137072</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control strategies for difficult sedation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a wide intra- and inter-individual variability in sedative dose requirements in mechani- cally ICU patients. Patient&#146;s heterogeneity, the frequent and variable organic dysfunctions, the drug interactions and the possibility of metabolite accumulation could explain this variability. However, this fact must not justify the use of excessive doses to achieve the goals of sedation. Frequently, in the absence of a specific motive, e.g. uncontrolled pain, physicians administer progressive sedative dose increases. Probably, the absence of maximum dose recommendations has originated the case&#146;s description of severe complications, sometimes mortal, or sedative toxicity, like propofol infusion syndrome. This SEMICYUC Analgesia and Sedation Work Group recommends not administering more than 4.5 mg/kg/h of propofol or 0.25 mg/kg/h of midazolam. The need to use more than these doses should force a change in the sedative or the combined administration of both. Depending on the clinical situation or the clinical patient&#146;s evolution, the use of clonidine, haloperidol or remifentanil could be better options (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romera, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe una amplia variabilidad intra e inter-individual en los requerimientos de sedantes entre los pacientes críticos ventilados. Aspectos como la heterogeneidad de los pacientes, las frecuentes y variables alteraciones orgánicas, las interacciones entre los fármacos que reciben y los efectos sedantes de los metabolitos que se pueden acumular pueden justificar esta variabilidad. Sin embargo, esta situación no puede, ni debe, justificar el uso de dosis muy elevadas para conseguir los objetivos. Ante la agitación de los pacientes ventilados y en ausencia de una causa médica tratable (como el dolor no controlado), los clínicos responden con un incremento progresivo de la dosis de sedantes administrados. Probablemente la carencia de recomendaciones, en cuanto a la dosis máxima y el límite de los sedantes, ha conducido a la aparición de toxicidad, a veces mortal, con el uso de estos fármacos. Este grupo de trabajo recomienda no superar dosis de 4,5 mg/kg/h de propofol y 0,25 mg/kg/h de midazolam. Necesidades superiores a esta dosis máxima obligaría al cambio de sedante o a la coadministración de un segundo fármaco. Dependiendo de la situación clínica del paciente y del objetivo a corto plazo de la estrategia de sedoanalgesia, la combinación de los dos sedantes o el uso de clonidina, haloperidol o remifentanilo son las alternativas válidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(supl.1): 31-37, feb. 2008. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de control de la sedación difícil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12617^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12617^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12617^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12617^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
