<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115725</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Politics of Health Care of the Man in Brazil and the challenges of its implementation: an integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims to identify the challenges for the implementation of the National Policy for Integral Attention to human health. It is an integrative review consisted of searching the databases LILACS, SciELO and BDENF the period between 2000 and 2012. The results initially found 3,738 articles that presented the descriptors Men's Health, Gender and Health and Primary distributed in the databases mentioned. After observing the intersection of descriptors cited articles that present information in context that answer research question of this study were selected fifteen (15) items to be part of this integrative review. Therefore, examine what males look for in a healthcare facility, and from this analysis plan actions in order to meet the health demands that the male population, are measures that can be taken through restructuring in Basic Health Units and the work of professionals who serve the males (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Da Silva Nogueira, Patrick Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carfesan, Carolina Saiberth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maciel, Mauro Moreira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Silas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza, Jacqueline Ribeiro de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tiene como objetivo identificar los retos para la implementación de la Política Nacional de Atención Integral a la salud humana. Se trata de una revisión integradora que consistió en buscar las bases de datos LILACS, SciELO y BDENF en el período comprendido entre 2000 y 2012. De los resultados encontrados, inicialmente 3.738 artículos presentaban los descriptores Salud del hombre, Género y Salud y Atención Primaria distribuidos en las bases de datos mencionadas. Después de observar la intersección de los descriptores citados, los artículos que presentan la información en contexto que responda a la pregunta de investigación de este estudio se seleccionaron quince (15) artículos de formar parte de esta revisión integradora. Por lo tanto, examinar lo que los hombres buscan en un centro de salud, y a partir de este análisis plantear acciones con el fin de satisfacer las demandas de salud de la población masculina, son medidas que se pueden tomar a través de la reestructuración de las Unidades Básicas de Salud y del trabajo de los profesionales que atienden a los varones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 381-443, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Política de atención a la Salud del hombre en Brasil y los retos de su implantación: una revisión integrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
