<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121932</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary lymphoma of the cervix: pregnancy after conservative treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The cervix is a rare localization of lymphomas, with an incidence of 0.41- 0.6% of extranodal lymphomas. The initial symptom is usually vaginal bleeding. Diagnosis is made by biopsy. There is no standard treatment due to the low incidence of this tumor. Surgery causes irreversible loss of reproductive capacity. We report a case that illustrates the possibility of conservative treatment of primary cervical lymphoma with chemotherapy and radiotherapy in local disease if the patient wishes to preserve her reproductive ability. However, the techniques of ovocyte preservation or embryo or ovarian tissue transposition should be considered before treatment, due to its negative effects on fertility in young women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heras-Sedano, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos-González, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapico-Goñi, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Cuetos, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Blázquez, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle-Rubido, Cristina del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cérvix representa una rara localización de linfomas, con una incidencia del 0,41-0,6% de linfomas extranodales. El síntoma de inicio suele ser el sangrado vaginal, siendo diagnosticado en biopsia. No existe tratamiento estándar debido a su baja incidencia. La cirugía supone la pérdida irreversible de capacidad reproductiva. Este caso apoya la posibilidad de un manejo conservador de linfoma primario de cérvix con quimioterapia y RT si la enfermedad está localizada y se desea preservar el potencial genésico de la paciente. Sin embargo, las técnicas de criopreservación de ovocitos, embriones o transposición de tejido ovárico deberían ser planteadas previo al tratamiento, debido al mal pronóstico de este sobre la fertilidad en pacientes jóvenes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(5): 225-229, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma primario de cérvix: gestación tras tratamiento conservador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54698^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10048^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54698^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54698^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
