<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81618</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Granulocyte-Apheresis in ocular Behçets disease resistant to medical treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the feasibility of granulocyte apheresis (GCAP) in patients with Ocular Behçets Disease (BD) resistant to immunosuppressive therapy (prednisone, cyclosporin, azathyoprine or mycophenolate mofetil). Methods: Prospective observational study of five cases, carried out in a university centre. Four patients were resistant to medical treatment and one refused immunosuppressive drugs. The intervention procedure consisted of an extracorporeal GCAP using a column filled with cellulose acetate beads (Adacolumn, JIMRO, Takasaki, Japan). All patients received underwent a schedule of therapy of five sessions, once a week for five consecutive weeks. Visual acuity (Snellen lines), the degree of intraocular inflammation and doses of immunosuppressive therapy were measured and observed every week. Results: Visual acuity improved in the five cases. Intraocular inflammation was measured and observed in every case, relapses were avoided, and treatment with prednisone was reduced by more than half of the initial dose (average reduction 52.7%, SD 14). Conclusions: GCAP has been shown to be safe and effective as a new therapy in five cases of Ocular Behçets Disease refractory to medical treatment. Further research is needed in order to confirm the promising results of these initial investigations(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidaller Palacín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca Linares, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la viabilidad de la granulocitoaferesis (GCAP) en pacientes con enfermedad de Behçet (EB) ocular resistente al tratamiento con inmunosupresores (prednisona, ciclosporina, azatioprina o micofenolato mofetilo). Métodos: Estudio prospectivo de cinco pacientes, realizado en un hospital universitario de tercer nivel. Cuatro pacientes eran resistentes al tratamiento médico y uno rechazaba los fármacos inmunosupresores. El procedimiento consistió en realizar una GCAP extracorpórea mediante una columna rellena con gránulos de acetato de celulosa (Adacolumn®, JIMRO, Takasaki, Japón). Todos los pacientes fueron tratados con cinco sesiones, una semanal durante cinco semanas consecutivas. En cada sesión se controlaba la agudeza visual (AV) mediante las lineas de Snellen, el grado de inflamación intraocular y las dosis de tratamiento inmunosupresor. Resultados: La agudeza visual mejoró en los cinco casos. La inflamación intraocular se controló, no hubo recidivas y el tratamiento con prednisona se redujo en más de la mitad de la dosis inicial (reducción media de 52,7%, DE 14 ). Conclusiones: La GCAP ha demostrado ser un nuevo tratamiento seguro y eficaz en cinco casos de EB ocular resistente al tratamiento médico. Es preciso seguir investigando para confirmar los esperanzadores resultados de estos estudios iniciales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;79(7): 335-340, jul. 2004. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Granulocito-aferesis en Behçet ocular  refractario al tratamiento médico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
