<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126521</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal care in the opinion of residents of the village of Podkarpacie (Poland)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The last decade has brought significant changes in perinatal care in Poland with the changes proposed by the WHO. However, the introduction of any changes has been facing obstacles inherent in the attitudes of both women, as well as the routine approach of staff. Objective: To learn about the inhabitants of the village of perinatal care and the evaluation of selected aspects of quality of obstetric care. Methods: The sample consisted of 250 randomly selected residents of Podkarpacie region (Poland), aged 18-60 years of age, with at least one child. Original questionnaire was conducted by the study taking place in 2010. Results and Conclusions: Those women, whose births were less surgery, had the best evaluation of obstetric services. A significant aspect of obstetric care which is the comfort and security of labor in the hospital, thanks to the continuity of care provided by the same therapeutic team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ra&#156;, Renata</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kochmañska, Karolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasierb, Dominika</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorén Guerrero, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porada, Elzbieta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barna&#156;, Edyta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La última década ha traído modificaciones importantes en la atención perinatal en Polonia con los cambios propuestos por la OMS. Sin embargo, la introducción de cualquier cambio se enfrenta a obstáculos inherentes a las actitudes de las mujeres, así como la reticencia del personal. Objetivo principal: Conocer la opinión de las habitantes de las aldeas en cuanto a la atención perinatal se refiere y evaluar determinados aspectos de la calidad de la atención obstétrica. Metodología: La muestra fue de 250 residentes seleccionadas al azar de la región de Podkarpacie (Polonia), entre 18 y 60 a&amp;#241;os de edad que tenían al menos un hijo. Se realizó un cuestionario original llevándose a cabo el estudio en 2010. Resultados y conclusión principal: Aquellas mujeres cuyos nacimientos fueron menos intervenidos evaluaron mejor los servicios obstétricos. Un aspecto significativo fue la comodidad y seguridad, gracias a la continuidad de la atención prestada por el mismo equipo terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(1/2): 10-14, ene.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidado perinatal según la opinión de las mujeres procedentes de la región de Podkarpacie (Polonia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54693^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8595</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
