<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129078</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cementless acetabular component in coxarthrosis due to a acetabular fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the outcomes of cementless acetabular component for post-traumatic arthritis after acetabular fracture. Material and method. A prospective study of twenty-four patients with a mean age of 56years (range: 28-77) and a follow-up 8.4years (range: 5-15) treated with cementless total hip arthroplasty. The time from fracture to total hip arthroplasty was 3years (range: 5 months-14years). The fracture had been treated conservatively in 15 cases and with internal fixation in 9 cases. A clinical assessment was made using with Harris hip score, along with radiology with special interest in the socket. Results. Harris hip score increased from 35 points (range: 22-52) to 77 (range: 45-94). Unstable acetabular fixation was seen in 3 cases, 2 with osteolysis that required revision and 1 with a complete radiolucent line. The stem required revision in 1 case. There was 1 case of deep infection and 1 post-traumatic late dislocation. Survival for any cause at 12years was 78.4%. Discussion and conclusions. There are few studies on this topic, and all with a small number of cases. Acetabular failure rate is higher than routine total hip arthroplasty for non-traumatic osteoarthritis. Cementless total hip arthroplasty is a suitable treatment for post-traumatic arthritis after acetabular fracture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Reig, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizaur, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna-Berna, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valoración del componente acetabular no cementado en prótesis total de cadera por artrosis secundaria a fractura de cotilo. Material y método. Estudio prospectivo de 24 pacientes con edad media de 56 años (rango: 28-77) y seguimiento medio de 8,4 años (rango: 5-15), que fueron tratados con acetábulo no cementado atornillado. El tiempo medio entre la fractura y la prótesis fue de tres años (rango: 5 meses-14 años). La fractura había sido tratada conservadoramente en 15 casos y con fijación interna en 9 casos. Se realizó valoración clínica con la escala de Harris y radiográfica, con especial interés en el acetábulo. Resultados. La escala de Harris media se incrementó de 35 puntos (rango: 22-52) a 77 (rango: 45-94). Hubo tres aflojamientos de cotilo, dos con osteólisis que fueron revisados y uno con radiolucencia continua. El vástago femoral precisó revisión quirúrgica en un caso. Hubo un caso de infección profunda y una luxación tardía postraumática. La función de supervivencia de la artroplastia por cualquier causa a 12 años fue del 78,4%. Discusión y conclusiones. Son escasos los estudios al respecto y todos con pequeño número de casos. La tasa de fallos acetabulares es superior que la tasa en los casos no traumáticos. La prótesis no cementada es un tratamiento adecuado para las secuelas de fractura de cotilo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(3): 204-209, mayo-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Componente acetabular no cementado en coxartrosis por fractura de cotilo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
