<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82835</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial meningitis due to gram-negative bacilli in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Gram-negative bacilli are causative agents of bacterial meningitis in the neonatal period but rarely cause meningitis in adults without risk factors. Aim. To report on meningitis due to gram-negative bacilli (MGNB) in adults diagnosed in a hospital over a 25-year period. Patients and methods. We reviewed the medical records of all patients with an age &gt;= 14 years who had been diagnosed with MGNB between 1982 and 2006.  Results. Fifteen cases of MGNB are included (10.5% of the cases of bacterial meningitis with an identified aetiology), with a mean age of 48 years (14-79). Twelve (80%) were post-operative: recent neurosurgery (9 cases, 75%) and having a neurosurgical device (8 cases, 67%) were risk factors. Three (20%) were spontaneous: two were of a urinary origin and one had an undetermined origin. The aetiology was: Pseudomonas aeruginosa (3 cases), Escherichia coli (3 cases), Enterobacter aerogenes (2 cases), Pseudomonas fluorescens (1 case), Klebsiella pneumoniae (1 case), Morganella morganii (1 case), Acinetobacter anitratus (1 case), Acinetobacter iwoffii (1 case) and Flavobacterium brevis (1 case); in one patient with Gram positive staining for gram-negative bacilli, the culture was negative, and three of them (20%) were mixed infections (Staphylococcus spp.). Three patients (20%) died. Conclusions. In adults, gram-negative bacilli rarely cause spontaneous meningitis, but are a common causation of postneurosurgical meningitis and in those with neurosurgical devices. The mortality rate of MGNB is high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Laguna Del Estal, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Zubiri, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agud Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montero, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Cano Gómez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañeda Pastor, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los bacilos gramnegativos son agentes etiológicos de meningitis bacteriana en el período neonatal pero raramente causan meningitis en adultos sin factores de riesgo. Objetivo. Describir las meningitis por bacilos gramnegativos en adultos, diagnosticadas en un hospital durante un período de 25 años. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron las historias clínicas de los pacientes con edad &gt;= 14 años que habían sido diagnosticados de meningitis por bacilos gramnegativos entre 1982 y 2006.  Resultados. Se incluyen 15 casos de meningitis por bacilos gramnegativos (10,5% de las meningitis bacterianas de etiología  identificada), con una mediana de edad de 48 años (intervalo: 14-79 años). Doce (80%) fueron postoperatorias:neurocirugía reciente (9 casos, 75%) y ser portador de un dispositivo neuroquirúrgico (8 casos, 67%) fueron los factores  de riesgo. Tres (20%) fueron espontáneas: dos de origen urinario y una de origen no determinado. La etiología fue: Pseudomonas aeruginosa (3 casos), Escherichia coli (3 casos), Enterobacter aerogenes (2 casos), Pseudomonas fluorescens (1 caso), Klebsiella pneumoniae (1 caso), Morganella morganii (1 caso), Acinetobacter anitratus (1 caso), Acinetobacter iwoffii (1 caso) y Flavobacterium brevis (1 caso); en un enfermo con tinción de Gram positiva para bacilos gramnegativos el  cultivo resultó negativo, y tres (20%) fueron infecciones mixtas (Staphylococcus spp.). Tres pacientes (20%) fallecieron. Conclusiones. En adultos, los bacilos gramnegativos raramente causan meningitis espontánea, pero son una etiología frecuente de meningitis posneuroquirúrgicas y en portadores de dispositivos neuroquirúrgicos. La mortalidad de la meningitis por bacilos gramnegativos es elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(8): 458-462, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis bacteriana por bacilos gramnegativos en adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
