<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-31836</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic and therapeutic approach to cholestatic liver disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When cholestatic liver disease is present, liver ultrasound should be performed to ascertain if cholestasis is extrahepatic or intrahepatic. If bile ducts appear dilated and the probability of interventional treatment is high, endoscopic retrograde cholagio-pancreatography (ERCP) or trans-hepatic cholangiography (THC) should be the next step. If the probability of interventional therapeutics is low, cholangio-MRI should be performed. Once bile duct dilation and space occupying lesions are excluded, a work up for intrahepatic cholestasis should be started. Some specific clinical situations may be helpful in the diagnostic strategy. If cholestasis occurs in the elderly, drug-induced cholestatic disease should be suspected, whereas if it occurs in young people with risk factors, cholestatic viral hepatitis is the most likely diagnosis. During the first trimester of pregnancy cholestasis may occur in hyperemesis gravidorum, and in the third trimester of gestation cholestasis of pregnancy should be suspected. A familial history of recurrent cholestasis points to benign recurrent intrahepatic cholestasis. The occurrence of intrahepatic cholestasis in a middle-aged woman is a frequent presentation of primary biliary cirrhosis, whereas primary sclerosing cholangitis should be suspected in young males with inflammatory bowel disease. The presence of vascular spider nevi, ascites, and a history of alcohol abuse should point to alcoholic hepatitis. Neonatal cholestasis syndromes include CMV, toxoplasma and rubinfections or metabolic defects such as cystic fibrosis, alpha1-antitrypsin deficiency, bile acid synthesis defects, or biliary atresia. The treatment of cholestasis should include a management of complications such as pruritus, osteopenia and correction of fat soluble vitamin deficiencies. When hepatocellular failure or portal hypertension-related complications occur, liver transplantation should be considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ante la presencia de colestasis, se debe determinar si su naturaleza es extra o intrahepática. Si la ecografía hepática no muestra dilatación de la vía biliar ni lesiones' ocupantes de espacio, se debe iniciar el estudio de una colestasis intrahepática. Si la obstrucción de la vía biliar extrahepática es cuestionable o la probabilidad de intervencionismo terapéutico es baja, se debe completar el estudio mediante colangio-pancreatografia-RM (CPRM). Si la probabilidad de intervencionismo es alta, se debe realizar colangiopancreatografía retrógrada endoscópica (CPRE) o colangiografía transparieto-hepática (CTPH). En caso de colestasis intrahepática, determinadas situaciones específicas ayudan a orientar el diagnóstico. Si la colestasis intrahepática ocurre en ancianos, se debe sospechar colestasis por fármacos, mientras que en pacientes jóvenes con antecedentes de riesgo, la hepatitis viral es la causa más frecuente. En el primer trimestre del embarazo la hiperemesis gravídica es la causa más probable y en el segundo o tercero la colestasis gravídica. La historia familiar y el curso recurrente deben orientar hacia una colestasis intrahepática recurrente benigna. La presencia de colestasis intrahepática en una mujer de edad media debe hacer sospechar CBP, mientras que en un varón joven con EIIC, una colangitis esclerosante primaria. La presencia de arañas vasculares, ascitis e historia de abuso de alcohol, apuntan hacia una hepatitis alcohólica como causa más probable. En el periodo neonatal, los síndromes colestásicos incluyen infecciones por CMV, toxoplasma, rubeola o defectos metabólicos como la fibrosis quística, el déficit de alfa1-antitripsina, defectos en la síntesis de ácidos biliares o atresia biliar. El tratamiento de la colestasis debe incluir el manejo de complicaciones como el prurito, la osteopenia y el déficit de vitaminas liposolubles. En caso de insuficiencia hepatocelular o complicaciones de la hipertensión portal, el manejo es similar al de otras etiologías y se debe valorar el trasplante hepático (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;96(1): 60-73, ene. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje diagnóstico y terapéutico del síndrome colestásico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Cacho, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Serrano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rodríguez, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lledó, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santander, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, MªL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-31836</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1676</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
