<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131932</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-4007</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors for intimate partner violence in prison inmates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Etiological models of intimate partner violence (IPV) identify general risk factors in delinquency (sociodemographic, delinquent, and psychopathological) and specific factors in this type of aggression (characteristics of the couple relationship and attitudes favoring IPV). The goal of the present work is to study these factors in individuals convicted for drug trafficking and/or theft, so-called common delinquents (n = 89), comparing them with a group of partner aggressors (n = 50). Assessment was carried out with a mixed method, reviewing case files, clinical interviews for personality disorders, and self-reports. The results show a similar profile in sociodemographic and criminal characteristics and in attitudes favoring IPV. The differences emerge in variables of the couple relationship and psychopathological variables, finding higher prevalence of the antisocial disorder in common delinquents and of the borderline disorder in aggressors. The final model identifies the level of relationship satisfaction, control over the partner, blaming female victims, and incidence of borderline personality disorder as relevant variables. The implications of these results for penitentiary treatment as a preventive measure of IPV, both in IPV aggressors and in the general prison population, are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llor-Esteban, Bartolomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Jiménez, Jesús J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Hernández, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy-Fernández, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los modelos etiológicos de la violencia contra la pareja (VCP) identifican factores de riesgo generales en delincuencia (sociodemográficos, delictivos y psicopatológicos) y factores específicos en este tipo de agresión (características en la relación de pareja y actitudes que facilitan la VCP). El objetivo del presente trabajo es estudiar estos factores en sujetos condenados por tráfico de drogas y/o robo, denominados delincuentes comunes (n = 89), comparándolos con un grupo de agresores contra la pareja (n = 50). La evaluación se ha realizado a través de un método mixto, con supervisión de expedientes penitenciarios y entrevistas clínicas para los trastornos de personalidad y autoinformes. Los resultados muestran un perfil similar en características sociodemográficas, delictivas y en actitudes que favorecen la VCP. Las diferencias se dan en variables de relación de pareja y psicopatológicas, encontrando una mayor prevalencia del trastorno antisocial en los delincuentes comunes y del trastorno límite en los agresores. El modelo final identifica como variables relevantes el nivel de satisfacción en la relación, control sobre la pareja, culpabilización a las mujeres víctimas e incidencia del trastorno límite de personalidad. Se discuten las implicaciones de estos resultados en el tratamiento penitenciario, tanto de los agresores en VCP como de la población reclusa en general, como medidas preventivas de la VCP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. psychol. appl. legal context (Internet);7(1): 41-49, ene. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131932</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
