<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104973</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A new surgical strategy for multiple multiple bilobular liver metastases: right portal occlusion and torniquet in the parenchyma section line</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Right portal vein occlusion plus «in situ split» has recently been reported as a new method to hypertrophy the functional remnant volume (FRV) in 7 days after two-stage liver resection. It is a complex procedure associated with the occlusion of the intrahepatic collaterals between both lobes. We present an original technique for hypertrophying the FRV by occluding the right portal vein and the intrahepatic collaterals: a case is presented of a 35-year-old woman with an intestinal stromal tumour, 14 bilobar metastases and an estimated 24% FRV. Once the lesions were removed from the left lobe, we performed a right portal vein transection and applied a tourniquet on the Cantlie line, using the hanging manoeuvre. A 57% hypertrophy of the FRV was achieved by day 7, and the right hepatectomy was performed on day 8. Our technique is effective and simple to perform and if corroborated in future studies, this technique would be of choice in 2-stage liver resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín Hernández, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Conesa, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster Quiñonero, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Campos, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente, han publicado la oclusión portal derecha más split in situ como un nuevo método para hipertrofiar en 7 días el volumen residual (VR) tras las resecciones hepáticas en dos tiempos. Es una técnica compleja, fundamentada en ocluir las colaterales intrahepáticas entre ambos lóbulos. Presentamos una técnica original para hipertrofiar el VR ocluyendo la vena porta derecha y las colaterales intrahepáticas: mujer de 35 años con un tumor estromal intestinal y 14 metástasis bilobares, siendo el VR estimado del 24%. Una vez extirpadas las lesiones del lóbulo izquierdo, ocluimos la porta derecha y aplicamos un torniquete en la línea de Cantlie mediante maniobra de hanging. Al 7.° día hipertrofió el VR un 57% y al 8.° día se realizó una hepatectomía derecha. Nuestra técnica es eficaz y sencilla de realizar y, de corroborarse en futuros estudios, esta técnica sería de elección en las resecciones hepáticas en 2 tiempos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);90(3): 191-196, mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una nueva estrategia quirúrgica para metástasis hepáticas bilobares múltiples: oclusión portal derecha y torniquete en la línea de sección parenquimatosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6651^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
