<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037354</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of tendinitis and calcified subacromiodeltoid bursitis with shock waves</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the efficacy of treatment with shock waves in patients with tendinitis and calcified subacromiodeltoid bursitis refractory to convention rehabilitation-medical treatment. Patients and methods. From 1999 to 2003, a longitudinal descriptive study was performed on treatment with shock waves in 48 patients, 30 right and 18 left shoulders being affected. There were 17 men and 31 women whose mean age was 53.1 ± 12.53 years. Time from onset of the picture to treatment with shock waves was 37.85 ± 28.53 months. Acoustic waves of 0.04 mJ/mm2 of energy at 3-4 impulses/second were applied, beginning with 1500 impulses, which were increased according to the patient&#146;s tolerance in each session, to 2000 impulses. The number of sessions was 4.77 ± 1.31. Pain was assessed with the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), functional recovery with the performance of articular balance and variation of calcification size by ultrasonographic measure. A descriptive statistical study was performed and the results were accepted for p &lt; 0.05. Results. Previous pain improved in 91.48 % of the patients in our sample in the middle term and 93.75 % in the long term. There was improvement in function in 93.3 % of the patients, with alterations in previous mobility and in the ultrasonographic image in 91.17 % of patients with changes in calcification size. Step-wise, improvement of the pain stands out with complete remission in 8.5 % in the middle term and 18.78 % in the long term. There were significant improvements in 40.4 % in the middle term and 59.3 % in the long term, with considerable improvements in 19.1 % in the middle term and 9.37 % in the long term. There were mild improvements in 23.5 % in the middle term and 6.25 % in the long term and no improvement in 8.5 % in the middle and 6.25 % in the long term. Function evolved as follows: 45.5 % recovered complete long term mobility, 18.2 % obtained partial mobility recovery in the long term that practically did not interfere with their daily life activities; 4.5 % obtained no improvement in the long term. A total of 31.8 % of the persons without mobility limitation before treatment continued without it. Regarding the ultrasonographic evolution of the calcifications, changes were observed in their size in 31 patients (91.17 %), it disappearing in 10 (29.41 %). Conclusion. Extracorporeal shock wave treatment must be considered before surgical treatment in patients with tendinitis and calcified subacromiodeltoid bursitis refractory to conventional rehabilitation-medical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Arrebola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rodríguez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la eficacia del tratamiento con ondas de choque en pacientes con tendinitis y bursitis calcificadas subacromiodelto ideas refractarias al tratamiento médico rehabilitador convencional. Pacientes y método. Desde 1999 hasta 2003 se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo longitudinal del tratamiento con ondas de choque de 48 pacientes; en 30 el hombro afectado era el derecho y en 18, el izquierdo. Corresponden a 17 varones y 31 mujeres con una edad media de 53,1 ± 12,53 años. El tiempo transcurrido desde el comienzo del cuadro hasta el tratamiento con ondas de choque fue de 37,85 ± 28,53 meses. Se emplearon ondas acústicas de 0,04 mJ/mm2 de energía a 3-4 impulsos/s, comenzando con 1.500 impulsos, que se fueron incrementando, según la tolerancia del paciente en cada sesión, hasta 2.000 impulsos. El número de sesiones fue de 4,77 ± 1,31. Se evaluó el dolor con la Escala Analógica Visual(EAV), la recuperación funcional con la realización de un balance articular, y la variación del tamaño de las calcificaciones mediante medición ecográfica. Se realizó un estudio estadístico descriptivo y los resultados se aceptaron para p &lt; 0,05. Resultados. Mejoraron su dolor previo el 91,48 % de los pacientes de nuestra muestra a medio plazo y el 93,75 % a largo plazo, la función en el 93,3 % de los pacientes con alteraciones de la movilidad previa, la imagen ecográfica en el 91,17 % de pacientes, con cambios en el tamaño de las calcificaciones. Escalonadamente la mejoría del dolor destaca: remisión completa en el 8,5 % a medio plazo y en el 18,78 % a largo plazo; grandes mejorías en el 40,4 % a medio plazo y en el 59,38 % a largo plazo; apreciables mejorías tuvimos en el 19,1 % a medio plazo y un 9,37 % a largo plazo; discretas mejorías en el 23,5 % a medio plazo y en el 6,25 % a largo plazo; sin mejoría en el 8,5 % a medio y en el 6,25 % a largo plazo. La función evolucionó de la siguiente manera: el 45,5 % recuperó la movilidad completa a largo plazo; el 18,2 % obtuvo una recuperación parcial de la movilidad a largo plazo sin prácticamente interferir en sus actividades de la vida diaria; el 4,5 % no obtuvo mejoría a largo plazo. El 31,8 % de las personas sin limitación de la movilidad antes del tratamiento, continuó sin ella. En lo referente a la evolución ecográfica de las calcificaciones se objetivaron cambios en el tamaño de las mismas en 31 pacientes (91,17 %) y desaparecieron en 10 (29,41 %). Conclusión. Hay que considerar el tratamiento con ondas de choque extracorpóreas antes del tratamiento quirúrgico, en los pacientes con tendinitis y bursitis calcificadas subacromio deltoideas refractarias al tratamiento médico rehabilitador convencional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(1): 2-7, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de tendinitis y bursitis calcificadas subacromiodeltoideas con ondas de choque</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
