<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041973</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Instrumented insoles: clinical utility</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study is to provide information of how plantar pressure measurement through instrumented insoles can be recommended in clinical practice. Methods. A literature search was conducted to retrieve clinical trials investigating types of plantar pressure measurements; instrumented insoles as an in shoe data collection method; system specifications that instrumented insoles should have; advantages and disadvantages of this measurement system; common variables of interest, mainly peak pressure; foot topographic areas and the relationship between biomechanics and clinics features ; plantar pressures reflecting plantar support during gait. Personal experience is included. Results. Studies demonstrated a significant clinical application of plantar pressure assessment; we describe the results of a clinical case and those in a control case. Conclusions. Instrumented insoles are quantitative data tools for functional assessment during gait and therefore are recommended in clinical practice. They are useful assessing plantar pain, lower limb orthotic prescriptions and his effectiveness. Support exits for the interest of the instrumented insoles in the functional evaluation and evolutive control of musculoskeletal and neurologic diseases and plantar surface ulceration prevention in neuropathies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peydro de Moya, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ruiz, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Assucena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pradas Silvestre, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Aportar información sobre la utilidad de las plantillas instrumentadas en la práctica clínica. La estrategia de trabajo ha consistido en la descripción de: Tipos de sistemas de valoración de presiones plantares conocidos; sistema de plantillas instrumentadas; características que debería tener el sistema de plantillas instrumentadas; ventajas e inconvenientes de este tipo de instrumentación funcional; qué parámetros son de interés, comunicando que el de mayor utilización clínica es el de presiones máximas; áreas topográficas consideradas de mayor interés biomecánico, en cuanto a correlacionarlo con la exploración clínica; presiones plantares como reflejo de la forma de apoyo plantígrado, durante la marcha; para ello, se ha revisado la bibliografía circulante sobre sistemas de plantillas instrumentadas y sobre patología y cuadros sindrómicos que afecten a la forma de apoyar durante la marcha. Se ha incluido información personal empírica. Resultados. Aplicabilidad de las plantillas instrumentadas en la práctica clínica; descripción de un caso clínico, previa identificación de un caso control. Conclusiones. Las plantillas instrumentadas aportan datos cuantitativos de utilidad clínica en la valoración funcional de la marcha, el dolor plantar, la prescripción y la validación ortésica de los miembros inferiores, tanto en patología de aparato locomotor (traumática o no) como neurológica, la prevención de úlceras en neuropatías, relevante en la diabética, por impacto de lesiones, y control evolutivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(6): 324-330, nov.-dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plantillas instrumentadas. Utilidad clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23249^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23249^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5823^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
