<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124764</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teledermatology and Ocupational Health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The importance and impact of telemedicine has caused to be applied to all possible areas and the types of telemedicine have grown in parallel to the development of new technologies. The dermatology was one of the first specialties to adopt the telemedicine. The skin diseases pose a very important issue within the occupational pathology. So applying the teledermatology at workplace level could help to perform better and earlier diagnosis, at the same time that could have a significant impact on economic cost savings. Objective: Knowing the current state of the evidence in Teledermatology and its potential translation to the field of Occupational Medicine, and to identify existing knowledge and evidence on the following critical issues that set the potential interest of this translation: Diagnostic Accuracy; Cost-benefit and cost-effectiveness; Acceptability and patient satisfaction; Professional satisfaction; Reduction of time for diagnosis. Material and Methods: A literature review of the scientific literature published between 2006-2013 was performed. The MEDLINE, OSH UPDATE, IBSST, CISDOC, LILACS, WOK, ClinicalKey, SciELO, SCOPUS, OVIDSP, IBECS and Cochrane Library were searched. Results: 13 items including 2 systematic reviews, 6 clinical trials, and 5 cross-sectional studies were selected. The results show that Teledermatology has a diagnostic accuracy comparable to conventional query, this being between 5% -11% more accurate. Results also show that Teledermatology is cost-effective (1.78 times cheaper) when you consider displacement and loss of productivity, and decreasing average waiting time for consultancy. Conclusions: There are few references on Teledermatology applied to the workplace. Given the evidence collected on diagnostic accuracy, cost-effectiveness, acceptability, satisfaction, and reduced waiting times, this could be a useful tool for the Occupational Health because it would allow access to a specialized service providing early diagnosis and treatment, promoting the adoption of preventive measures, improving monitoring, and avoiding prolonged absences from work, due to consultation times or to prolonged labor incapacity while the occupational disease is examined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Gutiérrez, Olga de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meier de Taboada, Christian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rollón González, M. Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La importancia y el impacto de la telemedicina han provocado que se aplique a todas las áreas posibles del conocimiento médico y que los tipos de telemedicina hayan crecido de forma paralela al desarrollo de las nuevas tecnologías. La dermatología fue una de las primeras especialidades en la que se aplicaron tecnologías de telemedicina. Las enfermedades de la piel suponen la segunda causa de notificación de enfermedad profesional por lo que aplicar la teledermatología a nivel del ámbito laboral podría ayudar a llevar a cabo un mejor y precoz diagnóstico, al mismo tiempo que podría tener un significativo impacto en ahorro de costes económicos. Objetivo: Conocer el estado actual de la evidencia en Teledermatología y su potencial traslación al campo de la Medicina del Trabajo, así como identificar el conocimiento y evidencia existentes en los siguientes aspectos críticos que marcan el interés de esta potencial traslación: exactitud diagnóstica, coste-beneficio y coste-efectividad, aceptabilidad y satisfacción del paciente, satisfacción del profesional y reducción del tiempo para realizar el diagnóstico. Material y Métodos: Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica de la literatura científica publicada entre 2006-2013. Se consultaron las bases de datos MEDLINE, OSH UPDATE, IBSST, CISDOC, LILACS,WOK, Clinicalkey, Scielo, SCOPUS,OVIDSP, Biblioteca Cochrane e IBECS. Resultados: Se seleccionaron 13 artículos que incluyen 2 revisiones sistemáticas, 6 ensayos clínicos y 5 estudios transversales. La Teledermatología presenta una exactitud diagnóstica comparable a la consulta convencional, siendo ésta entre un 5%-11% más exacta, mostrándose coste-efectiva (1,78 veces más barata) si tenemos en cuenta desplazamientos y pérdida de productividad, con disminución en el tiempo de espera. Conclusiones: Existen pocas referencias sobre teledermatologia aplicada al ámbito laboral. Teniendo en cuenta la evidencia recogida sobre exactitud diagnóstica, coste-beneficio, aceptabilidad, satisfacción y reducción de tiempos de espera; ésta podría ser una herramienta útil para el Médico del Trabajo que permitiría el acceso a un servicio especializado facilitando un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz, promoviendo la adopción de medidas preventivas, mejorando el seguimiento y evitando ausencias prolongadas del puesto de trabajo, bien por tiempos de consulta o por incapacidad laboral por estudio de enfermedad profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(234): 161-178, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Telemedicina y su aplicación en Dermatología Laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32630^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
