<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116357</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the MF59-adjuvanted pandemic influenza A/H1N1 vaccine. Systematic review of literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of MF59-adjuvanted pandemic influenza A/H1N1vaccine in children. Methods: A systematic review of the literature was performed after searching the MedLine and Embase electronic databases, and manual search in specialties journals, with MeSH terms and free terms. Inclusion criteria were clinical trials with children vaccinated with MF59-adjuvanted influenza A/H1N1 vaccine, compared with other vaccines doses with/without MF59-adjuvanted. The immunogenicity and safety of the vaccine was recorded. The quality of the studies included was assessed by CASPe checklist. Results: Four clinical trials with moderate quality were selected. The local and systemic adverse effects were rare and mild, with no differences between groups. Seroconversion and seroprotection levels were higher with MF59-adjuvanted vaccines. Antibody titres were also higher with the adjuvant vaccines. Conclusions: The adjuvant vaccine has a good efficacy and safety profile. The adverse effects that may occur are common and appear similarly in both vaccination groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Linde, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Aragón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Peláez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yang, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande Tejada, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y la seguridad de la vacuna adyuvada MF59 en la gripe pandémica en población infantil. Métodos: Se ha elaborado una revisión sistemática de la literatura médica (2005-2012). Para ello se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica en fuentes de datos electrónicas como MedLine o Embase y búsqueda manual en revistas especializadas, utilizando descriptores MeSH y términos de búsqueda libre. Los criterios de inclusión fueron ensayos clínicos que incluyeran a niños vacunados frente a la gripe A/H1N1 con la vacuna adyuvada MF59 y se comparaba frente a otras dosis vacunales con o sin adyuvante MF59, registrando resultados de seguridad e inmunogenicidad. La calidad de los ensayos clínicos se evaluó utilizando los criterios del cuestionario CASPe. Resultados: Se seleccionaron 4 ensayos clínicos de calidad moderada. Los efectos adversos locales y sistémicos fueron de carácter leve o moderado, sin diferencias entre los grupos vacunados. Los porcentajes de seroconversión y seroprotección alcanzados fueron superiores con las vacunas que utilizaron el adyuvante MF59. Los títulos de anticuerpos alcanzados también fueron mayores en las vacunas adyuvadas. Conclusiones: La vacuna pandémica antigripal adyuvada con MF59 presenta un buen perfil de eficacia y seguridad. Los efectos adversos que puede ocasionar son comunes y se presentan de manera similar a los que acontecen al utilizar vacunas no adyuvadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(4): 208-217, oct. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116357</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la vacuna pandémica antigripal A/H1N1 adyuvada MF59. Revisión sistemática de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
