<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92278</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personal profile of teenagers with ideación pathological suicide</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Suicidal ideación is a variable that might determine clinical and pathological levels, in reference alos thoughts and deeper desires of the teenager on his own death. The aim of this investigation was to analyze possible existing correlations between the suicidal ideación and the personal profile in a sample of teenagers of the Community of Navarre. They informed a total of 1194 teenagers with ages between 14 and 18 years. The following instruments of measure were in use: The Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire (SIQ): Professional Manual of W. M. Reynolds and Million Adolescent Clynical Inventory (MACI) of T. Million. The results show the most significant personal features of the teenagers with ideación pathological suicide, from 65 opposing cases that present significant indexes of ideación suicide. This finding allows us to determine clinical pathological levels and to plan a possible personal profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Cabodevilla, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís Cordellat, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ideación suicida es una variable que puede determinar niveles clínicos patológicos, en referencia alos pensamientos y deseos más profundos del adolescente sobre su propia muerte. el objetivo de esta investigación fue analizar la posibles correlaciones existentes entre la ideación suicida y el perfil personal en una muestra de adolescentes de la Comunidad de Navarra. Participaron un total de 1194 adolescentes con edades entre 14 y 18 años. Se utilizaron los siguientes instrumentos de medida: el Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire (SIQ): Professional Manual de W. M. Reynolds y el Millon Adolescent Clynical Inventory (MACI) de T. Millon. Los resultados muestran los rasgos personales más significativos de los adolescentes con ideación suicida patológica, a partir de los 65 casos encontrados que presentan índices significativos de ideación suicida. Este hallazgo nos permite determinar niveles clínicos patológicos y trazar un posible perfil personal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;28(3): 443-455, sept.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92278</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil personal de adolescentes con ideación suicida patológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
