<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98637</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The efficiency of drug prescription: impact of a therapeutic exchange program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To assess the impact of substituting proton pump inhibitors (PPI) for omeprazole. Method We performed a community trial of the impact of a therapeutic exchange program in the primary care teams of a region compared with non-implementation in a control region. The study included patients prescribed a PPI between May 2008 and June 2009. The intervention consisted of providing educational sessions to physicians (n=68), as well as a list of patients receiving a PPI who were suitable for therapeutic exchange. Information was gathered from medical records (PPI prescribed, primary care team) and the pharmacy database (cost of defined daily doses of the PPI). The percentage of therapeutic exchange in each region before and after the intervention was compared through relative risk (RR). The percentage of omeprazole at the end of each study period and changes in PPI costs were also calculated. Results Therapeutic exchange was higher in the intervention group (RR: 4.2; 95%CI: 3.1-5.8) than in the control group (RR: 1.8; 95%CI: 1.2-2.6). The percentage of patients prescribed omeprazole increased from 86.2% to 89.3% in the intervention region and from 84.3% to 84.7% in the control region. The total cost of the PPI group decreased by 7.6% in the intervention region and increased by 2.0% in the control group. Conclusions This study demonstrates the effectiveness of the therapeutic exchange program. This is a simple intervention that is able to modify prescription and reduce its costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Allepuz, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benages, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosich, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arranz, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba, Glòria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar el impacto de un programa de intercambio terapéutico a omeprazol de los inhibidores de la bomba de protones (IBP).Método Ensayo comunitario que compara el impacto de un programa de intercambio terapéutico en los equipos de atención primaria de una comarca respecto a la no aplicación en una comarca control. Se incluyó a los pacientes con prescripción de un IBP entre mayo de 2008 y junio de 2009. La intervención consistió en sesiones educativas y facilitar a cada médico (n=68) los pacientes con un IBP que pudiera cambiarse a omeprazol. Se obtuvo información de la historia clínica (IBP prescrito, equipo de atención primaria) y de la aplicación de farmacia (coste de la dosis diaria definida de los IBP). A partir del riesgo relativo (RR) se comparó el porcentaje de intercambio terapéutico en cada comarca antes y después de la intervención. También se calculó el porcentaje de omeprazol al final de cada periodo de estudio y los cambios en los costes en IBP. Resultados Hubo más intercambios terapéuticos en el grupo de intervención (RR: 4,2; intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]:3,1-5,8) respecto al control (RR: 1,8; IC95%:1,2-2,6). En el grupo de intervención, el porcentaje de pacientes con omeprazol pasó del 86,2% al 89,3%, y en el control del 84,3% al 84,7%. El coste del grupo IBP disminuyó un 7,6% en el grupo de intervención y aumentó un 2,0% en el control. Conclusiones El programa de intercambio terapéutico se ha mostrado efectivo. Se trata de una intervención sencilla, capaz de modificar las prescripciones y reducir sus costes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(1): 58-64, ene. -feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficiencia en la prescripción de medicamentos: impacto de un programa de intercambio terapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51464</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
