<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149061</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acantholytic squamous cell carcinoma arising in actinic keratoacanthoma: Two cases with E-cadherin expression supporting a potentially different prognosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Among crateriform squamous proliferation, keratoacanthoma is considered as a squamous cell carcinoma or as a non-malignant, self-healing lesion that frequently becomes malignant. To date, published cases of neoplasms originating from keratoacanthoma are always conventional squamous cell carcinomas. Acantholytic squamous cell carcinoma arising in keratoacanthomas has not been previously reported. We present two crater-shaped nodular lesions on the face of elderly patients with clinical and histopathological features of keratoacanthoma with transformation areas to acantholytic squamous cell carcinoma. In the immunohistochemical study, Ki-67 and p63 immunostaining supports the diagnosis of acantholytic squamous cell carcinoma ex-keratoacanthoma. We suggest that E-cadherin expression and vimentin negativity could probably be related with less aggressive behaviour and a better prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Rabasco, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Estrada, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater Marco, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martorell Cebollada, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de las proliferaciones escamosas crateriformes, el queratoacantoma se considera como un carcinoma escamoso o como una lesión benigna autocurativa que frecuentemente se vuelve maligna. Las neoplasias descritas que se originan del queratoacantoma son siempre carcinomas escamosos convencionales. Carcinomas escamosos acantolíticos originados en queratoacantomas no se han descrito en la literatura. Presentamos 2 nódulos crateriformes en la cara de ancianos con características clínicas e histopatológicas de queratoacantoma con áreas de transformación a carcinoma escamoso acantolítico. En el estudio inmunohistoquímico, la expresión de Ki-67 y p63 apoya el diagnóstico de carcinoma escamoso acantolítico ex-queratoacantoma. Nosotros hipotetizamos que la expresión de E-cadherina y la negatividad de vimentina están probablemente relacionadas con menor agresividad y excelente pronóstico en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(1): 23-26, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de células escamosas acantolítico originado en queratoacantoma actínico: dos casos con expresión de E-cadherina indicando un pronóstico diferente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7805^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24548^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7805^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24548</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
