<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050843</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nephrolitiasis in a patient with cystic fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic fibrosis (CF) is caused by mutations in the CF transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) gene. Defects in the CFTR gene cause abnormal chloride conductance across the apical membrane of epithelial cells, which results in progressive lung disease and also affects other organs. Because life expectancy has increased, other complications of CF have become more apparent. We present a patient with CF and symptomatic nephrolithiasis. Several stones were evident in both kidneys. A 24-hour urine sample showed hyperoxaluria (141 mg/24 h/ 1.73 m 2) and hypocitraturia and (206 mg/24 h/1.73 m 2, 177 mg citrate/g creatinine). Nephrolithiasis should be included in the differential diagnosis of patients with CF and abdominal pain; urinary excretion of oxalate and citrate should be investigated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Cordero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orive Olondriz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elorz Lambarri, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrosis quística está causada por mutaciones en el gen regulador de la conductividad transmembrana (CFTR). Defectos en el gen CFTR ocasionan una conductividad alterada del cloro a través de la membrana apical de las células epiteliales, dando lugar a una enfermedad pulmonar progresiva y afectando también a diferentes órganos. Con el aumento de las expectativas de vida otras complicaciones de la fibrosis quística se han hecho más frecuentes. Presentamos una paciente con fibrosis quística y nefrolitiasis sintomática. Varios cálculos eran visibles en ambos riñones. En la muestra de orina de 24 h se evidenció hiperoxaluria (141 mg/24 h/1,73 m 2) e hipocitraturia (206 mg/ 24 h/1,73 m 2, 177 mg citrato/g creatinina). La nefrolitiasis debería estar presente en el diagnóstico diferencial de un paciente con fibrosis quística que tiene dolor abdominal y la excreción de oxalato y citrato debería ser investigada</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);65(2): 154-157, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefrolitiasis en un paciente con fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24256^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
