<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91748</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preterm infants: a close look at cognitive and behavioral outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Forty-seven prematurely born children and a control group of 25 full-term infants were evaluated at 6 months, 18 months (corrected ages), and at 46 months (non-corrected age). At each observation point, a developmental quotient (DQ) was computed and mothers were interviewed regarding their children´s behavioral problems. At the second observation point, mothers also completed a questionnaire on post traumatic symptoms following birth. However, when the DQ was corrected for expected term at the third observation point and socio-economic status was introduced as a covariate in the analysis, there was no longer any difference between the two groups. These findings suggest that control group studies comparing the outcomes of prematurely born children with those of children born full term should investigate such confounding factors more closely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muller Nix, Carole</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pierrehumbert, Blaise</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forcada Guex, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ansermet, Francoix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borghini, Avala</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un total de 47 niños prematuros y un grupo control de 25 bebés nacidos a término fueron evaluados a los 6 y 18 meses (edad corregida) y a los 46 meses (edad no corregida9. Se computó un cociente de desarrollo (CD) para cada momento de observación y las madres fueron entrevistadas sobre los problemas conductuales de sus hijos, además de rellenar un cuestionario sobre síntomas postraumáticos después del nacimiento. La diferencia entre ambos grupos desapareció al corregirse el CD en el tercer momento de observación, según la fecha de nacimiento esperada e introducirse el nivel socioeconómico como covariable. Estos hallazgos ponen de manifiesto que tales factores de confusión deberían de ser objeto de mayor atención al comparar los resultados de los nenes prematuros con los nenes nacidos a término (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(15): 9-22, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niños nacidos prematuramente: una mirada atenta a los resultados cognitivos y conductuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
