<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157277</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determination of the glycemic index and glycemic load of fermented dairy products in sedentary healthy adults and athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Glycemic Index (GI) and glycemic load (GL) of natural dairy products fermented with lactobacilli may be useful for diabetic patients and the general population. Objective: To measure the GI and GL in natural dairy products fermented with lactobacilli in sedentary individuals and athletes, and seeing if there is any difference between them. Methods: The study was conducted in Mexico City (DF) according to the ISO26642:210, with a group of 10 sedentary individuals and 10 athletes. The GI was determined in the following diary drinkable products, all adjusted to contain 25 g of carbohydrates: Soful, Yakult, Gastroprotect, BeneGastro, Bonacult, Lala Bio 4 and Skimmed milk with sucrose (SMS). Results: The GI of most dairy fermented products were low for sedentary and athletes, but in athletes Yakult and Bonacult showed the highest GI and Yakult&#146;s GI can be considered as medium for these group; these two dairy products had the lowest protein/carbohydrates ratio. SMS, which contain unfermented carbohydrates, had the highest GI in both groups. The GL of dairy fermented products was 4 to 7.6 and only Gastroprotect had statistically the lowest GL, it may be due to its low GI, even its serving size was not the least among dairy fermented products. Conclusion: The GI and GL levels were relatively low for all the dairy products considered on each of the groups studied, therefore the moderate consumption of these can be recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cervantes Covarrubias, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Jiménez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Guerrero, Josefina Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Chávez, Alejandra N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Zepeda, Rodrigo Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oropeza Hernández, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosas Romero, Reina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el índice glucémico (IG) y la carga glucémica (CG) de productos lácteos fermentados (PLF) con lactobacilos puede ser una recomendación útil para pacientes diabéticos y para la población en general. Objetivo: el objetivo del estudio fue medir el IG y la CG de PLF con lactobacilos en sujetos sedentarios y deportistas, y evaluar si existe diferencia entre ellos. Métodos: el estudio se realizó en México (DF) de acuerdo con la ISO26642:210 (Organización Internacional de Normalización). Los participantes fueron: 10 sedentarios y 10 deportistas. Los PLF analizados fueron: Soful, Yakult, Gastroprotect, BeneGastro, Bonacult, Lala Bio 4 y leche descremada con sacarosa (LDS) y la cantidad de alimento que ingirieron dependió de ajustar a 25 g los HC en la porción. Resultados: el IG de la mayoría de los PLF fue bajo para ambos grupos de sujetos; en los deportistas los PLF Yakult y Bonacult presentaron los mayores IG y solo el Yakult puede considerarse como de IG medio para este grupo; estos dos PLF presentaron la menor relación de proteína/HC. La LDS, lácteo con los HC no fermentados, presentó un IG alto para ambos grupos. La CG de los PLF se encontró entre 4 a 7,6 y solo Gastroprotect presentó estadísticamente la menor CG, lo que pudo deberse a su bajo IG, aun cuando su tamaño de ración no fue la menor, entre los PLF. Conclusión: en general los valores de IG y CG de los PLF fueron bajos para ambos grupos. Por tanto, su consumo puede recomendarse en forma moderada. El IG y CG entre productos lácteos con azúcares fermentados y con azúcares no fermentados fueron diferentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(5): 1095-1101, sept.-oct. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación del índice glucémico y la carga glucémica de productos lácteos fermentados en sujetos adultos sanos, sedentarios y deportistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56127^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38402^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
