<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63609</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To describe the findings obtained with magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in patients with ano-rectal atresia, after treatment by posterior sagittal anorectoplasty (PSARP), who have fecal incontinence and to describe its usefulness in the evaluation of causes of incontinence. Subject and methods: Twelve patients, 9 men and 3 women, with anorectal atresia were examined with 0.5T MRI after performing PSARP for imperforate anus. The study included T1-weighted, T2-weighted and proton-density, axial, sagittal and coronal planes. The location of descended neorectus and the degree of development of pelvic musculature were evaluated. Results: Normal development of anus levator muscles and sphincterian complex were observed in six patients, with correct situation of neorectus between anus levator muscles and sphincterian complex in five of them and eccentric in the other one. Diverse grades of striate muscular complex underdevelopment were showed in the other six cases, moderate grade in four of them and severe hypoplasia in the other two. Spinal and urogenital congenital anomalies were found in these patients. Sagittal and coronal T1-weighted MR images were the most useful planes in evaluating the relationship between anus levator muscles and sphincterian complex and axial T1-weighted MR images in the evaluation of the level of development of striated muscle complex in the evaluation of patients. Conclusions: MRI is useful in the evaluation of patients with fecal incontinence after performing PSARP for anorectal atresia. Unsuitable neorectus position or striated musce complex hypoplasia are causes of postoperative incontinence in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sarría Octavio de Toledo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros Mendoza, L. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Mombila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los hallazgos obtenidos mediante resonancia magnética (RM) en pacientes con incontinencia fecal previamente intervenidos de anorrectoplastia sagital posterior (ARPSP) por atresia de ano y definir su utilidad en la valoración de su causa. Material y métodos: Se examinaron con RM 0,5T a 12 pacientes, 9 varones y 3 mujeres, a los que previamente se les realizó ARPSP por atresia de ano. El estudio incluía secuencias potenciadas en T1, T2 y DP con planos axiales, sagitales y coronales. Se valoraba el posicionamiento del neorrecto descendido entre los músculos elevadores del ano y complejo esfinteriano y el grado desarrollo de la musculatura pelviana. Resultados: Seis pacientes presentaban un desarrollo adecuado de los músculos elevadores del ano y complejo esfinteriano, con correcto posicionamiento del neorrecto en 5 de ellos y situación excéntrica en 1. En los otros 6 casos se observaron diversos grados de subdesarrollo del complejo muscular estriado, 4 de ellos en grado moderado y en 2, grave. En el último grupo se observaron anomalías congénitas, disráficas espinales y del sistema urogenital. Los planos sagital y coronal potenciados en T1 fueron los más útiles para evaluar la interrelación entre músculos elevadores del ano y complejo esfinteriano, mientras que los planos axiales fueron útiles en la valoración del grado de desarrollo del complejo muscular estriado. Conclusiones: La RM es útil en la evaluación de pacientes con incontinencia fecal tras ARPSP por malformación anorrectal. Una inadecuada posición del neorrecto o hipoplasia del complejo muscular estriado son causas de incontinencia postoperatoria en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(3): 232-238, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63609</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d5345^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5345^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1009^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1009^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1009^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28277^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28277^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1010^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
