<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046038</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diastematomyelia: a form of spinal dysraphism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diastematomyelia is a rare form of occult spinal dysraphism (less than 3 % of cases) that is more frequent in children and mainly affects females. Clinically, there are three groups of manifestations: cutaneous, neurological and orthopedic deformities.                 We present the case of an 11-year-old girl with a recent, incidental diagnosis of diastematomyelia.                 Although this entity is unusual, it should be considered together with other forms of spinal dysraphism in children with congenital cutaneous markers of spinal dysraphism, even when these are vague and the patient is asymptomatic. Due to the frequency with which cutaneous manifestations appear, the intervention of a dermatologist is desirable in the diagnosis of this entity.                 A high index of suspicion is important when evaluating neonates and infants, given that an early diagnosis can alter neurologic prognosis, improving the quality of life of these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bordel Gómez, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diastematomielia es una forma rara de disrafia espinal oculta (menos del 3 % de los casos de disrafismo espinal) que es más frecuente en niños y que afecta principalmente al sexo femenino. Clínicamente se presenta con tres grupos de manifestaciones: cutáneas, neurológicas y deformidades ortopédicas.                 Presentamos el caso de una niña de 11 años de edad diagnosticada recientemente de diastematomielia de forma casual.                 A pesar de ser una entidad inusual debe tenerse en cuenta al igual que otras formas de disrafismo, ante niños que presentan estigmas cutáneos sugerentes de disrafia espinal, aún cuando estos sean imprecisos y el paciente se encuentre asintomático. Debido a la frecuencia con la que aparecen las manifestaciones cutáneas es deseable la intervención de un dermatólogo en el proceso diagnóstico de este cuadro.                 Es importante tener un alto índice de sospecha al evaluar a neonatos y lactantes, dado que el diagnóstico precoz puede modificar el pronóstico neurológico, mejorando la calidad de vida de estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(5): 485-488, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046038</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diastematomielia: una forma de disrafia espinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9629^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9165^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9629^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29127^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7162^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
