<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59794</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reference population values of the Spanish version of the COOP/WONCA charts of quality of life in an urban adult population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Reference population values of the Spanish version of the COOP/WONCA charts of quality of life in an urban adult population Background and objective: We intended to obtain reference population values of the COOP/WONCA charts of health-related quality of life (HRQOL) among a Spanish urban adult population. Material and method: Cross sectional study based on data from the Survey of Health of the City of Madrid 2005. 7341 adults were selected by biphasic cluster sampling. The variable HRQOL was measured through COOP/WONCA charts of quality of life (9 dimensions), culturally validated for Spanish people. Other variables included age, sex, marital status, and social class, zone of origin and level of education. Statistical treatment included descriptive statistics for the dimensions and summation of HRQOL, significance tests (Kruskal-Wallis, Mann-Whitney, ANOVA), analysis of internal consistency and correlation. Results: Highest mean values were found in the dimensions Changes in the State of Health, Health Status, Physical Form and Social Support. The average value of the dimensions and the summation of HRQOL increased significantly with age, and in parallel to a lowering of the social class and depending on the country of origin (higher in native people). They were also higher in women. The alpha of Cronbach for the questionnaire was 0.77.  Conclusions: Reference population values were obtained for a Spanish urban adult population according to sex, age, social class and status of native or immigrant people. All ratings increased with age and were highest in women. The availability of benchmarks values contribute to the score&#146; interpretation, which would ease the systematic use of tools of self-assessed health in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Otero,  Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizán-Tudela, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Gallardo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Olalla, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: el objetivo del estudio ha sido obtener valores poblacionales de referencia de las viñetas COOP/WONCA de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) para población adulta española de medio urbano. Material y método: se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo y transversal basado en los datos de la Encuesta de Salud de la Ciudad de Madrid de 2005. Se eligió a 7.341 adultos mediante muestreo por conglomerados bietápico. La variable CVRS se midió a través de las viñetas COOP/WONCA de calidad de vida (9 dimensiones), validadas culturalmente para población española. Otras variables estudiadas fueron: edad, sexo, estado civil, clase social, lugar de origen y nivel de estudios. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante índices de estadística descriptiva para las dimensiones y el sumatorio de CVRS, pruebas de contraste de hipótesis (Kruskal-Wallis, Mann-Whitney, ANOVA) y análisis de consistencia interna y de correlación. Resultados: los valores medios más altos se encontraron en las dimensiones Cambios en el Estado de Salud, Estado de Salud, Forma Física y Apoyo Social. Aumentó significativamente el valor medio de las dimensiones y del sumatorio de CVRS con la edad, a medida que se desciende en la clase social y según el país de origen (mayor en autóctonos); los valores fueron también más altos en mujeres. El coeficiente alfa de Cronbach para el cuestionario fue de 0,77.Conclusionesse han obtenido valores poblacionales de referencia para población adulta española de medio urbano según sexo, grupos de edad, clase social y condición de autóctono o inmigrante económico. Contar con valores de referencia contribuye a la interpretación de las puntuaciones obtenidas, lo que ayudaría a emplear de forma sistemática instrumentos de salud percibida en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(9): 336-343, mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores poblacionales de referencia de la versión española de las viñetas COOP/WONCA de calidad de vida en población adulta urbana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50343</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
