<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138331</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability study of performance indicators in asobal league</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this research was to validate the performance indicators ofered by the so-called game oficial statistics of the ASOBAL league. A sampling of events in three matches (n=7950). The variables used were the criteria which make up the observation system (placing, throwing area, way of finishing throwing, disciplinary measures, fouls, ofensive actions, defense actions, goal areas and goalkeeper eficiency), the oficial observer to compile statistics and two trained observers for the study. The data capture was performed using a system of field formats used by two trained observers. The agreement study proves the (objectivity) reliability of the analyzed sampling. The Generalizability study shows the reliable accuracy of it (&amp;#1866;=1; &amp;#961; 2=.999), the appropriate functioning of the observation system (&amp;#1866;=.000; &amp;#961; 2=.000) and the accuracy of generalization of the results (&amp;#1866;=.998; &amp;#961; 2=.998). Finally, the study of decision, where three new designs based on the original design data are proposed (variation of the number of observers, criteria and matches) , certified that the results obtained in the study generalizability of the original design, not were improvable with alternative designs. To sum up, the performance indicators are reliable and the results can be used accurately for research works (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Mendo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, Sergio José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antúnez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Asobal  Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación fue validar los indicadores de rendimiento ofrecidos por las denominadas estadísticas oficiales de juego de la liga ASOBAL. Se realizó un muestreo de eventos sobre tres partidos (n=7950). Las variables utilizadas fueron los criterios que conforman el sistema de observación (localización, zona de lanzamiento, forma de finalización del lanzamiento, sanciones disciplinarias, faltas, acciones de ataque, acciones de defensa, zonas de la portería y eficacia del portero), el observador oficial encargado de elaborar las estadísticas, y dos observadores entrenados para el estudio. La recogida de datos se realizó mediante un sistema de formatos de campo, utilizado por los dos observadores entrenados. El análisis de calidad del dato confirma la fiabilidad (objetividad) de la muestra analizada. El estudio de generalizabilidad manifiesta la precisión de medida (&amp;#1866;=1; &amp;#961; 2=.999), el adecuado funcionamiento del sistema de observación (&amp;#1866;=.000; &amp;#961; 2=.000) y la capacidad de generalización (&amp;#1866;=.998; &amp;#961; 2=.998). Finalmente el estudio de decisión donde se proponen tres nuevos diseños con sobre la base de los datos del diseño original (variación del número de observadores, de criterios y partidos), certificó que los resultados obtenidos en el estudio de generalizabilidad del diseño original no eran mejorables con los diseños alternativos. Se concluye que los indicadores de rendimiento analizados son fiables, pudiendo generalizar los resultados de forma precisa para la realización de trabajos de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(1): 255-264, ene.-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de fiabilidad de los indicadores de rendimiento en la liga asobal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50295^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
