<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60541</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infections in immunosuppressed patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Molecular biology techniques represent a major advance in the microbiologic diagnosis of infectious diseases, since these methods are able to detect etiological microorganisms with high sensitivity. Moreover, these procedures can also establish prognostic and therapeutic efficacy markers with a sufficiently short turnaround time for the results to have a real impact on the clinical management of immunosuppressed patients. However, these techniques still have substantial limitations that should be solved in the near future: lack of standardization, inter- and intra-assay variability, the difficulty of comparing results among different laboratories and low positive predictive value, due to their high sensitivity, leading to problems in the interpretation of results. The present article reviews the usefulness of molecular biology techniques in the diagnosis and clinical management of infectious diseases caused by human cytomegalovirus, Epstein-Barr virus, human herpes viruses 6 and 7, JC and BK viruses, &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Pneumocystis jiroveci&lt;/i&gt; in immunosuppressed patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Niubó, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Martínez, Miriam J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pumarola, Tomàs</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas de biología molecular han representado un importante avance en el diagnóstico microbiológico de las enfermedades infecciosas, al ser capaces de detectar el microorganismo causal con elevada sensibilidad y establecer marcadores pronósticos y de eficacia terapéutica, en un tiempo lo suficientemente breve para que los resultados generados tengan un impacto determinante en la evolución clínica del paciente inmunodeprimido. Sin embargo, continúan teniendo importantes limitaciones que deberán solucionarse en el futuro, de tal forma que no son excluyentes de otras metodologías utilizadas en microbiología: falta de estandarización, variabilidad intraanálisis e interanálisis, dificultad de comparar resultados entre diferentes laboratorios y bajo valor predictivo positivo, debido a su elevada sensibilidad, que dificultan la interpretación de los resultados. En el presente trabajo, se revisa la utilidad de las técnicas de biología molecular para el diagnóstico y el seguimiento de la infección en el paciente inmunodeprimido por citomegalovirus humano, virus de Epstein-Barr, virus del herpes simple 6 y 7, virus JC y BK, &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt; y &lt;i&gt;Pneumocystis jirovecii&lt;/i&gt;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.9): 58-65, jul. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60541</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones en el paciente inmunodeprimido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37992^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31793^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19278^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31867^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14515^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31829^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31042^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
