<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162645</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of rules modification and competition system on levels of satisfaction in basketball players under 14</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the present study was to analyze the opinion and satisfaction of the basketball players after the application of a tournament in which both the rules and the competition system are modified and adapted. Semi-structured interviews were conducted with 44 male and female players (under-14). From a quantitative and qualitative analysis of the data, the following results were obtained: a) The players responded before the tournament that the rules that conform the current regulation are relatively adequate, indicating as rules to modify those related to the increase of the time of Play and effectiveness at launch; B) Following the implementation of the new tournament, players indicate high levels of satisfaction with the new rules, especially those related to increased participation and efficiency at launch (basket height, the possibility of playing 4x4 situations And 1x1); C) Despite being especially pleased with the structure of the new tournament, most of them prefer a normal tournament (5x5). The reasons given are not based on exclusively sporting aspects, if not on organizational aspects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez Egido, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Toro, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañadas Alonso, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar la opinión y la satisfacción de los jugadores de baloncesto tras la aplicación de un torneo en el que se modifican y adaptan tanto el reglamento como el sistema de competición. Se realizaron entrevistas semi-estructuradas a 44 jugadores de categoría infantil (under-14) masculino. A partir de un análisis cuantitativo y cualitativo de los datos se obtuvieron los siguientes resultados: a) Los jugadores respondieron antes del torneo que las reglas que conforman el reglamento actual son relativamente adecuadas, señalando como reglas a modificar las relacionadas con el incremento del tiempo de juego y de la eficacia en el lanzamiento; b) tras la aplicación del nuevo torneo, los jugadores señalan elevados niveles de satisfacción con las nuevas reglas, especialmente las relacionadas con el incremento de la participación y de la eficacia en el lanzamiento (altura de la canasta, la posibilidad de jugar situaciones de 4x4 y de 1x1); c) a pesar de mostrarse especialmente satisfechos con la estructura del nuevo torneo, la mayoría de ellos prefieren un torneo normal (5x5), aunque las razones expresadas no se basan en aspectos exclusivamente deportivos, sino organizativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.1): 59-64, 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de la modificación de reglas y sistema de competición sobre los niveles de satisfacción en jugadores de baloncesto under 14</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
