<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166877</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is there a role for antiarrhythmic drugs?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antiarrhythmic drugs form a varied group of compounds with a range of different mechanisms of action and distinct side-effect profiles. In general, they are moderately effective but, frequently, have a narrow therapeutic margin and can even be lethal in some cases if not used properly. Drug selection is influenced by the type of arrhythmia to be treated and by the patient&#146;s clinical status (especially the presence of underlying heart disease). It is important to acknowledge that, in some types of arrhythmia, catheter ablation or implantable devices such as defibrillators have been shown to be more effective than antiarrhythmic drugs. This review article considers the role of drug treatment in the principle forms of arrhythmia encountered in clinical practice, with particular emphasis on the risk- benefit balance in each clinical setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cañadas Godoy, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Planas, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cavazos, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Castellano, Nicasio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Villacastín, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los fármacos antiarrítmicos son un grupo de compuestos heterogéneo, con mecanismos de acción diversos y distintos perfiles de efectos secundarios. En general tienen una eficacia moderada y, en muchas ocasiones, un margen terapéutico estrecho. En algunos casos, pueden incluso resultar letales si no se usan con el adecuado conocimiento. La selección del tratamiento está condicionada por el tipo de arritmia que se va a tratar y el perfil del paciente (especialmente, la cardiopatía de base). Es importante tener en cuenta que, en algunas de las arritmias, la ablación con catéter o dispositivos como el desfibrilador han resultado ser de eficacia superior que los fármacos antiarrítmicos. En la presente revisión se analiza el papel de los fármacos en las principales arritmias encontradas en la práctica clínica, con especial atención a la relación riesgo/beneficio en cada uno de los escenarios clínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.A): 69a-77a, 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166877</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Hay un lugar para los fármacos antiarrítmicos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13994^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19362^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1288^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
