<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60400</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cholestasis associated with prolonged parenteral nutrition in neonates: The role of urso-deoxycholic acid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The morbidity associated with prematurity occasionally leads to the use of prolonged parenteral nutrition, with the subsequent development of cholestasis being one of its complications. Patients and methods: This is a two year retrospective study which compared biochemical markers of liver damage and cholestasis in premature babies who received or did not receive urso-deoxycholic acid for parenteral nutrition associated cholestasis. Results: Of a total of 24 recruited patients 17 received urso-deoxycholic acid and 7 did not. In the treated group significant decreases (P&lt;0.05) in gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase and conjugated bilirubin were found after four and five weeks of treatment, respectively. Moreover, a significant correlation (P&lt;0.01) between conjugated bilirubin and duration of total parenteral nutrition was established. Conclusions: Patients who were promptly treated with urso-deoxycholic acid showed a more rapid decrease in biochemical markers of cholestasis, but not of cytotoxicity in the hepatobiliary complications secondary to prolonged parenteral nutrition. However, the present study has limitations derived from its design and therefore it would be desirable launch a randomized trial with sufficient power to evaluate the benefits derived from prophylactic or therapeutic use of urso-deoxycholic acid in the hepatobiliary conditions associated with the prolonged use of parenteral nutrition in the premature infants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáenz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubells, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vento, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garzón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La morbilidad asociada a la prematuridad hace necesaria en ocasiones la administración de una nutrición parenteral prolongada (NPP) que tiene como una de las complicaciones asociadas el desarrollo de colestasis. Material y métodos: Análisis retrospectivo de 2 años que incluyó el estudio de marcadores de daño hepatocelular e indicadores de colestasis en neonatos con NPP tratados o no con ácido ursodesoxicólico (AUDC). Resultados: De 24 pacientes estudiados, 17 recibieron AUDC y 7 fueron controles. En el grupo tratado se evidenció un descenso significativo (p&lt;0,05) en las cifras de gammaglutamil transpeptidasa y de bilirrubina conjugada a partir de las 4 a las 5 semanas de tratamiento, respectivamente, comparado con el grupo no tratado. Asimismo, se constató una correlación significativa (p&lt;0,01) entre las cifras de bilirrubina conjugada máxima y el tiempo de nutrición parenteral total. Conclusiones: Los pacientes que recibieron AUDC experimentaron un descenso más rápido de los marcadores bioquímicos de colestasis, pero no de los de citotoxicidad en la enfermedad hepatobiliar asociada a NPP. Sin embargo, el presente estudio tiene limitaciones derivadas de su diseño retrospectivo y, por tanto, sería deseable realizar un estudio aleatorizado con potencia estadística adecuada para evaluar la utilidad tanto profiláctica como terapéutica del AUDC en las complicaciones hepáticas de la NPP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(6): 547-552, jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colestasis asociada a la nutrición parenteral prolongada en el período neonatal: posible eficacia del ácido ursodesoxicólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14982^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
