<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048368</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary calculi in myelomeningocele adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: the improvements in the management of newborns with myelomeningocele (MMC) have        obtained a big increase in survival, allowing them to get longevity like never before, but data regarding urologic diseases        during adult age are still missing. We herein evaluate the features of urinary lithiasis in adults born with MMC and the        therapies used for its treatment.        Material and method: we review 52 patients diagnosed at birth of MMC, between 18 and 40 years old, treated in our        institution, with a mean follow-up of 6.7 years.        Results: 10 patients (19.2%) were diagnosed of urolithiasis. Three developed kidney calculi and one of them, with 7        more patients, developed bladder calculi (15.3%). The neurological level was &gt;= L2 in 3 cases, L2-S1 in 5, and &gt;= S1 in the        other two. The type of neurogenic dysfunction of inferior urinary tract was multiple lesion of lower motor neurone in 6        cases, upper motor neurone in 1 case, multiple mixed lesion in 1 case and in case it was impossible to determine. Two        patients had a bladder augmentation procedure and one of these with other 3 patients had a non-functional AMS-800        artificial urinary sphincter. Bladder stones were treated endoscopically in 14 procedures and by suprapubic cystolithotomy        in 4 procedures, combined with removal of AMS-800 in 3 of them. One patient spontaneously passed a small stone.        In one case, 2 ESWL and 2 percutaneous nephrolithotomies were needed. Three patients developed multiple recurrences        during follow-up.        Conclusions: urinary lithiasis is common in adults with MMC. Some distinct features of these patients, together with        their anatomical configuration and some therapies used in them, cause diagnostic, therapeutic and prophylaxis issues        for the calculi they may develop</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez Cordero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdú Tartajo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Merino, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Amo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Casado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los avances en el tratamiento de los nacidos con mielomeningocele (MMC) han logrado un        gran aumento en su supervivencia, permitiéndoles una longevidad nunca antes alcanzada, pero todavía son escasos los        datos concernientes a los problemas urológicos que estos enfermos plantean durante su vida adulta. Hemos evaluado        las características de la litiasis urinaria en adultos nacidos con MMC así como los tratamientos empleados en la misma.        Material y métodos: Revisamos 52 pacientes nacidos con MMC de entre 18 y 40 años, atendidos durante los últimos        14 años en nuestro hospital, con una media de seguimiento de 6,7 años.        Resultados: Se diagnosticaron de litiasis urinaria 10 pacientes (19,2%). Tres formaron cálculos renales (5,7%), y uno        de ellos, junto con 7 pacientes más, desarrollaron cálculos vesicales (15,3%). El nivel neurológico fue &amp;#8804; L2 en 3 casos, L2-        S1 en 5, y &gt;= S1 en otros dos. El tipo de disfunción neurógena del tracto urinario inferior fue de lesión múltiple pura de        neurona motora inferior en 6 casos, de neurona motora superior en 1, lesión múltiple mixta en otro, no pudiéndose valorar        en el restante. Dos pacientes tenían una ampliación vesical y uno de estos junto con otros 3 pacientes era portador        de AMS-800 no funcionantes. La litiasis vesical se trató endoscopicamente en 14 ocasiones y mediante cistolitotomía        suprapúbica en 4, junto a la retirada de AMS-800 en 3 de ellas. Un paciente expulsó un pequeño cálculo. En un paciente        fueron necesarias 2 litotricias extracorpóreas y 2 nefrolitotomías percutáneas. Tres pacientes tuvieron múltiples recidivas.        Conclusiones: La litiasis urinaria es frecuente en los adultos con MMC. Determinadas características de estos pacientes,        junto con su configuración anatómica y algunos tratamientos empleados en ellos, ocasionan problemas de diagnostico,        tratamiento y prevención de los cálculos que forman</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(7): 675-683, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Litiasis urinaria en adultos con mielomeningocele</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1460^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1460^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24010^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24010^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22873^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24256^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4151^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
