<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044359</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of psychiatric disorders in patients with fecal incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the presence of psychiatric alterations in patients with fecal incontinence.   Patients and method. Eighty consecutive patients (67 women) with fecal incontinence were evaluated. All the patients completed the the specific GHQ-28 questionnaire to evaluate psychiatric symptoms. The questionnaire had previously been validated in the Spanish language. A score equal to or higher than 6 points was considered to indicate pathology. Incontinence was evaluated by the Cleveland Clinic Florida-Fecal Incontinence severity score (range 0 - 20). Psychiatric antecedents prior to fecal incontinence were recorded.    Results. Thirty-two patients (40%) had pathological scores on the GHQ-28 questionnaire (mean 13.59, range: 7-26). The mean Cleveland score was 11.52 (range: 2-20). Patients with pathological GHQ-28 scores had higher fecal incontinence scores (14.28 vs 9.68; p &lt; 0.0001). A significant lineal correlation was found between GHQ-28 scores and the severity of fecal incontinence (p &lt; 0.0001). Psychiatric antecedents were found in 17 patients (21.3%). In these patients no correlation was found between GHQ-28 score and the severity of incontinence. In the subgroup of patients without psychiatric antecedents this correlation was maintained (p &lt; 0.003). Of these, 20 (31.7%) had pathologic scores on the GHQ-28, and the mean incontinence severity score was significantly higher than that of those with a normal GHQ-28 score (13.15 vs. 9.25; p &lt; 0.004).  Conclusions. The prevalence of psychiatric alterations is high in patients with fecal incontinence and is correlated with its severity. Patients with psychiatric antecedents can bias evaluation of the association between psychiatric alterations and the severity of fecal incontinence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ciga, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oteiza, Fabiola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, Mario de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armendáriz, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar la presencia de alteraciones psiquiátricas en las personas con incontinencia fecal. Pacientes y método. Ochenta pacientes (67 mujeres) diagnosticados de incontinencia fecal. Todos cumplimentaron el cuestionario específico GHQ-28, validado en lengua española para evaluación de alteraciones psiquiátricas; es patológica una puntuación igual o superior a 6. La gravedad de la incontinencia se evaluó con la escala de la Cleveland Clinic-Florida (rango, 0-20). Se recogieron los antecedentes psiquiátricos anteriores a su incontinencia fecal.    Resultados. Treinta y dos pacientes (40%) presentaban puntuaciones patológicas en el cuestionario GHQ-28 (media, 13,59; rango, 7-26). La media de gravedad de la incontinencia ha sido de 11,52 puntos (rango, 2-20). Los pacientes con puntuaciones patológicas en el cuestionario GHQ-28 tenían puntuaciones mayores en la escala de gravedad de incontinencia (14,28 frente a 9,68; p &lt; 0,0001). Se ha encontrado una correlación lineal significativa (p &lt; 0,0001) entre las puntuaciones del GHQ-28 y la gravedad de la incontinencia fecal. Presentaban antecedentes psiquiátricos 17 pacientes (21,3%) en los que se pierde la correlación entre la puntuación del GHQ-28 y la gravedad de la incontinencia. En el subgrupo sin antecedentes se mantiene esta correlación (p &lt; 0,003). De ellos, 20 (31,7%) presentaban puntuaciones patológicas del GHQ-28, con una media de gravedad de la incontinencia significativamente superior a aquellos con puntuación normal (13,15 frente a 9,25; p &lt; 0,004).                 Conclusiones. La presencia de alteraciones psiquiátricas es alta en los pacientes con incontinencia, y tiene correlación con la gravedad de la incontinencia. Los antecedentes psiquiátricos pueden sesgar la valoración de los pacientes con incontinencia fecal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(4): 241-244, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044359</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de problemas psiquiátricos en pacientes con incontinencia fecal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5345^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
