<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053256</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The virtude of that precious balsam: approach to Don Quixote from the psychopharmacological perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most outstanding novel of the Spanish literature, Don Quixote, represents the source to which the different specialists who intend to deepen their knowledge of the late Renaissance society usually address. This masterpiece of Miguel de Cervantes has been frequently approached from the psychopathological perspective to obtain a psychiatric diagnosis of its main character, Alonso Quijano. Also, other clinical approaches from the traumatological and general therapeutical view (oils, ointments, balms and other pharmacy preparations) have been frequent. We have tackled Don Quixote from the psychopharmacological perspective, a barely explored field. In this work, we intend to study the therapeutical cures used during the Cervantine time for the treatment of insane and mentally disturbed people (sedatives like opium, laxatives like hellebore, tonics, irritants and surgical techniques like bloodlettings and «fuentes») and we analyze the limited and unspecific therapies, mainly of herbal origin (balms, purgatives and emetics), which Cervantes reveals to us in his novel. Among them, rhubarb root (Rumex alpinus), seeds of spurge (Euphorbia lathyris), St. John's Wort (Hypericum perforatum), main ingredient of Aparicio's oil, and rosemary (Rosmarinus officinalis), primary component of the famous balsam of Fierabras, should be highlighted. We have also examined the possible scientific influences which might have inspired Cervantes in this field, mainly the works of Juan Huarte de San Juan The examination of men's wits and the one of Andres Laguna Dioscorides' materia medica</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Muñoz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álamo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obra cumbre de la literatura española, El Quijote, constituye una fuente donde habitualmente beben los diferentes especialistas que pretenden conocer con mayor profundidad la sociedad renacentista tardía. Esta obra magistral de Miguel de Cervantes ha sido frecuentemente abordada desde la perspectiva psicopatológica para obtener un diagnóstico psiquiátrico de su principal personaje, Alonso Quijano. También son frecuentes los abordajes clínicos desde la traumatología y desde la terapéutica general (análisis de aceites, ungüentos, bálsamos y demás preparados de botica). Nosotros nos acercamos a El Quijote desde la vertiente de la psicofarmacología, un campo escasamente abordado. En el presente trabajo se estudian los remedios terapéuticos empleados en la época cervantina para el tratamiento de los locos y enajenados (sedantes, como el opio; evacuantes, como el eléboro; tónicos, irritantes y técnicas quirúrgicas, como las sangrías y fuentes) y se analizan las escasas e inespecíficas terapias, fundamentalmente de origen herbal, que Cervantes nos revela en su novela (bálsamos, purgantes y eméticos). Entre ellas cabe mencionar la raíz de ruibarbo (Rumex alpinus), las semillas de tártago (Euphorbia lathyris), la hierba de San Juan (Hypericum perforatum), ingrediente del aceite de Aparicio y el romero (Rosmarinus officinalis), ingrediente del célebre bálsamo de Fierabrás. También se analizan las posibles influencias científicas en que se pudo inspirar Cervantes en este campo, fundamentalmente las obras de Juan Huarte de San Juan Examen de ingenios para las ciencias y de Andrés Laguna Dioscorides, acerca de la materia medicinal y de los venenos mortíferos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(3): 149-161, mayo-jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La virtud de aquel precioso bálsamo: aproximación a El Quijote desde la vertiente de la psicofarmacología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8686^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
