<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127031</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in patients with knee and hip osteoarthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the quality of life in patients with knee and hip osteoarthritis through self-assessment and those made by the physician. Materials and methods. An observational and cross-sectional multicenter study in which 628 traumatologists or rheumatologists evaluated 1,849 patients with knee and/or hip osteoarthritis, aged &amp;#8805; 50 years old, and representative of 49 Spanish provinces. Each researcher evaluated three patients and also completed the SF-12v2 health questionnaire. The patients completed the WOMAC and SF-12v2 questionnaires. Results. The patients were 68.5 ± 9.5 years old, 61.5% had knee osteoarthritis, 19% had hip osteoarthritis, and 19.5% in both locations. Older patients and those who had both knee and hip osteoarthritis had a poorer quality of life, according to patients and researchers. Physical health perceived by the researchers was better than patients reported (36.74 ± 8.6 and 35.21 ± 8.53; respectively, p &lt; 0.001), and the mental health score was similar between physicians and patients. Kellgren/Lawrence scale and test Timed Up &amp; Go predict better the quality of life, assessed by WOMAC and SF-12v2 questionnaires. Discussion. This is the Spanish study on quality of life in osteoarthritis of the knee and hip of larger amplitude and number of patients. Conclusion. These results could be considered as reference values of Spanish population aged &amp;#8805; 50 years with knee or hip osteoarthritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcés-Puentes, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras-Sotos, J. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>M. Bernad-Pineda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la calidad de vida de pacientes con artrosis de rodilla y cadera a través de autovaloraciones y las realizadas por el médico. Material y método. Estudio observacional, transversal y multicéntrico en el que 628 traumatólogos o reumatólogos evaluaron a 1.849 pacientes con artrosis de rodilla y/o de cadera con edad mínima de 50 años, distribuidos en 49 provincias españolas. Cada investigador evaluó a tres pacientes y cumplimentó el cuestionario de salud SF-12v2. Los pacientes respondieron los cuestionarios WOMAC y SF-12v2. Resultados. Los pacientes tenían de 68,5 ± 9,5 años de edad, el 61,5% tenía artrosis de rodilla, el 19% de cadera y el 19,5% en ambas localizaciones. Los pacientes de más edad y los que tenían artrosis de rodilla y de cadera presentaban peor calidad de vida, según la opinión de los pacientes y los investigadores. La salud física percibida por los médicos fue mejor que la manifestada por los pacientes (36,74 ± 8,6 y 35,21 ± 8,53; respectivamente, p &lt; 0,001) y la puntuación del componente mental de salud asignada por los pacientes y los médicos fue similar. La Escala de Kellgren/Lawrence y el test Timed Up &amp; Go pronostican mejor la calidad de vida evaluada con los cuestionarios WOMAC y SF-12v2. Discusión. Este es el estudio español sobre calidad de vida en artrosis de rodilla y cadera de mayor envergadura por amplitud y número de pacientes. Conclusiones. Estos resultados podrían ser considerados como valores de referencia de población española de 50 años o mayores con artrosis de rodilla y/o de cadera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(5): 283-289, sept.-oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla y/o cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
