<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048257</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the Use of New Drugs in a Primary Care District</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The use of new drugs has undergone a majorincrease in recent years. This study is aimed at ascertaining thedegree to which pharmaceutical novelties are being used in onehealthcare district in Zaragoza, describing which are those mostused and the trend thereof over the course of time in addition toanalyzing the characteristics of those centers associated with a greateruse of these drugs.Methods: A descriptive study analyzing all of the dispensationsof fifty new active ingredients marketed within the January 1, 2000 -December 31, 2003 period in one healthcare district. The percentageof use of novelties throughout the first year these drugs were marketedat each primary care center was calculated, the characteristicsof those centers associated with a greater degree of innovationhaving been analyzed.Results: Seventy-six percent of the fifty new drugs marketedwere barely innovative in comparison to the existing ones. The tennew drugs most prescribed began being used during the first fourmonths immediately after coming out on the market. The percentageof use of new drugs as compared to all of the drugs prescribed at thehealthcare centers studied fell within the 0.3% -1.18% range. In theanalysis made by centers, the «per-patient expense» and the «consultationsper physician» are positively correlated with a greater useof new drugs, whilst the percentage of retirees showed a reverseratio.Conclusions: A high degree of variability exists in the percentageof use of pharmaceutical novelties among the primary care centers.The centers having the largest number of consultations perphysician are those tending toward more readily incorporating thesenew drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lallana Álvarez, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabanaque Hernández, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La utilización de nuevos fármacos ha aumentadode forma importante en los últimos años. El objetivo de este trabajoes conocer la utilización de novedades farmacéuticas en un área desalud de Zaragoza, describir cuales son las más utilizadas y su evoluciónen el tiempo y analizar las características de los centros que seasocian con un mayor uso de estos medicamentos.Métodos: Se trata de un estudio descriptivo en el que se analizarontodas las dispensaciones de 50 nuevos principios activos comercializadosentre el 1-1-2000 y el 31-12-2003 en un área de salud. Secalculó el porcentaje de utilización de novedades durante el primeraño de su comercialización, en cada centro de atención primaria, y seanalizaron las características de los centros que se asociaban conmayor grado de innovación.Resultados: El 76% de los 50 nuevos fármacos comercializadoseran escasamente innovadores respecto a los ya existentes. Las dieznovedades más prescritas comenzaron a utilizarse en el primer cuatrimestretras su aparición en el mercado. El porcentaje de utilizaciónde novedades respecto al total de fármacos prescritos en los centrosde salud estudiados osciló entre el 0,3% y el 1,18%. En el análisisefectuado por centros, el «gasto por paciente» y las «consultas pormédico» se correlacionaron positivamente con un mayor uso demedicamentos nuevos, mientras que el porcentaje de pensionistaspresentó una relación inversa.Conclusiones: Existe una gran variabilidad en el porcentaje deutilización de novedades farmacológicas entre los centros de atenciónprimaria. Los centros con mayor número de consultas por facultativoson los que tienden a incorporar los nuevos medicamentos conmayor facilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(3): 379-389, mayo-jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en la utilización de nuevos medicamentos en un área de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
