<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114178</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High-flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy: employment in ward</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The high-flow nasal cannula (HFNC) oxygen therapy is a respiratory support usually used in intensive care units. In our hospital we used it in the pediatric ward (infants and children) since April 2009. Our aim is to test the clinical out­comes, security, and assess the acceptance of its use by the nursing service. Patients and methods: We reviewed the use of HFNC in acute respiratory failure (ARF) during 2011, establishing three groups: G1, bronchiolitis; G2, children under 2 years with previous episodes, and G3, children over 2 years with previous episodes. Prospectively, we assessed the severity of the ARF, comparing the improvement of the patients, considering the transition of severe distress to moderate distress at 6 respectively 12 hours of the clinical onset. We also realized a survey to all the paediatric ward nurses about their perception of the HFNC (installation and maintenance, interference with medications, diet, side effects, tolerance...). Results: In our study, 33 patients received HNCF. We saw an improvement in all three groups (p &lt;0.001), without significant differences between them. Taking separately, we found an improvement in each one of them, G1 (p &lt;0.001), G2 (p= 0.003) and G3 (p= 0.006). The perception of nursing about the HFNC is that it's easy to apply, so generally, they had a positive impression about this respiratory support. Conclusions: The HFNC it's a respiratory support with obvious clinical benefits, easy to use, well accepted by nurses and, as we think, applicable in a hospital ward. Anyway, we mustn't forget that are critically patients requiring maximum vigilance and that not all of them respond favorably (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cernat, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiano, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Len, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La oxigenoterapia de alto flujo (OAF) es un soporte respiratorio normalmente empleado en las unidades de cuidados intensivos. En nuestro hospital lo llevamos utilizando en planta (lactantes y escolares) desde abril de 2009. El objetivo de este estudio es comprobar los resultados clínicos y su seguridad, así como valorar la aceptación de su uso por parte de enfermería. Pacientes y métodos: Se ha revisado el empleo de OAF en la insuficiencia respiratoria aguda (IRA) durante 2011, estableciendo tres grupos: G1, bronquiolitis; G2, menores de 2 años con episodios previos, y G3, mayores de 2 años con episodios previos. Prospectivamente, hemos valorado la gravedad de la IRA y comparado más tarde su mejoría, considerando el paso de grave a moderado a las 6 y 12 horas de su inicio. Asimismo, se ha realizado una encuesta al personal de enfermería sobre su percepción de la OAF (montaje y mantenimiento, interferencia con medicaciones, alimentación, efectos secundarios, tolerancia...). Resultados: Han recibido OAF 33 pacientes. En conjunto, mejoran todos (p &lt;0,001), sin diferencias significativas entre ellos. Separadamente, hay mejoría en los tres grupos: G1 (p &lt;0,001), G2 (p= 0,003) y G3 (p= 0,006). La percepción del personal de enfermería es que se trata de un sistema de fácil aplicación, y de forma generalizada se tiene una impresión positiva de este soporte respiratorio. Conclusiones: La OAF supone un soporte respiratorio de evidente beneficio clínico, de fácil aplicación y bien asumido por la enfermería. Creemos que es aplicable en una planta de hospitalización, pero sin olvidarnos de que se aplica a pacientes graves que requieren la máxima vigilancia y que no todos responderán favorablemente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;71(6): e134-e138, jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Oxigenoterapia de alto flujo en cánulas nasales: empleo en una planta de hospitalización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
