<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165448</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic precision of the submandibular skinfold, minimum waist circumference and minimum waist to height ratio, as adipose overweight and obesity indicators in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obesity is caused by the excess of adipose tissue in the body, and is considered one of the most important public health issues of the 21st century, particularly in childhood. One of the most used methods for obesity diagnosis is the body mass index, however, it is not an effective method to identify adiposity. Other anthropometric dimensions beyond weight, height and the relationship between them, may constitute an alternative to identify and assess obesity and adiposity in children. This study seeks to evaluate the diagnostic accuracy of submandibular skinfold, minimum waist circumference and minimum waist to height ratio, as markers of overweight and obesity due to excess adiposity in children. Methods: Six anthropometric variables (weight, height, minimum waist circumference [PCM], tricipital fold [PT], subscapular fold [PSE] and submandibular or submental depression [PSM]) were evaluated in 1,858 school-aged children (6 to 11 years). BMI for age was calculated based on the World Health Organization references. Adiposity was estimated with Latin American and Spanish references. A standard was created from both references to test all 3 proposed variables for association, sensibility and specificity tests to generate cutoff points. Results: According to the standard created, 15.8% of the study population was overweight with moderate adiposity, while 12.2% presented obesity with high adiposity, for a combined prevalence of 28.0%. All three variables studied were significantly correlated (&lt;0.001) with the BMI and triceps skinfold (as an adiposity indicator). The area under the curve of the ROC curves ranged from 0.835 to 0.993 for submandibular skinfold, 0.942 to 0.993 for minimum waist circumference, and from 0.909 to 0.991 for minimum waist to height ratio. The lowest sensitivity and specificity were found in submandibular skinfold for 11-year-old girls (70.6%) and for 9-year-old girls (79.8%), respectively. Discussion: Both, minimum waist circumference and minimum waist to height ratio were significantly higher in boys, while triceps and subscapular skinfolds were in girls (p&lt;0.001). This can be attributed to the different body composition characteristics between genders. The highest association of body mass index was observed with the minimum waist circumference (girls, r = 0.926; boys, r = 0.924), while submandibular skinfold presented the highest association with tricipital skinfold (boys, p = 0.857; girls, R = 0.821). As a standard to analyze sensitivity and specificity, a variable was created to group subjects who simultaneously presented: a) overweight with moderate adiposity; and, b) obesity with high adiposity. This allows not only to diagnose excess weight but, concomitantly, adiposity. Conclusion: All three proposed variables effectively identify excess weight and excess adiposity in both boys and girls from 6 to 11 years of age, so they can be used as an alternative to the body mass index and those skinfolds that require a more invasive evaluation. Also, because their application in the field is simple, could be eligible as alternatives for epidemiological surveillance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochoa González, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos García, César Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loreto Garibay, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad es una enfermedad caracterizada por el exceso de tejido adiposo en el cuerpo y es considerada uno de los problemas de salud pública más importantes del siglo 21, particularmente en la edad infantil. Uno de los métodos más utilizados para su diagnóstico es el Índice de masa corporal, sin embargo, este no identifica eficazmente la adiposidad. Otras dimensiones antropométricas más allá del peso, la talla y la relación entre ellas, pueden constituir una alternativa para identificar y valorar el exceso de peso y adiposidad en población infantil. Este estudio busca evaluar la precisión diagnostica del pliegue submandibular, el perímetro de cintura mínima y el índice cintura mínima-estatura, como indicadores de sobrepeso y obesidad por exceso de adiposidad en población infantil. Métodos: Se evaluaron 6 variables antropométricas (peso, estatura, perímetro de cintura mínima [PCM], pliegue tricipital [PT], pliegue subescapular [PSE] y pliegue submandibular o submentoniano [PSM]), en 1,858 niños de 6 a 11 años de edad. Se calculó el IMC para la edad con las referencias de la Organización Mundial de la Salud y se estimó adiposidad con referencias latinoamericanas y españolas. Se creó un estándar a partir de ambas referencias con el cual se realizaron correlaciones y pruebas de sensibilidad y especificidad para generar puntos de corte para las 3 variables propuestas. Resultados: De acuerdo a la variable creada, 15.8 % de la población general presentó sobrepeso con adiposidad moderada, mientras que 12.2 % presentó obesidad con adiposidad elevada, para una prevalencia combinada de 28.0 %. Las tres variables estudiadas se correlacionan significativamente (&lt;0.001) con el IMC y el pliegue tricipital (como indicador de adiposidad). El área bajo la curva de las curvas ROC osciló entre 0.835 a 0.993 para pliegue submandibular, 0.942 a 0.993 para perímetro de cintura mínima y entre 0.909 a 0.991 para índice cintura mínima-estatura. Así mismo, la sensibilidad y la especificidad más bajas se encontraron en pliegue sumbandibular para mujeres de 11 años (70.6%) y para mujeres de 9 años (79.8%) respectivamente. Discusión: Se observó que tanto el perímetro de cintura mínima, como el índice cintura mínima-estatura fueron significativamente mayores en los niños, mientras que los pliegues tricipital y subescapular lo fueron en las niñas (p&lt;0.001). Lo anterior puede atribuirse al diferencial de composición corporal entre ambos sexos. La mayor asociación del índice de masa corporal se presentó con el perímetro de cintura mínima (niñas, r= 0.926; niños, r= 0.924), mientras que la del pliegue submandibular se presentó con el pliegue tricipital (niños, p= 0.857; niñas, r= 0.821). Como estándar para analizar la sensibilidad y especificidad, se creó una variable para agrupar a sujetos que presentaran simultáneamente: a) sobrepeso y adiposidad moderada; y, b) obesidad y adiposidad elevada. Esto nos permite no solo diagnosticar exceso de peso sino concomitantemente adiposidad. Conclusiones: Las tres variables propuestas identifican eficaz y paralelamente exceso de peso y exceso de adiposidad tanto en niños como en niñas de 6 a 11 años de edad, por lo que pueden ser utilizadas como una alternativa al índice de masa corporal y aquellos pliegues cutáneos que requieren una evaluación más invasiva. Así mismo, su facilidad de aplicación en campo, las presenta como instrumentos elegibles, alternativos o complementarios para la vigilancia epidemiológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(2): 162-172, 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Precisión diagnóstica del pliegue submandibular, perímetro de cintura mínima e índice cintura mínima-estatura, como indicadores de sobrepeso y obesidad por adiposidad en población infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
