<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89595</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge of and satisfaction with the approval of the nurse prescription of nurses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the knowledge, satisfaction and capabilities of nurses regarding nurseprescribing after the approval of the Nurse Prescription Law.Methods: A cross-sectional study carried out in the School of Nursing at the University of Barcelona(UB). The participants included 485 nurses taking a Masters or Specialist degree andteaching staff in these courses. The main variables were: satisfaction, information and knowledgeabout the recently approved Law, knowledge about the current skills on the prescribedproducts, nurse perception of their own prescribing ability, and opinion on information andtraining as regards the new law. The secondary variables included: years of professional experience,area and job position, postgraduate course and socio-demographic data. The study wasconducted from March to April 2010 using a self-administered ad hoc questionnaire with 29items on the topic and previously piloted on site.Results: A total of 345 nurses participated, of whom 87.2% (301) taking a Masters degree. Ofthese, 72.3% (238) were aware and stated to have knowledge of the Law passed, although95.9% (303) of them said they lacked information on it. The mean score on satisfaction with theapproval of the Prescription Law was 6.24±2.08. Of all the nurses, 57.6% (189) of them saidthey were currently able to prescribe health products and 41.3% were capable of prescribingdrugs (134).Conclusions: Nurses showed a high level of satisfaction with the Nurse Prescriptionlaw. Currently, many nurses are independently prescribing pharmacological and health products (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ortega, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera-Jaime, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada-Masllorens, Joan María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoIdentificar el nivel de conocimiento, satisfacción y capacitación de las enfermeras con relación a la prescripción enfermera tras la aprobación de la Ley 28/2009.MétodoEstudio observacional descriptivo transversal realizado en la Escuela de Enfermería de la Universidad de Barcelona. Los sujetos a estudio fueron 485 enfermeras en formación máster o especialización y docentes de dicha escuela. Las variables principales de estudio fueron: satisfacción, conocimiento e información de la aprobación de la Ley, conocimiento de los elementos autorizados a prescribir, percepción de capacidad prescriptora de las enfermeras y opinión de la necesidad formativa e informativa respecto a la Ley. Como secundarias: años de experiencia profesional, ámbito laboral, curso formativo y sociodemográficas. La recogida de datos se realizó entre los meses de marzo y abril de 2010 mediante un cuestionario autoaplicable ad hoc de 29 ítems, probado previamente.ResultadosParticiparon 345 enfermeras, el 87,2% (301) alumnas en formación máster. El 72,3% (238) de las enfermeras conocían la aprobación de la ley, pero un 95,9% (303) indicó tener insuficiente información. La satisfacción media con la aprobación de la Ley se situó en 6,24±2,08. El 57,6% (189) de las enfermeras opinaron estar capacitadas para prescribir productos sanitarios y un 41,3% (134), para prescribir fármacos.ConclusionesHay satisfacción con la aprobación de la Ley 28/2009. Actualmente muchas enfermeras prescriben productos farmacológicos y sanitarios de forma autónoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);21(2): 84-90, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento y satisfacción de la aprobación de la prescripción enfermera (Ley 28/2009) en enfermeras de formación máster y especialidad de la Universidad de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
