<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90213</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidisciplinary management of ovarian epithelial cancer. Radiological diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the context of a multidisciplinary approach forthe diagnosis and treatment of ovarian cancer, the contributionof radiology includes the following four fundamentalpoints: identification of the lesion, its characterization,study of its extension and evaluation of itsevolution. This article describes the findings and keydiagnostic elements in MDCT (Multidetector ComputedTomography) and MR (Magnetic Resonance), thecontribution and indication of other technologies likePET (Positron Emission Tomography), and outlines theemergent techniques based on functional image analysis(dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI studies and MRIdiffusion studies)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ostiz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el contexto del abordaje multidisciplinar parael diagnóstico y tratamiento del cáncer de ovario, laaportación del radiólogo incluye cuatro puntos fundamentalesque son: identificación de la lesión, caracterización,estudio de extensión y valoración evolutiva.En el presente trabajo se describen los hallazgos y clavesdiagnósticas en TCMD (Tomografía Computarizadamultidetector) y RM (Resonancia Magnética), la aportacióne indicación de otras tecnologías como el PET(Tomografía por Emisión de Positrones) y se esbozanlas técnicas emergentes basadas en imagen funcional(estudios dinámicos con contraste en RM y estudios dedifusión por RM)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(2): 275-288, mayo-ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo multidisciplinar del cáncer epitelial de ovario. Diagnóstico radiológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
