<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90542</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish Version of the Itch Severity Scale: The PSEDA Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The Itch Severity Scale (ISS) facilitates objective assessment of the intensity of pruritus. The aim of this study was to validate a Spanish version of the ISS in patients with atopic dermatitis. Material and methods: A prospective epidemiological study was undertaken in patients diagnosed with atopic dermatitis at least 1 year previously and a control group without the disease. Patients with atopic dermatitis were stratified according to the status of the lesions (active or inactive) and questionnaires were completed at baseline and 3-month and 6-month follow-up. Data were collected on sociodemographic variables relating to atopic dermatitis (including the modified Eczema Area and Severity Index [mEASI]), concomitant disease, and patient measures such as ISS, Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI), and Children's DLQI (cDLQI). Results: A total of 207 children (2-17 years) were included: 56 control subjects, 103 patients with active lesions, and 48 with inactive lesions. The mean (SD) age of the participants in this age group was 8.1 (4.0) years. A total of 261 adults (&amp;#8805; 18 years) were included: 89 control subjects, 124 patients with active lesions, and 48 with inactive lesions. The mean age of the adult participants was 32.3 (13.4) years. A response rate of &gt; 80% was obtained on the pediatric ISS (feasibility) and the responses correlated with the mEASI and cDLQI at baseline (P&lt;0.001) as an indicator of validity. An effect size of 0.988 was observed (sensitivity to change) along with a Chronbach &amp;#945; of 0.840 (internal consistency). A response rate of &gt;95% was obtained on the adult ISS (feasibility) and the responses correlated with the mEASI and DLQI at baseline (P&lt;0.001) as an indicator of validity. An effect size of 1.0 was observed (sensitivity to change) along with a Chronbach &amp;#945; of 0.825 (internal consistency). Conclusions: The Spanish version of the ISS is feasible, valid, sensitive to change, and displays good reliability based on internal consistency in both children and adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roset, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daudén, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Perez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: El cuestionario Itch Severity Scale (ISS) permite evaluar objetivamente la intensidad del prurito. El presente estudio pretende validar la versión española del cuestionario ISS en pacientes con dermatitis atópica (DA). Materiales y métodos: Estudio epidemiológico prospectivo, incluyendo pacientes con DA de más de un año de evolución y un grupo control sin DA. Los pacientes con DA se estratificaron según actividad de las lesiones (activas/inactivas), realizando una visita basal y dos de seguimiento (3 y 6 meses). Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas, relacionadas con la DA (incluyendo el modified Eczema Area and Severity Index o mEASI), enfermedades concomitantes y medidas del paciente como ISS, Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) o Children's DLQI (cDLQI). Resultados: Se incluyeron 207 pacientes pediátricos (2-17 años): 56 controles, 103 con lesiones activas y 48 inactivas, con una edad media (DE) de 8,1(4,0) años. Los adultos fueron 261 pacientes (&amp;#8805; 18 años): 89 controles, 124 con lesiones activas y 48 inactivas, con una edad media (DE) de 32,3 (13,4) años.ISS pediátricos: tasa de respuesta &gt; 80% (factibilidad), correlacionándose con mEASI y cDLQI en visita basal (p&lt;0,001) (validez), effect size de 0,988 (sensibilidad al cambio) y alpha de Cronbach de 0,840 (consistencia interna).ISS adultos: tasa de respuesta fue &gt; 95% (factibilidad), correlacionándose con mEASI y DLQI en visita basal (p&lt;0,001) (validez), effect size de 1,0 (sensibilidad al cambio), alpha de Cronbach de 0,825 (consistencia interna). Conclusiones: La versión española del ISS se mostró factible, válida, sensible al cambio y fiable en términos de consistencia interna, tanto en niños como en adultos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(7): 527-536, sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión española de la escala de intensidad del picor (Cuestionario Itch Severity Scale, ISS). Estudio PSEDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11976^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
