<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90309</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of leader&#146;s cultural competences with the cultural adap-tation inventory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this work consisted in construct and validates, in Spanish language, an inventory (Inventory of Cultural Adaptation -IAC-) to assess cultural variables to predict cultural adaptation of migrant leaders. The final version consisted of 15 items distributed in three dimensions: Opening to new experiences, Autonomy and independence, Acceptance of the cultural diversity. The obtained results allow affirming that is an instrument with satisfactory psychometric properties (reliability and validity). To obtain the validity evidence were used other instruments (Big Five - John, 1990; Intergrupal Anxiety- Stephan &amp; Stephan, 1985; Multi-cultural attitudes scale - Berry &amp; Kalin; Intercultural Leadership scale and Sociodemographic survey, designed ad hoc). Participated 374 leaders, 241 of them had leaded personnel outside their country, the stays outside had lasted in average 3,45 years (DE=4.99). On the other hand, participated 133 leaders, they didn&#146;t leaded personnel outside their country. All of them lived in Buenos Aires City and conurbano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Solano, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo consistió en construir y validar un inventario (Inventario de Adaptación Cultural &#150;IAC-) en idioma español para evaluar variables culturales predictoras de la adaptación de líderes migrantes. La versión final consta de 15 ítems distribuidos en tres dimensiones: Apertura a experiencias nuevas, Autonomía e independencia, Aceptación de la diversidad cultural. Los resultados obtenidos permiten afirmar que presenta propiedades psicométricas satisfactorias (fiabilidad y validez). Para lograr las evidencias de validez se utilizaron otros instrumentos (Big Five - John, 1990; Ansiedad intergrupal - Stephan &amp; Stephan, 1985; Escala de Actitudes multiculturales - Berry &amp; Kalin; Escala de Liderazgo Intercultural y Encuesta sociodemográfica, diseñadas ad hoc). Participaron 374 líderes, 241 habían liderado personal en el exterior en un promedio de 3,45 años (DE=4.99). Por otro lado, participaron 133 líderes que no habían liderado en el exterior. Todos eran residentes de la Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires y Conurbano Bonaerense (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(2): 507-517, mayo-ago. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90309</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de las competencias culturales de los líderes mediante el inventario de adaptación cultural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52938^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
