<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120197</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In spite of the reduction in the number of fatal traffic accidents in Spain over the last few years, there is, however, some room for improvement. This paper sets out to analyse the perception of blood alcohol level and ability to predict this and the objective and subjective ability to drive after alcohol intake in a meal setting. After a meal with free consumption of alcohol, the alcohol in the breath was measured, first asking about the estimated level and ability to drive. After each measurement, the participant was informed of his/her results. 34 persons participated. The average age (range) was 56 (28-85) years old. The average consumption was 6 (2-10) alcohol units. The average time to reach 0.25mg/l (the legal limit authorized for driving in Spain) was 83 (15-165) min. The correlation between consumption and time to reach 0.25 was r=0.42 (p=0.013). No statistical significance was found in the repeated differences between breathalyser value and subjective estimation; 22 persons declared some capability to drive in spite of there being an objective/ subjective level over 0.25. The capacity to predict the level of alcohol in the breath in repeated measurements was poor in spite of giving the real value in each determination. A high degree of incoherence/ imprudence for driving was observed, as over 50% of participants stated that they were able to drive although their alcohol level was objectively or subjectively over the limit in some determinations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codern, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Conxita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que la siniestralidad en carretera en España ha disminuido en los últimos años, queda un amplio margen de mejora. En este trabajo se pretende analizar la percepción de alcoholemia y la capacidad de predecirla tras medidas repetidas de la alcoholemia y la capacidad objetiva y subjetiva de conducción después de una ingesta de alcohol en el contexto de una comida. Tras una comida con ingesta libre de alcohol se procedió a la medición de la tasa de alcohol en aire espirado (AAE), preguntando antes por el nivel estimado y capacidad de conducción, después de cada medición se informaba del resultado obtenido. Participaron 34 individuos. La edad mediana fue de 56 (28-85) años. El consumo mediano 6 (2-10) unidades estándar de bebida. El tiempo mediano en alcanzar 0,25 mg/l (límite legal para conducir en España) fue de 83 (15-165) min. La correlación entre consumo de vino y tiempo hasta descender a 0,25, r=0,42 (p=0,013). No se halló significación estadística en las repetidas diferencias entre valor por alcoholímetro y estimación subjetiva; 22 individuos manifestaron en alguna determinación capacidad para conducir a pesar de un nivel objetivo o subjetivo&gt;0,25. Se observó poca capacidad de predicción para estimar la tasa de AAE en medidas repetidas a pesar de darse el valor real en cada determinación. Asimismo se considera alto grado de incoherencia/imprudencia para conducir, pues un porcentaje superior al 50% decían poder conducir a pesar de estar por encima de los límites legales de manera objetiva o subjetiva en alguna determinación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;39(1): 57-64, ene.-mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de alcoholemia y capacidad de predecirla tras la ingesta de vino. Actitud ante la conducción de vehículos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
