<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92437</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sterile non-traumatic corneal perforation treated with Tachosil®</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: An 83 year-old male reported to the emergency room with red eye and ocularpain. The slit-lamp examination showed a central corneal perforation of 1mm in diameter,with no associated infection or inflammatory process. The patient had no history of trauma.It was decided to apply a patch of Tachosil® at the site of corneal perforation. After 36 hoursof occlusion, a layer of fibrin covered the perforation, closing the defect. Successful healingof the corneal perforationwas observed in the follow-up, with no recurrences of the process.Conclusions: Tachosil® is collagen sponge with human fibrin and human thrombin used incardiological and neurosurgical surgery for haemostasis and the occlusion of vessels andmeninges. We present the first indication in ophthalmology of Tachosil® as an effectivealternative in the treatment of sterile non-traumatic corneal perforations less than 1.5mmin size(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montes-Mollón, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kubiak, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Herreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Parras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañones-Zafra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 83 años que acude a urgencias por dolor ocular en ojo derecho y enrojecimiento.En la exploración se objetivó una lesión perforante corneal central de 1mm dediámetro sin proceso infeccioso o inflamatorio concomitante ni antecedentes traumáticos.Procedimos al cierre urgente del defecto, aplicando un parche de Tachosil® sobre la zonaperforada. Tras 36 horas de oclusión un material fibrinoide ocluía la perforación cerrandoel defecto. En el posterior seguimiento no se presentaron recurrencias ni efectos adversospersistiendo el sellado completo del defecto.Conclusiones: Tachosil® es una esponja colágena de fibrinógeno y trombina humanos utilizadapara favorecer la hemostasia y la reparación tisular en cirugías cardíacas, urológicasy neuroquirúrgicas. Presentamos la primera indicación oftalmológica de Tachosil® comouna posible alternativa efectiva y de fácil uso en las perforaciones corneales no traumáticasestériles menores de 1,5mm(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(8): 264-266, ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92437</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perforación corneal no traumática estéril tratada con Tachosil®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24653^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12795^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27978^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
