<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97388</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic and cardiovascular risk factor control in a diabetic cohort. Four-year results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To assess control of blood glucose and other cardiovascular risk factors in diabetic patients monitored at an outpatient endocrinology clinic. To ascertain treatment used and its changes over time. Patients and methods A cohort of 424 randomly selected diabetic patients (both type 1 and type 2) was monitored from 2004 to 2008. Final cohort size was 343 patients. Data were collected about epidemiological characteristics, cardiovascular risk factors, chronic complications, glycemic, lipid and blood pressure control, and treatment at baseline and 4 years. Results After 4 years, the proportion of patients achieving glycosylated hemoglobin levels less than 7% remained stable (type 1: 18.5% in 2004 vs 21.7% in 2008, type 2: 26.6% vs 26.5%). The degree of achievement of lipid and blood pressure (BP) control levels increased in both groups. The complexity of treatment schemes used to achieve these results significantly increased. Conclusions Stabilization of glycemic control after 4 years of follow-up was a positive result, considering the long course of diabetes, progressive pancreatic function impairment, and complexity of our cohort. Treatment optimization significantly improved BP and lipid control in the study group(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marco Martínez, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Pazos, Alessandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamazares Iglesias, Ofelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre Marcos, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánovas Gaillemin, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Delgado, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Cortés, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Valorar el grado de control glucémico y del resto de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en una cohorte de pacientes diabéticos seguidos en consultas externas durante 4 años. Conocer el patrón de tratamiento utilizado y su evolución. Material y métodos Estudio de 424 pacientes diabéticos tanto tipo 1 (DM1) como tipo 2 (DM2), seleccionados aleatoriamente en 2004 y seguidos hasta 2008. La cohorte final fue de 343 pacientes. Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, complicaciones crónicas, datos de control glucémico, lipídico y tensional, así como de tratamiento al inicio y a los 4 años. Resultados Tras los 4 años, el porcentaje de pacientes que conseguían una hemoglobina glicada inferior a 7% se mantuvo estable (DM1 18,5 en 2004 frente a 21,7% en 2008 y DM2 26,6 frente a 26,5%). En ambos tipos de diabetes se incrementó de forma significativa el grado de consecución de objetivos de control lipídico y tensional. Para conseguir estos resultados las pautas de tratamiento se complicaron de manera significativa. Conclusiones La estabilización del control glucémico objetivada tras 4 años de seguimiento es un resultado positivo, considerando el largo tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad, el deterioro progresivo de la función pancreática y la complejidad de esta cohorte. Gracias a la optimización de los tratamientos utilizados, han mejorado de forma significativa el control tensional y lipídico del grupo estudiado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;59(2): 117-124, feb. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control metabólico y de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en una cohorte de pacientes con diabetes mellitus. Resultados a los 4 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
