<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76470</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Content validity of a structured behavioral interview</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper reports on an empirical study of the content validity of a Structured Behavioural Interview (SBI). The study was based on 11 experts&#146; ratings, using a method proposed by Lawshe (1975). A significant Content Validity Ratio (CVR) was found for 4 out of 14 questions and for 4 out of 10 general dimensions. A Content Validity Index (CVI) of.86 was obtained for the significant dimensions as a whole and of .68 for the questions. Additionally, reliability was estimated by using the coefficient of agreement between raters(6 or 12) and the result was .78, similar to the .75 value obtained in meta-analyses by Conway, Jako and Goodman (1995) and by Salgado and Moscoso (1995) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Choragwicka, Beata</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moscoso, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta un examen empírico de la validez de contenido de una Entrevista Conductual Estructurada (ECE), realizado a partir de las valoraciones de un panel de 11expertos, utilizando el método sugerido por Lawshe (1975). Se encontró la Razón de Validez de Contenido (RVC) significativa para 4 de las 14 preguntas y 4 de las 10 dimensiones.El Índice de Validez de Contenido (IVC) hallado para las dimensiones significativas era de.86 y para las preguntas significativas .68. También se estimó la fiabilidad del instrumento mediante un coeficiente de acuerdo entre 6 ó 12 evaluadores, obteniendo un valor promedio de .78, semejante al resultado .75 proveniente de los meta-análisis de Conway, Jako yGoodman (1995) y de Salgado y Moscoso (1995) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);23(1): 75-92, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez de contenido de una entrevista conductual estructurada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10752^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1084</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
