<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87976</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of cardiovascular risk in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The population aged 65 years or more is set to increase in the next few years, especially in Spain and elsewhere in Europe. Cardiovascular diseases (CVD) are the main cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide as well as in Spain. Most studies on vascular risk factors (VRF) have been performed in younger persons, usually aged less than 70 years and without associated pathologic conditions. Patients with pluripathologies are those with multiple chronic diseases and advanced age (a mean of 78 years) in whom the most significant diseases are cardiovascular, with several VRF, leading to high mortality. Strategies to reduce morbidity and mortality in this age group are required(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cantero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La población de 65 años o más se incrementará en las próximas décadas, sobre todo en España y resto de Europa. Las enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV) representan la principal causa de morbilidad y mortalidad en el mundo y también en nuestro país. La mayoría de estudios realizados sobre factores de riesgo vascular (FRV) se han hecho en personas más jóvenes, en general de menos de 70 años y sin otras condiciones patológicas asociadas. Los pacientes pluripatológicos son personas con múltiples patologías crónicas y edad avanzada, media de edad de 78 años, en los que las enfermedades más determinantes son las cardiovasculares, presentando varios FRV y ECV, con una elevada mortalidad. Hay que diseñar estrategias que disminuyan la morbimortalidad también en este grupo de edad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(supl.1): 2-7, mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del riesgo cardiovascular en el anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9265^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9265^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
