<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037251</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality on the surgical waiting list: a sentinel indicator</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To quantify and analyze mortality in patients on the Surgery Waiting List (SWL) and to evaluate its utility as a sentinel indicator. Material and method: A descriptive study was performed in which patients deleted from the SWL after surgery or death at the Hospital Clínico Universitario de Zaragoza (Spain) from 1999-2002 were compared. In the comparison of variables the Chi-square test, Student's t-test and the Mann-Whitney U test were used. Statistical significance was set at P¾.05. Results: Of 31,396 patients studied, 134 (0.43%) died while on the SWL. Deceased patients were older (74.5 ± 9.6) than those who underwent surgery (57.1 ± 19.5; P&lt;.000) and 70% were male (P&lt;.000). Sixty-five percent of the deceased were surgical priorities (P =.02). No differences were found in the mean waiting time. Among the deceased, the most common diagnoses for inclusion on the SWL were eye-related diseases (40.2%), neoplasms (17.9%) and genitourinary disorders (14.1%). A total of 50.7% of deaths occurred in hospital. In 22% of the patients the diagnoses for inclusion on the SWL and discharge details were inter-related. Conclusions: Four out of every 1,000 patients died while on the SWL, particularly elderly men scheduled as surgical priorities. Due to its low frequency (2 to 3 cases per month) and serious consequences, as well as the social alarm it produces, this indicator could be used as a sentinel event by hospital mortality committees</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castán-Ruizc, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrasa-Villara, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Majánc, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Broto-Civerab, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Gascad, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astier-Peñad, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Cuantificar y analizar la mortalidad de los pacientes en lista de espera quirúrgica (LEQ) y evaluar su utilidad como indicador centinela. Material y método: Estudio descriptivo en el que se comparó a los pacientes que salieron por intervención o fallecimiento de la LEQ del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Zaragoza entre los años 1999 y 2002. En la comparación de variables se utilizaron las pruebas de la *2, la t de Student y la U de Mann-Whitney. La significación estadística se estableció con una p ¾ 0,05. Resultados: De los 31.396 pacientes estudiados, 134 (0,43%) habían fallecido en la LEQ. Los fallecidos eran de más edad (74,5 ± 9,6 años) que los intervenidos (57,1 ± 19,5 años; p &lt; 0,000) y en el 70%, varones (p &lt; 0,000). El 65% de los fallecidos tenía una indicación quirúrgica de carácter preferente (p = 0,02). No había diferencias en la espera media. Los diagnósticos de inclusión más frecuentes en LEQ de los fallecidos eran los procesos oculares (40,2%), las neoplasias (17,9%) y las enfermedades genitourinarias (14,1%). El 50,7% de los fallecimientos ocurrió en el propio hospital y en un 22% de los casos los diagnósticos de inclusión en LEQ y del alta estaban relacionados. Conclusiones: Cuatro de cada 1.000 pacientes fallecen mientras esperan en LEQ, sobre todo varones de edad avanzada y en intervenciones de carácter preferente. Por su escaso número (2-3 casos/mes), graves consecuencias y alarma social, este indicador podría ser utilizado como suceso centinela por las comisiones de mortalidad de los hospitales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(4): 199-203, jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad en lista de espera quirúrgica: un indicador centinela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
