<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147747</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations of the Spanish Paediatric Endocrinology Society Working Group on Obesity on eating habits for the prevention of obesity and cardiovascular risk factors in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Childhood obesity is associated with a high risk of cardiovascular disease and early mortality. This paper summarises the currently available evidence on the implications of dietary factors on the development and prevention of obesity in paediatric patients. Evidence-based recommendations are: promote the consumption of slowly absorbed carbohydrates and reduce those with a high-glycaemic-index, avoid intake of sugar-sweetened beverages. Fat may provide up to 30-35% of the daily energy intake and saturated fat should provide no more than 10% of daily energy intake; reduce cholesterol intake, avoid formula milk with a high protein content during the first year; promote higher fibre content in the diet, reduce sodium intake, and have at least four meals a day, avoiding regular consumption of fast food and snacks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vela Desojo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliu Rovira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Lozano, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo Atance, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Campos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bahíllo Curieses, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lechuga-Sancho, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad infantil determina un riesgo elevado de enfermedad cardiovascular. Este artículo realiza una actualización sobre el papel que los factores dietéticos tienen sobre el desarrollo y la prevención de la obesidad en este grupo de edad. Según la evidencia científica, las recomendaciones recogidas son: promover el consumo de hidratos de carbono de absorción lenta y disminuir aquellos con índice glucémico alto, evitar el consumo de bebidas azucaradas, limitar el consumo de grasas a un 30% de las calorías totales diarias y el de grasas saturadas a un 7-10%, reducir la ingesta de colesterol, evitar durante el primer año las fórmulas con alto contenido proteico, aumentar la ingesta de fibra, reducir el aporte de sodio y realizar al menos 4 comidas al día evitando el consumo regular de comida rápida y de snacks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(3): 178.e1-178.e7, mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones del Grupo de Trabajo de Obesidad de la Sociedad Española de Endocrinología Pediátrica sobre hábitos de alimentación para la prevención de la obesidad y los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4786^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4786^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51826^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
