<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134487</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When routine D-J impalntation necessary during PNL?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We investigated the characteristics of patients who underwent Double-J catheter (D-J) implantation, the risk factors for prolonged urine leakage (PUL), and prediction of patients who require medical treatment. Methods: The data of 535 adult patients who underwent PNL due to kidney stone disease between January 2005 and December 2011 in our clinic were analyzed retrospectively. Patients were divided into 2 groups: Group 1 (n=77) (14.39%) included patients with Double-J catheter due to prolonged (&gt; 24 h) urinary leakage and Group 2 (n=458) (85.61%) patients without urinary leakage. Results: The mean stone burden was 951.94 ± 539.09 mm2 in Group 1, and 676.35 ± 296.65 mm2 in Group 2 (p&lt;0.05). DJ catheter was implanted in 11.33% of the patients with stone burden below 1000 mm2 versus in 51.21% of the patients with stone burden above 1000 mm2. In Group 1, the number of patients with two  or more accesses performed was 18.18%, whereas in Group 2 it was 8.5% (p &lt;0.05). Among all patients, DJ implantation was performed in 13.07 % of patients with a single access versus 26.41% of patients with two or more accesses. Also, DJ catheter was implanted in 41.46% of patients with residual stones versus 12.14% of stone-free patients. Three patients with stone burden above 1000 mm2, two or more accesses, and residual stone, all of them required DJ implantation. Conclusion: DJ implantation due to PUL had approximately 5-fold increase stone burden above 1000 mm2, 2-fold increase in patients undergoing two or more access and 3-fold increase in patients with residual stones. Therefore, we think that the D-J implantation is highly advisable in case of a stone load above 1000 mm2, two or more accesses, and in patients with residual stones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Demirbag, Asaf</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seckiner, Ilker</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erturhan, Sakip M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erbagci, Ahmet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulut, Ersan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayrak, Omer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigamos las características de los pacientes sometidos a colocación de catéter doble J (DJ), los factores de riesgo de fuga urinaria prolongada y la predicción de qué pacientes requieren tratamiento medico. Métodos: Analizamos retrospectivamente los datos de 535 pacientes adultos sometidos a nefrolitectomía percutanea (NLPC) entre Enero del 2005 y Diciembre del 2011 en nuestra clínica. Los pacientes fueron divididos en dos grupos: El Grupo 1(n=77) (14,39%) incluía pacientes con catéter doble J debido a fuga de orina prolongada (&gt;24h) y el Grupo 2 (n=458) (85.61%) pacientes sin fuga urinaria. Resultados: La carga litiásica media fue de 951.94 ± 539.09 mm2 en el Grupo 1, y 676.35 ±296.65 mm2 en el Grupo 2 p&lt;0.05). Se colocó catéter doble J en el 11,33% de los pacientes con una carga litiásica menor de 1000 mm2 frente al 51,21% de los pacientes con una carga superior a 1000 mm2. En el Grupo 1, el número de pacientes con dos o más accesos realizados fue de 18,18%, mientras que en el grupo 2 el 8,5% (p &lt;0.05). De todos los pacientes, se colocó DJ en el 13,07% con un único acceso en comparación con el 26,41 de los pacientes con dos o más accesos. También se colocó DJ en el 41,46% de los pacientes con litiasis residual frente al 12,14% de los pacientes sin cálculos residuales. Tres pacientes con los tres factores, una carga residual mayor de 1000 mm2, dos o más accesos y cálculos residuales requirieron colocación de DJ. Conclusiones: La colocación de un catéter doble J debido a la fuga urinaria prolongada es unas 5 veces más frecuente en pacientes con una carga litiásica superior a 1000 mm2, 2 veces en pacientes sometidos a dos ó más accesos y 3 veces en pacientes con cálculos residuales. Por lo tanto, pensamos que la colocación del DJ es altamente aconsejable en caso de carga litiásica superior a 1000 mm2, dos o más accesos y en el paciente con cálculos residuales. (Artículo en inglés) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(2): 172-177, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuándo es necesaria la colocación rutinaria de catéter doble J durante la efrolitectomía percutánea?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
