<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141344</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protein malnutrition incidence comparison after gastric bypass versus biliopancreatic diversion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: bariatric surgery is widely employed nowadays. Nutritional complications following malabsorptive bariatric surgery are common. Objectives: to compare protein malnutrition incidence, the amount of protein intake and the influence of various risk factors in patients undergoing Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB) and biliopancreatic diversion (BPD). Methods: retrospective study comparing the development of hypoalbuminemia in 92 patients undergoing BPD and 121 RYGB, before surgery and 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months after it. Protein intake was estimated by serum prealbumin. The influence of prior body mass index (BMI), age and sex was analyzed. Results: hypoprealbuminemia was found in around 40% of patients 3 months after both procedures, decreasing to about 10% after 2 years of surgery. Hypoalbuminemia incidence was close to 20% in the first post-surgery year in BPD, persisting in 10-15% of cases thereafter. After RYGB, hypoalbuminemia incidence was lower (5-9% in all postoperative follow-up measurements). During the first year after surgery, hypoalbuminemia was more frequent after BPD than after RYGB (at the 3rd month (OR:3.9; p=0.006; 95%CI:1.5-10.4), 6th (OR:5.0; p=0.002; 95% CI:1.8-13.8), and at the 12th month (OR:4.4;p=0.007;95%;CI:1.5-12.8)), but not after the first year. A higher preoperative BMI favored it (OR: 1.03; p=0.046; 95% CI:1-1.06), as well as greater age during the first 6 months. Conclusion: Patients with BPD had a higher risk for hypoproteinemia than those undergoing RYGB, especially during the first year post-surgery. Higher preoperative BMI, and age (in the short-term period) could have a significant inverse relation to hypoproteinemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez Llanos, José Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bray, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina González, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón Lesmes, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Esteban, Basilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Ferrer, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sala-Walther, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la cirugía bariátrica es muy empleada actualmente y en las malabsortivas, las complicaciones nutricionales son habituales. Objetivos: comparar la incidencia de malnutrición proteica e ingesta estimada de proteínas en pacientes intervenidos de bypass gástrico en Y-de-Roux (BGYR) y derivación biliopancreática (DBP), y la influencia de algunos factores de riesgo. Métodos: estudio restrospectivo comparando el desarrollo de hipoalbuminemia en 92 pacientes intervenidos mediante DBP y 121 de DBP (prequirúrgico, a los 3, 6, 12, 18 y 24 meses postquirúrgicos). La ingesta proteica se estimó mediante prealbúmina. Se evaluó la influencia del índice de masa corporal (IMC) previo, la edad y el sexo. Resultados: se encontró hipoprealbuminemia en torno al 40% de los pacientes a los 3 meses tras ambas técnicas, disminuyendo hasta el 10% a los dos años. La incidencia de hipoalbuminemia fue cercana al 20% durante el primer año tras DBP, persistiendo posteriormente en un 10-15% de los casos. Tras el BGYR, dicha incidencia fue menor (5-9% en todos los momentos). Así, durante el primer año postquirúrgico la hipoalbuminemia fue más frecuente tras DBP [3 meses: (OR:3,9;p=0,006; 95%CI:1,5- 10,4), 6 meses (OR:5,0; p=0,002; 95% CI:1,8-13,8), y al año (OR:4,4;p=0,007;95%;CI:1,5-12,8)], pero no así después. Un mayor IMC prequirúrgico favoreció la inicidencia de hipoalbuminemia (OR:1,03; p=0,046; 95% CI:1-1,06), así como una mayor edad a los 6 meses postquirúrgicos. Conclusión: los pacientes intervenidos mediante DBP tuvieron mayor riesgo de presentar hipoproteinemia que tras BGYR, especialmente durante el primer año postquirúrgico. Un mayor IMC postquirúrgico y la edad (a los 6 meses) podrían favorecer la aparición de hipoproteinemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(1): 80-86, jul. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la incidencia de malnutrición proteica tras bypass gástrico versus derivación biliopancreática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16599^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7198^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24537^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
