<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108616</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strategies to improve Down syndrome screening program: the experience at Dexeus Institut (Barcelona)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the improvement in the effectiveness of trisomy 21 (T21) screening according to the different strategies employed. Material and methods. An early T21 screening was performed on all single pregnancies from October 2003 to November 2009, combining maternal age, the measurement of nuchal translucency (NT), and the determination of the biochemical markers, pregnancy- associated plasma protein A (PAPP-A) and free human chorionic gonadotropin (&amp;#946;-hCG). Measurement of the ductus venosus pulsatility index (DVPI) has been included in the assessment of the risk index since October 2008. The biochemical parameters were measured using the Kryptor analyser, in a one time (analytical determinations and ultrasound on the same day) or a two time strategy (analytical determinations between 2 and 4 weeks prior to the measurement of NT). The calculation of the combined T21 risk index was performed using the program marketed by SsdwLab5-Software. Results. A total of 13,132 pregnancies were included, with 61 cases of T21. Distribution curves of the biochemical and ultrasound parameters are described. Different strategies have been introduced since 2003 with the purpose of improving the effectiveness of Down's syndrome (DS) screening. These have led to an improvement in the detection rate (DR) (84.4% to 100%), and a reduction in the false positive rate (FPR) (5.8% to 3.6%). Assuming a DR of 85%, the FPR have significantly decreased from 7.6% to 1.3%. Conclusions. The effectiveness of SD screening improves when we use our own distribution curves of the biochemical parameters available, we periodically update their values, when we move from one to two-time screening strategy, and incorporate the DVPI as a first line parameter in the assessment of the risk index. We suggest including these strategies in the standard T21 screening policies in experienced centres in order to reduce unnecessary invasive tests(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarria Tellería, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comas Gabriel, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabrià Rius, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. evaluar la mejora en la efectividad del cribado de trisomía 21 (T21) desde la implementación del programa y en función de las distintas estrategias empleadas. Material y métodos. hemos realizado un cribado temprano de T21 en todas las gestaciones únicas atendidas en nuestro centro desde octubre del 2003 hasta noviembre del 2009, combinando la edad materna, la medición de la translucencia nucal (TN) y la determinación de los marcadores bioquímicos de proteína plasmática A asociada al embarazo (PAPP-A) y &amp;#946;-gonadotropina coriónica humana libre (&amp;#946;-hCG). Desde octubre de 2008 se ha incorporado la medición del índice de pulsatilidad del ductus venoso (IPDV) en el cálculo del índice de riesgo. Los parámetros bioquímicos se han determinado mediante el analizador Kryptor, en una estrategia en un tiempo (determinación analítica y ecográfica el mismo día) o en dos tiempos (determinación analítica entre 2 y 4 semanas previas a la medición de la TN). El cálculo del índice de riesgo combinado de T21 se ha efectuado mediante el programa comercializado SsdwLab5-Software. Resultados. se incluye un total de 13.132 gestaciones, con 61 casos de T21. Se describen las curvas propias de normalidad de parámetros bioquímicos y ecográficos. Desde el año 2003 se han ido incorporando diferentes estrategias a fin de mejorar la efectividad del cribado de síndrome de Down (SD), las cuales permiten observar una mejoría de la tasa de detección (TD) (84,4 frente a 100%) y una reducción de la tasa de falsos positivos (TFP) (5,8 frente a 3,6%). Asumiendo una TD del 85%, la TFP desciende significativamente del 7,6 al 1,3%. Conclusiones. nuestra experiencia refleja una efectividad mayor del cribado de SD si disponemos de curvas propias de normalidad de los parámetros bioquímicos, actualizamos periódicamente sus valores de normalidad, realizamos el cribado en una estrategia en dos tiempos e incorporamos el valor del IPDV como parámetro de primera línea en el cálculo del índice de riesgo. Sugerimos incorporar estas estrategias en el cribado estándar de T21 en centros con experiencia con el fin de reducir las pruebas invasivas innecesarias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);22(2): 41-50, abr.-jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias para mejorar el cribado de síndrome de Down: experiencia en el Instituto Dexeus (Barcelona)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11686</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
