<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119193</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of early rehabilitation of the corpus cavernosum after radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Primary: to evaluate the importance of early rehabilitation of the corpus cavernosum on erectile function after radical prostatectomy. Secondary: to analyse the factors associated with better response. Material and method: Retrospective study in patients treated with intracavernous injections after radical prostatectomy between 1 January 2006 and 31 December 2008. We included patients lacking a history of erectile dysfunction prior to surgery, not responding to phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors. All patients underwent colour echo-doppler after injection of prostaglandin E1 10-20 mg. The outcomes of these 2 groups were then compared according to how early rehabilitation began after surgery (early, &lt; 6 months, or late, &gt; 6 months). Results: There were 82 patients included in the study. In the multivariate analysis, predictive factors of good response to treatment were: early onset of rehabilitation (OR: 0.06; 95% CI: 0.014-0.26), higher peak systolic velocity during the test (OR: 1.01; 95% CI: 1.01-1.1) and favourable histopathological stage (OR: 0.15; 95% CI 95%: 0.036-0.6). The colour echo-doppler procedure after prostaglandin E1 injection showed abnormal values more frequently in the lateonset than in the early group (89.5% [n = 34] vs. 65.9% [n = 29]; P = .01). Corporal veno-occlusive dysfunction was presented by 40.2% (n = 33) of subjects, with the late-onset group presenting higher values (5.53 ± 1.4 cm/sec) than the early group (4.75 ± 1.03 cm/sec) (P = .005). The presence of functional erections at 18 months&#146; follow-up was higher in the early onset group (P &lt; .001). Conclusions: According to this study, early erectile dysfunction rehabilitation after radical prostatectomy achieves better results than late rehabilitation in patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campos-Hernández, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Castro, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena-Tapia, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-López, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco-Valiente, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-García, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Primario: evaluar la importancia de una rehabilitación precoz de los cuerpos cavernosos sobre la función eréctil tras prostatectomía radical. Secundario: analizar los factores asociados a una mejor respuesta. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo en pacientes tratados con inyecciones intracavernosas tras prostatectomía radical entre el 1 de enero de 2006 y el 31 de diciembre de 2008. Se incluyeron enfermos sin antecedentes de disfunción eréctil previa a la cirugía, no respondedores a inhibidores de la 5-fosfodiesterasa. En todos se realizó ecodoppler color tras inyección de prostaglandina E1 10-20 mg. Se compararon 2 grupos en función de la precocidad del inicio de la rehabilitación tras la cirugía (precoz, &lt; 6 meses, o tardía, &gt; 6 meses). Resultados: Se incluyeron 82 pacientes. En el análisis multivariante, fueron factores predictores de buena respuesta al tratamiento: inicio precoz de la rehabilitación (OR: 0,06; IC 95%: 0,014- 0,26), mayor velocidad pico sistólica durante el test (OR: 1,01; IC 95%: 1,01-1,1) y estadio anatomopatológico favorable (OR: 0,15; IC 95%: 0,036-0,6). El ecodoppler color tras inyección de prostaglandina E1 presentó valores anormales con mayor frecuencia en el grupo de inicio tardío frente al precoz (89,5% [n = 34] vs. 65,9% [n = 29]; p = 0,01). El 40,2% (n = 33) de los sujetos presentaron fracaso del mecanismo corporovenooclusivo, presentando valores más elevados el grupo de inicio tardío (5,53 ± 1,4 cm/seg) frente al precoz (4,75 ±1,03 cm/seg) (p = 0,005). La presencia de erecciones funcionales a los 18 meses del seguimiento fue mayor en el grupo de inicio precoz (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: Según el presente estudio, en pacientes tras prostatectomía radical la rehabilitación farmacológica precoz de la erección presenta mejores resultados comparada con la tardía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 4-9, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la rehabilitación precoz de los cuerpos cavernosos tras prostatectomía radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11891^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10919^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
