<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151678</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric prediction of penitentiary recidivism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Attempts to predict prison recidivism based on the personality have not been very successful. This study aims to provide data on recidivism prediction based on the scores on a personality questionnaire. For this purpose, a predictive model combining the actuarial procedure with a posteriori probability was developed, consisting of the probabilistic calculation of the effective verification of the event once it has already occurred. Method: Cuestionario de Personalidad Situacional (CPS; Fernández, Seisdedos, &amp; Mielgo, 1998) was applied to 978 male inmates classified as recidivists or non-recidivists. Results: High predictive power was achieved, with the area under the curve (AUC) of 0.85 (p &lt;.001; Se = 0.012; 95% CI [0.826, 0.873]. The answers to the CPS items made it possible to properly discriminate 77.3% of the participants. Conclusions: These data indicate the important role of the personality as a key factor in understanding delinquency and predicting recidivism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baños Rivera, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina García, Pedro Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: los intentos para predecir la reincidencia penitenciaria basándose en la personalidad no han tenido mucho éxito. Este trabajo tiene como objetivo ofrecer datos sobre la predicción de la reincidencia a partir de las puntuaciones en un cuestionario de personalidad. Método: se aplicó el Cuestionario de Personalidad Situacional (CPS; Fernández, Seisdedos y Mielgo, 1998) a 978 reclusos varones clasificados como reincidentes o no reincidentes y se elaboró un modelo predictivo combinando el procedimiento actuarial con el concepto de probabilidad a posteriori, consistente en realizar cálculo probabilístico a partir de la constatación efectiva del suceso una vez ya se ha producido. Resultados: se logró un elevado poder predictivo, siendo el área bajo la curva (AUC) de 0.85 (p&lt;0.001; Se = 0.012; 95% IC [0.826, 0.873]. Las respuestas a los ítems del CPS permitieron discriminar adecuadamente al 77,3% de los participantes. Conclusiones: estos datos indican el papel importante de la personalidad como factor clave para entender la delincuencia y predecir la reincidencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);28(2): 194-200, mayo 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predicción psicométrica de la reincidencia penitenciaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56074^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53813^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
