<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159875</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PHQ-2 as frst screening insstrument of prenatal depression in primary healtg care, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Prenatal depression is a major public health problem that is barely treated. Based on existing literature, depression during this period is associated with negative consequences for the mother and the baby. Therefore it is important to make an adequate screening in this population. The aim of this study was to determine the discriminant validity and cut-off of the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-2) as a screening tool to identify the depression in pregnant women living in Spain. Method: The sample included 1,019 female participants, aged between 19 and 45 years, who participated voluntarily, and received prenatal care during the first trimester. Participants completed a sociodemographic questionnaire, PHQ-2 and PHQ-9. The research has been developed within the Obstetrics and Gynecology department at two public hospitals in two different Spanish Regions. The research was conducted between 2014 and 2016 performing a ROC curve analysis to determine the discriminative capacity and cut-off for PHQ-2. Results: 11,1 % out of 1019 participants were diagnosed with depression. The area under the curve of PHQ-2 was 0,84 p &lt;0,001. With the cutoff 2 the sensitivity and specificity of 85,4 % and 79,5% respectively. Conclusions: A score &amp;#8805;2 is an appropriate cut-off in PHQ-2 to detect depression during pregnancy. The use of PHQ-2 could precede PHQ-9 as a brief screening tool for antenatal depression in obstetric settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Méndez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares Crespo, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Balbuena, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelao Legazpi, Pilar Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Muñoz, María de la Fe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Barrientos, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Le, Huynh-Nhu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La depresión prenatal es un importante problema de salud pública que apenas recibe tratamiento. La depresión durante este período está asociada con consecuencias negativas tanto para la madre como para el bebé. Por ello, es importante realizar un cribado adecuado en mujeres embarazadas. El objetivo del presente estudio fue conocer la capacidad discriminativa y el punto de corte del cuestionario PHQ-2 como primer instrumento de cribado para identificar la depresión en mujeres embarazadas que viven en España. Método: Participaron voluntariamente 1.019 mujeres, de edad comprendida entre los 19 y los 45 años, que acudieron a revisión obstétrica en el primer trimestre del embarazo. Las participantes completaron un cuestionario sociodemográfico y los cuestionarios PHQ9 y PHQ2. La investigación fue desarrollada en dos hospitales públicos de dos comunidades autónomas diferentes. Se llevó a cabo entre los años 2014 y 2016. Se realizó un análisis con curva ROC para determinar la capacidad discriminativa y el punto de corte del PHQ-2. Resultados: De las 1.019 participantes el 11,1% fueron diagnosticadas de depresión. El área bajo la curva del PHQ2 fue de 0,84 p&lt;0,001. Con el punto de corte de 2 la sensibilidad y especificidad fueron de 85,4% y 79,5% respectivamente. Conclusiones: La puntuación de corte &amp;#8805;2 es adecuada para la discriminación de la depresión durante el embarazo mediante el cuestionario PHQ2 y podría servir como cribado previo al PHQ-9 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;91: 0-0, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PHQ-2 como primer instrumento de cribado de la depresión prenatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
