<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12947</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The FACES II in the evaluation of family cohesion and adaptability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study contrasts the cohesion and adaptabilty of 31 Spanish, 20 Anglo-Australian, and 30 Spanish inmigrant families. FACES II was used to measure the ideal and perceived cohesion and adaptability of three family members (father, mother, and one child) in the 81 family sample. Results show that the inmigrant families adapted their ideas and practices selectively: like Spanish families, they maintained higher levels of ideal adaptability than the Anglo-Australian families, yet their ideal and perceived cohesion was similar to the Anglo-Australian families. Data showed that there are significant similarities across cultures in the perception of actual family cohesion and adaptability, while there are significant differences across cultures in ideal family cohesion and adaptability. These results imply that cross-cultural psychology researchers should consider both similarities and differences between cultures and families, and that change in immigrant families ideals and practices occurs at varying rates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Larrosa, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio contrasta la cohesión y la adaptabilidad de 31 familias españolas, 20 anglo-australianas y 30 familias españolas emigrantes en Australia. El FACES 11 se utilizó para medir la cohesión y la adaptabilidad percibida e ideal de tres miembros de la familia (madre, padre y un hijo/a) en la muestra de 81 familias. Los resultados indican que las familias emigrantes adaptaron sus ideas y prácticas selectivamente: al igual que las familias españolas, mantuvieron unos ideales de adaptabilidad más elevados que las familias anglo-australianas. Los datos muestran que existen semejanzas significativas entre las culturas en la percepción de la cohesión y adaptabilidad actual de las familias, mientras que se dan diferencias significativas entre las culturas en los ideales de cohesión y adaptabilidad familiar. Estos resultados implican que la psicología transcultural debería considerar que hay semejanzas y diferencias entre las culturas y las familias, así como que el cambio en los ideales y prácticas de las familias emigrantes se produce a diferentes niveles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(1): 159-166, ene. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El FACES II en la evaluación de la cohesión y la adaptabilidad familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3490</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
