<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77433</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Young patient with eyelid Merkel carcinoma: Mohs microsurgery versus exenteration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: We present the case of a 47-year-oldfemale suffering from progeria who developed aneyelid Merkel cell carcinoma (MCC) followingcyclosporine treatment for a corneal transplant. Sheunderwent excision of the lesion by Mohs micrographicsurgery (MMS) and received adjuvant treatmentwith radiotherapy. Later she had a recurrenttumour for which a wide excision with orbital exenterationwas performed. The patient was fit and wellat the 24-month follow-up.Discussion: MCC is an aggressive tumour that hasa larger incidence in elderly people, women andimmunosuppressed patients. Our approach with thepatient must be global, avoiding risk factors in predisposedsubjects. MMS seems unsuitable for thetreatment of MCC; if tumour recurrence occurs awide resection should be performed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Alonso, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio-García, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Prieto, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de una pacientede 47 años afecta de progeria que después de tratamientocon ciclosporina por trasplante corneal presentócarcinoma de Merkel (MCC) palpebral. Trasexéresis completa mediante cirugía de Mohs(MMS) y tratamiento adyuvante con radioterapia,recidivó y fue necesario realizar exenteración orbitaria.La paciente se encuentra asintomática tras 24meses de seguimiento.Discusión: El MCC es un tumor agresivo conmayor incidencia en ancianos, mujeres e inmunodeprimidos.Nuestra visión del enfermo debe ser globalevitando añadir factores de riesgo a pacientes yapredispuestos. La MMS parece desaconsejada en eltratamiento del MCC, debiendo realizar una excisiónradical si se produce recidiva(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(11): 581-584, nov. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77433</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente joven con carcinoma de Merkel palpebral: microcirugía de Mohs versus exenteración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23573^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
