<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61288</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Colorectal adenomas: postpolypectomy surveillance strategies and chemoprevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Colorectal adenomas are the most fully characterized premalignantlesions in the development of colorectal cancer. Consequently,the identification and resolution of these lesions, aswell as the follow-up of affected patients, are a priority in theprevention of this neoplasm. The studies presented in the annualmeeting of the American Gastroenterological Association2008 show that the results of current surveillance strategiescan be improved with a view to reducing the rate ofinterval neoplasia. Improvement of these results includes optimizationof the endoscopic technique (colonic preparation,cecal intubation, withdrawal time, etc.) as well as the incorporationof new diagnostic methods and the possible administrationof chemopreventive drugs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castells, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los adenomas colorrectales constituyen la lesión premalignamejor caracterizada en el desarrollo del cáncer colorrectal. Poreste motivo, la identificación y la resección de estas lesiones y elseguimiento de los pacientes que las han presentado son objetivosfundamentales en la prevención de esta neoplasia. Los estudiospresentados en el congreso de la American GastroenterologicalAssociation demuestran que es posible mejorar losresultados obtenidos con las estrategias de vigilancia actualescon el fin de disminuir la tasa de neoplasias de intervalo. La mejorade estos resultados incluye la optimización de la técnica endoscópica(preparación colónica, intubación cecal, tiempo deretirada, etc.), así como la incorporación de nuevas modalidadesdiagnósticas y la posible administración de fármacos quimiopreventivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;31(supl.4): 57-61, oct. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenomas colorrectales: estrategias de vigilancia tras polipectomía y quimioprevención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
