<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66243</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender differences during landings after jumping</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analyse, in a population of applicants to a Faculty of Sports Sciences, the kinetics of the push off, flight and Lansing phases in a jump test, and to study the differences between men and women. Methodology: The jumps of 180 applicants to a faculty of Sports Sciences (132 men, mean age: 19.8+/-3.0 years, and 48 women, mean age: 19.6+/-3.3 years) were recorded with a Quattro Jump Kistler force plate. Vertical ground reaction forces and the position of the centre of gravity in a counter movement jump were analysed. Results: The men´s group reached higher heights of the centre gravity during the flight phase (men= 35.77+/-4.55 cm, women = 26.08+/-3.33 cm; p&lt;0.001) and greater vertical forces in the second peak of the landing phase (F2) (men = 7.41+/-2.20 BW, women = 5.72+/-1.82 BW; p&lt;0.001) (BW = body weight). Women showed greater vertical displacement of the centre of gravity during the landing phase (men = 10.21+/-2.26% of subject´s height, women = 10.84+/-2.21%; p&lt;0.05). The values of F2 in the population studied have been greater than those found in other studies performed with higher landing heights, but with the aim of maximal softening. Conclusion: The results of the present study support the necessity of prophylactic interventions to teach proper landing techniques among specific populations. The greater values of F2 in the men´s group could have be caused by the higher landing heights and the shorter vertical displacement of the centre of gravity during the landing phase, compared to the women´s group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegre, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abián, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, Amador J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar, en una población de aspirantes al ingreso en una Facultad de Ciencias del Deporte, la cinética de la batida, vuelo y amortiguación de sus saltos y estudiar las diferencias entre los subgrupos de hombres y mujeres. Metodología: Se analizaron los saltos de 180 sujetos, 132 eran hombres (edad= 19.8+/-3.0 años) y 48 mujeres (edad = 19.6+/-3.3 años). Se utilizó una plataforma de fuerzas Quattro Jump de Kistler. Se analizaron las fuerzas de reacción verticales y la posición del centro de gravedad en un salto con contramovimiento. Resultados: Los hombres lograron mayores alturas del centro de gravedad en el vuelo (hombres = 35.77+/-4.55 cm, mujeres = 26.08+/- 3.33 cm; p&lt;0.001) y mayores segundos picos de fuerza en la amortiguación (F2) (hombres = 7.41+/-2.20 BW, mujeres = 5.72+/-1.82 BW; p&lt;0.001) (BW = veces el peso corporal). Las mujeres mostraron un mayor recorrido del centro de gravedad durante la amortiguación (hombres = 10.21+/-2.26%, mujeres =10.84+/-2.21%; p&lt;0.05). Los valores obtenidos en F2 en el conjunto de la población estudiada han sido superiores a los registrados por otros autores en alturas de caídas mayores, en las que el objetivo era lograr la máxima amortiguación. Conclusiones: Los resultados de este estudio justifican la necesidad de intervenciones profilácticas para enseñar a amortiguar correctamente las caídas de saltos. El mayor valor obtenido en F2 por los hombres podría ser debido a que caían desde mayor altura que las mujeres y al mayor recorrido del centro de gravedad registrado por las mujeres que les protegía de valores altos en F2</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;23(116): 441-449, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de sexo durante la amortiguación de caídas en tests de salto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
