<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87584</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immediate effect of kinesio tape on the reflex response of the vastus medialis regarding the use of two different application techniques: facilitation and inhibition of muscle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo analyze the immediate effect of Kinesio Tape (KT) with two techniques (inhibition and facilitation) on reflex response of vastus medialis.MethodsThirty healthy individuals volunteered to take part in this study (25.9±6.2 years, 67.1±12.9kg; and 171.1±9.5cm). An electrogoniometer was used to determine the onset of the imbalance and superficial electromyography was recorded to compare intensity and latency of the reflex response of the vastus medialis under three different conditions: without KT, with KT origin-insertion and with KT insertion-origin. In order to assess the inter-observer reliability, two groups of researchers independently calculated the response intensity (maximum peak of the normalized electromyography) and latency (the time it takes between the start of the imbalance and the onset of reflex response).ResultsHigh correlations between groups were found for the variables (0.773&amp;#8804;ICC&amp;#8804;0.883). With regards to the effect of the KT, significant differences between the three conditions, without KT, with KT origin-insertion and with KT insertion-origin, were not found (P&amp;#8805;.05).ConclusionsThe results suggest that the application of KT origin-insertion and KT insertion-origin does not have an immediate effect on the reflex response of the analyzed muscle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merelló Peñalver, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tolsá Gil, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Segarra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Gramage, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ridaura, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar el efecto inmediato del Kinesio Tape (KT) mediante dos técnicas de aplicación (inhibición o facilitación muscular), sobre la respuesta refleja del vasto interno del cuádriceps.Material y métodoEn el estudio participaron voluntariamente 30 sujetos sanos (25,9±6,2 años; 67,1±12,9kg; 171,1±9,5cm). Se utilizó un goniómetro electrónico para determinar el inicio del desequilibrio y electromiografía de superficie para comparar la intensidad y la latencia de la respuesta refleja del vasto interno entre tres condiciones diferentes: sin KT, con KT aplicado de origen a inserción y con KT aplicado de inserción a origen. Con la finalidad de valorar la fiabilidad interobservador, dos investigadores calcularon de forma independiente la intensidad de la respuesta refleja (máximo pico de la electromiografía normalizada) y la latencia de la respuesta refleja (tiempo desde el inicio del desequilibrio hasta la aparición de la respuesta refleja).ResultadosSe obtuvieron correlaciones elevadas entre los grupos para las variables de estudio (0,773&amp;#8804;ICC&amp;#8804;0,883). Con relación al efecto del vendaje, no se encontraron diferencias significativas en las 3 condiciones (sin KT, KT origen-inserción y KT inserción-origen) (p&amp;#8805;0,05).ConclusionesLos resultados obtenidos sugieren que tanto la aplicación de facilitación como la de inhibición no tienen un efecto inmediato sobre la respuesta muscular refleja del músculo analizado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(1): 13-18, ene. - feb. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto inmediato del kinesio tape sobre la respuesta refleja del vasto interno ante la utilización de dos técnicas diferentes de aplicación: facilitación e inhibición muscular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50351^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
