<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95960</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of our study was to determine the feasibility and safety of a program for laparoscopic adrenalectomy(LA), on an ambulatory basis, at the General Hospital of Ciudad Real (HGCR).Material and method: A retrospective study was undertaken from January 2006 to June 2008. Co-morbidity and characteristics of the adrenal masses to be excised were assessed, as well as hospital length of stay and postoperative complications, to see whether they could have been included in an outpatient program according to strict selection criteria. Results: During the study period 16 adrenalectomies were performed at our institution; 12 of them by laparoscopy. Applying Gill&#146;s criteria for outpatient surgery, the group of candidates consisted of 6 patients who met the following characteristics: mean age was 51.67 years (44-65), 3 tumours were functioning and the other 3 incidental findings. The ratio left/right was 2:1.The mean tumour size was 3.75 cm (1-5 cm). All cases underwent a lateral transperitoneal LA approach, the mean operative time was 83 minutes (30-150). No postoperative complications occurred.The average length of stay was 2.83 days (2-3), with regularoral analgesia requirements for 1-3 days.Conclusion: Our results show that, by applying strict selectioncriteria, it would be safe and feasible to under go an ambulatory program of adrenalectomy by experienced surgeons in advanced laparoscopic techniques, achieving high patients&#146; satisfaction and no morbidity. Controlled studies are still required to provide appropriate criteria for optimal results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Sánchez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Paz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Atienza, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzanares Campillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de nuestro estudio fue determinar la factibilidad y seguridad de un programa de adrenalectomía laparoscópica (AL) en régimen ambulatorio (CMA) en el Hospital General de Ciudad Real (HGCR).Material y método: Realizamos una revisión retrospectiva de las adrenalectomías realizadas en el HGCR desde enero de 2006a junio de 2008. La morbilidad y las características de las mas asadrenales extirpadas fueron evaluadas, al igual que la estancia hospitalaria y las complicaciones postoperatorias para ver si podrían haber sido incluidos en un programa de CMA según estrictoscriterios de selección. Resultados: Se realizaron 16 adrenalectomías durante esteperiodo; 12 por vía laparoscópica. Aplicando los criterios de Gill para cirugía ambulatoria, el grupo de candidatos consistiría en 6 pacientes que presentaban las siguientes características: la edad media fue de 51,67 años (44-65), 3 eran funcionantes y 3 incidentalomas. El ratio izquierdas/derechas fue 2:1. El tamaño tumoral medio fue de 3,75 cm (1-5 cm). En todos los casos se practicó AL transperitoneal lateral con tiempo operatorio medio de 83 minutos(30-150 minutos). No se registraron complicaciones postoperatorias. La estancia media fue de 2,83 días (2-3 días), con requerimientos de analgesia oral habitual durante 1-3 días. Conclusión: Nuestros resultados muestran que aplicando estrictos criterios de selección, es seguro y factible iniciar un programa ambulatorio de adrenalectomías por cirujanos expertos en técnicas laparoscópicas avanzadas, con alta satisfacción y nula morbilidad. Aún se necesitan estudios controlados que propicien criterios adecuados para unos resultados óptimos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;15(1): 26-30, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adrenalectomía y cirugía mayor ambulatoria. ¿Es posible?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
