<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141778</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-2345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress fracture in metatarsals: concerning two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Stress fractures occur when a bone with normal elastic strength is subjected to higher loads than its mechanical strength. Although they may occur in any location they are more frequent in the metatarsals, these being the areas subject to greatest load. The clinical presentation for stress fractures is highly nonspecific, which means that a detailed history is key to a suspected diagnosis. X-rays may be normal in the first stages, with gammagraphy and magnetic resonance being the gold standards for diagnosis in the initial stages. It is recommended that a study of possible underlying causes which may have contributed to the fracture is carried out. Generally the treatment is conservative, although in some cases, such as those occurring in the 5th metatarsal, surgical treatment may be necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casorrán Berges, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baltanás Rubio, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno García, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Río Martínez, PS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fracturas de estrés se producen cuando un hueso con resistencia elástica normal es sometido a cargas superiores a su resistencia mecánica. Aunque pueden producirse en cualquier localización, son más frecuentes a nivel de metatarsos, al ser zonas anatómicas sometidas a mayor carga. La clínica de las fracturas de estrés es muy inespecífica, por lo que una historia detallada es clave para el diagnóstico de sospecha. La radiología puede ser normal en los primeros estadios, siendo la gammagrafía y la resonancia magnética los gold standards para el diagnóstico en etapas iniciales. Es recomendable realizar un estudio de posibles causas subyacentes que hayan podido contribuir a la fractura. Generalmente el tratamiento es conservador, aunque en algunos casos, como en las localizadas en el 5º metatarsiano, puede ser necesario tratamiento quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. osteoporos. metab. miner. (Internet);7(2): 67-70, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de estrés en metatarsos: a propósito de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24657^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
