<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147730</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SEIP-AEPAP-SEPEAP consensus document on the aetiology, diagnosis and treatment of bacterial skin infections in out-patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Skin infections are a common cause for dermatological consultations in the paediatric setting. A review is presented of the clinical manifestations, diagnosis and treatment of the main bacterial skin infections, as well as the diagnosis and treatment of super-infected puncture and bite wounds. The most prevalent bacteria in skin infections are Staphylococcus aureusand Streptococcus pyogenes. Treatment is usually empirical, since microbiological studies are only recommended under certain circumstances or lack of improvement with common therapies. Superficial skin infections can be treated with local antiseptics or antibiotics (mupirocin or fusidic acid). Systemic treatment is usually reserved for patients with extensive or severe disease or with other risk factors. Systemic treatment depends on the suspected infecting bacteria, with penicillin, amoxicillin, amoxicillin-clavulanic acid and first or second generation cephalosporin being the most frequently used drugs. Due to the low incidence of community-acquired methicillin-resistant infection by S. aureus in Spain, the use of clindamycin or co-trimoxazole is only recommended after severe disease, relapses or a clear epidemiological background (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraga-Llop, FA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Casaño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conejo-Fernández, AJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Chamorro, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro-Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Couceiro, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero-Artigao, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfayate, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones cutáneas constituyen un motivo de consulta frecuente en dermatología pediátrica. Se revisan las manifestaciones clínicas, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de los principales cuadros infecciosos bacterianos de la piel, así como de la sobreinfección de las heridas punzantes y por mordedura. Las bacterias más prevalentes en las infecciones cutáneas son Staphylococcus aureus (S. aureus) y Streptococcus pyogenes. El tratamiento es generalmente empírico y solo ante determinadas circunstancias o mala evolución clínica se recomienda el estudio microbiológico. Las infecciones cutáneas superficiales pueden tratarse con antisépticos y antibióticos tópicos (mupirocina o ácido fusídico). El tratamiento sistémico se reserva para formas extensas, graves o con otros factores de riesgo del huésped. En estos casos, el antibiótico de elección dependerá, entre otros factores, de los patógenos sospechados; los más utilizados son penicilina, amoxicilina, amoxicilina-ácido clavulánico y cefalosporinas de primera o segunda generación. Considerando la baja incidencia de S. aureus resistente a la meticilina de adquisición comunitaria en nuestro país, no se recomienda modificar el tratamiento empírico salvo en circunstancias de especial gravedad, recurrencia o antecedente epidemiológico, en cuyo caso el tratamiento recomendado es clindamicina o trimetoprima-sulfametoxazol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(2): 121.e1-121.e10, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147730</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento de consenso SEIP-AEPAP-SEPEAP sobre la etiología, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de las infecciones cutáneas bacterianas de manejo ambulatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5810^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
