<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102036</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-2885</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metallic ureteral stent (Resonance®) in lithiasis and benign compressive pathology: initial experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Upper urinary tract obstructive uropathy in  high-morbidity patients can beresolved by placing a double-J metal catheter (Resonance®) over one year, with regular replacements.We evaluated those patients who received the above catheter due to either extrinsic or intrincic disease or lithiasis, by following them up for longer than one year. MATERIAL AND METHODS: Fifteen ASA IV patients (10 males and 5 females) 76 years old (range: 45-95) who received the Resonance®-type double-J catheter were prospectively evaluated;short-term and long-term complications were assessed, as well as replacement troublesand patient progress. RESULTS: Indication was stone in 7 cases and extrinsic pathology in 8. One patient developed haematuria and 3 long-term bladder irritability. Nine patients (60%) needed a change of the catheter one year following placement. Two patients died due to other causes before replacement.Upon catheter removal no patient showed inlays. CONCLUSIONS: Long-time use of double-J metal catheters is a therapeutic alternative to be considered for patients with high morbidity and associated advanced age, both in an extrinsic pathology and in lithiasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanchez Martín, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angerri, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sangüedolce, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Snatillana, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicnecio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La uropatía obstructiva del tramo urinario superior en pacientes con altamorbilidad, puede ser solucionada con la colocación de un catéter doble J metálico (Resonance®), de un año de duración y con recambios periódicos. Valoramos a los pacientes a los que se les ha colocado dicho catéter por patología extrínseca/intrínseca, o por litiasis con más de un año de seguimiento. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Se analizan retrospectivamente a 15 pacientes ASA IV (10 varones y 5mujeres), con edad media de 76 años (rango 45-95) a los que se colocó el catéter doble J tipoResonance®, valorando las complicaciones a corto y largo plazo así como las dificultades enel recambio y la evolución.RESULTADOS: La indicación del catéter metálico fue litiasis 7 casos y compresión extrínseca 8 casos. Un paciente presentó hematuria y 3 irritabilidad vesical. En 9 casos (60%) se ha cambiado el catéter al año de la colocación. Dos pacientes fallecieron antes del recambio porotras causas. Ningún paciente presentó incrustaciones.CONCLUSIONES: El catéter ureteral metálico doble J tipo Resonance® es una buena opción para pacientes complejos con elevada comorbilidad y/o edad avanzada, que presentan uropatíaobstructiva, incluida la litiasis. Es de fácil manejo y tiene escasos efectos secundarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Fund. Puigvert;31(2): 53-58, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102036</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catéter ureteral metálico (Resonance®) en litiasis y patología en compresiva benigna: experiencia inicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29144^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
