<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058721</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The use of optical coherence tomography in hereditary optic neuropathies: description of a family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: This report describes two siblings, a    woman aged 44 years and her brother aged 29    years, who both complained of visual loss in both    eyes. The woman had bilateral optic nerve (ON)    temporal pallor and severe reduction of ON fibre    layer thickness in this area. Both she and her brother    had cecocentral defects in perimetry and color    vision deficiency with a marked tritanopia deficit.    Discussion: ON pallor, limited to the temporal    region, is the basic criterion for the diagnosis of    dominant optic atrophy. Optical coherence tomography    can be a useful technique in defining the    diagnosis and improving the follow-up of patients    with this pathology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés-Santos, A de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Tocino, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchidrián-Mayo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta una mujer de 44 años y    su hermano de 29 años con mala agudeza visual en    ambos ojos. Presentan ambos una palidez temporal    en el nervio óptico (NO) bilateralmente, con una    severa disminución de fibras del NO en esta área,    déficit centrocecal en el campo visual y una alteración    de los colores en forma de tritanopia.    Discusión: La palidez del NO que afecta a la región    temporal es un criterio básico en el diagnóstico de    atrofia óptica dominante. La Tomografía Óptica de    coherencia se presenta como una técnica útil en el    diagnóstico y posterior seguimiento de esta patología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;83(1): 57-62, ene. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de la tomografía óptica de coherencia en neuropatías ópticas hereditarias. Descripción de una familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
