<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167525</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in transplant patients, compared to other stressful health situations in pulmonary patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transplantation may imply severe biopsychosocial impairments. In order to know the quality of life of patients one year after transplantation, 58 subjects were compared to three different groups of patients (stabilized and acute COPD patients, and lung cancer patients in a surgery unit). Patients filled in two questionnaires: EORTC QLQ-C30 (quality of life) and HAD (anxiety and depression). The quality of life dimensions with inter-group differences were physical, role, emotional and cognitive functioning, global health status, and a number of symptoms (fatigue, dyspnea, insomnia and appetite loss). There were differences in depression, and but not in anxiety. Transplant and surgical patients showed better quality of life and affective status than chronic pulmonary patients. Discriminant analysis showed that the transplant group was the best described group. We conclude that patients, one year after transplantation, show similar quality of life as asymptomatic hospitalised patients, somewhat better than chronic patients in a stabilized stage of the disease, and much better than severe chronic patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borda Más, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán Rodríguez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez San Gregorio, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Rodríguez, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante puede llevar asociado importantes deterioros en el funcionamiento biopsicosocial. Para conocer la calidad de vida de los enfermos un año después del trasplante, se comparó a 58 trasplantados con tres grupos diferentes de enfermos (pacientes con EPOC estabilizados y descompensados, y enfermos quirúrgicos de cáncer de pulmón). Se les evaluó con el EORTC QLQ-C30 (calidad de vida) y el HAD (ansiedad y depresión). Las dimensiones de calidad de vida con diferencias intergrupales eran las de funcionamiento físico, del rol, emocional y cognitivo, la escala global de salud, y algunos síntomas (fatiga, disnea, insomnio y pérdida de apetito). Aparecían diferencias en depresión, pero no en ansiedad. En general, los trasplantados y los enfermos quirúrgicos tendían a mostrar mayores niveles de calidad de vida y mejor estado afectivo que los enfermos respiratorios crónicos. En el análisis discriminante los trasplantados eran el grupo mejor delimitado. Concluimos que el enfermo, un año después del trasplante, muestra una calidad de vida similar a la de un enfermo hospitalizado asintomático, algo mejor a la de un enfermo crónico en un momento de estabilidad clínica y mucho mejor que la de un enfermo crónico grave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);20(2): 266-272, abr.-jun. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167525</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida de los trasplantados en relación a otras situaciones médicas estresantes vividas por los enfermos pulmonares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
