<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131009</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The psychotherapeutic group: some considerations on its diagnostic possibilities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Based on the experience with psychotherapeutic groups of adolescents, this paper intends to show: I) the possibilities that the group offers to the individual diagnosis of its members, and II) the particular characteristics of the diagnosis of the group as such. To this end, initial group sessions have been analyzed in order to detect the presence of manifest and latent aspects that characterize a certain moment of the group life, and make such a diagnostic approach possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hebe Sosa de Turelli, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir de la experiencia con grupos psicoterapéuticos con adolescentes, en este trabajo se intenta mostrar: I) las posibilidades que los grupos ofrecen para el diagnóstico individual de sus miembros, y II) las características particulares del diagnóstico del grupo como tal. Para esto se ha realizado el análisis de las primeras sesiones a fin de detectar la presencia de aspectos manifiestos y latentes que caracterizan un momento dado de la vida del grupo y que permiten dicha aproximación diagnóstica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(8): 27-33, nov. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El grupo psicoterapéutico. Consideraciones sobre sus posibilidades diagnósticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
