<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114318</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Modificación of health parameters in workers exposed to cold</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: working in a cold environment can cause damage to the health of workers. The objective was to find changes in health parameters (analytical, blood pressure and number of infections). Subject and methods: Cohort study comparing two populations of 75 workers performing similar tasks in their jobs (mainly cutting and packaging of perishable products), in similar conditions except for occupational exposure to cold in the first group. It was obtained three parameters calculated for each effect on cold exposure: relative risk, confidence limits and level of statistical significance (p). The significance level was set to a value of p&lt;0,05. Results: Statistically significant differences were found between exposed an unexposed workers in diastolic blood pressure variables (RR = 1.12, CI (95%) = 1,01-1,23; and P=0,03) and number of infections suffered (P=0,0486). There was no statistically significant differences in other variables. Conclusion: In this study, the exposure to temperatures from  to 10ºC causes in the group of workers exposed a decrease in diastolic blood pressure levels and an increase in the number of suffered infections compared to the unexposed control group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Felipe Gómez, Francisco Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Delgado, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente Madero, Jose Luis de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernandez Ortega, Mª Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Carrasco, Mª Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Trenado, Juan Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El trabajo en ambientes fríos puede provocar daños a la salud de los trabajadores y ser causa de cuadros de incapacidad temporal. El propósito de este trabajo fue hallar alteraciones en diferentes parámetros de salud (analíticos, tensión arterial y  número de infecciones). Sujetos y método: Estudio de cohortes comparando dos poblaciones de 75 trabajadores que realizaban tareas similares en sus puestos de trabajo (principalmente corte y envasado de productos perecederos), en unas condiciones parecidas a excepción de la exposición laboral a frío del primer grupo, realizando el cálculo de tres parámetros para cada efecto de la exposición al frío: Riesgo relativo, Límites de Confianza y grado de significación estadística (p). el nivel de significación se estableció para un valor de p menor de 0,05. Resultados: se hallaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre expuestos y no expuestos para las variables presión arterial diastólica (RR=1,12; I. C (95%)= 1,01-1,23; y P = 0,03) y número de infecciones padecidas (P= 0,0486). No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el resto de variables. Conclusiones:; En este estudio , la exposición a temperaturas de 5 a 10 ºC ocasiona en el grupo de trabajadores expuestos una disminución de las cifras de presión arterial diastólica y un aumento en el número de infecciones padecidas con respecto al grupo control no expuesto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;21(1): 8-13, abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modificación de parámetros de salud en trabajadores expuestos a frío</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3112^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
