<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154122</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malnutrition and cognitive development if infants in rural marginalized areas in Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the relationship between nutritional status measured by anthropometry and the mental, psychomotor and language development of infants in marginalized rural areas of Mexico. Method: Cross-sectional study with 576 infants aged from 7 to 26 months in four rural locations. Variables consisted of measures of anthropometric and cognitive development. Results: Infants with short stature had a lower rate of language development, while birth weight was marginally associated with psychomotor development. Conclusion: Although acute malnutrition (identified by underweight) is no longer a problem in rural areas of Mexico, chronic malnutrition (expressed as stunting) is still common and is associated with alterations in mental development in the child population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Quintero, María del Refugio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Hernández, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chávez Villasana, Adolfov</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán Amaro, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la relación entre el estado nutricional medido por antropometría y el desarrollo mental, psicomotor y del lenguaje en infantes de zonas rurales marginadas de México. Método: Estudio transversal con 576 infantes de 7 a 26 meses de edad de cuatro localidades rurales. Las variables fueron antropométricas y de desarrollo cognitivo. Resultados: Los infantes con baja estatura tuvieron un menor índice de desarrollo del lenguaje, mientras que el peso al nacer se relacionó marginalmente con el desarrollo psicomotor. Conclusión: Aunque la desnutrición aguda (identificada por el peso) ya no es un problema en las zonas rurales de México, la desnutrición crónica (expresada como baja estatura) sigue siendo frecuente y se relaciona con alteraciones en el desarrollo mental de la población infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(4): 304-307, jul.-ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desnutrición y desarrollo cognitivo en infantes de zonas rurales marginadas de México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5284^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54301^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
