<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140910</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The fibroid as clinical problem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Uterine fibroids are the most common benign tumours that affect women of reproductive age and they represent the main indication for surgery for benign uterine pathology. In 25% of cases, they become clinically apparent, causing heavy menstrual bleeding, pelvic pain and/or infertility. Therefore, fibroids have a notable impact on the economic costs for the health system and also on the quality of life of the women they afflict. Although MRI is the most precise technique to diagnose fibroids, ultrasound remains the most cost-effective method. Surgery has been the treatment of choice for years, and several minimally invasive procedures have recently been developed. There are a wide variety of conservative medical treatment options, which are continually expanding. Research on the biology of these tumours can lead to new therapeutic options for the management of fibroids as we better understand the role that growth factors and genetic mutations play in them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arqué, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calaf, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D´Angelo, Emanuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los miomas uterinos son los tumores benignos más frecuentes en la mujer en edad reproductiva y constituyen la principal indicación de cirugía por patología uterina benigna. En el 25% de los casos se manifiestan clínicamente, causando sangrado menstrual abundante, dolor pélvico y/o infertilidad. Tienen, por lo tanto, un impacto notable en el coste económico que supone su seguimiento y tratamiento para el sistema sanitario por un lado y, por otro, influyen sustancialmente en la calidad de vida de las mujeres que los padecen. A pesar de que la resonancia magnética es la técnica más precisa para su diagnóstico, la ecografía sigue siendo la técnica de elección por ser la más coste-efectiva. La cirugía ha sido, durante años, el tratamiento de elección. En los últimos años se han desarrollado técnicas quirúrgicas mínimamente invasivas para su tratamiento. Sin embargo hay un amplio abanico de posibilidades terapéuticas conservadoras que, día a día, se va ampliando. La investigación de la biología de estos tumores puede proporcionar nuevas opciones terapéuticas, puesto que conocemos mejor el papel que ejercen los factores de crecimiento y las mutaciones genéticas en ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(supl.1): 1-6, jul. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140910</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El mioma como problema clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
