<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18187</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the spanish version of the aggresion questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this study was to analyze the psychometric properties of the aggression questionnaire (AQ) (Buss and Perry, 1992) using a large sample of students from different educational settings in the community of Madrid (N= 1.382, 49% males &amp; 51% females. This questionnaire, which has been used extensively in many studies of aggressive behavior in youths and adolescents, is one of the most valid self-report techniques to assess two types of aggression: physical and verbal; and two types of emotions associated with aggression: anger and hostility. The results of this study provide psychometric support for the use of the Spanish version of this questionnaire as a reliable and valid instrument to assess different levels of aggression, anger and hostility in youths and adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu Rodríguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Fernández, M. Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graña Gómez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El principal objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar las propiedades psicométricas del Cuestionario de Agresión (AQ) (Buss y Perry, 1992). Este cuestionario, ampliamente utilizado en multitud de estudios sobre el comportamiento agresivo en jóvenes y adolescentes, constituye una de las técnicas de auto-informe más avalada para la medición específica de dos tipos de agresión: la física y la verbal, y de dos emociones relacionadas con la agresividad de los sujetos: la ira y la hostilidad. A tenor de los resultados obtenidos en relación a sus propiedades psicométricas en una amplia muestra de sujetos pertenecientes a diferentes centros educativos de la Comunidad de Madrid (1.382 sujetos, 49,9 por ciento varones y 50,1 por ciento mujeres, con edades comprendidas entre los 15 y los 25 años), la versión española del Cuestionario de Agresión permite evaluar; con las suficientes garantías psicométricas, diferentes niveles de agresividad, ira y hostilidad en jóvenes y adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 476-482, mayo 2002. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación psicométrica de la versión española del Cuestionario de Agresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
