<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042438</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the surgeon as a factor in the surgical treatment of rectal cancer with preoperative radiotherapy. A comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In the last few years, changes have been introduced in rectal cancer surgery that have improved its results. These changes include autosuture devices, total mesorectal excision, and neoadjuvant treatment. The aim of the present study was to determine whether the surgeon influences the results of surgical treatment for rectal cancer.   Patients and methods. A comparative, retrospective study was performed in 194 consecutive patients with rectal cancer who underwent preoperative radiotherapy. The patients were divided into two groups according to the type of surgeon performing the intervention: group I: 3 surgeons with 101 patients; group II: 16 surgeons with 93 patients. Results. Sphincter-preserving surgery was performed in 77% of patients in group I and in 52% of those in group II (p &lt; 0.001). In group I anterior resection was performed in 100%, 100% and 58% when the tumor was between 11-15 cm, 6-10 cm and 1-5 cm, respectively, compared with 100%, 69% and 23.5% in group II. Complications occurred in 41% of patients in group I and in 48% of those in group II (p = 0.037). Length of hospital stay was 9.9 days in group I and 13.9 days in group II (p &lt; 0.001). Local recurrence occurred in 3.5% of patients in group I and in 11.3% of those in group II (p = 0.054). Survival was similar in both groups.  Conclusions. The surgeon is a key factor in rectal cancer, despite the introduction of autosuture devices, neoadjuvant treatment, and total mesorectal excision. These patients should be operated on by experts in this type of surgery and not by surgeons who perform these interventions only occasionally (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frutos, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Quiteria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Manuel de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, Graciela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los últimos años se han introducido cambios en la cirugía del cáncer de recto que han mejorado sus resultados, como máquinas de autosutura, extirpación total del mesorrecto y tratamiento neoadyuvante. El objetivo es saber si el factor cirujano influye en los resultados del tratamiento quirúrgico del cáncer de recto.  Pacientes y métodos. Estudio comparativo retrospectivo en 194 pacientes intervenidos de forma consecutiva de cáncer de recto y sometidos a radioquimioterapia preoperatoria. Los pacientes fueron divididos en 2 grupos según el tipo de cirujano que realizaba la intervención: grupo I, 3 cirujanos con 101 pacientes, y grupo II, 16 cirujanos con 93 pacientes.  Resultados. En el grupo I se realizó una cirugía conservadora de esfínteres en el 77% de los pacientes y en el grupo II en el 52% (p &lt; 0,001). En el grupo I se realizó una resección anterior en el 100, 100 y 58% cuando el tumor se localizó entre 11-15, 6-10 y 1-5 cm, respectivamente, frente a 100, 69 y 23,5% en el grupo II. Ocurrieron complicaciones en el 41% del grupo I y en el 48% del grupo II (p = 0,037). La estancia hospitalaria fue de 9,9 días en el grupo I y de 13,9 en el grupo II (p &lt; 0,001). Presentaron recidiva local el 3,5% del grupo I y el 11,3% del grupo II (p = 0,054). La supervivencia fue similar.  Conclusiones. El factor cirujano tiene un papel fundamental en el cáncer de recto, pese a la introducción de las máquinas de autosutura, tratamiento neoadyuvante y extirpación total del mesorrecto. Estos pacientes deberían ser intervenidos por cirujanos expertos y no por cirujanos que tratan el cáncer de recto de forma ocasional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(2): 89-94, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del factor cirujano en el tratamiento quirúrgico del cáncer de recto con radioquimioterapia preoperatoria. Estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
