<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147838</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse events self-declaration system and influenza vaccination coverage of healthcare workers in a tertiary hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: During the influenza vaccination campaign 2011-2012 we established a self-declaration system of adverse events (AEs) in healthcare workers (HCW). The aim of this study is to describe the vaccinated population and analyse vaccination coverage and self-declared AEs after the voluntary flu vaccination in a university hospital in Barcelona. Methods: Observational study. We used the HCW immunization record to calculate the vaccination coverage. We collected AEs using a voluntary, anonymous, self-administered survey during the 2011-2012 flu vaccination campaign. We performed a logistic regression model to determine the associated factors to declare AEs. Results: The influenza vaccination coverage in HCW was 30.5% (n = 1,507/4,944). We received completed surveys from 358 vaccinated HCW (23.8% of all vaccinated). We registered AEs in 186 respondents to the survey (52.0% of all respondents). Of these, 75.3% (n = 140) reported local symptoms after the flu vaccination, 9.7% (n = 18) reported systemic symptoms and 15.1% (n = 28) both local and systemic symptoms. No serious AEs were self-reported. Female sex and aged under 35 were both factors associated with declaring AEs. Conclusions: Our self-reporting system did not register serious AEs in HCW, resulting in an opportunity to improve HCW trust in flu vaccination (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aldea, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Munoz, Cesar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sequera, Víctor Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, Sebastiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivé, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trilla, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilajeliu, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayas, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Durante la campaña de vacunación antigripal 2011-2012 establecimos un sistema de autodeclaración de acontecimientos adversos (AA) en el personal sanitario (PS). El objetivo de este estudio es describir la población vacunada y analizar la cobertura de vacunación y los AA autodeclarados tras la vacunación voluntaria del PS frente a la gripe en un hospital universitario de tercer nivel en Barcelona. Métodos: Estudio observacional. Para el cálculo de la cobertura de vacunación se utilizó el registro de vacunación de profesionales sanitarios del hospital. Los AA se recogieron mediante una encuesta voluntaria, anónima y autoadministrada durante la campaña de vacunación antigripal 2011-2012, y se analizaron mediante regresión logística. Se construyó un modelo de regresión logística para determinar los factores que predisponen a declarar AA. Resultados: La campaña alcanzó una cobertura de vacunación antigripal del 30,5% (n = 1.507/4.944) del PS. De los vacunados, el 23,8% (n = 358) respondieron la encuesta de AA autodeclarados. El 52,0% (n = 186) de los que respondieron a la encuesta declaró haber presentado algún tipo de AA. De estos, el 75,3% (n = 140) refirió signos y síntomas locales tras la vacunación, el 9,7% (n = 18), signos y síntomas sistémicos, y el 15,1% (n = 28), síntomas tanto locales como sistémicos. No se declaró ningún AA grave. Ser mujer y tener menos de 35 años se asoció a declarar algún tipo de AA. Conclusiones: El sistema de autodeclaración no registró AA graves en el PS, suponiendo una oportunidad para aumentar la confianza del PS en la vacuna antigripal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(4): 155-159, feb. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistema de autodeclaración de acontecimientos adversos y cobertura de vacunación antigripal en profesionales sanitarios en un hospital universitario de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50229</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16855^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
