<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74226</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstetric haemorrhage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Massive obstetric haemorrhage is a very important cause of maternal morbidity and mortality in developed countries and in third world countries. Massive obsteric haemorrhage has a coagulopathic component and a vascular or surgical component that are often associated in the same patient. Nearly two thirds of patients cannot be identified with risk factors for obstetric haemorrhage, although a good knowledge and early identification of associated risk factors is helpful for its prevention in many cases. Obstetric haemorrhage is not always adequately identified or treated, because blood loss is underestimated by clinical observation. Postpartum haemorrhage is the cause of 95% of all obstetric haemorrhages. In this group, the main cause is uterine atony. Women&#146;s resuscitation objective is thr intravascular volume restoration, to reach and adequate tissue perfussion pressure. Once an obstetric haemorrhage is diagnosed, it is very important a coordinated, rapid and protocolized treatment. Rational use of blood components, team work with the blood bank, the use of pharmacological and surgical resources readily, are necessary actions in this context. It is highly recommended prompt implication of senior staff in severe obstetric haemorrhage resolution. It is recommended the use of local protocols for each maternity. This protocol must be known by all team members and it must be adapted to local hospital characteristics, and should be periodically revised. High risk patients for obstetric haemorrhage, must be transferred to a level III hospital where all resources can be used if necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puertas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch Arévalo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brogly, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alsina, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemorragia masiva obstétrica es una causa muy importante de mortalidad y morbilidad materna en los países industrializados y del tercer mundo. La hemorragia masiva obstétrica tiene un componente vascular y/o quirúrgico y un componente de coagulopatía. Aunque en dos tercios de los casos de hemorragia postparto precoz no se encuentre ningún factor de riesgo asociado, es muy importante la identificación de los mismos. La hemorragia obstétrica puede, en ocasiones, no ser tratada adecuadamente. La apreciación clínica habitualmente infra estimada pérdida hemática. La hemorragia postparto suele ser la responsable del 95% de las hemorragias postparto y la atonía uterina es la causa más frecuente. El objetivo de la reanimación es restaurar el volumen sanguíneo circulante y mantener una presión de perfusión adecuada. Una vez diagnosticada una hemorragia obstétrica es fundamental actuar de manera secuencial y rápida. El uso racional de los derivados sanguíneos y el trabajo en equipo con el banco de sangre, así como la utilización de medidas tanto quirúrgicas como farmacológicas precoces y decididas en las hemorragias graves, son actitudes necesarias, por lo que se recomienda la implicación directa del personal con más experiencia en la resolución de una hemorragia obstétrica grave. Se recomienda que toda maternidad tenga un protocolo consensuado y conocido por todo el personal de la misma. El protocolo de actuación debe estar adaptado a las características de cada unidad obstétrica y debe revisarse periódicamente. Las enfermas con factores de riesgo de presentar una hemorragia obstétrica deben ser trasladas a un centro de asistencia de nivel III (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;19(2): 49-60, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia obstétrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1838</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14994^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
