<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98399</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of CADASIL disease in normotensive and non-diabetics with lacunar infarct</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: CADASIL (Cerebral Autosomal Dominant Arteriopathy with Subcortical Infarcts and Leukoencephalopathy) is characterized by recurrent cerebral ischemic episodes of the lacunar subtype usually without traditional vascular risk factors. We investigated the frequency of CADASIL among selected patients with cerebral ischemia of the lacunar subtype. Methods: we studied patients under 65 years old who presented cerebral ischemia of the lacunar subtype without hypertension, diabetes mellitus or other causes that explained the cerebral ischemia. On the skin biopsies, we performed immunostaining analysis on 5&amp;#956;m frozen sections with monoclonal antibody anti-Notch 3 (1E4). We also performed a genetic analysis of the Notch 3 gene (exons 3,4,5,6,11 and 19). Results: of 1.519 patients analyzed, only 57 (3.7%) fulfilled the selection criteria, and 30 of them accepted to participated in the study. We studied 30 patients, mean age was 53 years (range 34 to 65), 50% were men and all patients suffered a lacunar stroke. Immunostaining analysis was positive in two patients (6.6%) and the genetic analysis confirmed a mutation characteristic of CADASIL in exon 4 nt 622C/T (Arg 182 Cys) and 694 T/C (Cys206Arg) respectively. Conclusions: CADASIL disease was present in 6.6% of patients younger than 65 years with a lacunar stroke and without hypertension or diabetes mellitus. Screening for CADASIL should be considered in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baiget, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboix, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruscalleda, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Villalta, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Fábregas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cocho, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la enfermedad de CADASIL (Cerebral Autosomal Dominant Arteriopathy with Subcortical Infarcts and Leukoencephalopathy) se caracteriza por isquemias cerebrales recurrentes de tipo lacunar, habitualmente en pacientes sin factores de riesgo vascular. Analizamos la frecuencia de enfermedad de CADASIL en pacientes con infarto lacunar sin factores de riesgo vascular clásicos. Métodos: estudiamos pacientes con un primer infarto lacunar menores de 65 años sin hipertensión, diabetes mellitus u otra causa que justificara la isquemia cerebral. Realizamos estudio inmunohistoquímico de 5&amp;#956;m de espesor sobre biopsia cutánea usando el anticuerpo monoclonal anti-Notch 3 (1E4). Además del estudio inmunohistoquímico se realizó en todos los casos el estudio genético del gen Notch 3 de los exones 3, 4, 5, 6, 11 y 19. Resultados: de 1.519 pacientes con infarto lacunar, sólo 57 (3,7%) cumplieron los criterios de selección, y 30 de ellos aceptaron participar en el estudio. Analizamos 30 pacientes con edad media de 53 años; el 50% fueron hombres y todos presentaron un primer infarto cerebral tipo lacunar. El estudio inmunohistoquímico y genético confirmó la enfermedad de CADASIL en dos pacientes (6,6%) en el exón 4 nt 622C/T (Arg 182 Cys) y 694 T/C (Cys206Arg) respectivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;26(6): 325-330, jul.-ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de la enfermedad de CADASIL en pacientes normotensos y no diabéticos con infarto lacunar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38632^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54503^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38632^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
