<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163030</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autism: the importance of dysmorphology in the identification of associated medical conditions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Autism spectrum disorders (ASD) are characterized by deficits in communication and social interaction, associated with restricted interests and stereotyped behaviors. Considered as a neurodepelopment disorders, they present a recognized neurobiological basis. Genetic causes as chromosomes abnormalities, or genetic defects are the most recognized etiologies, followed by the environmental factors. Development. Dysmorphia are congenital alterations of the shape of a part of a living being, produced during its development. Their recognition is essential in delineating a syndrome or a specific entity. In the case of ASD, is possible to differentiate primary or idiopathic forms, from secondary or syndromic ones. In this work we describe the dysmorphological aspects related to ASD that will allow us to define a diagnostic presumption and guide the complementary studies according to them. Conclusions. The identification of these specific medical entities, associated with ASDs is fundamental since it allows inferring the possible evolution, preventing eventual complications and granting adequate genetic counseling  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruggieri, Víctor L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arberas, Claudia L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los trastornos del espectro autista (TEA) se caracterizan por déficits en la comunicación e interacción social asociados a intereses restringidos y conductas estereotipadas. Considerados trastornos del neurodesarrollo, presentan una base neurobiológica reconocida. Las causas genéticas, las anomalías cromosómicas o los defectos génicos son las etiologías más frecuentemente reconocidas, seguidas por factores tóxicos y ambientales (epigenéticos). Desarrollo. Las dismorfias son alteraciones congénitas de la forma de una parte de un ser vivo, producidas durante su desarrollo, y su reconocimiento es esencial en la delineación de un síndrome o una entidad específica. En el caso de los TEA permiten diferenciar las formas primarias o idiopáticas de las secundarias o sindrómicas. En este trabajo describimos los aspectos dismorfológicos vinculados a los TEA que permitirán definir una presunción diagnóstica y orientar los estudios complementarios de acuerdo con ellos. Conclusiones. La identificación de estas entidades médicas específicas, asociadas a los TEA, es fundamental, ya que permite inferir la posible evolución, prevenir eventuales complicaciones y otorgar un asesoramiento genético adecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(supl.1): s27-s31, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autismo: importancia de la dismorfología en la identificación de entidades médicas asociadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6976^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
