<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27938</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beliefs which legitimize political violence against the innocent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article analyses the arguments and beliefs published in a newspaper with links to a terrorist group, in an attempt to legitimize the kidnapping and murder of an innocent victim. Widespread public outcry against this act of brutality led the newspaper to create a version of the facts which attempted to reduce their emotional impact and maintain a positive image of the aggressive group. The methods used included: the attribution of responsibilities to the enemy, depersonalization of the victim, and an asymmetric evaluation of suffering (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corte, Luis de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabucedo, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Amalio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo analiza los argumentos y creencias publicados por un periódico vinculado a un grupo terrorista, en un intento de legitimar el secuestro y asesinato de una víctima inocente. La amplia respuesta ciudadana contra ese acto criminal obligó -a ese periódico a crear una versión de los hechos en la que se intentaba tanto reducir su impacto emocional como mantener la imagen positiva del grupo agresor. Los métodos a los que recurrió fueron: la atribución de responsabilidades al enemigo, la despersonalización de la víctima y la valoración asimétrica del sufrimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(4): 550-555, nov. 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Creencias legitimadoras de la violencia política contra los inocentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3433^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
