<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105908</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Choking phobia: Care plan in Children and Adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eating disorders are a common problem in childhood. Swallowing phobia is characterised by fear of choking on having consumed food, liquids or tablets. Although they are considered a minor disorder and have low prevalence, there has been an increase in its incidence in children and adolescents in the past few years. The analysis of four cases treated in our day hospital for this speci&amp;#64257;c phobia provides an assessment and the care necessary for its treatment and solution, in collaboration with other professionals and the family The importance of the role that nurses have in the treatment of this psychological disorder is emphasised, as well admission to Day Units, the correct application of the treatment plan, the establishment of robust and reliable links with the family and the patient, and the motivation for therapeutic change by the whole family. It is essential to include the disorder in the differential diagnosis of eating disorders in children, as well as knowledge of this by community workers, in order to establish adequate early treatment to improve therapeutic outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naranjo-Díaz, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puntí-Vidal, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralbas-Ortega, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-Núñez, Eloísa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valls-Ibáñez, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones alimentarias son un problema frecuente en la edad pediátrica. La fobia a tragar se caracteriza por miedo a atragantarse al ingerir comida, líquidos o pastillas. Aunque es un trastorno considerado menor y de baja prevalencia, en estos últimos años se ha observado un aumento de su incidencia en la etapa infantil y juvenil. En el análisis de 4 casos atendidos en nuestro hospital de día por esta fobia específica, se establece la valoración y los cuidados necesarios para su tratamiento y solución, en colaboración con los demás profesionales implicados y la familia. Es de destacar el importante rol que posee enfermería en el tratamiento de este trastorno psicológico, en los dispositivos de hospitalización parcial, para la correcta aplicación del plan terapéutico, el establecimiento de vínculos robustos y de confianza con la familia y el propio usuario, así como en la motivación para el cambio terapéutico por parte de todo el núcleo familiar. Es indispensable la inclusión del trastorno en el diagnóstico diferencial de los trastornos de alimentación en la infancia y su conocimiento por parte de los profesionales comunitarios, con la finalidad de poder establecer un adecuado tratamiento precoz que mejore los resultados terapéuticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);22(4): 231-233, jul.-ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fobia a tragar: plan de cuidados en la infancia y adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
