<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153189</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of endobronchial ultrasound-guided transbronchial needle aspiration in the diagnosis of mediastinal tuberculosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Mediastinal tuberculosis (TB) is rare and a diagnostic challenge. Transbronchial needle aspiration guided by endoscopic ultrasonography (EBUS-TBNA) is an essential tool for staging and diagnosing patients with lung cancer but to date there are no studies in our environment evaluating its efficacy in mediastinal TB. Methods: Patients with a final diagnosis of isolated intrathoracic tuberculous lymphadenitis over a 6-year period were included. We analyzed the cases on whom EBUS-TBNA was performed. Results: Forty-six patients with mediastinal lymphadenopathy without pulmonary involvement were identified and 29 underwent EBUS-TBNA. In 28 of 29 patients (96.6%) EBUS-TBNA was diagnostic and cytological findings confirmed granulomas in 93% of cases. Microbiological investigation revealed positive TB culture in 14 (48.2%) and positive PCR for Mycobacterium tuberculosis in 30% of cases on whom it was carried out. Eighty-four per cent of the patients were immigrants and when compared with the native population we found statistical differences in immune status and culture yield. Conclusion: EBUS-TB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Álvarez, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chalela, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curull, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pijuan, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Font, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badenes Bonet, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La tuberculosis (TBC) ganglionar mediastínica es rara y su presentación intratorácica es un reto diagnóstico. La punción aspirativa transbronquial guiada por ultrasonografía endobronquial (PATb-USEB) podría ser útil para su diagnóstico, pero no disponemos de estudios que evalúen su eficacia en nuestro medio. Métodos: Se analizaron retrospectivamente todos los pacientes con TBC ganglionar mediastínica aislada diagnosticados entre 2008 y 2014. Se identificaron los pacientes con diagnóstico definitivo a quienes se les realizó PATb-USEB. Resultados: Se identificaron 29 casos, siendo la PATb-USEB diagnóstica en 28 pacientes (96,6%). Los hallazgos citológicos confirmaron granulomas en el 93% de los casos. El cultivo fue positivo en 14 (48,2%) y la PCR para Mycobacterium tuberculosis, en el 30% de los casos en los que se realizó. El 84% de los pacientes eran inmigrantes y al compararlos con la población nativa se encontraron diferencias significativas en el estado inmunológico y el rendimiento del cultivo. No se registraron complicaciones derivadas del procedimiento. Conclusión: La PATb-USEB es una técnica de primera línea, efectiva y segura en el diagnóstico de pacientes con sospecha de TBC mediastínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(12): 532-535, jun. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153189</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la punción aspirativa transbronquial guiada con ultrasonografía endobronquial en el diagnóstico de la tuberculosis mediastínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55010^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55010^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8650^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55010^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8650^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
