<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050342</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Location of nonpalpable lesions of breast using radioactive maker</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development and diffusion of mammography techniquein the last decade has led to an increase in the diagnosisof nonpalpable breast lesions (NPL).The location of nonpalpable lesions labeling techniques with a high level of precision are required to excise these lesions.The advances of image techniques such ultrasonographyand digital mammography, have achieved this objectivewith high accuracy but they are not devoid of complications.Radioguided occult lesion localisation (ROLL) is a new techniquefor the location of nonpalpable lesions. The aim of thiswork is to review the results published in the literature on thissubject.The ROLL technique consists in the use of a radioactivemarker for NPL location. It is a multidisciplinary techniquethat involves the specialities of nuclear medicine, radiology,surgery and pathological anatomy. This procedure was initiatedin the European Institute of Oncology of Milan in 1998 andhas acquired great diffusion due to its great precision. Currently,it is considered as a new alternative for the correct removalof this type of lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Climent, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fliquete, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo y difusión de la técnica de la mamografía hadado lugar a que, en el último decenio, se haya observado unincremento del diagnóstico de lesiones mamarias de pequeñotamaño, muchas de ellas no palpables.La localización de este tipo de lesiones precisa de técnicasde marcado que aseguren la máxima precisión para su correctaextirpación. Los avances de las técnicas de imagen como laecografía y la estereotaxia digital, han conseguido este objetivocon gran exactitud pero en ocasiones, no están exentas decomplicaciones.El objetivo de este trabajo es una revisión y puesta al día delos resultados analizados en la literatura de una nueva técnicapara la localización de las lesiones no palpables (LNP) conocidacomo ROLL (Radioguided occult lesion localisation).La técnica ROLL consiste en la utilización de radiofármacospara la localización de LNP. Es una técnica multidisciplinaren la que colaboran las especialidades de medicina nuclear, radiología,cirugía y anatomía patológica. Este procedimientofue iniciado en el Instituto de Tumores de Milán en 1998, yestá adquiriendo gran difusión por su gran precisión, pudiendoconsiderarse como una nueva alternativa para la correcta extirpaciónde este tipo de lesiones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);19(2): 41-45, abr.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050342</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Localización de lesiones no palpables de mama mediante utilización de radiofármacos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
