<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153022</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic restraint management in Intensive Care Units: Phenomenological approach to nursing reality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To identify nursing experience on physical restraint management in Critical Care Units. To analyse similarities and differences in nursing experience on physical restraint management according to the clinical context that they are involved in. Method: A multicentre phenomenological study was carried out including 14 Critical Care Units in Madrid, classified according to physical restraint use: Common/systematic use, lacking/personalised use, and mixed use. Five focus groups (23 participants were selected following purposeful sampling) were convened, concluding in data saturation. Data analysis was focused on thematic content analysis following Colaizzi's method. Findings: Six main themes: Physical restraint meaning in Critical Care Units, safety (self-retreat vital devices), contribution factors, feelings, alternatives, and pending issues. Although some themes are common to the 3 Critical Care Unit types, discourse differences are found as regards to indication, feelings, systematic use of pain and sedation measurement tools. Conclusions: In order to achieve real physical restraint reduction in Critical Care Units, it is necessary to have a deep understanding of restraints use in the specific clinical context. As self-retreat vital devices emerge as central concept, some interventions proposed in other settings could not be effective, requiring alternatives for critical care patients. Discourse variations laid out in the different Critical Care Unit types could highlight key items that determine the use and different attitudes towards physical restraint (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Gil, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toraño-Olivera, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-González, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acevedo-Nuevo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco-Rodríguez-Rey, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco-Sanz, TR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís-Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin-Rivera, BE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Láiz-Díez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comprender la experiencia vivida por los enfermeros respecto a la gestión de la inmovilización terapéutica en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos. Explorar similitudes y diferencias en la experiencia enfermera respecto al manejo de la inmovilización terapéutica según el medio en el que están insertos. Método: Estudio fenomenológico multicéntrico en 14 Unidades de Cuidados Críticos de la Comunidad de Madrid estratificadas según el uso de inmovilización terapéutica: frecuente/sistemático, escaso/individualizado y mixto. Recogida de datos: 5 grupos de discusión (23 participantes). Muestreo intencional por propósito. Tamaño muestral: hasta saturación de datos. Análisis crítico temático del contenido guiado por el método de Colaizzi. Resultados: Emergen 6 grandes temas: 1) significado de inmovilización terapéutica en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos, 2) seguridad (autorretirada de dispositivos de soporte vital), 3) factores favorecedores, 4) sentimientos, 5) alternativas y 6) problemas pendientes. Aunque se significan los mismos temas en los 3 tipos de unidades, se observan diferencias en el discurso (indicación, sentimientos, herramientas validadas para la medición de dolor, sedación&#133;). Conclusiones: Para conseguir una reducción real de la inmovilización terapéutica en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos, resulta clave la comprensión profunda de su uso en el medio específico. Al identificarse como eje central la autorretirada de dispositivos de soporte vital, algunas medidas propuestas en otros ámbitos podrían no resultar pertinentes, precisándose alternativas encaminadas a pacientes críticos. Las variaciones del discurso planteadas en los distintos tipos de unidades podrían arrojar luz sobre los puntos clave que determinan las diferencias de uso y actitudes hacia la inmovilización terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;27(2): 62-74, jun. 2016. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la inmovilización terapéutica en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos: aproximación fenomenológica a la realidad enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7285^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
