<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158683</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low-dose computed tomography to diagnose fetal bone dysplasias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of cleidocranial dysplasia diagnosed by low-dose fetal computed tomography (CT) in the 25th week of gestation. Severe bone dysplasia was suspected because of the fetus&#146; low percentile in long bones length and the appearance of craniosynostosis on sonography. CT found no abnormalities incompatible with life. The effective dose was 5 mSv, within the recommended range for this type of examination. Low-dose fetal CT is a new technique that makes precision study of the bony structures possible from the second trimester of pregnancy. In Spain, abortion is legal even after the 22nd week of gestation in cases of severe fetal malformations. Therefore, in cases in which severe bone dysplasia is suspected, radiologists must know the strategies for reducing the dose of radiation while maintaining sufficient diagnostic quality, and they must also know which bony structures to evaluate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guasp Vizcaíno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Filardi, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fernández-Montes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de displasia cleidocraneal diagnosticado en la semana 25 de gestación mediante tomografía computarizada (TC) de baja dosis fetal. La sospecha era de displasia ósea grave debido al percentil bajo en los huesos largos y la apariencia ecográfica de craneosinostosis. La TC no demostró alteraciones incompatibles con la vida. La dosis efectiva de la prueba fue de 5 mSv, dentro del rango recomendado para estas exploraciones. La TC de baja dosis fetal es una técnica emergente que permite estudiar estructuras óseas con precisión a partir del segundo trimestre de gestación. En España, es legalmente posible interrumpir el embarazo en caso de malformación grave del feto incluso si se sobrepasa la semana 22 de gestación. Por tanto, ante la sospecha de una displasia ósea grave, el radiólogo debe conocer las estrategias para disminuir la dosis manteniendo una calidad diagnóstica suficiente, y conocer las estructuras óseas que debe evaluar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);58(6): 496-500, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tomografía computarizada fetal de baja dosis para diagnosticar displasias óseas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26453^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2998^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2998^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
