<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87784</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of body composition measures by dual X-ray absortiometry, bioimpedance and skinfolds in women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Comparative study of body composition measures by dualX-ray absortiometry, bioimpedance and skinfolds in womenBody composition assessments are important importantmeasurements for the diagnosis and monitoring of obesity. Thepresent study compared the body mass index (IMC) with body fatcontent estimated by skinfold (PT), bioelectric impedance (BIA) anddual X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) in adult women (n = 91).Although body fat estimations between methods differed, correlationbetween the various body composition methods was positive andstatistically significant (IMC-BIA, DEXA, PT: 0.902, 0.780, 0.722,respectively; BIA-DEXA, PT: 0.794 y 0.674 respectively; DEXA-PT:0.787, all correlations p &lt; 0.001). In relation to concordance indexesbetween measurements to classify individuals in normo- oroverweight, it was globally low, with the exception of theconcordance between body mass index with bioimpedance, whichwas good, and body mass index with triceps skinfold, which wasacceptable. In conclusion, the outcomes obtained in the present studysuggest that body fat content estimation can be very differentdepending on the method employed but the good correlation existingbetween methods permits to compare body fat content evolutionduring a dietary intervention, if the analysis is always performed bythe same method in the same individual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, J. Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Diez, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas-Carretero, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Morentín, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Ruiz de Eguilaz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las medidas de composición corporal son herramientas normalmenteempleadas para el diagnóstico y seguimiento de la obesidad.En el presente trabajo se estudiaron las diferencias entre el índice demasa corporal (IMC), contenido de grasa medido por pliegues cutáneos(PT), impedancia bioeléctrica (BIA) y absorciometría dual derayos-X (DEXA), como métodos de medida de composición corporalen mujeres adultas (n = 91). Aunque la estimación de grasa corporalentre los métodos fue diferente, la correlación entre las medidasde composición corporal fue positiva (IMC-BIA, DEXA, PT: 0,902,0,780, 0,722, respectivamente; BIA-DEXA, PT: 0,794 y 0,674 respectivamente;DEXA-PT: 0,787, todas las correlaciones p &lt; 0,001) yestadísticamente significativa. En cuanto a la concordancia entremétodos para clasificar individuos en normopeso o sobrepeso, fueen general baja, excepto en el caso del índice de masa corporal conla bioimpedancia, que fue buena, y el índice de masa corporalcon la medida del pliegue tricipital, que fue aceptable. En conclusión, los resultados de este estudio apuntan a que la medida delcontenido de grasa puede ser diferente en función del método deestimación empleado, pero la buena correlación entre ellos permitecomparar la evolución del contenido de grasa durante una intervencióndietética, siempre y cuando se tome como referencia el mismoaparato para un mismo individuo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;76(2): 209-222, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de medidas de composición corporal por absorciometría dual de rayos X, bioimpedancia y pliegues cutáneos en mujeres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
