<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82780</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of lumbar sympathectomy in the treatment of occlusive peripheral vascular disease in lower limbs: Systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objectives: The aim of this work has been to check the scientific evidence on the efficacy of lumbar sympathectomy in the treatment of peripheral arterial disease of lower limbs. Material and Methods: Systematic review of the literature. Data Source: MedLine, Embase, Cochrane Library, INHATA, CRD, BioMed Central, and ClinicalTrials.gov register. Mesh terms: sympathectomy, peripheral vascular disease, lower extremity, vascular therapy, iliac artery, femoral artery, popliteal artery. Inclusion criteria: adult patients with occlusive peripheral arterial disease of lower limbs treated with sympathectomy. The quality was evaluated by means of the criteria of the CASP checklist and &#147;ad hoc&#148; questionnaire. Results: Four clinical trials and four observational studies were included. Sympathectomy did not show significant differences for mortality, amputations and grade of intermittent claudication. When it was assessed regarding local anaesthetics or prostaglandin-E1, differences were not detected. Chemical sympathectomy showed better results than surgical sympathectomy in hospital stance.Conclusions: Evidence on the efficacy of sympathectomy does not show differences related to conventional treatments. Both sympathectomy techniques (surgical and chemical) do not report statistical differences regarding mortality or amputations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Aragón, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Calderón, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y Objetivos: Este trabajo revisa la efectividad de la simpatectomía lumbar en el tratamiento de la enfermedad arterial periférica de miembros inferiores mediante una revisión sistemática. Material y Método: Revisión sistemática de la bibliografía. Fuentes de datos utilizadas: Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library, INHATA, CRD, BioMed Central y el registro de ensayos clínicos ClinicalTrials.gov. Los términos MeSH usados fueron &#147;sympathectomy&#148;, &#147;peripheral vascular disease&#148;, &#147;lower extremity&#148;, &#147;vascular therapy&#148;, &#147;iliac artery&#148;, &#147;femoral artery&#148; y &#147;popliteal artery&#148;. Se incluyeron pacientes adultos con arteriopatía periférica oclusiva de miembros inferiores tratados con simpatectomía lumbar. La calidad de los estudios se evaluó mediante los criterios del listado de comprobación CASP (Critical Appraisal Skills Programme) y un cuestionario realizado ad hoc. Resultados: Se incluyeron 4 ensayos clínicos y 4 estudios observacionales. La simpatectomía no aportó diferencias significativas en cuanto a mortalidad, amputaciones y gravedad de la claudicación intermitente. Cuando se valoró frente a anestésicos locales o prostaglandina E1 tampoco hubo diferencias. La simpatectomía química registró mejores resultados en relación con la estancia hospitalaria que la simpatectomía quirúrgica.Conclusiones: La evidencia sobre la eficacia de la simpatectomía no ofrece diferencias en relación con los tratamientos farmacológicos convencionales. Ambas técnicas de simpatectomía (quirúrgica y química) no presentan diferencias estadísticamente significativas en términos de mortalidad ni amputaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);134(11): 477-482, abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82780</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la simpatectomía lumbar en el tratamiento de la arteriopatía periférica oclusiva de miembros inferiores: revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13942^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8335^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
