<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80443</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional epidemiological overlap in Latin America</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In Latin America is being lived a controversial epidemiologic situation with regard to the nutritional state of its inhabitants due to the coexistence of malnutrition and obesity. The purpose of this study is to carry out a reflexive analysis about that nutritional epidemiological superposition. Method: A critical and discussion review has been made according to the main results observed by means of a descriptive cross-sectional bibliographic study.Results: The 32 selected papers illustrate that Latin America is living a period of transition between the famine and the non- transmissible illness related to nutrition. Malnutrition persists with an increase of obesity registered in all the countries and affecting mainly women and children. Nutritional problems are determining a high morbility and they are one of the firsts mortality causes.Conclusions: The articles studied are heterogeneous in methodology, field, time and objectives considered, although all of them decribe the evolution and magnitude of the problem in the different Latin American countries. There is not MeSH (Medical Subject Headings) descriptor to index properly the scientific production about nutricional transition(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wanden-Berghe, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En Iberoamérica se vive una situación epidemiológica absurdamente paradójica respecto al estado nutricional de sus habitantes, coexistiendo la desnutrición con la obesidad. El propósito de este trabajo es realizar un análisis reflexivo sobre esta superposición epidemiológica nutricional.Método: Se ha realizado una revisión crítica y de discusión de los principales resultados observados mediante un estudio bibliográfico descriptivo transversal.Resultados: Los 32 artículos seleccionados ponen de manifiesto que Iberoamérica vive un momento de transición entre la hambruna y las enfermedades no transmisibles relacionadas con la nutrición. La desnutrición persiste con un incremento de la obesidad registrado en todos los países, que afecta mayoritariamente a las mujeres y a la población infantil. Los problemas nutricionales están condicionando una alta morbilidad y se constituyen como una de las primeras causas de mortalidad.Conclusiones: Los artículos estudiados son heterogéneos en metodología, ámbito, tiempo de realización y objetivos contemplados, aunque describen la magnitud del problema y la evolución que ha seguido en los diferentes países iberoamericanos. No existe un descriptor MeSH (Medical Subject Headings) que indexe adecuadamente la producción científica sobre transición nutricional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(1): 5-8, ene.-mar.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Superposición epidemiológica nutricional en Latinoamérica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50330</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50331</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
