<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036326</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The development of the physical therapy in educative centers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of the physical therapy in educative centers has characteristics different from those from other scopes of performance. Physiotherapist exerts its functions in a pedagogical context, where the objective is the formation of children and young people, sharing with all the scholastic community east intention. The effective legal norm in the Comunidad Autónoma de la Región de Murcia, from year 2003, it gathers the differentiating aspects of the development of the physical therapy in this frame, and it regulates the functions of physiotherapist agreed with the characteristics of the job. This article the competitions are delimited and defined that physiotherapist makes in this context, explaining which concrete activities need for the exercise the profession and the characteristics the children and young people to whom it goes directed his performance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jaso Margarit, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Conesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de la fisioterapia en centros educativos tiene unas características diferentes a las de otros ámbitos de actuación. El fisioterapeuta ejerce sus funciones en un contexto pedagógico, donde el objetivo es la formación de niños y jóvenes, compartiendo con toda la comunidad escolar este propósito. La normativa legal vigente en la Comunidad Autónoma de Murcia, desde el año 2003, recoge los aspectos diferenciadores del desarrollo de la fisioterapia en este marco, y regula las funciones de fisioterapeuta acorde con las características del puesto de trabajo. En este artículo se delimitan y definen las competencias que realiza el fisioterapeuta en este contexto, explicando las actividades concretas que necesita para el ejercicio de la profesión y las características de los niños y jóvenes a los que va dirigida su actuación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);27(3): 146-151, may.-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de la fisioterapia en centros de educación primaria y secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12955^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
