<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97787</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The doctor facing death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Changes arise in relation to death throughout history. Collect the most significant speech of the process of a group of doctors whose task was to work on the doctor-patient relationship, analyzing the emerging arising in relation to the issue of death. Are evident in the medical defense mechanisms of denial intense face of death of patients over the more complex relationship with his own death. We work on these anxieties and defense mechanisms in noting that the task force is a useful tool for preparing for difficult medical problems facing the death of patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Esteban, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se plantean los cambios en relación a la muerte a lo largo de la historia. Se recoge el discurso más significativo del proceso de un grupo de médicos cuya tarea era trabajar sobre la relación médico-paciente, analizando los emergentes surgidos en relación a la problemática de la muerte. Se evidencian en los médicos mecanismos defensivos de negación muy intensos frente a la muerte de los pacientes, mayores cuanto más compleja es su propia vinculación con la muerte. Se trabajan estas ansiedades y mecanismos defensivos en grupo operativo observando que es un instrumento de gran utilidad para la elaboración de estas dificultades de los médicos frente a la problemática de la muerte de los pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;32(113): 67-82, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El médico frente a la muerte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
