<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044060</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction in acute myocardial infarction mortality over a five-year period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To assess recent changes in the management of patients with acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and their impact on mortality using data from the PRIAMHO I and II registries (1995 and 2000). Pacients and method. Of the 168 public hospitals in Spain, 24 and 58 contributed to the 1995 and 2000 PRIAMHO registries, respectively. Results. Patients in the PRIAMHO II registry (n=6221) were significantly older, more often female, and proportionally more likely to have coronary risk factors or a previous myocardial infarction, or to have undergone revascularization than those in PRIAMHO I (n=5242). Reperfusion therapy was administered more often (46.9% vs 41.9%, P&lt;.001) and earlier (48 min vs 60 min, P&lt;.001). Antiplatelet drugs were given to 96.1% vs 89.1% of patients, beta-blockers to 51.1% vs 30.1%, and ACE inhibitors to 41.6% vs 24.9% (P&lt;.001 for all comparisons). In addition, 28-day mortality was 11.3% and 14.2% (P&lt;.001), respectively, and one-year mortality, 16.4% and 18.5% (P&lt;.001), respectively. The adjusted hazard ratio for mortality at one year in PRIAMHO II compared with PRIAMHO I was 0.78 (95% CI, 0.70-0.86, P&lt;.001; adjusted for age, sex, diabetes, smoking, dyslipemia, hypertension, previous MI and CABG, ST-elevation status and Killip class at admission, and hospital characteristics). Conclusions. Even though patients registered in 2000 formed a higher risk group than those registered in 1995, one-year mortality after AMI decreased by 22% over the five-year period. This improvement was due to more frequent and earlier reperfusion therapy and better use of antithrombotics, beta-blockers and ACE inhibitors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arós, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Magda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ancillo, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subirana, Isaac</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loma-Osorio, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pabón, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Analizar los cambios en el tratamiento de los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio y su repercusión en la mortalidad en los registros PRIAMHO I y II (1995 y 2000). Pacientes y método. De los 168 hospitales públicos españoles, 24 y 58 participaron en los registros PRIAMHO I y II, respectivamente. Resultados. En el registro PRIAMHO II (n = 6.221) comparado con el registro PRIAMHO I (n = 5.242) había un mayor porcentaje de pacientes mayores y más mujeres, y los pacientes tenían una mayor proporción de factores de riesgo coronario, infarto de miocardio previo y revascularización. Asimismo, el tratamiento de reperfusión se administró con más frecuencia (el 46,9 frente al 41,9%; p &lt; 0,001) y más rápidamente (48 frente a 60 min; p &lt; 0,001). Se administró tratamiento antiagregante al 96,1 frente al 89,1% de los pacientes, bloqueadores beta al 51,1 frente al 30,1% e inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina al 41,6 frente al 24,9% (p &lt; 0,001 para todos los casos). La mortalidad a los 28 días y al año fue del 11,3 y el 14,2% (p &lt; 0,001) y del 16,4 y el 18,5% (p &lt; 0,001), respectivamente. La hazard ratio ajustada de la mortalidad a 1 año en PRIAMHO II en comparación con PRIAMHO I fue de 0,78 (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,70-0,86), con un valor de p &lt; 0,001 (ajustado por edad, sexo, diabetes, tabaquismo, dislipemia, hipertensión, antecedentes de infarto de miocardio y revascularización, elevación del segmento ST y clase de Killip en el momento del ingreso, y características del hospital). Conclusiones. Aunque los pacientes registrados en el año 2000 formaban un grupo de mayor riesgo, la mortalidad al año se redujo en un 22% en el período de 5 años. Los factores causantes de esta mejoría son la administración más rápida y frecuente de tratamiento de reperfusión y un mayor uso de fármacos antitrombóticos, bloqueadores beta e inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(3): 200-208, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción de la mortalidad por infarto agudo de miocardio en un período de 5 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
