<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118000</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ambulatory blood pressure measurement is indispensable to good clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traditional clinic or office blood pressure measurement (OBPM) is limited in the amount of information it can provide for the adequate management of hypertension; ambulatory blood pressure measurement (ABPM), which can diagnose white coat hypertension in as many as 20% of people who appear to have hypertension with OBPM, and masked hypertension which may affect 10 and 20% of the population, is a vastly superior technique. Furthermore, nighttime BP measured by ABPM is superior to OBPM in predicting cardiovascular events. Perhaps the greatest value for ABPM will be to enable blood pressure control in the aging community, thereby leading to prevention of stroke. There should be an imperative to change contemporary clinical practice if we are to avert the burden of stroke and heart failure in an aged population. We have adequate drugs to achieve effective BP lowering in the vast majority of patients; what we lack is the determination to achieve effective BP control as early as possible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>O&#146;Brien, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La información que la medida tradicional de la presión arterial (PA) en la consulta (o en el hospital) (MPAC) puede proporcionar para el manejo adecuado de la hipertensión es limitada. Es una técnica muy superior la monitorización ambulatoria de la PA (MAPA), que puede diagnosticar la hipertensión de bata blanca en hasta el 20% de los que parecen tener hipertensión con MPAC, y la hipertensión enmascarada, que puede afectar a un 10-20% de la población. La PA nocturna medida por MAPA también es superior a MPAC en la predicción de acontecimientos cardiovasculares. Quizás el valor más importante de la MAPA es que puede monitorizar la PA en la comunidad de ancianos, con prevención de ictus. Es imperativo cambiar la práctica clínica contemporánea si queremos evitar la carga de ictus e insuficiencia cardíaca en los ancianos. Tenemos medicamentos apropiados para bajar la PA con eficacia en la gran mayoría de los pacientes. Lo que nos hace falta es tener la determinación para lograr un control eficaz de la PA tan pronto como sea posible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;26(5): 213-217, sep.-oct. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118000</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La monitorización ambulatoria de la presión arterial es imprescindible para la buena práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
