<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32594</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural disorders in Alzheimer's disease. Data from a populational study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. The purpose of this work was to study the characteristics of the behavioural disorders (non-cognitive or neuropsychiatric symptoms) presented by subjects with Alzheimer&#146;s disease from a sample of the population together with their relation to the cognitive and functional impairment suffered by these patients. Patients and methods. NEDICES is a longitudinal populational study based on the census of neurological diseases in subjects above the age of 64. In 2001, a study was conducted of the situation of 83 subjects who had started suffering from Alzheimer&#146;s disease between 1994 and 1997. Due to death and a number of other reasons, only 32 of them could be examined. Patients were administered a structured interview with scales referring to the cognitive state, functional capacity, severity of the dementia and the presence and severity of neuropsychiatric disorders. Results. All the patients studied presented some non-cognitive symptom. Apathy was the most frequent (93.8%), followed by irritability (81.1%), anxiety (75.0%), dysphoria (71.8%) and agitation-aggressiveness (56.2%). The least frequent were deliria (50.2%), altered nocturnal behaviour and aberrant motor activity (37.6%), altered appetite and eating, and hallucinations (24.9%), disinhibition (21.8%) and euphoria (21.6%). The degree of cognitive impairment and the presence of non-cognitive symptoms exerted a similar and independent effect on functional capacity. Only 56.3% of the patients were treated with some kind of anticholinesterase or psychotropic medication. Conclusions. Our census-based populational study confirmed the high prevalence rate of non-cognitive symptoms in patients with Alzheimer&#146;s disease. These data confirm the notion that these symptoms are intrinsic manifestations of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Investigar las características de las alteraciones del comportamiento (síntomas no cognitivos o neuropsiquiátricos) que presentan los sujetos con enfermedad de Alzheimer procedentes de una muestra poblacional y su relación con el deterioro cognitivo y funcional que muestran estos pacientes. Pacientes y métodos. El NEDICES es un estudio poblacional longitudinal basado en el censo sobre enfermedades neurológicas en sujetos mayores de 64 años. En 2001 se estudió la situación de 83 sujetos que habían iniciado una enfermedad de Alzheimer entre 1994 y 1997. Sólo pudieron examinarse 32, debido a fallecimientos y a otras causas. Se realizó una entrevista estructurada con escalas referentes a la situación cognitiva, la capacidad funcional, la gravedad de la demencia y la presencia y gravedad de alteraciones neuropsiquiátricas. Resultados. Todos los pacientes estudiados presentaban algún síntoma no cognitivo. La apatía fue el más frecuente (93,8 por ciento), seguido por la irritabilidad (81,1 por ciento), la ansiedad (75,0 por ciento), la disforia (71,8 por ciento) y la agitación-agresión (56,2 por ciento). Los menos frecuentes fueron los delirios (50,2 por ciento), las alteraciones del comportamiento nocturno y la actividad motora aberrante (37,6 por ciento), las alteraciones del apetito y la alimentación y las alucinaciones (24,9 por ciento), la desinhibición (21,8 por ciento) y la euforia (21,6 por ciento). El grado del deterioro cognitivo y la presencia de síntomas no cognitivos tuvieron una influencia similar e independiente sobre la capacidad funcional. Sólo el 56,3 por ciento de los pacientes se trataban con algún tipo de medicación anticolinesterásica o psicotrópica. Conclusiones. Confirmamos en un estudio poblacional con base en el censo la alta prevalencia de síntomas no cognitivos en los pacientes con enfermedad de Alzheimer; este dato reafirma que estos síntomas son manifestaciones intrínsecas de la enfermedad. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(10): 901-905, mayo 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones del comportamiento en la enfermedad de Alzheimer. Datos de un estudio poblacional</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vega Quiroga, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, M de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Pareja, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32594</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12471</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
