<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80835</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic transumbilical cholecystectomy. Results with the gel device and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The appearance of single transumbilical incision surgery has opened a new era in the minimally invasive approach of cholecystectomy. Specific ports for this technique have made it easier to perform. Introduction We report our initial experience, from July 2008 to June 2009 and give an updated bibliographic review. Patients and methods A prospective, longitudinal and interventional study that included 30 patients with symptomatic cholelithiasis, from 10 July 2008 to 30 June 2009, on whom a single transumbilical incision laparoscopic cholecystectomy was performed (LESS technique), without other minilaparoscopic ports or traction stitches. Patients and methods A gel port was used for all surgeries (R-Port, Tri-Port®), as well as straight and roticulating laparoscopic graspers. Patients and methods Surgical time, analgesia requirements, postoperative hospital stay, conversions and complications were registered. Results The median age was 34.8 years (range, from 21 to 53), with a BMI between 21kg/m2 and 39.5kg/m2 (mean 25.8kg/m2). Surgical time was 65.1 minutes (ranging from 40 to 150) and postoperative length stay was less than 24 hours. Postoperative pain was measured with the VAS scale, giving a low score. Up to now, two wound infections and a bile leak have been observed. Conclusions LESS cholecystectomy is a safe and feasible technique performed by experienced surgeons in minimally invasive surgery, and requires a greater learning curve than that of the conventional laparoscopic cholecystectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Diez,  Federico del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Sancho Téllez,  Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Hove,  Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garijo Álvarez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Elosua,  Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez López, José Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Jiménez, Jesus</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La aparición de la cirugía con una única incisión transumbilical ha venido a abrir una nueva época en el abordaje mínimamente invasivo de la colecistectomía. La existencia de puertos específicos para este abordaje facilita su realización. Introducción Presentamos la experiencia inicial de nuestro grupo, entre julio de 2008 y junio de 2009 y una puesta al día de la bibliografía sobre el tema. Pacientes y método Se realizó un estudio prospectivo, longitudinal y de intervención, que incluyó a 30 pacientes con colelitiasis sintomática, entre el 10 de julio de 2008 y el 30 de junio de 2009, a los que se les realizó una colecistectomía por una única incisión transumbilical (técnica laparoendoscopic single site surgery), sin apoyo en otros puertos de minilaparoscopia ni puntos tractores. Pacientes y método Las intervenciones se realizaron utilizando un puerto de gel (R-Port®, Tri-Port®) y pinzas de laparoscopia rectas convencionales y articuladas. Pacientes y método Se estudiaron el tiempo quirúrgico, la necesidad de analgesia postoperatoria, la estancia media, las conversiones y las complicaciones. Resultados La edad media fue de 34,8 años (rangos que fluctúan entre 21 y 53 años), con un body mass index de entre 21 y 39,5kg/m2 (media de 25,8kg/m2). La duración media de la intervención fue de 65,1min (rango que varía entre 40 y 150min) y la estancia media fue menor de 24h. El dolor postoperatorio medido con la escala visual analógica fue bajo. Hasta la fecha se han presentado 2 infecciones de herida y una fuga biliar. Conclusiones La colecistectomía laparoendoscopic single site surgery es una operación técnicamente reproducible por cirujanos con experiencia en cirugía mínimamente invasiva, segura, que requiere una curva de aprendizaje mayor que la colecistectomía laparoscópica convencional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);87(5): 293-298, mayo 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colecistectomía laparoscópica transumbilical. Resultados con el dispositivo de gel y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
