<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043040</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Underlying causes of recurrent pneumonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the relative frequency and describe the predisposing causes of recurrent pneumonia in infants and children aged between 1 month and 14 years.                 Methods: We retrospectively reviewed the medical records of a tertiary care pediatric hospital covering a 10-year period, from January 1994 through December 2003. Children with cystic fibrosis were not included in the analysis. Recurrent pneumonia was defined as at least two pneumonia episodes in a 1 year period or at least three episodes over a lifetime.                 Results: Of 1644 children hospitalized with pneumonia, 106 (6.4 %) met the criteria for recurrent pneumonia. An underlying cause was identified in 92 patients (86.7 %). Of these, the underlying cause was diagnosed prior to pneumonia in 67 (72.8 %), during the first episode in 12 (13 %) and during recurrence in 13 (14.1 %). Underlying causes included asthma in 28 patients (30.4 %), congenital cardiac defects in 27 patients (29.3 %), aspiration syndrome in 25 patients (27.1 %), immune disorder in nine patients (9.7 %), pulmonary anomalies in two patients (2.1 %), and anhidrotic ectodermal dysplasia in one patient (1 %).                 Conclusions: Recurrent pneumonia occurred in 6.4 % of all children hospitalized for pneumonia. The underlying cause was identified in 86.7 % of the children. The most common causes were asthma, congenital cardiac defects, and aspiration syndrome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Micó, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezuelo Huerta, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frontera Izquierdo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abeledo Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la frecuencia relativa y describir las causas subyacentes de la neumonía recurrente en niños de un mes a 14 años de edad.                 Métodos: Revisión de las historias clínicas de un hospital terciario en un período de 10 años, desde enero de 1994 hasta diciembre de 2003. No se incluyeron los niños con fibrosis quística. Se define neumonía recurrente como al menos dos episodios de neumonía en un período de un año, o al menos tres episodios en cualquier período.                 Resultados: De los 1.644 niños hospitalizados por neumonía, 106 (6,4 %) cumplían los criterios de neumonía recurrente. Se diagnosticó una causa subyacente en 92 (86,7 %). De los 92 niños, en 67 (72,8 %) la causa subyacente se conocía antes de la neumonía, en 12 (el 13 %) fue diagnosticada en el primer episodio neumónico y en 13 (14,1 %) no se diagnosticó hasta después de la recurrencia. Las causas subyacentes fueron asma en 28 casos (30,4 %), cardiopatía congénita en 27 casos (29,3 %), síndrome de aspiración en 25 casos (27,1 %), inmunodeficiencia en 9 casos (9,7 %), anomalías pulmonares en 2 casos (2,1 %) y displasia ectodérmica anhidrótica en un caso (1 %).                 Conclusiones: La neumonía recurrente constituye el 6,4 % del total de niños hospitalizados por neumonía. Se identificó la causa subyacente en el 86,7 % de los casos. El asma, la cardiopatía congénita y el síndrome de aspiración fueron las causas más frecuentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(5): 409-412, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas subyacentes de neumonía recurrente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
