<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161022</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of CONUT against NRS-2002 in the assessment of nutritional risk in hemato-oncology patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Early detection of nutritional risk in patients with hematologic cancer through appropriate screening is of vital importance. The Nutrition Control method (CONUT) identifies patients with nutritional risk based on the determination of albumin, total cholesterol and total lymphocytes while the Nutritional Risk Screening (NRS-2002) test is identified as subjective, gives a specific score for patients with Hematological cancer. Objectives: To compare the prevalence of nutritional risk between these two tools, as well as to describe their utility in this population. Material and Method: Cross-sectional study, with nutritional risk assessment by CONUT and NRS-2002, carried out in the area of hospitalization of the Hemato-oncology service of the National Cancer Institute in Mexico City. Statistical analysis was performed using Pearson chi2 test, ANOVA, sensitivity and specificity tests, and comparison of medians. Results: A total of 94 patients participated, of which 43% were women and 57% were men. The median age was 32 years. According to the assessment of nutritional risk measured with CONUT, 41% of the patients presented low nutritional alert, 29% moderate and 30% high. The NRS-2002 detected 48% of patients without risk of malnutrition and 52% with risk. Using the NRS-2002 as the gold standard, CONUT had a sensitivity of 73% and a specificity of 57%. Greater sensitivity and specificity were observed in the elderly group (100 and 75%, respectively). Discussion: The prevalence of malnutrition with both tests is high, according to Nutritional Risk Screening the related risk factors are weight loss and age. CONUT has not been specifically validated for the hemato-oncologic patient, in this study we found that it has a low sensitivity and specificity probably due to metabolic alterations due to the disease and / or alterations in the biochemical values provoked by the antineoplastic treatment, However, the test shows greater sensitivity and specificity in the group of older adults, the probable relationship in this age group is the predisposition to present greater weight loss and protein loss, although more studies will be needed to confirm this fact. Conclusions: More than 50% of the sample of this study had nutritional risk with both sieves. The older the age, the greater the frequency of nutritional risk. CONUT was not an adequate diagnostic test for hematologic cancer patients, however, it may be useful in the older adult group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baltazar Luna, Eréndira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chico Barba, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Alvarez, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sámano, Reyna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La detección temprana del riesgo nutricional en pacientes con cáncer hematológico a través de tamizajes apropiados es de vital importancia. El método de Control Nutricional (CONUT) detecta a los pacientes con riesgo nutricional basado en la determinación de albúmina, colesterol total y linfocitos totales mientras que el Nutritional Risk Screening (NRS-2002) prueba identificada como subjetiva, otorga una puntuación específica para pacientes con cáncer hematológico. Objetivos: Comparar la prevalencia de riesgo nutricional entre estas dos herramientas, así como describir su utilidad en esta población. Material y Método: Diseño transversal, con evaluación del riesgo nutricional por CONUT y NRS-2002, realizado en el área de hospitalización del servicio de Hemato-oncología del Instituto Nacional de Cancerología en la Ciudad de México. El análisis estadístico se realizó con la prueba chi2 de Pearson, ANOVA, pruebas de sensibilidad y especificidad y comparación de medianas. Resultados: Participaron 94 pacientes de los cuales el 43% eran mujeres y el 57% hombres. La mediana de edad fue de 32 años. De acuerdo a la valoración del riesgo nutricional medido con el CONUT el 41% de los pacientes presentaban alerta nutricional baja, el 29% moderada y el 30% alta. El NRS-2002 detectó al 48% de los pacientes sin riesgo de desnutrición y el 52% con riesgo. Tomando como estándar de oro el NRS-2002, el CONUT presentó una sensibilidad del 73% y una especificidad de 57%. En el grupo de adultos mayores se observó mayor sensibilidad y especificidad (100 y 75% respectivamente). Discusión: La prevalencia de desnutrición con ambas pruebas es elevada, de acuerdo al Nutritional Risk Screening los factores de riesgo relacionados son la pérdida de peso y edad. El CONUT no ha sido validado específicamente para el paciente hemato-oncológico, en este estudio encontramos que tiene una sensibilidad y especificidad bajas probablemente debido a las alteraciones metabólicas por el padecimiento y/o a las alteraciones en los valores bioquímicos provocadas por el tratamiento antineoplásico, sin embargo, la prueba muestra mayor sensibilidad y especificidad en el grupo de adultos mayores, la probable relación en este grupo de edad es la predisposición a presentar mayor pérdida de peso y pérdida proteica, aunque se necesitarán más estudios para confirmar este hecho. Conclusiones: Más del 50% de la muestra de este estudio tuvo riesgo nutricional con ambos tamizajes. A mayor edad mayor frecuencia de riesgo nutricional. Estadísticamente CONUT no fue una prueba diagnóstica adecuada para la población con cáncer hematológico estudiada, sin embargo, puede ser útil en el grupo del adulto mayor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(1): 17-23, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del CONUT frente al NRS-2002 en la valoración del riesgo nutricional en pacientes hemato-oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
