<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69172</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate lung function abnormalities in children who underwent haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) and to compare these abnormalities between autologous and allogenic transplantation. Patients and methods: Prospective observational study from 1996 to 2005. Ninety-three children receiving HSCT, 47 autologous and 46 allogenic, were included. Lung function tests were performed before transplantation and at 2, 6, 12 and 24 months afterwards. The following indices were determined: forced expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV1), FEV1/ forced vital capacity (FVC), total lung capacity (TLC), and carbon monoxide diffusing capacity (DLCO). Paired Student's t-test was used for statistical analysis of data. Results: Before HSCT, 6,8 % of the children had FEV1 &lt; 80 %, 1 % FEV1/FVC &lt; 80 %, 7,8 % TLC &lt; 80 % and 13.5 % DLCO &lt; 70 %. At 2 months, FEV1/FVC, TLC and DLCO were significantly reduced, when compared to pre-transplantation values (p=0.05, 0.011 and p &lt; 0.001, respectively). Lung function gradually improved from 6 months post-transplantation, but did not reach pre-transplantation values at 24 months. No significant differences were found when comparing allogenic and autologous transplantation, apart from a lower FEV1/ FVC value at 6 months (p=0.02) in the first group. Conclusions: An important proportion of children who undergo HSCT have early pulmonary abnormalities (at 2 and 6 months after transplantation) with partial recovery at 24 months (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Vicent, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Pérez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Asensi, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle Cabrera, T. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madero López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las alteraciones de la función pulmonar en niños tras un trasplante de progenitores hematopoyéticos. Comparar dichas alteraciones tras realizar un trasplante autólogo y un trasplante alogénico. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional, prospectivo, desde 1996 hasta 2005. Se realizó un test de función pulmonar a 93 niños sometidos a trasplante, 47 con trasplante autólogo y 46 con trasplante alogénico, antes del trasplante y a los 2, 6, 12 y 24 meses posteriores a éste. Se determinaron las alteraciones en el volumen espiratorio forzado en un segundo (FEV1), FEV1/capacidad vital forzada (FCV), capacidad pulmonar total (TLC) y capacidad de difusión (DLCO). Se realizó un análisis estadístico de los datos mediante comparación de medias de datos relacionados. Resultados: Antes de la realización del trasplante, el 6,8 % de los pacientes presentó FEV1 inferior al 80 %, el 1 % presentó FEV1/FVC inferior al 80 %, el 7,8 % tuvo TLC inferior al 80 % y el 13,5 % presentó una alteración aislada de la DLCO. Todos los parámetros empeoraron tras el trasplante, y dicho empeoramiento fue máximo a los 2 y a los 6 meses posteriores al trasplante. A los 6 meses, el 8 % de los niños presentó FEV1/FVC inferior al 80 %, un 25 % presentó TLC inferior al 80 % y otro 13 % DLCO inferior al 70 % con el resto de los parámetros normales. A partir de los 6 meses la función pulmonar mejoró, pero a los 2 años no había llegado al punto inicial. Fueron estadísticamente significativos el descenso de FEV1/FVC a los 2 meses (p=0,05), de TLC a los 2 meses (p=0,011) y DLCO a los 2 meses (p &lt; 0,001). No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre trasplantes autólogos y alogénicos salvo por FEV1/FVC, más alterado en el grupo de pacientes sometidos a trasplantes alogénicos a los 6 meses (p=0,02). Conclusiones: Tras el trasplante de progenitores se producen importantes alteraciones de la función pulmonar, sobre todo en los primeros 2 meses posteriores al trasplante, con una mejoría posterior a partir de los 6 meses, que no alcanza los valores previos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);69(5): 406-412, nov. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69172</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8727^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6547^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6547^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2098^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
