<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153989</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The patients and their diagnosis at La Castañeda General Asylum. An approach from quantitative history (México, 1910-1968)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During its 58 years in operation (1910-1968), the Manicomio General La Castañeda housed 61,480 people. In this paper, we present an overview of the general characteristic of the patients based on a 20% sample of the overall population. We divided the text in three sections: in the first part we argue that the history of the institution comprises three distinctive periods characterized by demographic changes that coincide with administrative reforms. In the second, we present the general characteristics of La Castañeda's psychiatric population. Finally, we describe the most salient demographic changes, which stemmed either from socio-political events, technological innovations or clinical transformations. Some of the most salient results of the analysis of the sample show that the inmate population had short periods of hospitalization in the asylum (an average of 18 month), as well as a lower mortality rate (24.2%) in comparison to contemporary mental institutions. Families played a fundamental role in the care of their mad relatives, which accounts for the relatively short periods of hospitalization as well as the low death rates. Consequently, for this particular institution, chronic patients weren't such a serious problem as believed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sacristán, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Molina, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordorika Sacristán, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Carrillo, Ximena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Manicomio General La Castañeda, fundado en la Ciudad de México, albergó a 61.480 pacientes entre 1910 y 1968. El objetivo de este artículo es presentar un panorama general de la población que ingresó a esta institución y los diagnósticos que recibieron los internos, análisis realizado a partir de una base de datos construida con una muestra de 20% de la población total. El artículo se divide en tres partes: en la primera, proponemos tres etapas para comprender la historia de La Castañeda cuya periodización es definida por cambios demográficos que coinciden con reformas administrativas; en la segunda, exponemos las características generales de la población psiquiátrica de La Castañeda; y finalmente, describimos los principales cambios demográficos, los cuales obedecieron a factores socio-políticos, innovaciones tecnológicas y transformaciones en la clínica. Como características principales de la población de La Castañeda tenemos la brevedad del encierro (18 meses en promedio) y la reducida mortalidad (23.8%) en comparación con otras instituciones del mismo tipo. En dicha circulación poblacional encontramos que las familias desempeñaron un papel determinante al asumir el cuidado de sus parientes locos. Así, el encierro prolongado de pacientes crónicos no fue un problema que aquejara al Manicomio General de forma tan severa como se ha creído (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;68(1): 0-0, ene.-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los pacientes del manicomio La Castañeda y sus diagnósticos. Una propuesta desde la historia cuantitativa (México, 1910-1968)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10600^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12003^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10600^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12003^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12004^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
