<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147228</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using didactic materials to promote educational values in basketball young teams</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to promote the teaching and learning of basketball from an educational perspective in the formative stages, Real Madrid Foundation Basketball Schools, through the research project entitled 'For a REAL Education: Values and Sport', has developed a series of teaching materials available to assist coaches and players develop the practice of basketball in the best educational context. These materials offer coaches the opportunity to improve their quality as teachers, both in training and competition, including the educational values in daily practice, making also participants the players and their families. The main objective of this study, after several seasons of project development, has been analyzed the use that the coaches make from the different didactic materials. The study population was 15 basketball coaches from Real Madrid Foundation Basketball Schools, with an average experience of 4.7 years. These teachers have trained a total of 580 male and female players from the youngest categories, U10, U12, U14 and U16. The instrument used was a questionnaire designed expressly with questions related to the study objective. The results indicate that most used material, to be considered useful, it has been a manual book called 'Introduction to Basketvalues' (68%); followed by the 'White Card' program (41%) and the paper 'Quarterly Player Assessment' (38.5%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Franco Martín, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Martín, Pedro Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Sánchez, Ana Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Vila, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán González, Luis Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Fuentes-Guerra, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la intención de promover la enseñanza y aprendizaje del baloncesto desde una perspectiva educativa en las etapas de formación, las Escuelas de Baloncesto de la Fundación Real Madrid, a través del proyecto de investigación denominado 'Por una Educación REAL: Valores y Deporte', ha elaborado una serie de materiales didácticos que permitan ayudar a los entrenadores y jugadores a desarrollar la práctica del baloncesto en el mejor contexto educativo. Dichos materiales ofrecen a los entrenadores la posibilidad de mejorar su calidad como docentes, tanto en los entrenamientos como la competición, incluyendo los valores educativos en la práctica diaria, haciendo también partícipes a los jugadores y sus familias. El objetivo principal de este estudio, después de varias temporadas de desarrollo del proyecto, ha sido analizar el uso que los entrenadores hacen de los diferentes materiales didácticos. La población de estudio ha sido 15 entrenadores de la Escuelas de baloncesto de la Fundación Real Madrid, con una experiencia media de 4,7 años. Estos docentes han entrenado a un total de 580 jugadores y jugadoras de las categorías benjamín, alevín, infantil y cadete. El instrumento utilizado fue un cuestionario diseñado ex profeso con preguntas vinculadas al objetivo del estudio. Los resultados indican que el material más usado, por ser considerado muy útil, ha sido un libro-manual denominado 'Iniciación al Valorcesto' (68%); le siguen el programa 'Tarjeta Blanca' (41%) y el documento de 'Evaluación Trimestral' (38,5%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 227-230, oct. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de materiales didácticos para fomentar valores educativos en baloncesto de formación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50133</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
