<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122355</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protrusion of acetabular screws as a cause of liner fracture in ceramic-on-ceramic total hip arthroplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fracture of the liner in ceramic-on-ceramic total hip arthroplasty is a rare event. In the case reports described in the literature, the reason is usually due to trauma or femoro-acetabular impingement because of excessive anteversion of the acetabular component. In this paper we present the case of a 54 year-old woman with a ceramic-on-ceramic total hip arthroplasty in which the liner broke because the acetabular screws heads were protruding in the joint cavity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Natera Cisnero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crusi, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La rotura del inserto en las artroplastias totales de cadera con par de fricción cerámica-cerámica es un hecho infrecuente y se suele producir por un traumatismo o un conflicto femoro-acetabular por excesiva anteversión del componente acetabular. Se presenta el caso de una mujer de 54 años portadora de una artroplastia total de cadera cerámica-cerámica en la que en un contexto atraumático se produjo rotura del inserto por protrusión articular de los tornillos acetabulares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);25(1): 37-39, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protrusión de los tornillos acetabulares como causa de rotura de inserto en artroplastia total de cadera cerámica-cerámica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53565^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36039^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30722^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2553^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53565^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53565^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36039^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
