<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151646</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The impact of the IL-1B, IL-1Ra, IL-2, IL-6 and IL-10 gene polymorphisms on the development of Behcet's disease and their association with the phenotype</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: This trial was designed to investigate the effects of the interleukin (IL)-1&amp;#946;, IL-1Ra, IL-2, IL-6, IL-10 gene polymorphisms on Behcet's disease (BD) occurrence and the association between the polymorphisms and the phenotype. Materials and method: The study population consisted of 71 patients and 70 age and gender-matched healthy subjects. Each of the participants had 2cc of blood withdrawn, which was placed into a whole blood tube, and the DNA was obtained using the NucleoSpin® Blood DNA Isolation kit. To display the band lengths, the products were amplified using the primary pairs of the interleukins investigated and developed in a 2% agarose gel. Results: There were no significant differences between the groups with respect to the IL-1Ra, IL-1&amp;#946;, IL-2, IL-6 and the IL-10 gene polymorphism distributions. In the patient group the IL-1RN2 gene polymorphism was detected to be statistically correlated with the presence of articular involvement (p = 0.0283) and the IL-1&amp;#946; gene polymorphism was statistically correlated with the presence of an ocular lesion (p = 0.0178). The evaluation of the IL-2 gene polymorphism (p = 0.0065) and IL-10 gene polymorphism (p = 0.0483) distributions with respect to age of BD onset revealed a statistically significant distribution. Conclusion: The statistical correlations between the articular involvement and IL-1RN, the ocular involvement and the IL-1&amp;#946;, and the age of disease onset and the IL-2 and IL-10 gene polymorphisms, detected for the first time in the literature, suggest that these polymorphisms could be statistically associated with the disease symptoms and used as prognostic factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bar&amp;#305;&amp;#351;, Sava&amp;#351;</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akyol, Mesut</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dursun, Ahmet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akyürek, Ömer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Este estudio fue designado para investigar los efectos de los polimorfismos genéticos de interleucina (IL)-1&amp;#946;, IL-1Ra, IL-2, IL-6 e IL-10 en la ocurrencia de la enfermedad de Behcet (EB) y la asociación entre los polimorfismos y el fenotipo. Materials y método: La población de estudio consistió en 71 pacientes y 70 sujetos sanos emparejados por edad y sexo. A cada participante se le extrajeron 2cc de sangre y el ADN se obtuvo usando el kit NucleoSpin® Blood DNA Isolation. Para mostrar las longitudes de las bandas, los productos fueron amplificados usando los primeros pares de las IL investigadas y se desarrollaron en un gel de agarosa al 2%. Resultados: No hubo diferencias significativas entre los grupos en relación con las distribuciones de los polimorfismos genéticos de IL-1Ra, IL-1&amp;#946;, IL-2, IL-6 e IL-10. En el grupo de pacientes, el polimorfismo genético de IL-1RN2 detectado se correlacionó estadísticamente con la presencia de afección articular (p = 0,0283), y el polimorfismo genético de IL-1&amp;#946; se correlacionó estadísticamente con la presencia de lesión ocular (p = 0,0178). La evaluación de la distribución del polimorfismo genético de IL-2 (p = 0,0065) e IL-10 (p = 0,0483) en relación con la edad de inicio de la EB reveló una distribución estadísticamente significativa. Conclusión: La correlación estadística entre afección articular e IL-1RN, afección ocular e IL-1&amp;#946;, y la edad de inicio de la enfermedad y los polimorfismos genéticos de IL-2 e IL-10, detectados por primera vez en la literatura médica, evidencian que estos polimorfismos se asociaron estadísticamente a los síntomas de la enfermedad y se podrían usar como factores pronósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(9): 379-383, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de los polimorfismos genéticos de IL-1 beta, IL-1Ra, IL-2, IL-6 e IL-10 en el desarrollo de la enfermedad de Behcet y su asociación con el fenotipo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4980^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29472^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52277^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29489^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30030^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52275^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
