<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109771</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient safety: use of quality management to prevent medication errors in the hospital medication use cycle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the medication errors in the medication use cycle in a general public hospital, and to identify intervention strategies in relation to the detection and prevention of these errors. Methods. Descriptive study with cross-sectional design. General public hospital of 190 beds, in Rosario (Argentina). Daily and systematic data collection of the circuit of use of medicines during May 2009. Once the errors were identified and classified, an interdisciplinary group sequentially applied different quality management tools to recognize and weigh causes, and propose solutions. (Flowchart, Cause Effect Diagram, Brainstorming, Nominal Group and Matrix Decision). Results. Information on 60 patients was retrieved during the study period, with 506 medication errors detected. The impact indicators showed the following values: 8.4 errors/patient and 88.6 errors/100 patients-day. From the causes identified, two were defined as relevant: &#147;Double prescription&#148; and &#147;Lack of clear policy&#148;. Of the various solutions proposed, an intervention strategy was defined to include a differently designed form for &#147;prescription/indication/administration&#148; in the clinical history which could be updated daily, with a duplicate to Pharmacy for the distribution, as well as a Standard Operating Procedure to standardize this new way of working. Conclusion. This work achieved, through quality management, the commitment of a team of health professionals to seek and make changes for patient safety, and to improve the quality of services provided by the hospital(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bianchi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colautti, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salamano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palchik, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Traverso, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir los errores de medicación en el circuito de uso de medicamentos en una sala general de internación de un Hospital Público de referencia, e identificar estrategias de intervención en relación a la detección y prevención de estos errores. Método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Hospital público general, de 190 camas, en Rosario (Argentina). Recolección de datos en forma diaria y sistemática del circuito de uso de medicamentos en una sala de internación general durante mayo 2009. Una vez identificados y caracterizados los errores, un grupo interdisciplinar aplicó en forma secuencial herramientas de gestión de calidad para reconocer causas y proponer y ponderar soluciones. (Flujograma, diagrama de causa y efecto, tormenta de ideas, grupo nominal y matriz de decisión). Resultados. En el período de estudio se obtiene información de 60 pacientes, con detección de 506 errores de medicación. Los indicadores de incidencia mostraron los siguientes valores: 8,4 errores/paciente y 88,6 errores/100 pacientes-día. De las causas identificadas se definieron como relevantes: «la doble prescripción» y «la falta de normativas claras». De las diferentes soluciones propuestas se planteó como estrategia de intervención incluir en la Historia Clínica una planilla de «prescripción/indicación/administración» con un diseño diferente, habilitando actualización diaria, con un duplicado para la dispensación en Farmacia. Se genera un procedimiento operativo estándar para normatizar esta nueva modalidad de trabajo. Conclusiones. Este trabajo logra, a través de la gestión de la calidad, el compromiso del equipo de salud para generar cambios que buscan tanto la seguridad del paciente como mejorar la calidad de las prestaciones que brinda el hospital(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;28(1): 28-35, ene.-feb. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad del paciente: aplicación de gestión de calidad para prevenir errores de medicación en el circuito de uso de medicamentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
