<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113070</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Given the current context of social concern regarding the rights of senior citizens, this study describes and evaluates a program of assertive social skills training (ASST) for elderly people. The participants (2 men and 13 women) were distributed into two groups: the experimental group (EG, which received the ASST) and the placebo group (PG, which was exposed to interactive presentations on several topics). Pre-test and post-test evaluations with IHSI-Del-Prette and the monitoring of the scores indicated the acquisition and maintenance of a repertoire of especially assertive social skills by the EG, but not by the PG. The authors discuss the reliability and importance of the study with a placebo design for assessing the internal validity of the intervention programs in, their critical features and also the importance of this kind of intervention for the elderly in today&#146;s world</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Braz, Ana C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prette, Almir del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prete, Zilda A. P de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dado el contexto actual de preocupación social cuanto a los derechos de los ancianos, este estudio describe y evalúa un programa de entrenamiento de habilidades sociales asertivas (ASST, assertive social-skills training) para personas de edad avanzada. La muestra (2 hombres y 13 mujeres) participaran de uno de dos grupos: experimental (GE, que recibió el ASST) y placebo (GP, con presentaciones interactivas de temas diversos). Las evaluaciones con IHSI-Del-Prette pre, post-test y el seguimiento de las medidas indicaran adquisición y mantenimiento de repertorio de habilidades sociales, especialmente asertivas, para EG, pero no para PG. Los autores discuten la viabilidad y la importancia de los estudios con diseño placebo para evaluar la validez interna de los programas de intervención, sus características esenciales sino también la importancia de este tipo de intervención para los ancianos en la realidad contemporána (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(2): 373-387, mayo-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113070</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
