<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105191</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infant feeding in recent immigrant population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The excess or deficiency of nutrients have related health problems. The aim of this study is to describe the eating habits of immigrants on their arrival and their relationship with socio-demographic variables and pathologies associated. Methods A descriptive, observational transversal study. Population: immigrants between 6 months and 15 years. Variables: age, sex and country of origin. Children under 24 months food supply introduction according to WHO and ESPGHAN. In the entire population: cereal/farinaceous rations, fruits, vegetables, milk, protein, legumes, oils and fats, pastry, sweets and candy, soft drinks, salty snacks, nuts, cocoa, tea and coffee. Presence or not: low share, obesity and caries. Results In children under 24 months were found significant percentages in incorrect introduction of certain foods (36.7% milk cow). In the studied population: inadequate basic foodstuffs (28.4% in vegetables), not needed developed food excesses (47.2% in sausages) and incorrect diet in 32.6%. Found statistical significance between origin and deficit of foods (milk 39.1% of Indo-Pakistanis) or excess (sausages 71.8% of the Caribbean). In the dietary's assessment: correct 57.1% of Maghrebi or incorrect 48.1% of Pakistani Indus and 43.1% in the Eastern Europe. Conclusions Inadequate habits of nutrition and their association to certain regions must be taken into account because of the risk on childhood and adult health. Resources to specific preventive and educational actions are needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riera-Vidal, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Gil, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masvidal-Aliberch, Rosa Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos-Gallego, Elisa de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estabanell-Buxó, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Rodríguez, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El exceso o defecto de nutrientes se ha relacionado con problemas de salud. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer los hábitos alimentarios de los inmigrantes a su llegada y su relación con variables sociodemográficas y patologías asociadas. Material y métodos Estudio descriptivo observacional transversal. Población: niños inmigrantes con edad entre 6 meses y 15 años. Variables: edad, sexo y país de procedencia. En los menores de 24 meses introducción de los alimentos según la OMS y la ESPGHAN. En toda la población: raciones de cereales/farináceos, frutas, verduras, lácteos, proteínas, legumbres, aceites/grasas, bollería, dulces y golosinas, bebidas refrescantes, aperitivos salados, frutos secos, cacao, té y café. Presencia o no de: talla baja, obesidad y caries. Resultados En los menores de 24 meses de edad se encontraron porcentajes elevados de introducción incorrecta de ciertos alimentos (36,7% leche de vaca). En la población estudiada se observan raciones insuficientes de alimentos (28,4% en verduras), excesos (47,2% en embutidos) y dieta incorrecta en el 32,6%. Se encontró significación estadística entre procedencia y déficit de alimentos (lácteos el 39,10% de los indopakistaníes) o excesos (embutidos en el 71,8% de los de Caribe). En la valoración de la dieta: correcta en el 57,1% de los magrebíes o incorrecta del 48,1% de los indopakistaníes y 43,1% en los de Europa del Este. Conclusiones Se han de tener en cuenta las prácticas alimentarias inadecuadas encontradas y la asociación a ciertas procedencias por al riesgo que pueden suponer para la salud infantil y adulta. Su abordaje requiere recursos para acciones preventivas y educativas específicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);22(3): 118-125, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alimentación en población infantil inmigrante recién llegada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52954^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
