<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154752</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic venous insufficiency in workers without risks factors who remain long hours standing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The chronic venous insufficiency (CVI) is a prevalent pathology in the today&#146;s society. The arising problems represent an important cause of economic costs and absenteeism in the workplace. Current working conditions, such as long working hours, standing for long periods of time, inadequate load weight as well as bad humidity and temperature conditions, contribute to the development of this pathology. In this essay, a systematic review of existing bibliography related to chronic venous insufficiency and standing up long time at working hours has been conducted. In order to determine the evidence level of the evaluated studies the criteria established by the Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN) has been considered. In particular, a significant positive link between long period of time standing and a risk for suffering chronic venous insufficiency has been found. However, the existing literature is not specific enough to establish a threshold that determines the number of working hours required to be considered an extreme period of time standing. In order to determine if the chronic venous insufficiency should be considered an occupational disease, it is required to design and conduct further research on this topic. These studies are necessary to establish new evidence in order to make the society aware and generate new health prevention and promotion campaigns so that economic costs and quality of life could continue improving (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Astudillo, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jou, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solar, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eurgencios, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia venosa crónica (IVC) es una patología prevalente en la sociedad actual. Los problemas derivados de ella, son una causa importante de gasto económico y absentismo laboral. Las condiciones laborales actuales, como jornadas de larga duración, con largas horas en bipedestación, inadecuada carga de pesos y malas condiciones de humedad y temperatura, contribuyen al desarrollo de esta patología. En este trabajo se ha realizado una revisión sistemática de la bibliografía existente en relación a la insuficiencia venosa crónica y el tiempo en bipedestación de las jornadas laborales. Para determinar el nivel de evidencia de los estudios evaluados, se han seguido los criterios del Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN). En particular, se ha concluido que existe una asociación significativamente positiva entre el tiempo prolongado en bipedestación y el riesgo de padecer insuficiencia venosa crónica. Sin embargo, la literatura actual no permite establecer un umbral que determine el número de horas considerado como bipedestación prolongada. Para poder valorar si la insuficiencia venosa crónica debería considerarse una enfermedad profesional, es necesario diseñar y llevar a cabo nuevos estudios de investigación en esta dirección. Estos estudios son necesarios para poder establecer evidencias de cara a concienciar a la sociedad y generar campañas de prevención y promoción de la salud que disminuyan los costes económicos y mejoren la calidad de vida de la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;62(243): 141-156, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia venosa crónica en trabajadores sin factores de riesgo que permanecen horas prolongadas en bipedestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
