<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125779</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity of psychoanalysis in the XXI century. New challenges</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autor starts by wondering what it means nowadays to be a psychoanalyst. He considers that one of the ways to look for answer is to follow the evolution of the psychoanalytical method from its origins to the present. In order to get the issued focused, he reviews chronologically the works of Freud since their origins &#150;the cathartic method he learned from Breuer &#150; up to his final works. He goes forward gathering those technical articles as well as clinical histories in which the way Freud worked can be appraised. After giving some insights about what he considers the most important landmarks in the development of the methos after Freud, he finally undertakes a personal reflection connected with his training experience and subsequent professional trajectory. He then approaches the question of the psychoanalysis as cure versus psychoanalytic psychotherapy, ending with the exposition of three clinical cases in which the current way of working with patients can be appraised, both with those susceptible of pursuing the standard cure as with dose in hich the method has to be adapted to their peculiarities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Prieto, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor comienza interrogándose sobre qué es ser psicoanalista hoy. Piensa que una de las formas para buscar respuestas es hacer un recorrido por la evolución del método psicoanalítico desde sus orígenes a la actualidad. Para centrar el tema hace un recorrido cronológico por la obra de Freud desde los orígenes, el método catártico que aprendió de Breuer, hasta el final de su obra. Va recogiendo tanto los artículos técnicos como los historiales clínicos, en los que se puede apreciar cómo trabajaba Freud. Da unas pinceladas por lo que considera los hitos más importantes del desarrollo del método después de Freud y finalmente emprende una reflexión personal, entroncada con su experiencia de formación y trayectoria ulterior. Se plantea la problemática del psicoanálisis cura tipo versus psicoterapia psicoanalítica y finaliza con la exposición de tres casos clínicos donde se puede apreciar el trabajo actual con pacientes tanto susceptibles de emprender la cura tipo como otros en los que el método tiene que ser adaptado a sus peculiaridades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(67): 13-68, nov. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigencia del psicoanálisis en el siglo XXI. Nuevos retos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38897</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
