<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137805</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity and leisure habits and relation with Ruffier Index in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the study was to assess and correlate physical activity practice and fitness level in adolescents. A total of 884 students (age=16,4±0,8 years) answered the modified version of the 'Assessment of Physical Activity Level Questionnaire (APALQ)' and aerobic capacity was assessed through the Ruffier Test. The mean Ruffier Index (IR) was 11,1±4,6 and the mean Physical Activity Index (IAF) was 13,8±4,4. The relationship between IAF and IR, and between sedentary activities in leisure time and IR, was significant (r=-0,31; p=0,000). although weak. Boys showed higher physical fitness values (t= -8,78; p= 0,000) and spent more time practicing physical activity. These differences were significant for both regulated and not regulated physical activity and for participation in competition (p=0.000). Girls spent more time in sedentary activities like reading and studying (p=0.000). It is necessary to promote physical activity and sport practice, especially among girls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robledo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Aparicio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez González, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cabrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pastor, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinero, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue medir y correlacionar la práctica de actividad física y con el Índice de Ruffier (IR) en adolescentes. A un total de 884 alumnos (edad=16,4±0,8 años) se les midió la actividad física con la Versión modificada del Assessment of Physical Activity Level Questionnaire (APALQ) y se evaluó la capacidad de adaptación al esfuerzo mediante el Test Ruffier. La media del Índice de Ruffier  fue 11,1±4,6 y el Índice de actividad física (IAF) 13,8±4,4. Las relaciones entre IAF y el IR, y entre horas de ocio sedentario e IR resultaron ser significativas aunque débiles (r=-0,31; p=0,000). En el IR los chicos presentaron valores superiores (t= -8,78; p= 0,000) a las chicas. También destinan más tiempo a la práctica de AF y estas diferencias fueron significativas en AF reglada y no reglada y en participación en competición (p=0,000), mientras que las chicas destinan más tiempo a actividades sedentarias como leer y estudiar (p=0,000). Es necesario promover la práctica de actividades físico-deportivas, especialmente entre las chicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(57): 165-180, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad física y ocio y su relación con el Índice de Ruffier en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
