<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143697</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of performing and prescribing physical exercise in patients diagnosed with anxiety and depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the prevalence of physical exercise practice in patients diagnosed with anxiety and/or depression. Design: Cross-sectional, observational study. Location: Sabugo and la Magdalena primary care centers in Avilés. Participants: Patients aged 18 to 75 years diagnosed with anxiety and/or depression, consumers of psychoactive drugs in the three months previous to the realization of the study. We selected 376 patients by simple random sampling stratified by health center, making them a telephone survey. Main measurements: Age, sex, physical exercise realization, type and duration of exercise, diagnosis of anxiety and/or depression, exercise prescription, prescriber health personnel and use of psychotropic medication. Results: 294 participants (78.19% of selected) with a mean age of 55.33 years (55.32 ± 12.53 SD) and 78.2% were female. 60.9% were diagnosed with anxiety, 59.5% with depression and 20.4% both diagnoses. 62.9% used antidepressants, benzodiazepines 76.9% and 39.79% both treatments. 58.5% (95%CI: 52.70-64.31) performed exercise of which 44.77% did it 3-5 times/week. The mean duration was 1.24 h each time (95%CI: 0.53-1.96). The physical exercise was prescribed to the 59.18% (95%CI: 53.39-64.97); 90.23% by the family physician, 63.22% primary care nurse, 17.24% psychiatrist and 5.17% psychologist. The adherence to the prescription was 59.77% (95%CI: 52.20-67.34). Conclusions: The percentage of anxious and/or depressed patients who practiced exercise is similar to the general population but should be higher. The exercise prescription by health personnel is insufficient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olaya Velázquez, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Castro, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Martínez, Bibiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar la prevalencia de la práctica y la prescripción de ejercicio físico en pacientes diagnosticados de ansiedad y/o depresión. Diseño: Descriptivo observacional transversal. Emplazamiento: Centros de Salud de Sabugo y Magdalena de Avilés. Participantes: Pacientes de 18-75 años diagnosticados de ansiedad y/o depresión consumidores de psicofármacos en los 3 meses previos a la realización del estudio. Se seleccionan 376 pacientes mediante muestreo aleatorizado simple estratificado por centro de salud, realizándoseles una encuesta telefónica. Mediciones principales: Edad, sexo, realización de ejercicio físico, tipo y duración del mismo, diagnóstico de ansiedad y/o depresión, prescripción de ejercicio físico, personal sanitario prescriptor y consumo de psicofármacos. Resultados: Participaron 294 (78,19% de los seleccionados) con una edad media de 55,33 años (55,32 ± 12,53 DE) y el 78,2% eran mujeres. El 60,9% estaban diagnosticados de ansiedad, el 59,5% de depresión y el 20,4% de ambas. El 62,9% consumían antidepresivos, el 76,9% benzodiazepinas y el 39,79% ambos tratamientos. El 58,8% (IC 95%: 52,70-64,31) realizaban ejercicio físico de los cuales el 44,77% lo hacía entre 3-5 veces/semana. La duración media fue de 1,24 h cada vez (IC 95%: 0,53-1,96). Al 59,18% (IC 95%: 53,39-64,97) se le prescribió la realización de ejercicio físico (90,23% médico y 63,22% enfermera de atención primaria, 17,24% psiquiatra y 5,17% psicólogo). La adherencia a la prescripción fue del 59,77% (IC 95%: 52,20-67,34). Conclusiones: El porcentaje de pacientes ansiosos y/o deprimidos que realizan ejercicio físico es similar al de la población general aunque debería ser mayor. La prescripción de ejercicio físico por parte del personal sanitario es insuficiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(7): 428-437, ago.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143697</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de realización y prescripción de ejercicio físico en pacientes diagnosticados de ansiedad y depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
