<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143366</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A 5-year review of surgical techniques and implant characteristics in 2876 consecutive augmentation mammaplasties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We conducted a study to evaluate the breast augmentation techniques and type of implants (material, surface, volume) in the last years in our group of Day Unit Plastic Surgery at Centro Médico Platinum in Caracas, Venezuela. We retrospectively review2876 consecutive augmentation mammoplasties and augmentation-mastopexies, performed in the last 5 years. The average age of the patients was 30,8 years (71% under 35years). All the implants were silicone gel filled prosthesis, round,86% smooth surface and 77% high profile; 97% were placed in the subpectoral plane. The average volume was 386 cc for the right breast, and 387 cc for the left breast (minimum 200 cc and maximum.600 cc). There was an inverse relationship between age and volume (p = 0.001). As for the volume used, the behavior was homogeneous among the 27 plastic surgeons of the group. Perthese® and La Femme® were the most used brands. The use of extra-high profiles increased in recent years (p = 0,002).In just over half (51%) patients, mammary augmentation was combined with a mastopexy. In 13% breast surgery was combined with another surgical procedure. The augmentation mammoplasty predominated in patients under 35 years, and augmentation mastopexies in the older ones. In conclusion, we comprobed that in our area, silicone gel-filled, smooth surface, high profile mammary implants are mostly used, placed on a retropectoral plane. In older patients, breast augmentation is combined with mastopexies and smaller sizes are used. In recent years use of extra-high profile implants is increasing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flores, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colombo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es estudiar las técnicas quirúrgicas en mamoplastia de aumento y los tipos de prótesis (material, superficie, volumen) empleadas en los últimos años por nuestro grupo de Cirugía Plástica Ambulatoria del Centro Médico Platinum en Caracas, Venezuela, revisando para ello retrospectivamente2876 mamoplastias de aumento y aumentopexias consecutivas, realizadas en los últimos 5 años. La edad promedio de las pacientes del grupo de estudio fue30,8 años (71% menores de 35 años). En todas empleamos prótesis rellenas de gel de silicona, redondas, 86% de superficie lisa y 77% de perfil alto. El 97% se colocaron en el plano retropectoral. El volumen promedio fue de 386 cc para la mama derecha y de 387 cc para la mama izquierda (mínimo de 200 cc y máximo de600cc). Hubo una relación inversa entre edad y volumen(p = 0,001). En cuanto al volumen utilizado, el comportamiento fue homogéneo entre los 27 cirujanos plásticos del centro. Perthese® y La Femme®, fueron las marcas más empleadas. El uso de perfiles extra-altos aumentó en los últimos años (p = 0,002).En poco más de la mitad (51%) de las pacientes, se combinó el aumento mamario con una pexia. En el 13% la cirugía mamaria se combinó con otro procedimiento quirúrgico. Las mamoplastias de aumento predominaron en menores de 35 años, y las aumentopexias en las pacientes de mayor edad. En conclusión, comprobamos que en nuestro medio se utilizan mayoritariamente prótesis rellenas de gel de silicona, redondas, lisas, de perfil alto, colocadas en un plano retropectoral. En pacientes de mayor edad se combinó el aumento mamario con lapexia y se utilizaron tamaños de prótesis más pequeñas. En los últimos años ha aumentado el uso de prótesis de perfil extra-alto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;41(3): 219-232, jul.-sept. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143366</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión a 5 años de técnicas quirúrgicas y características de los implantes en 2876 mamoplastias de aumento consecutivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32332^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13208^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11917^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
