<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97577</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tretament of Urogenital Fistula in Women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: We aimed to assess the results of the genitourinary fistula cases intervened in our center in a ten year period. Patients and methods: We evaluated the clinical data regarding genitourinary fistula from the medical records of 42 female patients who underwent surgery for this condition between May 2001 and June 2010. Age, previous medical history, diagnostic tools used, operative data and clinical outcomes of the patients were evaluated retrospectively. Results: The mean age of patients was 51 years. Of 42 patients, 28 had vesicovaginal, 11 had ureterovaginal, and 3 had vesicouterine fistulas. Etiology of vesicovaginal fistula was surgical trauma in 71,5% and obstetric trauma in 28,5% of the patients. O&#146;Connor technique was performed as a single procedure in 12 vesicovaginal fistula cases, and ureteroneocystostomy was added in 3. Transvesical repair was performed in 9, and transvaginal repair in 3 of the patients. All of 11 patients with ureterovaginal fistula were of iatrogenic origin; ureteroneocystostomy was performed in 6, and Boari flap was performed in 5 of these patients. Three vesicouterine fistulas were repaired primarily. Success rates in vesicovaginal, ureterovaginal and vesicouterine fistulas were 96, 100 and 100 percent, respectively. Conclusion: In experienced hands and according with the related basic surgical principles, operative treatment in genitourinary fistula represents an effective modality with high success rate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Faydacý, G. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albayrak, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Horuz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Çetinel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akça, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Göktaþ, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: Nos hemos propuesto evaluar los resultados de los casos de fístula genitourinaria intervenidos en nuestro centro en un período de 10 años. Material y métodos: Hemos evaluado la información clínica que respecta a la fístula genitourinaria a partir del historial médico de 42 pacientes femeninas, que se sometieron a cirugía por esta afección entre mayo de 2001 y junio de 2010. La edad, el historial médico, las herramientas de diagnóstico utilizadas, la información quirúrgica y los resultados clínicos de las pacientes fueron evaluados retrospectivamente.   Resultados: La media de edad de las pacientes fue de 51 años. De 42 pacientes 28 tenían fístula vesicovaginal, 11 ureterovaginal y tres vesicouterina. La etiología de la fístula vesicovaginal era traumatismo quirúrgico en el 71,5% y traumatismo obstétrico en el 28,5% de las pacientes. La técnica de O&#146;Connor se llevó a cabo como único procedimiento en 12 casos de fístula vesicovaginal, añadiendo la ureteroneocistostomía en tres. La reparación transvesical se llevó a cabo en 9 y la reparación transvaginal en tres de las pacientes. Los 11 casos de fístula ureterovaginal eran de origen yatrogénico. La ureteroneocistostomía se llevó a cabo en 6 de estas pacientes y el flap de Boari en 5. Fundamentalmente se repararon tres fístulas vesicouterinas. El índice de éxito en las fístulas vesicovaginal, ureterovaginal y vesicouterinas fue del 96, 100 y 100% respectivamente. Conclusión: En manos expertas, y de acuerdo con los principios básicos de cirugía, el tratamiento quirúrgico en la fístula genitourinaria representa una modalidad efectiva con un alto índice de éxito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;36(3): 191-195, mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la fístula urogenital en la mujer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13910^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29578^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29573^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
