<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149182</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autism, epilepsy and mitocondrial disease: points of contact</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Autism is a neurodevelopmental disorder with unknown etiology, although several different specific organic conditions have been found to be associated with autism in about 10 to 37% of cases. Autism with regression has been reported in one third of autistic children with previously normal development. Epilepsy is quite common in autism spectrum disorders. The rate of comorbidity varies between 20-30% of cases, depending upon the age and type of disorder. Major risk factors for epilepsy in autistic children are mental retardation and additional neurological disorders, as well as some specific associated medical conditions like chromosomal abnormalities, phakomatosis and inherited metabolic disorders. Aim. To review the possible linkage between autism, epilepsy and mitochondrial dysfunction. Development. The hypothesis of a disturbed bioenergetic metabolism underlying autism has been suggested by the detection of high lactate levels in some patients. Although the mechanism of hyperlactacidemia remains unknown, a likely possibility involves mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation dysfunction in neuronal cells. Reduced levels of respiratory mitochondrial enzymes, ultraestructural mitochondrial abnormalities and a broad range of mitochondrial DNA mutations suggest a linkage between autism, epilepsy and mitochondrial disorders. Conclusions. Though mitochondrial disorders are a rare cause of autism in children, we must keep in mind this etiology in autistic patients with epilepsy and associated signs of neurologic and/or systemic dysfunction. Finding biochemical or structural mitochondrial abnormalities in an autistic child does not necessarily imply a primary mitochondrial disorder but can also be secondary to technical inaccuracies or another genetic disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Peñas, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El autismo es un trastorno del neurodesarrollo de etiología desconocida, aunque se refiere su asociación con patologías orgánicas hasta en un 10-37% de los casos. El autismo con regresión (&#145;regresión autista&#146;) se presenta en un tercio de los niños autistas con desarrollo psicomotor inicial normal. La epilepsia es muy frecuente en los trastornos del espectro autista y su tasa de comorbilidad varía entre un 20-30%, dependiendo de la edad y del tipo de trastorno. Los factores que más incrementan el riesgo de epilepsia son la presencia de signos neurológicos asociados, como el retraso mental, y la evidencia de determinadas asociaciones, como cromosomopatías, facomatosis y metabolopatías congénitas. Objetivo. Revisar la posible conexión entre autismo, epilepsia y enfermedad mitocondrial. Desarrollo. Desde que se evidenció una elevada incidencia de acidosis láctica en autistas, se ha especulado con una posible alteración del metabolismo bioenergético y oxidativo en estos niños. La alteración de complejos de la cadena respiratoria, la presencia de anomalías ultraestructurales mitocondriales y la evidencia de una amplia gama de mutaciones del ADN mitocondrial en autistas, sugiere que exista una conexión entre autismo, epilepsia y enfermedad mitocondrial. Conclusiones. Aunque las enfermedades mitocondriales son una causa muy rara de autismo, se debe investigar esta etiología en autistas con epilepsia y signos asociados de disfunción neurológica y/o sistémica. El hallazgo de anomalías bioquímicas o ultraestructurales sugerentes de enfermedad mitocondrial no proporciona un diagnóstico definitivo, dado que pueden deberse a un falso positivo por error técnico o bien a otro trastorno genético distinto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;46(supl.1): s79-s85, feb. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autismo, epilepsia y enfermedad mitocondrial: puntos de encuentro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36033^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
