<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96146</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heart rate and oxygen uptake responses in male athletes in duathlon sprint competitions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to describe the percentages loads of heart rate and oxygenconsumption achieved by athletes in duathlon sprint competitions (5km run, 20km bike and2.5km run = C1-BK-C2) For the study, the physiological data were collected from five duathlonsprint competitions very similar in altitude and terrain. Ten male athletes, chosen from highnational level duathletes, participated in the study. Continuous recordings of heart rate wereobtained during competitions and subsequently in the laboratory where they were tested bytwo maximal graded exercise tests, one on a treadmill and another on a cycle ergometer, toobtain physiological reference values for each athlete. The results show that athletes had avery similar percentage of heart rate in the three competition sectors, with C1: 94.63%±3%;BK: 94.50%±2.94% and C2: 92.71%±3.54%.The oxygen consumption levels were estimated as a dependent variable by linear regression,from heart rate and oxygen consumption values of the effort test, showing a similar values inthree segments (C1: 89.70%±6.11%; BK: 85.73%±6.89%, C2: 87.30%±8.67%). The lowest VO2%of BK with respect to C1 and C2 (p &lt; .01) could be justified by lower use of total muscle mass andtherefore a lower energy expenditure. The study showed that in sprint duathlon competitionsthe per cent load of the heart rate range between 92% and 95% of maximal heart rate andoxygen consumption between 85% and 89% of VO2max, confirming high levels of maximal aerobicpower and heart rate. These data being considered as a reference for the use of sports trainingloads in continuous, variable continuous, and long interval extended types of sport(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ronconi, Mauro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvero-Cruz, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niveles de consumo de oxígeno fueron estimados mediante regresión lineal, a partir de losvalores de frecuencia cardiaca-consumo de oxígeno de la prueba de esfuerzo, evidenciándoseen los tres segmentos unos valores de C1: 89,70±6,11%; BK: 85,73±6,89%; C2: 87,30±8,67%)El menor valor del porcentaje de VO2 del tramo en BK con respecto a C1 y C2 (p &lt; 0,01) podríaestar justificado por una menor utilización del total de masa muscular y, por tanto, un menorgasto energético. El estudio evidencia que en competiciones de duatlón en modalidad sprint elporcentaje de carga de la frecuencia cardiaca está entre el 92 y el 95% de la frecuencia cardiacamáxima, y el consumo de oxígeno, entre el 85 y el 89% del VO2max, confirmándose unos altosniveles de la potencia aeróbica máxima y de la frecuencia cardiaca y considerándolos comoparámetros de referencia para la utilización de cargas de entrenamiento deportivo tanto detipo continuo, continuo variable e interválico extensivo largo, en esta modalidad deportiva(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);46(172): 183-188, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta de la frecuencia cardiaca y consumo de oxígeno de atletas varones en competiciones de duatlón sprint</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10281^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
