<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042391</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metastatic involvement of the central nervous system in breast cancer: role of Herceptin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The metastatic involvement pattern of breast cancer has been changing in recent years and, in this sense, an increase in the incidence of metastatic involvement of the central nervous system (CNS) is being observed. In this situation, the role that the introduction of new therapeutic agents has must still be defined. In this article, we review the possible role played by treatment with Herceptin in the appearance of metastatic involvements of the CNS</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ocaña Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Hernández, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El patrón de afectación metastático del cáncer de mama está cambiando en los últimos años y, en este sentido, se está observando un aumento en la incidencia de afectación metastásica del sistema nervioso central (SNC). En esta situación el papel que puede tener la introducción de nuevos agentes terapéuticos está por definir. En este artículo revisaremos el posible papel que puede desempeñar el tratamiento con Herceptin en la aparición de afectación metastásica del SNC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(11): 553-555, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afectación metastásica del sistema nervioso central en el cáncer de mama: papel del Herceptin</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
