<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129851</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical disaster in temporomandibular joint: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Temporomandibular-ankylosis brings extensive limitations on the patient quality of life. Surgical treatment is frequently necessary associated with a continuous rehabilitation. The anatomy of this region and potential complications of this surgery must be thoroughly known to avoid iatrogenic injuries. Case presentation. A young patient underwent surgical treatment of congenital bilateral ankylosis with disastrous consequences such as facial palsy, deafness and cerebrospinal leaks on the right side related to intraoperative trauma involving structures of the external, middle and inner ear. Conclusion. Since there is no corrective treatment for this type of injuries, the craniomaxillofacial surgeon and other professionals who carry out interventions of this nature need perfect knowledge of the anatomy of the temporal bone and lateral skull base, taking into account the risk of surgical disasters like the one here reported (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Machado De Carvalho, Guilherme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iwakura, Cassio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rizzato Paschoal, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caixeta Guimarães, alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nizam Pfeilsticker, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, Fabio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La anquilosis temporomandibular se asocia a importantes limitaciones de la calidad de vida del paciente. Con frecuencia, es necesario un tratamiento quirúrgico asociado a una rehabilitación continua. Para evitar las lesiones yatrogénicas, se requieren conocimientos exhaustivos de la anatomía de esta región y de las complicaciones potenciales de la cirugía. Presentación del caso. Un paciente joven se sometió a tratamiento quirúrgico de una anquilosis bilateral congénita con consecuencias catastróficas, como parálisis facial, sordera y extravasación de líquido cefalorraquídeo en el lado derecho relacionada con el traumatismo intraoperatorio, que afectó a las estructuras del oído externo, medio e interno. Conclusión. Puesto que no se dispone de un tratamiento corrector para este tipo de lesiones, tanto el cirujano experto en cabeza y cuello como otros profesionales que efectúan intervenciones de esta naturaleza necesitan unos conocimientos óptimos sobre la anatomía del hueso temporal y la base del cráneo, y deben tener en cuenta el riesgo de una catástrofe quirúrgica como la descrita en este paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;36(3): 113-118, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catástrofe quirúrgica en la articulación temporomandibular: informe de caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d855^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33765^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33765^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d855^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
