<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133076</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drugs having latex and therapeutic alternatives in hospital formulary</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To analyze the latex content of drugs in hospital formulary and establish possible therapeutic alternatives. Methods: All drugs susceptible of having latex were selected and written information was obtained from manufacturers. A therapeutic alternative was found for each of them, if possible. Results: Written information from manufacturer was obtained for 605 (97.9%) and from label information for 8 of 632 selected drugs. For 43.9% of not safe drugs (total 57) on patients with latex allergy, a therapeutic alternative was found in hospital formulary. Conclusions: Knowing drugs having latex improve the prescription security, while the therapeutic alternatives chart eases the validation. The published data updates the scarce and variable information for patients and healthcare professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Damas Fuentes, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero Gómez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sangil Monroy, Nayra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez León, Moisés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñero González, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Lantigua, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el contenido en látex de los medicamentos en la guía farmacoterapéutica y establecer alternativas en un hospital de tercer nivel. Método: Se seleccionaron los medicamentos susceptibles de contener látex en su material de acondicionamiento, se solicitó al laboratorio fabricante información y se buscaron posibles alternativas incluidas en guía farmacoterapéutica. Resultados: De las 618 especialidades seleccionadas se obtuvo información escrita del laboratorio para 605 (97.9%) y en ficha técnica para 8. De las 57 (9,2%) especialidades con riesgo en pacientes con alergia al látex se encontró una alternativa en guía para el 43,9%. Conclusiones: Conocer las especialidades con látex aumenta la seguridad en la prescripción, mientras que la disponibilidad de una tabla de equivalencias terapéuticas facilita la validación. Los datos publicados vienen a actualizar la información del contenido en látex de los medicamentos para pacientes y personal sanitario, generalmente escasa y variable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;39(1): 44-58, ene.-feb. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133076</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicamentos con látex y alternativas en guía farmacoterapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54217^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
