<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135335</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiotherapy in the treatment of acromegaly: techniques, indications, results and complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently available therapies for acromegaly are surgery, medical therapy and radiotherapy. The goals of these therapies are normalize excessive hormone secretion, to reduce the clinical signs and symptoms and to control tumour size. These goals should be accomplished while preserving pituitary function and with a few side effects as possible. Indications for radiotherapy include patients refusing surgery or in whom medical and surgical therapies failed. Conventionally fractionated radiotherapy at least 45 Gy can lower GH levels and normalize IGF-I, but there is a long lag time 5-10 years, before this effect is achieved. The most common complications are the development of new hipopituitarism. New high precision techniques using several fractions (stereotactic radiotherapy) or high doses in single fraction (radiosurgery) are an effective procedure in acromegaly with the potential benefit in reducing the volume of normal brain irradiated. Comparison of results of hormone normalization in radiosurgery series to radiotherapy series is made difficult by the different values used by investigators, and endocrine cure rates whit radiosurgery fairly wide variations (20-80%) but in reports in which the data are examined by the same authors, the response is significantly faster with radiosurgery. The optimal timing of administration of antisecretory medications with respect to the date of radiation needs to be clarified for the negative effect in radiation response. To know the real advantages of new techniques in endocrine cure rate and toxicity level is necessary to use correct cure criteria and long-term prospective studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Magallón de Sebstián, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de la acromegalia incluye cirugía, medicación y radioterapia. El objetivo común es normalizar la hipersecreción hormonal, reducir los síntomas y controlar el tamaño tumoral. Esto debería cumplirse manteniendo, además, la función hipofisaria normal y con la menor morbilidad posible. La radioterapia esta indicada en los casos de rechazo a la cirugía y/o fracaso del tratamiento médico o quirúrgico. Una radioterapia convencional con dosis de al menos 45 Gy pueden normalizar las concentraciones de hormona del crecimiento y factor de crecimiento similar a la insulina tipo I, pero se requiere un tiempo prolongado, de 6 a 10 años para conseguirlo. La complicación más frecuente es el hipopituitarismo. Nuevas técnicas de alta precisión en las que se utilizan varias fracciones (radioterapia estereotáxica) o altas dosis en una única fracción (radiocirugía) son efectivas, con el beneficio potencial de reducir el volumen de tejido sano irradiado. La comparación de resultados en la probabilidad de normalización bioquímica entre radiocirugía y radioterapia es muy compleja por los diferentes valores utilizados en las diversas series. Con radiocirugía, los porcentajes de curación son muy dispares (20-80%), pero en los trabajos en los cuales los datos son examinados por los mismos autores, la respuesta es significativamente más rápida con radiocirugía. El momento adecuado para administrar el tratamiento médico en relación con la fecha y la irradiación debe ser definido debido al efecto negativo que ejerce con la radioterapia. Para conocer la verdadera ventaja de estas nuevas modalidades en la curación y la reducción de los efectos secundarios es necesario que se empleen los criterios de curación correctos y que se realicen estudios amplios, prospectivos y con seguimientos prolongados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(supl.3): 35-41, oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioterapia en el tratamiento de la acromegalia: técnicas, indicaciones, resultados y complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29853^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11335^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11335^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38634^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38634^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38634^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29853^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
