<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30542</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Histopathological changes at the surgical site in experimental animals following partial cricoid resection and thyrotracheal anastomosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To study in an animal model the local healing process after partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis. MATERIAL AND METHODS: Partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis was performed in 17 New Zealand rabbits. Experimental animals were gradually sacrificed and the laryngotracheal complex was removed to proceed to a histopathological study. RESULTS: An acute inflammatory response followed by a chronic inflammatory process was found in the surgical site. Normal tissue architecture was established after an eight week period. Anteroposterior and transverse diameters at all levels of the upper respiratory tract were not significantly altered at any time along the healing process. Experimental animals remained free from symptoms during the follow-up period. CONCLUSIONS: These results support that partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis is a safe procedure for the treatment of severe laryngotracheal stenosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar en un modelo animal el proceso de reparación tisular que tiene lugar tras la realización de una resección cricoidea parcial con anastomosis tirotraqueal. Material y métodos: Realizamos un estudio experimental en 17 conejos New Zealand a los que se realizó el citado procedimiento. Los animales fueron sacrificados escalonadamente y el complejo laringotraqueal fue extraído y sometido a un estudio histopatológico. Resultados: La zona operada mostró una reacción inflamatoria primero aguda y luego crónica que se fue resolviendo a lo largo del tiempo, restableciéndose una arquitectura tisular normal alrededor de las ocho semanas de la intervención; los diámetros anteroposterior y transverso de la vía aérea superior a sus distintos niveles no se vieron alterados de manera significativa en ningún momento. Los animales permanecieron asintomáticos durante todo el período postoperatorio. Conclusiones: La resección cricoidea parcial con anastomosis tirotraqueal es un procedimiento seguro para el tratamiento de las estenosis laringotraqueales severas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;55(3): 131-138, mar. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios histopatológicos en la unión quirúrgica en animales de experimentación sometidos a resección cricoidea parcial y anastomosis tirotraqueal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Morera,E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontes, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernáldez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorospe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavilán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30542</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d3431^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14524^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3431^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14524^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
