<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66263</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Secondary sterility in male patients is due to sperm alterations in a high proportion of cases. But, obstructive azoospermia set up a very important cause of sterility, because a surgical repair is possible. Some of the factors cause obstructive azoospermia are the herniorrhaphy intervention, including secondary inflammatory reaction, and epididymal lesion or epididymitis. Currently, both cases are important due to high frequency of these aetiologies. Besides we should identified obstructive cause to provide a surgical repair (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castellanos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balda Manzanos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Rubio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esterilidad secundaria masculina es debida en una elevada proporción de casos a alteraciones en el esperma. Por otro lado, la azoospermia obstructiva constituye una causa importante de esterilidad, al ser subsidiaria de reparación quirúrgica. Entre los factores que intervienen en la azoospermia obstructiva encontramos la cirugía tras herniorrafia, en donde cabe destacar los procesos inflamatorios subsiguientes, y la lesión epididimaria o epididimitis previa. La importancia de los casos presentados radica actualmente, en la elevada frecuencia de dichas etiologías y en la identificación de causas obstructivas, dado que son potencialmente resolubles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(6): 656-658, jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66263</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10031^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10031^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
