<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107248</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of lymphatic malformations with ok-432 sclerosis. Our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The elective treatment of lymphatic malformations has always been surgical resection. However sclerotherapy with a variety of substances is being used as an alternative to surgery special yin the last years. The aim of this essay is to present our results usings clerosis with OK-432.Materials and methods. We have reviewed all patients affected by lymphatic malformation that have been treated by sclerosis with OK-432. Each procedure was performed under general anesthesia by a radiologist and a pediatric surgeon. Results. Fifteen patients have been treated. On the whole, 36 procedures have been performed, with a mean of 2.4 for each patient. The mean amount of OK-432 injected was 1.5 milligrams (mg) in each procedure. 73% of the patients showed nearly complete or complete (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedor, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las malformaciones linfáticas se han tratado clásicamente mediante exéresis quirúrgica. En los últimos años se ha extendido el tratamiento mediante esclerosis con diferentes sustancias, entre las que destaca el OK-432. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar nuestra experiencia con este tratamiento .Material y Métodos. Revisión de los pacientes con diagnóstico de malformación linfática, tratados mediante esclerosis con OK-432 en nuestro centro. Los procedimientos se realizaron bajo anestesia general mediante control ecográfico y quistografía previa por parte del radió-logo intervencionista pediátrico y un cirujano de la sección. Resultados. 15 pacientes han sido tratados. En total se han realizado 36 procedimientos, 2,4 infiltraciones de media por paciente con una cantidad media de 1,5 miligramos (mg) de preparado diluido inyectado en cada una. Los resultados han sido satisfactorios en el 73% de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;23(2): 88-91, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107248</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las malformaciones linfáticas mediante esclerosis con OK-432. Nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38052^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12978^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
