<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131077</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Public policies in promoting health school teen: design of managersl</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article focuses on public policies to promote adolescent health school, proposed and developed under the responsibility of managers in education and health in the city of Recife-PE. It is a qualitative research is an exploratory-descriptive. Participants were 26 subjects, among managers of health and education of Recife-PE. Data collection occurred from August to October 2011 and we used the technique of recording. Data analysis was based on the technique of the Collective Subject Discourse (CSD). The results presented are composed of two central ideas: Unveiling public policy in promoting adolescent health and education challenges and breakthroughs in the development and implementation of the School Health Program. And so we conclude that the study through their findings about the reality of public policies related to health care for adolescents, especially School Health Program, a basis for a critical reflection on the managerial limitations in the implementation and effectiveness of policies intersectoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leite Meirelles Monteiro, Estela Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares de Lima, Luciane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenorio de Souza Cavalcanti, Ana Márcia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aquino, Jael Maria de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa Silva, Andrea Rosane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brandão Neto, Waldemar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tuvo como objetivo conocer las políticas públicas de promoción de la salud del adolescente en la escuela propuestas y desarrolladas bajo la responsabilidad de los gestores de educación y salud en el municipio de Recife-PE. Investigación cualitativa del tipo exploratoria-descriptiva. Participaron de la investigación 26 sujetos, entre gestores de salud y de educación de Recife-PE. La recolección de datos ocurrió entre los meses de agosto y octubre de 2011 y se grabaron las declaraciones. El análisis de los datos se basó en la técnica del Discurso del Sujeto Colectivo (DSC). Los resultados presentados están compuestos por dos Ideas Centrales: Desvelando las políticas públicas en la promoción de la salud del adolescente en la escuela y Los desafíos y avances en la implantación y desarrollo del Programa Salud en la Escuela. Y, así, concluimos que el estudio a través de sus resultados sobre la realidad de las políticas públicas dirigidas a la atención a la salud del adolescente, en especial el Programa Salud en la Escuela, proporciona recursos para una reflexión crítica sobre las limitaciones administrativas en la ejecución y efectividad de las políticas intersectoriales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;14(37): 250-267, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Políticas públicas en la promoción de la salud del adolescente en la escuela: concepción de los gestores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d299^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
