<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90642</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in prevalence of risk factors and global cardiovascular risk in general population of Albacete, Spain (1992-94 a 2004-06)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To establish strategies for prevention of cardiovascular disease implies to know its epidemiology and evolution in time. The objective of this study is to know the prevalence of risk factors and cardiovascular risk in two moments during the following of a grownup general population. Methods: Study of cohorts, followed at random selected general population during 12 years (1992-94 to 2204-06). Two transversal studies were made, one at the beginning and the other one at the end of this followup. The population in this study was 18 years and older registered in the province of Albacete. andom sampling, stratified and two-stage. The sample size for the first cut was 2121 subjects and for second one 1577. One specific anamnesis was made, physical examination, measurement of blood pressure, electrocardiogram and extraction of venous blood. The studied variables were: age, sex, personal and familiar antecedents, risk factors and global cardiovascular risk. Results: 1322 subjects went to the appointment for the first examination (mean age 48.2 years. 53.6% women) and 997 for the second (mean age 52.8 years. 56.7% women). Has Increased the prevalence of hypertension (32.7% to 41,2%), diabetes (9,8 to 11,4%), obesity (27,8 to 34,3%) and hypercolesterolemia (47,5 to 53,5%), whereas smokers have decreased (32,6 to 23,7%) and have handicapped the average values of arterial pressure (132/81 to 129/73 mmHg), glycaemia (100,8 to 92,8 mg/dl) and LDL-cholesterol (128,7 to 116,7 mg/dl) and also a lowering of cardiovascular risk with Framingham (10,8% to 8,2%) and Score (2,3% to 1,6%). Conclusions: In the last years an increasing prevalence of risk factors has been seen (hypertension, diabetes and hypercolesterolemia), a better control of them, and lower prevalence of smoking and cardiovascular risk in the population has also be seen(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Massó Orozco, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigao Rodenas, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión Valero, Lucinio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Abril, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Divisón Garrote, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbayo Herencia, Julio A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Establecer estrategias de prevención de la enfermedad cardiovascular implica conocer su epidemiología y evolución en el tiempo. El objetivo del estudio es conocer las prevalencias de los factores de riesgo y del riesgo cardiovascular en dos momentos de seguimiento de una población general adulta. Métodos: Dentro de un estudio longitudinal y prospectivo con población general seleccionada al azar seguida durante 12 años (1992-94 a 2004-2006) se hacen dos análisis trasversales al inicio y en el último corte de seguimiento. La población objeto de estudio fueron personas mayores de 18 años censadas en la provincia de Albacete. Muestreo aleatorio, estratificado y bietápico. Tamaño muestral 2.121 y 1.577 sujetos en cada uno de los cortes. Se hizo anamnesis, exploración física, medida de presión arterial, electrocardiograma y extracción de sangre venosa. Las variables estudiadas fueron: edad, sexo, antecedentes personales y familiares, factores de riesgo y riesgo cardiovascular global. Resultados: En el primer examen acudieron a la cita 1.322 sujetos (edad media 48,2 años. 53,6% mujeres) y 997 en el segundo (edad media 52,8 años. 56,7% mujeres). Hubo un aumento en la prevalencia de hipertensión (32,7% a 41,2%) diabetes mellitus (9,8 a 11,4%), obesidad (27,8 a 34,3%) e hipercolesterolemia (47,5 a 53,5%), una disminución de fumadores (32,6 a 23,7%), de valores medios de presión arterial (132/81 a 129/73 mmHg), glucemia (100,8 a 92,8 mg/dl) y col-LDL (128,7 a 116,7 mg/dl) y un descenso del riesgo cardiovascular con Framingham (10,8% a 8,2%) y Score (2,3% a 1,6%). Conclusiones: En los últimos años se observa un aumento en la prevalencia de factores de riesgo (hipertensión, diabetes e hipercolestrerolemia), un mejor control de los mismos, una menor prevalencia de fumadores y menor riesgo cardiovascular en la población(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(3): 275-284, may.-jun.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la prevalencia de los factories de riesgo y del riesgo cardiovascular global en población mayor de 18 añor de la provincia de Albacete (1992-94 a 2004-06)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
