<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048849</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of restless legs syndrome: importance of diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Restless legs syndrome (RLS) affects 5%-10% of the population. RLS is frequently underdiagnosed and is related to impaired quality of life. RLS is characterized by an irresistible urge to move the legs and paraesthesia in the lower limbs that worsens during rest, especially at night. This syndrome is frequently associated with sleep disorders, anxiety, and depression. The etiology is unknown and the physiopathology consists of dopaminergic dysfunction. Symptomatic treatment is available and is effective in 70% of patients. This case report intends to illustrate the importance of an accurate and prompt diagnosis of RLS, allowing appropriate treatment to be initiated. Case report: We present the case of a 69-year-old woman with a 35-year history of RLS, which was not properly diagnosed until the previous year. The lack of correct diagnosis resulted in ineffective treatment of RLS and a loss of confidence in other therapeutic strategies. Discussion: The case reported herein highlights the importance of being alert to the presence of RLS in patients with symptoms of insomnia, anxiety, or depression</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Terán Sedano, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Solano, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carazo Jiménez, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraguas Herráez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome de las piernas inquietas (SPI) es un trastorno común que afecta al 5-10% de la población. El SPI está infradiagnosticado y se relaciona con peor calidad de vida. Se caracteriza por necesidad imperiosa de mover las piernas y parestesias en miembros inferiores que empeoran con el reposo y durante la noche. Se asocia con trastornos del sueño, depresivos y ansiosos. La etiología es desconocida y la fisiopatología consiste en una disfunción dopaminérgica. Se dispone de un tratamiento sintomático eficaz en un 70% de los casos. El caso clínico presentado pretende ilustrar la importancia de realizar un correcto diagnóstico de SPI que permita instaurar un adecuado tratamiento. Caso clínico: Mujer de 69 años con síntomas de SPI desde hace 35 años. Hasta hace un año no ha sido correctamente diagnosticada. Esto conllevó un tratamiento ineficaz del SPI y una pérdida de confianza en otras estrategias terapéuticas. Discusión: Este caso clínico señala la importancia de descartar el SPI en pacientes con síntomas de insomnio, depresión o ansiedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);13(4): 145-147, jun.-jul. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso de síndrome de piernas inquietas: importancia del diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
