<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125474</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">&#147;The shared decision-making process in the treatment of psychiatric patient: empirical studies and capacity assessment&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is empirical research on shared decision making in mental health, above all in depression and schizophrenia, and somewhat less in addictions. Studies carried out in recent years produce evidence showing that it improves the quality of decisions and it seems to be effective in decision making (increased knowledge and participation, promotes greater consistency with the patient values and preferences), increasing user satisfaction mostly. However, there is tiny evidence of its effectiveness on health outcomes. One of the key elements of shared decision-making processes is the determination of the patient&#146;s capacity to make the clinical decisions in question. This is an assessment that has a core role in the delicate balance between autonomy and beneficence / non-maleficence in health care. Thus, a proper assessment of the capacity of the patient to make decisions might be useful to protect both principles and to avoid two types of errors: first, to ignore unjustifiably the patient autonomy to safeguard their welfare, and secondly, the unwarranted respect for their autonomy for the price of their welfare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villagrán, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Ruiz-Granados, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Saiz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe investigación empírica sobre experiencias de decisión compartida en salud mental, preferentemente en depresión y esquizofrenia, y algo menos en adicciones. La evidencia disponible a partir de los estudios llevados a cabo en los últimos años muestra que esta práctica mejora la calidad de las decisiones y parece efectiva en el proceso decisorio (aumenta el conocimiento y la participación, favorece una mayor congruencia con los valores y preferencias del paciente), aumentando, generalmente, la satisfacción del usuario. Sin embargo, existe escasa o mínima evidencia acerca de su eficacia sobre indicadores de resultados de salud. Uno de los elementos claves de los procesos de decisión compartida es la determinación de la capacidad del paciente para tomar la decisión clínica en cuestión. Se trata de un juicio clínico que posee un papel relevante en el difícil equilibrio entre autonomía y beneficencia/no maleficencia en la atención sanitaria. Así, una adecuada evaluación de la capacidad de tomar decisiones del paciente debe servir para proteger ambos principios y evitar dos tipos de errores: por un lado, el soslayar injustificadamente la autonomía del paciente para salvaguardar su bienestar; por otro, el injustificable respeto a su autonomía al precio de su bienestar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(123): 491-505, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El proceso de decisión compartida en el tratamiento del paciente psiquiátrico: estudios empíricos y evaluación de la capacidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33537^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37676</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
