<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77615</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Problematic bacteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Because of the special characteristicsof the critical patients, infections are one of the primarycomplications they suffer so that multiresistant microorganismstake on a special importance in this type of patient.Sources. Search in Medline using the words ICU(Intensive Care Unit), multidrug resistant, critical patient.Development. Glycopeptide resistant enterococcishow a reduced prevalence in our setting and the VISAand hVISA are isolated sporadically. MRSA is, on theother hand, a major problem. In 2003-2005, it was alreadyaccounting for 28%-38% of the S. aureus isolated in theICU, with a high percentage of fluoroquinolone (&gt;90%)and macrolide (&gt;65%) co-resistance. The extended-spectrumbeta-lactamase producing enterobacteria (BLEE) alsoare a growing problem, worsened by their frequentco-resistance with fluoroquinolones, about 30% accordingto some studies. Carbapenem resistance in A. baumanniihas doubled in recent years, with values greaterthan 50%, almost always associated to enzymes of theOXA group. P. aeruginosa also maintains high resistancevalues (25%-30% of resistance to imipenem, ceftazidimeor ciprofloxacin), but more stable. However, highrates of multi-resistance are also observed, now about50% of the isolations of imipenem resistant P. aeruginosaare also to fluoroquinolones. As a whole, recent studiesshow that the multiresistance has multiplied inrecently years by 5 in P. aeruginosa and by 7 in A. baumannii  Conclusions. Multiresistant bacteria infections areone of the greatest problems to combat in critical patientsand control of their spreading and the developmentof active antimicrobials against them is one of theprincipal challenges at present(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Bellido, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las especiales características de los pacientescríticos hacen que la infección sea una de las principalescomplicaciones en los mismos y que los microorganismosmultirresistentes tengan una especial importancia eneste tipo de pacientes.Fuentes. Búsqueda en Medline bajo los epígrafes ICU(Intensive Care Unit), multidrug resistant y critical patient.Desarrollo. Los enterococos resistentes a glicopéptidosmuestran una prevalencia reducida en nuestro medio y losVISA y hVISA se aíslan de manera esporádica. MRSA constituyeen cambio un problema mayor; en 2003-2005 suponeya el 28-38% de los S. aureus aislados en UCI, con un altoporcentaje de corresistencia a fluoroquinolonas (&gt;90%) ymacrólidos (&gt; 65 %). Las enterobacterias productoras debetalactamasas de espectro extendido (BLEE) constituyentambién un problema creciente, agravado por su frecuentecorresistencia con fluoroquinolonas, cerca del 30% segúnalgunos estudios. La resistencia a carbapenemas en A. baumaniise ha doblado en los últimos años con cifras superioresal 50 %, mediada casi siempre por enzimas del grupoOXA. P. aeruginosa mantiene cifras de resistencia tambiénaltas (25-30% de resistencia a ceftazidima, a ciprofloxacinoy a imipenem), pero más estables. No obstante, se observantambién cifras altas de multirresistencia, ya que cerca del 50% de los aislamientos de P. aeruginosa resistentes a imipenemlo son también a fluoroquinolonas. En conjunto, estudiosrecientes muestran que la multirresistencia se hamultiplicado en los últimos años por 5 en P. aeruginosa ypor 7 en A. baumanii.Conclusiones. Las infecciones por bacterias multirresistentesson uno de los mayores problemas que hay que combatiren pacientes críticos, y el control de su difusión y el desarrollo de antimicrobianos activos frente a ellas uno de los principales retos en el momento actual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;21(extr.1): 2-6, jul. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bacterias problemáticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
