<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127769</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dermoscopic Findings for the Early Detection of Melanoma: An Analysis of 200 Cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Dermoscopy is a complementary technique that has led to major advances in the diagnosis of pigmented skin lesions. The aim of this study was to describe the dermoscopic features of a series of melanomas and analyze the differences between melanomas in situ and invasive melanomas. Material and methods: We retrospectively recorded epidemiological, clinical, histologic, and dermoscopic features of a series of 200 primary melanomas. We performed a descriptive and analytical study of the dermoscopic features identified. Results: The mean age of the patients was 63 years and there was a similar distribution of male and female patients. The most common histologic subtypes were superficial spreading melanoma (62.5%) and lentigo maligna (25.5%); 67% of the melanomas had a Breslow thickness of less than 1 mm and 24.5% were melanomas in situ. Overall,the most common global dermoscopic features were the multicomponent pattern (33.5%), the reticular pattern (18%), and the nonspecific pattern (15.5%). The most common local features were structureless homogeneous areas (67.5%), white-blue structures (58%), an atypical pigmented network (55.5%), and irregularly distributed dots and globules (44%). The following features were more common in invasive melanomas than in melanomas in situ: blue, gray, red and white colors, multicomponent and homogeneous patterns, dots and globules, blue-white structures, homogeneous areas, a blue-white veil, white shiny structures, a reverse pigment network, and milky-red areas. The reticular pattern was more common in melanomas in situ. Discussion: The use of dermoscopy has contributed to the early diagnosis of melanoma. The most common dermoscopic features of melanoma are multiple structures and colors (multicomponent pattern), an atypical reticular pattern (with wide, irregular meshes), and an absence of distinguishing features (nonspecific pattern) associated with the presence of vascular structures. Conclusions: Dermoscopy facilitates the diagnosis of melanoma and could be useful for differentiating between melanoma in situ and invasive melanoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avilés-Izquierdo, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro-Ochaita, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciudad-Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La dermatoscopia es una técnica complementaria que ha supuesto un gran avance en el diagnóstico de las lesiones pigmentadas. El objetivo del presente trabajo es describir las características dermatoscópicas de una serie de melanomas y analizar las diferencias entre los melanomas in situ y los melanomas invasivos. Material y métodos: Se obtuvieron de forma retrospectiva los datos referentes a las características epidemiológicas, clínicas, histológicas y dermoscópicas de una serie de 200 melanomas primarios. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y analítico de las variables dermoscópicas. Resultados: La edad media de los pacientes fue de 63 años, con una distribución similar por sexos. Los tipos histológicos más frecuentes fueron el melanoma de extensión superficial (62,5%) y el lentigo maligno (25,5%). El 67% de los melanomas tuvieron un índice de Breslow menor de 1 mm y un 24,5% fueron melanomas in situ. Los patrones dermatoscópicos globales más frecuentes fueron el multicomponente (33,5%), el reticular (18%) y el inespecífico (15,5%). Las estructuras dermatoscópicas más frecuentes fueron las áreas homogéneas desestructuradas (67,5%), las estructuras blanco-azuladas (58%), el retículo pigmentado atípico (55,5%) y los puntos y glóbulos de distribución irregular (44%). Los colores azul-gris, rojo y blanco, los patrones multicomponente y homogéneo, los puntos y glóbulos, las estructuras blanco-azuladas, las áreas homogéneas, el velo azul-blanquecino, las estructuras blancas brillantes, el retículo invertido y las áreas rojo lechosas fueron más frecuentes en los melanomas invasivos que en los melanomas in situ. El patrón reticular fue más frecuente en los melanomas in situ. Discusión: El uso de la dermatoscopia ha contribuido al diagnóstico precoz del melanoma. Los datos dermatoscópicos más frecuentes en el melanoma son la presencia de múltiples estructuras y colores (patrón multicomponente), un patrón reticular atípico con una red ensanchada e irregular y la ausencia de criterios dermatoscópicos (patrón inespecífico) asociada a la presencia de estructuras vasculares. Conclusiones: La dermatoscopia facilita el diagnóstico de melanoma. Podría tener utilidad para diferenciar los melanomas in situ de las formas invasivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(7): 683-693, sept. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127769</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hallazgos dermoscópicos para la detección precoz del melanoma. Análisis de 200 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4649^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4649^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38795^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38795^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
