<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045889</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors determining the duration of temporary disability and return to work in a health district of Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the factors associated with the incidence and duration of temporary work incapacity (TWI) in a health district.         Design. Descriptive and retrospective study.         Setting. South health district of the province of Lugo, Spain.         Participants. A random sample of 1513 cases was selected among the total of episodes of TWI, during 3 years period.         Main measures. The main factors analyzed are, on the one hand, the socio-demographic characteristics of the patient, his or her social security (SS) scheme, diagnosis that justifies         the TWD, and the prescription date; and, on the other hand, the age, sex, specialised training, time in the post and years in practice of the physician who prescribes the TWI. The comparison of the means was carried out using variance analysis and the Kruskal-Wallis test. The relative effect of each variable on the probability of returning to the work was estimated through Cox regression models.         Results. The mean duration of the episodes of TWI was of 74±103 days. The most frequent diagnoses were those of the bones-muscles and joints (BMAJ), injuries and poisonings (IAP), and respiratory diseases (RD). The probability of returning to work is reduced with the increase of the age, with agrarian and autonomous SS affiliates, with diagnoses of mental disease or diagnoses of the circulatory system, and in cases prescribed by older doctors or less time in the post.         Conclusions. The mean duration of the episodes of TWD is higher than that of other Spanish studies. The most influential factors in the return to work are the age of the patient, the SS scheme and the diagnosed illness</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bugarín-González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadarso-Suárez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés-Cuadrado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hervada-Vidal, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Barcala, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilariño-Pombo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lado-Lema, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar los factores asociados con la incidencia y la duración de la incapacidad temporal (IT) en un área sanitaria.         Diseño. Descriptivo, retrospectivo.         Emplazamiento. Área Sanitaria Sur de la provincia de Lugo.         Participantes. Una muestra de 1.513 episodios de IT seleccionada aleatoriamente entre el total de éstos, durante un período de 3 años.         Mediciones principales. Se analizaron las características sociodemográficas del paciente, el régimen de la seguridad social (SS), el diagnóstico que justifica la IT y la fecha de la prescripción; del médico prescriptor se analizaron la edad, el sexo, la formación especializada, la antigüedad en la plaza y los años de ejercicio. La comparación de medias se realizó mediante el análisis de la varianza y el test de Kruskal-Wallis. El efecto relativo de cada variable sobre la probabilidad de volver al trabajo se estimó mediante modelos de regresión de Cox.         Resultados. La duración media de los episodios de IT fue de 74 ± 103 días. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes fueron los del sistema osteomioarticular (SOMA), las lesiones y envenenamientos (LYE) y las enfermedades respiratorias (NML). Se reduce la probabilidad de volver al trabajo con el incremento de la edad, en los regímenes de seguridad social autónomos y agrarios por cuenta propia, en los diagnósticos de enfermedades mentales y del aparato circulatorio, y cuando el médico prescriptor es de mayor edad o menos antiguo en la plaza.         Conclusiones. La duración media de los episodios de IT es superior a la de otros estudios españoles. Los factores que más influyen en la reincorporación al trabajo son la edad del paciente, el régimen de la seguridad social y la enfermedad diagnosticada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;37(8): 431-436, mayo 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinantes de la duración de la incapacidad temporal y la vuelta al trabajo en un área sanitaria de Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
