<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054409</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New growth references of the World Health Organization based on breast fed infants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The World Health Organization Multicenter Growth Reference Study is a multinational project to develop new growth references for infants and young children. The design combines a longitudinal study from birth to 24 months with a cross-sectional study of children aged 18 to 71 months. The pooled sample from the six participating countries (Brazil, Ghana, India, Norway, Oman, and the United States) consists of 8440 children.         The new WHO Child Growth Standards confirm that all children worldwide, given an optimum start in life, have the same potential for growth and prove that differences in children's growth to the age of 5 years are more influenced by nutrition, feeding practices, environment, and healthcare than by genetics or ethnicity.         The new standards are based on the breast fed child as the norm for growth and development. For the first time, this ensures coherence among the tools used to assess growth and national and international infant feeding guidelines, which recommend breast feeding as the optimal source of nutrition during infancy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano de la Torre, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio multicéntrico de la Organización Mundial de la Salud sobre el patrón de crecimiento infantil es un proyecto multinacional desarrollado para elaborar nuevas referencias de crecimiento para lactantes y niños pequeños. Combinó un seguimiento longitudinal desde el nacimiento hasta los 24 meses y un estudio transversal en niños entre 18 y 71 meses de edad. La muestra final incluye 8.440 lactantes de Brasil, Estados Unidos, Ghana, India, Noruega y Omán.         El nuevo patrón confirma que todos los niños del mundo, si reciben una atención adecuada desde el comienzo de sus vidas, tienen el mismo potencial de crecimiento, y que las diferencias en el crecimiento infantil hasta los 5 años dependen más de la nutrición, el medio ambiente y la atención sanitaria que de factores genéticos o étnicos.         El nuevo patrón se basa en el niño alimentado con leche materna como norma esencial para el crecimiento y el desarrollo, lo que asegura una coherencia entre los instrumentos utilizados para evaluar el crecimiento, y las directrices sobre alimentación infantil que recomiendan la leche materna como fuente óptima de nutrición durante el período de lactancia</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(2): 177-183, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevo patrón de crecimiento infantil de la Organización Mundial de la Salud basado en lactantes amamantados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7400^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7400^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16554^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7400^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7406^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7412^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
