<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058462</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiological diagnosis of sexually-transmitted infection (2007)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sexually transmitted infections (STIs) constitute an important world-wide public health problem. The use of sensitive and specific laboratory methods for diagnosing this condition is crucial to reduce the transmission and sequelae of STI. The present review describes current microbiological methods for the diagnosis of STIs. Neisseria gonorrhoeae and Chlamydia trachomatis are the pathogens most frequently involved in urethral and cervical infection. Culture continues to be the gold standard for diagnosing gonorrhea. Nucleic acid amplification assays are considered the new gold standard for C. trachomatis, although culture is till the most specific technique. Genital ulcers due to Treponema pallidum, Haemophilus ducreyi, or herpes simplex virus have little clinical and bacteriological correlation; therefore, it is essential to establish the microbiological diagnosis. Lesions present in the primary or secondary period of syphilis can be diagnosed by dark field microscopy. Serologic diagnosis for the remaining periods is based on non-treponemal tests associated with confirmatory treponemal tests. Cell culture is considered the gold standard for herpes simplex virus although molecular methods also have a sensitivity and specificity near 100%. Currently, microbiologic diagnosis of H. ducreyi and venereal lymphogranuloma is achieved with the use of molecular methods on samples obtained from the ulceration or lymph adenopathy. The diagnosis of genital warts in immunocompetent patients is based on clinical findings in most cases because the lesions are sufficiently characteristic. Culture is considered the reference method in Trichomonas vaginalis infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Otero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lepe, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones de transmisión sexual (ITS) constituyen un importante problema de salud pública a nivel mundial. El diagnóstico microbiológico precoz mediante técnicas sensibles y específicas es crucial para una reducción exitosa de la transmisión y de las secuelas de las ITS. La presente revisión realiza una descripción de los métodos actuales empleados en el diagnóstico. Neisseria gonorrhoeae y Chlamydia trachomatis son los patógenos más frecuentes en la uretritis y la cervicitis. El cultivo sigue siendo la técnica de referencia para el diagnóstico de la gonococia; en el caso de C. trachomatis, las técnicas de amplificación de ácidos nucleicos se consideran el nuevo patrón de referencia, aunque el cultivo sigue siendo la técnica más específica. Las úlceras genitales debidas a Treponema pallidum, Haemophilus ducreyi o virus del herpes simple tienen una pequeña correlación clinicobacteriológica y, por tanto, es esencial llevar a cabo estudios microbiológicos para establecer el diagnóstico. Las lesiones presentes en el período primario o secundario de la sífilis se pueden diagnosticar por microscopia de campo oscuro; el diagnóstico serológico en el resto de períodos implica la realización de pruebas no treponémicas junto con pruebas treponémicas confirmatorias. Para el virus del herpes simple, el cultivo celular se considera el método de referencia; los métodos moleculares también tienen una sensibilidad y especificidad cercanas al 100%. Actualmente, el diagnóstico microbiológico de H. ducreyi y del linfogranuloma venéreo se basa en el empleo de técnicas moleculares sobre muestras obtenidas de la ulceración o adenopatía. El diagnóstico de las verrugas genitales en el paciente inmunocompetente en la mayoría de los casos es sólo clínico al ser las lesiones suficientemente características. Respecto a las infecciones por Trichomonas vaginalis, el cultivo se considera el método de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(1): 32-37, ene. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico microbiológico de las infecciones de transmisión sexual (2007)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15030^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
