<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99940</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unfunded childhood vaccines. What is the coverage in an urban healthcare center?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the coverage rate for unfunded childhood vaccines, and whether they were administered correctly, in children seen recently at an urban healthcare center in a middle socioeconomic area. Materials and methods: we performed a cross-sectional descriptive study, analyzing the pneumococcus, rotavirus, and varicella vaccination records in the computerized clinical histories of every child, seen by either of two pediatricians, who could have been given all the doses recommended for these vaccines. Results: the study included 162 children of immunization age for pneumococcal disease, 112 for rotavirus, and 160 for varicella. The coverage rates for complete immunization as specified in the recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Vaccines were 64.81%, 66%, and 58.1%, respectively. 11.73% of those who started pneumococcal vaccination and 2.68% of those who started rotavirus vaccination did not complete the recommended number of doses. There were no significant differences in vaccination rates between the two pediatricians. Conclusions: we found evidence of mid-range vaccine coverage rates and incomplete vaccination courses. The financial resources of the families and the educational efforts of the Nursing and Pediatrics staff account for these vaccination rates. We do not know the epidemiological effect of these vaccination rates on the diseases that they are meant to prevent. We need to promote equity in healthcare services when it comes to immunizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero Bregón, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Fernández, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Moreno, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustamante Marcos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriada Álvarez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago García, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la tasa de cobertura de las vacunas infantiles no financiadas y si son administradas correctamente, en los niños atendidos recientemente en un centro de salud urbano de nivel socioeconómico medio. Material y métodos: se realiza un estudio transversal, descriptivo, analizando el registro de vacunas frente al neumococo, rotavirus y varicela de la historia informatizada de los niños atendidos por dos pediatras, que hayan podido recibir todas las dosis recomendadas. Resultados: se han incluido 162 niños susceptibles de vacunación frente a neumococo, 112 para el rotavirus y 160 para varicela. Las tasas de cobertura para la vacunación completa según recomendaciones del Comité Asesor de Vacunas han sido el 64,81, el 66 y el 58,1%, respectivamente. El 11,73% de los que inician la vacunación frente al neumococo y el 2,68% del rotavirus no completan el número de dosis recomendadas. No hubo diferencias de vacunación significativas entre ambos pediatras. Conclusiones: nos encontramos con unos niveles de cobertura vacunal medios y con pautas incompletas. Los recursos económicos de las familias y la labor educativa del personal de Enfermería y Pediatría son los responsables de estas tasas vacunales. Desconocemos el efecto epidemiológico sobre las enfermedades que se quieren prevenir, de estas tasas vacunales. Es necesario fomentar la equidad en las prestaciones sanitarias relacionadas con las vacunas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;14(53): 21-26, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99940</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacunas infantiles no financiadas, ¿cuál es la cobertura en un centro de salud urbano?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35386^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33082^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30984^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
