<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131945</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anorexia nervosa in a worker: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the management of a case of anorexia nervosa (body mass index, &#150;BMI&#150;, 13,6 Kg/m2) in a bank teller. The case was detected through routine occupational health surveillance. After being evaluated by different specialists (general practitioner, psychiatrist and endocrinologist) and being closely monitored (by psychology, nursing, and occupational medicine), the worker regained weight to a near normal BMI (17 Kg/m2) in less than a year and a half. Eating disorders area common pathology (non-occupationally related), but their high prevalence (5% of the population over a lifetime) and social and job-related impact (affecting more than 20% of cases), make them a necessary focus of attention for health promotion in the workplace. Health prevention, promotion and surveillance may be also reinforced at the workplace (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Fernández, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Ruipérez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Astray, María-Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-García, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso-Barbero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Garrido, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe la gestión de un caso de anorexia nerviosa (índice de masa corporal IMC 13,6 kg/m2) en una cajera de una oficina bancaria. El caso se detectó durante un reconocimiento rutinario de vigilancia de la salud. Tras ser valorada por distintos especialistas (medicina de familia, psiquiatría y endocrinología) y de un estrecho seguimiento (por psicología, enfermería y medicina del trabajo) recupera peso hasta casi la normalidad (IMC 17 kg/m2) en menos de año y medio. Los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria son considerados patología común (no laboral), pero su alta prevalencia (5% de la población a lo largo de la vida) y su repercusión laboral y social (afectando a más del 20% de los casos), los convierten en foco potencial de atención desde la promoción de la salud en el trabajo. La prevención, promoción y vigilancia de la salud de la población pueden ser reforzadas desde la empresa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);18(1): 17-19, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anorexia nerviosa en una trabajadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51559</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
