<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74990</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Voriconazole for the therapy of mycoses in recipients of solid organ transplants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Invasive fungal infections (IFI) are the third cause of infectious complications inrecipients of solid organ transplants (SOT), showing an incidence of 5-42%depending of the trasplanted organ. Moreover, IFI account for significantmorbility and mortality in SOT, ranging between 25-95% depending on thetype of fungus and its organ localization. Different strategies (prophylaxis,preemptive treatment, treatment, antifungal combinations, routes ofadministration) have been tested to improve the prognosis of IFI in SOT.To reach this objective, it was essential to have access to new antifungalsshowing a higher spectrum of activity on the fungal pathogens, both classicaland emerging, and showing improvements in pharmacokinetic andpharmacodynamic characteristics, ease of administration and acceptability andlower rates of adverse effects. Introduction of voriconazole in the therapeuticarsenal has facilitated to reach these goals due to its special pharmacologicalcharacteristics, its in vitro antifungal activity and the in vivo clinical efficacydemonstrated in different studies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solé, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salavert, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones fúngicas invasoras (IFI) suponen la tercera causa decomplicaciones infecciosas en los pacientes receptores de trasplantede órganos sólidos (TOS), con una incidencia del 5-42%, dependiendo delórgano trasplantado. Además, constituyen una importante causa demorbilidad y mortalidad en los TOS, que oscila entre el 25-95%, según el tipode hongo y su localización. Diferentes estrategias (profilaxis, tratamientoanticipado, terapia dirigida, combinaciones, vías de administracióncomplementarias) han sido ensayadas para mejorar el pronóstico de las IFIen los TOS. Para su aplicación, era esencial disponer de nuevos antifúngicos,con un espectro más amplio sobre los patógenos fúngicos, tradicionalesy emergentes, con mejoras en las propiedades farmacocinéticas yfarmacodinámicas, comodidad de administración y menor tasa de efectosadversos. En este sentido, la introducción de voriconazol en el arsenalterapéutico ha facilitado la consecución de estos objetivos por sus especialescaracterísticas farmacológicas, por la actividad antifúngica in vitro y por laeficacia clínica in vivo que ha demostrado en diferentes estudios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(3): 217-222, 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Voriconazol como terapia de las micosis en receptores de Trasplantes de Órganos Sólidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
