<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146638</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Work-related commom mental disorders in Navarra, Spain (2009-2012)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine work-related mental health morbidity and correct psychosocial risks. Methodology: In this pilot study conducted at a mental health center, work-related common mental disorders were identified and population incidence was estimated. We next described cases reported from primary care centers in the period 2009 to 2012, via the Occupational Health Surveillance Program. Incidence was calculated by socioeconomic variables. Associations among variables (Chi 2 test), their prevalence ratios (PR) and the correlation of risks (kappa coefficient) were compared. Reporting of these cases to the occupational health services and subsequent actions are described. Results: In the pilot study, 17.5% of common mental disorders were work-related (7.2 x 1000 workers / year). Among the reported cases, incidence was higher in unskilled occupations, feminized economic activities and the services sector. Seventy per cent of cases were associated with hostile behavior and 14.2% with organizational factors. In addition, 83.2% of cases led to sickness absence episodes. Managing directors were at greater risk of bullying (PR 3.92 95%CI 2.35-6.53) as compared to other risks. Overall, 20% of cases ended in job dismissal, particularly in cases of mistreatment or bullying (PR 1.64 95%CI 1.24-2.16). Conclusions: It is necessary to implement reporting systems and prevention programs for work-relaed mental disorders, especially for collectives of workers with high risk profiles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García López, Vega</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Sueskun, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la morbilidad mental poblacional de origen laboral y corregir el riesgo psicosocial de los casos notificados. Métodos: Mediante estudio piloto en un Centro de Salud Mental se identificaron los trastornos mentales comunes de origen laboral y se estimó la incidencia poblacional. Posteriormente describimos los casos notificados desde centros de salud, entre los años 2009 y 2012 adheridos al sistema de vigilancia epidemiológica ocupacional. Calculamos incidencias por variables sociolaborales. Se contrasta la asociación entre variables (Chi 2), Razones de Prevalencia (RP) y concordancia de riesgos (índice Kappa). Se describe la comunicación de los casos a los Servicios de Prevención y su actuación. Resultados: En el estudio piloto el 17,5% de los trastornos fueron de origen laboral (7,2 por 1000 trabajadores/año). De los casos notificados se observa mayor incidencia en actividades económicas feminizadas, servicios y ocupaciones menos cualificadas. El 70% de los casos derivan de conductas hostiles y el 14,2% de factores organizativos. El 83,2% cursa con incapacidad temporal. Los directores-gerentes tienen mayor riesgo de sufrir acoso (RP 3,92 IC95% 2,35-6,53) que otros riesgos. En conjunto el 20% de los casos termina en despido, con mayor frecuencia en supuestos de maltrato o acoso moral (RP 1,64 IC95% 1,24-2,16). Conclusiones: Es necesario implementar sistemas de notificación y programas preventivos de los trastornos mentales comunes de origen laboral, especialmente en los trabajadores con perfiles de mayor riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);18(4): 192-199, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos mentales comunes derivados del trabajo en Navarra (2009-2012)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
