<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154196</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Feeding practices with human milk in newborns less than 1.500 g or less than 32 weeks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is currently no unified policy on either breastfeeding support or enteral nutrition practices, as regards human milk (HM) in pre-term newborns. The aim of this study was to describe breastfeeding support measures, as well as the use of HM in very preterm infants in Spanish public hospitals. Method: A questionnaire on enteral feeding practices was distributed. Data were analysed from units caring for newborns less than 32 weeks or 1,500g. A univariate analysis was performed comparing level II and III care units. Results: There was a 91% response rate. A total of 93 units cared for infants less than 32 weeks or 1,500g (17 level II and 76 level III), and 49% of the units recorded the breastfeeding rate on discharge. Around 75% (70/93) had a guideline on managing HM (level III 81 vs. level II 47%,P=.002), and 25% had access to donor human milk. Just under half (46%) started trophic feeding in the first 6h. Target enteral feeding volume in stable preterm infants was &amp;#8805; 180ml/kg/day in 89% of the units (level III 93% vs. level II 70%, P =.017). HM fortifier was used in 96% of the units. In 92%, it was added when the required enteral volume was tolerated. In 59% of the units, adjustments in the quantity of fortifier were made according to weight, and in 36%, it depended on analytical criteria. Some units (9%) used pure protein fortifier. Conclusions: There is a marked variability in breastfeeding support measures and in feeding practices of preterm infants in Spanish neonatal units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alba Romero, Concepción de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Flores, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Maestro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Díaz, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Utrera Torres, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lora Pablos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallás Alonso, Carmen R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Actualmente no existe una política unificada de cómo promocionar la lactancia materna en la unidad neonatal ni sobre la práctica de nutrición enteral con leche materna (LM) en los prematuros. Nuestro objetivo fue describir las medidas de apoyo a la lactancia y la utilización de LM en grandes prematuros de los hospitales públicos españoles. Método: Se distribuyó un cuestionario sobre prácticas de alimentación enteral. Se analizaron los datos de las unidades que atendían a menores de 32 semanas o 1.500g. Se realizó un análisis univariante comparando las unidades de nivel II y III. Resultados: La tasa de respuesta fue del 91%. Un total de 93 unidades atienden a menores de 32 semanas o de 1.500 g (17 de nivel II y 76 de nivel III). El 49% registra la tasa de lactancia al alta. En el 75% (70/93) existe una guía de manejo de LM (nivel III 81 vs. nivel II 47%; p=0,002). El 25% dispone de leche donada. El 46% inicia alimentación trófica en las primeras 6 h. En el 89% el volumen máximo de LM administrado es &amp;#8805;180ml/kg/día (nivel III 93 vs. nivel II70%; p=0,017). Se fortifica en el 96% de las unidades y el 92% la inicia a partir de un volumen determinado de leche. Para modificar la cantidad de fortificante, el 59% utiliza la curva de peso y el 36% criterios analíticos. El 9% emplea fortificante proteico puro. Conclusiones: Existe una gran variabilidad en las medidas de apoyo a la lactancia y en las prácticas de alimentación enteral de los grandes prematuros en las unidades españolas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);85(1): 26-33, jul. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154196</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas de alimentación con leche materna en recién nacidos menores de 1.500 g o de menos de 32 semanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52501^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
