<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104388</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From its introduction in the decade of the 70&#146;s the evolution of the calcium channel blockers has allowed to resolve the uncertainty initially generated by those first-generation drugs. These, are characterized by a smaller oral availability, a fast vasodilator action and a short duration of action. Manidipine arises as a dihydropyridinecalcium antagonist of third generation with real additional advantages regarding to previous generations. They show high lipophilia, a more prolonged action and as well as a prolonged average life at the level of his receptor and, in addition, some theoretical advantages among others calcium antagonists, improvements on the renal function by reducing the intraglomerular pressure and microalbuminuria. Nevertheless, the clinical evaluation of these last properties still depends on the results derived from clinical trials. Besides to go deep in its role in their antihypertensive effect, we presented a brief review on new cardiometabolic aspects of these dihydropyridines calcium antagonists focusing in manidipine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez,  J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buset Ríos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Esparragón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su introducción en la década de los 70, la evolución de los calcioantagonistas ha permitido solventar la incertidumbre inicialmente generada por aquellos fármacos deprimera generación. Éstos se caracterizan por una menor disponibilidad oral, una acción vasodilatadora rápida y corta acción. El manidipino surge como un derivado dihidropiridínico de tercera generación con ventajas adicionales reales frente a las generaciones anteriores, como son su alta lipofilicidad, su acción más prolongada y una vida media prolongada a nivel del receptor y, además, algunas ventajas teóricas entre otras, mejoras sobre la función renal reduciendo la presión intraglomerular y la microalbuminuria. Sin embargo, la evaluación clínica de estas últimas propiedades depende aún de los resultados que se deriven de la experiencia clínica. Además de ahondar ensu papel en la reducción de la presión arterial, presentamos una breve revisión sobre nuevos aspectos cardiometabólicos de los calcioantagonistas dihidropiridínicos, centrándonos en el manidipino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;29(3): 203-207, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades cardiometabólicas del manidipino: ¿más allá de la reducción de la presión arterial?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51236^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22879^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38788^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14953^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
