<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69128</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular risk in patients undergoing haemodialysis is higher than in the non-uremic population. These patients also have more risk factors, both modifiable and genetic. In the case of metabolic syndrome, understood as a series of modifiable risk factors, nurses have a relevant role in its treatment as it is based on following a suitable diet, taking exercise and control over medication. The aim of this work is to identify patients whome et the diagnostic criteria of metabolic syndrome and review the bibliography to establish guidelines for action aimed at reducing cardiovascular risk factors. The results show that the proportion of patients in the unit with an excess of abdominal fat and with a body mass index higher than recommended is high. These data justify the need to draw up a specific training plan aimed at these patients, since the latest studies analysed determine that the reduction of abdominal fat and the body mass index are the main factors in reducing resistance to insulin and cardiovascular risk. The guidelines aimed at improving patient information and education on following a healthier lifestyle are drawn up taking into account criteria of diet, exercise and control over medication, which have proven their effectiveness in preventing the risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Picó Mira, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Roig, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca Alonso, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huéscar Massó, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iborra Moltó, Carmelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El riesgo cardiovascular en los pacientes tratados con hemodiálisis es más elevado que en la población no urémica. Estos pacientes además tienen más factores de riesgo, tanto modificables como genéticos. En el caso del síndrome metabólico, entendido como un conjunto de factores de riesgo modificables, las enfermeras tenemos un papel relevante en su tratamiento ya que se basa en el seguimiento de una dieta adecuada, en la realización de ejercicio físico y en un control de la medicación. El objetivo de este trabajo es identificar los pacientes que cumplen los criterios diagnósticos del síndrome metabólico y revisar la bibliografía para establecer pautas de actuación dirigidas a reducirlos factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Los resultados muestran que la proporción de pacientes en la unidad con exceso de grasa abdominal y con un índice de masa corporal por encima de lo recomendable es elevada. Estos datos justifican la necesidad de elaborar un plan de formación específica dirigida a estos pacientes, ya que los últimos estudios analizados determinan que la reducción de la grasa abdominal y del índice de masa corporal, son los factores principales para reducir la resistencia a la insulina y el riesgo cardiovascular. Las pautas de actuación dirigidas a mejorar la información y formación de los pacientes sobre el seguimiento de un estilo de vida más saludable, se elabora teniendo en cuenta criterios alimentarios, de ejercicio físico y de control de la toma de medicación, que han demostrado su eficacia en la prevención del riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;11(2): 89-94, abr.-jun. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69128</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
