<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76966</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstructive uropathy secondary to vesico-ureteral endometriosis: clinical, radiologic and pathologic features</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To report the case of a 37 year-old woman suffering from endometriosis of the urinary tract, that presented with lumbar and pelvic pain associated to cyclic recurrent haematuria.METHODS: Following history, physical examination, abdomino-pelvic ultrasound (USS), CT scan and cystoscopy with biopsies, surgical treatment was indicatedRESULTS: Imaging (USS-CT) revealed a protrusion of the left bladder hemi-trigone with a nodular, irregular thickening and ipsilateral grade II-III/IV uretero-hydronefrosis. Cistoscopy confirmed a swollen and oedematous lesion in left hemi-trigone that seemed extrinsic in origin. With the clinical diagnosis of a possible neoplasia of gynaecological origin, the patient underwent surgical treatment consisting in radical hysterectomy with bilateral oophorectomy, partial cystectomy and left ureteroneocystostomy.CONCLUSIONS: The frequency of endometriosis in the urinary tract is relatively low and therefore, endometriosis presenting with ureteral obstruction (uretero-hydronephrosis) has been rarely reported in the literature and should be part of the differential diagnosis in young women, especially if symptoms are cyclic. The treatment is surgery and the final diagnosis by pathology report(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Jiménez, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Pulido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julve Villalta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antuña Calle, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Palanca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Carrillo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Moreno, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amores Ramírez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Describir un nuevo caso de afectación del tracto urinario por endometriosis en una mujer de 37 años que consultó por dolor pélvico, lumbar y hematuria de carácter cíclicos.MÉTODO: Tras la realización de historia clínica y exploraciones complementarias como ecografía abdominal, TAC abdominopélvico y cistoscopia con toma de biopsias se indicó tratamiento quirúrgico.RESULTADOS: En las pruebas de imagen realizadas (ECO-TAC) se apreció una impronta y engrosamiento nodular e irregular de la hemibase vesical izquierda, con afectación ureteral y dilatación pielocalicial grado II-III/IV. En la cistoscopia se observó lesión congestiva y edematosa a nivel de hemitrígono izquierdo. Con el diagnóstico clínico de neoformación ginecológica localmente avanzada con afectación uréterovesical se realizó tratamiento quirúrgico consistente en histerectomía, anexectomía bilateral, cistectomía parcial y ureterocistoneostomía izquierda.CONCLUSIONES: La frecuencia de la afectación del tracto urinario por endometriosis es relativamente baja, sin embargo, la afectación ureteral obstructiva (hidronefrosis) es un hecho escasamente referido en la literatura consultada y que debe tenerse en cuenta ante cuadros de este tipo en mujeres jóvenes, principalmente si se acompaña de síntomas cíclicos. El diagnóstico definitivo es histológico y el tratamiento quirúrgico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(8): 653-656, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uropatia obstructiva secundaria a endometriosis vésico-ureteral: características clínico radiológicas y anatomopatológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14951</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14951^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
