<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056021</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thyroid dysfunction and diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 1 diabetes is an autoimmune endocrine disorder that often occurs    in association with other autoimmune diseases, including autoimmune    thyroid disease. These diseases are associated with organ-    specific autoantibodies. Using these autoantibodies to screen    subjects makes it possible to diagnose both diseases, even before    the clinical signs develop. In this review, the author examines major    publications dealing with the prevalence of thyroid autoimmunity in    type 1 diabetic patients (children and adults), as well as in other less    common conditions, such as latent autoimmune diabetes in adults    (LADA), and during pregnancy. Furthermore, he also analyzes the    prognostic value of thyroid autoimmunity, that is, its value in predicting    progression to either overt or subclinical hypothyroidism, its influence    on glycemic control or on growth in terms of height and weight,    and current therapeutic options. Finally, current recommendations for    screening for autoimmune thyroid disease in type 1 diabetic patients    are summarized</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escalada, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1) es una enfermedad autoinmunitaria    que predispone a la aparición de otras similares. La combinación    más frecuente es la asociación de DM1 y enfermedad tiroidea autoinmunitaria.    Ambas se caracterizan por la existencia de autoanticuerpos    específicos de órgano, que pueden tener un papel en el cribado    de dichas enfermedades para su diagnóstico precoz. En este artículo    se analizan las principales publicaciones referentes a la prevalencia    de autoinmunidad tiroidea en pacientes con DM1 en diferentes    grupos de edad (niños, adultos), así como en situaciones especiales    (diabetes autoinmunitaria latente del adulto y embarazo). Asimismo,    se analiza la significación pronóstica de la presencia de dicha autoinmunidad    tiroidea, es decir, su valor predictivo de evolución a disfunción    tiroidea, la influencia sobre el control metabólico y el crecimiento,    y las posibilidades terapéuticas contempladas en la    actualidad. Finalmente, se recogen las recomendaciones actuales    referentes al cribado de estas enfermedades tiroideas autoinmunes    en los pacientes con DM1</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(3): 172-178, mayo-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos tiroideos y diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19403^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29203^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
