<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160329</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current results of RIRS and comparison with PCNL</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The objective of this article is to show the current situation regarding two surgical techniques for the treatment of renal lithiasis, RIRS (Retrograde intrarenal surgery) and PCNL (Percutaneous nephrolithotomy), specially concerning the larger size stones. We perform a literature review on the topic and add the experience with both techniques at our center. Besides, we also analyze the role of RIRS in comparison with the percutaneous techniques in smaller size lithiasis. Methods: We review the results obtained in the literature and our experience. We offer our opinion in reference to the indications of RIRS in these cases based on such review and our experience. Results/conclusions: RIRS is a safe and effective technique, with a similar success rate to PCNL if one assumes the possibility of retreatment in stones &gt;2cm. Its low complication rate, fast postoperative recovery and short hospital stay make this technique a therapeutic alternative to PCNL in this type of patients. Compared with percutaneous techniques less invasive than classical 24 to 30 Ch. accesses (miniperc or microperc), RIRS offers a higher stone free rate. If we also consider that RIRS is associated with shorter hospital stay and lower bleeding risk, even without significant differences in the global complication rate we could consider RIRS as the first line endourological treatment in stones &lt;2cm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ganau Ituren, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palmero Martí, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valls González, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del siguiente trabajo es mostrar la situación actual en lo referente a dos técnicas quirúrgicas para el tratamiento de la litiasis renal, CRIR (Cirugia Retrógrada Intrarrenal) y NLPC (Nefrolitotomía Percutánea), sobre todo en lo referente a litiasis de mayor tamaño. Para ello revisamos la literatura al respecto y añadimos la experiencia de nuestro centro en relación a ambas técnicas. Por otro lado, también se analiza el papel de CRIR frente a técnicas percutáneas en litiasis de menor tamaño. Métodos: Revisión de los resultados descritos en la literatura y la experiencia de nuestro centro. Ofrecemos nuestra opinión en base a esta revisión y experiencia propia, en lo referente a las indicaciones de la CRIR en estos casos. Resultados/conclusiones: La CRIR es una técnica segura y eficaz, con una tasa de éxito similar a NLPC si se asume la posibilidad de retratamiento en litiasis &gt;2cm. Su baja tasa de complicaciones, la rápida recuperación postoperatoria y la corta estancia hospitalaria hacen de esta técnica una alternativa terapéutica a la NLPC en este tipo de pacientes. En comparación con técnicas percutáneas de menor invasividad que los accesos clásicos de 24 ó 30 Ch. (mini o microPERC), la CRIR ofrece una mayor tasa libre de litiasis que estas técnicas. Si además, consideramos que la CRIR se acompaña de menor estancia hospitalaria, riesgo de sangrado, aún sin encontrar diferencias significativas en la tasa de complicaciones globales, podríamos considerar la CRIR como tratamiento endourológico de primera línea en las litiasis &lt;2cm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(1): 147-154, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160329</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados actuales de la CRIR y comparación con NLPC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
