<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154470</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of cardiometabolic risk among childhood acute leukemia survivors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Survivors of childhood acute leukemia (AL) face an increased risk of metabolic and cardiovascular late effects which increase their long-term morbimotality. Objective: To assess the prevalence of obesity, insulinresistance, dyslipidemia and hypertension as cardiometabolic risk factors in survivors of a childhood AL, and also to determine possible causes for these adverse cardiometabolic traits. Material and methods: A retrospective cohort study of 47 pediatric acute leukemia survivors diagnosed between 0-15 years, with a ten years follow-up. Results: Forty percent of participants had at least one cardiometabolic risk factor. Dyslipidemia (increased LDL cholesterol) was the most frequent (38.3%), secondly overweight/obese (31.9%), followed by systolic hypertension (23.4%). Females in contrast to males had an increased risk of developing all three risk factors (RR 1.6; RR 3.16; RR 1.69; p &lt; 0.05). Only 19.4% of participants developed insulin resistance, while none were diagnosed with diabetes mellitus. High risk acute leukemia survivors were significantly more likely than low risk leukemia survivors to manifest multiple cardiometabolic traits like overweight/obesity, insulin resitance and dyslipidemia (RR 3.56; RR 2.39; RR 2.53; p &lt; 0.05). Also, those who received hematopoietic cell trasplantation had an increased prevalence of overweight/obesity, increased LDL-cholesterol and systolic hypertension. Radiotherapy treatment was also associated with insulin resitance and systolic hypertension (RR 2.47; RR 2.53; p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: There is an increased risk of overweight/obesity, dyslipidemia, insulin resistance and systolic blood pressure modifi cation in childhood acute leukemia survivors, specially in those who were diagnosed as a high risk acute laukemia and those treated with more aggressive treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo Escribano, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labarta Aizpun, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corella Aznar, Elena Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vigil, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Montañés, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper Villagrasa, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayerza Casas, Ariadna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los supervivientes de leucemia aguda (LA) infantil presentan un riesgo incrementado de alteraciones metabólicas y cardiovasculares que aumentan su morbimortalidad a largo plazo. Objetivo: estimar la prevalencia de obesidad, resistencia a la insulina, dislipemia e hipertensión arterial como factores de riesgo cardiometabólico (FRCM) en un grupo de supervivientes de LA infantil, y analizar las posibles causas asociadas a su desarrollo. Material y métodos: estudio observacional retrospectivo en 47 supervivientes de LA tratados en un periodo de 4 años, que recibieron seguimiento durante 10 años. Resultados: el 40% de los participantes presentaron al menos un FRCM durante el seguimiento, siendo la dislipemia (aumento LDL) el más frecuente (38,3%), seguido de obesidad/sobrepeso (31,9%) y HTA sistólica (23,4%). El sexo femenino se estableció como factor de riesgo para el desarrollo de todos ellos (RR 1,6; RR 3,16; RR 1,69; p &lt; 0,05). Ningún superviviente desarrolló diabetes mellitus, pero sí resistencia a la insulina el 19,4%. Los pacientes con leucemias de peor pronóstico presentaron mayor riesgo de desarrollar obesidad, resistencia a la insulina y aumento de LDL (RR 3,56; RR 4,08; RR 2,53; p &lt; 0,05). Los pacientes tratados con trasplante de progenitores hematopoyéticos presentaron mayor riesgo de obesidad, aumento de LDL e HTA sistólica (RR 2,86; RR 2,39; RR 3,12; p&lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: existe un aumento en la prevalencia de obesidad/sobrepeso, dislipemia, resistencia a la insulina y alteración de la tensión arterial sistólica en supervivientes de leucemia aguda infantil a lo largo del tiempo, especialmente en aquellos con enfermedades y tratamientos más agresivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 549-555, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del riesgo cardiometabólico en pacientes supervivientes de leucemia aguda infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23872^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31019^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
