<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131211</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fingertip pulse oximeter: a new tool for self-care in asthma?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the overall treatment of asthma is a priority to know the state of knowledge and attitudes of children, their families and their environment (schools, sports), and also what resources are available of them. Some pediatricians in primary care, pediatric pulmonologists, and other health health caregivers, they use a finger Pulse Oximeter recently. And now many patients also use them. We wonder: do the patients with chronic respiratory pathology use finger Pulse Oximeter? Is this technology easily accessible? Is it advisable? We present a real case, and also type-case of use of finger Pulse Oximeter and its utilities in primary care, emergency and specialized (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zafra Anta, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas Martín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medino Muñoz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando López de la Manzanara, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el tratamiento global del asma resulta prioritario saber el estado de conocimientos y actitudes de los niños, sus familias y su entorno (centros escolares, deportivos), y también de qué recursos disponen. Algunos pediatras de Atención Primaria, neumopediatras y otros sanitarios utilizan desde hace poco tiempo un pulsioxímetro de dedo o dactilar. Y ahora muchos pacientes también lo usan. Nos hemos preguntado: ¿los pacientes con patología respiratoria de repetición o crónica utilizan pulsioxímetro dactilar?, ¿esta tecnología es fácilmente accesible?, ¿es recomendable? Presentamos un caso real, y también sirve de caso tipo de pulsioximetría dactilar y sus utilidades en Atención Primaria, Urgencias y Atención Especializada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(64): 317-320, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131211</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pulsioxímetro dactilar: ¿una nueva herramienta para el autocontrol en asma?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
