<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81957</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Creative intelligence and thinking styles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The thinking styles (legislative, ejecutive and judicial styles) and creativity had been put in relation in the Sternberg&#146;s theory of Mental Self-Government. The general objective of this work is to explore the relationship between thinking styles and creativity in students of the faculty of Psychology and Education. The Sternberg-Wagner Thinking Styles Inventory and the test of Corbalán (CREA) were administrated in a sample composed by 237 students. The research was conducted with a mean difference analisys between the most creative subjects (using one standard deviation over the mean as the cutpoint to identify the most creative subjects) and the medium and low creativity persons. Mean differences in the use of the legislative style between the high creative students and the rest were founded. This results indicate that the high creativity students prefer the legislative styles. The data founded here suggests that the CREA seems to be a good instrument to discriminate those subjects with high creativity capacities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Martínez, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Brufau, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Teoría del Autogobierno Mental de Sternberg ha relacionado diferentes estilos de pensamiento (legislativo, ejecutivo y judicial) con la creatividad (Sternberg, 1999). El objetivo general de este trabajo es explorar la relación existente entre los estilos de pensamiento y la creatividad. El Cuestionario de Estilos de Pensamiento (TSI) de Sternberg y Wagner y el Test de Inteligencia Creativa (CREA) de Corbalán y colaboradores fue administrada a una muestra total de 237 alumnos, pertenecientes a la Facultad de Psicología y de Educación de la Universidad de Murcia (España) que cursan 2º y de 1º de carrera respectivamente. La investigación se llevó a cabo a través de un análisis de comparación de medias entre los estudiantes más creativos (situados sobre una desviación típica por encima de la media en creatividad) y de creatividad media y baja. Los resultados arrojan diferencias de medias entre los alumnos más creativos indicando una mayor tendencia a utilizar el estilo de pensamiento legislativo en individuos creativos lo que coincide con la teoría del autogobierno mental de Sternberg. Con todo ello podemos decir que el CREA resulta un buen instrumento para discriminar aquellos sujetos con altas capacidades creativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;26(2): 254-258, jul.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de pensamiento y creatividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
