<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-20302</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking Prevention Policies in European Countries and Companies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Many companies are exploring the issue of adopting measures to deal with involuntary smoking. The most comprehensive policies aim at systematically taking action in all possible directions (informing employees, stipulating specific smoking areas, treatment for quitting smoking...). Many agencies are likewise carrying out initiatives for intervention at companies. This study reviews interventions currently being carried out and their components, based on company studies from different European countries. The main common principles for a smoking prevention policy with the greatest prospects for success are identified. This information can be used as a reference for a European model for policies on smoking at the workplace (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Muchas empresas se plantean la adopción de medidas para afrontar el tabaquismo involuntario. Las políticas más integrales se proponen actuar sistemáticamente en todas las direcciones posibles (con información a los trabajadores, delimitación de espacios, apoyo terapéutico para dejar de fumar...). Asimismo, muchas agencias desarrollan iniciativas de intervención en las empresas. En este trabajo se revisan las intervenciones existentes y los elementos que las integran, a partir de estudios de empresas de distintos países europeos. Se identifican los principios comunes en la puesta en práctica de una política de prevención del tabaquismo con mayores garantías de éxito. Esta información puede utilizarse como referencia para un modelo europeo de política sobre tabaquismo en el medio laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;77(1): 75-95, ene. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Políticas de prevención del tabaquismo en empresas europeas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Melero, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-20302</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
