<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121784</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Executive functions development, from childhood to youthhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The executive functions are among the most complex cognitive processes in the human; during development they support the conformation of several capacities for organization and control of behavior and cognition. In this article an extensive review on the most relevant scientific literature is presented, with a developmental range from childhood to youth hood. An analysis on the developmental characteristics of the main executive functions is offered. The review indicates that the hypothesis stated by Victoria Anderson a decade ago, is accurate: the executive functions develops in a sequential form, with a curvilinear behavior: an intense progression during childhood, with slowness by early adolescence. Effects of additional factors like school level, parenting, and cultural context are also analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flores-Lázaro, Julio C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Preciado, Rosa E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Miramonte, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las funciones ejecutivas se encuentran entre los procesos más complejos del humano; su desarrollo permite la conformación de diversas capacidades de control, y organización de la conducta y la cognición. En este artículo se presenta una extensa revisión de la literatura más relevante a nivel internacional sobre el tema. Se abarca el proceso de desarrollo desde la niñez hasta la juventud, analizando las características de desarrollo de las principales funciones ejecutivas. Se muestra que la hipótesis planteada por Victoria Anderson hace ya una década es correcta: las funciones ejecutivas se desarrollan de forma secuencial y curvilínea: un intenso progreso en la infancia, con una desaceleración a inicios de la adolescencia. También se analiza el efecto de otros factores adicionales a la edad como son el efecto de la escolaridad, los estilos parentales y el contexto cultural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(2): 463-473, mayo-ago. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de funciones ejecutivas, de la niñez a la juventud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1544</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
