<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108915</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shoulder musculoskeletal disorders in primary care. A cross-sectional study in a health care center of the Valencia Health Care Agency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Musculoskeletal shoulder problems are a common cause of morbidity in the general population and can lead to occupational and domestic functional alterations. The main objective of this study is to calculate the prevalence of musculoskeletal shoulder disorders in the health care setting. Material and method We conducted a cross-sectional study to calculate the prevalence of shoulder disorders in a primary health care setting. To acquire information, interconsultation documents and the statistical records from a Basic Rehabilitation Unit, concerning the years 2009 and 2010, were employed. Results A total of 1,565 patients were attended in the medical centre during the study period, 268 cases of which were included in the study. Prevalence of shoulder problems was 17.12% which peaked between the ages of 50 and 59. The most frequent diagnosis categories were &#147;non-specific&#148; and &#147;subacromial syndrome&#148;, while the least represented was &#147;acromioclavicular syndrome&#148;. DiscussionThe population characteristics (gender distribution and mean age) coincide with those presented in other studies done in a health care setting. Distribution per age group follows a similar pattern to that detected in a health care setting. The prevalence figures tend to show high variability due to the methodological differences found among the different studies. It can be concluded that musculoskeletal shoulder disorders affect one fifth of the study population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora-Amérigo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Such-Sanz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frau-Escales, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Langa-Revert, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Querol-Fuentes, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Los problemas músculo-esqueléticos que afectan al hombro representan una significativa causa de morbilidad en la población que pueden provocar alteraciones funcionales, tanto a nivel laboral como doméstico. El objetivo principal del presente estudio es calcular la prevalencia de trastornos músculo-esqueléticos del hombro en un entorno sanitario. Material y método Se plantea un estudio transversal de cálculo de prevalencia de afectación del hombro en un entorno de atención primaria. Para recoger la información se han utilizado el documento interconsulta y los registros estadísticos de una Unidad Básica de Rehabilitación referentes a los años 2009 y 2010.ResultadosLa población total atendida en el centro de salud durante el periodo de estudio fue de 1.565 pacientes. El total de casos incluidos en el estudio fuer de 268. La prevalencia de problemas de hombro se sitúa en el 17,12%, con un pico de afectación entre los 50 y 59 años. Las categorías diagnósticas más frecuentes fueron «inespecífico» y «síndrome subacromial» y la menos representada fue «síndrome acromioclavicular». Discusión Las características de la población coinciden con las presentadas en otros estudios realizados en un entorno de sanidad pública, en cuanto a distribución por sexos y edad media. La distribución por grupos de edad sigue un patrón similar al detectado en un entorno sanitario de atención primaria. Las cifras de prevalencia tienden a presentar una gran variabilidad debido a diferencias metodológicas entre los distintos estudios. Se puede concluir que los trastornos músculo-esqueléticos del hombro afectan a una quinta parte de la población estudiada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(1): 10-17, Ene. -Feb. 2013. ilus, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108915</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos músculo-esqueléticos del hombro en atención primaria. Estudio de prevalencia en un centro de la Agencia Valenciana de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
