<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84756</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schizotypy and pathological personality profile in siblings of patients with psychosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Schizotypy has been proposed to be the expression of the genetic vulnerability to schizophrenia. Schizotypal features have been associated with personality dimensions found in patients with psychosis. In this study, we compared the Dimensional Assessment of Personality Pathology - Basic Questionnaire (DAPP-BQ) scores of patients with psychosis, siblings scoring higher on schizotypy (SSHS), and siblings scoring lower (SSLS). The SSHSs displayed a DAPP-BQ profile characterized by high scores in the dimensions of affective lability, anxiousness, submissiveness, social avoidance, identity problems, oppositionality, narcissism, and restricted expression, distinguishing them from the SSLS. Due to these dimensions, SSHSs are more similar to the patients&#146; DAPP-BQ profile. The results suggest that this pathological personality profile might contribute to increase the risk of developing psychosis in siblings who have more schizotypal features (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Zotes, José Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labad Alquézar, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaviria Gómez, Ana Milena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Oyarzábal, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Samaniego, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esquizotipia y perfil de personalidad patológica en hermanos de pacientes psicóticos. La esquizotipia ha sido propuesta como la expresión de la vulnerabilidad genética para la esquizofrenia. Las características esquizotípicas han sido asociadas con las dimensiones de personalidad encontradas en pacientes con psicosis. En este estudio comparamos las puntuaciones del Dimensional Assessment of Personality Pathology - Basic Questionnaire (DAPP-BQ) de pacientes con psicosis, hermanos con puntuaciones altas en esquizotipia (SSHS) y hermanos con puntuaciones bajas (SSLS). Los SSHS mostraron un perfil del DAPP-BQ caracterizado por puntuaciones elevadas en las dimensiones de labilidad afectiva, ansiedad, sumisión, evitación social, problemas de identidad, oposición, narcisismo y expresión restringida, distinguiéndolos de los SSLS. Estas dimensiones hacen a los SSHS más parecidos al perfil del DAPP-BQ de los pacientes. Los resultados sugieren que este perfil de personalidad patológica podría contribuir a incrementar riesgo de desarrollar psicosis en los hermanos que tienen más características esquizotípicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(1): 80-86, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esquizotipia y perfil de personalidad patológica en hermanos de pacientes psicóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
