<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88199</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complexity of emergency care in XXI century Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, the authors explore the factorsthat, in their opinion, currently explain the complexityof emergency care in Spain. Since the start of theXXI century, and in spite of the fact that accident andemergency medicine in the world is undergoing considerablescientific-technical progress, accident andemergency care in Spain is immersed in a care maelstromacting on a terrain that is ill-prepared for the successiveemergent technological advances to take rootand develop. This problem is due to the persistenceof numerous obstacles preventing progress, with thelack of specialisation and the corporative spirit of themanagement boards of some scientific societies playinga principal and direct role in this. Due to all ofthis, advances are frequently achieved more throughinertia, or through the overflow of information fromother disciplines, than due to the initiative of the professionalsof emergency medicine in Spain. Similarly,there is a growing tendency amongst these professionalsto move to other disciplines or fields of care thatoffer better working conditions or simply better professionalexpectations(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Murillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Pérez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los autores desarrollan en este artículo los factoresque a su juicio explican actualmente la complejidadde la asistencia urgente y emergente en España. Desdeel inicio del siglo XXI, y a pesar de que la medicina deurgencias y emergencias en el mundo está viviendo unconsiderable progreso científico-técnico, la asistenciaurgente en España está inmersa en una vorágine asistencialque actúa sobre un terreno poco abonado paraque arraiguen y se desarrollen los avances tecnológicosque sucesivamente van emergiendo. Este problemaes debido a la persistencia de múltiples obstáculosque impiden el progreso incidiendo, principalmentey de manera directa, la ausencia de especialidad y elcorporativismo de las juntas directivas de algunas sociedadescientíficas. Por todo ello, los avances sonpropiciados frecuentemente más por la propia inerciao por el rebosamiento de información desde otras disciplinas,que por el propio empuje de los profesionalesde la medicina de urgencias y emergencias en España.Asimismo, estos profesionales presentan una progresivaincidencia de transfuguismo hacia otras disciplinaso ámbitos de la asistencia que ofrecen mejores condicioneslaborales o simplemente mayores expectativasprofesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(supl.1): 7-11, ene.-abr. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88199</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complejidad de la asistencia urgente en la España del siglo XXI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6931^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
