<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038005</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The skin as an expression of neurological alterations in the neonate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The skin is involved in many different genetic syndromes    and diseases with multiple organ involvement.    Neurodevelopmental disorders appear in many of these    entities and knowledge of these cutaneus alterations may    provide clues to their diagnosis. Recognizing these skin    disorders in the newborn allows early identification of    neonates with a biological risk of epilepsy and motor    and/or cognitive disorders and enables them to be followed    up. This helps to plan the management of these patients    and, in many entities, to predict their natural history    and provide genetic counseling to the family. This    review examines the cutaneus signs that may provide important    clues in the neonate that help to identify entities    that carry a risk of neurodevelopmental disorders in the    neonate</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quero Jiménez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alix Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas Laguna, R. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alteración de la piel forma parte de diferentes síndromes    genéticos y de enfermedades con afectación multiorgánica.    Muchas de estas entidades cursan con alteración    del neurodesarrollo y la piel constituye una importante    pista para el diagnóstico de estas entidades nosológicas.    El reconocimiento en el recién nacido de los trastornos cutáneos    asociados a alteraciones del SNC permite: a) identificar    precozmente una población de recién nacidos con    riesgo biológico de epilepsia y de trastorno motor y/o cognitivo;    b) incluir a estos recién nacidos en programas de    seguimiento, formular planes de tratamiento y/o intervenciones    terapéuticas, y c) en muchas entidades predecir la    historia natural del trastorno y aportar consejo genético a    la familia. Esta revisión examina los signos cutáneos que    pueden aportar importantes pistas en el recién nacido    para el reconocimiento de entidades con riesgo de trastorno    del desarrollo neuroevolutivo en el neonato</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);62(6): 548-563, jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La piel como expresión de alteraciones neurológicas en el recién nacido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
