<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143888</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship of nutritional status, body and mandibular bone mineral density, tooth loss and fracture risk (FRAX) in pre-and postmenopausal women with periodontitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: During menopause there is weight gain and a decrease in bone mineral density (BMD) that has been related with periodontal disease (incidence between 5-30%); therefore, it is essential to assess the risk factors related with anthropometry and BMD. Objective: To assess the relationship between body mass index (BMI), skeletal composition, waist circumference, tooth loss, fracture risk, BMD of the spine, hip, femur, and mandible in pre and post-menopausal women with periodontitis. Subjects and methodology: We studied 60 women aged 35-60 years, divided in 4 groups (n = 15): Control group: premenopausal women without periodontitis; Experimental group 1: premenopausal women with periodontitis; Experimental group 2: postmenopausal women without periodontitis; and Experimental group 3: postmenopausal women with periodontitis. Periodontitis was diagnosed by means of a computerized digital periodontal probe; BMD of the mandible by means of digital radiograph with X ray conversion, the number of teeth by digital panoramic radiograph. We measured: BMI, skeletal composition, waist circumference, risk fracture by the FRAX questionnaire. Results: The variables with a negative correlation with periodontitis were: weight, BMI, and BMD of the mandible with risk fracture (p &lt; 0.05). The group that showed differences (ANOVA) was EG3: with older age, lower height, lower BMD of the mandible, and lower number of teeth (P &lt; 0.05). Conclusion: Periodontitis in the presence of menopause is related with older age, lower height, low BMD of the mandible, and lower mayor number of teeth. Higher fracture risk is associated with low weight and BMI and low BMD of the mandible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivarez-Padrón, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Méndez, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Mendoza, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávalos-Vázquez, Karla Fabiola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-García, Mario Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera-Barreiro, M de los Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Durante la menopausia existe aumento de peso y disminución de densidad mineral ósea (DMO) el cual se ha relacionado con enfermedad periodontal (incidencia entre 5 a 30%), de ahí que sea indispensable evaluar factores de riesgo relacionados con antropometría y DMO. Objetivo: Evaluar la relación entre el índice de masa corporal (IMC), complexión esquelética, circunferencia de cintura, pérdida dentaria, riesgo de fractura, DMO de columna, cadera, fémur y mandíbula en mujeres pre y postmenopáusicas con periodontitis. Sujetos y metodología: Se estudiaron 60 mujeres de 35-60 años, se estudiaron 4 grupos (n = 15): Grupo control: mujeres premenopáuscas sin periodontitis, Grupo experimental 1: mujeres premenopáusicas con periodontitis, Grupo experimental 2: mujeres postmenopáusicas sin periodontitis y Grupo experimental 3: mujeres postmenopáusicas con periodontitis. La periodontitis fue diagnosticada con sonda periodontal digital computarizada, la DMO de mandíbula por radiografía digital con conversión de rayos X, el nú- mero de dientes por radiografía panorámica digital. Se obtuvo: el IMC, la complexión esquelética, circunferencia de cintura, riesgo de fractura mediante el cuestionario FRAX. Resultados: Las variables con correlaciones negativas a periodontitis: peso, IMC y DMO mandibular con riesgo de fractura (P &lt; 0,05). El grupo con diferencias (ANOVA) fue el GE3: con mayor edad y con menor: talla, DMO mandibular y número de piezas dentarias (P &lt; 0,05). Conclusión: La periodontitis con presencia de menopausia se relaciona con mayor edad, menor talla, DMO mandibular baja y menor número de piezas dentarias. Con mayor riesgo de fractura en mujeres: con bajo peso e IMC y DMO mandibular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(6): 1419-1426, jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación del estado nutricio, densidad mineral ósea tanto corporal como mandibular, pérdida dentaria y riesgo de fractura (FRAX), en mujeres pre y postmenopáusicas con periodontitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29135^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54019^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
