<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141335</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequently used vegetable oils in south America: features and properties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent decades, the consumption of vegetable oils has increased in our society, being an important part of the diet worldwide. South America is a major producer of an important variety of vegetable oils. The composition of vegetable oils is not standard as it varies greatly in the amount of saturated, monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fatty acids, and particularly in the amounts of omega-6 and omega-3, which are associated with the source either plant species, seed, plant or fruit, providing different nutritional benefits. The purpose of this article is to review and update the data and evidence about the consumption of oils produced and commercialized in South America, such as soybean oil, corn, palm, sunflower, canola and olive oils, and also to determine health effects from studies related with the topic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres García, Jairo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanhueza Catalán, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de aceites vegetales se ha incrementado en las últimas décadas en nuestra sociedad y son parte importante de la dieta en todo el mundo. Sudamérica es un gran productor de diferentes aceites vegetales. La composición de los aceites vegetales no es estándar, ya que varía considerablemente en el aporte de ácidos grasos saturados, monoinsaturados y poliinsaturados, y particularmente en el aporte de ácidos grasos omega-6 y omega-3, asociado a la fuente de origen, ya sea especie vegetal, semilla, planta o fruto, aportando cada uno diferentes beneficios nutricionales. El propósito de este artículo es revisar y actualizar la evidencia sobre el consumo de aceites producidos y comercializados en Sudamérica, como el aceite de soja, maíz, palma, girasol, canola y oliva, así como los efectos en la salud, a partir de estudios relacionados con el tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(1): 11-19, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceites vegetales de uso frecuente en Sudamérica: características y propiedades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19295^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5331^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
