<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91700</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social impact of the visits to the Pediatric Emergency Department due to fever</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients and methods. Prospective descriptive study among all patients between 2 months and 18 years old that visited our pediatric emergency department complaining about fever. We contacted by telephone 7-10 days after being discharged and made a questionnaire about the repercussion in the feeding, rest, level of activity and attendance at school. We asked about employee absenteeism of the parents, the need of other caretakers, and also unscheduled revisits to the Pediatrician. Results. There were 641 visits complaining about fever, and 328 (51%) of them attended our survey. There were problems in the feeding (60.1%), rest (45.4%) and level of activity (53%) as well as school absenteeism (49.7%), labor (28.3%) and necessity of other caretakers (41.8%). There were unscheduled revisits in 147 patients (44.8%), 69.4% with its habitual Pediatrician, 19% in a Pediatric Emergency department and 11,6% in both. Conclusions. Fever determines an alteration in the quality of life of children and familiar dynamics and produces an important number of revisits. In the Pediatric Emergency services we should include information to advice families about that impact (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rovira Amigo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmiento Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del trabajo es conocer el impacto social de la fiebre, es decir, la repercusión que produce a corto plazo en el niño y el entorno familiar. Pacientes y métodos.  Estudio descriptivo prospectivo de las consultas por fiebre de pacientes entre 2 meses y 18 años a los que, en el plazo de 7-19 días, se les realizó un cuestionario vía telefónica sobre la repercusión en la alimentación, descanso, nivel de actividad, asistencia al centro escolar, absentismo laboral de los padres, necesidad de otros cuidadores y necesidad de reconsultas no programadas. Resultados. De un total de 641 consultas por fiebre, 328 (51%) atendieron a la encuesta telefónica. Se encontraron problemas en la alimentación (60,1%), descanso (45,4%) y nivel de actividad (53%) así como absentismo escolar (49,7%), laboral (28,3%) y necesidad de otros cuidadores (41,8%). Reconsultaron 147 pacientes 844,8%), 69,4% con su Pediatra habitual, 19% en Urgencias de Pediatría y 11,6% en ambos. Conclusiones. La fiebre determina una alteración de la calidad de vida del niño y de la dinámica familiar y origina un importante número de reconsultas. En el manejo de niño febril en urgencias deberíamos incluir la información adecuada a las familias sobre el impacto social de la fiebre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;66(2): 96-100, mar.-abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91700</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto social de las consultas pro fiebre en Urgencias de Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
