<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153176</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of two days treatment with orlistat on plasma leptin in obese patients without weight loss</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Little is known about the impact of orlistat on the leptin system. We studied the plasma leptin and satiety sensation response for two days of orlistat treatment without hypocaloric diet and weight loss. Material and methods: Twenty obese female subjects were recruited from our medical outpatient clinics. All of these subjects had previously received advice on dietary restriction and lifestyle modification, but remained obese with a stable body weight for at least six months before recruitment for the study. Results: Subjects were given 120 mg orlistat 3 times daily and were asked to maintain their usual diet. At baseline and two days after the treatment with orlistat, physical examination, hunger and blood analysis were repeated. There were no significant differences observed regarding energy dietary intake, body weight and waist-hip ratio, or in plasma glucose, insulin c-peptide concentrations. Only plasma leptin and triglycerides concentrations decreased (p: 0.0001 and 0.01 respectively). Decrease in plasma leptin concentration was positively correlated with changes observed in plasma triglycerides concentration (p: 0.01, r2: 0.45). Pre-dinner hunger increased and was negatively correlated with decrease in leptin (p: 0.0001, r2: 0.74) and triglycerides (p: 0.02, r2: 0.59). Conclusion: These data suggest that the partial fat malabsorption induced by the treatment with orlistat quickly reduces plasma triglycerides and leptin. This decrease is associated with increased appetite before intake following the main meal of the day (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boj-Carceller, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Valle, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Ferrando, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Paris, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escanero-Marcén, Jesús Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: poco se conoce sobre el impacto de orlistat en el sistema leptina. Estudiamos la respuesta de la leptina plasmática y la sensación de saciedad tras dos días de tratamiento con orlistat sin dieta hipocalórica ni pérdida de peso. Material y métodos: reclutamos veinte mujeres obesas en nuestras consultas externas de medicina. Habían recibido restricción dietética y modificación del estilo de vida, pero se habían mantenido obesas con peso corporal estable durante seis meses antes de su inclusión en el estudio. Resultados: las pacientes tomaron 120 mg de orlistat 3 veces al día y mantuvieron su dieta habitual. Al inicio y dos días después del tratamiento con orlistat se repitieron el examen físico, la sensación de hambre y la analítica. No hubo diferencias significativas en el consumo de energía de la dieta, el peso corporal y la relación cintura-cadera, así como en glucosa sérica, insulina y péptido C. Solamente las concentraciones de leptina y triglicéridos en suero disminuyeron (p: 0,0001 y 0,01, respectivamente). La disminución de la concentración de leptina en suero se correlacionó positivamente con cambios en la concentración de triglicéridos (p: 0.01, r2: 0,45). La sensación de hambre aumento antes de la cena y se correlacionó negativamente con la disminución de la leptina (p: 0,0001, r2: 0,74) y triglicéridos (p: 0,02, r2: 0.59). Conclusión: estos datos sugieren que la malabsorción parcial de grasas por el tratamiento con orlistat disminuye rápidamente los niveles plasmáticos de triglicéridos y leptina. Este descenso se asoció con aumento del apetito antes de la ingesta que sigue a la comida principal del día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(2): 292-297, mar.-abr. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del tratamiento de dos días con orlistat sobre los niveles de leptina plasmática en pacientes obesas sin pérdida de peso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1072^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12910^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33085^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
