<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94865</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The current state of the art concerning quality of life in parkinson´s disease: II determining and associated factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Health-related quality of life (HRQL) in Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is an area that is receiving a growing amount of interest as the new biopsychosocial model of medicine is adopted. Aim. This paper is the second part of a review of the current state of the art concerning HRQL in PD and focuses on its main determining and associated factors. Development. A total of 56 studies are reviewed and the determining factors are grouped according to different variables,  which may be disease-related (including motor and non-motor symptoms), sociodemographic (level of schooling, economic factors, gender and others), psychological and related to mental status (depression, anxiety, cognitive impairment, physicianpatient relationship and others), and disability. The following characteristics of the studies were taken into account: the type of design (longitudinal or cross-sectional), the instrument used for measuring the HRQL (generic or specific), the statistical  method employed (univariate or multivariate) and the sample size. Conclusions. Most of the studies are cross-sectional and the majority use the 39-item Parkinson&#146;s Disease Questionnaire as a measure of HRQL with multivariate data analysis. The three most important factors determining HRQL in PD are depression, the stage of the disease and the time elapsed since onset of the disease. Nevertheless, the preferred methodology does not allow for causal inferences, due to the scarcity of  longitudinal studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Forjaz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frandes Payo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en la enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) es un tema al que se dedica un interés creciente, a medida que se adopta el nuevo modelo biopsicosocial de la medicina. Objetivo. Este artículo es la segunda parte de una revisión sobre el estado actual del conocimiento sobre la CVRS en la EP, que se centra en sus principales determinantes y factores asociados. Desarrollo. Se revisan 56 estudios y se agrupan los determinantes en variables relativas a la enfermedad (incluyendo síntomas motores y no motores), sociodemográficas (nivel de educación, factores económicos, género y otras), psicológicas y de estado mental (depresión, ansiedad, deterioro cognitivo, relación médicopaciente y otras), y de discapacidad. Se tomaron en cuenta las siguientes características de los estudios: el tipo de diseño  (longitudinal o transversal), el instrumento para medir la CVRS (genérico o específico), el método estadístico (univariante o multivariante) y el tamaño muestral. Conclusiones. La mayoría de los estudios son transversales y utilizan mayoritariamente el Parkinson&#146;s Disease Questionnaire, versión de 39 ítems, como medida de CVRS con un análisis de datos multivariante. Los tres determinantes de la CVSR en la EP más importantes son la depresión, el estadio de la enfermedad y la duración de enfermedad.  Sin embargo, la metodología preferentemente utilizada no permite inferencias causales, debido a la escasez de estudios longitudinales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(12): 655-660, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual del conocimiento sobre calidad de vida en la enfermedad de Parkinson: II. Determinantes y factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
