<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110010</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Establishment of a Stable Urethral Stricture Model in New Zealand Rabbits</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To explore the method of building a stable urethral stricture (US) model in New Zealand white rabbits. Methods: Through 10X magnification optical microscope, a resection of 1.0cm urethral mucosa was made in 6 male rabbits and other 6 male rabbits were controlled. After 60 days, the rabbits were evaluated with urethrography, urethral pressure profile (UPP) and histology. Result: Urethrography demonstrated a stricture with narrow lumen and discontinuous mucosa in the resection group. The urethras of the control animals were all normal. UPP showed that the urethral pressure on operative site in the controlled group was 14.67±2.16cmH2O, and 27.83±3.71 cmH2O in the resection group. There was significant statistical difference between the two groups (P&lt;0.01). The urothelium was well-distributed, covered without any inflammatory cells in the controlled group, which had 3-4 layers of the epithelial cells. And the urothelium was unequally covered with neutrophils and lymphocytes in the resection group. Conclusions: We establish the way to build a stable urethral stricture model of New Zealand rabbits by the microsurgical technique, which is a good laboratory model to research all kinds of urethral stricture. Urethrography and histology combined UPP are the reliable methods to identify the urethral stricture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fang, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zhao, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sun, Ch</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sun, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ding, Q</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feng, Ch</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zheng, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Li, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar el método de construir un modelo de estenosis uretral estable en conejos blancos de Nueva Zelanda. Métodos: A través de un microscopio óptico de 10 aumentos se realizó una resección de 1cm en la mucosa uretral de 6 conejos machos y se controló a otros 6 conejos hembras. Después de 60 días se evaluó a los conejos a través de uretrografía, perfil de presión uretral (PPU) e histología. Resultado: La uretrografía mostró una estenosis con lumen estrecho y mucosa discontinua en el grupo de resección. Las uretras de los animales de control eran normales. El PPU mostró que la presión uretral en el sitio de la operación en el grupo de control fue de 14,67±2,16 cmH2O y 27,83±3,71 cmH2O en el grupo de resección. Hubo una diferencia estadísticamente significativa entre los 2 grupos (p&lt;0,01). El urotelio estaba bien distribuido, cubierto sin células inflamatorias en el grupo de control, con 3-4 capas de células epiteliales. Además, el urotelio se cubrió con neutrófilos y linfocitos de manera desigual en el grupo de resección. Conclusiones: Establecemos la forma de construir un modelo de estenosis uretral estable en conejos de Nueva Zelanda a través de la técnica microquirúrgica, que puede suponer un buen modelo de laboratorio para investigar todo tipo de estenosis uretrales. La uretrografía y el PPU combinado con la histología son los métodos de confianza para identificar la estenosis uretral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(3): 162-166, mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Establecimiento de un modelo estable de estenosis uretral en conejos de Nueva Zelanda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
