<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84713</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review and future perspectives on recommended calcium intake</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The suitability of recommended calcium intakes has been the subject of debate in recent years. The present work reviews the recommendations currently made for different population groups in Spain and other countries. To date, these recommended intakes have mainly been based on the role of calcium in the formation and maintenance of bone; less attention has been paid to its other roles in health (e. g., its effect on blood pressure, the prevention of cancer or the regulation of body weight), or the interaction of calcium with other nutrients. However, an increasing number of reports highlight the importance of calcium in these other areas - information that should be taken into account when assessing the suitability of recommended calcium intakes. It should also be remembered that the calcium intakes of a large proportion of the population are lower than those recommended. This paper reviews the suitability of current calcium recommendations for different groups of the population and highlights the areas where research is needed to help determine the intakes that would provide the greatest short and long term health benefits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Anta, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navia Lombán, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Sobaler, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La adecuación de las ingestas recomendadas para el calcio ha sido objeto de debate en los últimos años, por ello en la presente revisión se hace un resumen de las recomendaciones, nacionales e internacionales, que existen actualmente sobre la ingesta de calcio en diferentes grupos de población. Para marcar dichas ingestas hasta el momento se ha tenido en cuenta, fundamentalmente, el papel del calcio en la formación y mantenimiento de la masa ósea, prestando menos atención a su interacción con otros nutrientes y a otras funciones de este mineral en la salud, como su efecto sobre la tensión arterial, prevención del cáncer o regulación del peso corporal. Sin embargo, cada vez hay más estudios que ponen de manifiesto la implicación del calcio en dichos aspectos, por lo que deben tenerse en cuenta a la hora de evaluar la adecuación de las actuales ingestas recomendadas, sobre todo teniendo en cuenta que una gran parte de la población no llega a cubrir dichas recomendaciones. Se señalan aspectos en los que es necesario investigar en el futuro para ir perfilando los aportes del mineral que pueden condicionar mayores beneficios sanitarios a corto y largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(3): 366-374, mayo-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión y futuras perspectivas sobre las ingestas recomendadas de calcio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32109</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23096^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
