<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115689</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mucosecretor adenocarcinoma of the lung with pleural involvement presenting as a pneumothorax. Presentation of a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The combination of a pneumothorax and lung cancer is rare and diagnosis is complex. Clinical suspicion of cancer must be based on radiological findings and the existence of risk factors. We discuss the mechanisms involved in the development of pneumothorax in patients with lung cancer, as well as the clinical significance, the recommended diagnostic approach, and therapeutic guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobenes Gutierrez, R. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Guerra, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Hernandez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida Pérez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La asociación de un neumotórax y un carcinoma broncopulmonar es infrecuente y el diagnóstico es complicado. La sospecha clínica debe hacerse a partir de los hallazgos radiográficos y la existencia de factores de riesgo. Son discutidos los mecanismos implicados en la aparición del neumotórax en pacientes con neoplasias de pulmón, así como el significado clínico y la conducta diagnóstica y terapéutica recomendada en estos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(7): 391-395, oct. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenocarcinoma mucosecretor de pulmón con diseminación pleural que se manifiesta con neumotórax. Presentación de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31802^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31802^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31802^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
