<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85746</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric Study of NASA-TLX Mental Workload Index in a Sample of Spanish Workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to assess the psychometric properties of NASA-Task Load Index using several groups of Spanish workers. The sample consisted of 398 workers who belonged to seven different jobs. All workers assessed the perceived mental workload when perform their jobs, due to each of the six dimensions of mental workload that distinguishes the NASA-TLX: effort, mental demand, physical demand, temporal demand, performance and frustration. The results showed that NASA-Task Load Index had a acceptable internal consistency and a factorial structure formed by two components. The first of the two components was formed by all of the NASA-TLX dimensions except frustration. The second was formed only by frustration dimension. Significant differences in the profiles of mental workload experienced by workers on the basis of their jobs were found for all NASA-TLX dimensions except in performance(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Valdehita, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Ramiro, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luceño Moreno, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar las propiedades psicométricas del instrumento de evaluación de la carga mental de trabajo NASA-TLX en distintos grupos profesionales españoles. La muestra estuvo formada por 398 trabajadores que pertenecían a siete sectores profesionales diferentes. Todos los trabajadores evaluaron la carga mental percibida en sus puestos de trabajo, debida a cada una de las seis dimensiones de carga que distingue el NASA-TLX: esfuerzo, demanda mental, demanda física, demanda temporal, rendimiento y frustración. Los resultados mostraron una consistencia interna aceptable y una estructura factorial constituida por dos factores. Uno de los factores estaba formado únicamente por la dimensión &#147;frustración&#148;, mientras que el otro factor englobaba a las cinco dimensiones restantes. Por último, se encontraron diferencias importantes en los perfiles de carga mental entre los grupos profesionales considerados, en todas las dimensiones de carga, excepto en rendimiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);26(3): 191-199, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85746</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio Psicométrico del Índice de Carga Mental NASA-TLX con una Muestra de Trabajadores Españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5326^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31990^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31990^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4726^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
