<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135395</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic kidney disease in Primary Health Care: Prevalence and associated risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of chronic kidney disease and associated risk factors in subjects over 60 years of age, as well as its staging by determining the glomerular filtration rate (GFR). Design: Cross-sectional observational study. Setting: Primary Health Care. Participants: Patients &amp;#8805; 60 years of age who were seen in 40 Primary Health Care centres with serum creatinine measured in a central laboratory between January 1 and December 31, 2010. Exclusion criteria: kidney transplant, home care. Main measures: Social-demographic and anthropometric data, cardiovascular risk factors, and diseases established according to electronic clinical records. Serum creatinine was measured using standardised Jaffe kinetic method, and GFR estimated with MDRD-4-IDMS and CKD-EPI. Results: A total of 97,665 subjects (57.3% women, median age 70.0 years [Q1: 65.0, Q3: 77.0]). GFR-MDRD prevalence &lt; 60 = 15.1% (16.6% in women, 13.2% in men; P &lt; .001) and increased with age. Multivariate analysis showed a positive association between GFR-MDRD &lt; 60 and age (OR = 1.74; 95% CI 1.70 to 1.77), hypertension (OR = 2.18; 95% CI 2.08 to 2.30), heart failure (OR = 2.03; 95% CI 1.83 to 2.25), atrial fibrillation (OR = 1.57; 95% CI 1.41 to 1.76), ischaemic heart disease (OR = 1.40; 95% CI 1.30 to 1.50), peripheral arterial disease (OR = 1.31; 95% CI 1.09 to 1.57), dyslipidaemia (OR = 1.28; 95% CI 1.23 to 1.33), diabetes (OR = 1.26; 95% CI 1.17 to 1.34), and stroke (OR = 1.17; 95% CI 1.09 to 1.25). The GFR-CKD-EPI model showed an increase in OR with age and male sex, that became significant as a chronic kidney disease risk factor. Conclusions: Chronic kidney disease has considerable prevalence in subjects &amp;#8805; 60 years seen in Primary Health Care, more in women, and increasing with age. Hypertension, more than diabetes, was the main associated cardiovascular risk factor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Latre, Luisa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré González, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador González, Betlem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cunillera Puertolas, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruipérez Guijarro, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pascual, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la prevalencia y los estadios de la enfermedad renal crónica según la estimación del filtrado glomerular (eFG), y los factores de riesgo asociados en individuos &amp;#8805; 60 años. Diseño: Estudio observacional transversal. Emplazamiento: Atención Primaria. Participantes: Sujetos &amp;#8805; 60 años de 40 centros de Atención Primaria con determinación de creatinina sérica entre 1 enero-31 diciembre de 2010. Criterios de exclusión: trasplante renal, atención domiciliaria. Mediciones principales: Variables sociodemográficas, antropométricas, factores de riesgo y enfermedad cardiovascular según registro en historia clínica electrónica, concentración de creatinina sérica según método Jaffé cinético compensado estandarizado y eFG según MDRD-4 IDMS y CKD-EPI. Resultados: Fueron analizados 97.665 individuos (57,3% mujeres, mediana de edad 70,0 [Q1: 65,0; Q3: 77,0]). Prevalencia de eFG-MDRD &lt; 60 = 15,1% (16,6% en mujeres, 13,2% en hombres; p &lt; 0,001) con aumento progresivo con la edad. El análisis multivariante detectó una asociación positiva entre eFG-MDRD &lt; 60 y edad (OR = 1,74; IC 95% 1,70-1,77), HTA (OR = 2,18; IC 95% 2,08-2,30), insuficiencia cardiaca (OR = 2,03; IC 95% 1,83-2,25), fibrilación auricular (OR = 1,57; IC 95% 1,41-1,76), cardiopatía isquémica (OR = 1,40; IC 95% 1,30-1,50), arteriopatía periférica (OR = 1,31; IC 95% 1,09-1,57), dislipidemia (OR = 1,28; IC 95% 1,23-1,33), DM (OR = 1,26; IC 95% 1,17-1,34) y AVC (OR = 1,17; IC 95% 1,09-1,25). El modelo con eFG-CKD-EPI mostró un aumento de la OR con la edad y sexo masculino, que cobró significación como factor de riesgo. Conclusiones: La enfermedad renal crónica presenta una importante prevalencia en pacientes &amp;#8805; 60 años atendidos en Atención Primaria, mayor en mujeres que en hombres, y aumentando con la edad. La HTA, más que la DM, fue el principal factor de riesgo cardiovascular asociado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(4): 236-245, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad renal crónica en Atención Primaria: prevalencia y factores de riesgo asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
