<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119478</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical significance of suicidal behaviour in delusional disorder: A 44 case-series descriptive study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Suicidal behaviour in delusional disorder (DD) has been poorly studied. This study aimed to describe the prevalence of clinically significant depression, suicidal ideation and behaviour in these patients, and to relate them with psychotic or depressive symptoms. Patients and method: A cross-sectional study including 44 outpatients with DD (DSM-IV-TR) was conducted. Demographic and clinical data, as well as scores in clinical assessment scales: Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS), Personal and Social Performance Scale, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (17-item version) and Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale, were recorded. The sample was divided into 2 groups according to presence or absence of comorbid depression (CD). Results: Fifteen patients (34.1%) had CD, 14 (31.8%) suicidal ideation and 7 (15.9%) suicidal behaviour in the previous 2 years. Patients with CD had an earlier age at onset and for a first psychiatric appointment, and had higher scores on the PANSS general subscale (p = 0,043) and in intensity of suicidal ideation (p = 0,001). Conclusions: In our sample, patients with DD and CD have more frequently suicidal ideation and behaviour than those without CD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gónzalez Rodríguez, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo Arroyo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penadés Rubio, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán Campos, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Andreu, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La conducta suicida en el trastorno delirante (TD) ha sido escasamente estudiada. El objetivo del estudio fue describir la prevalencia de depresión clínicamente significativa, ideación y conducta suicida en TD, y relacionar el suicidio con síntomas psicóticos y/o depresivos. Pacientes y método: Se realizó un estudio transversal que incluyó 44 pacientes ambulatorios con TD (DSM- IV -TR). Se registraron datos sociodemográficos, clínicos y puntuaciones en las escalas clínicas: Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS), Personal and Social Performance Scale, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (17-item version) y Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale. Se dividió la muestra según la presencia o ausencia de comorbilidad depresiva (CD). Resultados: Quince pacientes (34,1%) presentaron CD, 14 (31,8%) ideación suicida y 7 (15,9%) conducta suicida en los 2 años previos. Los pacientes con CD presentaron una edad de inicio más precoz, se vincularon antes a la red de salud mental y presentaron puntuaciones más altas en la subescala general de la PANSS (p = 0,043) y en intensidad de la ideación suicida (p = 0,001). Conclusiones: En nuestra muestra, los pacientes con TD y CD presentan con más frecuencia ideación y conducta suicida, respecto a los que no presentan CD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(7): 299-302, abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la conducta suicida en el trastorno delirante: descripción de una serie de 44 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
