<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79576</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disciplined nursing, pastoral power and medicalizated rationality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A foucalist view at the silence of the war that nursing lives, where the medicalized rationality lef's articulate the pastoral power and the social control anxiated by the stated. The nursing docility, it's power in frot of individuals and collectivities, as well as the weight it ostents in the hegemonic sanitary systems. Draws an utility centralized in the construction of the heteronomous subjectivity in the peoples and collectivities health, distancing the discipline from its own fundamental ethical principles an from its final ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irigibel-Uriz, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Mirada Foucaultiana al silencio de la guerra que vive enfermería, en donde la racionalidad medicalizadora permite articular el poder pastoral y el control social ansiados por los Estados. La docilidad enfermera, su poder ante los individuos y colectividades, así como el peso que ostenta en los sistemas sanitarios hegemónicos, dibuja una utilidad centrada en la construcción de la subjetividad heterónoma en salud de las personas y colectividades, distanciando a la disciplina de sus principios éticos fundamentales y de su fin ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;17(4): 11-11, oct.-dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermería disciplinada, poder pastoral y racionalidad medicalizadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13308</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
