<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117266</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of protein-energy wasting syndrome and its association with mortality in haemodialysis patients in a centre in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Malnutrition has been described in patients with chronic kidney disease as well as its association with cardiovascular risk and mortality in haemodialysis patients. Recently, the new term 'protein energy wasting' has been proposed with new diagnostic criteria (biochemical and anthropometric markers) for early identification of patients at risk for protein energy wasting and mortality. The aim of this study was to examine the prevalence, evolution over time and prognostic significance of PEW in a Spanish dialysis centre for the first time in Spain. Patients and methods: an observational study that included 122 prevalent haemodialysis patients at our centre. Between January 2010 and October 2012, three visits were carried out in which clinical, biochemical, anthropometric and body composition parameters were collected using BIS (bioelectrical impedance spectroscopy) along with their respective dialytic characteristics, in accordance with the criteria of the new definition. We analysed the prevalence (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mahíllo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Gómez, M. Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egido, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Parra, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-Iguacel, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrero, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La malnutrición ha sido descrita en los pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica, y su asociación con el riesgo cardiovascular y la mortalidad en pacientes en hemodiálisis. Recientemente se ha propuesto una nueva terminología, protein energy wasting, con nuevos criterios diagnósticos (marcadores bioquímicos y antropométricos), para identificar precozmente a los pacientes con riesgo de presentar desgaste proteico-energético (DPE) y riesgo de mortalidad. El objetivo de este estudio fue observar por primera vez en España la prevalencia, la evolución en el tiempo y el significado pronóstico del DPE en un centro de diálisis español. Pacientes y métodos: estudio observacional que incluyó a 122 pacientes prevalentes en hemodiálisis en nuestro centro. Entre enero de 2010 y octubre de 2012 se realizaron tres visitas, en las cuales se recogieron parámetros clínicos, bioquímicos, antropométricos, composición corporal mediante el uso de bioimpedancia espectroscópica y sus características dialíticas respectivas según los criterios de la nueva definición. Se analizó la prevalencia de DPE en cada visita, la progresión de los parámetros de malnutrición y los posibles factores asociados a DPE. Tras un período de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;33(4): 495-505, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del síndrome de desgaste proteico-energético y su asociación con mortalidad en pacientes en hemodiálisis en un centro en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53519^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30409^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
