<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93833</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive variables of training proficiency in the local police</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Police selection includes a period of training in which candidates acquire the relevant skills and knowledge for work. This study was carried out with the Local Police of Zaragoza. It examines the validity of general mental ability, the personality dimensions and theoretical knowledge applied to work, in order to predict training proficiency. A multiple regression correlational analysis and path analysis were carried out using the data of 240 candidates to be police officers. The results show that training proficiency can be predicted by general mental ability, theoretical knowledge applied to the job and three personality dimensions: conscientiousness, openness to experience and agreeableness. A causal model is presented, including the direct and indirect effects the variables have on training proficiency in the case of local police officers(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berges Saldaña, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La selección policial incluye un periodo de entrenamiento en el que los aspirantes adquieren conocimientos y destrezas relevantes para el trabajo. Este trabajo, realizado en la Policía Local de la ciudad de Zaragoza, examina la validez de la habilidad mental general, las dimensiones de personalidad y los conocimientos teóricos aplicados al trabajo, para predecir el aprovechamiento de la formación. Se realizaron análisis correlacionales, de regresión múltiple y path analysis con los datos correspondientes a 240 aspirantes a policía. Los resultados muestran que el aprovechamiento formativo se puede predecir a partir de la habilidad mental general, los conocimientos teóricos aplicados al puesto y tres dimensiones de personalidad, conciencia, apertura a la experiencia y amigabilidad. Se presenta un modelo causal que incluye los efectos directos e indirectos de las variables sobre el aprovechamiento de la formación en el caso de los policías locales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);27(3): 163-176, 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables predictivas del aprovechamiento formativo en la policía local</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29881^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1376^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29881^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3264^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54383</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12029^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
