<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106421</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">"Teaching how to be a doctor": an analysis of the opinions of doctors involved in the teaching of clinical practice (I). Conclusions from the qualitative analysis and methodology for a quantitative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today, the teaching of medicine must focus primarily on the clinical competencies expected of a physician, which enable them to practise their career in an adequate manner. In this regard, the clinical setting is the ideal place to teach-learn such competencies. Yet, the teaching of clinical medicine through the teaching of clinical practice has, as we stand today, its drawbacks, which must be identified, and also its strengths, which need to be fostered. In this work we present the first data from 'Teaching how to be a doctor', a cross-sectional study conducted in the hospital setting in centres associated with the Universidad Complutense in Madrid. We report the qualitative analysis of the opinions of professionals involved in the teaching of clinical practice, which was carried out by means of a structured and pre-coded survey, with both open-ended and semi-open-ended questions. The weaknesses that were detected include: the excessive theoretical component of the teaching, some specific shortcomings in training (interprofessional relationships and communication), scarce promotion of research, the continued presence of the medical resident exam (MIR) as a referent and the rift between teaching and healthcare duties in hospitals. Some of the strengths of the current teaching practice include: students are very well prepared on finishing their training, they have a high level of academic achievement and, significantly, we are beginning to see some innovative changes in the way medicine is taught (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Fuentes, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez-Cortés, Jesús Millán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enseñanza de la medicina en el momento actual debe centrarse de forma primordial en las competencias clínicas propias del médico, que le permitan un ejercicio profesional adecuado. En este sentido, el entorno clínico es el lugar idóneo para la enseñanza-aprendizaje de tales competencias. Sin embargo, la enseñanza de la medicina clínica a través de la enseñanza de clínica práctica tiene, a día de hoy, limitaciones que deben identificarse y que coexisten con fortalezas, las cuales deben fomentarse. En este trabajo se presentan los primeros datos de 'Enseñar a ser médicos', un estudio trasversal realizado en el ámbito hospitalario de los centros asociados a la Universidad Complutense de Madrid. Se presenta el análisis cualitativo de la opinión de los profesionales implicados en la enseñanza de la práctica clínica, mediante una encuesta estructurada y precodificada, con preguntas abiertas y semiabiertas. Entre las debilidades detectadas cabe citar: el excesivo componente teórico de la enseñanza, algunas carencias formativas específicas (relaciones interprofesionales y comunicación), el escaso fomento de la investigación, el mantenimiento del examen de médico interno residente (MIR) como referente y la escisión entre las funciones docentes y asistenciales en el entorno hospitalario. Entre las fortalezas de la enseñanza actual: la elevada preparación del alumno, su elevado rendimiento académico y, de forma significativa, el inicio de cambios innovadores en el enseñanza de la medicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);15(3): 143-147, sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106421</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">"Enseñar a ser médicos": un análisis de opinión de los médicos implicados en la docencia de la clínica práctica (I). Conclusiones del análisis cualitativo y metodología para un estudio cuantitativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
