<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047398</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment and management of intradialysis pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain is a frequent symptom in patients who under go haemodialysis (HD), directly affecting their quality of life. However, its characteristics in this type of patient are not well known and there are no publications prior to this study dedicated exclusively to assessing pain during a haemodialysis session. This study assesses the characteristics of intradialysis pain, including its prevalence, intensity, qualitative characteristics and measures applied to control it. For these purposes, validated valuation scales widely used in the control of oncological pain were used, which were extended with a specific survey that evaluated aspects of pain related to the dialysis itself, including timing, frequency or influence of the treatment parameters. The entire information compilation process took place during the haemodialysis sessions. The prevalence of pain in HD was 92.1%, only in 3 cases (7.89%) was the pain level zero. 28.9% of patients identified the procedure itself as the cause of the pain, the second most frequent cause after pain of ischemic origin. The Pain Management Index (PMI) showed clear under-treatment, which was most marked the more intense the pain described by the patient. However, the measures taken during haemodialysis for the control of the episodes of pain detected were efficient in a reasonable percentage of cases, which indicates that most of the pain episodes are not perceived by us</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Llull, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calero, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Amer, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calls Ginesta, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Navarro, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor es un síntoma frecuente en los pacientes sometidos a hemodiálisis (HD), afectando directamente su calidad de vida. Sin embargo, sus características en este tipo de pacientes son poco conocidas y no existen publicaciones previas a este estudio en las que se valore de forma exclusiva el dolor durante una sesión de hemodiálisis. El presente estudio evalúa las características del dolor intradiálisis, incluyendo su prevalencia, intensidad, características cualitativas y medidas aplicadas para su control. Se utilizan para ello escalas de valoración validadas y ampliamente usadas en el control del dolor oncológico, que fueron ampliadas con una encuesta específica en la que se valoran aspectos del dolor relacionados con la propia diálisis, incluyendo temporalidad, frecuencia o influencia de los parámetros del tratamiento. Todo el proceso de recogida de información se realizó durante las sesiones de hemodiálisis. La prevalencia de dolor en HD fue de un 92,1%, sólo en 3 casos (7,89%) el nivel de dolor fue 0. Un 28,9% de los pacientes identificaron el propio procedimiento como causa del dolor, segunda causa más frecuente tras el dolor de origen isquémico. El Índice de Manejo del Dolor (PMI) indicó un claro infra-tratamiento, tanto más acentuado cuanto más intenso era el dolor descrito por el paciente. Sin embargo, las medidas llevadas a cabo durante la hemodiálisis para el control delos episodios de dolor detectados fueron eficaces en un porcentaje razonable, lo que indica que la mayor parte delos episodios de dolor pasan desapercibidos ante nuestros ojos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;9(2): 65-70, abr.-jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y manejo del dolor intradiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
