<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127444</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The prison of Jerez de los Caballeros (Badajoz) in the 19th century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article considers the situation of prisoners in Spanish jails, taking the circumstances of the inmates at the prison of  Jerez de los Caballeros as a particular example. Documents from the Jerez Municipal Historical Archives were studied along with other contemporary and more current publications. The results show that the conditions of the buildings bordered on the ruinous, the facilities were in poor condition or unavailable and health and hygiene were practically inhumane. Pathologies of the prisoners posed a threat to the general population, as there was the risk of outbreaks of epidemics, but almost nothing is known about them. Efforts by the authorities to remedy structural problems and health problems were few and mostly ineffective due to due to economic difficulties. Medical assistance was provided by local doctors in exchange for a fee (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peral-Pacheco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Guzmán, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo hemos estudiado la coyuntura de los presos en las cárceles españolas en general y de Jerez de los Caballeros en particular. Para ello hemos analizado la documentación del Archivo Histórico Municipal de Jerez, así como publicaciones actuales y de la época. Como resultado hallamos que las condiciones de los edificios rozaban la ruina, los enseres estaban en pésimo estado o simplemente no existían y la situación higiénico-sanitaria rayaba en lo inhumano. Las patologías de los presos podían suponer una amenaza para la población general, al existir el riesgo de extenderse en forma de epidemias, aunque no se sabe casi nada de ellas. Los esfuerzos de las autoridades fueron escasos y poco efectivos, debido a las carencias económicas, para subsanar los problemas estructurales y de salud. La asistencia médica corría a cargo de los facultativos locales a cambio de unos honorarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;16(3): 75-83, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cárcel de Jerez de los Caballeros (Badajoz) durante el siglo XIX</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
