<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111901</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tofacitinib and Other Kinase Inhibitors in the Treatment of Psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Protein kinases play a crucial role in the intracellular signaling pathways involved in inflammation and cell proliferation. Advances in our understanding of these metabolic pathways and of the role played by intracellular signaling in the pathogenesis of psoriasis have led to research in this area and the development of a new class of drugs for the treatment of psoriasis and other inflammatory processes. Since kinase inhibitors are small molecules, oral and topical treatments are possible. The future role of these molecules in the therapeutic arsenal used to treat psoriasis is as yet unknown because in most cases they are still in the early stages of research. The fact that these drugs may cost much less than biologic therapies could favor their approval in coming years. Tofacitinib, a Janus kinase inhibitor, is the drug that has reached the most advanced stage of research and has shown the most promising results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alsina, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Santos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Ibáñez, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las proteínas cinasas desempeñan un papel fundamental en las vías de señalización intracelular implicadas tanto en la proliferación celular como en la inflamación. El mejor conocimiento de estas vías metabólicas, y del mecanismo patogénico de las señales intracelulares de la psoriasis, está provocando el desarrollo e investigación de un nuevo grupo de fármacos en el tratamiento de esta enfermedad y de otros procesos inflamatorios. Los inhibidores de las cinasas son moléculas de pequeño tamaño que van a permitir un tratamiento vía oral o tópico. El futuro papel de estos fármacos dentro del arsenal terapéutico de la psoriasis está todavía por determinar, ya que la mayoría de moléculas están en fases precoces de investigación. Su hipotético coste inferior al de los tratamientos biológicos pudiera favorecer su aprobación en los próximos años. Tofacitinib, un inhibidor de las cinasas Janus, es el fármaco con investigación más avanzada y resultados prometedores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(4): 304-310, mayo 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tofacitinib y otros inhibidores de las cinasas en el tratamiento de la psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52252^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52252^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9124^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38846^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10967^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52252^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10967^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
