<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60017</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High power 980 NM Diode Laser: preliminary results in the treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: A clinical evaluation of the use of a 980 nm diode laser in the treatment of bladder outlet obstruction secondary to benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH), focused on perioperatory morbidity and results in a short-term follow-up.METHODS: Fifteen patients were included in the study. All of them were evaluated by IPSS and Quality of Life (QoL) questionnaires, digital rectal examination, PSA, ul-trasound scan and uroflowmetry. Prostate vaporization was performed with a laser of diode at 980 nm (Inter-medic; Barcelona, Spain) using a 600 microns side-fire fiber. In the follow-up any event was recorded, as well as the IPSS and QoL scores and Qmax.RESULTS: Mean age of the patients was 66.7 years(45-75). The range of prostate volume was 20-76 cc (median 41.3 cc). Mean delivered energy was 161,012 kJ (78,3-243). No patient showed either a significant hematic loss or fluid absorption syndrome. A 22F urethral three-way catheter was inserted and removed between 12-40 hours in the postoperatory period. After a mean follow-up of 5,5 months (2-9) the average IPSS and QOL questionnaires scores changed, respectively, from 22,4 (19-26) and from 3 (2 -4) to an average of 6,8 (1 &#150; 13) (p&lt;0,01) and 1,4 (0 &#150; 3), respectively, at the end of follow-up (p &lt;0,01). Qmax increased from 6,4 ml/s (5-11,9) baseline to 19,7 ml/s (13,9-24 (p &lt;0,01). No patient showed urinary incontinence. Retreatment was not nee-ded though three patients needed a short-time catheterization (24 hours) after developing acute urinary retention in the first 48h hours.CONCLUSIONS: Our preliminary results suggest that prostate vaporization using 980 nm diode laser with output power up to 120 W, is effective and associated to minimal morbidity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clemente Ramos, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">CONCLUSIONES: Nuestros resultados preliminares sugieren que la vaporización prostática con láser de diodo de 980 nm utilizando potencias de hasta 120 W es efectiva y asociada a escasa morbilidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(2): 125-130, mar. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Láser de diodo-980 mm de alta potencia: resultados preliminares en el tratamiento de la hiperplasia benigna de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52877^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52877^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15237^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52877^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
