<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050125</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of the Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMA-IR) as method to value the insulin resistance in adults that present at least one of the five criteria for metabolic syndrome as defined by the NCEP-ATP-III</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To establish the utility of HOMA-IR as a mathematical        model to value the insulin resistance (IR) in adults having at least        one of the 5 criteria of the metabolic syndrome (MS) as defined by        the NCEP-ATP-III and to correlate it with simple clinical methods as        the body mass index (BMI) and the waist circumference (WC). Material        and methods: We analyzed data from a survey conducted in 2004 with 125 adults without diabetes mellitus aged &gt;20 years        living in the city of Guayaquil-Ecuador, chosen because they presented        at least 1 of the 5 criteria of the MS defi ned by the NCEP-ATP-III. All        of them were submitted to physical examination and measurement (BMI,        WC, and blood pressure) and basal laboratory analyses (glucose, cHDL,        triglycerides and insulin), in search of the other criteria. HOMAR-IR was        calculated by means of the formula: plasmatic insuline before food intake        (mUI/L) 3 plasmatic glucose before food intake (mmol/L)/22.5. It was        considered IR when HOMA-IR values were equal or greates than        9.8. Results: The prevalence of IR was of 57.6%. Men with central        obesity had an HOMA-IR higher than those with non central obesity        (p &lt;0.05). The plasmatic concentrations of triglycerides (p &lt;0.02), glucose        (p &lt;0.02), and insulin (p &lt;0.001) were higher in the obese        women with IR than in obese women with normal insulin sensitivity        (NIS). Among men the plasmatic concentration of insulin was higher in        the obese ones with IR than in those with NIS (p &lt;0.02). The BMI        and the cHDL didn&#146;t differ statistically in none of the subgroups. Conclusions:        The prevalence of IR, measured through HOMA-IR, in        adults with high risk of MS is high. The uses of HOMA-IR to evaluate        a patient during the diagnosis constitutes a very useful tool because        it is not very expensive, it is of easy and quick implementation,        little invasive and it brings clinical information of great practical        value.        The WC can be a simple clinical tool to determine central obesity        and it is possible to use it to predict which individuals would probably        have the MS, independently of total body fat calculated by means of        the BMI</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tagle, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tagle, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Establecer la utilidad del HOMA-IR como método matemático        para valorar la resistencia a la insulina (RI) en individuos        que presentan al menos uno de los cinco criterios para el diagnóstico        del síndrome metabólico (SM) de acuerdo con el NCEP-ATPIII        y correlacionarlo con métodos clínicos sencillos, como el índice        de masa corporal (IMC) y el perímetro de cintura (PC). Material y        métodos: Se analizan los datos de una encuesta realizada en el        año 2004 en 125 individuos sin diabetes mellitus de entre 20 y        79 años que viven en Guayaquil (Ecuador), escogidos por presentar        al menos uno de los cinco criterios del SM definido por el        NCEP-ATP-III. A todos se les realizó un examen físico (IMC, PC y        presión arterial [PA]) y determinaciones basales de laboratorio        (glucosa, cHDL, triglicéridos e insulina) en búsqueda de los otros        criterios. El HOMA-IR se calculó mediante la fórmula: Insulina plasmática        en ayunas (mUI/L) 3 glucosa plasmática en ayunas (mmol/        L)/22,5. Se consideró RI cuando los valores HOMA-IR eran iguales        o superiores a 2,8. Resultados: La prevalencia de RI fue del        57,6%. Los varones con obesidad central tuvieron un HOMA-IR        más alto que aquéllos con obesidad no central (p &lt;0,05). Las        concentraciones plasmáticas en ayunas de triglicéridos (p &lt;0,02),        glucosa (p &lt;0,02) e insulina (p &lt;0,001) fueron más altas en las        mujeres obesas con RI que en las mujeres obesas con sensibilidad        normal a la insulina (SNI). Entre los varones, la concentración plasmática        de insulina fue más alta en los obesos con RI que en aquellos        con SNI (p &lt;0,02). El IMC y las lipoproteínas de alta densidad        (cHDL) no se diferenciaron estadísticamente en ninguno de los        subgrupos. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de RI, medida a través        del HOMA-IR, en individuos con alto riesgo de SM es alta. La utilización        del HOMA-IR para evaluar a un paciente durante el diagnóstico        constituye una herramienta muy útil por ser poco costosa,        de fácil y rápida realización, poco invasiva y aportar información        clínica de gran valor práctico.        El PC puede servir como herramienta clínica sencilla para evaluar la        obesidad central y es posible emplearlo para predecir qué individuos        probablemente tienen SM, independientemente de la grasa corporal        total calculada mediante el IMC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;22(4): 284-290, oct.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMA-IR) como método para valorar la resistencia a la insulina en individuos que presentan al menos uno de los cinco criterios para síndrome metabólico definido por los criterios del NCEP-ATP-III</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
