<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049410</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound and CT study of duodenal pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The radiological evaluation of the duodenum has traditionally been based on barium transit studies; however, ultrasound (US) and computed tomography (CT) are becoming more important in the assessment of this portion of the intestine and the structures that surround it. This report describes and illustrates the CT and US findings for different entities that affect the duodenum, including diseases of the duodenum itself and those of neighboring organs that affect this portion of the small intestine. We classify the pathologies by etiology into congenital, traumatic, iatrogenic and foreign bodies, bezoars, hematologic, inflammatory and neoplastic. Moreover, we present the incidental duodenal and periduodenal findings in US and CT that radiologists should be familiar with given the widespread use of these techniques</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cogollos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanc, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ripollés, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvillo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballestín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El análisis radiológico del duodeno se ha basado tradicionalmente en el tránsito baritado, pero actualmente la ecografía y la tomografía computarizada (TC) están adquiriendo cada vez más importancia para valorar este tramo intestinal y las estructuras que lo rodean. En este trabajo se presentan los hallazgos en TC y ecografía de diversas entidades que afectan al duodeno, tanto por alteraciones propias, como por patología de órganos vecinos que afecten a este tramo intestinal. Para ello se han clasificado como patología congénita, traumática, iatrogénica y cuerpos extraños, bezoares, patología hematológica, inflamatoria y neoplásica. Además, se presentan los hallazgos incidentales duodenales y periduodenales en ecografía y TC que, dado el uso frecuente de estas técnicas, es necesario conocer</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(5): 263-272, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ecografía y tomografía computarizada de la patología duodenal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4439^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1654^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4446^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
