<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039256</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors for voiding dysfunction and cystocele</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the clinical and urodynamic features of a series of women with post void residual urine (disbalanced voiding ) and various degrees of associated cystocele. METHODS: 119 female patients were studied by clinical evaluation, urodynamics, and imaging tests (VCUG). All patients underwent history and genitourological examination (evaluating cystoceles from grade 0 to 3), neuro-urological examination, and complete urodynamic study. Fifty patients (42%) underwent radiological studies of the upper urinary tract. Disbalanced voiding was defined as existence of post void residual greater than 20% of the voided volume. Urethral resistance was measured by URA. Structural obstruction was characterized by PURR (CHESS classification). Functional obstruction was studied by DURR and perineal EMG (associated with flowmetry). Detrusor contractile power was evaluated by W max, W 80-20, and duration of contraction. Urodynamic terminology and measurements complied with the International Continence Society (ICS) standards. Statistical significance was established at 0.05. Statistical analysis was done by Student&#146;s t for quantitative variables , and Pearson`s chi-square for non parametric variables. RESULTS: 119 patients were enrolled. Mean age was 55.84 yr. (range 15-87). Regarding post void residual (114 valid uroflowmetry studies), 25 patients were classified as voiding disbalance (21.9%) and 89 as balanced (74.8%). Regarding clinical data, there were only significant differences between groups in voiding difficulty. For uroflowmetry, only the percentile of the Maximal flow (Qmax) showed significant differences (35 vs. 22 for balanced/disbalanced voiding respectively, p = 0.02). Pressure/volume studies demonstrated bladder hyperactivity in 16 cases (64%) in the group of disbalanced voiding and 31 cases (34.8%) in the normal voiding group (p = 0.008), which presented associated with increased urethral resistance (URA)(p = 0.01) . In the pressure/flow study, there were significant differences in the URA (14.7 vs. 25.3, p = 0,001). There were statistically significant differences in the degree of constrictive (0.5 vs. 1.1, p = 0.009) and compressive (0.5 vs. 1.1; p = 0.04) obstruction (Chess classification). There were not significant differences in the analysis of isometric contractility (Wmax), but there were in the isotonic contractility (W80-20) and detrusor contraction duration. These latter differences presented significant association with the degree of cystocele. DURR and perineal EMG data did not show differences between groups. Radiological abnormalities of urethral morphology were statistically different between groups, presenting in 10% of the patients with normal voiding and 50% of the disbalanced voiding group, although there was not statistical association with obstruction (p = 0.64) . The existence of cystocele did not show a statistical association with these variables either. CONCLUSIONS: Disbalanced voiding appeared with organic obstruction of the lower urinary tract (constrictive most significantly), as well as detrusor abnormal contractility, but whereas the first was not significantly associated with presence and grade of cystocele, the second showed such association</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dambros, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vírseda Chamorro, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Sierra, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Díaz, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adot Zurbano, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Casado, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Fernández, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silmi Moyano, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Valorar las características clínicasy urodinámicas de una serie de mujeres con residuopostmiccional (micción descompensada) y diferentesgrados de cistocele asociado.MÉTODOS: Se estudiaron 119 pacientes de sexofemenino mediante evaluación clínica, urodinámica, yradiológica (cistouretrografías). Todas las pacientes fueronsometidas a historia clínica, exploración física uroginecológica(valorando el cistocele, al vasalva, degrado 0 a grado 3), exploración física neurourológicay estudio urodinámico completo. A 50 pacientes(42%), se les realizó estudio radiológico del tracto urinarioinferior (TUI). Se consideró micción descompensada(MD), la existencia de un residuo postmiccional(RP) mayor del 20% del volumen miccional. La resistenciauretral se midió mediante el URA. La tipificación dela obstrucción estructural se realizó mediante el PURR(clasificación CHESS). El estudio de la obstrucción funcionalse realizó mediante el DURR y la EMG perineal(asociada a la flujometría libre). La potencia contráctildel detrusor se valoró mediante el Wmax, W80-20 yduración de la contracción del detrusor. La terminologíaurodinámica y medidas siguieron las normas de laInternational Continence Society, ICS. La probabilidadde los diferentes análisis estadísticos se consideró significativapor debajo de 0.05, analizándose las variablescuantitativas mediante el test de la T de Student, ylas variables no paramétricas mediante la chi cuadradode Pearson.RESULTADOS: La edad media de las pacientes (119),fue de 55.84 años (rango 15-87). En relación con elRP (114 flujometrías valorables), fueron etiquetadas deMD, 25 pacientes (21.9%) y compensada (MC), 89(74.8%). Respecto a los datos clínicos, solo existierondiferencias significativas (DS) entre ambos grupos en ladificultad miccional. En los datos flujométricos, existierontan solo DS en el percentil (nomogramas deHaylen), del Qmax (35 MC vs 22, MD; p=0,02). Enla cistomanometría, se demostró hiperactividad vesicalen la MD en 16 casos (64%) frente a 31 casos (34,8%)en la MC (p=0,008), que presentó relación con incrementode la resistencia uretral (URA) p=0,01. En el estudioP/F, se demostró DS en el valor del URA (14.7 MCvs 25.3 MD; p=0,001). Existieron DS en los grados deobstrucción constrictiva (0.5 MC vs 1.1 MD; p=0,009)y compresiva (0.02 MC vs 0.4 MD; p=0,04)(clasificaciónCHESS). Estos datos no presentaron relaciónsignificativa con el grado de cistocele. No existieronDS en los análisis de contractilidad isométrica (Wmax),pero sí en la contractilidad isotónica (W80-20) y duraciónde la contracción del detrusor. Estas últimas diferenciassi presentaron relación significativa con elgrado de cistocele. Los datos de DURR y EMG perineposalno arrojaron DS entre ambos grupos. Las alteracionesde la morfología uretral radiológica fueron estadísticamentediferentes entre ambos grupos estandopresente en el 10% de la MC vs 50% de la MD(p=0,01), aunque no presentó relación estadística(p=0,64), con la obstrucción. La presencia de cistocele,así mismo, no modificó estadísticamente ninguno detodos los datos anteriores.CONCLUSIONES: La micción descompensada, acompañótanto a la obstrucción orgánica (más significativamenteconstrictiva) del tracto urinario inferior, como ala afectación contráctil del detrusor, pero, mientras queen la primera condición no se relacionó significativamentecon la presencia y grado de cistocele, en lasegunda si se demostró dicha asociación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(4): 316-323, mayo 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de descompensación miccional y cistocele</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
