<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91744</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Considerations on the organization of the child psychiatric services in Italy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent sociological research on childhood and adolescence in Italy has highlighted the following problematic: a weakening of the support network of equals and family; violence and risk behaviour in adolescents, and the problem of unaccompanied foreign minors. These same themes are found among the clinical issues handled by the Italian neuro-psychiatric services and the European Community. This paper illustrates the organizational model of Emilia-Romagna characterized by the concept of an integrated service system, amongst which is the Adolescent Neuro- Psychiatric Service of Bologna (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Stefano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fioritti, Angelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigon, Giancarlo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientes investigaciones sociológica sobre la infancia y la adolescencia en Italia señalan como principales problemas: un debilitamiento de la red de apoyo tanto de los iguales como familiar, violencia y comportamiento de riesgo en los adolescentes, así como la situación de los menores extranjeros no acompañados. Los mismos aspectos se encuentran entre los temas clínicos que refieren los servicios de neuropsiquiatría italiana y la Comunidad Europea. El artículo ilustra el modelo organizativo de la Emilia Romagna caracterizado por el concepto de red integrada de los equipamientos, entre los que se encuentra el servicio de neuropsiquiatría de la adolescencia de Bolonia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(14): 57-64, nov. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones sobre la organización del servicio de psiquiatría de la edad evolutiva enItalia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7727^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
