<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110857</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complete congenital heart block and maternal autoantibodies anti-Ro positives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital heart block is a rare anomaly produced by an injury to the specialized cardiac conducting tissue, with secondary alterations in the transmission of stimuli from the atria to the ventricles. This defect can be associated with structural heart disease and maternal autoimmune diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus syndrome or the presence of anti-Ro and anti-La autoantibodies. Prenatal diagnosis is given by echocardiography, which shows persistent fetal bradycardia, and allows detection of fetal hemodynamic deterioration, requiring finalization of pregnancy. Intrauterine therapy consists of sympathomimetics and steroid agents and a pacemaker can be implanted in the newborn as a definitive treatment at the end of the pregnancy. We report the case of an asymptomatic mother at week 26 of pregnancy who presented to the emergency department with abdominal pain. On examination, an anomalous fetal heart rate was detected and congenital heart block was confirmed. The only abnormal result of maternal blood test was the presence of positive anti-nuclear antibodies and anti-Ro autoantibodies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pato Mosquera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Vilar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Couso Cambeiro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bloqueo cardíaco congénito (BCC) es una entidad poco frecuente que se produce por la lesión del tejido de conducción cardíaco, con una alteración secundaria de la transmisión de los impulsos auriculares a los ventrículos. Se puede asociar a cardiopatías estructurales y a enfermedades autoinmunes como el lupus eritematoso sistémico o a la presencia de autoanticuerpos anti-Ro y anti-La. El diagnóstico prenatal se realiza mediante ecografía y ecocardiografía al objetivar una bradicardia fetal mantenida; ambas técnicas permiten asimismo el seguimiento y la valoración de finalización de la gestación ante la presencia de signos de deterioro hemodinámico. El tratamiento médico intraútero se efectúa con fármacos inotrópicos y corticoides y una vez finalizada la gestación la terapia definitiva generalmente será la implantación de un marcapasos. Presentamos el caso de una gestante de 26 semanas que acude a urgencias por dolor abdominal. Durante la exploración se objetiva un latido fetal anómalo confirmando la existencia de un BCC. Como único hallazgo analítico materno alterado se encuentra la presencia de anticuerpos de origen autoinmune ANA y anti Ro positivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);40(2): 93-96, mar.-abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo aurículo-ventricular congénito completo y anticuerpos maternos anti-Ro positivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1329^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
