<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151249</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social anxiety in adolescence: psychoevolutionary and family factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Research on protective or risk factors of social anxiety in adolescence has advanced significantly in last decades. However, there is scarce evidence about the role of family and social context in the development of this problem. The aim of this study was to analyze the predictive value of parenting styles, parental discipline, social competence and self-esteem, in the development of social anxiety during adolescence, taking into account the gender and age of adolescents. The sample consisted of 2060 Andalusian teenagers who were studying Obligatory Secondary Education (52.1% boys). Multiple regression analyses were performed. These analyses explained between 27.7% and 33.8% of the variance of social anxiety and highlighted its positive relationship with negative self-esteem, normative adjustment and parental control, and its negative relationship with social adjustment. These results are discussed emphasizing the importance of focusing on supporting the development of self-esteem and social competence of youths and working with their parents to promote positive parenting practices, adapted to the developmental level of the children, to prevent social anxiety in adolescence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ruiz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ortziz, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio sobre los factores de riesgo y protección relacionados con el desarrollo de la ansiedad social en la adolescencia ha avanzado notablemente en las ultimas décadas. Sin embargo, no existe mucha evidencia sobre el papel del contexto familiar y social inmediato. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar el valor predictivo de los estilos educativos, la disciplina parental, la competencia social y la autoestima sobre la ansiedad social adolescente, en función del sexo y de la edad de los jóvenes. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 2060 estudiantes andaluces de Educación Secundaria Obligatoria (52,1% chicos). Se realizaron análisis de regresión múltiple que explicaron entre un 27,7% y un 33,8% de la varianza de la ansiedad social y destacaron su relación positiva con la autoestima negativa, el ajuste normativo y el control parental, y su relación negativa con el ajuste social. Se discute la importancia de trabajar la autoestima y competencia social de los jóvenes, así como de favorecer practicas parentales positivas y adaptadas al nivel evolutivo de los hijos para prevenir el desarrollo la ansiedad social en este periodo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;24(1): 29-49, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad social en la adolescencia: factores psicoevolutivos y de contexto familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
