<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113218</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intramedullary reaming in Ribbing disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ribbing disease is a rare benign sclerosing bone dysplasia. It presents with an increased bone density at the diaphysis with cortical endosteal/periosteal thickening and affects predominantly the lower extremities. We report a case of a 28 year-old woman with a this condition in her tibia that occluded the medullary cavity, with severe pain that could not be relieved with anti-inflammatory therapy. Several cases have been published on pain relief after intramedullary reaming. We performed this treatment with the surgical steps to avoid complications such as a fracture or false route that may occur due to the difficulty in piercing the closed medullary cavity. Pain improved immediately after surgery, and the patient is asymptomatic after one year. The natural progression of ribbing disease is to stabilise, but there are no data published with long term follow-up after intramedullary reaming (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eslava-Gurrea, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Morentin-Garraza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noain-Sanz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Ribbing es una displasia ósea esclerosante benigna poco frecuente. Se presenta con un incremento de la densidad ósea a nivel diafisario con engrosamiento cortical endo/periostal que predomina en extremidades inferiores. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 28 años con una lesión de estas características a nivel tibial, que llega a obstruir por completo el canal medular, y con dolor muy intenso no controlable con analgésicos habituales. Está publicado en varios casos cómo el fresado endomedular alivia de forma notable los síntomas. Aplicamos dicho tratamiento detallando los pasos quirúrgicos empleados para evitar una fractura y falsa vía que puede producirse por la dificultad de traspasar el tapón óseo escleroso. La paciente mejoró inmediatamente en el postoperatorio encontrándose asintomática al año de la intervención. En su evolución natural la enfermedad tiende a estabilizarse, no hay datos a largo plazo en los pocos casos publicados con fresado endomedular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(3): 231-234, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fresado endomedular en la enfermedad de Ribbing</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3993^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3993^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
