<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152677</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation and validation of the Perception of Restraint Use Questionnaire (PRUQ) on the use of physical restraints on the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. To adapt and to validate in a Spanish population the Perception of Restraint Use Questionnaire (PRUQ), which assesses the importance that professionals give to the use of physical restraints when caring for older adults. Methods. After a process of forward-back translation and linguistic adaptation, a Spanish version of the original questionnaire was obtained. A descriptive cross-sectional multicenter study was then carried out. Based on non-probability sampling, 20 centers from three Spanish regions were selected; 830 professionals agreed to participate. Results. 15 of the 17 items of the original questionnaire were translated literally and two required minor modifications. All were considered acceptable by an expert panel (content validity index of 0.89); a pilot study confirmed the adequate feasibility of the questionnaire. The principal components analysis identified three dimensions that explained 66.2% of variance. The confirmatory factor analysis of this tridimensional model showed an acceptable fit [CFI = 0.936; RMSEA = 0.080], being factor loadings and factor correlations statistically significant (p&lt;0.001). The internal consistency (Cronbach&#146;s alpha) for the total score was 0.92 and the test-retest reliability (ICCa) was 0.87 (95% CI: 0.78 to 0.92) over an interval of three weeks. Conclusions. The Spanish version of the PRUQ shows good psychometric characteristics and is adapted to the cultural context of this country. It may be considered a useful tool to assess in which situations professionals consider the use of physical restraints most necessary, helping to design training activities aimed at rationalizing its application (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fariña-López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penelo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez-Guerra, GJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Francés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Adaptar y estudiar las propiedades psicométricas en población española del Perception of Restraint Use Questionnaire (PRUQ), que mide la importancia que dan los profesionales al uso de restricciones físicas en personas mayores. Material y métodos. Tras un proceso de traducción-retrotraducción y de adaptación lingüística, se obtuvo una versión en español. A continuación, se realizó un estudio multicéntrico, descriptivo y transversal para evaluar sus propiedades psicométricas. Mediante un muestreo no probabilístico se seleccionaron 20 centros de tres comunidades autónomas; aceptaron participar 830 profesionales. Resultados. De los 17 ítems del cuestionario, 15 pudieron traducirse de manera literal; en dos hubo que realizar modificaciones menores. Un panel de expertos consideró todos aceptables (índice de validez de contenido de 0,89); un estudio piloto confirmó la adecuada factibilidad del cuestionario. El análisis en componentes principales identificó tres dimensiones que explicaban el 66,2% de la varianza. El análisis factorial confirmatorio de este modelo tridimensional mostró un ajuste aceptable [CFI = 0,936; RMSEA = 0,080], siendo las cargas y las correlaciones factoriales estadísticamente significativas (p &lt; 0,001). La consistencia interna (alfa de Cronbach) de la puntuación total fue de 0,92, y la fiabilidad test-retest (CCIa) de 0,87 (IC 95%: 0,78 a 0,92) en un intervalo de tres semanas. Conclusiones. La versión española del PRUQ muestra buenas propiedades psicométricas y se adapta al contexto cultural de este país. Puede considerarse útil para evaluar en qué situaciones se consideran más necesarias las restricciones físicas, lo que ayudaría a diseñar actividades de formación encaminadas a racionalizar su aplicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;39(1): 13-22, ene.-abr. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación y validación española del Perception of Restraint Use Questionnaire (PRUQ) sobre el uso de restricciones físicas en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
