<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153009</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of biomarkers in abdominal pain management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abdominal pain conditions that fall into the category of acute abdomen (AA) are the most important ones to identify quickly. Diagnostic delay can lead to death or significant complications. Biological markers have the potential to improve the diagnostic and prognostic capacity of clinical assessment and the conventional complement of tests. This review aims to explore the relevance of several markers to the management of AA in the emergency department. Creactive protein (CRP), procalcitonin, and lactate are the biomarkers most often used in the emergency department. CRP is often analyzed in the context of AA, but it is very difficult to establish a cutoff that gives good sensitivity and specificity. The kinetics of CRP make it the most sensitive biomarker and one that is appropriate for assessing severity before the onset of clinical signs of severe sepsis or altered hemodynamics. Lactate is a marker of poor tissue perfusion, a key element in the management of severe sepsis and septic shock in AA. Since lactate testing is easy and inexpensive, this important biomarker is useful in the emergency department (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baena-Delgado, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Rodríguez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Murillo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Valverde, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero-Pérez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las manifestaciones de las enfermedades que subyacen bajo el término de dolor abdominal agudo (DAA) como motivo de consulta en urgencias, pueden ser sutiles en su inicio y variables en el tiempo, lo que dificulta su reconocimiento precoz. Entre ellas son prioritarias las englobadas bajo el término de abdomen agudo (AA) o situación de DAA tiempo-dependiente. Los biomarcadores pueden mejorar el manejo de estos pacientes, añadiendo información adicional a la valoración clínica y a las exploraciones complementarias, e incrementando la capacidad diagnóstica y pronóstico. Los biomarcadores más utilizados en urgencias son la proteína C reactiva (PCR), la procalcitonina (PCT) y el lactato. La PCR ha sido el marcador más estudiado en el diagnóstico del DAA, y es muy difícil establecer un punto de corte que proporcione buena sensibilidad y especificidad. La PCT es el biomarcador más sensible y adecuado, gracias a su particular cinética, para valorar la gravedad antes de que los signos clínicos de sepsis grave o alteración hemodinámica hagan su aparición. El lactato es un marcador de hipoperfusión tisular y elemento clave en el manejo de la sepsis grave y del shock séptico en el abdomen agudo, lo que añadido a su fácil y rápida obtención y a su bajo coste, definen su importancia y utilidad en los servicios de urgencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(3): 185-192, jun. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los biomarcadores en el manejo del dolor abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
