<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055399</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training in tele-surgery and robotic surgery: six years experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last 20 years there has been a move in all surgical specialties towards less invasivesurgical procedures. The most recent step is robotic surgery or better described as surgical telemanipulation technology which has slowly been adapted worldwide for many reasons including: cost, learning curve, availabletechnology, and applicability to the different surgical specialties. Nonetheless, its use continues to grow in all surgical fields. Our center has been a pioneer in the use and training of robotic surgical techniques. In this manuscript,we describe the organization and experience of our training program</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Evelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Randolph Chitwood, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wiley Nifong, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos 20 años todas las especialidadesquirúrgicas han tratado de ofrecer procedimientosmenos invasivos. El paso más reciente ha sido la adaptación de la cirugía robótica o mejor dicho de técnicas de tele-cirugía. Esta tecnología ha sido incorporadalentamente por varias razones incluyendo: el coste, la curva de aprendizaje, y las limitaciones tecnológicas.Nuestro centro ha sido uno de los pioneros en el uso y entrenamiento de la cirugía robótica. En esta monografía vamos a describir nuestros resultados y experienciade nuestro programa de entrenamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(4): 363-369, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento en tele-cirugía y cirugía robótica: seis años de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
