<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163591</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of dietetic changes in the perior of Ramadan</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Amongst the changes affecting daily habits during the month of Ramadan, we can distinctively observe the dietetic changes, either qualitatively of quantitatively. Our essential objective of this study is to evaluate the changes brought about by the fasting during Ramadan among Muslims. Methods: We analyzed the daily diet by carrying out a prompting survey among 100 volunteer Muslims during the period of Ramadan. We calculated inventory of 3 days consumed food and the preparation and quality of meals. Results: Observing significant changes in diets during Ramadan. The diet is a hyper-protein dominated by the intake of proteins (27%). As for the repartition of energy between meals, we concluded also disequilibrium by taking the most part of energy during the first meal. Conclusions: It would be essential to re-adjust the diet during Ramadan in order to reach the most equilibrium possible, which should be necessarily based on adequate education and adaptable nutritional information before the beginning of the month of Ramadan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agoumi, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López García de la Serrana, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveras López, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Entre las modificaciones introducidas en los hábitos de vida por el mes de Ramadán, destacan los cambios dietéticos, tanto cualitativos como cuantitativos. El objetivo fundamental del presente estudio es evaluar las modificaciones producidas por el ayuno de Ramadán en la población musulmana. Material y métodos: Se analizó la dieta diaria realizando una encuesta recordatorio a 100 voluntarios musulmanes de los que se encontraron bajo este periodo. Consistió en un inventario de 3 días sobre los alimentos consumidos, su preparación y su cantidad. Resultados: Se dedujeron cambios significativos en la dieta de ramadán. Ésta resultó ser hiperprotéica, donde predominaba la ingesta de proteínas (27%). De la repartición de energía entre las comidas, se dedujo que es igualmente desequilibrada siendo la mayor parte de energía concentrada en la primera comida. Conclusiones: Sería esencial hacer reajustes en la dieta de ramadán a fin de equilibrarla lo máximo posible. Para ello habrá que promocionar una adecuada educación e información nutricional adaptada al mes de ramadán antes de que empiece dicho mes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(3): 25-28, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las modificaciones dietéticas en el periodo de Ramadán</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29390^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23550</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
