<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113402</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food components with physiological activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Foods in good sanitary conditions bring substances with physiological activity, some of them without nutritive capability, that may reduce the risk of degenerative diseases, that are considered the main cause of death in developed countries. The knowledge of such physiological effects comes from epidemiological and clinical studies carried on in humans, and animals too. We know that vegetal steroids have an hypocholesterolemic effect as a fact of its competition with cholesterol across the small intestine; antioxidants neutralize free radicals; lemonem, organ-sulphured compounds, indols, lignans and conjugated linoleic acid, have chemopreventive properties and others; soy isoflavones, protect against some tumours and cardiovascular diseases; dietary fibre, increases intestine health and prevents the risk of cardiovascular diseases; probiotics and prebiotic agents, increase the gastrointestinal health; mono-unsaturated and poly-unsaturated fatty acids prevent cardiovascular diseases; and bioactive peptides, have anti-hypertensive effects. Effects in cellular differentiation or tumours better responding to specific compounds are yet fully ignored, as the factor affecting to bioavailability; the safety borders or the efficient dose, of special interest when they are added to foods in a higher than natural concentration. However, these compounds may help us to prevent several chronic diseases into a properly equilibrated sufficient diet, with a wide variety of fruits and vegetables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Grana, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los alimentos con unas condiciones sanitarias adecuadas aportan sustancias con actividad fisiológica, muchas de ellas sin capacidad nutritiva, que pueden reducir el riesgo de padecer enfermedades degenerativas, las cuales constituyen la principal causa de muerte en los países desarrollados. El conocimiento de sus efectos fisiológicos procede principalmente de estudios epidemiológicos y clínicos en animales, y seres humanos. Así, los esteroles vegetales, tienen efecto hipocolesterolémico al competir con el colesterol en el intestino delgado; los antioxidantes, neutralizan radicales libres; el limonemo, los compuestos organosulfurados, indoles, lignanos y ácido linoleico conjugado, poseen propiedades quimiopreventivas y otras; las isoflavonas de soja, protegen frente algunos cánceres y enfermedades cardiovasculares; la fibra alimentaria, mejora la salud intestinal y previene el riesgo de enfermedades cardiovasculares; los agentes probióticos y prebióticos, mejoran la salud gastrointestinal; los ácidos grasos monoinsaturados y poliinsaturados, previenen las enfermedades cardiovasculares; y los péptidos bioactivos, tienen efectos antihipertensivos. No se conocen totalmente los efectos sobre la diferenciación celular o qué cánceres responden mejor a compuestos específicos, ni los factores que afectan a la biodisponibilidad; los márgenes de seguridad o la dosis eficaz, de especial interés cuando se añaden a alimentos en una concentración mayor que de forma natural. No obstante, estos componentes pueden ayudar en la prevención de diversas enfermedades crónicas siempre que la dieta sea suficiente, con una amplia variedad de frutas y hortalizas y equilibrada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;64(1): 12-20, ene.-mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113402</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Componentes de los alimentos con actividad Fisiológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2316^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5656^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50323</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
