<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96878</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Simplifying the surgical treatment of the gummy smile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human beings possess a highly expressive face, there are people who when smile, show the gums above the base of the teeth causing an antiesthetic aspect. This situation has negative repercussions altering the spontaneity of the facial expression. In the etiology of the gingival smile, dental, skeletal and soft tissue factors take part. We present a new surgical variant that offers an excellent alternative for the treatment of the gingival smile with soft tissue alterations. Fifteen female patients were treated; 7 had rhinoplasty together with correction of gingival smile; the remaining 8 patients were exclusively gingival smile surgery; agesvaried from 17 to 38 years. All the treated improved their appearance and selfesteem. There were no complications or problems related to the wound. The results are permanent in the medium and long term and the patient&#146;s smile is normal because of improvement of their expression, maintaining muscular function and sensitivity. The proposed technique is simple, easily reproducible, ambulatory and with an average operating time of one hour. It is well tolerated by the patients since it does not interfere with their daily activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chacón Martínez, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Govea, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Porras, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Costilla, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Cárdenas, H. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Adam, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sonrisa es una de las expresiones más comunes del ser humano como muestra de satisfacción, alegría o felicidad. Algunas personas al sonreír muestran la encía por encima de la base de los dientes, lo que ocasiona un aspecto antiestético. Esta situación repercute negativamente en el individuo, ya que altera la espontaneidad de la expresión facial. En el origen de la sonrisa gingival intervienen factores dentales, esqueléticos y de tejidos blandos. Proponemos una variante quirúrgica innovadora para corregir la sonrisa gingival en pacientes con alteraciones de los tejidos blandos. Se intervinieron quirúrgicamente 15 mujeres de entre 17 y 38 años de edad. En 7 de ellas se practicó rinoplastia además de corrección de la sonrisa gingival. Las 8 restantes se sometieron exclusivamente a corrección de la sonrisa gingival. Las 15 pacientes intervenidas mejoraron su apariencia y autoestima. No hubo complicaciones o problemas relacionados con la herida quirúrgica. Los resultados han sido permanentes a medio y largo plazo. La sonrisa delas pacientes es normal, mejoró su expresión y se conservaron la sensibilidad y la función muscular La técnica propuesta es sencilla y de fácil reproducción; el tiempo quirúrgico estimado es de una hora y la operación es de tipo ambulatoria. Suele ser bien tolerada por los pacientes y no altera sus actividades cotidianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;37(1): 43-49, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96878</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Simplificando el tratamiento quirúrgico de la sonrisa gingival</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8221^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9248^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12636^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
