<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113481</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health professionals&#146; knowledge on Chagas disease in the province of Almeria, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Health professionals who care for patients with imported diseases often lack enough training. The aim of the study is to assess the knowledge of Chagas disease among doctors and nurses attending at-risk pregnant women in our province. Method: descriptive study through a performed anonymous and voluntary knowledge questionnaire for 278 physicians and nurses working at maternity and children's health services in the three hospitals in the province. In Poniente Hospital was established in 2007 a program of screening for the disease in pregnant women. For statistical analysis, quantitative variables were described using the mean and standard deviation. For comparison of qualitative variables we used the chi-square test or Fisher exact test as appropriate. Differences in age and years of experience depending on the hospital were measured by Brown-Forsythe robust test. Results: 116 (41.7%) professionals agreed to participate in the study. 80 (69%) were women and 36 (31%)men,mean age 36.78 years. By professional categories, physicians have a mean of 73.9% correct responses, the nurses 50.7%. Poniente Hospital had the highest percentage of correct answers on aspects of the geographical distribution of the disease (73.7%), the mechanisms of transmission (86%) and diagnosis (82.5%). Conclusions: The Poniente Hospital professionals generally have a better Knowledge about Chagas disease compared with two other professionals hospitals, which probably is related to the existence of the screening program for the disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Izquierdo, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Sánchez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador-Sánchez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Coronas, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Vilches, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Metz, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Los profesionales sanitarios de la provincia de Almería atienden a pacientes con enfermedades importadas para las que en muchas ocasiones carecen de suficiente formación. El objetivo del estudio fue valorar los conocimientos que tienen sobre diferentes aspectos de la enfermedad de Chagas los profesionales médicos y de enfermería que trabajan en tres hospitales de Almería atendiendo a mujeres gestantes. Método: estudio descriptivo trasversal realizado en el año 2011 a través de un cuestionario, anónimo y voluntario, a 278 sanitarios (personal médico y personal de enfermería) del área materno-infantil de los tres hospitales de la provincia. En el hospital de Poniente se instauró en 2007 un programa de despistaje de la enfermedad en mujeres embarazadas. Para el análisis estadístico, las variables cuantitativas se describieron con la media y su desviación estándar. Para la comparación de las variables cualitativas se utilizó la prueba chi2 de Pearson o la prueba exacta de Fisher según correspondiera. Resultados: 116 (41,7%) profesionales aceptaron participar en el estudio. 80 (69%) fueron mujeres y 36 (31%) hombres, con edad media de 36,78 años. El personal médico presentó una media de respuestas correctas del 73,9% y el personal de enfermería del 50,7%. El hospital de Poniente tuvo mayor porcentaje de respuestas correctas en aspectos relativos a la distribución geográfica de la enfermedad (73,7%), los mecanismos de transmisión (86%) y el diagnóstico (82,5%). Conclusiones: Los profesionales del hospital de Poniente presentan de forma general un mejor conocimiento de la enfermedad de Chagas en comparación con los profesionales de los otros dos centros hospitalarios, lo que probablemente se relaciona con la existencia del programa de despistaje de la enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(3): 267-275, mayo-jun.2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113481</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento de la enfermedad de Chagas por parte de los profesionales sanitarios de tres hospitales en la provincia de Almería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
