<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28260</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the literature on the value of magnetoencephalography in epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Magnetoencephalography (MEG) it is a non-invasive technique of recording the brain activity, based on the detection of magnetic fields. Aim. It is sought to determine the relative contribution of MEG to the handling of patients with epilepsy concerning to other diagnostic technics like scalp EEG, v-EEG (v-EEG), electrocorticography (EcoG), magnetic resonance (MR and MRf), positron emission tomography (PET) and single photon emission tomography (SPECT). Method. It has been carried out it a critical revision of the literature, using the approaches of the evidence-based medicine (EBM). In the databases MEDLINE and HEALTH-START, among the years 1996 and 2001, it were found 1169 references. After the one sieved, 36 were selected, of those that chose 22 definitively for their analysis: 3 articles were classified as of technical effectiveness and 19 as effectiveness in diagnostic accuracy. For the methodological quality, 2 were classified as of group B, 16 in C and 4 in D. Eighteen articles make reference to MEG and pharmaco-resistant epilepsy, while other 4 they make reference to MEG and pharmaco-sensitive epilepsy. Sensibility is highly variable, being bigger in extratemporal epilepsy (44-92.9%), then in temporal (33.3-80%) and smaller in mesial temporal (42.3-53%). Specificity is bigger for patient with anatomical lesions. Conclusions. 1. Localization of interictal activity is better in neocortical lateral regions, diminishing in mesial ones, 2. The methodological deficiencies of the articles prevent to carry out a meta-analysis of the data (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La magnetoencefalografía (MEG) es una técnica no invasiva de registro de la actividad cerebral, basada en la detección de los campos magnéticos. Objetivo. Se pretende establecer la contribución relativa de la MEG al manejo de los pacientes con epilepsia frente a otras técnicas diagnósticas como el EEG de cuero cabelludo, la videoelectroencefalografía (v-EEG), la electrocorticografía (ECoG), la resonancia magnética (RM y RMf), la tomografía por emisión de positrones (PET) y la tomografía computarizada por emisión de fotón único (SPECT). Desarrollo. Para lograr nuestro objetivo, se ha realizado una revisión crítica de la literatura, empleando los criterios de la medicina basada en la evidencia (MBE). En las bases de datos MEDLINE y HEALTH-START, entre los años 1996 y 2001, se encontraron 1.169 referencias. Tras el cribado, se seleccionaron 36, de las que se eligieron definitivamente 22 para su análisis: tres artículos se clasificaron como de eficacia técnica, y 19 como de eficacia en exactitud diagnóstica. Por la calidad metodológica, dos se clasificaron en el grupo B, 16 en el C y cuatro en el D; 18 artículos hacen referencia a MEG y epilepsia farmacorresistente, mientras que otros cuatro hacen referencia a MEG y epilepsia farmacosensible. La sensibilidad es muy variable, y es mayor en la epilepsia extratemporal (44-92,9 por ciento), luego en la temporal (33,3-80 por ciento) y menor en la temporal mesial (42,3-53 por ciento). La especificidad es mayor para pacientes con lesiones anatómicas. Conclusiones. 1. La localización de la actividad intercrítica es mejor en las regiones neocorticales laterales, y disminuye en las regiones mesiales; 2. Las deficiencias metodológicas de los artículos impiden realizar un metaanálisis de los datos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(10): 951-961, nov. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión bibliográfica sobre la utilidad de la magnetoencefalografía en la epilepsia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Sola, RG </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido Rivas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28260</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d286</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9375</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
