<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159599</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A healthy public administration through healthy organizational practices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present study we have proposed a theoretical model based on Kopelman, Brief &amp; Guzzo&#146;s model (1990), in which transformational leadership is positioned as an antecedent of organizational climate, and the psychological capital, as a consequence of that climate. The theoretical model was tested using structural equations in a sample of 277 employees of a public Administration. The good fit of the data according to the revised goodness of fit indexes, both in the confirmatory analysis for each variable and in the structural model statistically validates our theoretical model, accepting the study hypotheses. This makes clear the need for the Administration to propose transformational leadership measures at the individual, team and organizational levels to strengthen the achievement of positive outcomes through positives organizational climate and psychological capital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mañas Rodríguez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz Pardo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio se muestra una propuesta teórica basada en el modelo de Kopelman, Brief y Guzzo (1990) en la que se ha posicionado al liderazgo transformacional como antecedente del clima organizacional, y al capital psicológico como consecuente de dicho clima. Nuestra propuesta ha sido probada haciendo uso de ecuaciones estructurales en una muestra compuesta por 277 empleados de una Administración pública. El buen ajuste de los datos según los índices de bondad de ajuste revisados, tanto en los análisis confirmatorios para cada variable como del modelo estructural final valida estadísticamente nuestra propuesta teórica, aceptándose las hipótesis de estudio. Se hace de esta manera evidente la necesidad de que la Administración plantee medidas basadas en el liderazgo transformacional a nivel individual, de equipos de trabajo y de organización para fortalecer la consecución de resultados organizacionales positivos a través de un clima organizacional y un capital psicológico positivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(1): 160-167, ene. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159599</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una administración pública saludable a través de prácticas organizacionales saludables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16701</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10751</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
