<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89612</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic use of proton pump inhibitors: Is the risk of osteoporosis and fractures real?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract Proton pump inhibitors (PPI) are one of the most widely used groups of drugs and theirpotential toxicity is periodically reviewed, emphasizing aspects originally considered secondary.The present review analyzes the physiological and pharmacological bases and the scarce clinicalevidence for a potential association between the continued administration of PPI and thedevelopment of osteoporosis and bone fractures. Both disorders are clearly related to calciumhomeostasis and are highly important in elderly patients due to their poor general prognosisand disabling consequences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martí-Cabrera, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Masanet, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esplugues, Juan V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen Los inhibidores de la bomba de protones (IBP) constituyen uno de los grupos farmacológicosmás usados y su potencial toxicidad se revisa periódicamente haciendo hincapié enaspectos que en un primer momento se habían considerado secundarios. En la presente revisiónse analizan las bases fisio-farmacológicas y la limitada evidencia clínica de una potencial relaciónentre la administración continuada de IBP y la aparición de osteoporosis y fracturas óseas.Ambas patologías están claramente relacionadas con la homeostasis del calcio, y son de granimportancia en pacientes de edad avanzada por su mal pronóstico general y las consecuenciasinvalidantes que conllevan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(4): 271-277, Abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es real el riesgo de osteoporosis y riesgo de fracturas con el uso crónico de inhibidores de la bomba de protones?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d877^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4871^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
