<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041907</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Skin cancer prevention and sun protection counselling</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last decades, the incidence of skin cancer has been on the rise in Europe, includingSpain, and other developed countries with a mainly white race population. The increaseis probably a result of several factors, including increased exposure to ultraviolet radiation,particularly during childhood. This paper reviews risk factors and primary prevention measures for skin cancer, focused on children and adolescent photoprotection. We examinethe effectiveness of the interventions and the recommendations of expert groups from othercountries on this issue. Finally, we propose the preventive recommendations of the spanishgroup PrenvInfad/PAPPS Infancia y Adolescencia for primary prevention of melanoma andother types of skin cancer for Primary Care offices. These recommendations are primarily:counselling parents and teenagers to avoid excessive sun exposure (keeping away from thesun at central hours of the day, staying in the shade, using protective clothing and widebrimmedhats) and the use of solar cream, but not as the only protection measure from ultravioletradiation, and, when possible, participate in educative campaigns in school andcommunity settings to prevent skin cancer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino Moína, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las últimas décadas se ha producido un aumento en la incidencia de cáncer de pielen Europa, incluida España, y en otros países desarrollados con predominio de población deraza blanca. Este incremento se atribuye en parte al aumento de la exposición a los rayos ultravioleta,especialmente durante la infancia. En este trabajo se revisan los factores de riesgoy las medidas de prevención primaria del cáncer de piel dirigidas a la fotoprotección enla población general pediátrica. Se analiza la efectividad de las diferentes intervenciones ylas recomendaciones de los grupos de expertos de otros países sobre este tema. Finalmentese proponen las recomendaciones preventivas del grupo español PrevInfad/PAPPS Infanciay Adolescencia para la prevención primaria del melanoma y otros cánceres de piel desde elámbito de las consultas de Atención Primaria y que se resumen en dar consejo sobre evitaciónde la exposición solar excesiva (evitar las horas centrales del día, buscar la sombra, utilizarsombrero y ropas protectoras) y fomentar el uso de cremas protectoras, aunque no comoúnica medida de barrera frente a las radiaciones ultravioleta y, cuando sea posible, participaren las campañas educativas sobre prevención del cáncer cutáneo que se produzcanen el ámbito escolar y comunitario</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;7(26): 231-253, abr.-jun. 2005. mapas, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041907</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención del cáncer de piel y consejo de protección solar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13861^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13859^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34640</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
