<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118388</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SUHCAT study, part 3: a map of educational and research activity in hospital emergency services in Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the training, educational, and research activities of hospital emergency department staff in Catalonia, Spain, and to analyze differences in these activities between hospitals of various types. Methods: The heads of 79 of the 82 hospital emergency departments in Catalonia (96%) responded to questions about the training undertaken by emergency department staff and the characteristics and results of educational and research activities carried out by these physicians and nurses. The survey also asked about the number of hours available to staff for these activities. Medical residency training was excluded. Statistics were compiled for three levels of emergency department volume (high, medium, and low), for private and public hospital status, and for level of complexity of public hospitals (technologically well equipped, comprehensive general, other referral, or local).Results: In 31.6% of the departments, a portion of the shift was reserved for training staff physicians; 23.1% reserved time for nurse training. A median (interquartile range) of 5% (3%-10%) of contracted time was reserved for training physicians and 2% (1%-3%) was allotted for nurse training. Departmental sessions were organized for emergency physicians and nurses in 79.7% and 94.2% of the hospitals, respectively. Emergency physicians from 79.5%, 76.9%, and25.6% of the hospitals attended the conferences of Catalan, Spanish, and international emergency medicine associations, respectively. Nurses from 57.7%, 29.8%, and 3.8% of the departments attended these conferences. Undergraduate medical students were taught in 59.5% of the departments and postgraduate training was given in (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró, Òscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Netto, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boqué, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Fábrega, Francesc Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escalada, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gené, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar las actividades formativas, docentes e investigadoras realizadas en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios (SUH) de Cataluña, y compararlas en función de las características de estos SUH y de los hospitales. Método: Se entrevistó a los responsables de 79 de los 82 SUH de Cataluña (96%), que respondieron a preguntas referentes a las actividades formativas en las que participan los profesionales de urgencias, las características y resultados de las actividades docentes e investigadoras llevadas a cabo por ellos y la disponibilidad de tiempos por parte de médicos y enfermeros para realizarlas. Se excluyeron de este análisis los datos referentes a la formación de residentes. Se analizaron las respuestas según la actividad del SUH (alta, media, baja), el uso del hospital (privado, público) y la complejidad del hospital público (alta tecnología o alta resolución, referencia, comarcal).Resultados: El 31,6% de SUH protege parte de la jornada laboral para la formación de sus facultativos y el 23,1% parte de la jornada de sus enfermeros, con unas medianas del 5%(p25-75: 3-10%) y el 2% (1-3%) del tiempo contratado, respectivamente. Existen sesiones propias del servicio para los facultativos y los enfermeros en el 79,7% y 94,2% de los SUH, respectivamente. La presencia de facultativos y enfermeros al congreso catalán y español y en congresos internacionales de la especialidad existió en el 79,5%, 76,9% y 25,6% de los SUH para los primeros, y en el 57,7%, 39,8% y 3,8% para los segundos. Existen estudiantes de pregrado de medicina y de enfermería en el 59,5% y el 81% de SUH, respectivamente; y de postgrado en el 22,8% y 40,5%. El 24,1% y 36,7% de SUH tienen algún profesional de medicina o enfermería, respectivamente, que imparte clases teóricas de pregrado en sus facultades, y el 35,4% y 25,3% respecto a clases de postgrado. La mediana de presentaciones anuales a congresos de los SUH  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);26(1): 47-56, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio SUHCAT (3): mapa docente e investigador de los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5280^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
