<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153210</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mineral metabolism disorders, vertebral fractures and aortic calcifications in stable kidney transplant recipients: The role of gender (EMITRAL study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The relationship between mineral metabolism disorders, bone fractures and vascular calcifications in kidney transplant recipients has not been established. Method: We performed a cross-sectional study in 727 stable recipients from 28 Spanish transplant clinics. Mineral metabolism parameters, the semi-quantification of vertebral fractures and abdominal aortic calcifications were determined centrally. Results: Vitamin D deficiency (25OHD3&lt;15ng/ml) was more common in female recipients at CKD-T stages I&#150;III (29.6% vs 44.4%; p=0.003). The inverse and significant correlation between 25OHD3 and PTH was gender-specific and women exhibited a steeper slope than men (p=0.01). Vertebral fractures (VFx) with deformity grade &amp;#8805;2 were observed in 15% of recipients. Factors related to VFx differed by gender; in males, age (OR 1.04; 95% CI 1.01&#150;1.06) and CsA treatment (OR: 3.2; 95% CI: 1.6&#150;6.3); in females, age (OR 1.07; 95% CI: 1.03&#150;1.12) and PTH levels (OR per 100pg/ml increase: 1.27; 95% CI: 1.043&#150;1.542). Abdominal aortic calcifications were common (67.2%) and related to classical risk factors but not to mineral metabolism parameters. Conclusions: Vitamin D deficiency is more common among female kidney transplant recipients at earlier CKD-T stages, and it contributes to secondary hyperparathyroidism. Prevalent vertebral fractures are only related to high serum PTH levels in female recipients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcen, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amo, Montserrat del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esforzado, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henríquez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomés, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anaya, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Minerva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuberes, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perello, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castelao, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Constantino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Alamillo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belmonte, Amado Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rinne, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Checa, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrero, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayes, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Alex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campistol, Josep María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beneyto, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escuin, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paschoalin, Raphael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, Vicens</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Benoit, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: La relación entre las alteraciones del metabolismo mineral, las fracturas óseas y las calcificaciones vasculares en receptores de un trasplante renal no han sido establecidas. Método: Realizamos un estudio transversal en 727 receptores estables procedentes de 28 centros de trasplante españoles. Se determinaron de manera centralizada los parámetros del metabolismo mineral; también se centralizó la semicuantificación de las fracturas vertebrales y de las calcificaciones de la aorta abdominal. Resultados: La deficiencia de vitamina D (25OHD3 &lt; 15ng/ml) fue más frecuente en mujeres y en los estadios CKD-T I-III (29,6 vs. 44,4%; p=0,003). La relación inversa y significativa observada entre los niveles de 25OHD3 y PTH fue modificada por el género de tal manera que la pendiente fue mayor en las mujeres que en los hombres (p=0,01). Un 15% de los receptores mostró alguna fractura vertebral (VFx) con un grado de deformidad &amp;#8805;2. Los factores relacionados con la VFx diferían en función del género: en los hombres, la edad (OR: 1,04; IC 95%: 1,01-1,06) y el tratamiento con CsA (OR: 3,2; IC 95: 1,6-6,3); en las mujeres la edad (OR: 1,07; IC 95%: 1,03-1,12) y los niveles de PTH (OR per 100pg/ml increase: 1,27; IC 95%: 1,043-1,542). Las calcificaciones de la aorta abdominal fueron comunes (67,2%) y se relacionaron con los factores de riesgo clásicos, pero no con los parámetros del metabolismo mineral. Conclusiones: La deficiencia de vitamina D es más frecuente en las mujeres receptoras de un trasplante renal y en los estadios más tempranos de la CKD-T, y es un factor que contribuye al desarrollo de hiperparatiroidismo secundario. Las VFx prevalentes están relacionadas con unos niveles más elevados de PTH solamente en las mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;36(3): 255-267, mayo-jun. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones del metabolismo mineral, fracturas vertebrales, y calcificaciones aórticas en receptores estables de trasplante renal: papel del género (estudio EMITRAL)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29128^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16519^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54540^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
