<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92392</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and its relation to social skills and leadership evaluated with an evaluation system of the behavior of children and adolescents (BASC)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Numerous studies have documented that children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) show a low social competence. Objective. To compare the symptomatic severity of ADHD, as well as associations to different subtypes, sex and comorbidities, with social functioning (&#147;ability&#148; and&#147;  leadership&#148;) estimated through a Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC) for parents and teachers. Patients and methods. We have retrospectively analyzed 170 patients with ADHD, diagnosed between 2007 and 2010. Social &#147;ability,&#148; &#147;leadership,&#148;&#147;hyperactivity&#148; and &#147;attention-deficit&#148; sections of BASC and cardinal symptoms of ADHD measured through a Spanish scale for de evaluation of DHD (E-DHD) were registered. Results of these variables are analyzed according to the normative data by age and sex, and processed in Z values. Results. The ratings for social skills were significantly lower in patients with conduct disorder or oppositional defiant disorder as informed by parents (p&lt;0.05). Symptomatic intensity of ADHD showed significant (p&lt;0,001) and inverse relation with social &#147;ability&#148; as parents. &#147;Attention-deficit&#148; scores were related with social &#147;ability&#148; and &#147;leadership&#148; as parents and teachers. Conclusions. Intensity of attention deficit was the only variable that showed a significant relation with the social skills and leadership according to the BASC scores, independently of the informer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prados-Parra, Baldomero</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Mayoralas, Daniel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja-Pérez, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Arribas, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz-Borrega, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardos-Véglia, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Savaté, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Jaén, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Jareño, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Numerosos estudios han documentado que los niños con trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) experimentan una baja competencia social. Objetivo. Comparar la intensidad sintomática del TDAH, así como la asociación de los diferentes subtipos, sexo y comorbilidades con el funcionamiento social (&#147;habilidad social&#148; y &#147;liderazgo&#148;) estimado a través de un sistema de evaluación de la conducta de niños y adolescentes para padres y profesores (BASC).Pacientes y métodos. Se analizan retrospectivamente 170 pacientes evaluados con diagnóstico de TDAH entre 2007 y 2010. Se analizan y comparan, entre otros, los datos de habilidades sociales, liderazgo, hiperactividad y déficit de atención del BASC y los síntomas cardinales del TDAH de la escala para la evaluación del déficit de atención con hiperactividad (EDAH). Los resultados de estas variables son analizados acorde a los datos normativos por edad y sexo, y transformados en valores Z. Resultados. Las puntuaciones correspondientes a habilidades sociales fueron significativamente menores en los pacientes con trastorno disocial o negativista según progenitores (p&lt;0,05). En el análisis de la intensidad sintomática del TDAH se observó una relación inversamente significativa (p&lt;0,001) entre la intensidad de la hiperactividad y las habilidades sociales según los padres. La puntuación de déficit de atención se correlacionó de igual forma con las habilidades sociales y liderazgo según padres y profesores. Conclusiones. La intensidad del déficit de atención fue la única variable que, con independencia del informador, se relacionó de forma significativa con las habilidades sociales y el liderazgo según el BASC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(6): 339-348, nov.-dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención/ hiperactividad y su relación con las habilidades sociales y de liderazgo evaluadas a través de un sistema de evaluación de la conducta de niños y adolescentes (BASC)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
