<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-10397</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frontal sinus monostotic fibrous dysplasia with orbital extension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a localized monostotic fibrous dysplasia in the frontal sinus with orbital extension and persistency after the first surgery; it had to be operated again with a fronto-orbitary reconstruction. The fibrous dysplasia is a rare bony alteration with transformation of the healthy bony tissue for a disestructuredone. Its etiology is unknown and can be associated to different syndromes, such as Albright's Disease. Its treatment is surgical, but presents a high percentage of recurrence, this is the xenson why it needs a close follow up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de displasia fibrosa monostótica localizada en el seno frontal con extensión orbitaria y persistencia tras la primera intervención, siendo operado nuevamente con reconstrucción fronto-orbitaria. La displasia fibrosa es una alteración ósea infrecuente con transformación del tejido óseo sano por otro fibro-óseo desestructurado, es de etiologia desconocida y puede asociarse a varios síndromes, entre ellos el síndrome de Albright (sólo en casos de displasia poliostótica). Su tratamiento es quirúrgico aunque presenta altas tasas de recidiva, por lo que su seguimiento debe ser continuado. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(3): 203-206, mar. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia fibrosa monostótica de seno frontal con extensión orbitaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Valladares Molina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gozalbo Navarro, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldasoro Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agut Fuster, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pereira, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-10397</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d10095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5760</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5492^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5492^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
