<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049678</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Odontogenic myxoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Odontogenic myxoma is an uncommontumor of the jaws, benign but locally invasive. It consists ofscarce cells with a spindle or star shape embedded in amyxoid stroma. This tumor is considered to originate fromdental papilla of the developing teeth though there is somecontroversy about its histogenesis. Case presentation: Anodontogenic myxoma from the right lower jaw in a 27-yearold male patient is reported. Microscopically the tumor iscomposed mainly of relatively uniform cells lying in amyxofibroid background. Immunostaining of tumor cellsshows uniform positivity with vimentin and patchy stainingwith muscle specific actin. Cells are negative for keratin,desmin and S-100 protein. The proliferative index (measuredby Ki-67) is very low (lesser than 1%)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kilmurray, Leslie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Esponera, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El mixoma odontogénico es un tumorpoco frecuente de la mandíbula, benigno pero localmenteinvasivo. Se caracteriza por mostrar escasas células de morfologíafusiforme o estrellada con abundante estromamixoide. Aunque la histogénesis es controvertida se creeque se origina a partir de la papila dental en desarrollo.Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de un mixoma odontogénicoafectando el maxilar inferior derecho de un pacientevarón de 27 años de edad. Histológicamente el tumor estabacompuesto fundamentalmente por células de tamaño ymorfología uniformes inmersas en una matriz mixoide. Lastécnicas de inmunohistoquímica utilizadas muestran positividaduniforme con vimentina y parcheada con actina muscularespecífica. Las células son negativas para desmina,proteína S-100 y citoqueratinas. El índice proliferativo(medido con Ki-67) es muy bajo (inferior al 1%)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;39(2): 125-127, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mixoma odontogénico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24273^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
