<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054591</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adult attention-deficit/hiperactivity disorder: descriptive study in a memory unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is the main neurological diagnosis in Chilean children.        Its profile and evolution in adults has not been appropriately studied, despise its personal and social impact. Aim. To describe        the characteristics of adults with ADHD evaluated in a memory unit, verifying the existence of differences depending on        gender. Patients and methods. A demographic and symptomatic evaluation protocol was applied to all patients diagnosed with        ADHD who consulted at the Memory Unit of the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, during the year 2004. Results.        Eighty six patients were included. Average age was 37, being 53% male. Most patients were diagnosed for the first time in        adulthood, corresponding to an ADHD of combined type. The main patients&#146; complaints were forgetfulness and distraction. A        stressing factor capable of worsening the symptoms was identified in 59% of patients. Depression was the principal comorbidity,        with a significantly higher incidence in women. Conclusions. The limitations of ADHD diagnostic criteria available        for adult patients are discussed. Differences depending on gender were analyzed, describing a predominantly disruptive        profile in men and depressive profile in women. There is a clear under-diagnosis of female children with ADHD, with a        potential negative impact on their neuropsychological development. The differential diagnosis with mild cognitive impairment, in        patients complaining of recent memory decline is discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galdames-Contreras, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nervi-Nattero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernhardi, R. von</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oporto-Segura, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Hernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) constituye el diagnóstico neurológico        más frecuente en niños chilenos. Su evolución en el adulto se ha reconocido recientemente y no se ha estudiado suficientemente        en nuestro medio, a pesar de su constatado impacto personal y social. Objetivo. Describir las características de los adultos        diagnosticados como TDAH en una Unidad de Memoria, verificando la existencia de diferencias según sexo. Pacientes y        métodos. Se aplicó una escala de evaluación demográfica y sintomática a todos los pacientes con diagnóstico de TDAH, ingresados        en la Unidad de Memoria de la Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, durante el año 2004. Resultados. Se incluyó        a 86 pacientes. El promedio de edad fue de 37 años, el 53% del sexo masculino. La mayoría de los diagnósticos correspondió        a TDAH de tipo combinado, sin existir diagnóstico previo. Los motivos de consulta principales fueron los problemas de        memoria y distracción. En el 59% de los pacientes se identificó un factor estresante que pudo haber empeorado los síntomas,        favoreciendo la consulta. La comorbilidad principal fue la depresión, con una incidencia significativamente mayor en mujeres.        Conclusiones. Se plantean las limitaciones de los criterios diagnósticos de TDAH en el adulto. Se analizan las diferencias        por sexo, encontrándose en varones un perfil más disruptivo y en mujeres uno más depresivo. Existe un subdiagnóstico evidente        en mujeres con TDAH de la infancia, con un impacto potencial importante en la evolución neuropsicológica de esa        población. Se discute el diagnóstico diferencial con deterioro cognitivo leve, en los pacientes que refieren un deterioro reciente        de la memoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(9): 519-523, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad del adulto: estudio descriptivo en una Unidad de Memoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
