<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121046</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost effectiveness of type 2 Diabetes Mellitus patient care handled by family doctor versus educational strategy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the cost effectiveness of type 2 Diabetes Mellitus patient care handled by family doctor versus educational strategy. Design: Cost effectiveness study. Participants: Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus patients falling into two groups: patients under family doctor and those in educational strategy. Main Surveyed Data: The assessed effectiveness with modification of the biochemical values: glycemia, total cholesterol and triglycerides. The estimated cost in US Dollars is defined by rate of use and unit cost for family medicine services, laboratory, medicines and educational strategy. The analysis included cost effectiveness ratio and projection. Results: The best cost effectiveness ratio for plasma glucose is presented in the educational strategy alternative; for every 100 US$ spent, glucose is reduced 10,42 mg/dl. In family doctor strategy, the reduction is 2,57 mg/dl for the same amount. The trend is similar for cholesterol and triglycerides; the body mass index showed no reduction in either of the alternatives. Conclusions: The best cost effectiveness ratio is found in educational strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vargas-Daza, emma rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Arteaga, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal-Ríos, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galicia-Rodríguez, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el coste-efectividad de la atención del paciente con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 manejado por el médico familiar versus estrategia educativa. Diseño del estudio: Estudio coste-efectividad. Participantes: Pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 integrados en dos grupos: pacientes atendidos por médico familiar y pacientes insertos en una estrategia educativa. Mediciones principales: La efectividad evaluada con la modificación de los valores bioquímicos: glucemia, colesterol total y triglicéridos. El coste estimado en dólares americanos ($US) definido por la intensidad de uso y el coste unitario de los servicios de medicina familiar, laboratorio, medicamentos y la estrategia educativa. El análisis incluyó relación coste-efectividad y proyección. Resultados: La mejor relación coste-efectividad para la glucosa plasmática se presenta en la alternativa estrategia educativa, por cada 100 $US invertidos la glucosa disminuye 10,42 mg/dl; en la estrategia médico familiar por la misma cantidad desciende 2,57 mg/dl. La tendencia es similar para el colesterol y los triglicéridos; el índice de masa corporal no presentó descenso en ninguna de las alternativas. Conclusiones: La mejor relación coste-efectividad se identifica en la estrategia educativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;6(3): 123-130, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-efectividad de la atención del paciente con diabetes mellitus tipo II manejado por el médico familiar versus estrategia educativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
