<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77784</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The «Affect Balance Scale». Its psychometric properties as a tool for measuring positive and negative affect in the spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Along with life satisfaction, affect balance is suggested to be a component of subjective well-being. Affect balance refers to the individual&#146;s emotional responses when doing evaluative judgments on his/her life. Affect balance results from the consideration of both positive and negative emotions experienced over a given period of time. This paper describes the characteristics of the Affect Balance Scale (EBA, a Spanish version of the Positive and Negative Affect scale by Warr et al., 1983) using a sample of Spanish adults. METHOD: Two hundred and nineteen individuals aged 18 to 64 yr (Mean = 30.54, SD = 10.79, 62.1% females) voluntarily participated in the study. Subjects were selected from several community settings. Participants responded in only one measurement 4 measures assessing affect balance, general personal competence, health status and life satisfaction. RESULTS: The EBA showed appropriate psychometric properties -Cronbach&#146;s alphas were 0.82 and 0.75 respectively for the Positive Affect subscale and Negative Affect subscale. Item behavior was also correct, showing their feasibility and relevance for assessing Affect Balance. A two-factor structure was found that fitted the theoretical structure. Nevertheless, two items need to be reformulated. The analysis of the possible relationship between positive and negative affect by means of structural equation modeling supports a close inverse relation between both dimensions of affectivity. The scale also showed a convergent validity with measures of personal global competence, health status and life satisfaction. CONCLUSIONS: Results confirm the utility and appropriateness of the EBA for the assessment of the Affect Balance in the Spanish population. Furthermore, the EBA can be considered a suitable tool for the study of Subjective Well-Being (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy Izquierdo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Balance Afectivo se ha propuesto como uno de los componentes, junto con la Satisfacción Vital, del Bienestar Subjetivo. El Balance Afectivo se refiere a las respuestas emocionales de la persona cuando hace juicios valorativos sobre su vida, y es el resultado de la consideración de las emociones tanto positivas como negativas experimentadas a lo largo de un período de tiempo determinado. Este estudio presenta las características de la Escala de Balance Afectivo (EBA) (versión española de la escala de Afecto Positivo y Negativo de Warr et al., 1983) en una muestra española adulta obtenida de la población general. METODOLOGÍA: Participaron voluntariamente en este estudio 219 personas con edades comprendidas entre los 18 y 64 años (M= 30.54; dt= 10.79; 62.1% mujeres) procedentes de diferentes contextos comunitarios. Los participantes respondieron 4 medidas sobre balance afectivo, competencia personal inespecífica, salud general y satisfacción vital en una única administración. RESULTADOS: Respecto a las propiedades psicométricas de la EBA, las subescalas de Afecto Positivo y Afecto Negativo muestran una elevada consistencia interna, con valores de alfa de Cronbach de 0.82 y 0.75 respectivamente. Sus elementos muestran un adecuado comportamiento que refleja su pertinencia y relevancia para la medida del Balance Afectivo. La estructura factorial arroja un modelo bifactorial perfectamente ajustado a la propuesta teórica. No obstante, dos ítems necesitarían ser reformulados. El análisis de la posible relación entre el afecto positivo y el afecto negativo realizado utilizando un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales apoya la estrecha relación inversa entre ambas dimensiones de la afectividad. La escala muestra una adecuada validez convergente con medidas de competencia personal inespecífica o global, de salud física y mental y de satisfacción vital. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;19(2): 157-189, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La «Escala de Balance Afectivo». Propiedades psicométricas de un instrumento para la medida del afecto positivo y negativo en población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
