<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153656</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish validation of the Nursing Observed Illness Intensity Scale in psychiatric units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The reviews of recent literature reveal that there is no really useful scale to monitor patient condition. However, the English version of the Nursing Observed Illness Intensity Scale (NOIIS) has demonstrated to be an objective and quick evaluation of patient status in psychiatric inpatients units. In this context, our aim is demonstrate the usefulness, reliability, and validity of Spanish version of the NOIIS in mental health units. Methods. After the translation and re-translation of NOIIS, 34 patients completed it. To evaluate the reliability, the scale was administered by two professionals. To control the validity data were obtained from other psycho-pathological scales (BPRS, pathological dimensional scale DSM-5, ICG scale, and the social functioning scale SIX). Results. The Cronbach Alpha reliability showed higher values of 0.89 by item, and 98% for total scored. We found a 70% Pearson correlation between NOIIS and BPRS (P = .00), and to a lesser extent between NOIIS and ICG and with the DSM-5 pathological dimensional scale. In addition, we observed a negative correlation between the NOIIS and SIX scale. Conclusion. Even though our sample was small, the results show that the Spanish version of the NOIIS is applicable in the hospital setting. Furthermore, it has also demonstrated its reliability between raters, and the validity compared to other scales used in mental health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bowers, Len</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musallam, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervilla, Jorge A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La revisión de la investigación existente evidencia las deficiencias en la oferta de instrumentos útiles para controlar el estado de pacientes psiquiátricos institucionalizados. Sin embargo, la escala Nursing Observation Illness Intensity Scale (NOIIS) en inglés ha demostrado evaluar de manera objetiva y rápida el estado de los pacientes en unidades de hospitalización psiquiátrica. En este contexto, nuestro principal objetivo es demostrar la utilidad, así como la fiabilidad y la validez, de la escala NOIIS en español. Método. Tras la traducción y retrotraducción de la escala NOIIS, esta se administró a una muestra de 34 pacientes. Para evaluar la fiabilidad, la escala fue administrada por 2 profesionales, y para controlar su validez se recogieron datos de otras escalas psicopatológicas (BPRS, la escala de dimensiones psicopatológicas DSM-5, la escala ICG y la escala de funcionamiento social SIX). Resultados. El coeficiente alpha de Cronbach mostró valores superiores a 0,89 por ítem, y una fiabilidad del 98% para la puntuación total de la escala. La correlación de Pearson entre la NOIIS y la escala BPRS fue de 70% (p = 0,00). Además, se observó una correlación negativa entre la NOIIS y la SIX. Con la ICG y la escala de dimensiones psicopatológicas DSM-5 también se encontró correlación, aunque inferior a la BPRS. Conclusión. A pesar de que la muestra fue pequeña, los resultados muestran que la versión en español de la NOIIS es aplicable en el medio hospitalario. Asimismo, se demuestra la fiabilidad entre jueces y la validez con respecto a otras escalas de uso en enfermería en salud mental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);23(2): 54-59, mayo-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación española de la Escala de Observación Enfermera de la Intensidad Sintomática en unidades de hospitalización psiquiátrica (NOIIS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
