<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154261</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Imaging diagnosis in Focal Therapy for prostate cancer: Multiparametric Magnetic Resonance Imaging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of prostatic multiparametric MRI (mpMRI) has increased significantly over the last years, and has emerged as a crucial test for diagnosis, staging and treatment of prostate cancer (PCa). The use of the various available sequences (T2W, T1W, diffusion, perfusion and spectroscopy), as well as the different parameters they associate, not only enables to determine the group of patients subsidiary of focal ablative therapy, but also to perform a proper determination of the áreas to treat, as well as to monitor the development of therapy and to evaluate both oncological results and possible therapeutic failures. Despite the excellent results showed in the different studies, it is necessary to reach a consensus about its use on the different features associated with focal therapy, since it is a technique that requires not only large experience in its operation but also standardization. All this make it a complex technique and not free of difficulties in its interpretation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lista Mateos, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Gallo, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de la imagen por Resonancia magnética multiparamétrica (RMmp) de próstata ha aumentado de forma significativa en los últimos años, y ha emergido como una prueba crucial en el diagnóstico, estadiaje y tratamiento del cáncer de próstata (CaP). El empleo de las distintas secuencias disponibles (T2W, T1W, difusión, perfusión y espectroscopia), así como de los diferentes parámetros que asocian, permiten no sólo determinar el grupo de pacientes subsidiarios de terapias ablativas focales, sino realizar una correcta determinación de las áreas a tratar, así como monitorizar el desarrollo de la terapia, y evaluar tanto los resultados oncológicos como los posibles fallos terapeúticos. A pesar de los excelentes resultados mostrados en los distintos estudios, es preciso alcanzar un consenso sobre su utilización en los distintos aspectos asociados al tratamiento focal, dado que es una técnica que requiere no sólo amplia experiencia en su manejo sino que precisa de una estandarización, que en el momento actual la convierten en una técnica compleja y no exenta de dificultad en su interpretación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;69(6): 291-301, jul.-ago. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154261</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modalidades de imágen en Terapia Focal: Ecografía Multiparamétrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26352^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30992^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
