<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120684</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical study of naturactis dental implants postextraction dental procedures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Dental implants places in dental fresh sockets, have a variable success according to different authors, between 92,7% and 98%. Its principle indication is to substitute teeth admitting dental extraction. Its principle advantage is a shorter time of treatment up to loading of the prosthesis, also it avoids a second surgery and improves the healing process. As an inconvenient we remark, the need for guided tissue regeneration. Material and method: 60 dental implants (Naturactis from Euroteknika Groupe, Sallanches &#150; Francia) were placed immediate after dental extraction with a clinical protocol. 33 patients were included in this study, based on some inclusion criterias. We analyzed clinical aspects like (age, gender, toxic habits), surgical aspects (insertion torque, periodontal evaluation, ostell stability measure), radiology (crestal alveolar resorption). All these cases were analyzed during 10 months. Mucoperiostical flaps were avioded in all cases. Results: All dental implants placed, achieved at least 35 NM after placed, as well a &gt;63 ISQ measured with Ostell. The surgical protocol was approved by surgeons. 4 of all the implants placed failed in the early stages (&lt;1 month). We verify no crestal bone loss in the first 6 months after the implants were placed. Healing and post surgical procedures were correct without any complication described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Font, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones-Ilundain, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ripollés de Ramón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones-Ilundain, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los implantes inmediatos postextracción tienen un éxito variable según diferentes autores entre un 92,7% y 98,0%. Su principal indicación es la sustitución de dientes susceptibles de extracción. Su ventaja principal es la de acortar el tiempo de tratamiento rehabilitador y evitar una segunda cirugía. Como inconveniente destaca el requerir, generalmente, técnicas de regeneración tisular guiada. Material y método: 60 implantes Naturactis de Euroteknika (Euroteknika Groupe, Sallanches &#150; Francia) fueron colocados de forma inmediata postextracción siguiendo un protocolo clínico de actuación. 33 pacientes fueron incluidos en este estudio en base a unos criterios de inclusión. Se analizaron variables clínicas (edad, sexo y hábitos tóxicos), quirúrgicos (torque de inserción, evaluación periodontal, estabilidad con Ostell) radiológicos (pérdida ósea crestal). Todos ellos fueron analizados 10 meses vista. Se evitaron las descargas mucoperiósticas en todos los casos. Resultados: Los implantes colocados obtuvieron un torque de inserción &gt;35 Nm tras su colocación así como unos valores &gt;63 ISQ de Ostell. El protocolo quirúrgico fue satisfactorio por los operadores. 4 implantes del total fracasaron de forma temprana (&lt;1 mes). Se constató ausencia de pérdida ósea crestal en los primeros 6 meses de su colocación. La cicatrización y postoperatorio fue satisfactoria con ausencia de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;25(3): 135-142, dic. 2013. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120684</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico de los implantes dentales Naturactis en postextracción dental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38811^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
