<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036414</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gait analysis in Parkinson&#146;s disease and response to dopaminergic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: The objective of this study was to analyze the gait abnormalities in patients with idiopathic Parkinson&#146;s disease(PD), and their response to dopaminergic treatment. PATIENTS AND METHOD: 15 patients and 15 healthyage-matched subjects were included for comparison between pathologic and «normal» gait, and 24 PD patients were included to assess the effects of treatment. Gait analysis was achieved with a new 3D-photogramme try system. RESULTS: Patients had significative lower velocity, stride length, step length and hip and knee ranges when compared with control subjects. There were no differences in cadence, step width and relative times of gait-cycle. There were no differences in the patients&#146; gait variables after administration of a dopaminergic medication. CONCLUSIONS: Gait analysis allows quantification of gait disturbances in patients with PD and the potential effects of treatment. The results of this study suggest a certain degree of«levodopa-resistance» in gait in these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Izco, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poza Aldea, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Massó, José Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Munáin, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: Analizar objetivamente las alteraciones de la marcha en pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson (EP)y los cambios observados tras la administración de medicación dopaminérgica. PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se incluyó a 15 pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson para la comparación de la marcha con un grupo de 15 individuos sanos de la misma edad y a24 pacientes para la comparación antes y después de la administración de la medicación. Se realizó el análisis con un nuevosistema de fotogrametría tridimensional. RESULTADOS: Los pacientes presentaron de forma significativa una menor velocidad, longitud de zancada, de paso y menores amplitudes articulares de cadera y rodillaque el grupo control, sin diferencias en la cadencia, base de sustentación ni en los tiempos relativos del ciclo de la marcha. No se encontraron diferencias significativasen la comparación de la marcha antes y después de la administración de la medicación dopaminérgica. CONCLUSIONES: El análisis de la marcha permite cuantificar las alteraciones de la marcha en pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson y el potencial efecto de intervenciones terapéuticas. Los resultados indican un cierto grado de resistencia a la levodopa en la marcha de estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(2): 50-52, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la marcha en la enfermedad de Parkinson y su respuesta al tratamiento dopaminérgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5823^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
