<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61879</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the clinical results and the nursing workloads and costs of opportunist screening in a Breast Diagnostic Imaging Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this work is to analyse the diagnostic impact and nursing workloads and costs of opportunist screening (OS). After analyzing the diagnostic impact and nursing workloads and costs of opportunist screening (OS). After analyzing the activity carried out between 2003 and 2006, a high volume of activity and consumption of resources is observed. It thus concludes that it is necessary to reduce the nursing workloads and costs encouraging the participation in Programmes and introducing management strategies to reduce costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Tabanera, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baroja Mazo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gómez, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lag Asturiano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz Miranda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Miravete, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar el impacto diagnóstico y la carga asistencial del screening oportunista (SO). Se analizó la actividad  desarrollada entre 2003 y 2006. Se estudiaron 24.317 pacientes (9.487 remitidas como SO) y se realizaron44.269 mamografías en el Programa Poblacional. El SO supuso el 42% de la demanda, 39% de pacientes, 33,69% de estudios y 22,32% de costes. El coste/carcinoma fue 964 URVs, frente a 461,16 URVs en Programa y 195,64 URVs en sintomáticas. El SO supone un alto volumen de actividad y consumo de recursos. Es necesario reducir la carga asistencial promoviendo la participación en Programas e introduciendo estrategias de gestión para reducir costes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(235): 175-184, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los resultados clínicos y la carga asistencial del screening oportunista en una Unidad de Diagnóstico por la Imagen de la Mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16648^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
