<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132781</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the efficacy and safety of a preparation based on hops, echinacea, burdock and vitamin E in the oral treatment of mild to moderate acne</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A  longitudinal,  prospective,  open-label  study  was performed in  order  to  evaluate  the  efficacy  and safety of a preparation of extracts of hop strobile, echinacea root, burdock root and vitamin E (AsepxiaTM) in the oral treatment (8 weeks) of mild to moderate acne. 548 patients completed the study, showing a reduction average of 17 acne lesions (mean: 30,3  initial  lesions  versus  13  final  lesions).  The reduction of inflammatory lesions was, in average, 20,9% for papules and 35,7% for pustules, while the reduction of non-inflammatory lesions was 41% for open comedones and 43,4% for closed comedones.  Adverse  reactions  during  the  study  were shown by 1,8% of the patients, but only 1,3% were considered related to the preparation. All of them were mild reactions. The response to the treatment was evaluated as positive in the 92% of the cases by physicians and in 91% by patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, Eduardo A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realizó un estudio abierto, prospectivo y longitudinal que evaluó la eficacia y seguridad de un preparado a base de extractos de estróbilo de lúpulo, raíz de equinácea, raíz de bardana y vitamina E (Asepxia®), administrado por vía oral durante 8 semanas, en el tratamiento del acné leve o moderado. Completaron  el  estudio  548  pacientes,  observándose una disminución promedio de 17 lesiones (media de 30,3 lesiones iniciales frente a 13 lesiones finales). La disminución media de lesiones inflamatorias fue de 20,9% para las pápulas y 35,7% para las pústulas; en lesiones no inflamatorias, fue de 41% en comedones abiertos y 43,4% en comedones cerrados. El 1,8% de los pacientes presentó alguna reacción adversa durante el estudio, aunque solamente 1,3% se consideraron relacionadas con el preparado. Todas las reacciones adversas fueron clasificadas  como  leves.  El  porcentaje  de  casos evaluados como respuesta positiva fue del 92% por parte de los médicos y del 91% por parte de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;8(2): 149-158, jul.-dic. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la eficacia y seguridad de un preparado a base de lúpulo, equinácea, bardana y vitamina Een el tratamiento oral del acné leve a moderado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35735^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35735^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30958^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30958^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30958^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26462^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26804^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36695</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
