<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135348</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of anti-streptococcal, anti-enolase, and anti-neural antibodies in subjects with earlyonset psychiatric disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Infection with group A Streptococcus (Strep A) can cause post-infectious sequelae, including a spectrum of childhood-onset obsessive-compulsive (OCD) and tic disorders with autoimmune origin (PANDAS, Pediatric Autoimmune Neuropsychiatric Disorders Associated with Streptococcal Infections). Until now, no single immunological test has been designed that unequivocally diagnoses these disorders. In this study, we assessed the detection of serum antibodies against human brain enolase (AE), neural tissue (AN) and Streptococcus (AS) as a laboratory tool for the diagnosis of early-onset psychiatric disorders. Methodology. Serum antibodies against human brain enolase, total brain proteins, and total proteins from StrepA were detected by ELISA in 37 patients with a presumptive diagnosis of PANDAS and in 12 healthy subjects from Mexico and Cuba. Results. The antibody titers against human brain enolase (AE) and Streptococcal proteins (AS) were higher in patients than in control subjects (t-student, tAE=-2.17, P=0.035; tAS=-2.68, P=0.01, n=12 and 37/group, df=47, significance level 0.05), while the neural antibody titers did not differ between the two groups (P(t)=0.05). The number of subjects (titers&gt; mean control + CI95) with simultaneous seropositivity to all three antibodies was higher in the patient group (51.4%) than in the control group (8.3%) group (X2 =5.27, P=0.022, df=1, n=49). Conclusions. The simultaneous detection of all three of these antibodies could provide valuable information for the etiologic diagnosis of individuals with early-onset obsessive compulsive disorders associated with streptococcal infection and, consequently, for prescribing suitable therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López , Yaumara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riverón, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Casamichana, Mavil</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bobes, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Lázaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente-Sandoval, Camilo De la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Canovas, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Niubo, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanzagorta, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolini, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manrique, Viana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Genis-Mendoza , Alma D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La infección por Estreptococo del grupo A puede ocasionar secuelas post-infecciosas entre las que se han reportado un espectro de trastornos obsesivos-compulsivos y tics de aparición en la edad pediátrica y origen autoinmune (PANDAS). No ha sido diseñada una prueba inmunológica que permita diagnosticar inequívocamente estos trastornos. En este trabajo se evaluó la detección en suero de anticuerpos contra Enolasa cerebral humana (AE), tejido neural (AN) y Estreptococo (AS) como herramienta de laboratorio para el diagnóstico de trastornos psiquiátricos de inicio temprano. Metodología. Los anticuerpos séricos contra Enolasa cerebral humana, proteínas totales del Estreptococo y proteínas totales cerebrales fueron detectados mediante la metodología de ELISA en 37 individuos con diagnóstico presuntivo de PANDAS y en 12 sujetos sanos de México y Cuba. Resultados. Los títulos de anticuerpos contra AE y AS fueron más elevados en el grupo de pacientes vs controles (t-student, tAE=-2.17, P=0.035; tAS=-2.68, P=0.01, n=12 y 37/grupo, gl=47, nivel de significación de 0.05), mientras que los títulos de anticuerpos AN no difirieron entre ambos grupos (P(t)=0.05). La seropositividad (títulos &gt; mediacontrol + IC95) simultánea a los tres anticuerpos fue mayor (51.4 %) en los individuos del grupo de los pacientes comparado con los controles (8.3%) (X2 =5.27, P=0.022, gl=1, n=49). Conclusiones. La detección simultánea de los tres anticuerpos séricos podría brindar información útil para el diagnóstico etiológico de los individuos con trastorno obsesivo compulsivo de inicio temprano asociados con la infección por Estreptococo y en consecuencia para indicar una terapéutica adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;43(2): 35-41, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135348</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de anticuerpos antiestreptococos, anti-enolasa y antineurales en sujetos con trastornos psiquiátricos de inicio temprano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d916^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10944</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10944^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
