<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145781</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pauci-inmune glomerulonephritis in a 68 years old man</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 68 years old male with macroscopic hematuria and constitutional symptoms as fever and weith loss. Without anything interesting in the anamnesis neither in the phisical exploration. In the laboratory test had an elevation of creatinine of 4 mg/dL and ten days before it was of 1,4 mg/dL. In the urine analyisis: proteinuria of 1,5 G/24 h, and hematuria. At the second day we made a renal biopsy where we could seen segmental glomerular necrosis and crescent fromation in 80% of the glomeruli. In the inmune study c-ANCA anti-PR3 was positive. In the complementary studies we didn&#146;t find others organs affected. With the diagnosis of pauci-inmune glomerulonephritis limited to the kidney we began treatment with corticosteroids and cyclophospahmide. As the renal funtion was severy affected the patient need one dialyisis sesion. We began with l g intravenous methylprednisolone daily for 3 days followed by oral prednisone 60 mg daily tapering to 10 mg daily by 3 months. This was combined with 150 mg oral cyclophosphamide daily. Seven plasma exchanges were performed. At the begining of treatment creatinine was 7 mg/dL, it was decreasing rapidily and three week after cretinine was 3 mg/DI and he was asymptomatic. One year after treatment, creatinine is 1,4 mgldL and the urine analysis is normal, C-ANCA are negative (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acevedo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varón de 68 años sin antecedentes de interés, que acude a urgencias por cuadro de hematuria macroscópica de diez días de evolución. El cuadro se acompañaba de malestar general y febrícula. La exploración física fue anodina y en las pruebas complementarias destacaba una elevación de la velocidad de sedimentación, hematuria y proteinuria en rango no nefrótico; creatinina de 4 mg/dl (creatinina de diez días antes de 1,5 mg/dl). Se realizó estudio inmunológico donde destacó: c-ANCA positivo con especificidad antiproteinasa-3. Tras la realización de las exploraciones oportunas se descartó afectación extrarrenal. Se realizó biopsia renal en la que se objetivo proliferación extracapilar con semilunas en el 80% de los glomérulos. Inmunofluorescencia negativa. La función renal fue empeorando hasta alcanzar una creatinina de 7 mg/dL, requiriendo una sesión de hemodiálisis, y con el diagnóstico de glomerulonefritis extracapilar pauci-inmune idiopática también llamada «vasculitis renal» se comenzó tratamiento con bolos de metilprednisolona, ciclofosfamida oral y plasmaféresis. La función renal mejoró rápidamente siendo la creatinina a los veinte días de comienzo del tratamiento de 2 mg/dL. Al año y medio de tratamiento la creatinina es de 1,4 mg/dL, el sedimento de orina es normal y los ANCAs negativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;24(supl.3): 101-104, 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glomerulonefritis rápidamente progresiva en varón de 68 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33077^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23025^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1330^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15059^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15059^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
