<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66157</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary or spontaneous pneumomediastinum is an uncommondisease. However, in the pediatric age, it is frequently associated with asthma and above all with complication of a first asthmatic episode. Usually it is found as a casual diagnosis, although when there are symptoms, these may be quite different, the most frequent being chest pain and dyspnea. The diagnosis suspicion is often made on palpating subcutaneous cervical emphysema, although the diagnostic certainty is obtained from the chest x-ray. It has a benign course and is resolved quickly after symptomatic treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tazón Varela, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Herrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Mier, L. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Vega, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El neumomediastino espontáneo o primario es una entidad poco frecuente, pero que en edad pediátrica se asocia con asiduidad a asma y sobre todo como complicación de una primera crisis asmática. La mayoría de veces se trata de un diagnóstico casual, aunque en caso de producir síntomas, éstos pueden ser muy variados, siendo los más frecuentes el dolor torácico y la disnea. El diagnóstico de sospecha se realiza en muchas ocasiones al palpar enfisema subcutáneo de localización cervical, aunque es la radiografía de tórax el diagnóstico de certeza. El curso es benigno y se resuelve con celeridad tras tratamiento sintomático</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(5): 249-252, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66157</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d33351^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13610^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
