<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153352</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of a tool to assess motor coordination in Primary</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Motor coordination is a complex evolutionary process which is gradually acquired. The optimum age for the achievement of these coordination processes is between 6 and 11 years old (Primary Education). The aim of this study is to design and validate a tool which will allow assessing the motor coordination level of the students. Method: Subjects and Sample. Students from Primary Education public schools. &#145;Convenience&#146; sampling, with a total of 2512 subjects. Tool: Qualitative observation test and objective evaluation of the implementation of the abilities developed in 7 tasks. Results: Reliability: Internal Consistency (Cronbach Alpha 0.827), test-retest reliability (correlation coefficient; 0.99) and inter-observer agreement (correlation coefficient; 0.95). Validity has been verified by the experts&#146; intuitive perception, issuing a largely favourable opinion. Conclusion: The 3JS test is a reliable, valid and effective tool for measuring the motor coordination development in students between 6 and 12 years old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Hurtado, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Truan, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenizo Benjumea, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravelo Afonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morilla Pineda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La coordinación motriz es un proceso evolutivo complejo de adquisición progresiva. La edad óptima para la adquisición de esos procesos coordinativos es de 6 a 11 años (Educación Primaria). El objetivo del presente estudio es diseñar y validar un instrumento que permita evaluar el nivel de coordinación motriz del alumnado. Método: Los sujetos son alumnado de Primaria en centros públicos. Muestreo por conveniencia, con una muestra total de 2512 sujetos. Instrumento: Test cualitativo de observación y evaluación objetiva de la ejecución de la habilidad desarrollada en 7 tareas. Resultados: La Consistencia interna (Alfa de Cronbach 0.827), estabilidad temporal (coeficiente correlación: 0.99) y concordancia inter-observadores (coeficiente correlación: 0.95). La validez se comprobó mediante la opinión intuitiva de expertos, siendo la opinión mayoritariamente favorable. Conclusión: El test 3JS es un instrumento fiable, válido y eficaz para medir el desarrollo de la coordinación motriz en el alumnado de 6 a 12 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;16(62): 203-219, jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153352</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de instrumento para evaluar coordinación motriz en Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
