<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162951</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We present a case of family aggregation of severe pneumonia with Streptococcus pneumoniae isolation in wife.  Case 1. A 54 year old man was admited on July 27 for chest pain and fever. The chest radiograph LID consolidation. Microbiology: Streptococcus pneumoniae urinary antigens and Legionella pneumophila serogroup 1: negative. Negative blood cultures and sputum culture. A few hours later he was transferred to intensive care from septic shock. It was established antibiotic therapy with levofloxacin and ceftriaxone. He had persistent fever despite antibiotic, which improved after administration of vancomycin. Favorable clinical evolution.  Case 2. 50 year old woman, wife of case 1, consulting on July 31 with fever and cough. The Rx chest bilateral basal alveolar condensation, small right pleural effusion. Microbiology: positive urine pneumococcus antigen, was isolated Streptococcus pneumoniae serotype 1 in blood cultures. Thoracentesis pleural exudate with pH 7.46, negative culture. He presented hypotension, oliguria, severe sepsis, and ICU admission the day of admission. Initially it treated with ceftriaxone and azithromycin. By persistent fever, later with levofloxacin and vancomycin, with recovery.  Conclusions: We present a family outbreak of severe pneumonia with pneumococcal serotype 1 isolation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llopis Pastor, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión Valero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borras Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briones Urtiaga, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Ortega, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Presentamos una agregación intrafamiliar de neumonía grave, con aislamiento de Streptococcus pneumoniae en la esposa.  Caso 1. Hombre de 54 años, ingresa el 27 de julio por dolor torácico y fiebre. Radiografía de tórax consolidación LID. Microbiología: antígenos urinarios negativos. Hemocultivos y cultivo de esputo negativos. A las pocas horas es trasladado a Cuidados Intensivos por shock séptico. Se instauró levofloxacino y ceftriaxona. Fiebre persistente, que mejoró tras la administración de vancomicina. Evolución favorable.  Caso 2. Mujer de 50 años, esposa del caso 1, consulta el 31 de julio por fiebre y tos. Rx tórax condensación alveolar basal bilateral, pequeño derrame pleural derecho. Microbiología: antígeno neumococo en orina positivo, Streptococcus pneumoniae serotipo 1 en los hemocultivos. Toracocentesis exudado pleural con pH 7,46, cultivo negativo. Presentó hipotensión, oliguria, sepsis grave, e ingreso en UCI el mismo día del ingreso. Inicialmente se trata con ceftriaxona y azitromicina. Por persistencia de la fiebre, posteriormente con levofloxacino y vancomicina, con recuperación.  Conclusiones: Presentamos un brote familiar de neumonía grave con aislamiento de neumococo serotipo 1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;20(1): 26-29, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía familiar grave con aislamiento de Streptococcus pneumoniae</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
