<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114306</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A mutation in gene SOS1 causes a classic Phenotype in Noonan Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Noon syndrome (NS) (OMIM 16350) is an autosomal dominant genetic syndrome echaracterized by a dysmorphic phenotype (with similarities to Turner syndrome), short stature and congenital heart disease. Its prevalence is estimated in 1/1000 y 1/2500 live newborns. Common physical findings include a distinctive facial appearance with ptosis, ocular hypertelorism, downslanting palpebral fissures and low set ears. Other frequent manifestations include short stature pectus excavatum, psychomotor/mental delay, congenital heart disease and cryptorchidism in males. Currently, four genes are associated to NS: PTPN11, KRAS, SOS1 y RAF1, and all of them codify proteins involved in the Ras/MAPK signaling pathway (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puisac Uriol, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribate Molina, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnedo Muñoz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Noonan (SN) (OMIM 16395950) es un trastorno genético autosómico dominante caracterizado por un fenotipo dismórfico (similar al síndrome de Turner), talla baja y cardiopatía congénita. La incidencia del SN se estima entre 1/1000 y 1/2500 de recién nacidos vivos. El fenotipo se caracteriza por unos rasgos faciales peculiares que incluyen ptosis palpebral, hipertelorismo ocular, fisuras palpebrales inclinadas hacia abajo, y orejas de implantación baja. Otros hallazgos frecuentes son talla baja, pectus excavatum retraso mental de grado variable, defectos cardíacos y criptorquidia en varones. En la actualidad existen 4 genes relacionados con el SN, PTPN11, KRAS, SOS1, y RAF1, Y todos ellos codifican proteínas que participan en la vía de señalización Ras/MAPK (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;49(2): 55-57, sept. 2009. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una mutación en el gen SOS1 causa un Fenotipo clásico en el Síndrome de Noonan</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34449^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9821^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32751</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34468^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
