<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052884</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Craniopharyngioma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 19-years-old man developed a rapid decreased and blurred vision together with a left incongruos homonimus hemiapnopia. Visual field defects suggested a chiasmal lesion and we considered necessary additional neuroradiological investigation. Magnetic resonance imaging of the brain showed a located cranipharyngioma in the suprasellas region that produced a mass effect with compression of the chiasma. The patient has neurosurgical resection one week later and a complete restoration of visual function followed its removal. The probability of visual recovery in tumor-related optic neurophaties is usually correlated with the severity and duration of the optic pathway compromise. The combination of a slowly progressive disminution of vision with optic disc oedema on the side of field loss implicates compression of the optic nerve at its junction with the chiasm</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solanas Álava, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Barreras, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chacón Vallés, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abarzuza Cortaire, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Marco, Nelson Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristóbal Bescós, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un varón de 19 años desarrolló una rápida disminución de visión y borrosidad junto con una hemianopsia homónima izquierda incongruente. Las lesiones en el campo visual sugirieron una lesión quiasmática y consideramos necesaria una investigación neuroradiológica adicional. La imagen de la resonancia magnética mostró un craneofaringioma localizado en la región supraselar que producía efecto masa con compresión del quiasma. El paciente fue sometido a una extirpación quirúrgica una semana después consiguiendo una completa recuperación de la función visual. La probabilidad de recuperación visual en las neuropatías ópticas asociadas con tumores está generalmente relacionada con la severidad y duración de la afectación de la vía óptica. La combinación de una lenta y progresiva disminución de visión con un edema de papila en el lado de la pérdida de campo visual implica compresión del nervio óptico en la unión con el quiasma</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;46(1): 38-41, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052884</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Craneofaringioma. Diagnóstico en la consulta de Oftalmología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34346^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34346^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28067^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34346^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3413^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28067^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3413^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15186</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
