<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143772</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of prevalence and association between asthma symptoms and obesity in the pediatric population of Pamplona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The objective of this study is to determine the prevalence of asthma symptoms and overweight-obese in children aged 6-7years and adolescents aged 13-14 years within the metropolitan area of Pamplona, and analyse the risk of asthma within the age groups and the influences if sex on this relationship Methods: The study is based on data of asthma symptoms and body mass index of 4,413 children and adolescents obtained from the International Study of Asthma and Allergies phase III questionnaire. Unconditional logistic regression was used to obtain adjusted odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) for overweight-obesity and asthma symptoms in both groups, taking as reference the group of normal weight. Afterwards, it was stratified by sex. Results: The prevalence of overweight-obesity in the group aged 6-7 years was 23.9% and in the group of teenagers was 11.5%. The prevalence of asthma symptoms in both age groups was lower than the Spanish average. The obese children aged 6-7 years had a higher risk of asthma symptoms. When it was stratified by sex, an increased risk in all asthma symptoms was observed only in obese girls. No relationship between obesity and asthma was observed n the adolescents group. Conclusions: Obesity in children is related to asthma symptoms. Obese girls have an increased risk and more severe asthma symptoms than boys (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Azcona San Julián, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Fernández, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillen Grima, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Zallo, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguinaga-Ontoso, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Monzó, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermoso-de-Mendoza-Cantón, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo de este estudio es determinar la prevalencia de síntomas de asma y de sobrepeso-obesidad de niños de 6-7años y adolescentes de 13-14 años del área metropolitana de Pamplona, así como analizar si los niños-adolescentes con sobrepeso u obesidad presentan un mayor riesgo de padecer asma y si el sexo modifica esta relación. Métodos: Los datos de síntomas de asma e índice de masa corporal (IMC) de 4.413 niños y adolescentes se obtuvieron del cuestionario International Study of Allergies and Asthma fase III. Se realizó regresión logística no condicional para obtener las odds ratios ajustadas (OR) y los intervalos de confianza del 95% (IC del 95 %) para sobrepeso-obesidad y síntomas de asma en ambos grupos, tomando como referencia el grupo de normopeso. Posteriormente se estratifico por sexo. Resultados: la prevalencia de sobrepeso-obesidad en el grupo de 6-7 años fue de 23,9% y en el grupo de adolescentes de 11,5%. La prevalencia de síntomas de asma en ambos grupos de edad fue inferior a la media española. Los niños de 6-7 años obesos presentaron mayor riesgo de síntomas de asma. Al estratificar por sexo, se observó un aumento de riesgo en todos los síntomas de asma solo en niñas obesas. En el grupo de adolescentes no se observó relación entre obesidad y asma. Conclusiones: La obesidad en niños está relacionada con los síntomas de asma. Las niñas obesas presentan un mayor riesgo y mayor gravedad de síntomas de asma que los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(3): 519-525, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de prevalencia y asociación entre síntomas de asma y obesidad en la población pediátrica de Pamplona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
