<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101592</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient selection for less Urological surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Laparoendoscopic single-site surgery (LESS) should theoretically improve perioperative results and cosmesis minimizing skin incision. LESS surgery is technically demanding and the result of any procedure depends on the surgeon skill and experience, on the condition to be treated and finally on careful patient selection. As cosmesis is the main advantage over standard laparoscopy, LESS is particularly indicated in young patients with low BMI. While at the beginning LESS surgery was limited to demolitive procedures, increasing experience lead to widen indications to reconstructive and more challenging conditions. New technologies and robotics may increase LESS indications in the next future(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sio, Marco de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Damiano, Rocco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rane, Abhay</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quattrone, Carmelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tanabalan, Chandaran</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Cirugía laparoscópica por puerto único (LESS) debería teóricamente mejorar los resultados perioperatorios y cosméticos minimizando la incisión cutanea. La cirugía LESS es técnicamente demandante y el resultado de cualquier procedimiento depende de la habilidad y la experiencia del cirujano, de la enfermedad que se ha de tratar y finalmente de una cuidadosa selección del paciente. Siendo la cosmética la principal ventaja sobre la laparoscopia convencional estándar, la cirugía LESS está particularmente indicada en pacientes jóvenes con índice de masa corporal bajo. Mientras que al principio la cirugía LESS estaba limitada a procedimientos de extirpación, el aumento de la experiencia ha llevado a que se amplíen las indicaciones a cirugía reconstructiva y otras situaciones más desafiantes. Las nuevas tecnologías y la robótica pueden incrementar las indicaciones de LESS en un futuro próximo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(3): 280-284, abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección del paciente para cirugía urológica por puerto único (LESS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
