<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116681</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstructive Inflammatory Tracheal Pseudomembrane</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pathologies acquired after the establishment of an artificial airway include stenosis, granulomas and the formation of pseudomembranes, to name a few. The most common form of presentation in adults is circumferential stenosis, which often requires therapeutic endoscopic measures to achieve resolution. This Case Report describes the case of an obstructive inflammatory tracheal pseudomembrane secondary to repeated intubations that was resolved with conservative treatment. The clinical presentation of this entity generally includes the appearance of respiratory infection and/or atelectasis after the withdrawal of the orotracheal tube as a consequence of the accumulation of secretions between the tracheal wall and the pseudomembrane. Inflammatory pseudomembranes can resolve spontaneously with the help of glucocorticoids, although on occasion they require an invasive endotracheal procedure depending on the evolution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Lessmann, Astrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrego-Fernández, Alfons</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de las patologías adquiridas tras la instauración de una vía aérea artificial figuran las estenosis, los granulomas, la presencia de pseudomembranas y la formación de tabiques traqueales, entre otros. La forma más habitual de presentación en el adulto es la estenosis circunferencial, y para su resolución muchas veces requiere medidas endoscópicas terapéuticas. En esta Nota clínica se describe el caso de una pseudomembrana traqueal inflamatoria obstructiva (en forma de tabique traqueal) secundaria a intubaciones repetidas y que se resolvió con tratamiento conservador. La presentación clínica de esta entidad generalmente incluye la aparición de infección respiratoria y/o atelectasia tras la retirada del tubo orotraqueal, como consecuencia de la acumulación de secreciones entre la pared traqueal y el tabique formado. Los tabiques traqueales inflamatorios se pueden resolver espontáneamente con ayuda de glucocorticoides, y otras veces requieren de un procedimiento endotraqueal invasivo en función de la evolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(9): 402-404, sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabique traqueal inflamatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54205^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14527^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
