<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112193</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurse's attitudes to pain in children and their relation to continuing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Broadly speaking, attitude can be defined as one of the basic elements in personality development, which shapes a person's behavior. Objetive: To determine the attitude of nursing professionals to pain in children. Material: The universe of subjects consisted of 121 male and female nurses who worked in pediatric services at secondary-level health facilities in the province of Cienfuegos (Cuba). Method: A descriptive observational study was performed in the pediatric services of these health centers. The subjects were given a questionnaire to identify their attitude towards pain in children. This attitude was related to the variables, work experience and continuing education. The differences between response frequencies of the groups of participants were analyzed by means of the chi square test. Mean values were compared by using the Anova t-test for independent groups. The value regarded as statistically significant was p &lt; 0.05. Results: The results obtained showed that 71.1% of the participants have a negative attitude towards pediatric pain, and that this attitude is significantly related to their training. Conclusions: As nurses received more training, their attitude towards pain in children was found to be more tolerant and positive (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Aguilar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla López, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Espinosa, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Cordero, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mur Villar, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Generalmente, la actitud se ha definido como la fuerza integradora fundamental en el desarrollo de la personalidad y que da consistencia a la conducta del individuo. Objetivo: Determinar la actitud del personal de enfermería, ante el dolor en la infancia. Material: El universo estuvo constituido por 121 enfermeros(as) que laboran en los servicios pediátricos del nivel secundario de salud en la provincia de Cienfuegos (Cuba). Método: Se realizó un estudio observacional y descriptivo en los servicios de atención pediátrica; se les presentó un cuestionario para identificar la actitud que tienen hacia el niño con dolor y se relacionó dicha actitud con las variables de experiencia laboral y formación continuada. El análisis se efectuó valorando las diferencias entre las frecuencias de las respuestas de los distintos grupos de participantes, para lo que se utilizó la prueba de Chi cuadrado. La comparación de medias se efectuó con la prueba t de Anova para grupos independientes. Se consideró significación estadística una p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: Dentro de los principales resultados, se destaca que el 71.1% de los participantes tiene una actitud desfavorable hacia el dolor, lo que se relaciona significativamente con la capacitación. Conclusiones: En la medida en que se incrementan las acciones capacitantes, la actitud ante el dolor se hace más favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 2066-2071, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitud de enfermería ante el dolor infantil y su relación con la formación continua</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
