<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85059</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and Distribution of Asbestos Lung Residue in a Spanish Urban Population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionThe purpose of the present study is to analyse the prevalence and distribution of asbestos lung residue in the Barcelona urban population.Material and methodsLung autopsy samples were obtained from 35 individuals who had lived in Barcelona. The close family were interviewed in order to rule out asbestos exposure. Samples were obtained from three areas of the right lung during the autopsy: upper lobe apex, lower lobe apex, and lower lobe base. The samples were treated to remove organic material. The inorganic residue was analysed using a light microscope. The results were expressed as asbestos bodies (AB) per gram of dry tissue. Levels greater than 1000AB/g of dry tissue were considered as potentially causing disease.ResultsAB were detected in 29(83%) of the subjects, of which 86% had levels less than 300AB/g. Only one individual (3%) had values greater than 1000AB/g dry tissue. The asbestos residue was higher in the lower lung lobe in 17 individuals (48%) than in the rest, although no significant differences were seen as regards AB residue in the three lung areas studied.ConclusionsThe results of this study show that the urban population of Barcelona have asbestos levels in the lung that vary between 0 and 300AB/g dry tissue. No differences in the asbestos residues were detected in the lung areas studied in this population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Panades, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco-García, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recuero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEl objetivo del presente estudio es analizar la prevalencia y distribución de amianto en pulmón de población urbana de Barcelona.Material y métodosSe obtuvieron muestras pulmonares necrópsicas de 35 individuos que habían residido en Barcelona. Se llevó a cabo una entrevista con el familiar más cercano para descartar exposición al amianto. En el acto necrópsico, se obtuvieron muestras de 3 zonas del pulmón derecho: apical del lóbulo superior, apical del lóbulo inferior y base del lóbulo inferior. Las muestras fueron tratadas para la eliminación de la materia orgánica. El residuo inorgánico fue analizado mediante microscopía óptica. Los resultados se expresaron como cuerpos de amianto (CA) por gramo de tejido seco. Se consideraron como niveles potencialmente causantes de patología aquellos que superaron los 1.000CA/g de tejido seco.ResultadosSe detectaron CA en 29 sujetos (83%). El 86% de las muestras analizadas tenían niveles inferiores a 300CA/g. Únicamente un individuo (3%) presentó valores superiores a los 1.000CA/g tejido seco. En 17 individuos (48%), el depósito de amianto era mayor en el lóbulo pulmonar inferior que en el resto, aunque no se observaron diferencias significativas en cuanto al depósito de CA en las 3 zonas pulmonares estudiadas.ConclusionesLos resultados del presente estudio demuestran que la mayoría de la población urbana en nuestro medio tiene niveles de amianto en pulmón que oscilan entre 0&#150;300CA/g tejido seco. En esta población no se han detectado diferencias en el depósito de amianto, según las zonas estudiadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(4): 176-181, abr. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85059</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y distribución del depósito pulmonar de amianto en población urbana española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1200^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1200^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1200^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
