<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115711</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of mistakes in the utilization of medicines in patients of high pharmacological risk and analysis of his potential reasons in a hospitable entity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mistakes in the system of utilization of medicines (SUM) are a clinical problem that increases the morbidity - mortality in the hospitals and the cost of the treatment. The aim of the work was to detect the mistakes in the SUM, to establish the factors associated to his occurrence and his relation with the adverse event, in patients hospitalized with high pharmacological risk, in a hospital of the third level of Bogota; in a period of three months of the year 2012. Method: Direct observation was realized in 318 adults, the review of their clinical records in 309 of them and the review of the voluntary reports of adverse events related to medicines. The analysis of results was realized across descriptive statistics by Stata 10. Results: Thinking that the global prevalence of mistake for every 100 patient doses, in the whole system of utilization of medicines was 5 % or more in 95 % of the patients; the lack of round of pharmacological safety with 94.03 % and the omission mistake of the record after the administration of the medicine with 68.62 % were the observed mistakes, which occupied the first place in field and review of clinical histories respectively. Of the total of analyzed mistakes, 1.89 % managed to damage the patient Conclusions: The shifts in the morning and the weekend, the experience of the personnel of minor infirmary to 6 months, and the stay at hospital longer than 10 days were circumstances where the prevalence of mistakes was high. The nurse has the responsibility of controlling de development of each period of the SUM and to lead its continuous improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera Romero, Nathaly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno de Santacruz, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Espinosa, Sandra Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los errores en el sistema de utilización de medicamentos (SUM) son un problema clínico que aumenta la morbimortalidad y el costo del tratamiento. El objetivo del trabajo fue detectar los errores en el SUM, establecer los factores asociados a su ocurrencia y su relación con el evento adverso, en pacientes con alto riesgo farmacológico, en una entidad hospitalaria de tercer nivel de Bogotá; en un periodo de tres meses del 2012. Metodología: Se realizó observación directa en 318 pacientes adultos, la revisión de historias clínicas en 309 de ellos y la revisión de los reportes voluntarios de eventos adversos relacionados con medicamentos. Se utilizó la estadística descriptiva con Stata 10. Resultados: Se encontró que la prevalencia global de error por cada 100 dosis paciente, en todo el sistema de utilización de medicamentos fue del 5% o más en el 95% de los pacientes; la falta de ronda de seguridad farmacológica con un 94.03% y el error de omisión del registro después de la administración del medicamento con un 68.62% fueron los errores, que ocuparon el primer lugar en campo y revisión de historias clínicas, respectivamente. El 1.89% llegó a causar daño temporal al paciente. Conclusiones: Los turnos de la mañana y el fin de semana, la experiencia del personal de enfermería menor a 6 meses, y la estancia hospitalaria mayor a 10 días fueron circunstancias en donde la prevalencia de errores fue superior. La enfermera(o) tiene la responsabilidad de controlar el desarrollo de cada fase del SUM. y de liderar su mejora continua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 171-184, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115711</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de errores en la utilización de medicamentos en pacientes de alto riesgo farmacológico y análisis de sus potenciales causas en una entidad hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9905^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
