<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150547</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of early traumatic experiences in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of early traumatic experiences has been associated with a variety of psychiatric disorders in adulthood. This means that in clinical practice the assessment of and approach to previous traumatic events is important in patients with different mental disorders. The main purpose of this paper is, firstly, to provide a brief description and approximation of the main measurement instruments for the assessment of early traumatic experiences; and secondly to present the new self-report for the assessment of early traumatic experiences in patients with severe mental illness. The results show that most of the existing tools for assessing early traumatic experiences have little or no psychometric support and a number of instruments are designed to measure only one type of trauma, which reduces their clinical applicability. Similarly, there are few instruments that have been adapted to and validated in the Spanish population. Future studies should continue to examine the psychometric properties of this group of self-reports with the aim of improving the evaluation of early traumatic experiences in adulthood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lemos-Giráldez, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Álvarez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro-Ruiz, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca-Pedrero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paino, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez-Camblor, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de experiencias traumáticas tempranas se ha asociado con una gran variedad de alteraciones psicopatológicas en la edad adulta. Esto hace que en la práctica clínica sea importante la evaluación y el abordaje de eventos traumáticos previos en los pacientes con diferentes trastornos mentales. El objetivo fundamental de este trabajo fue realizar una breve descripción y aproximación a los principales instrumentos de medida para la evaluación de las experiencias traumáticas tempranas, preferentemente en adultos; y presentar un nuevo instrumento de medida para la evaluación de las experiencias traumáticas tempranas en pacientes con trastorno mental grave. Los resultados mostraron que la mayoría de los instrumentos existentes proporcionan escaso o ningún apoyo psicométrico y se centran en evaluar un solo tipo de experiencia traumática, lo que reduce su aplicabilidad en la práctica clínica. Del mismo modo, son escasos los instrumentos que han sido adaptados y validados en población española. Futuros estudios deberían seguir examinando las propiedades psicométricas de este conjunto de autoinformes, con la finalidad de mejorar la evaluación de las experiencias traumáticas en la edad adulta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;37(1): 36-44, ene.-abr. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de experiencias traumáticas tempranas en adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52949^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
