<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122239</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Splenic disorders in internal medicines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The spleen is the largest lymphopoietic organ, containing 25% of total lymphoid mass. It participates in cellular and humoral immunity and intervenes in the renovation of red cells and the elimination of bacteria. Splenic functions are reduced when the spleen is absent, which entails, amongst other complications, greater susceptibility to suffering from sepsis due to encapsulated organisms. We present 6 clinical cases admitted to the Internal Medicine serve with splenic pathology and we make a review of the approach to be used. The spectrum of splenic lesions in internal medicine is very wide. On occasions, a splenic pathology can be suspected due to clinical history, physical exploration or because of cytopenias in the analyses. Different complementary tests are available for completing study of these lesions. A splenectomy can be carried out in case of diagnostic doubt, with the most frequent diagnoses being hepatic cirrhosis and lymphoma/leukaemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojo Álvaro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Fernández de Tejerina, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Martínez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anniccherico Sánchez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oteiza Olaso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ricart, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bazo representa el mayor órgano linfopoyético, contiene el 25% de la masa linfoide total. Participa en la inmunidad celular y humoral e interviene en la renovación de los glóbulos rojos y en la eliminación de las bacterias. Las funciones esplénicas están reducidas cuando el bazo está ausente, lo que implica entre otras complicaciones, una mayor susceptibilidad para padecer una sepsis por organismos encapsulados. Se presentan 6 casos clínicos ingresados en el servicio de Medicina Interna con patología esplénica y se hace una revisión del abordaje a realizar. El espectro de lesiones esplénicas en medicina interna es muy amplio. En ocasiones se puede sospechar patología esplénica por la historia clínica, la exploración física o por citopenias en los análisis. Disponemos de diversas pruebas complementarias para completar el estudio de dichas lesiones. En caso de duda diagnóstica se puede realizar esplenectomía siendo los diagnósticos más frecuentes la cirrosis hepática y el linfoma/leucemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(1): 169-176, ene.-abr. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones esplénicas en medicina interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13539^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7149^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13541^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
