<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97299</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of the metabolic alkalosis induced by the diet in the high intensity anaerobic performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The purpose of this study is to compare the effects of two diets, one acidifier and the other alkalizer, on the sport performance in an extreme anaerobic stress test. Methods: For that purpose thirteen individuals were subjected to two such diets in a crossed test for two and a half days. Immediately after, they were tested in a maximumlactic anaerobic stress test of stable state to exhaustion on an ergo-cycle at 250W. Results: The assessment of the diets yielded a significant difference in the estimated NAE (net acid excretion) and a caloric deficit of 54% on the alkalizer diet,mainly due to a reduced ingestion of carbohydrates.The urinary pH increased by 83% for the individuals subjected to the alkalizer diet, 77% of those subjects experienced an increase in their blood lactate level during the test. The time to exhaustion while on the test improved or remained in 58% of the subjects, being the females who reacted best to the diet in 83% of the cases. Conclusions: There seems to be evidence of improvement in extreme anaerobic stress test to exhaustion from 60s to 2 mins of duration after consuming a diet with alkalizer potential (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Feriche Fernández-Castanys, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Enríquez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra-Hernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El propósito principal de este estudio es comparar el efecto de una alcalosis y acidosis inducidas por la dieta sobre el rendimiento en un esfuerzo anaeróbico láctico mantenido. Métodos: Para ello, trece sujetos activos se sometieron de forma cruzada a sendas dietas durante dos días y medio. Inmediatamente después realizaron una prueba de esfuerzo anaeróbica láctica máxima de estado estable hasta el agotamiento sobre cicloergómetro a 250W.Resultados: La valoración de las dietas mostró una diferencia significativa en la excreción renal neta de ácidos (NAE) estimada, así como un déficit calórico del54% en la dieta alcalinizante, debido principalmente a una ingesta reducida de hidratos de carbono. En un 83% de los sujetos aumentó el pH urinario tras la dieta alcalinizante. El 77% incrementó sus niveles de lactato en sangre en la prueba tras la dieta alcalina. Los tiempos hasta la extenuación durante la prueba mejoraron o se mantuvieron en un 58% de los sujetos, siendo las mujeres las que mejor respondieron a la dieta con un 83% de casos. Conclusiones: Parece haber evidencias de mejora de rendimiento en esfuerzos de tipo anaeróbico láctico hasta el agotamiento de 60 s a 2 min de duración tras consumir una dieta con potencial alcalinizante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(5): 768-773, sept.-oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la alcalosis metabólica inducida por la dieta en el rendimiento anaeróbico de alta intensidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51576^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d473^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d151^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
