<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162552</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dermoscopy for beginners (I): general information</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of skin cancer has been gradually increasing worldwide since the 1960s. It is currently a health and economic problem for the different health systems. Dermoscopy is a non-invasive in vivo diagnostic technique, developed to study skin lesions. It improves the diagnostic accuracy of hyperpigmented lesions, as well as an early diagnosis of potentially malignant lesions, especially melanoma. The time spent on physical examination is not significantly increased. New applications have currently been discovered for this technique. Dermoscopy requires a learning process. Due to the complexity of the topic, the text has been divided into 2 parts to try to simplify its presentation. This first part will focus on the more technical aspects and the characteristics of the device called dermoscope. In the second part, 2 diagnostical methods will be presented along with their easy interpretation and usefulness in Primary Care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios-Martínez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Alonso, RA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incidencia de cáncer de piel está aumentando paulatinamente en el mundo desde la década de 1960. Actualmente representa un problema sanitario y económico para los diferentes sistemas de salud. La dermatoscopia es una técnica diagnóstica in vivo, no invasiva, desarrollada para estudiar las lesiones cutáneas. Mejora la precisión diagnóstica de las lesiones hiperpigmentadas y el diagnóstico precoz de las lesiones potencialmente malignas, especialmente el melanoma. No incrementa significativamente el tiempo dedicado a la exploración física. Actualmente se están descubriendo nuevas aplicaciones para esta técnica. Requiere un proceso de aprendizaje. Debido a la complejidad del tema, hemos dividido el texto en 2 partes, para intentar simplificar su exposición. Esta primera parte se centrará en los aspectos más técnicos y en las características del dispositivo denominado dermatoscopio. En la segunda parte se expondrán 2 métodos diagnósticos de sencilla interpretación y gran utilidad en Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(3): 216-221, abr. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatoscopia para principiantes (I): características generales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
