<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045764</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of advanced group and individual interventions in tackling tobacco dependency in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. a) To compare the effectiveness of group advanced intervention and individual advanced intervention for smoking management in primary health care; b) to know if in group intervention exists an added positive effect due of the group and, if this is true, to characterize it; and c) to know the advantages and inconvenients that the participants attribute to each intervention.         Design. Control clinic trial randomized in individual scale.         Setting. Mallorca primary health centers, Spain.         Participants. Smokers &gt;5 packet-year or monoxid carbon levels &gt;15 ppm prepared for give up smoking. People younger than 18 years, people with terminal illness, and mental problems will be excluded.         Interventions. Candidates will be assigned to: a) group intervention; b) individual intervention; or c) short intervention or control group. Interventions will be done by a nurse and a general practitioner. Depth interview will be done for qualitative study.         Principal measurement. Maintained cessation during 12 months confirmed by expired-air carbon monoxide measurement.         Secondary measurements. Self-declared cessation and confirmed by expired-air carbon monoxide measurement months 1, 2, 3, 6, and 9, and tobacco reduction if there isn't abandonment.         Analysis. Intention treatment. Multilevel analysis will be done to determinate the positive effect added of the group if it's proved that exists. Content analysis for qualitative study.         Discussion. Randomization will prevent participants will be treated by their general practitioner o their nurse, this can mean worse results than results obtained in practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Montserrat, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. a) Comparar la efectividad de las intervenciones avanzadas grupal e individual en el abordaje del tabaquismo en atención primaria; b) conocer si en la intervención grupal hay un efecto positivo añadido debido al grupo y, si lo hay, caracterizarlo, y c) conocer las ventajas e inconvenientes que los participantes atribuyen a cada intervención.         Diseño. Ensayo clínico controlado     y aleatorizado a escala individual. Investigación cualitativa.         Emplazamiento. Centros de salud     de Mallorca.         Participantes. Fumadores de más de 5 paquetes-año o con concentraciones de monóxido de carbono superiores a 15 ppm preparados para dejar de fumar. Se excluirá a los menores de 18 años, a los pacientes terminales y a pacientes con determinados problemas mentales.         Intervenciones. Los candidatos serán asignados a: a) intervención grupal; b) interveción individual, o c) intervención breve o grupo control. Las intervenciones serán realizadas por una enfermera y un médico. Para el estudio cualitativo se efectuarán entrevistas en profundidad.         Medición principal. Abandono sostenido     a los 12 meses, confirmado mediante cooximetría.         Mediciones secundarias. Abandono autodeclarado y confirmado mediante cooximetría los meses 1, 2, 3, 6 y 9, y la reducción del tabaquismo si no hay abandono.         Análisis. Por intención de tratar. Se realizará un análisis multinivel para determinar el efecto positivo añadido del grupo si se demuestra que existe. Para el estudio cualitativo, se realizará un análisis de contenido.         Discusión. La aleatorización impedirá que los participantes sean tratados por su médico o su enfermera, lo que puede traducirse en resultados peores de los que se podrán obtener en la práctica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;36(8): 462-465, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de las intervenciones grupal e individual avanzadas para el abordaje del tabaquismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
