<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162841</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-graduate gerontology training in Spain: Number, characteristics, and contents taught in master courses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Population aging raises the need for specialised professionals to address the needs of the elderly. The aim of this paper is to describe the number, characteristics, and contents of the Master degree courses that are currently offered in Spain. Material and methods. There were 32 Master degree courses offered in the 2014-15 academic year. These required at least 60 ECTS (European Credit Transfer and Accumulation System). At least half of the course credits were based on contents directly related to old age, older people, or aging. An analysis was made that included, information on the institutional affiliation, official status, academic structure, and contents taught. A content analysis was performed on curriculum subjects, in order to classify the courses into multidisciplinary or specialised (with focus either on health, behavioural, or social sciences). Results. Most of the courses required mandatory class attendance, and lasted one academic year (60 ECTS). They also included the completion of a final project and a practicum. The majority (59%) of Master degree courses were classified as multidisciplinary. Of the remaining ones, 19% were labelled as specialised in behavioural sciences, 16% in health sciences, and 2% in social sciences. Conclusions. The field of higher education in gerontology in Spain seems to be consolidated, taking into account indicators such as the number of courses offered, their territorial distribution, or the number of official Master degree courses. While the academic structure of the courses is quite similar, in contrast, their contents and nature are highly diverse, which responds to the different training needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrat, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giuliani, María Florencia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Feliciano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El envejecimiento poblacional plantea la necesidad de contar con profesionales especializados para atender las necesidades de las personas mayores. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir el número, las características y los contenidos impartidos por los programas de máster que se ofertan actualmente en España. Material y métodos. Se identificaron 32 programas de máster ofertados en el curso 2014-2015, que requerían al menos 60 créditos ECTS y cuyos contenidos relacionados directamente con la vejez, las personas mayores o el envejecimiento suponían al menos la mitad de los créditos del programa. Se analizó la información relativa a la pertenencia institucional, el carácter propio u oficial, la estructura académica y los contenidos impartidos, entre otros. Las materias presentes en los planes de estudio fueron sometidas a un análisis de contenido, lo que permitió clasificar los programas en multidisciplinares o especializados (orientados a las ciencias de las salud, del comportamiento o sociales). Resultados. La mayoría de los másteres analizados eran presenciales y tenían un curso académico de duración (60 créditos ECTS). Asimismo, incluían la realización de un trabajo final y prácticas. El 59% de los másteres se clasificaron como multidisciplinares. De los restantes, el 19% se etiquetó como especializado en ciencias del comportamiento, un 16% en ciencias de la salud y el 2% en ciencias sociales. Conclusiones. La formación superior en gerontología en España parece estar consolidada atendiendo a indicadores como la cantidad de programas ofertados, su distribución territorial o el número de másteres oficiales. Aunque la estructura académica de los programas es muy similar, los contenidos y naturaleza de los programas son, en contraste, muy diversos, lo que da respuesta a necesidades formativas muy variadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);52(3): 135-141, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162841</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La formación gerontológica de posgrado en España: número, características y contenidos impartidos en programas de máster</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
