<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045391</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of acetylcholinesterase inhibitors and memantine in Alzheimer-type dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The therapeutic options to treat Alzheimer-typedementia (ATD) in recent years, have made it increasingly necessaryto become familiar with the employment pattern of these newmedicinal products.Methods: A cross-sectional observational study of the populationwith ATD treated with acetylcholinesterase inhibitors and/ormemantine in the Gallician Health Service. Databases were compiledwith the demographic variables and use data during April 2005 ofthe medicinal products studied.Results: Of the 5,110 patients with ATD, 70.47% were women.The mean age of the women was 80.12 and of the men was 78.61years old, with standard deviations of 6.66 and 7.03, respectively.The female sex was one of the factors associated with presentingATD to pharmacological treatment (OR: 1.932 [CI 95%:1.819-2.052]). The medication used most was donepezyl (44.46% ofpatients). Significant differences were found in that memantine wasused to treat more patients in the group of patients £ 64 years (19.7%in £ 64 years vs. 14% in &gt;64 years[p&lt;0.05]), and donepezyl was preferentiallyused in patients ³ 95 years (75% in ³ 95 years vs. 46.9%in &lt;95 years [p&lt;0,03]). No significant differences were observed inthe use of anti-dementia therapy, expressed in DDD/patient/day betweenthe sexes, age groups, or in the age groups separated accordingto sex.Conclusions: The use of memantine (in monotherapy or in combination)is more frequent in patients under 64 years old. Female sexwas found to be a factor associated with presenting ATD to pharmacologicaltreatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Represa Veiga, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo Romero, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portela Romero, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En los últimos años han aumentado las alternativasterapéuticas en el tratamiento de la demencia tipo Alzheimer(DTA), por lo que se hace necesario conocer el patrón de utilizaciónde estos nuevos medicamentos.Métodos: Estudio observacional transversal de la población conDTA tratada con inhibidores de la acetilcolinesterasa y/o memantinaen el Servicio Gallego de Salud. Se construyeron bases de datos conlas variables demográficas y datos de utilización durante abril de2005 de los referidos medicamentos.Resultados: De 5.110 pacientes con DTA, el 70,47% eran mujeres.La edad media de éstas fue de 80,12 y de 78,61 en los hombres,con desviaciones típicas de 6,66 y 7,03 respectivamente. El sexofemenino se mostró como un factor asociado a presentar DTA a tratamientofarmacológico (OR: 1,932 [IC 95%:1,819-2,052]). Elmedicamento más utilizado fue donepezilo (44,46% de los pacientes).Se hallaron diferencias significativas en el porcentaje de pacientescon memantina a favor de los pacientes £ 64 años (19,7% en £ 64años vs. 14% en &gt;64 años[p&lt;0,05]), y de donepezilo a favor de lospacientes ³ 95 años (75% en ³95 años vs. 46,9% en ³ 95 años[p&lt;0,03]). No se observaron diferencias significativas en la utilizaciónde la terapéutica antidemencia, expresada en DDD/paciente/díaentre sexos, grupos de edad, ni en la desagregación de los grupos deedad por sexos.Conclusiones: La utilización de memantina (en monoterapia oen combinación) es más frecuente en menores de 64 años. El sexofemenino se mostró como un factor asociado a presentar DTA a tratamientofarmacológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(6): 665-672, nov.-dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de los inhibidores de la acetilcolinesterasa y la memantina para el tratamiento clínico de la demencia tipo alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32110^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7366^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11313^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23620^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7366^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23620^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2255^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32110^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
