<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130299</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A destabolizing dialogics of social and sexual order: the argentinian physician Juan Lazarte in the anarchist magazine estudios (1932-1936)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper we analyze the articles published by Argentinean physician Juan Larzarte in the magazine Estudios in the 1930s. This took place within a publishing policy aimed at overcoming the exclusion of discourses opposing the established social order. The discourse practices we explore were dialogic while focusing on neo-Malthusian and eugenic propositions and the historical causes of a gendered social relations structuring a double sexual morals. Lazarte used several forms of intertextuality and suggested the compatibility of seemingly opposed approaches without getting round the differences and avoiding debates in dichotomic terms. These practices allowed the strategic use of eugenic rhetoric within the neo-Malthusian proposition aimed at the human species to reach a state of good living. As he did not consider history from an ideology of progress, and insisted on taking into account the different facets of any issue (biological, economic and cultural), Lazarte&#146;s discourse in Estudios contributed to configure a world defying the assumptions of a deterministic biopower, thus becoming a destabilizing power regarding the sexual and social order (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Lucena, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero-Mesa, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo analizamos los artículos del médico argentino Juan Lazarte publicados en la revista Estudios en los años 30 del siglo XX. Este hecho se produjo en el marco de una política editorial que pretendía superar la exclusión a que eran sometidos los discursos de oposición al orden social establecido. La práctica discursiva analizada se desarrolló sobre una dialógica en torno a las propuestas neomaltusianas y eugenésicas y a las causas históricas de unas relaciones sociales generizadas que estructuraban una doble moral sexual. Lazarte usó diversas formas de intertextualidad y señaló la compatibilidad de planteamientos que se mostraban opuestos en apariencia, sin obviar las diferencias, evitando los debates en términos dicotómicos. Esta praxis hizo posible un uso táctico de la retórica eugenésica en la propuesta neomaltusiana con la que se pretendía que la especie humana alcanzase un estado de buen vivir. Al no concebir la historia desde una ideología del progreso, y empeñarse en considerar los distintos aspectos de los problemas (biológicos, económicos y culturales), el discurso de Lazarte en Estudios contribuía a conformar un mundo que desafiaba los supuestos de un biopoder determinista, constituyéndose en un poder desestabilizador del orden sexual y social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;66(2): [p56], jul.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una dialógica desestabilizadora del orden social y sexual: el médico argentino Juan Lazarte en la Revista Anarquista Estudios (1932-1936)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54394^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
