<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153681</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal factors associated with umbilical cord blood pH values</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Perinatal asphyxia is the mayor cause of neonatal morbidity and mortality. The analysis of umbilical arterial cord blood pH remains an objective criterion used to determine the metabolic state of the newborn after birth, and therefore of fetal wellbeing. The aim was to identify the perinatal factors associated with umbilical arterial cord blood pH values. Materials and methods: A descriptive and analytical study was conducted between January 2010 and January 2013 at a tertiary hospital in the Southern Spain. The inclusion criteria were: Uncomplicated pregnancy and vaginal single delivery at term with vertex presentation. Independent variables with greater significance after the univariate analysis were: Age, parity, gestational age, epidural analgesia, birth plan, and episiotomy, duration of first labor stage and oxytocin use. It was considered as a dependent variable the umbilical arterial blood pH values (&lt; = 7.24; &gt; 7.24). The total number of women was 165. Statistical analysis was performed using logistic regression. Results: Epidural analgesia and gestational age more than or equal to 41 weeks have negatively influence the neonatal umbilical cord pH, while having presented a birth plan could have a protective influence. Conclusions: findings of this study provide to the professionals more evidence on the elements that may influence neonatal wellbeing, in order to act accordingly, anticipating risk situations and applying more effective care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo-Maestre, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo-Lopezosa, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Borrego, María Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El análisis del pH de sangre arterial de cordón umbilical sigue siendo un criterio objetivo usado para determinar el estado metabólico del recién nacido tras el parto, y por tanto del bienestar fetal. El objetivo de este estudio fue identificar los factores perinatales asociados con los valores de sangre arterial de cordón umbilical. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y analítico entre Enero de 2010 y Enero de 2013 en un hospital de tercer nivel en el sur de España, con mujeres atendidas por parto. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: embarazo sin complicaciones y parto vaginal único, a término, con presentación cefálica. Las variables independientes con gran significación tras un análisis univariante fueron: edad, paridad, edad gestacional, analgesia epidural, plan de parto, episiotomía, duración de la primera fase del parto, y uso de oxitocina. Como variable dependiente se consideró: los valores de pH de sangre arterial de cordón umbilical (&lt; = 7.24; &gt; 7.24). El número total de mujeres fue de 165. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante regresión logística múltiple. Resultados: La analgesia epidural y la edad gestacional mayor o igual a 41 semanas influyeron negativamente en el pH de cordón umbilical neonatal, mientras que haber presentado un plan de parto tuvo una influencia protectora. Conclusiones: Los hallazgos de este estudio proporcionan a los profesionales más evidencias sobre los elementos que pueden influenciar en el bienestar neonatal, con el fin de actuar en consecuencia, anticipándose a las situaciones de riesgo y aplicando una atención más eficaz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(43): 40-50, jul. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores perinatales asociados con los valores de pH de sangre de cordón umbilical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5422^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
