<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157340</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications in cranial reconstruction using PEEK prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cranial defects tend to carry functional and aesthetic consequences for the patient. The most suitable material to be used remains controversial. Methods. We report a retrospective review of patients whose cranial defects were reconstructed using a computer designed polyetheretherketone (PEEK)-patient specific implant) between 2008 and 2014 at the Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery Department, in Hospital Universitario La Paz, Madrid. Implants are designed individually to each patient with CAD-CAM system. Results. Seven patients underwent cranial reconstruction using a PEEK-patient specific implant. One case involved a one-step primary reconstruction and the rest of cases underwent a delayed reconstruction. Complications were: one seroma and one CSF leak, resolved with conservative treatment, and a wound dehiscence and an infection case whose defect was near the frontal sinus, resolved with removal of the implant. Conclusion. The ideal material for reconstructing cranial defects does not exist, but PEEK has demonstrated good outcomes. When autologous bone is not available or in selected cases with large defects, PEEK is a good option to reconstruct these defects. However, if the defect is related with paranasal sinuses, indication must be evaluated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Rodríguez, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Godoy, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián-Carretero, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgueño, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, José Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los defectos craneales tienen una repercusión importante en el paciente desde un punto de vista estético, psicológico y funcional. Actualmente no existe acuerdo sobre el material ideal para la reconstrucción de estos defectos. Material y métodos. Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo incluyendo a los pacientes con reconstrucción craneal con prótesis de polieteretercetona (PEEK) a medida entre los años 2008 y 2014 en el Servicio de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial del Hospital Universitario La Paz, Madrid. Las prótesis son diseñadas de manera específica para cada paciente con el sistema CAD-CAM. Resultados. Se reconstruyó a un total de 7 pacientes con defectos craneales con prótesis de PEEK. Solo en un caso, la resección y reconstrucción fueron realizadas en el mismo acto quirúrgico. En el resto de los casos se realizó una reconstrucción diferida. Las complicaciones que se presentaron fueron: un seroma y una fístula de LCR, que se resolvieron con tratamiento conservador; y una dehiscencia de la herida y un caso con episodios de infecciones repetidas, cuyo defecto estaba próximo al seno frontal, que terminaron con la retirada definitiva de la prótesis. Conclusión. El material ideal para la reconstrucción de defectos craneales no existe. Las prótesis de PEEK están obteniendo buenos resultados estética y funcionalmente. Cuando el hueso autógeno no esté disponible o en determinados casos con defectos grandes, las prótesis de PEEK pueden ser una buena opción. Sin embargo, si el defecto está en comunicación directa con los senos paranasales, debemos valorar bien la indicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(4): 199-205, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, ^pilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157340</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones en reconstrucción craneal con prótesis de polieteretercetona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3415^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5760^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31476^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38652^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5760^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38652^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5760^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
