<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136838</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pill-testing as selective prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Concern in the European Union has increased during the past years about the content of pills sold as ecstasy. However, within this context, the challenge of taking the necessary prevention measures is great &#150; in particular to approach and inform hard-to-reach target groups such as ecstasy consumers about health risks, as these groups do not access the traditional drug care systems. On-site pill testing originally emerged as a concrete response to the adulteration of pills commonly sold as ecstasy but is revealing now as an innovative means to approach specific risk groups. Although some countries nowadays offer comparable information regarding modus operandi, contents and aims of on-site pill testing projects, discussions about this issue are still very vivid and, sometimes, ideological. The present article&#146;s aim is to provide an objective overview of goals, methods, results and evaluation efforts of pill-testing projects. This overview gathers and discusses the most common opinions about these projects. The pseudo-legality of most projects is both the cause and consequence of the lack of rigorous evaluations in this area. Nevertheless, the information available nowadays in Europe opens the possibility of defining research and quality criteria (strategy, training, equipment) for pill testing projects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burkhart, Gregor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kriener, Harald</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, ha habido una creciente preocupación en la Unión Europea por el contenido de las pastillas que se venden bajo el nombre de éxtasis, debido a que éstas muchas veces podrían estar compuestas por otro tipo de sustancias. Sin embargo, es muy difícil tomar las medidas de prevención puesto que los consumidores de éxtasis constituyen un grupo diana al que es difícil llegar para informarles sobre los riesgos de salud ya que estas personas no acceden a los sistemas tradicionales de prevención. El análisis de pastillas originalmente surgió como respuesta específica a la adulteración de las pastillas pero ahora se revela también como una estrategia innovadora para alcanzar grupos de riesgo específicos. Si bien algunos países cuentan con información comparable sobre el modo de operación y los objetivos de los proyectos de análisis de pastillas, el debate sobre este tema sigue siendo candente ideológico. En este artículo se revisan los argumentos más frecuentes que giran en torno a estas intervenciones. La semi-legalidad de muchos de estos proyectos es, a su vez, causa y efecto de la escasez de evaluaciones más rigurosas en este campo. No obstante, la información disponible en este momento permite definir ciertos criterios de calidad (estrategia, formación, equipamiento) y de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);15(supl.2): 307-325, 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de pastillas como prevención selectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32121^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23605^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
