<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114739</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative anaphylaxis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Perioperative anaphylaxis may be a life threatening clinical condition and is typically due to the results of drugs used for anesthesia. Once anaphylaxis occurs, allergy studies are essential to identify the responsible agent so to prevent recurrences. The overall incidence is estimated at 1 in 10,000-20,000 anesthetic procedures. The most commonly involved agents are neuromuscular blocking agents, latex and antibiotics. The initial diagnosis is presumptive; including clinical signs and adrenalin is the treatment of choice. The aim of this article is to review etiology, diagnosis, prevention and treatment of perioperative anaphylaxis. It will be important to produce action protocols to ensure the detection of these reactions of anaphylaxis in outpatient surgery and to establish the correct follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Álvarez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Paz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rial Prado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Gómez, B. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Guzmán, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Arrondo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anafilaxia perioperatoria es un cuadro clínico que puede amenazar la vida del paciente, producido por fármacos o sustancias usados durante la anestesia. Después de una anafilaxia debe realizarse un estudio alergológico para identificar el agente responsable y prevenir recurrencias. La incidencia global se estima de 1 entre 10.000-20.000 anestesias. Los agentes más frecuentemente implicados son los bloqueantes neuromusculares, látex y antibióticos. El diagnóstico inicial es clínico y en el tratamiento es esencial la adrenalina. En este artículo se describe la clínica, pruebas diagnósticas, así como protocolos de prevención y tratamiento del cuadro de anafilaxia perioperatoria. Será importante desarrollar protocolos de detección y manejo precoz de estas reacciones en circuitos de cirugía ambulatoria y establecer un adecuado seguimiento posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;18(2): 81-88, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anafilaxia perioperatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
