<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156216</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dialogue about medicinal plants: meanings of students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims to know the meanings attributed by students to dialogue about medicinal plants in health care. It is a qualitative research with 65 students of two schools in the city of Pelotas/RS, from September 2011 to August 2012. The analyzed data was produced after 18 workshops from essays written by students and focus groups. The meetings allowed us to stimulate in the students values directed to the recognition of the family knowledge and the development of critical thinking about the safe use of medicinal plants, awakening them new visions of the world and providing a reflexion on the care practices. The use of Geertz and Freire referential in the workshops allowed dialogue with the culture of the students and discuss situations of life, becoming in perspective for educational practice nurses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ceolin, Teila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceolin, Silvana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heck, Rita Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendieta, Marjoriê da Costa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes, Ana Carolina Padua</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo tiene como objectivo conocer los significados asignados por escolares sobre el diálogo cerca de las plantas medicinales en el cuidado de la salud. Metodología cualitativa con 65 escolares de dos escuelas del municipio de Pelotas/RS. La recolección de datos ocurrió de septiembre/2011 a agosto/2012. El material analizado fue produccido al final de 18 oficinas a partir de textos escritos y grupos focales. Se observó que los encuentros permitieron estimular en los estudiantes valores dirigidos al reconocimiento del saber familiar y el desarrollo del pensamiento crítico sobre el uso seguro de las plantas medicinales, levantando nuevas visiones del mundo y proporciando una reflexión sobre las prácticas de cuidado. El empleo del marco teórico de Geertz y Freire en las oficinas permitió el diálogo con la cultura de los escolares y discutir situaciones de vida, transcurriendo en una perspectiva para la educación de las enfermeras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(45): 98-107, mayo-ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156216</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diálogo sobre plantas medicinales: significado de los escolares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
