<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145074</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conceptual analysis of shared decision-making process in mental health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the most important changes in health care in recent decades, regarding the therapeutic decisions, has been the transition from a model focused on the disease to other one focused on the patient. This entails the progressive replacement of a paternalistic approach by a more deliberative one and, in relation to pharmacological treatments, the concept of compliance or adherence to the therapeutic agreement. The concept of therapeutic agreement, on the other hand, has been referred to as the ultimate goal of a process of negotiation and co-responsibility in the decision to choose a treatment which has been called 'shared decision making process' (SDM). So far, the SDM has been poorly implemented in severe mental disorders, when not answered as inadequate given the alleged alteration of the seriously ill psychiatric patient&#146;s ability to make decisions. However, this inability is not always present so shared decision should be viewed as a premise and not as an exception. SDM involves the introduction of a procedure in stages (doctor-patient partnership, information  about options, pros and cons, deliberation about them and their relationship with the values and preferences of the patient, consensual decision). One of the most important barriers for the implementation of the shared mental health decision-making process is the question of the capacity of the mentally ill. Therefore, the evaluation of the capacity must be central in psychiatric clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villagrán, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Ruiz-Granados, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Saiz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los cambios más importantes en la atención sanitaria de las últimas décadas, en lo que a las decisiones terapéuticas se refiere, ha sido la transición desde un modelo centrado en la enfermedad a uno centrado en el paciente. Esto conlleva la progresiva sustitución de una aproximación paternalista por una más deliberativa y, en relación a los tratamientos farmacológicos, del concepto de cumplimiento o adherencia al de concordancia o acuerdo terapéutico. El concepto de concordancia, por su parte, ha sido contemplado como el objetivo final de un proceso de negociación y corresponsabilidad en la decisión de elegir un tratamiento al que se ha denominado proceso de decisión compartida (PDC) (shared decision making). Hasta el momento, el PDC ha sido escasamente implantado en trastornos mentales graves, cuando no contestado como inadecuado dada la presunta alteración de la capacidad del paciente psiquiátrico gravemente enfermo para tomar decisiones. Sin embargo, esta incapacidad no siempre está presente por lo que la decisión compartida debe contemplarse como premisa y no como excepción. El PDC implica la implantación de un procedimiento en etapas (asociación médico paciente, información sobre opciones, pros y contras, deliberación sobre las mismas y su relación con valores y preferencias del paciente, decisión consensuada). Un  de las barreras más importantes para la aplicación del proceso de decisión compartida en salud mental es la cuestión de la capacidad del enfermo mental. Por ello, la evaluación de la capacidad debe hacerse central en la práctica clínica psiquiátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;35(127): 455-472, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos conceptuales sobre el proceso de decisión compartida en salud mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
