<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116897</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hysteroscopic sterilization with Essure: experience at the Vall d&#146;Hebron University Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Female sterilization is frequently chosen as a permanent method of family planning. Traditionally, such methods have been associated with surgery, with abdominal incisions and a recovery period of several days. In the last few years, hysteroscopic sterilization has become more widely accepted, because this procedure can be performed in the office and is incisionfree, safe, rapid and permanent. In a large percentage of patients, no anesthesia is required. We report the results obtained by the Gynecology Service of the Vall d&#146;Hebron University Hospital in Barcelona, Spain, after 8 years of using the EssureW system as the method of choice in patients requiring permanent contraception. The devices implanted in the fallopian tubes trigger a process of fibrosis leading to tubal occlusion. The occurrence of this process was confirmed by follow-up hysterosalpingography performed 3 months after the procedure. Our results are similar to those reported in the literature, with a success rate (tubal occlusion at 3 months) of 98.8% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lopera-Vallejo, Andrés Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gregorio Iguarbe, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eyzaguirre Samillan, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esterilización femenina se elige con frecuencia como método permanente de planificación familiar. Clásicamente, los métodos definitivos de planificación familiar se asocian a una intervención quirúrgica, con incisiones abdominales y con un periodo de recuperación de algunos días. En los últimos años, la esterilización histeroscópica ha ganado adeptos ya que es un procedimiento que puede ser realizado en consulta, libre de incisiones, rápido, seguro, permanente y, en un gran porcentaje de ocasiones, sin requerimientos anestésicos. Presentamos los resultados obtenidos por el Servicio de Ginecología del Hospital Universitario Vall d&#146;Hebron, Barcelona (España) tras 8 años de implantación del sistema Essure® como método de elección para las pacientes que desean un método definitivo de anticoncepción. Los dispositivos implantados en las trompas desencadenan un proceso de fibrosis que producirá la oclusión tubárica. Esto es confirmado mediante la realización de una histerosalpingografía de control realizada 3 meses después del procedimiento. Nuestros resultados son similares a los reportados en la literatura, con una tasa de éxito (oclusión tubárica a los 3 meses) del 98,8% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(10): 497-501, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esterilización histeroscópica con Essure: experiencia en el Hospital Universitario Vall d&#146;Hebron</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13634^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
