<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90649</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity of a questionnaire for the assessment of work-related musculoskeletal symptoms and physical demands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Participatory ergonomics interventions are frequently based on the use of self-answered questionnaires intended to gathering information on work-related musculoskeletal symptoms and physical demands reported by workers. The aim of this study is to assess the validity of a questionnaire designed to be applied in these programs. Methods: Thirty five volunteer workers from ten different companies located in Valencia and Alicante (Spain) agreed to participate. Field work was developed in 2009. Three complementary approaches were applied: reproducibility in two administrations of the questionnaire; comparing data in the questionnaire with data from direct observation of workplaces; and comparing data in the questionnaire with data from routine reports of health surveillance and risk assessment in participating companies. Results: Agreement indices (weighted kappa, wK) in reproducibility analyses for musculoskeletal symptoms in the different parts of the body (thighs being the only exception) were between 0.32 (95%CI 0.05-0.59) and 0.70 (95%CI 0.41-0.99). In general, the same analyses for exposure to the different ergonomic risks yielded lower agreement indices; e.g., wK for neck positions between 0.36 (backwards, 95%CI 0.11-0.61) and 0.55 (forwards, 95%CI 0.30-0.80). In the analyses comparing with data from workplace observation, agreement indices were lower. Most items in the questionnaire show acceptable levels of agreement in reproducibility analyses, but lower indices when comparing with observation Conclusions: Most of musculoskeletal symptoms and physical demands self-reported by the workers in the questionnaire were not included in the companies' routine health surveillance and risk assessment reports.The questionnaire is a more sensitive tool than routine health surveillance and risk assessments practices in order to identify perceived problems by workers(AU)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ronda, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gadea, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En las intervenciones de ergonomía participativa es frecuente utilizar cuestionarios autoadministrados para obtener información acerca de los daños y riesgos ergonómicos percibidos por los trabajadores. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la validez de un cuestionario diseñado para su utilización en este tipo de programas. Métodos: Participaron 35 trabajadores voluntarios de diez empresas de Valencia y Alicante. El trabajo de campo se realizó en 2009. Se siguieron tres estrategias: análisis de repetibilidad en dos vueltas del cuestionario, comparación de las respuestas al cuestionario (primera vuelta) con la información obtenida mediante observación directa de los puestos de trabajo y comparación de la información recogida en el cuestionario con la incluida en los informes rutinarios de vigilancia de la salud y evaluación de riesgos disponibles en las empresas. Resultados: En el análisis de repetibilidad, la concordancia (Kappa ponderado, Kp) de los ítems que valoraban la presencia de síntomas musculoesqueléticos en las distintas zonas del cuerpo (con la excepción de "muslos") se situaron entre 0,32 (IC95% 0,05-0,59) y 0,70 (IC95% 0,41-0,99). En relación con la exposición a riesgos ergonómicos, se observaron en general concordancias más bajas, por ejemplo Kp para posturas del cuello entre 0,36 (cuello hacia atrás, IC95% 0,11-0,61) y 0,55 (cuello hacia delante, IC95% 0,30-0,80). En el análisis de comparación con la observación de los puestos de trabajo se encontraron las menores concor-dancias.La mayoría de las preguntas del cuestionario presentan niveles de concordancia aceptables en el análisis de repetibilidad. Conclusiones: En la comparación con la observación los índices son en general más bajos. La mayoría de los problemas referidos por los trabajadores en el cuestionario no se reflejaban en los informes rutinarios de las empresas. El cuestionario es más sensible que otras estrategias rutinarias (reconocimientos médicos, evaluaciones de riesgos) para identificar los problemas percibidos por los trabajadores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(4): 339-349, jul.-ago.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un cuestionario para identificar daños y exposición a riesgos ergonómicos en el trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
