<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97103</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of difficult airway predictors in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the usefulness of difficult airway predictors in the emergency department and the prognosticvalue of some of these predictors. Methods: A descriptive, observational study was carried out in the emergency department over a period of 14 months. We studied patients who required intubation to establish an airway, assessing the likelihood of difficult airway by Mallampati score, Cormack-Lehane classification, and sternomental distance and calculating the predictive value, sensitivity, and specificity of these variables by themselves and in combination. Results: We identified 137 patients requiring orotracheal intubation, which was successful in fewer than 3 attempts in 79.5% and in 5 minutes or less in 92.3%. In 98 patients we were able to assess the likelihood of difficult airway inadvance. The positive predictive value was 100% for the Mallampati score (sensitivity, 100%; specificity, 77.7%), 87.5%for the Cormack-Lehane classification (sensitivity, 98.8%; specificity, 100%), and 66.6% for the sternomental distance(sensitivity 85.7%; specificity, 96.0%). No gender-related differences in the incidence of difficult airway were observed. Conclusions: The Mallampati score had the best predictive value, sensitivity, and specificity. The difficulty of an airway could usually be predicted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santana Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Santos, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Salgado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar la efectividad del uso de predictores en el manejo de la vía aérea en el área de urgencias y el valor pronóstico de algunos predictores de vía aérea difícil. Método: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo, observacional, en el área de urgencias durante un periodo de 14 meses. La muestra estuvo constituida por pacientes con necesidad de control de la vía aérea, en los cuales se analizó la probabilidad de vía aérea difícil mediante la aplicación de los test de Mallampati, Cormack Lehane y Distancia Esternomentoniana. Se determinó su valor predictivo, sensibilidad y especificidad de manera independiente y combinados. Resultados: Se detectaron 137 pacientes, y en ellos la IOT se realizó en menos de 3 intentos en el 79,5% y en el 92,3% en 5 o menos minutos. En 98 pacientes pudo analizarse a priori la probabilidad de encontrar una vía aérea difícil. El test de Mallampati tuvo un valor predictivo positivo de 100%, el de Cormack Lehane de 87,5%, y la Distancia Esternomentoniana de 66,6%, mientras que la sensibilidad fue del 100, 77,7y 98,8%, respectivamente, y la especificiadad fue del 100, 85,7 y 96,0%, respectivamente. No hubo diferencias de género en la aparición de vía aérea difícil. Conclusiones: El test de Mallampati tuvo un mayor valor predictivo, sensibilidad y especificidad. El carácter de la vía aérea fue predicho mayoritariamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(4): 293-298, ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad del uso de predictores de vía aérea difícil en el área de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9524^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13635^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
