<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047775</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tools that measure nursing activity and its repercussion on health outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: when we talk about systems that measure workloads, care standards, appropriateness of the nursing staff, or theratio nurse/patient, the aim is to objectivise if this apportion meetsthe demands of the patients and system adequately. In this article,the first of a series of 10, we describe methodological aspects ofsystematic review, presenting the script of the series, together witha glossary of the abbreviations used.Objectives of the review: to identify those instruments and indicatorsthat describe the nursing staff and its correlation withpatient outcomes.Methodology: the consulted databases were: CINAHL, MEDLINE,EMBASE, Cochrane Plus Library, as well as the BDIE, CUIDEN andCUIDATGE national databases. Validation studies of the instrumentsrelating to the nursing staff were selected by two independentreviewers, establishing a relationship between nursing staffindicators and healthcare outcomes.Main results: 68 studies were included that allowed the identificationof 18 tools measuring nursing workload and 5 staff indicators.Conclusions of the reviewers: it is not possible to establish thevalidity of these instruments conclusively because there is no goldstandard. It is necessary to establish a standardised definition ofthe staff indicators</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solà, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subirana Casacuberta, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: cuando se habla de sistemas de medida de cargasde trabajo, sistemas de medida de cuidados, de adecuación de laplantilla de Enfermería o de la ratio enfermera-paciente, lo que sepretende es objetivar cuál es la adecuación de la actividad deEnfermería y conocer si esta adecuación da respuesta a las demandasde los pacientes y del sistema. En este artículo, primero de unaserie de 10, se describen los aspectos metodológicos de la revisiónsistemática y se presenta el guión de la serie.Objetivos: identificar aquellos instrumentos e indicadores quedescriban la plantilla de Enfermería y relacionarla con los resultadosde los pacientes.Metodología: las bases de datos consultadas fueron CINAHL,MEDLINE, EMBASE, Biblioteca Cochrane Plus y las bases de datosnacionales de Enfermería BDIE, CUIDEN y CUIDATGE. Se seleccionaronpor dos revisores independientes estudios de validación delos instrumentos relacionados con la plantilla de Enfermería, y enlos que se establece una relación entre indicadores de plantilla deEnfermería y resultados en salud.Resultados principales: se incluyeron 68 estudios que han permitidoidentificar 18 instrumentos de medida de cargas de trabajode Enfermería y 5 indicadores de plantilla.Conclusiones de los revisores: no es posible establecer la validezde estos instrumentos de una forma conclusiva, debido a que noexiste un gold standard. Es necesario determinar una definiciónestandarizada de los indicadores de plantilla</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(6): 22-27, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática de los instrumentos que miden la actividad de Enfermería y su repercusión sobre los resultados en salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
