<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136098</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of invasive candidiasis in pediatric and adult populations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Invasive candidiasis (IC) is the most frequent fungal disease in children and adults. Aims: To critically review and update the current epidemiology of Candida spp. disease in neonates, children and adults (critically ill patients and in oncohematologic patients and in solid organ transplant recipients). Methods: We searched the PubMed/Medline, discussing the current data. Results and conclusions: IC is associated with high attributable morbimortality and increased healthcare costs. In the last decades the incidence of invasive Candida spp. disease has increased in critically ill patients, has decreased in oncohematologic patients, although currently the involvement of non-albicans Candida species in the etiology of this disease is increasing steadily (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio, Amalia del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alhambra, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La candidiasis invasora (CI) es la enfermedad fúngica oportunista más frecuente, tanto en niños como en adultos. Objetivos: Se presenta una revisión actualizada sobre los aspectos epidemiológicos en neonatos, niños y adultos ingresados en unidades de cuidados intensivos, así como en pacientes oncohematológicos y receptores de trasplantes de órgano sólido. Métodos: Se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica en la base de datos PubMed/Medline. Se presenta una revisión actualizada. Resultados y conclusiones: La CI se asocia a una elevada morbimortalidad y costes económicos. En las últimas décadas, la enfermedad invasora debida a Candida spp. ha aumentado de forma significativa en pacientes críticos, ha disminuido en pacientes oncohematológicos, aunque en todas las distintas subpoblaciones son más prevalentes las especies de Candida diferentes de C. albicans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;26(1): 2-7, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de las candidiasis invasoras en población pediátrica y adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32203</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19278^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19278^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
