<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14011</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Some critical contributions to the search for a theoretical framework for coping in psychosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article defends the need to search for a theoretical framework to study coping in psychosis. A critical analysis is made of the Lazarus and Folkman model, both in the general sphere of illness and in the area of psychosis. The article ends with a discussion of the importance of this theoretical framework and a proposal for some modifications for its use in the sphere of psychotic patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galán Rodríguez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perona Garcelán, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se defiende la necesidad de buscar un marco teórico para estudiar el afrontamiento en psicóticos. Se hace un análisis crítico del modelo de Lazarus y Folkman, tanto en el ámbito general del enfermar como en el de la psicosis. Se concluye planteando la conveniencia de este marco teórico y proponiendo algunas modificaciones para su uso en el ámbito de los enfermos psicóticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(4): 563-570, nov. 2001.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Algunas aportaciones críticas en torno a la búsqueda de un marco teórico del afrontamiento en la psicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14544^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
