<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054288</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">X-linked Kallmann's syndrome: intra and interfamilial heterogeneity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Hypogonadotropic hypogonadism and anosmia characterize Kallmann's syndrome, whose X-linked form is due to mutations in the KAL1 gene. We studied a family with 6 affected members. Patients and method: We compare their clinical (chryptorchidism, micropenis, puberty, associated malformations), analytical (gonadotrophin releasing hormone test, and human chorionic gonadotropin test), genetic (cariotype), and radiological data of the described familiar cases with other reported sporadic cases. Results: The described cases carried the R191X mutation. We found phenotypic heterogeneity between the patients. Conclusions: We report the first familiar cases of Kallmann's syndrome due to the R191X mutation. Probably other genes and/or epigenetic factors determine the phenotype</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colino, Esmeralda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loidi, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El síndrome de Kallmann se caracteriza por hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo y anosmia, y su forma ligada al cromosoma X se debe a mutaciones en el gen KAL1. Estudiamos a una familia con 6 miembros afectados por dicho síndrome. Pacientes y método: Comparamos las características clínicas (criptorquidia, micropene, pubertad, malformaciones asociadas), analíticas (test de la hormona liberadora de gonadotropinas y test de gonadotropina coriónica humana), genéticas (cariotipo) y radiológicas de los casos familiares con las de otros casos esporádicos de la bibliografía. Resultados: Los casos descritos eran portadores de la mutación R191X. Encontramos una gran heterogeneidad fenotípica entre los casos familiares y esporádicos de esta mutación. Conclusiones: Describimos los primeros casos conocidos de síndrome de Kallmann por la mutación R191X. Probablemente otros genes y/o factores epigenéticos influyen en el fenotipo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(20): 777-779, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Kallmann ligado al cromosoma X: heterogeneidad interfamiliar e intrafamiliar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30678^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37289^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
