<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99472</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sodium intake in the diet of a group of adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Changes in the dietary habits of the population have led to an increase of sodium intake, mainly due to the great intake of manufactured products and the low consumption of homemade foods. These changes are especially important among adolescents, since they frequently include soft drinks, snacks or fast-food in their diets, foods with a high salt content or including sodium-rich additives. It is known the strong relationship between dietary sodium intake and blood pressure: a high sodium intake is related with hypertension and also with cardiovascular diseases. Moreover, sodium intake is associated with increased urinary calcium, therefore increasing bone losses. This fact might be an important risk factor for osteoporosis development. In the present study a dietary questionnaire was realized to 21 male adolescents aged 11-14 years, in order to calculate the sodium intake under their habitual diet and the contribution of the different food sources. The food intake was monitored during a 3-day period, by combining a 24-hour diet recall and two-days weighed dietary record. Data of food consumption were transformed into energy and nutrient vales using tables of food composition. Adolescents consumed an average of 4558 mg/day of sodium, overcoming in a great amount the current recommendations for this micronutrient. Canned and precooked foods contributed the highest percentage of the element in the diet (23.5%). According to these data, it would be extremely advisable to reduce sodium intake among adolescents, avoiding especially excessive processed food consumption, rich in sodium. These actions would be aimed to preventing possible diseases in adulthood such as hypertension and osteoporosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesías, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seiquer, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cambios en los hábitos alimentarios de la población han conducido a un incremento en la ingesta de sodio, debido, fundamentalmente, al aumento del consumo de alimentos de fabricación industrial, en detrimento de los preparados en el hogar. Estos cambios se acentúan especialmente en el colectivo adolescente, ya que frecuentemente incluyen en su dieta refrescos, snacks o fast-food, con elevado contenido de sal o aditivos con sodio. Es conocida la relación directa entre la ingesta dietética de sodio y la presión sanguínea, asociándose una ingesta elevada a hipertensión y a enfermedades cardiovasculares. Además, el sodio puede incrementar la eliminación de calcio en la orina, potenciando las pérdidas óseas, por lo que puede ser un factor de riesgo importante para el desarrollo de osteoporosis. En este estudio se realizó una encuesta alimentaria a 21 adolescentes varones de 11-14 años, con el fin de estimar la ingesta de sodio en su dieta habitual y la contribución de los distintos grupos de alimentos. Para ello se evaluó la ingesta de tres días, mediante recordatorio de 24 horas y registro de ingesta de dos días. Los datos del consumo de alimentos fueron transformados en valores de energía y nutrientes mediante tablas de composición de los alimentos. Los adolescentes consumieron una media de 4558 mg de sodio/día, superando en gran medida las recomendaciones actuales del micronutriente. Las conservas y precocinados fueron los alimentos que proporcionaron el mayor porcentaje del elemento en la dieta (23,5%). Debido al elevado consumo de sodio entre los adolescentes, se recomienda disminuir su ingesta, evitando especialmente un consumo excesivo de alimentos procesados, ricos en sodio. Con esto se pretende prevenir posibles problemas de salud en el futuro, como hipertensión u osteoporosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 145-152, jul. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de sodio en la dieta de un colectivo de adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7154^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13349^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13349^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
