<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141496</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gadolinium-based contrast agents for magnetic resonance imaging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gadolinium-based contrast agents are increasingly being used in magnetic resonance imaging. These agents can improve the contrast in images and provide information about function and metabolism, increasing both sensitivity and specificity. We describe the gadolinium-based contrast agents that have been approved for clinical use, detailing their main characteristics based on their chemical structure, stability, and safety. In general terms, these compounds are safe. Nevertheless, adverse reactions, the possibility of nephrotoxicity from these compounds, and the possibility of developing nephrogenic systemic fibrosis will be covered in this article. Lastly, the article will discuss the current guidelines, recommendations, and contraindications for their clinical use, including the management of pregnant and breast-feeding patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Muñoz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcin, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Álvarez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los medios de contraste basados en gadolinio son cada vez más utilizados en estudios de resonancia magnética. Son capaces de mejorar el contraste en las imágenes y aportar información sobre la función y el metabolismo, aumentando la sensibilidad así como la especificidad diagnóstica. Se describen los diferentes medios de contraste basados en gadolinio aprobados para uso clínico actualmente, sus características principales en base a su estructura química, estabilidad y seguridad. En términos generales son compuestos seguros. No obstante, las reacciones adversas producidas, la posible nefrotoxicidad inducida por estos compuestos, así como la posibilidad de desarrollar fibrosis sistémica nefrogénica serán temas tratados en la presente publicación. Por último, se mencionarán las actuales guías, recomendaciones y contraindicaciones en cuanto a su utilización en el ámbito clínico, incluyendo el manejo en pacientes gestantes y en la lactancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(supl.1): 21-28, jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contrastes basados en gadolinio utilizados en resonancia magnética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5821^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5821^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5821</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
