<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133178</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the economic crisis on the activity of a clinical research ethics committee</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Analyse the impact of economic and social crisis in volume and funding of clinical trials (CT) and observational studies(ES) from the activity of an Research Ethics Committee (REC).Method: REC memories 2003-2012 were reviewed. Financing of evaluated projects, CT and OS were analyzed classifying them into four groups: 1) promoted by pharmaceutical industry, 2) by scientific societies with industry support, 3) by scientific societies with government support and 4) unfunding. Two periods were compared: pre-crisis (2003-2007) and crisis (2008-2012).Results: During 10 studied years, 744 protocols were evaluated: a 71% of group 1, a 9% of group 2, a 3% of group 3 and a17% was no funding. Regarding OS, 40%, 5,4%, 8,6% and46% were the groups 1, 2, 3 and 4 respectively. Analyzing crisis versus pre-crisis period, statistically significant differences were observed in the decreasing of number of CT phase 2 and 3 and in the rising EO. Comparing crisis related to the pre-crisis period, the Group 4 increased statistically significantly. Conclusions: Evolution of total number of studies evaluated by REC tends to be maintained and even increased over time. REC maintains its activity and even increased at the expense of financing and unfunded OS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March López, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pla, Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Capafons, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcenillas, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar el impacto de la crisis económico-social en volumen y financiación de los ensayos clínicos (EC) y estudios observacionales (EO) a partir de la actividad de un Comité Ético de Investigación Clínica (CEIC).Método: Se revisaron las memorias del CEIC desde 2003 hasta2012. Se analizó la financiación de los EC y los EO clasificándolos en cuatro grupos: 1) promovidos por la industria farmacéutica,2) por sociedades científicas con soporte de la industria, 3)por sociedades apoyadas por las administraciones públicas y 4)sin financiación. Se compararon dos períodos: precrisis (2003-2007) y crisis (2008-2012).Resultados: Se evaluaron 744 protocolos: un 71% del grupo1, un 9% del grupo 2, un 3% del grupo 3 y un 17% carecía de financiación. En cuanto a los EO, un 40%, un 5,4%,un 8,6% y un 46% correspondían a los grupos 1, 2, 3 y 4respectivamente. Analizando periodo crisis versus precrisis, se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el número de los EC de fase 2 y fase 3 que disminuyeron yen los EO que aumentaron. En el periodo crisis respecto al precrisis, el Grupo 4 aumentó de manera estadísticamente significativa .Conclusiones: La evolución del número total de estudios evaluados por el CEIC tiende a mantenerse e incluso incrementarse en el tiempo. El CEIC mantiene su actividad e incluso la incrementa, a expensas de EO con y sin financiación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;38(6): 454-460, nov.-dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la crisis económica en la actividad de un comité ético de investigación clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36367^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
