<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140313</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic role of 18 F-FDG-PET or PET/CT in salivary gland tumors: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Salivary gland tumors are rare neoplasms that have not been extensively studied with 18 F-FDG-PET- or PET/CT up to now. This  review aims to evaluate the diagnostic performance of PET in this particular setting, analyzing the available literature. A comprehensive literature search in the PubMed/MEDLINE, Embase and Scopus databases was performed including articles up to November 2014, resulting in the selection of 22 articles. The studies selected suggest that: (1) PET is not useful in discriminating benign from malignant SGTs because of the overlap of uptake in both conditions; (2) PET not only is complementary to conventional imaging techniques for the staging and restaging but in some cases could also be superior to them; (3) PET may often have a highly positive impact on clinical decision making. Despite many limitations affecting the analysis, PET seems to be useful in SGTs. However, more extensive studies and cost-effectiveness analyses are desirable to determine its correct position in the diagnostic flow chart (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nicolai, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maroldi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Treglia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertoli, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lombardi, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giubbini, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertagna, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mattavelli, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores de las glándulas salivales son neoplasias raras que no han sido ampliamente estudiadas con PET o PET/TAC 18 F-FDG hasta el momento. Esta revisión tiene como objetivo evaluar el rendimiento diagnóstico de la PET en este contexto particular, analizando la literatura disponible. Se seleccionaron 22 artículos a partir de una búsqueda exhaustiva en las bases de datos PubMed/MEDLINE, Embase y Scopus hasta noviembre de 2014. Los estudios seleccionados sugieren que: 1) la PET no es útil para discriminar entre tumores de glándulas salivares benignos y malignos debido a la superposición de los niveles de captación en ambas situaciones; 2) la PET no es sólo complementaria a las técnicas de imagen convencionales para la estadificación y reestadificación, pudiendo ser en algunos casos superior; 3) a menudo la PET puede tener un gran impacto positivo en la toma de decisiones clínicas. A pesar de limitaciones que afectan el análisis, la PET parece ser útil en tumores de las glándulas salivares, si bien sería deseable la realización de estudios más amplios, así como el análisis de coste-efectividad para determinar su posición correcta en el diagrama de flujo diagnóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);34(5): 2995-302, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel diagnóstico de la PET o PET/TAC con 18 F-FDG en los tumores de las glándulas salivares: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37296^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37296^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
