<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135035</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications in brachial plexus surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Although traumatic brachial plexus injuries are relatively rare in trauma patients, their effects on the functionality of the upper limb can be very disabling. The authors&#146; objective was to assess the complications in a series of patients operated for brachial plexus injuries. Material and method: This was a retrospective evaluation of patients operated on by the authors between August 2009 and March 2013. Results: We performed 36 surgeries on 33 patients. The incidence of complications was 27.7%. Of these, only 1 (2.7%) was considered serious and associated with the procedure (iatrogenic injury of brachial artery). There was another serious complication (hypoxia in patients with airway injury) butit was not directly related to the surgical procedure. All other complications were considered minor (wound dehiscence, hematoma, infection). There was no mortality in our series. Conclusions: The complications in our series are similar to those reported in the literature. Serious complications (vascular, neural) are rare and represent less than 5% in all the different series. Given the rate of surgical complications and the poor functional perspective for a brachial plexus injury without surgery, we believe that surgery should be the treatment of choice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moragues, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suarez, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinazzo, Samantha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Si bien las lesiones traumáticas de plexo braquial son relativamente poco frecuentes en pacientes politraumatizados, sus efectos sobre la funcionalidad del miembro superior pueden ser muy invalidantes. Los autores se proponen evaluar las complicaciones de una serie de pacientes operados por lesiones de plexo braquial. Material y método Evaluación retrospectiva de pacientes operados por los autores entre agosto del 2009 y marzo del 2013.ResultadosSe realizaron 36 cirugías en 33 pacientes. La incidencia de complicaciones fue del 27,7%. Del total, solo una (2,7%) fue considerada grave y asociada al procedimiento (lesión iatrogénica de arteria humeral). Hubo otra complicación grave (hipoxia en paciente con lesión de vía aérea) pero sin relación directa con el procedimiento quirúrgico. El resto de las complicaciones fueron consideradas como menores (dehiscencia de herida, hematoma, infección). No hubo mortalidad en nuestra serie. Conclusiones Las complicaciones en nuestra serie es similar a lo publicado en la literatura. Las complicaciones graves (vasculares, neurales) son poco frecuentes y en todas las series consultadas representan menos del 5%. Dada la tasa de complicaciones de la cirugía y la pobre perspectiva funcional de una lesión de plexo braquial sin operar, creemos que la cirugía debe ser la opción de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);26(2): 73-77, mar.-abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones de la cirugía del plexo braquial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
