<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145996</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The first-line option in the treatment of patients with advanced fibrosis and cirrhosis due to genotype 1 hepatitis C virus is currently triple therapy with boceprevir/telaprevir and pegylated interferon-ribavirin. However, certain limitations could constitute a barrier to starting treatment or achieving sustained viral response in these patients. These limitations include the patient's or physician's perception of treatment effectiveness in routine clinical practice -which can weight against the decision to start treatment-, the advanced stage of the disease with portal hypertension and comorbidity, treatment interruption due to poor adherence, and adverse effects, mainly anemia. In addition, it is now possible to identify patients who could benefit from a shorter therapeutic regimen with a similar cure rate. This review discusses these issues and their possible effect on the use of triple therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Gómez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Guerra, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turnes, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albillos, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de los pacientes con fibrosis hepática avanzada y cirrosis por el virus de la hepatitis C en su modalidad de terapia triple con boceprevir/telaprevir e interferón pegilado-ribavirina representa actualmente la primera opción terapéutica en la mayoría de los pacientes con genotipo 1. Sin embargo, hay cuestiones que pueden constituir una barrera para iniciar el tratamiento o alcanzar la respuesta viral sostenida en este tipo de pacientes. Estas limitaciones van desde la percepción por parte del médico o paciente sobre la eficacia del tratamiento en la práctica clínica habitual, y que pueden desviarnos de la decisión de iniciar el tratamiento, grado avanzado de enfermedad con hipertensión portal y comorbilidad, hasta su interrupción por la mala adherencia y los efectos adversos, fundamentalmente la anemia. Por otra parte, actualmente se puede identificar pacientes que se benefician de un régimen terapéutico más corto, sin detrimento de una similar tasa de curación. En la presente revisión se evalúan estos aspectos y su posible interferencia en el uso de triple terapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;37(supl.1): 13-22, jul. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia triple en pacientes con fibrosis avanzada y cirróticos: aspectos relevantes en la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29469^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54578^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12663^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
