<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79817</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydromorphone: an option in the treatment of pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The analgesics opioids are one of the fundamental props in the pharmacological treatment of the moderate and severe pain, particularly in chronic oncology pain. The hydromorphone molecule is structurally very similar to morphine and it may be administered enterally or parenterally. It binds mainly to &amp;#956; opioid receptors and to a lesser extent to &amp;#948; receptors. The binding to the &amp;#956; receptor is responsible for the analgesic effect as well as for the appearance of side effects. Hydromorphone is available in 12-hour and 24-hour slow-release presentations. A 24-hour sustained release preparation has recently come available on the market in Spain which uses the OROS push-pull system. In the treatment of the acute pain, the clinical evidence demonstrates that hydromorphone has similar analgesic equivalence to other opioids. Treatment of oncological pain has been evaluated compared to other opioids and with different formulations, demonstrating it to be a drug equivalent to morphine as regards its analgesic effectiveness and side effects. There are no controlled clinical trials on the use of hydromorphone in the treatment of chronic nononcological pain. Conclusions, hydromorphone has a pharmacological profile, analgesic properties and side effects similar to morphine, but there is still controversy as regards hydromorphone-morphine equivalent doses and the oral-parenteral dose (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arizaga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Postigo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los analgésicos opioides constituyen uno de los pilares fundamentales en el tratamiento farmacológico del dolor moderado-grave, especialmente en el dolor agudo y el crónico oncológico. La molécula de hidromorfona es estructuralmente muy similar a la morfina, se puede administrar tanto por vía enteral como por vía parenteral, y se une principal-mente a los receptores opioides &amp;#956; y en menor grado a los receptores &amp;#948;. La unión a receptores tipo u es la causa del efecto analgésico, así como de los efectos secundarios. La hidromorfona se encuentra disponible en presentaciones de liberación inmediata y prolongada durante 12 o 24 horas. Recientemente, se ha comercializado en España una preparación de liberación sostenida durante 24 horas que utilizan el sistema OROS Puhs-Pull®. En el tratamiento del dolor agudo, la evidencia clínica demuestra que la hidromorfona presenta una equivalencia analgésica similar a otros opiodes. Respecto al tratamiento del dolor oncológico, se ha evaluado respecto a otros opioides y con diferentes formulaciones, y se ha observado que es un fármaco equivalente a la morfina en cuanto a eficacia analgésica y efectos secundarios. En el tratamiento del dolor crónico no oncológico, no hay ensayos clínicos controlados que otorguen evidencia científica a la hidromorfona en estos pacientes. Como conclusión, la hidromorfona presenta un perfil farmacológico, propiedades analgésicas y efectos secundarios similares a la morfina, todavía persisten ciertas controversias en lo referente a las dosis equianalgésicas entre la hidromorfona y la morfina y entre la dosis oral y la parenteral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(3): 153-161, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hidromorfona: una alternativa en el tratamiento del dolor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4131^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4131^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
