<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144096</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Controlled non-heart beating donor lung transplantation: Initial experience in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although the number of lung transplants in Spain is increasing annually, more organs are required to ease waiting lists. Controlled non-heart beating donors (NHBD) (Maastricht III) are a reality at international level, and contribute significantly to increasing donor numbers. In this study, we present our NHBD protocol and the initial experience in Spain using lung grafts from this type of donor. Three bilateral lung transplants were performed between January 2012 and December 2014. Preservation was by ex-vivo lung perfusion in 2 cases and by traditional cold ischemia in the other. None of the patients developed grade 3 primary graft dysfunction, no in-hospital mortality was recorded and 1-year survival was 100%. These initial results, and international experience, should help to develop similar protocols to encourage the use of controlled non-heart beating donors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela de Ugarte, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyos-Mejía, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Redondo, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez de Antonio, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laporta-Hernández, Rosalía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo-Cañaveral de la Cruz, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque el número de trasplantes pulmonares en España es cada año mayor, es necesario aumentar el número de órganos disponibles para aliviar las listas de espera. Los donantes en asistolia controlada (DAC) (Maastricht III) son una realidad a nivel internacional y contribuyen significativamente a aumentar el número de donantes. En este trabajo presentamos nuestro protocolo de DAC y la experiencia inicial en España usando injertos pulmonares provenientes de este tipo de donantes. Desde enero 2012 a diciembre 2014, se han realizado 3 trasplantes pulmonares bilaterales. De ellos, en 2 casos se realizó preservación ex vivo y en el otro preservación tradicional en frío. Ninguno de los pacientes desarrolló disfunción primaria del injerto grado 3, no se registró mortalidad hospitalaria y la supervivencia al primer año fue del 100%. Estos resultados iniciales, y la experiencia internacional, deberían contribuir al desarrollo de protocolos similares para fomentar el aprovechamiento de los DAC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(9): e1-e3, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia inicial en trasplantes pulmonares con donantes en asistolia controlada en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10105^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8196</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
