<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91360</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity and mental health, an inseparable duet?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The interrelationship between mind and body has been subject ofdiscussion and study among philosophers and psychologists throughouthistory. The potential capacity of physical exercise on mentalhealth is known; however, this correlation has not been demonstratedsufficiently.Objective: the objective of this work was to analyse the availableknowledge on the effect of physical activity on mental health and thepossible explanation to this relationship.Methodology: a review of articles published in scientific journals wascarried out using the pair review method, databases (Pubmed, Dialnet)and human resources (Google, Scielo). The following tag wordsin Spanish and English were used in the search: &#147;physical exercise&#148;,&#147;physical activity&#148;, &#147;mental health&#148;, &#147;anxiety&#148; and &#147;depression&#148;. Thesearch was not temporarily limited in time. The selection of articlestook into account that the Works had to be originals available bothas free full text in English and Spanish. Data was gathered on theeffects of exercise on mental health as well as on the hypothesisproposed to exclude such relationship.Results and conclusions: the practice of regular physical exercisepresents physical as well as psychological benefits that are positivefor mental health and human quality of life. This appears to beorganically explained by the changes that exercise produces in thebrain. Physical exercise is related to less anxiety, with protectionagainst depression and with the relief of its symptoms, with preservationof cognitive function and improvement of self-esteem,motivation, self-control and self-efficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Gómez, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Torralba, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Charlo Bernardos, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriarte Ramos, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaera Alquézar, Ana Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La interrelación entre la mente y el cuerpo ha sido objeto de discusióny estudio entre filósofos y psicólogos desde tiempos históricos.Se conoce la capacidad potencial del ejercicio físico sobre la salud mental,sin embargo, su eficacia no está suficientemente demostrada.Objetivo: el objetivo de este trabajo ha sido analizar el conocimientoexistente sobre el efecto de la actividad física en la salud mental y laposible explicación de dicha relación.Metodología: se realizó una revisión de artículos publicados en revistascon revisión por pares, empleando bases de datos (Pubmed,Dialnet) y recursos electrónicos (Google, Scielo). Para las búsquedasse utilizaron las siguientes palabras clave, en español y en inglés:&#147;ejercicio físico&#148;, &#147;actividad física&#148;, &#147;salud mental&#148;, &#147;ansiedad&#148; y &#147;depresión&#148;.No se limitó la búsqueda temporalmente. La selección deartículos tuvo en cuenta que fueran trabajos originales disponiblesa texto completo gratuito en español e inglés. Se recogió informaciónsobre los efectos del ejercicio en la salud mental, así como delas hipótesis propuestas para explicar dicha relación.Resultados y conclusiones: la práctica regular de ejercicio físicopresenta beneficios físicos y psicológicos que resultan positivos parala salud mental y la calidad de vida del ser humano, lo que parecetener su explicación orgánica en los cambios que la actividad físicaproduce en el cerebro. El ejercicio físico tiene relación con la disminuciónde la ansiedad, con la protección frente a la depresión y conel alivio de sus síntomas, con la preservación de la función cognitivay con la mejora en autoestima, motivación, autocontrol y la autoeficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(5): 64-69, jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad física y salud mental ¿dúo inseparable?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
