<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85384</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking-attributable deaths in Spain, 2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: This study estimates smoking-attributable mortality in Spain in 2006. Population and method: Source data included 1) smoking prevalence in Spain; 2) deaths occurred in Spain; and 3) relative risks of mortality by tobacco-caused diseases drawn from the Cancer Prevention Study II. All data corresponded to individuals aged 35 years and older. Results: In 2006, 53,155 smoking-attributable deaths were estimated (14.7% of all deaths occurred in individuals &amp;#8805; 35 years; 25.1% in men and 3.4% in women). Almost 90% (47,174) of these attributable deaths corresponded to men, and 11.3% (5,981) to women. The most frequent attributable deaths were: cancer (24,058), specially lung cancer (16,482), cardiovascular disease (17,560), specially ischemic heart disease (6,263) and stroke (4,283), and respiratory disease (11,537), specially chronic obstructive lung disease (9,886). Since 2001, a decrease in smoking-attributable mortality was observed in men and an increase in women. Conclusions:About one out of 7 deaths occurring annually in individuals &amp;#8805; 35 years in Spain is attributable to smoking (one in 4 in men and one in 29 in women). Despite a decreasing trend in the number of smoking-attributable deaths over time (except in women, where they increase), the toll of estimated attributable deaths is still very high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bañuelos Marco, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ruiz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Álvarez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba García, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Moreno, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Trullén, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Enríquez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Gañán, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Estimar la mortalidad atribuible al consumo de tabaco en España en 2006, y compararla con las estimaciones de años anteriores. Población y método:A partir de la prevalencia de tabaquismo y la mortalidad correspondientes a España, y los riesgos relativos de muerte por enfermedades causadas por el tabaquismo, procedentes del Cancer Prevention Study II, se ha calculado la mortalidad atribuible al tabaquismo en los individuos de edad &amp;#8805; 35 años. Resultados: En el año 2006 se produjeron 53.155 muertes atribuibles al tabaquismo en individuos &amp;#8805; 35 años, lo que supone el 14,7% (25,1% en varones y 3,4% en mujeres) de todas las muertes ocurridas en los mismos. El 88,7% (47.174) de estas muertes atribuibles corresponde a varones y el 11,3% (5.981) a mujeres. Por causas, destacan las muertes atribuibles por: tumores malignos (24.058), especialmente cáncer de pulmón (16.482), enfermedades cardiovasculares (17.560), especialmente cardiopatía isquémica (6.263) e ictus (4.283), y enfermedades respiratorias (11.537), especialmente enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (9.886). Desde el año 2001 prosigue el descenso en la mortalidad atribuible en los varones y el ascenso en las mujeres.Conclusiones: Una de cada 7 muertes ocurridas cada año en individuos mayores de 35 años en España es atribuible al consumo de tabaco (una de cada 4 en varones y una de cada 29 en mujeres). A pesar del descenso de las muertes atribuibles al tabaquismo respecto a años anteriores (excepto en las mujeres, en quienes aumenta), este número de muertes y el porcentaje de la mortalidad total que representa sigue siendo muy elevado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);136(3): 97-102, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad atribuible al consumo de tabaco en España en 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
