<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114503</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of patients with pulmonary embolism: Complications and developments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the survival after two years in consecutive patients diagnosed of pulmonary embolism (PE), thrombotic relapse and episodes of bleeding. Patients and Method: Cohort study of patients diagnosed consecutively of PE, with a two-year follow-up, analyzing survival and long-term complications (relapse and bleeding). Results: 165 consecutive patients diagnosed of PE were initially included in the study., Seventeen died during an acute event, .and 148 patients were finally included in the study, of which 50% were males, with mean age = 64.17 + 17.23 years. During follow-up, 34 patients died (23%), 5 were lost (3.4%), 13 relapsed (8.8%) and 16 (10.8%) suffered bleeding. Relapse appeared as PE (n=6), deep vein thrombosis (DVT) (n=6) or PE with DVT (n=1). Six of the patients with relapse initially appeared as idiopathic PE and seven of them as secondary PE. Of the 13 patients with relapse, 2 died after the two-year follow-up and none as a consequence of the relapse. In terms of bleeding, this event appeared 3.23 month (average, extreme range= 28.17 months) after an acute event; 37.5% were major bleeding events. The most frequent cause of death was cancer. The accumulated mortality incidence was 19.2% after one year and 29.6% after two years. The variables associated with less survival were serum creatinine greater than 2 mg/dl, the existence of prior neoplasm, dementia and dyslipidemia. Conclusions: Follow-up of PE patients must be strict during the first few months, as this is when the complications appear (death, relapse and hemorrhaging) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Galván, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Matute, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías-Hernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero-Candelera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ugarte-Fornell, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara-Palomares, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la supervivencia a 2 años de pacientes consecutivos diagnosticados de EP, las recidivas trombóticas y los eventos hemorrágicos. Pacientes y Método: Estudio de cohorte de pacientes diagnosticados de forma consecutiva de EP seguidos durante dos años, analizando la supervivencia y las complicaciones a largo plazo (recidivas y hemorragia).Resultados: 165 pacientes diagnosticados de forma consecutiva de EP, 17 fallecieron durante el evento agudo. Se incluyeron en el estudio 148 pacientes, 50% varones, con una edad de 64.17 +/- 17.23 años. Durante el seguimiento fallecieron 34 pacientes (23%), se perdieron 5 (3.4%), recidivaron 13 (8.8%) y 16 (10.8%) presentaron sangrado. Las recidivas se presentaron como EP (n=6), trombosis venosa profunda (TVP) (n=6) o EP con TVP (n=1). Seis de los pacientes con recidiva se presentaron inicialmente como EP idiopático, y 7 de ellos como EP secundario. De los 13 pacientes que presentaron recidiva, 2 fallecieron a los 2 años de seguimiento, y ninguno como consecuencia de la recidiva. En cuanto al sangrado, éste se produjo a los 3.23 meses (rango 28.17 meses) del evento agudo; el 37.5% fueron sangrados mayores. La causa de muerte más frecuente fue el cáncer. La incidencia acumulada de mortalidad fue del 19.2% al año y del 29.6% a los dos años. Las variables asociadas a una menor supervivencia fueron una creatinina mayor de 2 mg/dl, la existencia de neoplasia previa, la demencia y la dislipemia. Conclusiones: el seguimiento de los pacientes con EP debe ser más estrecho en los primeros meses, ya que en este periodo de tiempo se producen las complicaciones de la enfermedad (muerte, recidivas y hemorragias) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;25(2): 109-115, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento del paciente con embolismo pulmonar: complicaciones y evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
