<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86054</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Satisfied companion, a quality indicator in emergencies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the level of satisfaction of the accompanying person in the Emergency Department and to identify main factors that could influence satisfaction and to establish areas of improvement. Methodology. A retrospective descriptive study of family or companion of patients seen in the Emergency Department. A randomised telephone questionnaire was used. The statistics used were chi-squared for categorical variables and variance analysis for those showing a normal distribution. The analysis was made with the SPSS 16.0 programme. Results. A total of 117 responses were received, from a minimum sample size of 90. The demographic characteristics of the accompanying person did not influence the evaluation of the satisfaction, unlike of other studies. The fact of accompanying the patient and receiving periodic information showed differences in overall satisfaction of the accompanying person, as well as the waiting time. A long waiting time and the lack of company were the most frequent reasons for dissatisfaction. The accompanying person emphasised the feeling of isolation of the patient, the lack of health personnel, the long wait for assistance and the location of facilities. Conclusions. Rapid assistance, facilities for the accompanying person, information, empathy and friendliness are the factors which are the most appreciated when they come to Emergency Department(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogales-Cortés, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Tirado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Guijarro, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar el grado de satisfacción de los acompañantes de los usuarios del servicio de urgencias, identificar factores que puedan influir en su satisfacción y establecer las áreas de mejora. Método. Estudio retrospectivo descriptivo. Se incluyó en el estudio a los familiares y/o acompañantes del paciente durante su estancia en urgencias. El muestreo fue aleatorio sistemático y como instrumento se utilizó una encuesta telefónica. En el análisis bivariable, se utilizó el estadístico &amp;#967;2 para variables categóricas y análisis de varianza para las de distribución continua. El análisis se realizó con el programa SPSS 16.0. Resultados. Se obtuvieron 117 respuestas, frente a un tamaño muestral mínimo de 90. Las características sociodemográficas del acompañante no influyeron en la valoración de la satisfacción, a diferencia de otras investigaciones. Estar acompañando al paciente y recibir información periódica supusieron diferencias en la satisfacción general de los acompañantes, así como el tiempo de espera. La demora en la atención tras el primer contacto y la falta de acompañamiento fueron los motivos de insatisfacción más frecuentes. Los familiares destacaron como aspectos más negativos: la sensación de aislamiento del enfermo, la falta de personal, la demora en la asistencia, la ubicación y las instalaciones. Conclusiones. Rapidez en la asistencia, facilidades de acompañamiento, información, empatía y trato amable son las dimensiones que los acompañantes más valoran cuando acuden a un servicio de urgencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(1): 47-53, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acompañante satisfecho, un indicador de calidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
