<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65750</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ethanol extracts of the pneumatophores of Xylocarpus moluccensis (Family: Meliaceae) and Heritiera fomes (Family: Sterculiaceae) were assessed for in vitro antibacterial activities against a number of bacterial strains using the disc diffusion assay. Both extracts showed similar antibacterial profiles, and the zones of inhibitions were &gt;10 mm in the most cases. These extracts exhibited the most prominent activity against Enterobacter aerogenes, with the zones of inhibition of 19 and 21 mm, respectively. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined by the broth dilution method. The extract of X. moluccensis was the most potent against Shigella boydii and Shigella sonnie (MIC = 200 and 300 mg/mL, respectively). It can be assumed that that X. moluccensis and H. fomes could be potential sources for novel &#145;lead&#146; discovery for antibacterial drug development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paul, SK</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Auzi, AA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uddin, SJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nahar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarker, SD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mondal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evaluó la actividad antibacteriana in vitro de los extractos de etanol de los neumatóforos de Xylocarpus moluccensis (Familia: Meliaceae) y Heritiera fomes (Familia: Sterculiaceae) frente a diversas cepas bacterianas utilizando el ensayo de difusión en disco. Ambos extractos presentaron perfiles antibacterianos similares, y las zonas de inhibición fueron &gt;10 mm en la mayoría de los casos. Estos extractos presentaron la máxima actividad frente a aerógenos Enterobacter, siendo las zonas de inhibición de 19 y 21 mm, respectivamente. La concentración inhibitoria mínima(CIM) se determinó mediante el método de dilución en caldo de cultivo. El extracto de X. moluccensis fue el más potente frente a Shigella boydii y Shigella sonnie (CIM = 200 y 300 mg/mL, respectivamente). Se puede asumirque X. moluccensis y H. fomes podrían ser fuentes potenciales de nuevos descubrimientos para el desarrollo de fármacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;49(1): 77-82, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65750</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12862^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13139^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35302^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15139^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35883^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13142^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4834^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22927^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23292^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23292^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35946^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
