<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103942</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anatomy of the airway: anaesthetic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The difficult airway and its management have always been studied by anaesthetist with great interest but also with fear and concern. This situation has changed considerably in the last few years due to the great variety of machinery and artefacts available. Despite this, all of the techniques that are used today require the knowledge and clear understanding of the local anatomy. Some of the more recent techniques, like the nasal intubation in awake patients, need a very accurate knowledge of the vascularization and precisely, the innervation of certain structures. We will also use some of our final words discussing ultrasound assessment of the airway, as a new application to difficult intubation, but of course, its real efficiency will need to be tested in further studies. With this paper we start a series of chapters devoted to the anatomy and examination of the airway and the different methods to predict a difficult airway (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molano Díaz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flor Robledo, M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bertos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El manejo de la vía aérea, la correcta ventilación y oxigenación es un tema de constante preocupación para los anestesiólogos. Su manejo, gracias a la variedad de dispositivos disponibles en el mercado, ha cambiado mucho en los últimos años. Todas las técnicas que empleamos requieren amplios conocimientos anatómicos. Algunas, como la anestesia de la vía aérea para la intubación con el paciente despierto, precisan del reconocimiento de la vascularización e inervación de las estructuras anatómicas. Finalmente, dedicamos unas líneas a la ecografía de la vía aérea, cuya aplicación es novedosa y su eficacia real está aún por demostrar. Con este artículo iniciamos una serie de capítulos dedicados a la anatomía y exploración de la vía aérea, la realización de una valoración adecuada de la vía aérea y la prediccción de una vía aérea difícil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;17(2): 35-43, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anatomía de la vía aérea: implicaciones anestésicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12557^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10347^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10803^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14449^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54205^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14524^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8009^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
