<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116137</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotion, verbal context and facial expression perception: Tell me who you are and I will tell you how I perceive you</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Verbal context in the perception of facial expression facilitates the activation of conceptual knowledge through which is interpreted. With the aim of analyzing how emotion, via verbal context, modulates valence, arousal and control levels in the perception of facial expression, a first experiment was performed in which verbal context was generated using words with emotional content (positive, negative), prior to recognition of an expression mixed with happiness and sadness. In a second experiment, while maintaining both verbal and facial expression context neutral, a positive or negative affective state was induced either before or after the coding of verbal context. In the first experiment, the positive verbal context condition facilitated the face mixed with happiness to be perceived as an expression of greater security/trust (control) with respect to the face mixed with sadness. In the second experiment, the positive emotion induced prior to coding the verbal context produced the face to be perceived as having an expression of greater activation with respect to when the emotion was negative. The results are discussed from constructivist model of emotion</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gordillo León, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Héctor Lozano Bleda, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mestas Hernánez, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Nieto, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana Martínez, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, Rafael Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La percepción de la expresión facial en un contexto verbal facilita la activación del conocimiento conceptual a través del cual es interpretada. Con el objetivo de analizar cómo la emoción, a través del contexto verbal, modula la percepción de la expresión facial en sus niveles de valencia, activación y control, se realizó un primer experimento en el que se generó el contexto verbal mediante palabras de contenido emocional (positivo, negativo), antes del reconocimiento de una expresión mixta de alegría y tristeza. En un segundo experimento, manteniendo neutros tanto contexto verbal como expresión facial, se indujo un estado afectivo positivo o negativo, antes o después de la codificación del contexto verbal. En el primer experimento, la condición de contexto verbal positivo facilitó que la cara mixta de alegría se percibiera con una expresión de mayor seguridad/confianza (control) respecto a la cara mixta de tristeza. En el segundo experimento, la emoción positiva inducida de manera previa a la codificación del contexto verbal, generó que la cara se percibiera con una expresión de mayor activación, respecto a cuando la emoción fue negativa. Se discuten los resultados a partir del modelo constructivista de la emoción</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;19(2/3): 131-147, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Emoción, contexto verbal y percepción de la expresión verbal: Dime quién eres y te diré cómo te percibo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5250</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
