<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82101</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attachment: further an inspiring concept</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attachment Theory has provided important concepts to explain human relationships; nevertheless, the use of this theory is often very simple and doesn&#146;t respect its key concepts. Three theoretical aspects to take into consideration are analyzed: the attachment classification, the transmission of attachment patterns along the generations, and the attachment disorders. Also, three important opened matters about attachment are reviewed: the right definition of the concept, its use in practical settings (assessment and treatment), and the limits of the concept. Finally, attachment is set in a wider context where intersubjectivity occupies a main place to understand human behavior(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galán Rodríguez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Teoría del Apego ha proporcionado conceptos fundamentales para explicar las relaciones humanas; no obstante, el uso que se hace de esta teoría a menudo es muy simple y no respeta sus ideas centrales. Para ilustrarlo, se analizan tres aspectos teóricos a tener en cuenta: la clasificación de los tipos de apego, la transmisión intergeneracional de los patrones de apego, y los trastornos del apego. También se revisan tres importantes cuestiones a clarificar en relación al apego: su correcta definición, su uso en contextos aplicados (a nivel de evaluación y tratamiento), y los límites del concepto. Finalmente, el apego es situado en un contexto más amplio donde la intersubjetividad ocupa una posición central para comprender la conducta humana(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;30(108): 581-595, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82101</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El apego. Más allá de un concepto inspirador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1538^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1544^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
