<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90208</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Molecular subtypes of breast cancer: prognostic implications and clinical and immunohistochemical characteristics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Breast carcinomas are a heterogeneous groupof tumours, in both their clinical behavior and their prognosis.The aim of this article is to classify breast carcinomasaccording to molecular subtypes by means of immunohistochemicalmarkers and to analyse the clinicopathologicaland immunohistochemical characteristics and the patternsof survival and relapse of the different subtypes.Methods. Two hundred and seventy-two patients diagnosedwith breast cancer were classified into five subtypes: breastcarcinomas of the basal type, HER2 type, luminal A type,luminal B type and normal.Results. The most frequent breast carcinomas were: luminalA type carcinomas (62.5%), luminal B type carcinomas(18%), HER2 type carcinomas (9.9%), basal type carcinomas(8.4%) and normal phenotype carcinomas (1.4%). Significantlyand with greater frequency, the luminal type breastcarcinomas proved to be well differentiated tumours, ofsmall tumoral size, with negative axillary lymph nodes, at anearly stage at the time of diagnosis, with high levels of BCL-2 and a low Ki-67 proliferation index. On the contrary, thebasal type and HER2 carcinomas presented larger tumours,poorly differentiated, greater ganglionar involvement andmore advanced stages at the time of diagnosis. They expressedhigh Ki-67 proliferation indexes with greater frequencyand were the subtypes that showed a worse prognosis onglobal survival and progression-free survival curves.Conclusion. Breast cancer classification based on immunohistochemical(IHC) parameters makes a better prognosticdefinition possible. Both the basal type and the HER2 typebreast carcinomas present more unfavourable histopathologicaland IHC characteristics, as well as a worse survivaland less relapse time, while the luminal type breast carcinomasshow more benign characteristics and a better prognosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Beroiz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Grima, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba Iturriagagoitia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrechea Irigoyen, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Los carcinomas de mama representan un grupoheterogéneo de tumores, tanto en su comportamiento clínicocomo pronóstico. El objetivo del presente trabajo es clasificarlos carcinomas de mama en subtipos moleculares mediantemarcadores inmunohistoquímicos y analizar las característicasclinicopatológicas e inmunohistoquímicas y los patronesde supervivencia y recaída de los distintos subtipos.Material y métodos. Se han clasificado 272 pacientes condiagnóstico de carcinoma de mama en cinco subtipos: carcinomasde mama de tipo basal, de tipo HER2, de tipo luminalA, de tipo luminal B y normal.Resultados. Los carcinomas de mama más frecuentes fueronlos de tipo luminal A (62,5%), carcinomas de tipo luminal B(18%), carcinomas de tipo HER2 (9,9%), carcinomas de tipobasal (8,4%) y los de fenotipo normal (1,4%). Los carcinomasde mama de tipo luminal mostraron ser, con mayor frecuencia,de forma significativa, tumores bien diferenciados, depequeño tamaño tumoral, con ganglios axilares negativos,estadio precoz en el momento del diagnóstico, niveles altosde BCL-2 y bajo índice de proliferación con Ki-67. En cambio,los carcinomas de mama de tipo basal y HER2 presentabantumores de mayor tamaño, pobremente diferenciados, mayorcompromiso ganglionar y estadios más avanzados en elmomento del diagnóstico. Expresaban con mayor frecuenciaíndices de proliferación altos con Ki 67 y fueron los subtiposque en curvas de supervivencia global y de supervivencia librede progresión mostraron un peor pronóstico.Conclusión. La clasificación del cáncer de mama basada enparámetros inmunohistoquímicos (IHQ) permite una mejordefinición pronóstica. Tanto los carcinomas de mama detipo basal como HER2 presentan características histopatológicase IHQ más desfavorables así como peor supervivenciay menor tiempo de recaída mientras que los carcinomasde mama de tipo luminal manifiestan características másbenignas y mejor pronóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(2): 219-233, mayo-ago. 2011. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90208</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Subtipos moleculares del cáncer de mama: implicaciones pronósticas y características clínicas e inmunohistoquímicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
