<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75718</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Updating diagnosis and treatment in acute limb ischemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A systematic review of the medical literature was performed for relevant studies. We searched a number of electronic databasesand hand-searched relevant journals since January 2002 until November 2007. We considered studies in which diagnosisand treatment were evaluated to diminish the morbimortality. Isquemia acute of the extremity is defined as any abruptdiminution of the perfusión that causes a possible threat to the viability of the same one. Isquemia acute of continuous inferiorextremity associated to a high morbidity and mortality in spite of the advances in the perioperatorios cares and the techniquesof revascularización. In special the age patients outpost they are exposed to a high risk of local serious complicationsas as much sistémicas. The comorbidity, the metabolic upheavals associated to isquemia acute and the syndrome of reperfusiónare associate to this poor prognosis. In this article we set out an update in the handling of this type of patients presenting/displaying new features in diagnosis and treatment. For it we have made a revision of Literature published in the last5 years having centered in the works that contribute to new tools in diagnosis and treatment to us to reduce the high morbidityand mortality who present/display this type of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Marino, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpintero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Pedrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Río, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Blanco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La isquemia aguda de la extremidad es definida como cualquier disminución brusca de la perfusión que cause una posibleamenaza a la viabilidad de la misma. La isquemia aguda de extremidad inferior continua asociada a una alta morbilidady mortalidad a pesar de los avances en los cuidados perioperatorios y en las técnicas de revascularización. En especial lospacientes de edad avanzada están expuestos a un alto riesgo de complicaciones graves tanto locales como sistémicas. Lacomorbilidad, los trastornos metabólicos asociados a la isquemia aguda y el síndrome de reperfusión están asociados a estepobre pronóstico. En este artículo nos proponemos una actualización en el manejo de este tipo de pacientes presentandonovedades en diagnóstico y tratamiento. Para ello hemos realizado una revisión de la literatura publicada en los últimos 5años centrándonos en los trabajos que aportan nuevas herramientas en diagnóstico y tratamiento para reducir la elevadamorbilidad y mortalidad que presentan este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;11(1): 39-43, ene.-mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75718</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en diagnóstico y tratamiento de la isquemia aguda en extremidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30479^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23812^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
