<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159357</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity questionnaires for Spanish children and adolescents: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Questionnaires aimed at assessing the prevalence of physical activity are tools frequently used by health professionals. It is important to provide them with information about the characteristics and quality of these questionnaires. This systematic review aimed to identify and analyse the characteristics and psychometric properties of this type of questionnaires when administered to Spanish children and adolescents. A total of 14 questionnaires were found. Accurate validity values were obtained in two of them. Only two questionnaires obtained a score &gt;5 in the 'Qualitative Attributes and Measurement Properties of Physical Activity Questionnaires' checklist. Among the available questionnaires, the APALQ (9-18 years) and the ENERGY (12-14 years) seem to be the most accurate tools for assessing physical activity prevalence in Spanish children and adolescents, albeit with limitations that should be taken into account (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Lastra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cancela Carral, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valcarce Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Lemos, RI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayán Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuestionarios de valoración de la prevalencia de actividad física son herramientas muy empleadas por los profesionales de la salud. Es importante poner en su conocimiento la calidad y características de los mismos. Esta revisión sistemática tuvo como objetivo identificar y analizar las características y propiedades psicométricas de este tipo de cuestionarios cuando han sido aplicados a niños y adolescentes españoles. Se encontraron un total de 14 cuestionarios, obteniéndose valores de validez adecuados en dos de ellos. Solo dos cuestionarios obtuvieron una puntuación mayor que 5 sobre 10 en la evaluación de la calidad de sus propiedades de medida de acuerdo con la lista de comprobación Qualitative Atributes and Measurement Properties of Physical Activity Questionnaires. Los cuestionarios APALQ (9-18 años) y ENERGY (12-14 años), parecen ser, con sus limitaciones, los más adecuados de entre los disponibles para valorar la actividad física en niños y adolescentes españoles, contando ambos con limitaciones a considerar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;39(3): 417-428, sept.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159357</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionarios de actividad física para niños y adolescentes españoles: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
