<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95092</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological issues on patients with cancer: involvement to screening and appointment with psicooncologit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To know the cáncer patient´s characteristics assisted in the Psycho-Oncology, in Basurto Hospital Unit in order to improve the psychological assistance. Method: Retrospective and comparative research on demographic characteristics, medical, psychological and on visit in 115 cancer patients with psychotherapy treatment from 2001 to 2003. These patients are compared with 28 relative, 119 ordinary psychology patients, and with 120 cancer patients without psychological therapy. Results: The patients with cancer and psychological therapy are younger, they are in an expanded stage of the disease, with a decrease in the active medical treatments, and a worse prognoses. They have a familiar cancer history (background) and also psychological personal problems. 70% have a diagnostic DSM &#150;IV by means of a clinical interview, the adjustment disorders are the psychopathological diagnosis more frequent (80%) and it is associated with cancer context. Regarding the visit to the psychologist, doctors detect the psychological issues badly, being derived to the psychologist with very poor accurate, when the psychological issues are evident, even consolidated. Therefore, there is not much time left for a psychological therapy. Conclusion: cancer patients need psychological services specialized in this area, not only because the differences with the studied groups but also socio-demographic, medical and psychological characteristics. Methods of early diagnosis is needed to be introduced to meet the psychological issues of the cancer patient´s needs, to be sent to the Psycho-Oncology Unit, to enable its evaluation and treatment of the added distress of the illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>arana, Ziortza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las características de los pacientes con cáncer atendidos en la Unidad de Psico-Oncología del Hospital de Basurto, para mejorar la asistencia psicológica. Método: Estudio retrospectivo y comparativo de características demográficas y comparativo de características demográficas, médicas psicológicas y de consulta de 115 pacientes con cáncer y con tratamiento psicológico entre 2001 y 2003. Estos pacientes se compara con 28 familiares, 119 pacientes de psicología general y con 120 pacientes con cáncer sin tratamiento psicológico. Resultados: Los pacientes con cáncer y tratamiento psicológico son más jóvenes; están en un estadio avanzado de enfermedad, con activos y peor pronóstico; tiene historia familiar de cáncer, y antecedentes personales de problemas psicológicos; el 70% recibe diagnóstico DSM-IV, mediante entrevista clínica, la mayoría (80%) son trastornos adaptativos, relacionados con el contexto de la enfermedad. Respecto a la consulta con el psicólogo los médicos detectan mal los problemas psicológicos, derivan al psicólogo con poca precisión, cuando los problemas psicológicos están acentuados o consolidados y queda poco tiempo para un tratamiento psicológico. Conclusiones: Estos pacientes requieren un trabajo especializado, por sus diferencias con los grupos estudiados, tanto en características sociodemográficas como médicas y psicológicas. Se necesita implanta método de detección precoz de las necesidades y problemas psicológicos de los pacientes con cáncer, para derivarlos a la Unidad de Psicooncología y posibilitar su evaluación y el tratamiento del sufrimiento añadido a la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);4(1): 179-191, jun. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problema  Psicológico en Pacientes con cáncer: Dificultades de detección y derivación al Psicooncólogo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
