<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038683</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-8460</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anabolic treatment of osteoporosis. Influence of anti-resorptive treatments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent appearance of teriparatide (TRPT) for the anabolic treatment of severeosteoporosis reopens the need to explain some points in relatinship with itsuse associated with antirresorptive drugs.Osteoporotic women treated with alendronate (ALN) or raloxifene (RLX) maintaintheir capacity to respond to treatment with TRPT, although those pretreatedwith RLX have BMD gains similar to those expected in women withoutprevious treatment, while the response of those pre-treated with ALN ismore delayed and limited, although not abolished.Combined treatment with ALN and PTH (in women) or TRPT (in men) doesnot have any synergic effect, although the response on the lumbar BMD isgreater than that of ALN alone. On the femoral neck, the combined use of ALNreduces the apparent loss of BMD evaluated by DXA. On the contrary, thecombined use of ALN lessens the effect of anabolic treatment on the remodelingmarkers and volumetric BMD.In men previously treated with TRPT for 18 months, discontinuation oftreatment causes loss of lumbar BMD close to 4% in one year, while immediatetreatment with ALN induces an additional gain of 5% in the same period.In osteoporotic women treated with PTH for one year, later and immediatetreatment with daily ALN causes an important additional gain of BMD thatalmost doubles that obtained with PTH.One way or the other, absence of data on fractures makes it impossible to clarifydefinitively the doubts regarding the efficacy of the association of antiresorptiveand anabolic treatments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcia Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jodar Gimeno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez Diaz-Guerra, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hawkins Carranza, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reciente aparición de teriparatida (TRPT) para el tratamiento anabólico dela osteoporosis grave reabre la necesidad de esclarecer algunos puntos en relacióncon su uso asociado con fármacos antirresortivos.Las mujeres osteoporóticas tratadas con alendronato (ALN) o raloxifeno (RLX)mantienen su capacidad para responder al tratamiento con TRPT, aunque las pretratadascon RLX tienen ganancias de densidad mineral ósea (DMO) similaresa las esperadas en mujeres sin tratamiento previo, mientras que la respuesta delas pretratadas con ALN fue más retrasada y limitada, aunque no abolida.El tratamiento combinado con ALN y hormona paratiroidea (PTH) (en mujeres)o TRPT (en varones) no presenta ningún efecto sinérgico, aunque la respuestasobre la DMO lumbar es mayor que el de ALN solo. Sobre el cuellofemoral, el uso combinado de ALN reduce la pérdida aparente de DMO evaluadapor DXA. Por el contrario, el uso combinado con ALN atenúa el efectodel tratamiento anabólico sobre los marcadores de remodelado y la DMO volumétrica.En varones previamente tratados con TRPT durante 18 meses, la suspensióndel tratamiento produce una pérdida de DMO lumbar cercana al 4% en un año,mientras que el tratamiento inmediato con ALN induce en el mismo períodouna ganancia adicional del 5%. En mujeres osteoporóticas tratadas durante unaño con PTH, el tratamiento posterior e inmediato con ALN diario produjouna importante ganancia adicional de DMO que casi duplica la conseguida conPTH.Sea como fuere, la ausencia de datos sobre fracturas hace que las dudas en cuantoa la eficacia de la asociación de tratamientos antirresortivos y anabólicos nopuedan aclararse aún de forma definitiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. enferm. metab. óseas (Ed. impr.);14(2): 29-32, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento anabólico de la osteoporosis. Influencia de los tratamientos antirresortivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33002^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34394^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32988^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d706^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d706^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
