<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129819</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposed global treatment algorithm for hallux rigidus according to evidence-based medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hallux rigidus is the most common arthritis of the foot and ankle. There are numerous reviews on the surgical treatment, but few publications that address the effectiveness of conservative treatment. Objective. To present a comprehensive algorithm for treatment of all grades of this disease. Methods. Literature search in the following sources: Pubmed and PEDro database (physiotherapy evidence database) until October 2013 for articles on treatment hallux rigidus to record levels of evidence. Results. A total of 112 articles were obtained on conservative treatment and 609 on surgical treatment. Finally, only 4 met the inclusion criteria. Conclusions. The use of orthoses or footwear modifications, infiltration with hyaluronate, cheilectomy in moderate degrees and the metatarsophalangeal arthrodesis for advanced degrees, are the only procedures contrasted with grade B or moderate evidence in the treatment of hallux rigidus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paul, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andarcia-Bañuelos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valderrabano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barg, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bergua-Domingo, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El hallux rigidus es la artrosis más frecuente en el pie y tobillo. Existen numerosas revisiones respecto al tratamiento quirúrgico, pero escasas publicaciones que aborden la eficacia del tratamiento conservador. Objetivo. Presentar un algoritmo global de tratamiento completo para todos los grados de esta enfermedad. Métodos. Revisión sistemática de la evidencia disponible hasta octubre de 2013 utilizando las siguientes fuentes: Pubmed y PEDro database (physiotherapy evidence database) de artículos sobre tratamiento de hallux rigidus que comuniquen sus resultados y de los que pudieran obtenerse grados de recomendación. Resultados. Obtuvimos 112 artículos sobre tratamiento conservador y 609 sobre tratamiento quirúrgico. Finalmente solo 4 cumplían los criterios de inclusión. Conclusiones. El uso de ortesis a medida o modificaciones del calzado, la infiltración con hialuronato, la queilectomía en grados moderados y la artrodesis metatarsofalángica en grados avanzados, son los únicos procedimientos contrastados con grado de evidencia B o moderada en el tratamiento del hallux rigidus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(6): 377-386, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de algoritmo global de tratamiento del hallux rigidus según la medicina basada en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32845^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34188^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34188^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34188^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34188^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
