<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113586</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Actual situation about acute and chronic wounds in Spain: ATENEA study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Wounds are a health problem that affects a wide population of all ages and that require different interventions to ensure optimal care of patients who have them. Cross-sectional survey of national scope done by professional nurses, and carried out during the period September 2011-January 2012. Professionals who answered to the survey are nurses who work in hospitals, primary care centers or other centers. The survey, that includes a total of26 items, presents three main sections: 1. Social demographic data and personal details;2. Training received regarding wound treatment; 3. Questions related to management in wound care. This article presents the results for paragraphs 1 and 2. A total of 405professionals participated in the survey, and 340 completed the questionnaire for the evaluation. The different results obtained for each of the parameters are listed in the article. In future studies, it would be interesting to develop programs that enable us to assess the effectiveness of the different training modes in the healthcare environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Martínez,  Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beaskoetxea Gómez,  Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzanero López, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Morán, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerame Pérez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubiaur Barrenengoa, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Collado Enfermero, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Coiduras, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capillas Pérez,  Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia Gómez,  Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las heridas son un problema de salud que afecta a una amplia población de todas las edades y que requieren diferentes intervenciones para asegurar un cuidado óptimo delos pacientes que las presentan. Esta es una encuesta transversal de ámbito nacional dirigida a profesionales de enfermería realizada durante el periodo septiembre 2011-enero 2012. Los profesionales que respondieron a la encuesta son enfermeros/as que trabajan en hospitales, centros de atención primaria u otros centros asistenciales. La encuesta, con un total de 26 ítems, presenta tres grandes secciones: 1. Datos sociodemográficos y filiación; 2. Formación recibida en el cuidado y tratamiento de heridas;3. Preguntas relacionadas con el manejo en el cuidado de las heridas. En el presente artículo se presentan los resultados para los apartados 1 y 2. Un total de 405 profesionales participaron en la encuesta, de los cuales 340 cumplimentaron el cuestionario de forma completa para su evaluación. En el artículo se citan los diferentes resultados obtenidos para cada uno de los parámetros. En futuros estudios sería interesante desarrollar programas que permitan evaluar la efectividad de los diferentes modos formativos en el medio asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);24(1): 27-31, mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113586</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual sobre el manejo de heridas agudas y crónicas en España: Estudio ATENEA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15344^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
