<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166788</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The treatment of chronic stable angina is specified by European Society of Cardiology guidelines, which have been accepted by the Spanish Society of Cardiology. Treatment involves the use of medical therapy and myocardial revascularization, as appropriate. The guidelines recommend that all patients should undergo counseling and receive appropriate medication for the secondary prevention of ischemic heart disease in addition to drugs for controlling ischemia. High-risk patients can be easily identified using simple clinical risk scores. More detailed risk stratification may involve carrying out tests to detecting ischemia occurring while the patient is receiving optimal medical treatment, and coronary angiography. Factors associated with an increased risk include age, ischemia severity, left ventricular function, persistent ischemia on optimal medical treatment, and co-morbid conditions. The medical treatments used for controlling myocardial ischemia include beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers, nitrates, potassium channel blockers, If current inhibitors, and late sodium current inhibitors. Beta-blockers are still considered as first-line therapy, although data from recent clinical trials suggest that new anti-ischemic agents can provide greater benefits in a wide range of patients, observations that will be reflected in future versions of clinical practice guidelines. Currently there is some controversy about revascularization and new data from recent studies could have an influence on treatment strategies. However, at present, myocardial revascularization must be considered in patients with uncontrolled ischemia despite optimal medical therapy as well as in high-risk patients with lesions that are suitable for revascularization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Sendón, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Conde, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de la angina crónica estable está reflejado en las guías de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología, aceptadas por la Sociedad Española de Cardiología, e incluye el uso razonable de terapia médica y revascularización miocárdica. De acuerdo con las guías, todos los pacientes deben recibir los consejos y la medicación adecuados para la prevención secundaria de la cardiopatía isquémica, así como medicación para controlar la isquemia. Se puede identificar fácilmente a los enfermos en alto riesgo empleando escalas de riesgo clínicas sencillas. Una estratificación adicional del riesgo puede incluir pruebas de detección de isquemia cuando el paciente recibe el tratamiento médico adecuado y angiografía coronaria. Los factores relacionados con mayor riesgo incluyen edad, gravedad de la isquemia, función ventricular, persistencia de la isquemia con el tratamiento médico óptimo y comorbilidades. El tratamiento médico para controlar la isquemia incluye bloqueadores beta, antagonistas del calcio, nitratos, inhibidores de los canales de potasio, inhibidores de la corriente If e inhibidores de la corriente lenta del sodio. Todavía se considera que los bloqueadores beta son la primera opción terapéutica, aunque la información obtenida en ensayos clínicos contemporáneos indica un beneficio a favor del empleo de los nuevos fármacos antiisquémicos en un grupo amplio de pacientes y tendrá impacto en las próximas ediciones de guías de práctica clínica. La revascularización es actualmente objeto de controversia, con nueva información procedente de estudios recientes que influirán en las estrategias de tratamiento, pero la revascularización miocárdica aún debe considerarse en pacientes con isquemia no controlada a pesar del tratamiento médico óptimo, así como en pacientes en alto riesgo con lesiones adecuadas para revascularización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.B): 22b-30b, 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías de tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55872^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36020^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
