<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80559</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical relevance of the adverse reactions reports received from primary health care in the pharmacovigilance center of Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To analyze the clinical relevance of the adverse reactions reports and to compare this relevance with those sent by yellow card (YC) versus OMI-AP formularies within the Spontaneous Reporting Program. Material and method. Reports of suspected adverse reactions received from 1998 to 2007 were classified into one of the following groups: 1) spontaneous from health professionals, 2) spontaneous from drug companies, 3) published cases, 4) post-marketing studies. In regards to the first group, we selected those sent from primary health care and studied their clinical relevance according to the formulary used (YC or OMI-AP). Reports that fulfilled at least one of the following criteria were considered relevant: 1) new drug involved (&lt;5 years in the market), 2) serious or unknown adverse reaction reported. The annual evolution of the relevant and total reports was studied. Results: Out of the 3150 reports analyzed, 1651 were spontaneous from primary health care physicians and showed an increased annual evolution. The separate analysis of the 2 formularies showed a progressive increase in the total reports through the OMI-AP form that included a lower increase in the relevant reports. Simultaneously, the total number of reports received by YC decreased, although the percentage of relevant reports sent with this formulary was maintained. Conclusion: In Asturias, the acceptance of the OMI-AP form has made reporting of adverse reactions easier. We should continue working with automatized systems to collect information in order to obtain more efficient results in Pharmacovigilance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jimeno, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgueiro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manso, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Analizar la relevancia clínica de las notificaciones de reacciones adversas y, dentro del programa de notificación espontánea, comparar dicha relevancia en las notificaciones recibidas mediante tarjeta amarilla (TA) y OMI-AP. Material y método: Las notificaciones de sospechas de reacciones adversas recibidas entre los años 1998 y 2007 se clasificaron en: 1) espontáneas de profesionales sanitarios; 2) espontáneas de industrias farmacéuticas; 3) casos publicados, y 4) estudios poscomercialización. Del primer grupo se seleccionaron las procedentes de atención primaria, clasificándolas según el formulario (TA u OMI-AP) y analizando su relevancia clínica. Se consideraron clínicamente relevantes las notificaciones que cumplían alguno de los siguientes criterios: 1) principio activo nuevo implicado (&lt;5 años en el mercado); 2) reacción adversa notificada grave o desconocida. Se estudió la evolución anual de las notificaciones totales y relevantes. Resultados: Se obtuvieron 3.150 notificaciones, de las cuales 1.651 eran espontáneas procedentes de médicos de origen extrahospitalario y mostraban una evolución anual en aumento. Al analizar separadamente los 2 formularios se observó un progresivo incremento de la notificación a través de OMI-AP, que además incluía un aumento, aunque menor, de la notificación de casos relevantes. Simultáneamente disminuyó la notificación por TA, que mantiene su porcentaje de notificaciones relevantes. Conclusión: En Asturias, la aceptación del formulario de OMI-AP ha facilitado la notificación de reacciones adversas. Debemos seguir trabajando en sistemas automatizados de recogida de la información para obtener resultados más eficientes en farmacovigilancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(2): 63-68, feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relevancia clínica de las notificaciones de reacciones adversas de atención primaria recibidas en el centro de farmacovigilancia de Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5703^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33186</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11792</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
