<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85400</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking paradox in acute coronary syndrome without st-segment elevation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Although smoking habit is a well-known cardiovascular risk factor, it has been described that smokers admitted because of myocardial infarction have better prognosis than non smoker patients, which is known as &#147;the smoking paradox&#148;. The purpose of our work is to investigate whether this phenomenon occurs among patients admitted because of acute coronary syndrome without ST-segment elevation (NSTACS), and which factors help to explain it. Patients and Methods: We analysed 563 consecutive patients admitted because of NSTACS on the Coronary Unit of our hospital from January 2005 to December 2006. We analysed clinic and angiographic characteristics and their relationship with in-hospital complications and prognosis. Results: 155 Patients were smokers (27,53%). Smoker patients were younger, more often male, had less risk factors, and more often had a Killip I class at admission (91.6% vs. 79.3%). They had less commonly the combined endpoint of death, reinfarction or Killip Class IV (6.5 vs 13.6%, odds ratio 0,439, confidence interval 0,218 a 0,885, P=.018). This relationship was lost after adjusting to other significant clinical and angiographic data by logistic regression. Conclusions: Our study confirms the &#147;smoking paradox&#148; amongst NSTACS patients, which is explained by the lower prevalence of previous myocardial infarction, diabetes or multivessel disease. It is essential to recommend quitting the smoking habites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Díaz, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rubira, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Devesa Cordero, Carlonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvallo López, Mª Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández ortiz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amor Salamanca, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Aunque el tabaco es un conocido factor de riesgo cardiovascular, se ha descrito que en los pacientes ingresan por un infarto de miocardio parece observarse un mejor pronóstico, a corto plazo, en los que tienen antecedente de tabaquismo, lo que se conoce como &#147;paradoja del tabaco&#148;. El propósito de nuestro estudio es comprobar si este fenómeno se da en los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST (SCASEST) y qué factores contribuyen a explicarlo.Pacientes y método: Se analizaron 563 pacientes consecutivos que ingresaron por SCASEST en la Unidad Coronaria de nuestro centro desde enero de 2005 hasta diciembre de 2006. Se analizaron las características clínicas y angiográficas y su relación con las complicaciones y pronóstico intrahospitalario. Resultados: Un total de 155 pacientes eran fumadores (27,53%). Lo pacientes fumadores eran más jóvenes de media que los no fumadores, con más frecuencia fueron varones, presentaban menos factores de riesgo cardiovascular y con mayor frecuencia estaban en clase Killip I (91,6 frente a 79,3%). Los pacientes fumadores tuvieron con menor frecuencia el evento combinado de muerte, reinfarto o Killip IV (6,5 frente a 13,6%, odds ratio 0,439, intervalo de confianza del 95% 0,218 a 0,885, p=0,018). Esta relación perdió la significación estadística al ajustar mediante regresión logística en la que se incluyeron los datos clínicos y angiográficos significativos.Conclusiones: Nuestro estudio confirma la existencia de la &#147;paradoja del tabaco&#148; en el SCASEST, pero queda explicada por la menor prevalencia de infarto previo, diabetes mellitus o enfermedad multivaso. Es fundamental aconsejar a los fumadores el abandono del tabaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);136(4): 144-148, feb. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La paradoja del tabaco en el síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
