<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161827</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eyelid lymphoma in a patient with a gold weight implant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A male patient with an exposure keratopathy caused by lagophthalmos. A gold weight was implanted in the right upper eyelid. Eight months later, he presented with erythema and swelling of right upper eyelid. An incisional biopsy was performed, reporting extranodal marginal zone B cell lymphoma. Discussion: when a tumour at the site of a gold weight implant is refractory to treatment, it is essential to perform an incisional biopsy to establish the histopathological diagnosis. Ocular adnexal lymphomas are relatively common. The presence of foreign material can cause chronic inflammation that could be the stimulus for the development of a lymphoproliferative disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mansur, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Croxatto, JO</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Di-Nisio, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldecoa, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weil, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Paciente varón con queratopatía de exposición secundaria a lagoftalmos. Se colocó un implante de pesa de oro en el párpado superior derecho. Ocho meses después presentó eritema y edema en el sitio del implante. Se realizó una biopsia incisional que reveló un linfoma de células B de zona marginal extranodal. Discusión: Ante la presencia de una tumoración en el sitio del implante de una pesa de oro resistente al tratamiento médico, es esencial realizar una biopsia incisional para el diagnóstico anatomopatológico. Los linfomas de anexos oculares son relativamente comunes. La presencia de un material extraño puede provocar una inflamación crónica que podría ser el estímulo para el desarrollo de un desorden linfoproliferativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(4): 181-183, abr. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma palpebral en paciente con implante de pesa de oro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5243^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8403^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6193^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5243^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
