<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118376</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anayde Correa de Carvalho: historical legacy for the Brazilian Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The biographical narrative is one of the most traditional perspectives of the historical writings. Its methodological renovation means the rescue of the historical trajectories less known, utilizing new documental sets for this activity, such as the oral history. This paper intends to articulate within the scope of the Life Oral History, individual and collective happenings characterized by the personal experience of a nurse who lived the nursing professionalization in Brazil post-1930 - Anayde Correa de Carvalho. The outcomes of this reflection allow considering not only her interpretation about the first associative movements related to the Brazilian nursing which she reported through an extensive documentary but also her production and life experience have contributed to conforming the professional identity of the Brazilian Nursing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luchesi, Luciana Barizon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oguisso, Taka</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, Paulo Fernando de Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, Emiliane da Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La narrativa histórica es una de las más tradicionales perspectivas de la historia escrita. Su renovación metodológica implica rescatar trayectorias históricas poco conocidas, utilizándose para esa actividad nuevos conjuntos documentales, como es el caso de la oralidad. Este texto intenta articular, en el ámbito de la Historia Oral de Vida, acontecimientos individuales y colectivos caracterizados por la experiencia personal de una enfermera que ha vivido la profesionalización de la enfermería en Brasil, post-1930 - Anayde Correa de Carvalho. Los resultados de la reflexión permiten considerar no solamente sus interpretaciones registradas en un extenso  documentario sobre los primeros movimientos asociativos de la enfermería brasileña, como su producción y experiencia de vida contribuyeron para la formación de la identidad profesional de la enfermería brasileña (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(37): 30-41, sept.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anayde Correa de Carvalho: herencia histórica para la Enfermería brasileña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12960^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
