<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27830</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mixed hypotonia, neurological regression and atrophy of the cerebellum: manifestations that suggest infantile neuroaxonal dystrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="undefined">ilus</dc:description>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Infantile neuroaxonal dystrophy (INAD), or Seitelberger disease, is a neurodegenerative disease of unknown origin which is transmitted by autosomal recessive inheritance. Clinically, it courses with psychomotor stagnation and regression that begins at the age of one or two years, associated to hypotonia with mixed clinical features (segmentary and suprasegmentary) that progresses towards spastic tetraplegia and progressive optic atrophy and dementia; this leads to death before the age of ten years. Aims. To present the case of a 30-month-old child with INAD, in whom &amp;#945;-N-acetylgalactosaminidase deficiency and mitochondrial cytopathy were ruled out. Case report. Male aged 30 months with an initial overall retardation, and later regression, of psychomotor acquisitions. In the physical exploration the patient displayed serious neurological involvement with mixed hypotonia, muscular hypotrophy with generalised weakness and mild bilateral horizontal nystagmus. Complementary explorations with neuroimaging revealed a slight increase in the subarachnoid space, with atrophy of the vermis and cerebellar hemispheres. Neurophysiological tests (EMG and ENG), which were initially normal, later showed signs of denervation in the EMG, and the ENG revealed a decreased amplitude of motor responses, with preservation of conduction speed. Histological tests showed the presence of axons with axoplasm expanded by the inclusion of typical tubulovascular structures. Conclusion. The clinical features of our patient met all the criteria to satisfy a diagnosis of INAD, and he displayed a classic form of the disease. INAD must be considered when the clinician is faced with: 1. A clinical picture of stagnation and later regression of psychomotor development before the age of two years; 2. Hypotonia, muscular atrophy and initial overall areflexia, with later progression towards pyramidalism; 3. Initially normal EMG findings, with later signs of denervation; 4. Cerebellar atrophy (hemispheres and vermis); 5. Visual deficit, and 6. Histopathological proof of characteristic findings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La distrofia neuroaxonal infantil (DNAI) o enfermedad de Seitelberger, es una enfermedad neurodegenerativa de causa desconocida, transmisible bajo un patrón hereditario autosómico recesivo. Clínicamente, cursa con estancamiento psicomotor y posterior regresión, de inicio en el primer o segundo año de vida, asociado a hipotonía de semiología mixta (segmentaria y suprasegmentaria) que progresa a una tetraplejía espástica, atrofia óptica y demencia progresivas; la muerte sobreviene hacia el final de la primera década de la vida. Objetivos. Presentar un niño de 30 meses de edad con DNAI, en el que se descartó una citopatía mitocondrial y una deficiencia de la enzima Alfa -N-acetil-galactosaminidasa. Caso clínico. Varón de 30 meses de edad, con un retraso inicial de adquisiciones psicomotoras de forma global, con posterior regresión. En la exploración física presentó afectación neurológica grave con hipotonía mixta, hipotrofia muscular con debilidad generalizada y leve nistagmo horizontal bilateral. En las exploraciones complementarias destacó en la neuroimagen un leve aumento del espacio subaracnoideo, con atrofia del vermis y los hemisferios cerebelosos. Las pruebas neurofisiológicas -electromiografía (EMG) y electroneurografía (ENG)- fueron normales inicialmente; pero, más tarde, la EMG mostró signos de denervación, y la ENG, una disminución de la amplitud de las respuestas motoras, con preservación de la velocidad de conducción. Histológicamente, se demostró la presencia de axones con un axoplasma expandido que contenía las típicas inclusiones tubulovesiculares. Conclusión. El cuadro clínico de nuestro paciente cumple todos los criterios diagnósticos de DNAI, y se encuadra en una forma clásica de la enfermedad. La DNAI debe considerarse ante: 1) Clínica de estancamiento y posterior regresión del desarrollo psicomotor antes del segundo año de vida; 2) Hipotonía, atrofia muscular y arreflexia global inicial, con evolución posterior hacia un cuadro de piramidalismo; 3) Hallazgos electromiográficos iniciales normales, con signos posteriores de denervación; 4) Atrofia cerebelosa (hemisferios y vermis); 5) Déficit visual, y 6) Demostración histopatológica de hallazgos característicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(1): 25-28, jul. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipotonía mixta, regresión neurológica y atrofia cerebelosa: manifestaciones sugestivas de distrofia neuroaxonal infantil</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Blanco Barca, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Guitián, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Gago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eirís Puñal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bustillo, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintos Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27830</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32947</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
