<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119606</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-reported use of Internet among adolescents: Psychological profile of elevated internet use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Excessive use of the Internet, defined by the number of hours spent surfing the web, can affect an adolescent&#146;s social life and school performance, and as a consequence, lead parents to seek psychological help. In order to know the level and characteristics of Internet use among adolescents, determine the psychological profile of excessive Internet use and create a model that can predict it, a study with a probabilistic sample of 359 adolescents (12-17 years old) from the city of Girona has been carried out. Personality  (NEO-FFI), coping (ACS), hopelessness and Internet use have been evaluated. Among the subjects studied, 6.7% devote more than 30 hours a week to the Internet (more than four hours a day) and 10.2% remain connected after midnight (especially the boys). Surfing the Internet from one&#146;s own computer after midnight, coping by finding relief among other peers and feelings of hopelessness are the best indicators of elevated Internet use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Viñas Poch, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un uso excesivo de Internet, definido por el número de horas que una persona permanece navegando por la red, puede afectar a la vida social y escolar del adolescente y, como consecuencia de ello, llevar a sus padres a solicitar ayuda psicológica. Con el objetivo de conocer el nivel y las características del uso de Internet entre los adolescentes, determinar el perfil psicológico de un uso elevado de la red y construir un modelo que permita su predicción, se ha realizado un estudio con una muestra probabilística de 359 adolescentes (12-17 años) de la ciudad de Girona. Se ha evaluado la personalidad (NEO-FFI), el  afrontamiento (ACS), la desesperanza y el uso de Internet. Del total de sujetos estudiados,un 6,7% dedica más de 30 horas a la semana a Internet (superior a las 4 horas diarias) y un 10,2% permanece conectado a partir de medianoche (especialmente los  chicos). Navegar por Internet desde el propio ordenador a partir de medianoche junto con un afrontamiento centrado en buscar alivio en los demás y la presencia de sentimientos de desesperanza, son los mejores predictores del uso elevado de Internet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);9(1): 109-122, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso autoinformado de Internet en adolescentes: perfil psicológico de un uso elevado de la red</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
