<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134537</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food frequency questionnaires</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Food Frequency Questionnaires are dietary assessment tools widely used in epidemiological studies investigating the relationship between dietary intake and disease or risk factors since the early &#145;90s. The three main components of these questionnaires are the list of foods, frequency of consumption and the portion size consumed. The food list should reflect the food habits of the study population at the time the data is collected. The frequency of consumption may be asked by open ended questions or by presenting frequency categories. Qualitative Food Frequency Questionnaires do not ask about the consumed portions; semi-quantitative include standard portions and quantitative questionnaires ask respondents to estimate the portion size consumed either in household measures or grams. The latter implies a greater participant burden. Some versions include only close-ended questions in a standardized format, while others add an open section with questions about some specific food habits and practices and admit additions to the food list for foods and beverages consumed which are not included. The method can be self-administered, on paper or web-based, or interview administered either face-to-face or by telephone. Due to the standard format, especially closed-ended versions, and method of administration, FFQs are highly cost-effective thus encouraging its widespread use in large scale epidemiological cohort studies and also in other study designs. Coding and processing data collected is also less costly and requires less nutrition expertise compared to other dietary intake assessment methods. However, the main limitations are systematic errors and biases in estimates. Important efforts are being developed to improve the quality of the information. It has been recommended the use of FFQs with other methods thus enabling the adjustments required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela-Moreiras, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodrigo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranceta, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuestionarios de frecuencia de consumo son herramientas ampliamente utilizadas en los estudios epidemiológicos que investigan la relación entre ingesta dietética y enfermedad o factores de riesgo desde comienzos de la década de los 90. Los tres componentes principales de estos cuestionarios son la lista de alimentos, la frecuencia de consumo y el tamaño de la ración consumida. La lista de alimentos debe reflejar los hábitos de consumo de la población de estudio en el momento en que se recogen los datos. La frecuencia de consumo puede preguntarse de forma abierta u ofreciendo categorías de frecuencia de consumo. Los cuestionarios cualitativos no preguntan por la ración consumida; los semi-cuantitativos presentan raciones estándar y los cuestionarios cuantitativos solicitan al encuestado que estime el tamaño de la ración consumida en medidas caseras o en gramos. Esta última opción supone un esfuerzo importante para el participante. Existen versiones exclusivamente cerradas en un formato estandarizado y otras que incorporan preguntas abiertas sobre algunos hábitos y prácticas alimentarias específicas y permiten añadir alimentos y bebidas consumidos que no están incluidos en la lista. Pueden ser auto-administrados, en papel o en soporte web, o bien mediante entrevista personal o telefónica. Por su formato estandarizado, especialmente los cerrados, y por la forma de administración, son un método con un alto rendimiento en términos de coste-efectividad que ha favorecido su extendido uso en grandes estudios epidemiológicos de cohortes y también con otros diseños. También el coste de codificación y proceso de la información recogida resulta menos costoso y requiere menos experiencia en temas nutricionales que otros métodos de evaluación de la ingesta. Sin embargo, presenta el inconveniente de incorporar errores sistemáticos y sesgos importantes, por lo que en la actualidad se buscan procedimientos para mejorar la calidad de la información y se recomienda utilizarlos junto a otros métodos que permitan realizar los ajustes necesarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(supl.3): 49-56, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de Frecuencia de consumo alimentario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50330</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1075^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38408^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
