<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92925</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of objective and subjective aspects in the perception of quality among patients receiving physiotherapy for mechanical neck pain in primary care centers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo evaluate the influence of subjective and objective aspects on the perception of quality among patients with mechanical neck pain receiving physical therapy in primary care centers.Material and methodsA mixed study (qualitative and quantitative) was conducted in two phases. In the first phase, a qualitative study was performed using focus group techniques and a 24-item questionnaire was designed. In the second phase, the questionnaire was given to patients. Convenience recruitment was used. Of the 176 questionnaires provided, 142 were completed. To analyze the percentage of explanation for each objective and subjective aspect, a factorial analysis with varimax was applied.ResultsThe response rate was 80.7%. The factorial analysis provided six factors or components that explained the objective or subjective influence of certain aspects on patients¿ perceptions of quality. Of these six components, two included clearly subjective aspects, three included objective and subjective aspects and only one was clearly objective. These aspects were related to structure and installations, organization and communication and information.ConclusionsSubjective features cannot be excluded from patients¿ perceptions. Some objective and subjective measures are independent while others are interrelated. Physiotherapists should bear both objective and subjective aspects in mind when considering patients¿ perceptions of the quality of the treatment received (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meseguer-Henarejos, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carles-Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meseguer-Olmo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vidal, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canteras Jordana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoValorar la influencia de aspectos objetivos y subjetivos en las percepciones de calidad de los pacientes con cervicalgia mecánica que han recibido fisioterapia en centros de atención primaria.Material y métodosUn estudio mixto (cuali-cuantitativo) fue llevado a cabo en dos fases. En una primera fase, se realizó un estudio cualitativo usando la técnica de grupo focal y se diseñó un cuestionario con 24 ítems. En una segunda fase, se entregó el cuestionario en mano a los pacientes. El método de reclutamiento fue de conveniencia. Se entregó un total de 176 cuestionarios y el número total de participantes que respondieron al cuestionario fue 142. Un análisis factorial con varimax fue aplicado para analizar el porcentaje de explicación de cada aspecto objetivo y subjetivo.ResultadosLa tasa de respuesta ha sido del 80,7%. El análisis factorial ha proporcionado 6 factores o componentes que explican la influencia objetiva y subjetiva de ciertos aspectos en las percepciones de calidad de los pacientes. Dos factores han sido claramente subjetivos, 3 factores han sido objetivos y subjetivos y 1 solo claramente objetivo. Estos aspectos han sido relacionados con la estructura y las instalaciones, con la organización y con la comunicación e información.ConclusionesLos aspectos subjetivos no pueden ser excluidos de las percepciones de los pacientes. Algunas de las medidas objetivas y subjetivas son independientes mientras que otras medidas están implicadas entre sí. Los fisioterapeutas deben considerar tanto aspectos objetivos como subjetivos cuando se tienen en cuenta las percepciones de los pacientes de la calidad del tratamiento que reciben(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(4): 135-144, jul. -ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de aspectos objetivos y subjetivos en las percepciones de la calidad de los pacientes con cervicalgia mecánica que han recibido fisioterapia en centros de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
