<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93708</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors for postoperative acute kidney injury in a cohort of 2378 patients from 59 hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess risk factors for postoperative acute kidney injury (AKI) in adults with normal renal function hospitalized for major surgery. To analyze mortality and length of hospital stay in patients who develop postoperative AKI. Patients and methods: Data for analysis were drawn from the 2006 ARISCAT study. The dependent variable was postoperative AKI defined as a decline in renal function demonstrated by a rise in plasma creatinine level to twice the baseline measurement or a 50% reduction in the glomerular filtration rate. Bivariate and multivariate analyses were used to identify preoperative and intraoperative risk factors. Results: We analyzed 2378 of the ARISCAT cases, which had been enrolled from 59 participating hospitals; 25 patients (1.1%) developed AKI. Analysis identified 5 risk factors: age, peripheral arterial disease, type of surgical incision, blood loss, and infusion of colloids. The area under the receiver operating characteristic curve was 0.88% (95% confidence interval, 0.79%&#150;0.69%). Duration of hospital stay was longer for patients with postoperative AKI (21.8 days, vs 5.5 days for other patients; P=.007). Mortality was higher in patients with AKI at 30 days (36% vs 0.9%) and at 3 months (48% vs 1.7%). Conclusions: The incidence of postoperative AKI was slightly over 1%. Knowledge of postoperative AKI risk factors can facilitate the planning of surgical interventions and anesthesia to reduce subsequent morbidity and mortality and length of hospital stay(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar los factores de riesgo de la insuficiencia renal postoperatoria (IRP) en pacientes adultos con función renal normal sometidos a cirugía mayor con ingreso hospitalario, y analizar la mortalidad y la estancia hospitalaria de los pacientes que desarrollan IRP. Pacientes y métodos: Se analizan los datos del estudio multicéntrico de cohortes prospectivo ARISCAT realizado en 2006. La variable dependiente fue la IRP definida como un deterioro de la función renal demostrada por un aumento del doble de la creatinina plasmática basal, o descenso del 50% del filtrado glomerular estimado. Se realizó un análisis bivariable y multivariable para identificar los factores de riesgo pre e intraoperatorios. Resultados: Participaron 59 hospitales y fueron incluidos 2.378 pacientes, de los que 25 (1,1%) desarrollaron IRP. Se identificaron 5 factores de riesgo de IRP: edad, arteriopatía periférica, incisión quirúrgica, pérdidas hemáticas y la administración de coloides. El área bajo la curva ROC fue de 0,88 (IC 95%: 0,79-0,96). La estancia hospitalaria fue mayor en los pacientes que desarrollaron una IRP (21,8 frente 5,5 días, P=0,007). La mortalidad fue mayor a los 30 días (36% frente 0,9%) y a los tres meses (48 % frente 1,7%). Conclusiones: La tasa de la IRP fue ligeramente superior al 1%. La identificación de los factores de riesgo de la IRP puede ser útil para adecuar la planificación anestésica y quirúrgica, con el objeto de reducir la morbimortalidad postoperatoria y la estancia hospitalaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(9): 548-555, nov. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo de insuficiencia renal aguda postoperatoria. Análisis en una cohorte de 2.378 pacientes de 59 hospitales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
