<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113935</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of a responsive insertion technology (RIT) colonoscope versus a variable-stiffness colonoscope</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: recently, Olympus developed a new prototype (XCF-Q180AY2L) with responsive insertion technology (RIT), which besides the still known variable stiffness technology, included a passive bending section and a new high force insertion tube. Our objective was to investigate whether the use of this prototype could ease colonoscope insertion, increasing the cecal intubation rate, and/or shortening the cecal intubation time. Material and methods: the study was designed as a prospective observational study in 305 consecutive patients from a colo-rectal cancer screening program. We compared colonoscopies performed with conventional colonoscopes (CFH180AL/CFQ160L) with those performed with the prototype XCF-Q180AY2L. End points were mean cecal and terminal ileal intubation times, cecum intubation rate, and need for specific maneuvers. All colonoscopies were performed under sedation with intravenous propofol. Finally, 288 patients were included. Results: no complications were observed. Complete cecal intubation rate was 100 % in both groups. The ileum could be reached in 98.95 % of cases. Mean time required to reach the cecum was shorter in the prototype endoscope group (4.31 min, SD 2.63 min) than in the conventional endoscope group (4.66 min, SD 2.52 min) (p &lt; 0.05). Compared with the standard colonoscope group, we observed in the prototype group less subjective sensation of difficulty in the passage of the sigma (p &lt; 0.01), fewer maneuvers when it proved necessary to straighten the scope (p &lt; 0.01), and less frequent need to modify the stiffness of the endoscope (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusion: we concluded that the prototype endoscope (XCFQ180AY2L) facilitated colonoscope insertion, requiring slightly less time to reach the cecum than a standard colonoscope (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto de Frías, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Navas, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riva, Susana de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betés, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subtil, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herraiz, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: la casa Olympus ha desarrollado recientemente un nuevo endoscopio prototipo, denominado XCFQ180AY2L con tecnología RIT. Esta tecnología supone la incorporación, además de la función de rigidez variable ya conocida, de un segmento con flexión pasiva (PB, de sus siglas en inglés passive bending section) contiguo al segmento móvil del endoscopio, y un tubo de inserción que optimiza la transmisión de la fuerza desde los mandos al extremo distal del aparato (HFT, de sus siglas en inglés high force transmission tube). El objetivo del estudio es comprobar si el uso de este prototipo facilita el procedimiento de inserción del colonoscopio, incrementando la tasa de colonoscopias completas y/o disminuyendo el tiempo de intubación. Material y métodos: estudio observacional y unicéntrico en el que se incluyó de forma prospectiva a 305 pacientes comparando la proporción de colonoscopias completas, los tiempos medios de intubación cecal e ileal, y la necesidad de recibir maniobras específicas durante la colonoscopia, en función del colonoscopio utilizado: el colonoscopio prototipo XCF-Q180AY2L o un colonoscopio convencional, del tipo CFH180AL o CFQ160L, usados como control. Todos los procedimientos fueron realizados bajo sedación con propofol intravenoso. El estudio incluyó finalmente a 288 pacientes y no se observó ninguna complicación. Resultados: la tasa de colonoscopias completas fue del 100 % en ambos grupos. La ileoscopia se realizó en el 98,95 % de los casos. El tiempo medio de intubación fue menor en el grupo del prototipo (4,31 min, DE 2,63 min) que en el grupo control (4,66 min, DE 2,52 min) (p &lt; 0,05). En el grupo del prototipo se utilizó menos la función de rigidez variable (p &lt; 0,05), se necesitó menor número de rectificaciones cuando fue necesario hacer esta maniobra (p &lt; 0,01), y se obtuvo una menor sensación de dificultad al pasar el sigma (p &lt; 0,01). Conclusión: la conclusión fue que el colonoscopio prototipo (XCF-Q180AY2L) facilitó la inserción del colonoscopio, y disminuyó muy ligeramente el tiempo de inserción cecal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(4): 208-214, abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo entre un colonoscopio con tecnología RIT (&#147;responsive insertion technology&#148;) y un colonoscopio de rigidez variable convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34554^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33593^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33593^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34554^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
