<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052782</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence that emotional intelligence is related to job performance and affect and attitudes at work</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relation between emotional intelligence, assessed with a performance measure, and positive workplace    outcomes was examined in 44 analysts and clerical employees from the finance department of a    Fortune 400 insurance company. Emotionally intelligent individuals received greater merit increases    and held higher company rank than their counterparts. They also received better peer and/or supervisor    ratings of interpersonal facilitation and stress tolerance than their counterparts. With few exceptions,    these associations remained statistically significant after controlling for other predictors, one at    a time, including age, gender, education, verbal ability, the Big Five personality traits, and trait affect</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grewal, Daisy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kadis, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salovey, Peter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes, Paulo N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gall, Michelle</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La relación entre inteligencia emocional, evaluada con una medida de habilidad, y los resultados positivos en el lugar de trabajo fue examinada en 44 empleados analistas y oficinistas del departamento de finanzas de una compañía de seguros. Los individuos emocionalmente inteligentes recibieron mayores aumentos salariales por sus méritos y ocuparon puestos más altos en la compañía que sus compañeros. Además, en la evaluación realizada por sus iguales y/o por sus supervisores, fueron mejor valorados en facilitación interpersonal y tolerancia al estrés que sus compañeros. Con algunas excepciones, estas asociaciones continuaron siendo significativas tras controlar uno a uno otros predictores, incluidos la edad, el sexo, la educación, la habilidad verbal, los cinco grandes factores de personalidad y el estado de ánimo como rasgo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(supl.1): 132-138, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia de que la inteligencia emocional está relacionada con el rendimiento laboral y con el estado de ánimo y las actitudes en el trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4726^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
