<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113580</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Omental flap for management of sternal wound dehiscence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mediastinitis is one of the most serious complications from cardiac surgery. It is reported to occur in 0&#146;5-5% of sternotomy incisions, and this incidence is much higher in diabetic patients, obese, immunocompromised, COPD, etc. We report a case of a diabetic and morbid obese woman suffering mediastinitis after double coronary bypass surgery. For the reconstruction a transdiaphragmatictunnelled omental flap was used. The omentum isuseful to cover large defects. It has antiinfective properties and promotes revascularization of neighboring tissues. Omental flap can be a highly effective treatment for patients with large sternal wounds and immune disorders and wound healing disorders(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Sanz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Safont Albert, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorca García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hortelano Otero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno Silva, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mediastinitis es una de las complicaciones más graves de la cirugía cardíaca. Aparece en el 0,5-5% de las esternotomías y esta incidencia es mucho mayor en pacientes diabéticos, obesos, inmunodeprimidos, con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC), etc. Presentamos el caso de una paciente diabética, obesamórbida, que sufre mediastinitis tras doble by-pass coronario. Para la cobertura del defecto se empleó un colgajo de epiplon tunelizado transdiafragmático. El colgajo omental permite cubrir grandes defectos además de que posee capacidad antimicrobiana y favorece la revascularización tisular. Las características de este colgajo hacenque actualmente deba considerarse como primera elección en pacientes con grandes defectos esternales y trastornos de la inmunidad y la cicatrización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;39(1): 81-85, ene.-mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajo de omento para tratamiento de dehiscencia de herida esternal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8648^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13635^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
