<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042085</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management, prevention and control of pernicious anemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pernicious anemia is the most frequent cause of megaloblastic anemia in our area, and it is the result of a vitamin B12 deficiency due, itself, to the de-crease or absence of intrinsic factor (IF) because of gastric mucosa atrophy or autoimmune destruction of IF-producing parietal cells. With the existence of a severe gastric atrophy, there is a decrease in acid and IF production and a further change in vitamin B12 absorption. Fifty percent of the cases are associated to anti-IF antibodies, which presence in other autoimmune diseases is exceptional. In patients with pernicious anemia, measurement of anti-IF antibodies has high specificity (95%); however, measurement of anti-parietal cells antibodies has low specificity. The first-choice treatment is adminis-tration of vitamin B12 intramuscularly. The regimen is the administration of 1 mg of vitamin B12 daily for one week, weekly thereafter for one month and, then, every 2-3 months for life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz, R de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Navarro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anemia perniciosa es la causa más frecuente de anemia megaloblástica en nuestro medio y es consecuencia de una deficiencia de vitamina B12 debido a su vez a la disminución o ausencia de factor intrínseco (FI) por atrofia de la mucosa gástrica o por destrucción autoinmune de las células parietales productoras de éste. Ante la existencia de una atrofia gástrica intensa, se origina un descenso en la producción de ácido y FI y una posterior alteración en la absorción de vitamina B12. En un 50% de los casos se asocia a anticuerpos anti FI, cuya presencia en otras enfermedades auto-inmunes es excepcional. En pacientes con anemia perniciosa la determinación de anticuerpos anti FI tiene una alta especificidad (95%), sin embargo, la determinación de anticuerpos anticélulas parietales cuentan con una especificidad baja. El tratamiento de elección es la administración de B12 intramuscularmente. La pauta consiste en administrar 1 mg. de Vitamina B12 diariamente durante una semana, posteriormente semanal durante un mes y después cada 2-3 meses de por vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(6): 433-435, nov.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo, prevención y control de la anemia perniciosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5894^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d764^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d767^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d764^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15204^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
