<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044805</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Leisure and social Spaces in 50-93 years old people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As the people age increases of the free time,this as a result of the retirement especially for theman and in the woman as a result of the changeof the structure and familiar dynamics. These activitiesof free time can be individual or group; inthis case they require themselves of communitariansocial spaces.The displayed data comprise of the doctoralthesis &#147;Distribution and Perception of the time in50- adults 93 years of different cultural surroundings&#148;;displayed in October of the 2004 in theUniversity of Granada. Using a corelational andtranscultural descriptive design, the existence ofdifference with statistical meaning between the timedistributed by the adults in diverse activitiesof leisure is demonstrated through the ANOVA,between Granada and Antofagasta, in the all ofthem greater people use more time in the firstcity; in which greater social spaces for the developmentof these activities exist</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Herrera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapia Pinto, C. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A medida que las personas envejecen aumentasu tiempo libre, esto como consecuencia de lajubilación especialmente para el hombre y en lamujer como consecuencia del cambio de la estructuray dinámica familiar.Estas actividades de tiempo libre pueden serindividuales o grupales, en este caso se requierende espacios sociales comunitarios.Los datos presentados forman parte de la tesisdoctoral &#147;Distribución y Percepción del tiempoen adultos de 50-93 años de diferentes entornosculturales&#148;; presentado en octubre de 2004 en laUniversidad de Granada. Empleando un diseñodescriptivo correlacional y transcultural, se demuestraa través del análisis de ANOVA la existenciade diferencia con significación estadísticaentre el tiempo distribuido por los adultos en diversasactividades de ocio, entre Granada y Antofagasta,en todas ellas las personas mayoresutilizan más tiempo en la primera ciudad; en lacual existen mayores espacios sociales para eldesarrollo de estas actividades</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);22(2): 60-65, mar.-abr. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiempo libre y espacios sociales en personas de 50-93 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
