<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94020</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vermeer: the toxic colours of lead and mercury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">What is it about Johannes Vermeer? contemporary art lovers and historians ask. The enigmatic painter lapsed into obscurity after his death only to surface again in the 19th century and capture the imagination and esthetic taste of modern times. Even though he produced no more than 40 paintings, their originality and refinement place him among the greatest 17th-century Dutch artists. Vermeer's life story can only be patched together from public records, and the dramatic end of Vermeer`s life was told by his widow after his death.We contribute our point of view of the reason of his death because of a poisoning for lead and mercury and the repercussions that it had in his painting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pallas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñero, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">¿Qué sucede con Vermeer?, se preguntan los historiadores y amantes del arte. El enigmático pintor permaneció en la oscuridad después de su muerte hasta el siglo XIX, en donde capturaría la imaginación y el gusto estético de los tiempos modernos. Aunque han llegado a nosotros sólo treinta y seis de sus obras, su originalidad y refinamiento le colocan entre los más grandes artistas holandeses del siglo XVII. La vida de Vermeer sólo puede recompuesta a través de actas notariales y su dramático final es conocido por boca de su viuda. Nosotros pretendemos aportar un nuevo punto de vista de las razones de su muerte a causa de una intoxicación por plomo y mercurio, y las repercusiones que esta causa tuvo en su pintura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;28(2): 115-118, jul.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vermeer: los colores tóxicos del plomo y del mercurio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8807^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8807^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8034^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8034^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8807^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8683</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8807^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9619^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
