<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162507</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors related with lifestyle in patients with musculoskeletal disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Musculoskeletal disorders (MSDs) encompass a series of debilitating diseases with high incidence and prevalence, representing a high economic and social cost. Prevention is crucial, so is of great interest to determine modifiable risk factors, such as those related to lifestyle. Methods: A descriptive cross-sectional study was performed in 91 patients selected by systematic random sampling and were divided into three experimental groups according to the cause and evolution of its MSD (neck pain, knee pain and back pain). A biometric measurement, nutritional assessment, physical and occupational activity, muscle balance and oxidative status was performed. Results: The female is the most affected gender by the presence of musculoskeletal injuries such as neck pain and back pain. Overall, most patients (67.4%) had normal weight, overweight 24.41% and only 8.1% were obese type I. Patients with neck pain are the group doing less physical activity and worse muscular balance present. Oxidative stress was higher in patients with knee pain than in the other groups. Regarding the consumed diet, differences between experimental groups on the mineral content (Zn, Mn, Se and I) and vitamins (folate and ascorbic acid) are observed. Conclusions: Cholecalciferol intake and vitamins A and D is less than those recommended in all subjects, which promotes muscle disease. Folate intake was below recommendations, increasing susceptibility to oxidative stress. Obesity and oxidative stress related to the prevalence of the different types of MSDs studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Castro, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Fernández, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nestares, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teresa, Carlos de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Frías, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las enfermedades osteomusculares (EOM) engloban una serie de patologías discapacitantes con alta incidencia y prevalencia, representando un alto costo económico y social. Es fundamental su prevención, por lo que es de gran interés determinar factores de riesgo modificables, como son los relacionados con los hábitos de vida. Métodos: se realizó un estudio descriptivo y trasversal en 91 pacientes seleccionados mediante muestreo aleatorio sistemático y que fueron distribuidos en tres grupos experimentales según la causa y evolución de su EOM (cervicalgia, gonalgia y lumbalgia). Se realizó una medición biométrica, evaluación nutricional, de la actividad física y laboral, del balance muscular y del estado oxidativo. Resultados: el sexo femenino es el más afectado por la presencia de lesiones osteomusculares como cervicalgia y lumbalgia. En conjunto, la mayor parte de los pacientes (67,4%) tiene normopeso, el 24,41% sobrepeso y tan solo un 8,1% obesidad tipo I. Los pacientes con cervicalgia son el grupo que realiza menos actividad física y peor balance muscular presentan. El estrés oxidativo fue superior en pacientes con gonalgia que en los otros grupos. Con respecto a la dieta consumida, se observan diferencias entre grupos experimentales en el contenido mineral (Zn, Mn, Se y I) y vitamínico (folato y ácido ascórbico). Conclusiones: la ingesta de colecalciferol y vitaminas A y D es inferior a las recomendadas en todos los sujetos, lo que favorece la dolencia muscular. La ingesta de folato está por debajo de las recomendaciones, incidiendo en la mayor susceptibilidad al estrés oxidativo. La obesidad y estrés oxidativo se relacionan con la prevalencia de los diferentes tipos de EOM estudiados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(2): 444-453, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo relacionados con los hábitos de vida en pacientes con patología osteomuscular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15202^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
