<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78161</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sacroiliac joints: osteoarthritis or arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the most challenging aspects of treating the sacroiliac joint (SIJ) pain is the complexity of diagnosis. Imaging methods have gained importance for the diagnosis of SIJ diseases. CT and MR exams had equal efficacy superior to radiography in staging structural changes in the SIJ due to osteoarthritis or sacroiliitis. The diagnosis of spondyloarthropaty can be delayed for several years using certain radiography studies. MR imaging reveal early cartilage changes and active inflammatory changes in the subchondral bone and surrounding ligaments in spondyloarthropaties, as well as subperiosteal and transcapsular yuxtaarticular infiltrations characteristic of septic sacroiliitis, which could not be found by either CT of radiography. T1-WI with fat suppression (FS) and STIR images improve the demonstration of erosions and inflammatory changes respectively, on MR studies. Additional T1-FS after i.v. contrast has proven valuable in demonstrating the extension of inflammatory changes and abscesses in septic sacroiliitis, and in spondyloartropaties may be useful although this is debatable. Scintigraphy gives high sensibility only in early inflammatory changes and low specificity for the diagnosis of sacroiliitis due to high bone turnover in the SIJ, although specific radioprobes are useful in confirming the septic etiology and evaluating additional foci. This complex joint of very limited mobility shows a lot of structural variations and some anatomical degenerative changes due to age, which are necessary to know to an adequate image interpretation and diagnosis of disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amo Conill, Montserrat del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Batllé, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Díez, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomés Talló, Jaumé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los principales retos en el tratamiento del dolor de la articulación sacroilíaca (AS) es llegar a un adecuado diagnóstico. Las técnicas por imagen han ganado un gran protagonismo en este aspecto. La tomografía computarizada (TC) y la resonancia magnética (RM) presentan igual eficacia en la detección de cambios estructurales en artrosis y artritis, y ambas son muy superiores a la radiografía simple, la cual puede retrasar el diagnóstico. Además, la RM puede mostrar incipientes cambios en el cartílago y actividad inflamatoria aguda en el hueso subcondral y ligamentos en las espondiloartropatías y las infiltraciones subperiósticas y transcapsulares periarticulares características de la artritis séptica, que no pueden detectarse por TC ni en imágenes radiográficas. Las secuencias potenciadas en T1 con supresión de la grasa y STIR en los estudios de RM son más sensibles para demostrar erosiones y cambios inflamatorios, respectivamente. Las imágenes potenciadas en T1 con supresión de la grasa y tras la administración intravenosa de contraste en las artritis sépticas definirán la extensión de los cambios infecciosos y diferenciarán abscesos; en las espondiloartropatías pueden ser útiles, aunque su uso es controvertido. La gammagrafía ósea es sensible en artritis activas de inicio, pero poco específica debido a la actividad normal de esta articulación, aunque con radiofármacos específicos es útil para confirmar una artritis séptica y descartar otros focos infecciosos. Esta compleja articulación de movilidad limitada muestra un amplio espectro de variaciones y cambios degenerativos a lo largo de la vida, y es necesario conocerlas para facilitar la interpretación de las imágenes y realizar un adecuado diagnóstico de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(1): 40-43, ene.-feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sacroilíacas: artrosis o artritis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12822^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
