<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043469</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Temporary restoration material. Literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In endodontic treatment, the need of temporary restoration is obvious. Most of the times, endodontists do not wish or cannot finish the whole treatment in one session and thus the tooth must be left properly restored in order to avoid coronal leakage. Much time and research effort have been devoted to test the efficiency of several temporary coronal restorative materials. The aim of this article was to make a bibliographic review about the various materials that exist nowadays and the influence of coronal leakage in the prognosis of endodontic treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caudet García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unzeta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig Cayón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En endodoncia, la necesidad de restauracionesprovisionales es evidente. Con frecuencia el endodoncista no desea o no puede concluir el tratamiento en una sola sesión y durante este periodo el diente debe quedar restaurado de manera adecuada con el fin de eliminar vías de filtración. Se ha dedicado una gran cantidad de tiempo y esfuerzo de investigación a la evaluación de la eficacia de diversos materiales de obturación coronal intermedios. El objetivo del presente artículo ha sido realizar una revisión bibliográfica sobre los diferentes materiales que existen actualmente, y la influencia de la filtración coronal en el pronóstico del tratamiento endodóntico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);23(2): 114-121, abr.-jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Materiales de obturación temporal. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3809^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12762^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3777^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6322^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
