<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97227</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral malignant tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Its review the malign neoplasies principles in the oral cavity and it&#146;s describe the clinics characteristics, the differential diagnosis and the treatment. More than 90% of cancers of the oral cavity are squamous cell carcinomas. Squamous cells are flat, scale-like cells that normally form the lining of the oral cavity. The earliest form of squamous cell cancer is called carcinoma in situ, meaning that the cancer cells are present only in the lining layer of cells called the epithelium. Invasive squamous cell cancer means that the cancer cells have spread beyond this layer into deeper layers of the oral cavity. Verrucous carcinoma is a type of squamous cell carcinoma that makes up less than 5% of all oral cavity tumors. It is a low-grade cancer that rarely metastasizes but can deeply spread into surrounding tissue. Therefore, surgical removal of the tumor with a wide margin of surrounding tissue is advised. Minor salivary gland cancers can develop in the glands that are found through out the mucosal lining. There are several types of minor salivary gland cancers including adenoid cystic carcinoma, mucoepidermoid carcinoma and polymorphous low-grade adenocarcinoma. The tonsils and base of tongue contain immune system (lymphoid) tissue that can develop into a cancer. There are other tumors that will be described in this article. The treatment and outlook for cure (prognosis) are different from different tumors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Danielo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campana, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisan las principales neoplasias malignas de la cavidad oral con descripción de las características clínicas, diagnósticos diferenciales y tratamiento. Más del 90% de las neoplasias de la cavidad oral son carcinomas de células escamosas; están conformados por células escamosas planas que forman normalmente el revestimiento de la cavidad oral. Se denomina &#147;carcinoma in situ&#148; (forma temprana) cuando las células tumorales se encuentran dentro de la capa de revestimiento: el epitelio. El &#147;carcinoma invasivo&#148; implica una diseminación de dichas células hacia capas mas profundas de la boca. El carcinoma verrucoso es un tipo de carcinoma de células escamosas que puede representar hasta el 5% de los tumores de la cavidad oral. Es un cáncer de bajo grado que raramente metastatiza; pero puede extenderse hacia los tejidos circundantes. Es necesaria una extirpación con amplio margen de seguridad. Los carcinomas también pueden desarrollarse en las glándulas salivales menores que se encuentran en la mucosa de revestimiento. Existen varios tipos que incluyen el carcinoma adenoide quístico, carcinoma mucoepidermoide y el adenocarcinoma polimorfo de bajo grado. La lengua y la base de la misma contienen un sistema inmunológico que puede ser asiento de malignidad. Otros tumores menos frecuentes se describirán en esta presentación. El tratamiento y el pronóstico difieren según el tumor de origen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;38(6): 221-228, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores malignos de boca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9554^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22700^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22544^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12893^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22664^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
