<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112633</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative Hormonal Pattern in Patients Undergoing Radical Prostatectomy due to Prostate Cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: There is controversial evidence regarding preoperative testosterone (T) levels related to poor prognosis factors after radical prostatectomy (RP). The aim of this manuscript is to determine the relationship between preoperative T levels and final pathologic report together to biochemical recurrence after RP. Materials and methods: We prospectively analysed 143 patients submitted to RP from February 2008 to June 2010 in our centre. Pretreatment T and sex hormone-binding globulin levels were determined as part of our clinical protocol. Free calculated (fT) and bioavailable (bioT) T were calculated using Vermeulen&#146;s formula. Low T levels were defined as 346 ng/dL or less. A comparative analysis with variables pTNM, positive margins, tumour burden, Gleason score, multifocality and biochemical recurrence (using both PSA &gt; 0.4 ng/dL and PSA &gt; 0.2 ng/dL as cut-off values) was performed, according to preoperative levels of T. Results: Variables Gleason score, rate and number of positive margins, tumour burden, tumour multifocality, time to biochemical recurrence and pathological stage were not related to preoperative hormonal levels. Preoperative T &lt; 346 ng/dL was not found to be related to PSA recurrence (PSA &gt; 0,4 ng/dL log-rank, P = 0.512), although a trend was observed whenPSA &gt; 0,2 ng/dL (log-rank, P =0 .097). Conclusion: Preoperative T levels were not related to final pathological report or to biochemical recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leibar-Tamayo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcover, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Otero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casta&#152;neda-Argáiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sallent, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Los niveles preoperatorios de testosterona (T) relacionados con factores de mal pronóstico después de la prostatectomía radical (PR) han sido motivo de controversia. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar la relación entre los niveles preoperatorios de T, los resultados anatomopatológicos y la recidiva bioquímica tras la PR. Material y métodos: Analizamos de manera prospectiva 143 pacientes sometidos a PR desde febrero de 2008 a junio de 2010 en nuestro centro. Se determinaron los niveles preoperatorios de T y globulina transportadora de hormonas sexuales como parte de nuestro protocolo clínico. La T libre (Tl) y la biodisponible (Tbio) fueron calculadas usando la formula de Vermeulen. Se definieron niveles bajos de testosterona sérica como T menor o igual a 346 ng/dL. Se realizó un análisis comparativo analizando las variables pTNM, márgenes positivos, tamaño tumoral,escala de Gleason, multifocalidad, recidiva bioquímica (usando los 2 cortes de PSA &gt; 0,4 ng/dLy PSA &gt; 0,2 ng/dL como valores de corte) en función de los niveles preoperatorios de T. Resultados: Las variables Gleason, la tasa y número de márgenes positivos, el tamaño tumoral, la multifocalidad, el tiempo a recidiva bioquímica y el estadio patológico final no se correlacionaron con los niveles preoperatorios hormonales. Los niveles preoperatorios bajos de T (&lt; 346 ng/dL) no se relacionaron con recidiva bioquímica (PSA &gt; 0,4 ng/dL de log-rank, p = 0,512),aunque sí se observó una tendencia cuando PSA &gt; 0,2 ng/dL (log-rank, p = 0,097).Conclusión: Los niveles preoperatorios de T no se relacionaron con las características anatomopatológicas del cáncer de próstata ni con la presencia de recidiva bioquímica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(5): 280-285, mayo 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil hormonal preoperatorio en pacientes sometidos a prostatectomía radical por cáncer de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38104^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
