<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100462</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary care nurses think, analyze and propose improvements ion pharmacological adherente</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To find out how primary care nurses perceive and handle pharmacological non-adherence and to identify areas for improvement. Methods: A qualitative study including focal groups and in-depth interviews was carried out in May-June 2009 in the Sanitary Area V of Asturias, Spain. Interviews were recorded and transcribed in order to analyze the contents. Results: Data on how nurses assess and handle pharmacological adherence are presented, as well as the difficulties they face and proposals for improvement. They believe this problem should be taken care of by both practitioners and nurses. The difficulties they find are: prescription fields deficiently recorded; the sparse revalidation of prescriptions by general practitioners; the lack of activity recording protocols; and the insufficient training on pharmacology nurses have. They reject the marker system used by the community Healthcare System because the daily routine of the nurses is not appreciated. They propose improving the records, the availability of pharmacology training and nursing training, the development of adherence assessment protocols in the Sanitary Area and the implementation of multidisciplinary programs. Conclusions: Nurses give great relevance to the pharmacological non-adherence issue, and they devote time and effort to it. The impediments they highlight reduce the effectiveness of the interventions carried out. Training is necessary for a better handling of this issue, as well as the joint multidisciplinary participation of practitioners, nurses, pharmacists, social workers, clinical psychologists and managers, patients and relatives so as to implement strategies which may optimize the outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Castillo Arévalo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer cómo se percibe y aborda la adherencia farmacológica por enfermeras de Atención Primaria e identificar áreas de mejora. Método: Estudio cualitativo mediante grupos focales y entrevistas en profundidad realizado en mayo y junio de 2009 en el Área Sanitaria V de Asturias. Audiograbadas y posteriormente transcritas para análisis de contenido. Resultados: Se exponen los relativos a cómo valoran e intervienen sobre la adherencia farmacológica, las dificultades que encuentran y propuestas de mejora. Estiman que es un problema que debe ser tratado por médicos y enfermeras. Las dificultades que perciben son: el deficiente registro de los apartados de la receta, la escasa revalidación de la prescripción por los médicos; la ausencia de protocolos de registro de la actividad, y la insuficiente formación en farmacología por parte de las enfermeras. Rechazan el sistema de indicadores utilizados por el Sistema de Salud de la Comunidad por no valorar el quehacer cotidiano de las enfermeras. Proponen la mejora de los registros, formación en farmacología y metodología enfermera, el desarrollo de protocolos de valoración de la adherencia en el Área Sanitaria, y la implantación de programas pluridisciplinares. Conclusiones. Las enfermeras otorgan gran importancia al problema del incumplimiento farmacológico, dedicándole tiempo y esfuerzos. Las dificultades que señalan restan efectividad a las intervenciones que realizan. Se necesita formación para un mejor manejo de este problema y la participación pluriprofesional (médicos, enfermeras, farmacéuticos, trabajadoras sociales, psicólogos clínicos y responsables del ámbito gerencial), pacientes y familiares para poner en práctica estrategias que optimicen los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(25): 207-218, ene. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermeras de Atención Primaria opinan, analizan y proponen mejoras en el manejo de la adherencia farmacológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17513^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17513^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
