<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158592</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety symptoms, the mismanagement of negative emotions and the association with self-reported bruxism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper was to assess the relationship between anxiety and the mismanagement of negative emotions in people with bruxism symptoms. A total of 192 participants were included and divided into non-bruxism (n = 64) and bruxism (n = 128) groups. The bruxism group was subdivided into sleep bruxism (n = 26), awake bruxism (n = 52), and combined bruxism (n = 50). A non-experimental and cross-sectional descriptive method was used. The self-reported bruxism questionnaire (SBQ), the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) and Coping Strategies Inventory (CSI) were used. Statistical analysis was performed using structural equation modelling and the goodness of fit figures presented adequate values. Results showed a strong positive association between inadequate coping, anxiety symptoms and self-reported bruxism. The model showed that self-criticism and social withdrawal strategies have a direct effect on affective-cognitive and somatic anxiety symptoms; these symptoms predicted the clinical symptoms of bruxism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Landero-Hernández, René</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanegas-Farfano, Minerva TJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ramírez, Mónica T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Fierro, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar la relación entre la ansiedad y el manejo inadecuado de las emociones negativas en personas con síntomas de bruxismo, en una muestra de 192 participantes, separados en grupos sin bruxismo (n = 64) y bruxismo (n = 128), dividido este en los subgrupos bruxismo de sueño (n = 26), bruxismo en vigilia (n = 52) y bruxismo combinado (n = 50). Se utilizó un método descriptivo, no experimental y transversal. Se aplicó el Cuestionario de autoinforme de bruxismo (SBQ), el Inventario de ansiedad de Beck (BAI) y el Inventario de estrategias de afrontamiento (CSI). El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales, con estadísticos de bondad de ajuste de valores adecuados. Los resultados muestran una asociación fuerte y positiva entre el afrontamiento inadecuado, los síntomas de ansiedad y el bruxismo autoinformado. Las estrategias autocritica y retirada social tienen efecto directo sobre los síntomas de ansiedad afectivo-cognitivos y somáticos, y estos síntomas predicen los síntomas clínicos de bruxismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;22(2): 62-67, jul.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas de ansiedad, el manejo inadecuado de las emociones negativas y su asociación con bruxismo autoinformado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2040^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
