<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85896</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary circulation: what has 2010 brought?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In both thromboembolic disease and pulmonary hypertension, 2010 has been a prodigious year for interestingpublications. Some data have helped to elucidate the factors associated with a greater risk of thromboembolicdisease, such as long journeys and certain polymorphisms. New recommendations on diagnosis have beenmade, giving a greater role to computed tomography angiography. Magnetic resonance imaging is also gainingground. More accurate risk evaluation is one of the objectives of the new guidelines of the European Societyof Cardiology, which substitute some terms such as massive or submassive for high- and low-risk. Maintaininganticoagulation indefinitely in idiopathic pulmonary thromboembolism is recommended. Evidence on theefficacy of new drugs such as rivaroxaban, dabigatran and indraparinux is beginning to appear.In pulmonary hypertension, smoking seems to play a role as a risk factor. Some registries indicate that newtreatments have not improved survival. Greater knowledge has been gained of the role of inflammation in thepathogenesis of the disease and a Spanish study supports the role of the 6-minute walk test in patientevaluation. Some drugs are highlighted in the literature. Imatinib is promising but probably only in somepatients. Riociguat provides good results and inhaled treprostinil has emerged as a new option(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baloira Villar, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Díez, Javier de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tanto en el ámbito de la enfermedad tromboembólica como en el de la hipertensión pulmonar el año 2010 hasido pródigo en publicaciones de interés. Respecto a la primera, algunos datos han ayudado a conocer mejorlos factores asociados a mayor riesgo de presentarla, como viajes largos o ciertos polimorfismos. Desde elpunto de vista del diagnóstico, han aparecido nuevas recomendaciones, con mayor protagonismo de la angio-TC. La resonancia magnética también va ganando terreno. Establecer con mayor certeza el riesgo del pacientees uno de los objetivos de las nuevas guías de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología, que sustituyen algunostérminos como masivo o submasivo por otros como alto o bajo riesgo. Respecto al tratamiento, se abogapor mantener de forma indefinida la anticoagulación en casos de tromboembolismo pulmonar idiopático. Losnuevos fármacos, como rivaroxaban, dabigatran o indraparinux, empiezan a acumular evidencias acerca de sueficacia.Respecto de la hipertensión pulmonar, el tabaco parece desempeñar un cierto papel como factor de riesgo.Los resultados de algunos registros no parecen ser muy alentadores en cuanto a la mejoría de la supervivenciacon los nuevos tratamientos. Se comienza a conocer algo más el papel de la inflamación en la patogenia de laenfermedad y un estudio español refuerza el papel de la prueba de 6 min en la evaluación del paciente. Algunosfármacos empiezan a asomar en la literatura científica. El imatinib es prometedor pero seguramente sóloen algunos pacientes, riociguat muestra buenos resultados y treprostinil inhalado surge como nueva opción(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.1): 7-11, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Circulación pulmonar: ¿qué ha aportado el año 2010?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28274^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28274^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
