<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144018</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protein expression of metalloproteinases-2 (MMP-2) and its tissue inhibitor (TIMP-2) in aorta, fascia and plasma of patients with abdominal aortic aneurysm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are data that associates abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAA) with an increased prevalence of hernia disease. A possible structural alteration of extracellular matrix may be common in the degenerative process of the aortic wall and the abdominal fascia. Objective: Determine the expression of matrix metalloproteinases-2 (MMP-2) and tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases-2 (TIMP-2) in aortic wall tissue, abdominal fascia, and plasma of patients undergoing AAA versus patients with aortic occlusive disease (EAO). Material and methods: A pilot, prospective observational study was conducted, in which the protein expression of MMP-2 and TIMP-2 was analyzed in 10 patients with AAA, and in 10 with EAO, using an ELISA technique. Epidemiological data, history of hernias, and AAA diameters were collected. Results: In the subgroup of medium sized AAA with a history of hernia, over-expression of MMP-2 was found in fascia, and of TIMP-2 in aorta and fascia. As regards EAO without hernia (MMP-2 fascia: AAA = 4.53 [3.11-6.90], EAO = 1.87 [1.45-2.90], P=.04; TIMP-2 in aorta: AAA = 72.62 [9.26-161.12], EAO = 9.79 [5.55-25.61], P=.04, and TIMP-2 in fascia: AAA = 35.24 [13.15-61.08], EAO =4.98 [1.42-18.01], P=.02).The MMP-2 and TIMP-2 was increased in AAA fascia hernia disease compared with EAO without hernia (MMP-2: 4.31 [3.35-6.35] versus 1.87 [1.45-2.90], P=.009, and TIMP-2: 18.73 [7.76-57.97] versus 4.98 [1.42-18.01], P=.08).There was an increased TIMP-2 in the aortic wall, AAA (29.27 [14.05-140.30] vs. EAO 9.79 [6.19-32.74], P=.06). Conclusions: The MMP-2 and TIMP-2 are increased in aorta and fascia of patients with AAA, especially in the medium size, suggesting a role in the etiology. The increase in MMP-2 and TIMP-2 in the presence of hernia, enhances the idea of a common pathogenic mechanism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferruelo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañibano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existen datos que asocian los aneurismas de aorta abdominal (AAA) con un incremento de la prevalencia de la enfermedad herniaria. Una posible alteración estructural de la matriz extracelular puede ser común en el proceso degenerativo de la pared aórtica y de la fascia abdominal. Objetivo: Conocer la expresión de metaloproteinasas de matriz-2 (MMP-2) y el inhibidor tisular de metaloproteinasas-2 (TIMP-2) en pared aórtica, fascia abdominal y plasma de pacientes intervenidos de AAA frente a pacientes con enfermedad aórtica oclusiva (EAO). Material y métodos: Estudio piloto, observacional prospectivo. Se analizó la expresión proteica de MMP-2 y TIMP-2 en 10 pacientes con AAA y 10 con EAO. Recogimos datos epidemiológicos, antecedentes de hernias y diámetros del AAA. El análisis se realizó por técnica de ELISA. Resultados: En el subgrupo de AAA de mediano tamaño con antecedentes de hernia, encontramos sobreexpresión de MMP-2 en fascia y de TIMP-2 en aorta y fascia, respecto a EAO sin hernia (MMP-2 fascia: AAA = 4,53 [3,11-6,90]; EAO = 1,87 [1,45-2,90]; p = 0,04; TIMP-2 en aorta: AAA = 72,62 [9,26-161,12], EAO = 9,79 [5,55-25,61]; p = 0,04 y TIMP-2 en fascia: AAA = 35,24 [13,15-61,08], EAO = 4,98 [1,42-18,01]; p = 0,02). La MMP-2 y el TIMP-2 estaban aumentados en fascia de AAA con enfermedad herniaria frente a EAO sin hernia (MMP-2: 4,31 [3,35-6,35] versus 1,87 [1,45-2,90]; p = 0,009 y TIMP-2: 18,73 [7,76-57,97] versus 4,98 [1,42-18,01]; p = 0,08). En pared aórtica hubo aumento de TIMP-2 en AAA (29,27 [14,05-140,30] frente a EAO, 9,79 [6,19-32,74]; p = 0,06). Conclusiones: La MMP-2 y el TIMP-2 están aumentados, en aorta y fascia de pacientes con AAA, sobre todo, en los de mediano tamaño, lo que indica cierto papel en la etiología. El incremento de MMP-2 y TIMP-2 en presencia de hernia potencia la idea de un mecanismo patogénico común (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;67(6): 447-453, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión proteica de metaloproteinasa-2 (MMP-2) y su inhibidor tisular (TIMP-2) en aorta, fascia y plasma de pacientes con aneurisma de aorta abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33427</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5309^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
