<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98749</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recombinant viruses as tools to induce protective cellular immunity against infectious diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infections by intracellular pathogens such as viruses, some bacteria and many parasites, are cleared in most cases after activation of specific T cellular immune responses that recognize foreign antigens and eliminate infected cells. Vaccines against those infectious organisms have been traditionally developed by administration of whole live attenuated or inactivated microorganisms. Nowadays, research is focused on the development of subunit vaccines, containing the most immunogenic antigens from the particular pathogen. However, when purified subunit vaccines are administered using traditional immunization protocols, the levels of cellular immunity induced are mostly low and not capable of eliciting complete protection against diseases caused by intracellular microbes. In this review, we present a promising alternative to those traditional protocols, which is the use of recombinant viruses encoding subunit vaccines as immunization tools. Recombinant viruses have several interesting features that make them extremely efficient at inducing immune responses mediated by T-lymphocytes. This cellular immunity has recently been demonstrated to be of key importance for protection against malaria and AIDS, both of which are major targets of the World Health Organization for vaccine development. Thus, this review will focus in particular on the development of new vaccination protocols against these diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rocha, Carolina Damas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado, Alexandre Vieira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruña-Romero, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caetano, Braulia Costa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones por patógenos intracelulares como virus, algunas bacterias y numerosos parásitos son neutralizadas en la mayoría de los casos tras la activación de respuestas inmunitarias específicas mediadas por linfocitos T, que reconocen los antígenos extraños y eliminan las células infectadas. Las vacunas contra estos organismos infecciosos se han basado tradicionalmente en la administración de organismos enteros atenuados o inactivados. Actualmente la investigación se centra en el desarrollo de vacunas compuestas por subunidades que contengan los antígenos más inmunogénicos para cada patógeno particular. No obstante, si se administran vacunas de subunidades purificadas mediante los protocolos tradicionales de inmunización, los niveles inducidos de inmunidad celular son en su mayoría bajos e incapaces de generar una protección completa contra las enfermedades causadas por los microorganismos intracelulares. En esta revisión presentamos una prometedora alternativa a estos métodos tradicionales mediante el uso de virus recombinantes cuyo genoma codifica las subunidades de vacuna. Los virus recombinantes reúnen varias características que los hacen muy eficientes para inducir las respuestas inmunitarias mediadas por los linfocitos T. Recientemente se ha demostrado que la inmunidad celular es crucial en la protección contra la malaria y el SIDA, que son un objetivo prioritario de la Organización Mundial de la Salud en cuanto al desarrollo de vacunas. Por lo tanto, esta revisión se centra especialmente en el desarrollo de nuevos protocolos de vacunación contra estas dos enfermedades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;7(2): 83-94, jun. 2004. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de virus recombinantes para inducir inmunidad celular contra enfermedades infecciosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31318^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23126^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7295^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d267</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23130^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30273^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
