<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114351</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperplastic polyposis syndrome: phenotypic diversity and association to colorectal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Hyperplastic polyposis syndrome (HPS) is an uncommon disorder characterized by hyperplastic polyps (HP) occasionally associated with serrated adenomas (SA) or mixed polyps (MP) and defined by clinical criteria (OMS/Cleveland). HPS is heterogeneous regarding the number and size of polyps, and it is associated with colorectal cáncer (CRC) and a family history. Its genetic basis is unknow. We describe individuals with HPS criteria from a series of families assessed in our Unit of Genetic Advice for colonic polyposis. Our objective is to identify the clinical characteristics of this syndrome. Patients and methods: Retrospective study of 197 families with colonic polyposis (1998-2011), identifying patients with HPS criteria. To know the number of polyps, we took into account polypectomies and/or the histologic study of surgical samples. Polyps were classified into adenomas, serrated lesiones (HP and SA) and MP. Genetic studies revealed: microsatellite instability (MSI), MUTYH gene variants (p.Tyr165Cys, p.Gly382Asp and p.Glu396GlyfsX43) and APC gene. Results: Eighteen individuals, with a median age of 51.1 years, had criteria of HPS (11 M/7 F). Number of HP varied between 14 and 100 coexisting with classical adenomas, SA and MP in 14 individuals (77.8%). Localization of polyps: ascending and descending colon in 13 individuals (72.2%) and only descending colon in 5 (27.8%). A CRC was detected in 10/18 (55.6%) patients, and 3 of them had a double CRC, a family history in 3 patients (16.7%) and a history of HPS in one. IMS was not detected in 8 CRC nor in 3 adenomas studied; we detected 2/13 heterozygous mutations in the MUTYH gene(p.Gly382Asp) and one variant with an unknown biological significance in the APC gene (p.Ser926Pro). Conclusions: The phenotypic variability of HPS difficults its identification, hence it is important to adhere to the clinical criteria established for its classification as well as to establish screening guidelines for CRC on the basis of its high incidence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capellá, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Moranta, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El síndrome de poliposis hiperplásica (SPH) es un cuadro poco frecuente caracterizado por la presencia de pólipos hiperplásicos (PH) ocasionalmente asociados a adenomas serrados (AS) o pólipos mixtos (PM), y definido por criterios clínicos (OMS/Cleveland). El SPH es heterogéneo con respecto al número, tamaño de los pólipos, asociación a cáncer colorrectal (CCR) e historia familiar. Se desconoce su base genética. Describimos aquellos individuos que cumplen criterios de SPH dentro de la serie de familias valoradas en nuestra Unidad de Consejo Genético por una poliposis colónica. Nuestro objetivo es identificar las características clínicas de este síndrome. Pacientes y método: Estudio retrospectivo de 197 familias con poliposis colónica (1998-2011), en que se identificaron aquellos individuos con criterios de SPH. Para saber el número total de pólipos, se tuvo en cuenta las polipectomías y/o el estudio histológico de las piezas quirúrgicas. Los pólipos se clasificaron en adenomas, lesiones serradas (PH y AS) y PM. Los estudios genéticos realizados fueron: inestabilidad de microsatélites (IMS), variantes del gen MUTYH (p.Tyr165Cys, p.Gly382Asp y p.Glu396GlyfsX43) y el gen APC. Resultados: Un total de 18 individuos, con una edad media de 51,1 años, cumplían criterios de SPH (11 varones y 7 mujeres). El número de PH osciló entre 14 y 100,coexistiendo con adenomas clásicos, AS y PM en 14 individuos (77,8%). La localización de pólipos fue: colon derecho e izquierdo en 13 individuos (72,2%) y solo colon izquierdo en 5 (27,8%). Se detectó CCR en 10/18 (55,6%) pacientes, 3 de ellos (30%) presentaban un doble CCR, una historia familiar de CCR en 3 pacientes (16,7%) y de SPH en uno. No se detectó IMS en 8 CCR ni en los 3 adenomas estudiados; se detectaron 2/13 mutaciones en heterocigosis en el gen MUTYH (p.Gly382Asp) y una variante de significado biológico desconocido en el gen APC (p.Ser926Pro). Conclusiones: La variabilidad fenotípica del SPH dificulta su identificación, por lo que es importante seguir los criterios clínicos establecidos para su clasificación, así como establecer pautas de cribado de CCR dada la elevada incidencia del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(2): 62-66, jul. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de poliposis hiperplásica: diversidad fenotípica y asociación a cáncer colorrectal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28109^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31896^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
