<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054159</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethics and pediatric cardiopulmonary resuscitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) is a medical activity that involves major ethical issues. As in other areas of clinical ethics, CPR decisions must be based on the principles of autonomy, beneficence, nonmaleficence, and justice. The decision-making process is more difficult in emergency situations, and when the patient is a minor, the parents and the child's best interests must be taken into consideration. There are specific situations in which starting CPR is clearly indicated and others in which ceasing resuscitation maneuvers is justified. Do not attempt resuscitation orders must be respected by health staff. Other ethical issues involved in CPR include resuscitation of potential organ donors, learning CPR procedures, research in CPR, and the information given to the parents of children with cardiorespiratory arrest</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Núñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermana Tezanos, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Galán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Herce Cid, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP) es una actividad médica que presenta importantes aspectos éticos. Al igual que en otras áreas de la ética asistencial, las decisiones en relación con la RCP deben estar basadas en los principios de autonomía, beneficencia, no maleficencia y justicia distributiva. Las situaciones de emergencia vital hacen más difícil la toma de decisiones y el hecho de que el paciente sea menor de edad obliga a tener en cuenta a sus padres y considerar el mejor interés del niño. Existen situaciones en las que está claramente indicado el inicio de la RCP y otras en las que está justificado suspender las maniobras de reanimación. Los documentos de 'orden de no reanimar' deben ser respetados por el equipo reanimador. Otros aspectos éticos de la RCP incluyen la reanimación de posibles donantes de órganos, el aprendizaje de maniobras, la investigación en RCP y la información a los padres de los niños que han sufrido una parada cardiorrespiratoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(1): 45-50, ene. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ética y reanimación cardiopulmonar pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5080^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
