<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96842</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nebulized furosemide to treat breathlessness in emergency patients with advanced cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Three patients with advanced cancer and acute dyspnea for different reasons were treated with furosemide spray in a hospital emergency department. A single dose of 40 mg of nebulized furosemide was sprayed and inhaled in a single dose. Breathlessness improved significantly, bringing the episode under control, in patients with at least 50% of function according to the Palliative Performance Status (PPS) scale. However, furosemide did not improve the condition of apatient with end-stage dyspnea. No adverse effects were observed. Inhaling nebulized furosemide seems to be an effective treatment for breathlessness in patients with terminal cancer and a 50% PPS function assessment, although randomized controlled trials are needed to confirm this hypothesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quiñones Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Frías, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Jiménez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tres pacientes con cáncer avanzado y crisis de disnea por diferentes causas fueron tratados con furosemida nebulizada en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario. Cuarenta miligramos de furosemida fueron nebulizados e inhalados en una sola administración. La disnea mejoró de forma importante en los dos pacientes con una funcionalidad del 50% o más medida con el Palliative Performance Status (PPS), que controló el episodio. No fue así en el tercer paciente con disnea en fase final de la vida. No se observaron efectos adversos en ninguno de los casos. La inhalación de furosemida nebulizada parece ser efectiva en el tratamiento de la disnea en pacientes con cáncer terminal y un PPS igual o mayor al 50%, pero esta observación requiere ser confirmada con estudios randomizados controlados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(3): 208-210, jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96842</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Furosemida nebulizada como tratamiento en urgencias de la disnea en pacientes con cáncer terminal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19256^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
