<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95139</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality indicators in the acute coronary syndrome for the analysis of the pre- and in-hospital care process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a map of 27 indicators to measure the care quality given to patients with acute coronary syndrome attended in the pre- and hospital area. This includes technical process indicators (registration of care intervals, performance of electrocardiogram, monitoring and vein access, assessment of prognostic risk, hemorrhage and in-hospital mortality, use of reperfusion techniques and performance of echocardiograph), pharmacological process indicators (platelet receptors inhibition, anticoagulation, thrombolysis, beta-blockers, angiotensin converting inhibitors and lipid lowering drugs) and outcomes indicators (quality scales of the care given and mortality)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuset-Cabanes, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felices-Abad, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latour-Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruano-Marco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogal-Sáez, F. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuñat-de la Hoz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un mapa de 27 indicadores para medir la calidad de la asistencia prestada a los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA) que son atendidos en el ámbito pre e intrahospitalario. Se incluyen indicadores de proceso técnicos (registro de los intervalos asistenciales, realización del ECG, monitorización y acceso venoso, evaluación de los riesgos pronóstico, hemorrágico y de mortalidad intrahospitalaria, empleo de técnicas de reperfusión y realización de ecocardiografía), indicadores de proceso farmacológicos (antiagregación plaquetaria, anticoagulación, trombolisis, administración de beta-bloqueantes, inhibidores de conversión de la angiotensina e hipolipemiantes) e indicadores de resultado (escalas de calidad de la atención prestada y mortalidad) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(6): 397-417, ago.-sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores de calidad en el síndrome coronario agudo para el análisis del proceso asistencial pre e intrahospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
