<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95546</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">VAC® therapy in severe left leg injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The open fractures of the lower limb caused by high energy trauma, poses a major surgical challenge. These wounds have a significative complexity, with multiple lesions involving bone, muscle, nerves, vessels, skin and subcutaneous tissues. There are a wide spectrum of reconstructive options for the treatment, most of them requiring complex microsurgical transfers of autologous tissue. The Vacuum Assisted Therapy (VAC ®) has become a most useful tool for the plastic surgeon since the last century&#146;s 90 decade. Based in the application of negative pressure to the wound bed, promotes healing by granulation tissue formation, keeping the wound clean and avoiding bacterial colonization. Used as a primary method or in combination with others, VAC® therapy allows more conservative options in the treatment of these wounds, lowering the incidence of complications and avoiding the need of demanding and high cost surgical interventions. We describe the application of the VAC® therapy in a clinical case with complex lower limb open fracture and crush injury, showing its efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan Pérez, F. J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fracturas abiertas de los miembros inferiores debidas a traumatismos de alta energía, suponen un reto terapéutico debido a la gravedad de las heridas, la afectación importante de varios tipos de tejidos y a la complejidad de los procedimientos quirúrgicos necesarios para su tratamiento que pueden llegar hasta complicadas técnicas microquirúrgicas mediante colgajos libres, quedarse en un colgajo muscular o compuesto, pediculado, o bien mantener una actitud más conservadora. Esto último es posible desde la aparición en los años 90 de una nueva técnica, la Terapia Vacuum Assisted Closure ( TerapiaVAC ® ), que se basa en la aplicación de vacío o presión negativa sobre la herida. Este recurso terapéutico permite una pauta más conservadora de tratamiento de estas fracturas tan complejas, reduciendo los riesgos, la morbilidad y minimizando las complicaciones. Presentamos un caso de fractura del miembro inferior izquierdo, abierta, compleja, con policontusión y aplastamiento, que creemos muy demostrativo del excelente resultado clínico que se puede obtener mediante el empleo de la terapia con presión negativa con el Sistema VAC ® (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;36(3): 247-254, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia VAC® en traumatismo grave de pierna izquierda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8047^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5733^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
