<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75657</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organisational model for a traumatology and Orthopaedic Surgery Department in a Basic Regional Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Within a context of clinical-nursing process management which clearly emphasisses the control of health expenditure, the implementation of a model which gives prominence to the centrality of the patient seems to be the optimum model. Thus, the &#147;admission-hospitalization&#148; model is complemented with new forms of management which, as this work proposes, do not entail changes in quality, but rather progressive improvements and an optimization of the Service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canos i Areste, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En un contexto de gestión de procesos cínico-asistenciales que apuesta claramente por el control de gasto sanitario, la implementación de un modelo que potencie la centralidad del paciente se antoja como modelo óptimo. Así, el modelo &lt;ingreso-hospitalización&gt; se complementa con nuevas formas de gestión que, como propone este trabajo, no implica cambios de calidad, sino mejoras progresivas y optimización del Servicio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(243): 41-47, ene.-feb. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75657</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo organizativo para un Servicio de Traumatología y cirugía Ortopédica de un Hospital Comarcal Básico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19369^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51846</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
