<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119343</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognosis and treatment of dry mouth. Systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are no clearly established protocols for the treatment of dry mouth. The aim of this paper is a systematic review of the literature of the past 10 years using the words «dry mouth», «prognosis», «treatment» and «dentistry». The initial search found 1,450 entries and within the restriction «clinical trials OR randomized controlled trial OR systemic reviews» it has been reduced to 522, which 145 were meta-analysis and systematic reviews. Papers not relevant to the issue were removed reducing the entries to 53. Twenty-four were dismissed (8 irrelevant, 7 reviews without adequate information and 9 personal opinions). Of the 29 items tested, 15 were controlled trials, 2 uncontrolled trials, 4 observational studies, 2 systematic reviews and 5 non systematic reviews. The most studied patients were Sjögren's syndrome and the irradiated patients. Treatments are focused on the etiology, prevention, symptomatic, local salivary stimulation and systemic treatments. It can be concluded that treatment must be individualized, salivary substitutes and mechanical stimulation techniques can be applied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chimenos Küstener, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jané Salas, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No existen protocolos claramente establecidos para el tratamiento de la boca seca. El objetivo de este trabajo es realizar una revisión sistemática de la literatura médica de los últimos 10 años. Hemos utilizado las palabras: «dry mouth», «prognosis», «treatment» y «dentistry». En una primera búsqueda hemos encontrado 1.450 entradas. Con la restricción «clinical trials OR randomized controlled trial OR systemic reviews» se han reducido a 522, de las que 145 eran metaanálisis y revisiones sistemáticas. Se han eliminado las que no eran pertinentes al tema y han quedado reducidas a 53. Posteriormente se descartaron 24 (8 no pertinentes, 7 revisiones y 9 opiniones personales). De los 29 artículos analizados, 15 son ensayos clínicos controlados, 2 ensayos no controlados, 4 estudios observacionales, 2 revisiones sistemáticas y 5 revisiones. Los enfermos mejor estudiados son los pacientes con síndrome de Sjögren y los pacientes irradiados. El tratamiento se centra en el etiológico, preventivo, sintomático, de estimulación salival local y sistémicos. Podemos concluir que el tratamiento debe ser individualizado, pudiéndose aplicar sustitutos salivales y diferentes técnicas de estimulación mecánica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(3): 119-124, feb. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico y tratamiento de la boca seca. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12839^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12841^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
