<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124931</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of non-invasive hemoglobin measurements using the Masimo Rainbow Radical-7 ® device in a patient with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Circulatory assist devices such as extracorporeal membrane oxygenation are indicated in cases of cardiogenic shock refractory to optimal conventional treatment. Bleeding is a serious complication of such systems, mainly due to coagulation disorders caused by continuous administration of heparin, as well as platelet dysfunction. Serial coagulation and hemoglobin (Hb) measurements are essential. Hb measurements can be performed through repeated arterial blood gasometry, and more recently with a new spectrophotometric sensor, Masimo Rainbow Radical-7® device, which gives Hb values continuously and non-invasively. We report a case of a patient undergoing cardiac surgery who required extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe cardiogenic shock immediately after surgery. We compare the correlation and the level of agreement with Hb levels measured by 2 existing systems in clinical practice. Our results indicate that the Masimo® spectrophotometric monitor showed statistically comparable Hb values, in the correlation (r = .85; P &lt; .01) and in agreement with those obtained by serial blood gas analyzer, ABL800 FLEX® (wavelength). In view of these results we consider the Masimo® device as a valid alternative for the continuous follow-up of the Hb and control of bleeding in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artieda, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarragoikoetxea, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barberá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los dispositivos de asistencia circulatoria tipo oxigenación extracorpórea de membrana están indicados en casos de shock cardiogénico refractario al tratamiento convencional óptimo. La hemorragia es una grave complicación de dichos sistemas debido fundamentalmente a los trastornos de la coagulación provocados por la administración continua de heparina y a la disfunción plaquetaria. Los controles seriados de la coagulación y de la hemoglobina (Hb) son imprescindibles. Las mediciones de Hb se pueden realizar a través de gasometrías repetidas y más recientemente con un nuevo sensor espectrofotométrico, dispositivo Masimo Rainbow Radical-7®, que nos ofrece valores de Hb de forma continua y no invasiva. Presentamos el caso de un paciente sometido a cirugía cardíaca que requirió oxigenación extracorpórea de membrana por shock cardiogénico grave en el postoperatorio inmediato. Comparamos la correlación y el grado de concordancia respecto a los niveles de Hb cuantificados por 2 sistemas existentes en la práctica clínica. Nuestros resultados indican que el monitor espectrofotométrico Masimo® mostró valores de Hb equiparables estadísticamente, en correlación (r = 0,85; p &lt; 0,01) y concordancia, a los obtenidos por gasometrías seriadas con el Analizador ABL800 FLEX® (longitud de onda). Ante estos resultados consideramos el dispositivo evaluado como una alternativa válida para el seguimiento continuo de la Hb y el control de la hemorragia en este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;61(7): 388-391, ago.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las mediciones de hemoglobina no invasiva con el dispositivo Masimo Rainbow Radical-7 ® en un paciente portador de oxigenación extracorpórea de membrana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23632^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13436^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23632^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13436^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23632^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13436^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
