<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130392</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fair use of tests in health sciences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Standardized measurement instruments (tests) have become an essential tool in health sciences. The concept of equity in the development, adaptation and administration of psychometric tests was first introduced in «Standards for Educational and Psychological Testing» published in 1999 by the American Educational Research Association, the American Psychological Association, and the National Council on Measurement in Education. Despite its importance, this concept has been scarcely used in epidemiology and public health. Consequently, this methodological note aims to explain the concept of equity in testing and to provide tools and indications to detect and solve their inequitable use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doval, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rueda, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espelt, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliaga, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viladrich, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tárrega, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los instrumentos de medida estandarizados (tests) se han convertido en una herramienta imprescindible en las ciencias de la salud. En los estándares para pruebas educativas y psicológicas publicados en 1999 por la American Educational Research Association, la American Psychological Association y el National Council on Measurement in Education se introduce el concepto de equidad en el desarrollo, la adaptación y la administración de los tests psicométricos. A pesar de su innegable relevancia, este concepto ha sido poco utilizado en el mundo de la salud pública y la epidemiología. Por ello, la presente nota metodológica tiene como objetivo explicar el concepto de equidad en los tests y dar herramientas e indicaciones para detectar y solventar su uso no equitativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(5): 408-410, sept.-oct. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso equitativo de tests en ciencias de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33941</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
