<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114346</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the effect of physical group activities in patients with acquired brain injury in the subacute phase</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The term acquired brain injury (ABI) refers to any kind of non-degenerative injury that occurs in the brain.  Group physical activities (GPA) are an effective treatment that improves the functional capacity. Aims. To analyse the efficacy of a GPA programme in persons with ABI in the subacute phase so that they can be reintegrated physically in the community.Patients and methods. Thirty-three patients with ABI, aged 33.18 ± 10.39 years, took part in a 10-week GPA programme  (circuit workshops, simple equilibrium, dual equilibrium, dual displacement and physical-sports activities). At the start and  the end of the programme the following variables were evaluated: speed (10-metre walking speed test), resistance (sixminute walk test), dynamic balance (Step Test), functional capacity (Timed Up &amp; Go), safety perception scale (Activitiesspecific Balance Confidence Scale) and Physical Activity and Disability Survey (PADS), the average per hour intensity of the   ctivity and the number of steps outside the rehabilitation centre (using physical activity monitors). The t test for related  samples was used to evaluate the differences among the variables. Results. Significant differences were found (p &amp;#8804; 0.05) in the variables speed, resistance, balance, functional capacity,  perception of safety, perception of general activity performance (question 3 of the PADS) and number of steps. Conclusions. GPA programmes improve physical capacities, perception of safety, performance of activity in general and  the number of steps, which can lead to greater participation in the community (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodríguez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tejero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernández, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla Saldaña, Lázaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Alted, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El daño cerebral adquirido (DCA) hace referencia a cualquier tipo de lesión no degenerativa que se produce  en el cerebro. Las actividades físicas grupales (AFG) se presentan como un tratamiento efectivo para la mejora de la capacidad funcional.  Objetivo. Analizar la eficacia de un programa de AFG en personas con DCA en fase subaguda para su integración física en  la comunidad.  Pacientes y métodos. Treinta y tres pacientes con DCA, con una edad de 33,18 ± 10,39 años, participaron en un programa  de AFG (talleres de circuito, equilibrio simple, equilibrio dual, desplazamiento dual y actividades físico-deportivas) de 10  semanas. Al comenzar y concluir el programa se evaluaron las variables de velocidad (prueba de velocidad de la marcha en 10 metros), resistencia (prueba de marcha de seis minutos), equilibrio dinámico (Step Test), capacidad funcional  (Timed Up &amp; Go), escala de percepción de seguridad (Activities-specific Balance Confidence Scale) y Physical Activity and  Disability Survey (PADS), el promedio por hora de la intensidad de la actividad y el número de pasos fuera del centro de   rehabilitación (usando monitores de actividad física). La prueba t para muestras relacionadas se utilizó para evaluar las  diferencias en las variables.  Resultados. Se hallaron diferencias significativas (p &amp;#8804; 0,05) en las variables de velocidad, resistencia, equilibrio, capacidad  funcional, percepción de seguridad, percepción de realización de actividad general (pregunta 3 del PADS) y número de pasos.  Conclusión. Los programas de AFG mejoran las capacidades físicas, percepción de seguridad, realización de actividad en  general y número de pasos, lo que puede conllevar una mayor participación en la comunidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(2): 64-70, jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del efecto de las actividades físicas grupales en pacientes con daño cerebral adquirido en fase subaguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
