<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053714</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Connections between bone marrow and mesenchyme of the middle ear</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the presence of connections between the bone marrow of the ossicles and the mesenchyme that fills the future tympanic cavity.     Material and methods: Ninety temporal bones from embryos and foetuses were examined, selecting 15 aged between 20th to 30th weeks of development, to show connections between ossicle marrow and mesenchyme.     Results: The connections are transitory and appear in the malleus and the incus between 20th to 24th weeks of development, while in the stapes appear later, being between 24th to 28th weeks.     Conclusions: These connections may have an important role in the phagocytosis of the mesenchymal remains and join in the detritus elimination mechanisms produced during the regression</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gañet Solé, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sanz, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yus Gotor, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Whyte Orozco, Jaime Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Gimeno, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarrat Torres, Marco Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si existen conexiones entre la médula ósea de los osículos timpánicos y el mesénquima que rellena la futura cavidad timpánica.     Material y métodos: Se han examinado 90 huesos temporales pertenecientes a embriones y fetos, y se han seleccionado 15 de edades comprendidas entre las semanas 20 y 30 del desarrollo al presentar conexiones entre médula del osículo y el mesénquima.     Resultados: Las conexiones son de tipo transitorio y aparecen en el martillo y el yunque entre las semanas 20 y 24 de desarrollo, mientras que en el estribo se manifiestan posteriormente, entre las semanas 24 y 28.     Conclusiones: Estas conexiones pueden tener un papel importante en la fagocitosis de los restos mesenquimales y sumarse a los mecanismos de eliminación de los detritus producidos durante la regresión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(1): 4-6, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conexiones entre la médula ósea de los osículos y el mesénquima del oído medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4495^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10777</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8824</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14079^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
