<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97427</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New diagnosis of HIV infection in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The number of children of immigrant origin in the last few years has increased the cohort of HIV-infected children in the Community of Madrid. The objectives of the study were to evaluate the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of the new diagnosed children and describe the different subtypes of HIV-1.Patients and methods The new diagnosed children were analysed from the year 1997, divided into 3 periods: P1 (1997-2000), P2 (2001-2004), P3 (2005-2009). The regions and countries of origin, the clinical, immune and viral characteristics, as well as the response to treatment were analysed. The subtypes of HIV-1 were evaluated by phylogenetic analysis of protease genes and reverse transcriptase. Results We identified 141 new diagnoses of HIV infection, the percentage of immigrant origin in P1 was (22.5%), P2 (50%) and P3 (68%). The origin had changed from Latin America in P1 to sub-Saharan Africa in P3. There were no differences between Spanish and immigrant children in the age at diagnosis, the CDC clinical stage A/B/C, viral load, percentage of CD4 at diagnosis and actual. Better viral response was more likely in immigrants after the first regimen of HAART (Highly active antiretroviral treatment) independently of the treatment received. A total of 66 subtypes were obtained, 24% were subtypes non-B (56% recombinants forms). All subtypes of Spanish children (43) and Latin American (5) were subtypes B, and all the children from sub-Saharan Africa (14) were subtypes non-B. Conclusion There were no differences between immigrants and Spanish children infected by HIV, except the different subtypes of HIV-1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Granado, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>José, Maribel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez de Ory, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roa, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Ramos, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Tomé, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beceiro, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción En la cohorte de niños infectados de la Comunidad de Madrid ha aumentado el número de niños de procedencia extranjera en los últimos años. Los objetivos fueron evaluar las características epidemiológicas y clínicas en los nuevos diagnósticos y describir los diferentes subtipos del VIH-1.Pacientes y métodos Se analizaron los nuevos diagnósticos desde el año 1997, dividiéndolos en 3 periodos: P1 (1997-2000), P2 (2001-2004), P3 (2005-2009). Se analizó la procedencia según regiones geográficas y país de procedencia, las diferencias clínicas e inmunovirológicas así como respuesta al tratamiento. Se evaluó el subtipo genético del VIH-1 mediante análisis filogenético de los genes de proteasa y de la retrotranscriptasa. Resultados Se identificaron 141 nuevos diagnósticos de infección VIH, siendo el porcentaje de procedencia extranjera en P1 (22,5%), P2 (50%) y P3 (68%). La procedencia ha cambiado de Latinoamérica en P1 a África subsahariana en P3. No hubo diferencias de la media de edad al diagnóstico entre autóctonos y extranjeros, el estadio clínico CDC A/B/C, carga viral, porcentaje de CD4 al diagnóstico y actuales. Había una tendencia de mejor respuesta virológica en extranjeros tras el primer ciclo de TARGA (terapia antirretroviral de gran actividad) independiente del tratamiento recibido. Se obtuvieron 66 subtipos, el 24% eran subtipos no-B (56% formas recombinantes). Todos los subtipos de los autóctonos (43) y latinoamericanos (5) eran subtipos B, sin embargo, todos los niños procedentes de África Subsahariana (14) eran subtipos no-B. Conclusión No se encontraron diferencias entre niños infectados por VIH extranjeros o autóctonos, salvo los diferentes subtipos de VIH-1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(3): 131-136, mar. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos diagnósticos de infección VIH en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24525^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
