<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97106</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary embolism in the young adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary embolism is a frequently seen complication in the emergency department. Little information is available on the presentation of this event in patients under the age of 45 years, yet early detection and treatment continue to be the main predictors of clinical course. We aimed to describe the clinical presentation of emergency pulmonary embolism inpatients less than 45 years old, with emphasis on identifying risk factors. Cases of pulmonary embolism diagnosed in ourhospital&#146;s emergency department between September 2004 and December 2010 were reviewed retrospectively. Ourfindings confirm that pulmonary embolism is rare in patients under 45 years of age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Fuentes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Gil, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amer López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Cascón, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tromboembolismo pulmonar (TEP) es una entidad frecuente en urgencias. Existe poca información respecto a la presentación clínica del TEP en pacientes menores de 45 años, y su detección y terapéutica precoces continúan siendo predictores determinantes de su evolución. Nuestro estudio pretende caracterizar clínicamente el TEP en urgencias en pacientes menores de 45 años con especial hincapié en la identificación de sus factores predisponentes (FP). Revisamos retrospectivamente los TEP diagnosticados en urgencias de nuestro hospital entre septiembre de 2004-diciembre de 2010. Nuestro estudio confirma que el TEP es una complicación infrecuente en pacientes menores de 45 años y que en hasta 2 de cada 3 casos el riesgo trombótico es resultante de la suma de FP de bajo peso ponderado individual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(4): 307-310, ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tromboembolismo pulmonar en el adulto joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
