<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146967</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parotid hemangioma treated with propranolol: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Parotid hemangiomas are the most common salivary tumors of childhood. Due to the rapid and expansive growth, typical of these lesions, significant complications such as loss of organ function or permanent disfigurement may be present. In these cases, early therapeutic intervention can be crucial to minimize these undesirable effects. Propranolol is currently considered the drug of choice in the treatment of complicated infantile hemangiomas in various locations, with a good safety profile combined with excellent efficiency. We present the case of an infant girl, 45 days old, diagnosed with hemangioma of the right parotid and treated with propranolol; in this regard, we present a brief review of the management of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los hemangiomas parotídeos son los tumores salivares más frecuentes en la infancia. Debido al rápido y expansivo crecimiento característico de estas lesiones, pueden aparecer complicaciones significativas como pérdida de función del órgano o desfiguración permanente. En estos casos la intervención terapéutica precoz podría ser decisiva para minimizar efectos indeseables. El propranolol está considerado, actualmente, como el fármaco de primera elección en el tratamiento de los hemangiomas infantiles complicados, en múltiples localizaciones, presentando un adecuado perfil de seguridad así como una excelente eficacia. Se presenta el caso de una lactante de 45 días de vida diagnosticada de hemangioma de parótida derecha y que fue sometida a tratamiento con propranolol; a propósito de este caso se realiza una breve revisión del abordaje de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(11): e323-e329, dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemangioma parotídeo tratado con propranolol: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
