<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159382</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-2345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of low levels of vitamin D in patients with breast cancer who live in Northern latitudes 21-22º</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Vitamin D has been involved in various diseases, including cancer. Several studies have linked vitamin D levels with breast cancer. The aim of our study was to establish the importance of adequate vitamin D concentrations to prevent breast cancer. Materials and methods: The study included 76 patients. Dietary habits, sun exposure, body mass index (BMI), and skin type were evaluated. Vitamin D determination in serum was measured by liquid chromatography. Vitamin D receptor pleomorphism was analyzed by immunohistochemistry. Results: Vitamin D ingestion was deficient in 18 patients and 22 controls; and sufficient in 6 patients and 30 controls, odds ratio of 4.09, confidence interval 95% 1.04-11.0, (p=0.016). Sun exposure was present in 9 patients and 15 controls; 15 patients and 37 controls had less sun exposure or used protection. Two patients and 13 controls had normal levels of vitamin D (30-60), two patients and 26 controls had low levels (20-30), and 18 patients and 12 controls had very low levels (&lt;20). Odds ratio for patients with vitamin D serum levels of 20 ng/mL or less, or higher was 9, CI 95% 2.95-27.5, (p&lt;0.001). These levels were independent from BMI. Conclusion: Low concentrations of vitamin D are strongly related to breast cancer in a region with high solar exposure. More studies are needed to confirm this relationship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sotelo-Félix, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fisher, RF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rolon Padilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Riestra, HJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Jaime, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buz, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ordorica, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La vitamina D ha sido implicada en diversas patologías, entre las que se encuentra el cáncer. Diversos estudios han relacionado los niveles de vitamina D con el cáncer de mama. El objetivo de este estudio fue establecer la importancia de concentraciones adecuadas de vitamina D en la prevención del cáncer de mama. Materiales y métodos: Estudio transversal de casos/controles que incluyó a 76 mujeres: 24 eran pacientes con cáncer de mama (grupo de casos), mientras que 52 mujeres sin cáncer de mama fueron asignadas al grupo control. En todas ellas se evaluaron los hábitos alimenticios, la exposición solar, el índice de masa corporal (IMC) y el tipo de piel. Se midió la vitamina D mediante cromatografía de líquidos. Se analizó el pleomorfismo del receptor de vitamina D mediante inmunohistoquímica.  Resultados: La ingesta de vitamina D fue deficiente en 18 pacientes y 22 controles, y suficiente en 6 pacientes y 30 controles ( odds ratio=4,09, intervalo de confianza (IC) 95%: 1,04-11,0; p=0,016). La exposición solar estuvo presente en 9 pacientes y 15 controles; 15 pacientes y 37 controles estuvieron menos expuestas a la radiación solar y usaban protección. Dos pacientes y 13 controles tuvieron niveles normales de vitamina D (30-60 ng/mL); dos pacientes y 26 controles tuvieron niveles bajos (20-30 ng/mL); y 18 pacientes y 12 controles tuvieron niveles muy bajos (&lt;20 ng/mL). La  odds ratio entre las pacientes con niveles séricos de vitamina D &amp;#8804;20 ng/mL o mayores fue 9, IC 95%: 2,95-27,5, (p&lt;0,001). Estos niveles fueron independientes del IMC. Conclusión: Existe una estrecha relación entre bajas concentraciones de vitamina D y desarrollo de cáncer de mama en una región con alta exposición solar. Se requieren otros estudios para confirmar esta observación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. osteoporos. metab. miner. (Internet);8(4): 127-133, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159382</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de niveles bajos de vitamina D en pacientes con cáncer de mama que viven en latitudes 21&#150;22º Norte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53375^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
