<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048222</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical use of enteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Enteral Nutrition is among the most developed disciplines in modern Medicine. Technological advances, a better knowledge of malnutrition physiopathology and its involvement in the evolution of several clinical entities have made it possible to improve the nutritional attention paid to our patients. The use of EN has expanded as a first choice practice in patients with undernutrition or at risk of undernutrition that have a minimally functional intestine and are unable to cover their total calorie and protein requirements with natural or supplemented diets. Terms like "medical food" or "organ- or system-specific nutrition" or "pathology-specific nutrition" have revolutionized the EN field in the last 20 years with the emergence of specifically defined formulations. EN has been shown to be cost-effective in patients with malnutrition when the indication is established early. Home and Ambulatory Artificial Nutrition techniques are administratively regulated and, as they are widespread in our country, they allow some cost reductions in certain processes. Occasionally, the introduction, use or withdrawal of EN may constitute a situation of ethical conflict that should be avoided by making use of respect, companionship and shared information between the health team, patients and their substitutes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Hernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez Torres, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Nutrición Enteral es una de las disciplinas más desarrolladas en la medicina moderna. Los avances tecnológicos, el mejor conocimiento de la fisiopatología de la desnutrición, y su participación en la evolución de diferentes entidades clínicas han hecho posible mejorar el cuidado nutricional de nuestros pacientes. La utilización de la NE se ha extendido como una práctica de primera elección en pacientes desnutridos o en riesgo de desnutrición que tienen un intestino minimamente funcionante y no son capaces de cubrir con la alimentación natural o suplementación, el total de sus requerimientos calórico-proteicos. Términos como "alimento-medicamento" o "nutrición órgano o sistema-específica o nutrición patología-específica" han revolucionado el campo de la NE en los últimos 20 años con la eclosión de fórmulas específicamente definidas .La NE ha demostrado ser coste-efectiva en los pacientes desnutridos cuando se establece la indicación con precocidad. La Nutrición Artificial Domiciliaria y Ambulatoria es una técnica regulada administrativamente muy extendida en nuestro país que permite reducir el coste de algunos procesos. En ocasiones la utilización o la retirada de la NE puede constituir una situación de conflicto ético que debe ser evitado desde el respeto, el acompañamiento y la información compartida entre el equipo sanitario, los pacientes y sus sustitutos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(supl.2): 87-99, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización clínica de la nutrición enteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
