<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130682</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Convergent validity of two tests of conscientiousness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The absence of correspondence between objective measurement of behavior and measurement based on self-report along with generalized use of questionnaires as personality assessment instruments raises a problem with regard to the validity of assessment instruments in this area of study. The goal of this work is to obtain a convergent validity measure for an objective assessment computerized task of conscientiousness based on the development of a functional equally but morphologically different task. The features of the designed assessment task are commented upon. The sample was made up of 267 university graduates (194 males and 73 females). The high convergent validity value obtained (r= .638, p&lt;.001) is a first step in the validation process of both tasks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández López, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Bleda, José Hector</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shih, Pei-Chun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santacreu Mas, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La falta de correspondencia entre la medición objetiva del comportamiento y la medición basada en el autoinforme del individuo, unida al uso generalizado del cuestionario como instrumento de evaluación de la personalidad, plantea un problema en relación a la validación de instrumentos de evaluación objetiva en dicho ámbito de estudio. El objetivo del siguiente trabajo es la obtención de una medida de validez convergente para una prueba informatizada de evaluación objetiva de la minuciosidad a partir del desarrollo de otra prueba funcionalmente equivalente y morfológicamente distinta. Se exponen las características de la prueba de evaluación diseñada. La muestra la conformaron 267 titulados universitarios (194 hombres y 73 mujeres). El alto valor de validez convergente obtenido (r= .638, p&lt;.001) supone un primer paso en el proceso de validación de ambas pruebas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(1): 133-140, ene.-mar. 2009. grab, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez convergente de dos pruebas de evaluación de la minuciosidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
