<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102085</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A scan electron microscope analysis of a separated filed. A clinical case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The introduction of nickel-titanium rotary files has been a major development in endodontics. One of the major concerns about its use is the chance of file separation. Cyclic fatigue and torsional failure have been identified as two possible types of failure. A scanning electron microscope analysis was performed on a recent case of file separation. The scan has shown characteristics of torsional failure mixed with cyclic fatigue patterns. The both failures characteristics are presented and the clinical reasons that may lead to that failure are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martins, J. N . R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saura, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La introducción de las limas rotatorias de niquel-titanio ha supuesto un gran avance en Endodoncia. Una de las mayores preocupaciones acerca de su uso es la posibilidad de separación de la lima. La fatiga cíclica y el fallo de torsión han sido identificados como dos posibles causas de este error. SE realizó un análisis mediante microscopía electrónica de barrido en un caso reciente de separación de una lima. El análisis muestra características del fallo por torsión y de fatiga clínica. En este artículo se van a describir los dos tipos de fallos así como las razones clínicas que pueden llevar a estas situaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);29(3): 131-136, jul.-sept. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis mediante microscopía electrónica de barrido de una lima separada. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5683</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23316^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
