<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131184</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Life satisfaction and related socio-demographic factors during female midlife</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To assess life satisfaction and related factors in middle-aged Spanish women. Method This was a cross-sectional study including 235 women aged 40 to 65, living in Granada (Spain), healthy companions of patients visiting the obstetrics and gynecology clinics. They completed the Diener Satisfaction with Life Scale, the Menopause Rating Scale, the Perceived Stress Scale, the Insomnia Severity Index and a sociodemographic questionnaire containing personal and partner data. Internal consistency of each tool was also calculated. Results Almost two-thirds (61.3%) of the women were postmenopausal, and 43.8% had abdominal obesity, 36.6% had insomnia, 18.7% had poor menopause-related quality of life, 31.9% performed regular exercise, and 5.1% had severe financial problems. Life satisfaction showed significant positive correlations (Spearman's test) with female and male age, and inverse correlations with menopause-related quality of life, perceived stress and insomnia. In the multiple linear regression analysis, high life satisfaction is positively correlated with having a partner who performed exercise, and inversely with having work problems, perceived stress and the suspicion of partner infidelity. These factors explained 40% of the variance of the multiple regression analysis for life satisfaction in middle-aged women. Conclusion Life satisfaction is a construct related to perceived stress, work problems, and having a partner, while aspects of menopause and general health had no significant influence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Alonso, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadros, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Roncero, Gonzalo R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Baena, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadros-Celorrio, Ángela M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo El presente estudio investiga el grado de satisfacción vital en mujeres de mediana edad. Método Estudio observacional transversal de 235 mujeres de edad comprendida entre 40 y 65 años, domiciliadas en Granada, acompañantes sanas de pacientes asistentes a las consultas de obstetricia y ginecología, que cumplimentaron la Escala de Satisfacción Vital de Diener, la Escala de Puntuación de la Menopausia, la Escala de Estrés Percibido, el Índice de Severidad de Insomnio y un cuestionario sociodemográfico incluyendo datos personales y de la pareja. También se calculó la consistencia interna de cada instrumento. Resultados El 61,3% de las mujeres eran postmenopáusicas, el 43,8% tenían obesidad abdominal, el 36,6% sufría insomnio, el 18,7% tenía mala calidad de vida relacionada con la menopausia, el 31,9% hacia ejercicio con regularidad, y el 5,1% tenía problemas económicos graves. La satisfacción vital tuvo correlaciones (prueba de Spearman) positivas significativas con la edad femenina y la masculina, y negativas significativas con la calidad de vida relacionada con la menopausia, el estrés percibido y el insomnio. En el análisis de regresión lineal múltiple, la alta satisfacción vital se correlacionó positivamente con tener una pareja que hiciese ejercicio, e inversamente con tener problemas laborales, el grado de estrés percibido y la sospecha de infidelidad de la pareja. Estos factores explican el 40% de la varianza en el análisis de regresión múltiple para la satisfacción vital en mujeres de mediana edad. Conclusión La satisfacción vital es un constructo relacionado con el estrés percibido, los problemas laborales y tener pareja, mientras que los aspectos relacionados con la menopausia y la salud general no tuvieron influencia significativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(6): 315-322, nov.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Satisfacción vital y factores sociodemográficos en mujeres de mediana edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22129^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33368^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
