<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131601</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of the Modified Tonic Immobility Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Tonic Immobility Scale has been only studied in abuse and/or sexual assault survivors, but tonic immobility (TI) also occurs after other types of traumatic events. Consequently, we modified the scale for this purpose and studied its factor structure, internal consistency, and convergent, divergent and discriminant validity in 392 university students, most of whom had suffered one or more traumatic events of various kinds. The Fear subscale of the Modified Tonic Immobility Scale (MTIS)showed very low internal consistency, and must be eliminated or reformulated. Discrimination indices of items 5 and 8 were very low, and these items must be reformulated or removed. After removing the five previous items, the shortened version of the MTIS had a one-factor structure, although model fit was not completely satisfactory. This scale showed acceptable levels of reliability, convergent validity with post-traumatic symptomatology, divergent validity with measures of depression and anxiety, and discriminant validity differentiating between groups that had and had not experienced traumatic events. The psychometric properties of the shortened version of the MTIS should be studied further. It may also be advisable to add new items of TI in order to establish whether this is a construct with more than one dimensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peró, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bados, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Escala de Inmovilidad Tónica ha sido estudiada sólo en víctimas de abusos y/o agresiones sexuales, pero la inmovilidad tónica (IT) puede darse ante otros eventos traumáticos. En consecuencia, nos propusimos modificar la escala con este fin y estudiar su estructura factorial y otras propiedades psicométricas (consistencia interna y validez convergente, divergente y discriminante) en 392 universitarios, la mayoría de los cuales había padecido uno o más eventos traumáticos de distintos tipos. La subescala de miedo de la Escala Modificada de Inmovilidad Tónica (EMIT) mostró una consistencia interna muy baja y debe ser eliminada o reformulada. Los índices de discriminación de los ítems 5 y 8 fueron muy bajos y dichos ítems deben ser reformulados o eliminados. Después de eliminar los cinco ítems anteriores, la versión abreviada de la EMIT tuvo una estructura unifactorial, aunque el ajuste del modelo no fue totalmente satisfactorio. Esta escala mostró niveles aceptables de fiabilidad, validez convergente con sintomatología postraumática, validez divergente con medidas de depresión y ansiedad, y validez discriminante al diferenciar entre grupos que habían experimentado o no eventos traumáticos. Las propiedades psicométricas de la versión abreviada de la EMIT deben ser más estudiadas. Puede ser aconsejable añadir nuevos ítems de IT para determinar si este es un constructo con más de una dimensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(1): 66-73, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas de la Escala Modificada de Inmovilidad Tónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
