<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100427</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eligibility of schizophrenia inpatients to participate in clinical trials</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: This study assesses the potential eligibility of patients admitted to a psychiatric hospitalisation unit to take part in the major clinical trials based on schizophrenia treatment in clinical practice (CATIE, CUtLASS and EUFEST).Material and methods: A retrospective evaluation by consulting the medical records of 241 subjects (59.8% males and 40.2% females, mean age 39.7±13.0 years), admitted consecutively over one year to psychiatric hospitalisation unit with a diagnosis of schizophrenia or another psychosis. The influence of the factors involved in the non-eligibility in each of the clinical trials is analysed using logistic regression analysis.Results: Only 20.7%, 22.3%, and 22.5% of patients with schizophrenia or another psychosis would be eligible to participate in the CATIE, CUtLASS and EUFEST studies, respectively. The main factors involved in the non-eligibility were polytherapy with anti-psychotics (2 or more) (Odds Ratio (OR): 7.64, 95% confidence interval (CI): 3.06-19.06, P&lt;.001), mental retardation (OR: 16.67, 95% CI: 1.75-166.67, P=.014), and resistance, intolerance or contraindication to any of the anti-psychotics of the study (OR: 3.68, 95% CI: 1.13-11.99, P=.030).Conclusions: Three out of every four patients with schizophrenia or another psychosis admitted to a psychiatric hospitalisation unit are not represented in the major clinical trials on schizophrenia treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iniesta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domato, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tolosa, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraguas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portela, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Rodenas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayordomo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Este estudio pretende evaluar la potencial elegibilidad para la participación en los principales ensayos clínicos de tratamiento de esquizofrenia basados en la práctica clínica (CATIE, CUtLASS y EUFEST) de los pacientes ingresados en una unidad de hospitalización de psiquiatría.Material y métodos: Evaluación retrospectiva, mediante consulta de la historia clínica, de los 241 sujetos (59,8% varones y 40,2% mujeres, edad 39,7±13,0 años), ingresados de forma consecutiva a lo largo de un año en una unidad de hospitalización de psiquiatría con diagnóstico de esquizofrenia u otra psicosis. La influencia de los factores implicados en la no elegibilidad en cada uno de los ensayos clínicos se analizó mediante análisis de regresión logística.Resultados: Un 20,7, un 22,3, y un 22,5% de los pacientes con esquizofrenia u otra psicosis serían elegibles para participar en los estudios CATIE, CUtLASS y EUFEST, respectivamente. Los principales factores implicados en la no elegibilidad fueron la politerapia con antipsicóticos (2 o más) (Odds Ratio (OR): 7,64, intervalo de confianza (IC) 95%: 3,06-19,06, p&lt;0,001), el retraso mental (OR: 16,67, IC 95%: 1,75-166,67, p=0,014) y la resistencia, intolerancia o contraindicación a alguno de los antipsicóticos del estudio (OR: 3,68, IC 95%: 1,13-11,99, p=0,030).Conclusiones: Tres de cada cuatro pacientes con esquizofrenia u otra psicosis ingresados en una unidad de hospitalización de psiquiatría no están representados en los grandes ensayos clínicos de tratamiento de esquizofrenia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);5(2): 71-80, abr.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elegibilidad de pacientes con esquizofrenia ingresados en una unidad de hospitalización psiquiátrica para participar en ensayos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4681^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
