<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59756</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Embolotherapy of pulmonary arteriovenous malformations: long-term clinical and radiological follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary arteriovenous malformations (PAVM) are abnormal communications between the pulmonary arteries and pulmonary veins. The large majority are congenital and are commonly associated with Rendu-Osler-Weber disease or hereditary haemorrhagic telangiectasia. The PAVM may remain asymptomatic or manifest with hypoxemia, hemoptysis, hemothorax and/or neurologic symptoms. Despite its low incidence, the PAVM represent a serious entity that must be taken into account since untreated patients are in risk and present a poor prognosis. Transcatheter embolization with coils or detachable balloons is currently accepted as the treatment of choice. We present 6 patiens (5 women and one man) who underwent embolotherapy of PAVM showing the long-term clinical and radiological follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Revillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Aguilera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurera-Tendero, L. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triviño-Tarradas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canis-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las malformaciones arteriovenosas pulmonares (MAVP) son comunicaciones directas entre arterias y venas pulmonares sin lecho capilar normal entre ellos. La mayoría son congénitas y se asocian al síndrome de Rendu-Osler-Weber o telangiectasia hemorrágica hereditaria. Clínicamente pueden ser silentes o cursar con hipoxemia, hemoptisis, hemotórax y/o síntomas neurológicos por un mecanismo de embolia paradójica. A pesar de su baja incidencia, presentan un gran interés por el riesgo que suponen para el paciente no tratado. La terapia de elección en la actualidad es el tratamiento endovascular mediante embolización con coils o balones largables. Se presentan 6 pacientes (5 mujeres y un varón) con MAVP tratados en nuestro centro mediante embolización con coils y se muestra el seguimiento clinicorradiológico a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(1): 85-89, ene. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolización de malformaciones arteriovenosas pulmonares: seguimiento clinicorradiológico a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2586^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
