<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143970</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of isometric force in lower limbs and body composition in preterm infants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Strength is a physical quality with a clear influence on quality of life. It is determined by the structure of the musculoskeletal system, and depends on the muscular structure. It has been described that prematurity conditions both qualities. The aims of this study are to determine whether prematurity is associated with strength or body composition and evaluate the relationship between prematurity, strength and muscle mass. Material and methods: Case-control study. Participants were premature 7-to-11 year-old children and full-term birth controls. Strength was measured by a strength gauge and body composition from DEXA (duel-energy X-ray absorptiometry) scans. A total of 89 subjects were included and divided into three groups: 30 prematures with birth-weight &amp;#8804; 1500g, 29 prematures with birth-weight 1500-2000g, and 30 controls. Results:  Weight and BMI z-score was lower in the premature group. No differences were found in muscular mass or strength between groups. A ratio was established between strength and weight or muscular mass. It was observed that it was possible for them to move four times their weight, without finding any differences between groups or a relationship with birth-weight. Conclusions: Between 7 and 11 years of age, children who were premature have lower weight and BMI than the rest of the children. However, there were no differences in body composition or strength between preterm children and controls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz Fernández, JA de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboleda Franco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Patiño, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata Zubillaga, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fuerza es una cualidad con clara influencia sobre la calidad de vida. Está condicionada por la estructura del aparato locomotor y es directamente dependiente de la estructura muscular. Se ha descrito que ambas cualidades están condicionadas por la prematuridad. Son objetivos del estudio conocer si la prematuridad está relacionada con la fuerza o la composición corporal durante la infancia y valorar la relación entre prematuridad, fuerza y masa muscular. Material y métodos: Estudio de casos y controles realizado en niños de entre 7 y 11 años con desarrollo normal y controles a término de la misma edad. Se incluyó a 89 sujetos: 30 prematuros con peso al nacimiento &amp;#8804; 1.500g, 29 prematuros con peso al nacimiento &gt; 1.500g y 30 controles. Se analizaron antropometría, composición corporal mediante absorciometría de rayos X de energía dual y fuerza isométrica mediante banco inclinado y galga. Resultados: El peso y el IMC fueron menores en los niños que pesaron &amp;#8804; 1.500g. No se observaron diferencias en composición corporal ni fuerza. Se estableció una razón entre fuerza y masa muscular, resultando esta de un peso desplazado 4 veces superior al peso corporal, no encontrándose diferencias entre grupos ni relación con el peso al nacimiento. Conclusiones: Entre los 7 y los 11 años de edad, los niños que fueron grandes prematuros tienen un peso y un IMC menores al resto de los niños. No se encontraron diferencias entre prematuros y controles en cuanto a composición corporal y fuerza muscular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);83(4): 229-235, oct. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de fuerza isométrica en extremidades inferiores y composición corporal en prematuros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9309^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38640^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
