<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100532</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Administração de medicamentos: conhecimento de enfermeiros do setor de urgência e emergencia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Administration of medicines is an ally in the health recovery process, especially in the emergency and casualty sector. Since the nurse is the person with most responsibility in this practice and considering that any failing in this activity could have irreversible consequences for the patient, the study seeks to describe the knowledge of the nurses about this issue and to verify aspects of their training in a search for continuous updating and education in the health service. The study is descriptive and exploratory and of a quantitative approach. It was carried out in casualty and emergency units of the Distrito Sanitario Leste de Goiânia, Goiás. 37 nurses participated in the study, answering a self-administered questionnaire. A statistical and descriptive analysis was carried out, taking a confidence interval of 95% and factors with significance p &lt; 0,05. The study shows the training of nurses in terms of medicine administration in casualty and emergency units and highlights gaps that need to be remedied by ongoing training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues Silva Soares, CS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares Martins, IM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tanferri de Brito Paranaguá, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queiroz Bezerra, AL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomes Fazendeiro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado de Azevedo Filho, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intervención medicamentosa es una aliada en el proceso de recuperación de la salud, principalmente en el sector de urgencia y emergencia. Al ser el enfermero el principal responsable de esa práctica y considerando que cualquier fallo durante esta actividad puede tener consecuencias irreversibles para el paciente, el estudio objetiva describir el conocimiento de los enfermeros acerca de esta temática y verificar los aspectos de la formación, en busca de actualización y educación continuada en el servicio de salud. Estudio descriptivo, exploratorio, de abordaje cuantitativo, realizado en unidades de urgencia y emergencia del Distrito Sanitario Leste de Goiânia, Goiás. Participaron del estudio 37 enfermeros que respondieron a un cuestionario auto-aplicable. Se realizó análisis estadístico y descriptivo, considerando intervalo de 95% de confianza y factores con p &lt; 0,05 significantes. En el estudio, se constata la preparación de los enfermeros en cuanto a la administración de medicamentos en urgencia y emergencia y apunta lagunas que deben ser subsanadas por medio de la educación continuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 54-69, abr. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Administración de medicamentos: conocimiento de los enfermeros del sector de urgencia y emergencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30140^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
