<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164491</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elaboration and validation of the «Attitudes questionnaire towards professional ethics in Physiotherapy»</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: In the university context the creation and validation of questionnaires to be applied in assessment of new teaching models that guarantee the acquisition of ethical competence is necessary. This study aims at presenting the creation, assessment of internal consistence and unidimensionality of the &#145;Attitudes questionnaire towards professional ethics in Physiotherapy&#146; (CAEPFIS). Material and method: A questionnaire analyzing attitudes towards professional ethics in Physiotherapy students (CAEPFIS) was created by means of a study carried out with physiotherapy students in the last year of their degree (n=100). An analysis of internal consistency (Cronbach's Alpha) was carried out, whilst differentiator elements were detected and deleted. Afterwards, unidimensionality of the questionnaire was analyzed (factorial analysis of principal components, Barlett's test of sphericity and Kaiser-Meyer-OIkin KMO). Finally, the questionnaire comprised 33 items. Predictive Analytics Software (PASW) 18.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used. Results: CAEPFIS shows a high internal consistency (Cronbach's Alfa=0.898). Items of CAEPFIS are close to the desired unidimensionality (Factorial Analysis of Principal Components: KMO=0.762; &amp;#967;2=1,871.874; df=528; p&lt;0.001). The first factor shows a good proportion of total variance, explains the 25.8% of it and all items present weights higher than 0.3. Conclusions: CAEPFIS shows internal consistency and unidimensionality to be used as a tool of data collection to analyze attitudes towards professional ethics in physiotherapy students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sempere Rubio, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Añó, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas Moscardó, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués Sulé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En el contexto universitario resulta necesaria la elaboración y validación de cuestionarios para ser aplicados en la valoración de nuevos modelos formativos que garanticen la adquisición de la competencia ética. El objetivo de este estudio es presentar la elaboración, evaluación de la fiabilidad y unidimensionalidad del «Cuestionario de actitudes hacia la ética profesional en Fisioterapia» (CAEPFIS). Material y método: Se procedió a la elaboración de un cuestionario que analizara las actitudes hacia la ética profesional en estudiantes de Fisioterapia (CAEPFIS) mediante un estudio piloto con estudiantes de Fisioterapia de último curso (n=100). Se llevó a cabo un análisis de consistencia interna (alfa de Cronbach) y se detectaron y eliminaron los ítems indiferenciadores. Posteriormente, se analizó la unidimensionalidad del cuestionario (análisis factorial de componentes principales, prueba de esfericidad de Barlett y medida de adecuación muestral de Kaiser-Meyer-OIkin [KMO]). Finalmente, el cuestionario constó de 33 ítems. Se empleó Predictive Analytics Software (PASW) 18.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, EE. UU.). Resultados: El CAEPFIS presenta una elevada consistencia interna (coeficiente alfa de Cronbach=0,898). Los ítems del CAEPFIS se acercan a la unidimensionalidad deseada (análisis factorial de componentes principales: KMO=0,762; &amp;#967;2=1.871,874; df=528; p&lt;0,001). El primer factor muestra una buena proporción de la varianza total, explica el 25,8% de la misma y todos los ítems presentan pesos por encima de 0,3. Conclusiones: El CAEPFIS muestra fiabilidad y unidimensionalidad para ser empleado como instrumento de recogida de datos para analizar las actitudes hacia la ética profesional en estudiantes de Fisioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(4): 148-157, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración y validación del «Cuestionario de actitudes hacia la ética profesional en Fisioterapia»</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
