<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047857</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Models of public financing of rest homes. A comparative analysis of autonomous regions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: this study presents a comparative analysis of models of public financing of rest homes based on the current regulations in the distinct Autonomous Regions in Spain. Material and methods: the regulations for rest homes of the various Autonomous Regions were compiled and analysed. To do this, an exhaustive search of databases was performed and a survey was designed. The principal focus of this survey was on the specific legislation relating to the elderly, general data about rest homes, and regulations and quantifiable data about their financing. Information was also obtained from existing publications on this subject. Results: the study shows that the intense efforts of the Autonomous Regions on social policies for the elderly and care of the elderly in the last decade have consolidated a model for the public financing of rest homes. This model focuses on 3 areas: investments, the running of rest homes and financial aid for the residents, and criteria that entitle residents to receive financial aid. It also shows the wide variety of proposals and procedures incorporated in the regulations of the Autonomous Regions, giving shape to a series of public financing models with distinct organization and procedures to access services and benefits for the elderly. Discussion: the results indicate that residents and their families are the principal source of finance for rest homes. Public financing models have focused on guaranteeing the rights of the elderly (especially the rights of those in need of care) to be cared for in rest homes, and on fulfilling the social responsibility of public administrations. All of this is related to prolix regulations on financing the running of rest homes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anaut Bravo, Sagrario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oslé Guerendiáin, Camino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: se presenta un estudio comparativo de los modelos de financiación pública de las residencias para personas mayores a partir de la normativa autonómica vigente. Material y método: se ha procedido a recoger y analizar toda la normativa vigente en las diferentes comunidades autónomas (CCAA) acerca de residencias para personas mayores. Para ello se ha realizado una búsqueda exhaustiva en diversos servidores y se ha confeccionado un cuestionario. Los ejes temáticos del mismo eran: legislación específica referida a personas mayores, datos generales acerca de las residencias y normativa y datos cuantitativos acerca de su financiación. A ello se suma la aportación obtenida de la bibliografía existente. Resultados: se constata que la intensa labor legislativa de las CCAA en la última década en materia de políticas sociales para personas mayores y dependencia ha consolidado un modelo-base de financiación pública de las residencias. Este modelo se ha centrado en 3 áreas: inversiones, funcionamiento y ayuda directa a los usuarios, y en una tipología de beneficiario que se ajusta a ellas. Igualmente, se ha puesto de manifiesto la diversidad de propuestas y actuaciones que incorpora la normativa autonómica, dando forma a una serie de modelos autonómicos de financiación pública que introducen diferencias organizativas y de acceso a los servicios y prestaciones por parte de las personas mayores. Discusión: los resultados apuntan a que el usuario o su familia son la principal fuente de financiación de las residencias. Los modelos autonómicos de financiación pública se han centrado en garantizar el derecho de los mayores, sobre todo dependientes, a ser atendidos en las residencias y en completar la función social que corresponde a las administraciones públicas. Obviamente, ello está en relación con una prolija normativa sobre financiación para el funcionamiento de las residencias</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);41(4): 212-221, jul. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos de financiación pública de las residencias para personas mayores. Análisis comparativo por comunidades autónomas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30585^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
