<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046671</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analytical results int he population with diabetes of area 3 of Madrid: an analysis of quality of care in according the DRG</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We conducted a retrospective study to evaluate the adequacy        of glycemic, lipid and albumin excretion (EAU) management in        reference to target goals for diabetic patients in the area 3 of the        community of Madrid during 2002, this data were analysed according        the Diagnosis Related Group (DRG): 294, DM &gt;= 36 years and        295, DM = 36 years which reflect        an age-adjusted prevalence of 0,25% and 3,1% respectively. The        percentages of patients with &gt;= 2 determinations of HbA1c were        61% and 25%, complete lipid profile 66% and 60%, EAU in 72%        and 46% in DM = 36 years old respectively. 29% and        37% of patients achieved HbA1c = 36 respectively. In conclusion, analysis of the blood test in        diabetic patients is useful to evaluate the quality of care for this        population. In our health area some indicators of intermediate outcomes        and process of care outcomes were inadequate, and we        found differences in the patients followed by primary care physicians        and endocrinologists. It is necessary to increase to the efforts        and resources of public health to improve these results, contributing        to reduction of the chronic complications of this disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Manzanares, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo para evaluar los parámetros        de control glucémico, lipídico y excreción de albuminuria (EAU) así        como el grado de objetivo de control conseguido en pacientes con        diabetes del área 3 de la Comunidad de Madrid durante el año 2002,        analizando los datos atendiendo al Grupo Relacionado con el Diagnóstico        (GRD): 294, DM &gt;= 36 años y 295, DM = 36 años, con una prevalencia ajustada a la edad del 0,25%        and 3,1%, respectivamente. El porcentaje de pacientes con &gt;= 2 determinaciones        de HbA1c fue de 61 y 25%, realización de perfil lipídico        completo 66 y 60%, EAU 72 y 46% de los pacientes con DM = 36 años respectivamente. 29% y 37% de los pacientes tenían        HbA1c = 36 años respectivamente. En        conclusión, el análisis de las peticiones analíticas en pacientes con        diabetes es útil para evaluar la calidad asistencial en esta población.        En nuestra área de salud algunos indicadores de resultado intermedio        y de proceso son inadecuados, habiendo encontrado diferencias        en los pacientes seguidos por médicos de Atención Primaria y endocrinólogos.        Se precisa aumentar los esfuerzos y recursos de salud        pública para mejorar estos resultados y de este modo contribuir a la        reducción de las complicaciones crónicas de esta enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(4): 323-330, oct.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados analíticos en la población con diabetes del área 3 de Madrid: un análisis de calidad asistencial atendiendo al GRD</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d422^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
