<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114749</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug treatment adjustment to the clinical guidelines in octagenarians with acute myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine whether there is a linear association of age and aspirin, beta-blockers, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and statins; the extent to which elderly patients receive these treatments; and whether age is independently associated with these treatments. Design: A prospective cohort study. Setting: Coronary Unit of two hospitals in the Region of Murcia (Spain).Patients: Consecutive patients admitted with the diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction between January 1998 and January 2008.Interventions: None. Main outcomes: Those related to the administration of aspirin, beta-blockers, angiotens nconverting enzyme inhibitors and statins during stay in the Coronary Care Unit. Results: Regarding the remaining patients, octogenarians received a similar proportion of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (70.8% vs. 69.3%, p=0.41) and less often aspirin (90.4%vs. 94.6%, p&lt;0.001), beta-blockers (44.4% vs. 69.4%, p&lt;0,001) and statins (47.6% vs. 64.7%,p&lt;0.001). We were only able to demonstrate an abrupt and significant decrease in the use of statins after 80 years of age. Patient age was independently associated with the use of beta blockers (OR 0.59; 95%CI 0.47 - 0.73) and statins (OR 0.78; 95%CI 0.65 - 0.95). The lesser administration of these drugs was also associated with early mortality (OR 0.17, 95%CI 0.09 to0.33 and OR 0.14; 95%CI 0.08 to 0.23, respectively).Conclusions: Octogenarians less often receive aspirin, beta-blockers and statins, though old age was not an independent factor associated with lesser aspirin use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Fernández, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey-Carrión, M. D. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla-Serrano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea-García, J.H. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu-Soler, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galcerá-Tomás, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melgarejo-Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Pastor, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenías-Burillo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si existe una asociación lineal de la edad y la administración de aspirina ,betabloque antes, inhibidores de la enzima convertidora de la angiotensina y estatinas, en qué medida los pacientes de edad avanzada reciben estos tratamientos y si la edad se asocia de forma independiente a estos tratamientos. Diseño: Estudio de cohortes prospectivo. Ámbito: Unidades Coronarias de 2 hospitales de la Región de Murcia Pacientes: Pacientes consecutivos ingresados con el diagnóstico de infarto agudo de miocardio entre enero de 1998 y enero de 2008.Intervenciones: Ninguna. Variables principales: Las relacionadas con la administración de aspirina, betabloqueantes, inhibidores de la enzima convertidora de la angiotensina y estatinas durante la estancia en la Unidad Coronaria. Resultados: Respecto al resto de pacientes, los octogenarios recibieron en similar proporción inhibidores de la enzima convertidora de la angiotensina (70,8 vs 69,3%, p=0,41) y con menor frecuencia aspirina (90,4 vs 94,6%, p&lt;0,001), betabloqueantes (44,4 vs 69,4%, p&lt;0,001) y estatinas(47,6 vs 64,7%, p&lt;0,001). Solo pudo demostrarse una disminución brusca y significativa en la administración de estatinas a partir de los 80 años. La edad se asoció independientemente con la administración de betabloqueantes (OR 0,59; IC95% 0,47 - 0,73) y estatinas (OR 0,78;IC95% 0,65 - 0,95). La menor administración de estos fármacos también se asoció a una mayor (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(4): 248-258, mayo 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ajuste del tratamiento farmacológico a las guías de práctica clínica en pacientes octogenarios con infarto agudo de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
