<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053305</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maternal and paternal parenting styles: assessment and relationship with adolescent adjustment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study presents the validation of a scale that was elaborated to assess maternal and paternal parenting styles according to the perception of their adolescent children. The scale was applied to a sample composed by 848 adolescents aged from 12 to 17 years old, that also filled out the Youth Self Report, a life satisfaction scale and a substance use questionnaire. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses revealed a six factors structure for maternal and also for paternal parenting style. These dimensions showed significant relationships with most of the measures of adolescent adjustment considered in the study. Comparisons between boys&#146; and girls&#146; perceptions of paternal and maternal parenting styles revealed that, in spite of the high agreement between both styles, mothers were scored higher than fathers in every dimension of parenting style</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliva Delgado, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Jiménez, Águeda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Queija, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gaviño, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se presenta la validación de una escala elaborada para evaluar los estilos educativos parentales de madres y padres según la percepción de sus hijos adolescentes. El instrumento se aplicó a una muestra de 848 adolescentes de edades comprendidas entre los 12 y los 17 años, quienes también cumplimentaron el Youth Self Report, una escala de satisfacción vital y otra de consumo de sustancias. La realización de análisis factoriales exploratorios y confirmatorios reveló una estructura factorial de 6 dimensiones tanto en el estilo materno como en el paterno. Estas dimensiones mostraron una relación muy significativa con la mayoría de medidas de ajuste adolescente consideradas. La comparación de las percepciones que chicos y chicas tenían del estilo materno y del paterno reveló que, a pesar de la gran concordancia percibida entre ambos estilos, unos y otras concedieron puntuaciones más altas a sus madres en cada una de las dimensiones del estilo educativo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;23(1): 49-56, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos educativos materno y paterno: evaluación y relación con el ajuste adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
