<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84775</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The University of A Coruña, through the Podiatry and Nursing University, carried out for the Xunta de Galicia and the Spanish Work Ministry and Social Services, a podiatry project named &#147;Itinerant Podiatry Program to assist elderly people with dependency during the year 2005&#148;. Its main goal was to give podiatry care to people older than 65 who usually went to social centers that were managed by the Vice-presidency of Equality and Social Welfare. The total sample comprised 815 participants, selected by the Vice-Presidency of Equality and Social Welfare and the responsible of each one of the 16 centers. The aim was to identify the priorities of podiatry care in elderly people, by establishing a relationship between the socio-demographic characteristics and the podiatry pathologies. The majority of the participants were women (72.2%), aged 40 to 98 years, with a mean age of 74, received a contributory pension (91.4%) living with someone (79.3%) and had an elementary level of studies (74.5%). The most common podiatry pathologies were keratopathy (73.6%) hyperkeratosis (53.4%), callus (52%). Onycopathy (49.8%), onychogryphosis (22%), onychomycosis (18%), onichocriptosis (15%), (3, 7%) or other nail diseases (2,8%). According to the study, women are more prone to suffer keratopathy [OR 2.33; IC 95% (1.67-3.26)], hyperkeratosis (OR 1.96; IC 95% [1.43-2.67]) and callus [OR 2.44; IC 95% (1.776-3.352)]. Living with someone, diminishes the probability of suffering keratopathy (OR 0.50 [0.322-0.777]), primarily callus (OR 0.68 IC 95% [0.488-0.966]). Elderly people with higher level of studies have smaller probability of suffering nail diseases (p=0.032) (OR 0.50; IC 95% [(0.29-0.86]). Meanwhile, pensioners are more likely to have hyperkeratosis (p=0.011) (OR of 1.10 IC 95% [1.01-1.04](AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Fernández, Abián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manuel Romero Soto, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santalla Borreiros, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Manso, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Martín, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Cotelo, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Universidad de A Coruña a través de la Escuela Universitaria de Enfermería y Podología realizó para la Xunta de Galicia y el Ministerio de Trabajo y Asuntos Sociales, un proyecto de intervención podológica denominado &#147;Programa de Podología Itinerante para la atención a las personas mayores con dependencias 2005&#148;, cuyo objetivo principal era prestar atención podológica a las personas mayores de 65 años que acuden a los centros sociales gestionados por la Vicepresidencia de Igualdad y Bienestar de la Xunta de Galicia. En este programa se realiza un estudio sobre una muestra de 815 personas seleccionadas por la Vicepresidencia de Igualdad y Bienestar y los responsables de cada uno de los 16 centros, para identificar las prioridades de atención podológica en ancianos, estableciendo una correlación entre sus características socio-demográficas y la aparición de patologías quiropodológicas. La mayoría de la población de estudio eran mujeres (72,2%), con una media de edad de 74 años con un rango de edad de 40 a 98 años, con pensión contributiva (91,4%), que vivían acompañadas (79,3%), y con un nivel de estudios básico (74,5%). Las patologías podológicas más frecuentes han sido las queratopatías (73,6%) hiperqueratosis (53,4%) y helomas (52%). Onicopatías (49,8%), onicogrifosis (22%), onicomicosis (18%), onicocriptosis (15%), hematomas subungueales (3,7%) otro tipo de onicopatías (2,8%). Según los datos del estudio, el sexo femenino es más proclive a padecer queratopatías [OR 2,33; IC 95% (1,67-3,26)], hiperqueratosis [OR 1,96; IC 95% (1,43- 2,67)] y helomas (OR 2,44; IC 95% [1,776-3,352]) en particular. Que las personas mayores no vivan solas disminuye la probabilidad de padecer queratopatías [OR 0,50-0,77]), en concreto helomas [OR 0,68 IC 95% [0,48-0,966]. Los ancianos con mayor nivel de estudios tienen menor probabilidad de padecer onicopatías (p=0,032) (OR 0,50; IC 95% [(0,29-0,86]). Mientras que los pensionistas son más proclives a padecer hiperqueratosis (p=0,011) (OR de 1,10 IC 95% [1,01-1,04])(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;30(4): 176-183, oct.-dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología de los pies y características sociodemográficas de la población usuaria de los centros Sociales de mayores de Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9453^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5670^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33811^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5670^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
