<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167182</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preservatives in Personal Hygiene and Cosmetic Products, Topical Medications, and Household Cleaners in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Preservatives are added to cosmetic, household cleaning, and other industrial products to prevent the growth of microorganisms. Unfortunately, exposure to these substances can cause sensitization. Material and methods: Between January and June 2015, we analyzed the ingredients of 2300 products commercially available in Spain to identify the frequency of a wide variety of preservatives in different product categories. We analyzed 1093 skin care and cosmetic products sold exclusively in pharmacies (dermocosmetics), 458 household cleaning and personal hygiene and cosmetic products sold in supermarkets, 636 topical medications, and 113 cosmetic products sold in a herbal shop. Results: Phenoxyethanol, citric acid, sodium benzoate, and potassium sorbate were very common in all the cosmetic product categories. Parabens were present in 16.1% of dermocosmetic products, 14.45% of cosmetic products available in supermarkets, 0.88% of cosmetic products available in the herbal shop, 5.18% of topical medications, and in none of the cleaning products. Isothiazolinones were identified in 2.56% of dermocosmetic products, 18% of cosmetic products in supermarkets, 7.9% of cosmetic products in the herbal shop, 63.63% of household cleaners, and in none of the topical medications. Formaldehyde releasers were detected in 5.76% of dermocosmetic products, 6.42% of cosmetic products sold in supermarkets, 7.96% of cosmetic products sold in the herbal shop, 3.93% of topical medications, and 16.74% of household cleaners. Conclusions: Evaluation of the presence of preservatives in everyday products allows us to indirectly estimate exposure levels to each one. Measures restricting the use of the most problematic preservatives need to be strengthened (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eusebio-Murillo, Ester de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Mesonero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcántara-Nicolás, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Muñoz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Fuentes, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara-Sánchez, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melgar-Molero, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor-Nieto, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los conservantes se agregan a cosméticos, limpiadores domésticos y otros productos industriales para impedir el crecimiento de microorganismos. Desafortunadamente, pueden sensibilizar a usuarios expuestos. Material y métodos: Entre enero y junio de 2015 se analizaron las listas de los ingredientes de 2.300 productos de venta en España: 1.093 dermocosméticos, 458 productos de higiene, cosméticos y limpiadores domésticos de venta en supermercados, 636 medicamentos tópicos y 113 cosméticos de herbolario. Se evaluó la distribución de una amplia variedad de conservantes en las distintas categorías de productos. Resultados: Conservantes tales como el fenoxietanol, el ácido cítrico, el benzoato sódico y el sorbato potásico estuvieron ampliamente representados en todas las categorías de cosméticos. Se detectaron parabenos en el 16,1% de los dermocosméticos, el 14,45% de los cosméticos de supermercado, el 0,88% de los cosméticos de herbolario, el 5,18% de los medicamentos tópicos y ningún producto de limpieza. Se objetivaron isotiazolinonas en el 2,56% de los dermocosméticos, el 18% de los cosméticos de supermercado, el 7,9% de los cosméticos de herbolario, el 63,63% de los limpiadores domésticos y en ningún medicamento tópico. Contenían liberadores de formaldehído el 5,76% de los dermocosméticos, el 6,42% de los cosméticos de supermercado, el 7,96% de los cosméticos de herbolario, el 3,93% de los medicamentos tópicos y el 16,74% de los limpiadores. Conclusiones: La evaluación de la frecuencia de los conservantes en los productos de nuestro entorno permite una estimación indirecta del grado de exposición a cada uno de ellos. Se precisa impulsar medidas que conduzcan a una restricción en el uso de los conservantes más problemáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;108(8): 758-770, oct. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conservantes en productos de higiene y cosméticos, medicamentos tópicos y productos de limpieza doméstica en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51502</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10410^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5659^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
