<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155249</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Randomized clinical simulation trial of a Google Glass telemedicine application to assist orotracheal intubation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the effect of a Google Glass telemedicine application to allow a medical expert to make corrections in simulated out-of-hospital intratracheal intubations performed by nurses. Method. Randomized clinical simulation trial designed by the Universidad Católica de Murcia between November 2014 and February 2015. Volunteer nurses from the emergency medicine service of Murcia, Spain, were randomized to an intervention group to simulate intubations with telemedicine assistance (n=25) or a control group that did not receive assistance (n=25). The main outcome variable was satisfactory orotracheal intubation. Results. We observed statistically significant between-group differences in percentages of satisfactory intubation (telemedicine group, 96%, vs control group, 72%; P=.024) and time required to intubate the trachea (mean difference, 94.3 seconds, 95% CI, 40.7&#150;147.9 seconds; P=.001). Conclusions. Telemedicine assistance from an expert by way of a Google Glass application improves the success rate and completion times of nurses performing out-of-hospital intratracheal intubations in clinical simulations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juguera Rodríguez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Ríos, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ayuso, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasheras Velasco, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Solera, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Alonso, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar el efecto de la ayuda telemática, a través de las Google Glass® (GG), de un médico experto para la correcta intubación orotraqueal (IOT) realizada en simulación clínica por enfermeros de extrahospitalaria. Método. Ensayo aleatorizado de simulación clínica desarrollado en la Universidad Católica de Murcia de noviembre 2014 a febrero 2015. Se distribuyó aleatoriamente a los enfermeros voluntarios de la Gerencia de Emergencias 061 de Murcia en un grupo de 25 enfermeros con ayuda telemática mediante las GG (GpG) y un grupo de 25 enfermeros sin ayuda (GpC). La variable principal del estudio fue la correcta IOT. Resultados. Se hallaron diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos en los porcentajes de IOT correcta (96% GpG vs 72% GpC; p = 0,024) y en el tiempo de ejecución de la IOT [diferencia de medias 94,3 (IC95% 40,7-147,9) s; p = 0,001]. Conclusión. La ayuda telemática de un médico experto, a través de las GG, mejora los porcentajes y tiempos de la IOT correcta de los enfermeros de extrahospitalaria en situaciones clínicas simuladas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(4): 235-238, ago. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo de simulación clínica aleatorizado para evaluar el efecto de la telemedicina, a través de las Google Glass®, en la intubación orotraqueal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54836^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
