<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153395</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The analytic encounter with the archaic. Considerations on primitive agonies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article, drawing upon Freud&#146;s later texts, Constructions in analysis and Findings, ideas, problems, aims &amp;#64257;rstly to locate the territory of the archaic. The archaic, considered thus, would correspond to experiences without representative status, unconstructed, not even in the form of memories- not bound to word-representation and devoid of integration into subjectivity. Secondly, certain aspects of the repetition compulsion are examined, in light of that which, in terms of repetition, might introduce the &#147;fear of breakdown&#148; according to Winnicotfs postulates in his discussion of the &#147;primitive agonies&#148; which, according to the author, are inscribed within the &amp;#64257;eld of the archaic. Shored up by the developments advanced by Roussillon, the author sustains that the repetition compulsion is moreover an &#147;integration compulsion&#148;. Thirdl and in conclusion, the author calls to mind some of the characteristics of analysis and of the analyst Which might be favorable to the emer ence and subective appropriation of events that occurred, but have not yet been experienced: the &#145; life unlived&#148;, in Ogden&#146;s terms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojas-Urrego, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se apunta en primer término a situar el territorio de lo arcaico, partiendo de dos textos tardíos dc Sigmund Freud, Construcciones en el analisis y conclusiones, ideas, problemas. Lo arcaico, así tratado, correspondería a experiencias sin estatus representativo, no construidas aun en forma de recuerdos, no ligadas a representaciones de palabras y carentes de integración en la subjetividad. Son interrogados, en una segunda parte, ciertos aspectos de la compulsión de repetición, a la luz de lo que en términos de repetición podría introducir el miedo al derrumbe según los postulados de Winnicott al tratar de las agonías primitivas que, según el autor, se inscriben en el campo de lo arcaico. Con apoyo en los desarrollos propuestos por Roussillon, se sustenta que la compulsión de repetición es además una «compulsión de integración». El autor evoca, en tercer lugar y para terminar, algunas características del análisis y del analista que podrían favorecer la emergencia y la apropiación subjetiva de eventos que ocurrieron, mas no han sido aún vividos: la «vida no vivida», en términos de Ogden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(76): 217-235, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El encuentro analítico con lo arcaico. Consideraciones sobre las agonías primitivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54750^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
