<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048518</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical emergencies in the adult immigrant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The need for medical care of the immigrant population is growing in proportion to the increase in the number of immigrants resident in Spain. This article reviews the socio-demographic characteristics of the immigrant population that come for consultations in the emergency services and discusses those particularities, both medical (neurocysticercosis, tuberculosis, infection by the AIDS virus, hepatitis, malaria, parasitosis, Ulysses syndrome) and paramedical (knowledge of the health card, concept of medicine, language barrier), that differentiate them from the native population. Nonetheless, since we are dealing with a young population that is in principle healthy, their reasons for consultation do not greatly differ from the general population. It is worth drawing attention to the high level of satisfaction of this population with the care afforded them in the hospital emergency services</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Junyent, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La necesidad de atención médica de la población inmigrante crece en la misma proporción en que aumenta el número de inmigrantes residentes en España. En el presente trabajo se revisan las características sociodemográficas de la población inmigrante que consulta en urgencias y se discuten cuáles son las particularidades médicas (neurocisticercosis, tuberculosis, infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia adquirida, hepatitis, paludismo, parasitosis, síndrome de Ulises) y paramédicas (conocimiento de la tarjeta sanitaria, concepto de la medicina, barrera idiomática) que los diferencian de la población autóctona. No obstante, por tratarse de población joven, y en un principio sana, sus motivos de consulta no difieren en gran manera de la población general. Es de destacar la elevada satisfacción de esta población con la atención dispensada en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(supl.1): 27-34, ene.-abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urgencias médicas del inmigrante adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
