<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86816</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of the Stroop test in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. The aim of this study is to analyse the differences in the Stroop effect between cases with attention deficit hyperactivity  disorder (ADHD) and controls. It also seeks to find the best model based on the third task of the colours and words test (Stroop-CW) for predicting ADHD and to analyse the validity of the Stroop-CW test for diagnosing the disorder. Subjects and methods. The sample studied consisted of 100 cases of ADHD &#150;according to Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (DSM-IV) criteria&#150; and 100 controls, between 7 and 11 years of age, who were evaluated using the Stroop test. The controls were recruited at random and paired by age, sex and sociodemographic area with the cases. Results. The cases present a mean cognitive style that is significantly less flexible (d = &#150;1.06) and they also display a lower capacity to inhibit or control automatic responses than the controls at all ages (7 years: d = 1.67; 8 years: d = 1.02; 9 years: d = 1.32; 10 years: d = 2.04; 11 years: d = 0.89). The model of logistic regression analysis that best predicts ADHD is made up of age and Stroop-CW. The formulation derived from the model offers a sensitivity of 81% and a specificity of 72%, taking the criteria of the DSM-IV for ADHD as the reference test.  Conclusions. The Stroop-CW test presents usefulness and complementary criteria validity for the diagnosis of ADHD(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Azón, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Vilalobos, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés de LLano, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Mateos, Juan Delgado</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Pintado, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberola López, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar las diferencias entre casos de trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) y controles en el efecto Stroop, y buscar el mejor modelo basado en la tercera prueba del test de colores y palabras (Stroop-PC) que permita predecir el TDAH y analizar la validez del Stroop-PC para el diagnóstico del trastorno. Sujetos y métodos. Se estudia una muestra de 100 casos de TDAH &#150;criterios del Manual diagnóstico y estadístico de los trastornos mentales, 4 ed. (DSM-IV)&#150; y 100 controles, entre 7 y 11 años, evaluados mediante el test de Stroop. Los controles  fueron reclutados de forma aleatoria y emparejados según la edad, el sexo y la zona sociodemográfica con los casos. Resultados. Los casos presentan un estilo cognitivo medio significativamente menos flexible (d = &#150;1,06) y reflejan menor capacidad para inhibir o controlar respuestas automáticas que los controles en todas las edades (7 años: d = &#150;1,67; 8  años: d = &#150;1,02; 9 años: d = &#150;1,32; 10 años: d = &#150;2,04; 11 años: d = &#150;0,89). El modelo de regresión logística que mejor predice el TDAH está formado por edad y Stroop-PC. La formulación derivada del modelo presenta una sensibilidad del 81% y una especificidad del 72%, tomando como prueba de referencia los criterios del DSM-IV para el TDAH. Conclusiones. El Stroop-PC presenta utilidad y validez de criterio complementaria para el diagnóstico de TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(6): 333-340, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del test de Stroop en el trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3151</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
