<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102073</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endodontic restorative planning for esthetic and functional rehabilitation of maxillary incisors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the endodontic planning we should have a clinical plan jointly concerning the restoring possibilities. The case reports the endodontic and restorative treatment in two maxillary incisors with extensive carious lesion. The plan of clinical treatment relapsed in the periodontal therapy, endodontic treatment and for the crown reconstruction with the employment of intraradicular glass fiber post. The clinical case illustrates that the restorative planning of an endodontically treated teeth should be carried out to the endodontic treatment jointly preferable quickly as possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernando Machado-Silveira, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Severo Masotti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felberg, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la planificación del tratamiento endodóncico debemos establecer conjuntamente un plan clínico sobre las posibilidades restauradoras. El siguiente caso clínico describe el tratamiento endodóncico y restaurador en dos incisivos superiores ampliamente destruidos por caries. El plan de tratamiento clínico empezó en la terapia periodontal, tratamiento endodóncico y en la reconstrucción coronaria con el empleo de pernos intraconductos de fibra de vidrio. El caso clínico ilustra que la planificación restauradora de un diente endodonciado debe ser realizada a la mayor brevedad posible juntamente con el tratamiento del conducto radicular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);28(3): 141-146, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102073</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Planificación endodóncico-restauradora para la rehabilitación funcional y estética de incisivos superiores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3459^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3219^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
