<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104195</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Barriers to the normalization of telemedicine in a healthcare system model based on purchasing of healthcare services using providers&#146; contracts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Despite the clear political will to promote telemedicine and the large number of initiatives, the incorporation of this modality in clinical practice remains limited. The objective of this study was to identify the barriers perceived by key professionals who actively participate in the design and implementation of telemedicine in a healthcare system model based on purchasing of healthcare services using providers&#146; contracts. Methods We performed a qualitative study based on data from semi-structured interviews with 17 key informants belonging to distinct Catalan health organizations .Results The barriers identified were grouped in four areas: technological, organizational, human and economic. The main barriers identified were changes in the healthcare model caused by telemedicine, problems with strategic alignment, resistance to change in the (re)definition of roles, responsibilities and new skills, and lack of a business model that incorporates telemedicine in the services portfolio to ensure its sustainability. Conclusions In addition to suitable management of change and of the necessary strategic alignment, the definitive normalization of telemedicine in a mixed healthcare model based on purchasing of healthcare services using providers&#146; contracts requires a clear and stable business model that incorporates this modality in the services portfolio and allows healthcare organizations to obtain reimbursement from the payer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saigí, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo A pesar de la gran cantidad de iniciativas de telemedicina y de la decidida voluntad política por impulsar su uso, la incorporación a la práctica clínica habitual es todavía reducida. El objetivo del estudio fue identificar las barreras percibidas por los profesionales que participan activamente en el diseño y la puesta en marcha de proyectos de telemedicina en un modelo sanitario de concertación de servicios. Métodos Estudio cualitativo realizado a partir de los datos obtenidos mediante entrevistas semiestructuradas a 17 informantes clave de diferentes organizaciones del ámbito de la salud en Cataluña. Resultados Las barreras identificadas se agrupan en cuatro ámbitos: tecnológico, organizativo, humano y económico. Como barreras principales se señalan las relacionadas con las transformaciones en el modelo asistencial que comporta la telemedicina, la no siempre coincidente alineación estratégica, la resistencia al cambio ante la (re)definición de roles y responsabilidades, y la adquisición de nuevas habilidades y la ausencia de un modelo de negocio que incorpore la telemedicina a la cartera de servicios y permita asegurar su sostenibilidad. Conclusiones Además de una adecuada gestión del cambio y del necesario alineamiento estratégico, la incorporación definitiva de la telemedicina en la práctica clínica habitual en un sistema de salud público basado en la concertación de servicios requiere la definición de un modelo de negocio claro y estable, que incorpore la telemedicina en la cartera de servicios de la Administración y ofrezca a las organizaciones de salud la posibilidad de obtener el reembolso de la actividad realizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(5): 397-402, sep. - oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Barreras para la normalización de la telemedicina en un sistema de salud basado en la concertación de servicios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29453^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
