<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60038</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital hemidysplasia with ichthyosiform erythroderma and unilateral defects of the limbs. CHILD syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: CHILD syndrome is an X-linked dominant, male-lethal trait caused by mutations in the gene NSDHL, located at Xq28 and enconding a 3&amp;#946;-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase involved in the cholesterol biosynthetic pathway.  In CHILD syndrome a Ichthyosiform nevus is a caracteristic with lateralization patterns. Rigth side involvement occurs twice as often as left side involvemet. Case report: We describe a case of CHILD syndrome involving the left side of the body, absence of the left arm and reduction anomaly of the left leg and foot resulted in oligodactyly with only a finger. An ipsilateral inflammatory epidermal nevus with hyperkeratosis, parakeratosis, acanthosis and perivascular lymphohistiocytic infiltrate was strictly confined to the left half of the patient&#146;s body. Conclusions: We conclude that a diagnosis of CHILD syndrome can be based on clinical features such as the highly characteristic morphology of the CHILD nevus as thick laminated orthokeratosis and prominent keratotic follicular plugs containing dystrophic calcification (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moussou, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duro, EA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome CHILD, es una enfermedad ligada al sexo de expresión dominante, letal en los hombres, causada por una mutación en el gen NSDHL, localizado en el locus 28 del brazo corto del cromosoma X, que codifica la 3-&amp;#946; hidroxiesteroide deshidrogenasa involucrada en la síntesis del colesterol. En el síndrome CHILD un nevo ictiosiforme es una de sus características con patrones de lateralización, donde la afectación del lado derecho, es dos veces más frecuente que la del lado izquierdo. Caso clínico: Se describe un caso de síndrome de CHILD con afectación del lado izquierdo del cuerpo, ausencia del brazo izquierdo y anomalía de reducción de la pierna izquierda y el pie con oligodactilia que termina en un solo dedo. Un nevo epidérmico inflamatorio ipsilateral con hiperqueratosis, paraqueratosis, acantosis e infiltrado linfohistiocitico perivascular se encontraba limitado estrictamente a la mitad izquierda del cuerpo del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;49(207): 54-57, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60038</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemidisplasia congenita con eritrodermia ictiosiforme y defectos unilaterales de las extremidades. Sindrome CHILD</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13249^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7240^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7240^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28985^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28985^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31341^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7240^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28985^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31341^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13249^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
