<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112536</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of adverse events for patient safety in chronic pain treatment units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To identify preventive actions that minimise risk of patients safety in pain treatment units, and to cluster preventive actions into homogeneous groups. The current study is part of a project intended to improve patient safety in pain treatment units, and is aimed at identifying, prioritising and preventing patient safety risk. Material and methods. A group of experts was selected from professionals with a specific clinical background and experience in pain treatment units. This group was provided with information on patient safety and on known adverse events, errors and related causes. Through a brainstorming method the participants were asked: What changes or improvements would need to be undertaken to absolutely prevent the occurrence of each adverse event? The participant's proposals were analysed and grouped according to their homogeneity. Results. A total of 456 preventive actions were identified. The group that received the highest number of suggestions was the one including changes in the management of healthcare processes, followed by the group that considered improvements in clinical practice, training activities, protocols and policies, and patient communication. Conclusions. According to the consensus of the experts, management of healthcare processes and improvements in health care practices are the 2 interventions that are most likely to reduce patient safety risk in pain treatment units(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pazzis Die de Ortega, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ruiz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Cotelo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Lázaro, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Mateos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra de Hoyos, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Insausti Valdivia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Identificar acciones preventivas que minimicen el riesgo para la seguridad de los pacientes atendidos en las unidades de tratamiento del dolor, y agrupar en lotes las acciones preventivas que presenten características homogéneas. El trabajo es una parte de un proyecto de mejora de la seguridad de pacientes atendidos en dichas unidades, cuyo propósito global ha sido la identificación, priorización y prevención de riesgos. Material y métodos. Se seleccionó un grupo de expertos formado por profesionales con formación clínica específica y experiencia en programas y servicios de atención al dolor. Se les proporcionó formación en seguridad de pacientes e información sobre los eventos adversos identificados, los fallos y las causas asociados. Mediante la técnica de tormenta de ideas los participantes respondieron a la pregunta: ¿qué modificaciones o mejoras habría que hacer al proceso asistencial para evitar absolutamente la aparición de cada uno de los eventos adversos? Las propuestas generadas se consensuaron y agruparon en lotes en función de su homogeneidad. Resultados. Se identificaron 456 acciones preventivas. El apartado más numeroso fue el de las modificaciones en la organización del proceso asistencial, seguido de los de las mejoras en la práctica clínica, las actividades formativas, la protocolización y la comunicación con el paciente. Conclusiones. Según el consenso de los expertos, son los cambios organizativos y las mejoras en la práctica asistencial, las intervenciones que más podrían reducir el riesgo para los pacientes en las unidades de tratamiento del dolor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(4): 204-214, abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112536</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de eventos adversos para la seguridad del paciente en las unidades de tratamiento del dolor crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
