<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134308</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of occupational injuries by body part affected and type of injury in Spain, 1999-2001</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To study occupational injury trends in Spain in the period 1999 to 2001 by type of injury and body part affected. Method: The information refers to lost-time occupational injuries among workers in the Social Security system. The period of study included the years 1999 through 2001. The data were obtained from the Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs. Results: The most common type of injury was " twisting, sprains and strains", which is similar to that reported for mild lost-time occupational injuries. For serious accidents, the most frequent injury over the three-year study period was "fractures". For fatal occupational accidents during the three-year study period, the most common injury category was "multiple injuries" . For mild and serious accidents resulting in lost-time, the most frequently affected body part was the hand. In the case of fatal accidents, multiple body parts were most often involved. Conclusions: These results suggest that trends in type of injury and body part affected remained unchanged over these three years, indicating that similar risks persist and that control measures should be implemented in order to reduce this risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la evolución de las lesiones por accidentes de trabajo con baja en España en el período 1999 al 2001 según la naturaleza de la lesión y por la región anatómica afectada. Método: La información se refiere a los accidentes de trabajo con baja ocurridos a los trabajadores afiliados a la Seguridad Social que tienen cubierta dicha contingencia. El período de estudio ha sido los años 1999 al 2001. Los datos fueron obtenidos del Ministerio de Trabajo y Asuntos Sociales. Resultados: La naturaleza de la lesión más frecuente en los accidentes de trabajo con baja en los años estudiados ha sido "las torceduras, esguinces y distensiones", que coincide con la naturaleza de la lesión más frecuente en los accidentes leves de trabajo con baja. En cuanto a la naturaleza de la lesión más frecuente en los accidentes graves de trabajo con baja en los años del estudio ha sido "las fracturas". Y la naturaleza de la lesión más frecuente en los accidentes mortales de trabajo con baja fueron "las lesiones múltiples". En cuanto a la localización más frecuente del total de accidentes de trabajo con baja, de los accidentes leves de trabajo con baja y de los accidentes graves de trabajo con baja fueron las manos. En cuanto a los accidentes mortales de trabajo correspondió a las lesiones múltiples. Conclusiones: Sobre la base de los resultados obtenidos vemos que el tipo de lesión y su localización ha sido la misma en estos tres años, lo que nos indica que el riesgo sigue siendo el mismo y que se deberían tomar medidas preventivas que lo hicieran disminuir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);7(2): 70-75, abr.-jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134308</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicencia de lesiones por accidente de trabajo según su localización anatómica y tipo de lesión ocurridos en España (1999-2001)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
