<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80653</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Majorcan sobrasada: from tradition to industrial production</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sobrasada is the most typical Majorcan sausage, traditionally made along history in this island. On the XVth century, an important sausage tradition was developed in Majorca, and on the XVIIth century, sobrasada passed from a traditional meat reserve to be a characteristic sign of traditional Majorcan gastronomy. At the beginning of 1996 the European Union protected the product Sobrasada de Mallorca with a quality sign: Protected Geographical Direction. The sobrasada is a raw and ured sausage, made with pork meat, lean and lard, picked, and flavoured with paprika, pepper, alt and spices, mixed, stuffed and cured. This composition is controlled by law. The aim of this work is to explain the origin and history of Majorcan sobrasada, and the production method of this sausage, from traditional to industrial production in Majorca, as well as to give data related to its nutritional contribution(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llull, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tur Marí, Josep A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sobrasada es el embutido por excelencia de la isla de Mallorca. Su tradición y origen se remonta a lo largo de historia. En el siglo XVI, se desarró en Mallorca una importante tradición charcutera con los primeros signos distintivos propios y en el siglo XVll la sobrasada pasó de ser una reserva de carne a un signo característico de la gastronomía tradicional. A principios del 1996, la Unión Europea protegió la denominación Sobrasada de Mallorca con la denominación de calidad: Indicación Geográfica Protegida. La sobrasada es un embutido crudo curado, elaborado con carnes de cerdo, magro y tocino, picadas, adicionadas con pimentón, sal y especias, posteriormente amasadas, embutidas y curadas, Dicha composición se encuentra regulada por ley. Este trabajo da a conocer el origen y la historia de la sobrasada de Mallorca, estudia los sistemas de producción de la misma, desde la elaboración tradicional que se viene llevando a cabo en la isla de Mallorca, hasta la producción industrial. También se aportan datos relativos a su contribución nutricional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;15(3): 163-169, jul.-sep.2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sobrasada de Mallorca: de la tradición la la elaboración industrial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25293^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8631^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
