<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155325</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systematic review about personal growth initiative</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study aimed to realize a systematic review of publications about personal growth initiative. A literature review was realized in Bireme, Index Psi, LILACS, PePSIC, Pubmed - Publisher&#146;s Medline, Wiley Online Library, PsycINFO, OneFile, SciVerse ScienceDirect, ERIC, Emerald Journals, PsycARTICLES - American Psychological Association, Directory of Open Access Journals - DOAJ, SAGE Journals, SpringerLink, PLoS, IngentaConnect, IEEE Journals &amp; Magazines and SciELO databases. The literature review was performed from December of 2014 to January of 2015, without stipulating date limits for the publication of the articles. It was found 53 studies, excluded seven, and analyzed 46 researches. The studies aimed to investigate the psychometric properties of personal growth initiative scale and personal growth initiative scale II. The relations of personal initiative growth and others constructs were also evaluated. Furthermore the studies investigated the impact of interventions to promote personal growth initiative. Results of these studies showed that personal growth initiative was positively related to levels of well-being, selfesteem and others positive dimensions, and negatively to anxiety, depression and others negative factors (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tobo, Patricia Renovato</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro de Freitas, Clarissa Pinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Damásio, Bruno Figueiredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Koller,  Sílvia Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kamei, Helder Hiroki</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio busca realizar una revisión sistemática de publicaciones acerca de la iniciativa de crecimiento personal. Se realizó una revisión de literatura en las bases de datos Bireme, Index Psi, LILACS, PePSIC, Pubmed - Publisher&#146;s Medline, Wiley Online Library, PsycINFO, OneFile, SciVerse ScienceDirect, ERIC, Emerald Journals, PsycARTICLES - American Psychological Association, Directory of Open Access Journals - DOAJ, SAGE Journals, SpringerLink, PLoS, IngentaConnect, IEEE Journals &amp; Magazines y SciELO. La revisión de la literatura se realizó a partir de diciembre de 2014 a enero de 2015, sin estipular límites de fecha para la publicación de los artículos. De los 53 estudios hallados, se excluyeron 7 y se analizaron 46. Los estudios se enfocaron en investigar las propiedades psicométricas de la escala iniciativa de crecimiento personal y de iniciativa de crecimiento personal escala II. Las relaciones de crecimiento personal iniciativa y otros constructos también fueron evaluados. Además, los estudios investigaron el impacto de las intervenciones para promover la iniciativa de crecimiento personal. Los resultados de estos estudios mostraron que iniciativa de crecimiento personal se relaciona positivamente con los niveles de bienestar, la autoestima y otras dimensiones positivas, y negativamente con la ansiedad, depresión y otros factores negativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(3): 770-782, oct. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155325</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática sobre iniciativa de crecimiento personal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
