<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83763</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing role in patient management diagnosed chronic fatigue syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic fatigue syndrome is a serious, complex and debilitating fatigue characterized by intense physical and mental, that does not subside significantly after rest and worsens with activity.  The appearance of the disease requires the patient to reduce the activity diminished their quality of life. While there is no cure, the complexity of the disease requires an interdisciplinary approach where the mission of nursing is to identify the least healthy responses of each individual in relation to their health status and interfering with them by means of specific support, integrated support and follow a care plan tailored to the individual needs of each individual.  Fatigue, pain, sleep pattern disturbance, anxiety and lack of knowledge are the most prevalent health problems in patients treated at the Chronic Fatigue Unit, University Hospital Vall d'Hebron. Thus, in these problems and by developing a customized care plan process we use for Health Education as a tool for influencing the control of symptoms through interventions to improve the learning support, emotional support and Accompanying with the aim of helping the patient and their relatives are an adaptive response to their new health status and thus improve the quality of life(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sevillano Lalinde, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llinas Vidal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badía Royes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de fatiga crónica es una enfermedad grave, compleja y debilitante caracterizada por una fatiga intensa, física y mental, que no remite de forma significativa tras el reposo y que empeora con la acción.  La aparición de la enfermedad obliga al paciente a reducir la actividad deteriorando su calidad de vida. Si bien no existe un tratamiento curativo, la complejidad de la dolencia requiere un abordaje interdisciplinar donde la misión de enfermería consiste en identificar las respuestas menos saludables de cada individuo en relación a su situación de salud e interferir sobre ellas mediante intervenciones específicas de soporte, apoyo y acompañamiento integradas en un plan de cuidados adaptado a las necesidades individuales de cada persona.  La fatiga, el dolor, la alteración del patrón del sueño, la ansiedad y el déficit de conocimientos son los problemas de salud más prevalentes en los pacientes asistidos en la Unidad de Fatiga Crónica del Hospital Universitario Vall d´Hebron. Así, ante estos problemas y mediante la elaboración de un plan de cuidados personalizado, utilizamos el proceso de educación para la salud como herramienta para actuar sobre el control de la sintomatología mediante intervenciones de soporte para favorecer el aprendizaje, y de apoyo emocional y de acompañamiento. Todo ello con el objetivo de ayudar a que el paciente y sus allegados encuentren una respuesta adaptativa a su nuevo estatus de salud y así poder mejorar su calidad de vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(12): 812-819, dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo del paciente diagnosticado de síndrome de fatiga crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
