<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80134</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human immunodeficiency virus and AIDS associated immune reconstitution syndrome. State of the art</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the arrival of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART), immune reconstitution syndrome (IRS) has become an increasingly more frequent complication in patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection. This article presents a review of the available evidence on this subject, indexed in MEDLINE-PUBMED, BVS-BIREME, and BioMed Central. The review covers the definition, epidemiology, classification, and diagnostic criteria related to IRS. In addition, the clinical particularities of the most frequent etiologies are described, and a proposal for a therapeutic approach is formulated. The prognosis and future implications of this syndrome in the epidemiology of some infectious illnesses in the HIV-positive population are included. Several unresolved aspects are mentioned, such as those related to the pathophysiology of the condition, use of biomarkers for the diagnosis, and the need for evidence-based therapeutic algorithms to enable standardization of treatment for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bouza-Jiménez, Yadira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-Corcho, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Luego del advenimiento del tratamiento antirretroviral de gran actividad (TARGA), el síndrome de reconstitución inmunológica (SRI) es una complicación cada vez más frecuente en los individuos infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). El artículo tuvo como objetivo presentar una revisión de las evidencias científicas disponibles sobre el tema, indizadas en Medline, PubMed, BVS-BIREME y BioMedCentral. Éste abarcó la definición, la epidemiología, la clasificación y los criterios diagnósticos del SRI. Además, se describieron las particularidades clínicas de las etiologías más frecuentes y se realizó una propuesta de enfoque terapéutico. Se abordó el pronóstico y las implicaciones futuras de esta entidad en la epidemiología de algunas enfermedades infecciosas en la población VIH positiva. Se mencionaron varios aspectos aún inconclusos sobre el tema, sobre todo los relacionados con la fisiopatología, el uso de los biomarcadores para el diagnóstico y la necesidad de algoritmos terapéuticos basados en pruebas que permitan estandarizar la conducta ante estos enfermos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;28(2): 110-121, feb. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de reconstitución inmunológica asociado al virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana y sida. Estado del arte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30862^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52632^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52632^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
