<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113280</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Circumferential viscocanalostomy with suture tensioning in Schlemm canal (canaloplasty)&#150;one year experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To study the efficacy and the safety of ultrasound biomicroscopy assisted canaloplasty in the treatment of open-angle glaucoma (OAG). Methods: A prospective study of uncontrolled open-angle glaucoma patients, or patients with cataracts associated with controlled or uncontrolled OAG under maximal medical therapy who had been subjected to canaloplasty alone or combined with cataract surgery, respectively. Complications, Goldmann intraocular pressure (IOP) and mean number of drugs (ND) were evaluated at 1 day, 1 week, 1 month, and every 3 months. Results: Thirty five surgeries were performed (11 canaloplasties, 24 phaco-canaloplasties). The mean IOP (mmHg) dropped from 24.5 ± 5.1, in canaloplasty, and from 19.8 ± 6.4, in phacocanaloplasty, preoperatively, to medium-low levels at all follow-up periods (13.5 ± 1.0 and 11.0 ± 4.2, at 1 year in canaloplasty and phaco-canaloplasty, respectively). The number of grugs used dropped from 3.3 ± 0.5 before surgery to less than of 1 in all follow-up periods (0.5 ± 0.8 at 1 year). The complications were 2 microruptures of the trabeculodescemetic window, 5 entries in the collector channels, 5 choroidal space/anterior chamber passages, 10 hyphemas, 3 hypotonies, one peripheral Descemet detachment, one intracorneal hematoma, two peripheral anterior synechia, one internal iris prolapse, and two suture extrusions to the anterior chamber. Conclusions: Ultrasound biomicroscopy assisted Canaloplasty, alone or combined, provided a sustained IOP reduction to medium-low levels, led to a decrease in the number of drugs and had a good safety profile, making this a good alternative to trabeculectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amorim, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvão-Santos, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes-Cardoso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteves, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado-Borges, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: Estudiar la eficacia y la seguridad de la canaloplastia asistida por biomicroscopia ultrasónica en el tratamiento de glaucoma de ángulo abierto Métodos: Estudio prospectivo de pacientes con glaucoma de ángulo abierto no controlado o pacientes con catarata asociada a glaucoma descontrolado o controlado con tratamiento médico máximo, sometidos a canaloplastia simple o combinada. Fueron evaluados las complicaciones, la presión intraocular Goldmann (PIO) y el número medio de fármacos (NMF) en primer día, primera semana, primer mes y de 3 en 3 meses. Resultados: Se realizaron 35 cirugías (11 canaloplastias, 24 facocanaloplastias). La PIO media (mmHg) disminuyó de 24,5 ± 1,0 en canaloplastia y de 19,8 ± 6,8 en facocanaloplastia, en el preoperatorio, a niveles medio-bajos en todos los periodos de seguimiento (13,5 ± 1,0 y 11,0 ± 4,2, al año, en canaloplastia y facocanaloplastia, respectivamente). El NMF ha bajado de 3,3 ± 0,5 antes de la cirugía para niveles menores que uno en todos los tiempos de seguimiento (0,5 ± 0,8, al año). Como complicaciones se obtuvieron 2 microrroturas de la ventana trabeculodescemética, 5 entradas en los colectores, 5 trayectos coroideo/cámara anterior, 10 hipemas, 3 hipotonías, un desgarro periférico de la Descemet, un hematoma intracorneano, 2 sinequias anteriores periféricas, un prolapso interno de iris y 2 extrusiones de la sutura a la cámara anterior. Conclusiones: La canaloplastia asistida por biomicroscopia ultrasónica simple o combinada obtuvo reducciones sustentadas de la PIO para niveles medio-bajos así como en el NMF y con un buen perfil de seguridad, lo que la hacen una buena alternativa a la trabeculectomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;88(6): 207-215, jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113280</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Viscocanalostomía circunferencial con sutura de tensión en el canal de Schlemm (canaloplastia): un año de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14864^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28054^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
