<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89269</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of social phobia form a cognitive perspective: A case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Social phobia is one of the most disabling and poorly diagnosed anxiety disorders, presenting an anual prevalence of 1,2% in the European Union, somewhat higher in women than men. In the past decade, there has been a significant progress in cognitive models oriented towards the study and treatment of anxiety disorders. These new models focus on how, more than what, individuals with emotional disorders think. Models have evolved from &#147;fear of negative evaluation&#148;, as the central component of cognitive formulations in the a etiology and maintenance of this disorder, to a more purely cognitive processing that underlines: (a) increased self-focused attention linked to a decrease in the observation of others and their responses attentional bias -; (b) frequent excessively negative inferences about how one appears to others are made-interpretative bias -; (c) extensive use of overt and covert safety behaviours, and (d) problematic pre- and post-social event processing (Clark &amp; Wells, 1995; Wells, 1997, 2000). New empirical contributions indicate the superiority of cognitive therapy based on these cognitive processing models over exposure (Clark et al., 2006). We present a clinical case report of a 28 year old man undergoing a cognitive- behavioural intervention essentially based on cognitive models and techniques (Eysenck, 1997; Clark &amp; Wells, 1995). Comparison of pre and post-treatment results and generalization of objectives show therapeutic efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Vindel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Cejudo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fobia social es uno de los trastornos de ansiedad más discapacitantes y peor diagnosticados, presentando una prevalencia anual en la Unión Europea del 1,2% algo mayor en mujeres que en varones. En la última década ha habida un importante avance de los modelos cognitivos para el estudio y tratamiento de los trastornos emocionales, más que en el qué. Desde el &#147;miedo a la evaluación negativa&#148; como el componente central de las formulaciones cognitivas en la etiología y mantenimiento de este desorden, los modelos han evolucionado hacia un más puro procesamiento cognitivo que subraya: (a) incrementada atención centrada en uno mismo, ligada al decremento de la observación hacia los demás y sus conductas &#150;sesgo atencional-; (b) se hacen frecuentes inferencias excesivamente negativas acerca de cómo uno es visto por los demás &#150;sesgo interpretativo-; (c) amplio uso de conductas abiertas y encubiertas de seguridad; y (d) procesamiento problemático antes y después de un evento social (Clark &amp; Wells, 1995; Wells, 1997, 2000). Nuevas aportaciones empíricas muestran la superioridad de la terapia cognitiva frente a la exposición (Clark et al., 2006). A continuación presentamos un caso clínico de un varón de 28 años de edad, partiendo de una intervención cognitivo-conductual y basándonos fundamentalmente en modelos y técnicas cognitivas (Eysenck, 1997; Clark &amp; Wells, 1995). Los resultados pre y postratamiento y la generalización de los objetivos terapéuticos muestran la eficacia del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;14(2/3): 289-303, dic. 2008. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectivas cognitivas en el tratamiento de la fobia social: estudio de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
