<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109610</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update of the usefulness of alpha-blockers in the treatment of different urologic pathologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To review the role of alpha-blockers in various urological conditions such as benign prostatic hyperplasia, overactive bladder, chronic prostatitis, and erectile dysfunction and as expulsive treatment of distal ureteral stones. Material and methods. We reviewed the latest scientific evidence in all the fields mentioned above, performing a critical analysis. Conclusion. alpha-blockers are now considered first-line treatment in lower urinary tract symptoms secondary to benign prostatic hyperplasia, but the indications go beyond, and are able to improve, alone or in combination with other drugs, the previously mentioned pathologies. The uroselective properties of some alpha-blockers make them a highly safe medication(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moncada Iribarren, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brenes Bermúdez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Revisar el papel de los alfa-bloqueantes en distintos trastornos urológicos como son la hipertrofia benigna de próstata, la vejiga hiperactiva, la prostatitis crónica, la disfución eréctil y el tratamiento expulsivo de la litiasis ureteral distal. Material y método. Se revisa la evidencia científica más actual en todos los campos anteriormente citados, haciéndose un análisis crítico de los mismos. Conclusiones. Los alfa-bloqueantes se consideran en la actualidad el tratamiento de primera elección en los síntomas del tracto urinario inferior secundarios al crecimiento prostático benigno, pero sus indicaciones van más allá, pudiendo mejorar solos o en adyuvancia con otros fármacos los procesos patológicos anteriormente citados. La uroselectividad de alguno de ellos les hace que tengan una seguridad muy alta en su utilización(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(13): 582-587, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los alfa-bloqueantes en el tratamiento de distintos trastornos urológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11915^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d320^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
