<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039475</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral clarithromycin as a treatment option in chronic post-operative endophthalmitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To assess the outcome of medical treatment with oral clarithromycin in patients with chronic post-surgical endophthalmitis.    Methods: This prospective study was performed between January 1999 and September 2003. Patients with a diagnosis of chronic post-surgical endophthalmitis of bacterial etiology were included. All received 500 mg of oral clarithromycin twice a day for 14 days. The initial and final visual acuity, etiology, post-surgical time of presentation, treatment-delay time, and follow up were recorded. According to the treatment results, patients were distributed into 3 separate groups: 1) complete response, 2) partial response, 3) no response.    Data from these groups were compared by means of the Student&#146;s t test and Fisher exact test, depending on which was considered most suitable.    Results: Fifteen cases of chronic endophthalmitis (11 of Propionibacterium acnes, 4 of Staphylococcus epidermidis) were diagnosed.    A complete response was observed in 4 cases, partial response in 4 cases, and no response in 7 cases.    Final visual acuity greater than 0.5 was significantly more likely in the complete response group when compared with the no response group (Fisher exact test = 0.0454, p=0.05), however, the same comparison between the complete response group and the partial response group was not significant.    Conclusion: Medical treatment with oral clarithromycin could be useful in some patients with chronic post-surgical endophthalmitis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wainberg, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartucci, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellegrino, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bohórquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schlaen, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar la respuesta al tratamiento médico con claritromicina oral de pacientes con endoftalmitis post-quirúrgica crónica.Métodos: Este estudio prospectivo se desarrolló durante el período comprendido entre enero de 1999 y septiembre de 2003. Se incluyeron pacientes con diagnóstico de endoftalmitis crónica de comienzo tardío que tuvieran etiología bacteriana. Se les administró claritromicina oral en 2 tomas diarias de 500 mg durante 14 días. Se registraron la agudeza visual inicial y final, la etiología, el tiempo de aparición del cuadro, el tiempo de demora de la instauración del tratamiento y el tiempo de seguimiento post tratamiento. Acorde a la respuesta al mismo los pacientes fueron distribuidos en 3 grupos: 1) Respuesta total, 2) respuesta parcial, 3) respuesta negativa.Las comparaciones estadísticas se realizaron mediante t de Student y la prueba exacta de Fisher según se consideró necesario.Resultados: Fueron diagnosticados 15 casos de endoftalmitis crónica (11 por Propionibacterium acnes y 4 por Staphylococcus epidermidis).Se observó respuesta total en 4 casos, parcial en 4 y negativa en 7.La comparación de las proporciones de pacientes con agudeza visual final mayor a 0,5 entre el grupo de respuesta total y el de respuesta negativa fue significativo (prueba exacta de Fisher= 0,0454 p=0,05). En cambio la misma comparación entre el grupo de respuesta total y el de respuesta parcial fue no significativo.Conclusiones: El tratamiento médico con claritromicina oral puede ser útil en algunos pacientes con endoftalmitis post-quirúrgica crónica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(6): 339-344, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039475</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Claritromicina oral como opción terapéutica en endoftalmitis post-quirúrgicas tardías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24636^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30785^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
