<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036745</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Educational software for the teaching of nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A descriptive study with a qualitative approach where the aim was to identifythe way in which teachers and pupils enrolled in a Nursing course perceive theuse of educational software. Six students and three teachers participated in the study representing 13.3% of the students and the totality of the teachers. The data from the interviews were organised and analysed using the HyperRESEARCH1.65 software package. The results showed that the thoughts of the respondents is directly associated with the focus used for the evaluation of the program. For the teachers, the didactic correction was fundamental and for the students, stimulation was considered a key point. We conclude that the results here described will show a tendency to change proportionally to the extent in which the computer is routinely used at universities and its skillful use becomes necessary to progress in the studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leite de Araujo, Thelma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Venicios de Oliveira Lópes, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudio de carácter descriptivo con abordaje cualitativo donde se buscó identificarla manera por la cual profesores y alumnos de un curso de Enfermería percibíanla utilización de un software educativo. Participaron del estudio seis alumnos y tres profesores, representando el 13,3% de los alumnos y la totalidad de los docentes. Los datos de las entrevistas fueron organizados y analizados con el apoyo del software Hyper RESEARCH 1.65. Los relatos mostraron que el pensamiento de los sujetos está directamente asociado al foco utilizado para la evaluación del programa. Para los profesores, la corrección didáctica fue fundamental y para los alumnos la estimulación fue considerada un punto clave. Concluimos en que los resultados aquí apuntados tenderán a un cambio en la medida en la que el ordenador esté más presente en el uso cotidiano de las universidades y su dominio sea condición necesaria para el avance de los estudios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(2): 23-26, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036745</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Software educativo en la enseñanza de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32764</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
