<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115645</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of analytical parameters in Internal Medicine patients to detect adverse events</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the prevalence of prescription drugs, previously selected, that should be monitored by their analytical test, and the rate of alteration in these tests, with the aim of establishing priorities to facilitate monitoring. Method: Prospective observational study in the Internal Medicine department of a referral hospital of 350 beds. In a first phase, we selected some drugs which analytical monitoring is recommended for the medical literature, and after that, we reviewed the pharmacological treatment of all patients admitted with any of these drugs. The study was conducted in the last two month of 2011. Results: We included 271 patients, 128 (47%) were women. The mean age was 74.5 ± 14.4 years and the average stay of 7 ± 5.8 days. These patients accounted for 83% of all patients admitted to Internal Medicine during the study period. There were 828 drugs that must be monitored; each patient had an average of 3.1 ± 2.3. We reviewed 1837 analytical test, of which 401 (22%) were altered and 154 patients (57%) were affected for it. The pairs drug-analytical test altered most frequently found were creatinine increased and nephrotoxic drugs, hypokalemia in patients taking high efficiency diuretics and thrombocytopenia in patients treated with low molecular weight heparins. Conclusions: Our study highlights the importance of monitoring laboratory test associated with some drugs from the pharmacy department, as it demonstrates a high incidence of warning results. Our proposal for selection of drugs makes monitoring easier, and reaches large numbers of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iniesta-Navalón, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antequera-Lardón, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbieta-Sanz, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Molina, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello-Muriel, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rentero-Redondo, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la frecuencia con la que se prescriben una serie de fármacos, previamente seleccionados, sobre los que existen recomendaciones de monitorización mediante parámetros analíticos, y la prevalencia de analíticas alteradas con el fin de establecer prioridades para facilitar su seguimiento. Método: Estudio prospectivo observacional realizado en el servicio de Medicina Interna de un hospital de referencia de área de 350 camas. En una primera fase se realizó una selección de fármacos cuya monitorización analítica está recomendada en la bibliografía, y posteriormente se realizó un seguimiento de los pacientes ingresados con alguno de estos fármacos en su tratamiento. El estudio se llevó a cabo en el último bimestre de 2011. Resultados: Se incluyeron 271 pacientes, de los cuales 128 (47%) fueron mujeres. La edad media fue de 74,5±14,4 años y la estancia media de 7±5,8 días. Estos pacientes representaron el 83% de todos los pacientes ingresados en el servicio de Medicina Interna durante el periodo de estudio. Se registraron 828 medicamentos susceptibles de monitorización; cada paciente tuvo una media de 3,1±2,3. Se revisaron 1837 analíticas, de las cuales 401 (22%) estaban alteradas y afectaron a 154 pacientes (57%). Los binomios fármaco-parámetro analítico alterado más frecuentemente encontrados fueron incremento de creatinina-fármacos nefrotóxicos, hipopotasemia en pacientes tratados con diuréticos de alta eficacia y trombocitopenia en pacientes tratados con heparinas de bajo peso molecular. Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio se pone de manifiesto la importancia de vigilar desde el servicio de Farmacia ciertos parámetros analíticos relacionados con determinados fármacos, ya que se demuestra una elevada incidencia de resultados alertantes. Nuestra propuesta de selección de fármacos facilita el seguimiento y alcanza a gran cantidad de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(1): 35-40, ene.-feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de parámetros analíticos en pacientes de medicina interna para detectar efectos adversos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
