<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152238</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the distribution of physical activity in early childhood education students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The practice of physical activity (PA) is very important element of promoting health during childhood. However, little information is available with regards to PA patterns of children during a day. The aim of this study was to describe the bouts patterns of different lengths of time among three periods of daily life in nursery school students. 107 children (3.81±0.87 years; 19,64±4,32 kg, 1,19±0,29 m) were selected. The subjects wore an accelerometer (Actigraph GT3X) during 5 consecutive days. The level of PA was calculated using the cut-points proposed by Sirard et al. (2005) in order to analyze moderate-intensity bout patterns of 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10 and 12 min during three periods Monday to Friday, school hours and extracurricular time. Results showed that students accumulated 90% of their PA intermittently, corresponding to bouts of 1 to 2 min (p&lt; 0.001). Based on these findings, it was concluded that that children in nursery school accumulated high intermittent PA, consisted of 1 to 2 min bouts, and this information should be used to promote strategies during school timetable in order to increase PA in school (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calahorro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nikolaidis, PT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Luque, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica de actividad física (AF) es un elemento muy importante en la promoción de la salud durante la infancia. Sin embargo, hay pocos estudios que profundicen en las características de la AF que desarrollan los niños a lo largo del día. El objetivo del presente estudio fue describir la distribución de la actividad física de una intensidad determinada en bouts o secuencias de diferente duración y durante tres períodos: lunes a viernes, horario escolar y horario extraescolar. Se seleccionaron 107 alumnos de segundo ciclo de Educación Infantil (3,81±0,87 años; 19,64±4,32 kg, 1,19±0,29 m). Los sujetos llevaron un acelerómetro (Actigraph GT3X) durante 5 días consecutivos. Se calcularon los niveles de actividad física, de acuerdo con los puntos de corte propuestos por Sirard et al. (2005) y se analizó la agrupación de la AF de intensidad moderada y vigorosa (AFMV) en bouts de 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10 y 12 min de duración. Los resultados mostraron el predominio de una AF de carácter esporádico, donde alrededor del 90% de la AFMV se realizó en bouts de 1 y 2 min. Se observó un mayor volumen de bouts de 1, 2, 4, 5 y 6 min de duración de lunes a viernes y en horario extraescolar que en el horario escolar (p&lt; 0,001). Se pone de manifiesto que la AF en niños de estas edades tiene un carácter intermitente, realizándose en secuencias o intervalos cortos que oscilan entre 1 y 2 min de duración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 261-268, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152238</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la distribución de la práctica de actividad física en alumnos de educación infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35172</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55045^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
