<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164272</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status of the patient on hemodialysis and associated factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Malnutrition in chronic dialysis patients has a high prevalence and important repercussion in morbidity and mortality. Since there are no previous studies in our service, we propose a study whose objective is to evaluate the nutritional status and associated factors. Material and Method: A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional study, in the second trimester of 2015, in patients in the hemodialysis program of a county hospital. Age, sex, Charlson&#146;s index, dialysis technique, BMI, time on dialysis, albumin, CRP, cholesterol and serum transferrin were recorded. Subjective global assessment and Score Malnutrition Inflammation were used as instrument. Results: We analyzed 35 patients, mean age was 72.2 years (SD: 11.8), 34.3% were women, BMI was 27.1 (SD: 4.9), Charlson index 6.4 (DS: 1.7), 77.1% were on conventional dialysis and 22.9% were on-line hemodiafiltration. Regarding the MIS test, 46% had good nutritional status and 54% were malnourished. According to the VGS, 66% had good nutritional status, 31% risk of malnutrition and 3% severe malnutrition. VGS was related to BMI (p: 0.02), creatinine (p: 0.001), total cholesterol (p: 0.02), and CRP (p: 0.01); and it was not related to age, time on hemodialysis, Charlson&#146;s index, transferrin and albumin (p&gt; 0.05). The Score Malnutrition Inflammation (MIS) was related to BMI (p: 0.002), Charlson&#146;s index (p: 0.01), creatinine (p: 0.009) and CRP (p: 0.02); not with age, time on hemodialysis, total cholesterol, transferrin and albumin (p&gt; 0.05). Conclusions: There is good correlation between the two tools and analytical parameters used. Patients in on-line hemodiafiltration have good nutritional status. There is no single parameter that evaluate nutrition. The inclusion of nutritional assessment is suggested given the high prevalence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manresa Traguany, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Gea, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Vilaseca, Lídia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Monge, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Zambrano, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chevarria Montesinos, Julio Leonel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La desnutrición en pacientes crónicos en diálisis tiene una alta prevalencia e importante repercusión en la morbimortalidad. Dado que no existen estudios previos en nuestro servicio, planteamos un estudio cuyo objetivo es evaluar el estado nutricional y los factores asociados. Material y Método: Estudio descriptivo, observacional, transversal, el segundo trimestre de 2015, en los pacientes en programa de hemodiálisis de un hospital comarcal. Se registró la edad, sexo, I. de Charlson, técnica de diálisis, IMC, tiempo en diálisis, albúmina, PCR, colesterol y transferrina séricas. Se utilizó como instrumento la Valoración global subjetiva y el Score Malnutrición Inflamación. Resultados: Se analizaron 35 pacientes, la edad media fue 72,2 años (DS: 11,8), 34,3% fueron mujeres, el IMC es 27,1 (DS: 4,9), I. de Charlson 6,4 (DS: 1,7), 77,1% hacían diálisis convencional y 22,9% hemodiafiltración en línea. Según el test MIS el 46% tenía buen estado nutricional y 54% estaba mal nutrido. Según la VGS 66% tenía buen estado nutricional, 31% riesgo de desnutrición y 3% desnutrición severa. La VGS se relaciona con el IMC (p: 0,02), creatinina (p: 0,001), colesterol total (p: 0,02) y PCR (p: 0,01); no con la edad, tiempo en hemodiálisis, I. Charlson, transferrina y albúmina(p&gt; 0,05). El Score Malnutrición Inflamación (MIS) se relaciona con el IMC (p: 0,002), I. Charlson (p: 0,01), creatinina (p: 0,009) y PCR (p: 0,02); no con la edad, tiempo en hemodiálisis, colesterol total, transferrina y albúmina (p&gt; 0,05). Conclusión: Existe buena correlación entre las dos herramientas y los parámetros analíticos utilizados. Los pacientes en hemodiafiltración en línea tienen buen estado nutricional. No existe un único parámetro que valore la nutrición. Se sugiere que es necesaria la valoración nutricional dada la alta prevalencia que existe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;20(2): 120-125, abr.-jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional del paciente en hemodiálisis y factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
