<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038910</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposition and sensitization to Tyrophagus putrescentiae in a allergic population to Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus in Huelva, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In this work we analyzed the allergological importance of Tyrophagus putrescentiae (Tp) in Huelva (SE Spain). We studied the level of exposition and the grade of sensitization to Tp in a group of patients sensitized to Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus (Dpt). The allergenic cross-reactivity between Dpt and Tp was determined by RAST inhibition.                 Methods and results: We analyzed house dust samples from the dwellings of allergic patients with documented Dpt sensitization. Skin test (ST), conjunctival provocation (CP) and/or specific IgE (RAST) to Tp were performed when Tp was identificated in the house dust sample of the patient. Among the 136 dust samples studied, Dpt was the most frequently identified mite species (94,8 %) and Tp was found in third position (41,1 %) after Glycyphagus domesticus (54,4 %). Among the 45 patients studied, 23 (51,1 %) presented, at least, two positive tests, 18 (40 %) were not sensitized to Tp and 4 (8,8 %) showed contradictory results. 26 patients (57,7 %) inhabited in urban areas and 19 (42,2 %) in rural regions. We determined specific IgE (RAST) to Tp in 25 patients, and the results were positive in 12, with only 7 with values greater than 2 kU/L. No significant correlation were found between IgE-antibody levels to Dpt and Tp. The RAST inhibition studies confirmed the low cross-reactivity between these mites and only in one patient Dpt partially inhibited the IgE-binding to Dpt extract.                 Conclusions: Tp was the second more frequent storage mite in the house dust samples from patients allergic to Dpt in Huelva. However, only half of the exposed patients were sensitized to Tp and the majority inhabited in urban areas. No significant correlation were found between IgE-antibody levels to Dpt and Tp. The RAST inhibition studies confirmed the low cross-reactivity between these mites</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lombardero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteaga, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barber, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: En este trabajo se analiza la importancia alergológica del Tyrophagus putrescentiae (Tp) en la provincia de Huelva, determinando, tanto el nivel de exposición como el grado de sensibilización a dicho ácaro en una población de alérgicos a Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus (Dpt). Además también se estudió la reactividad cruzada existente entre Dpt y Tp mediante RAST inhibición.                 Métodos y resultados: Se analizaron muestras de polvo de las viviendas de alérgicos a Dpt y en aquellos pacientes donde se identificó Tp se realizaron pruebas cutáneas (PC), prueba de provocación conjuntival (PCC) y/o determinación de IgE específica (RAST) a dicho ácaro. Se analizaron 136 muestras de polvo en las que Dpt fue el ácaro más frecuente (94,8 %) y Tp apareció en tercer lugar (41,1 %) tras Glycyphagus domesticus (54,4 %). De los 45 pacientes estudiados, en 23 (51,1 %), al menos dos pruebas fueron positivas, 18 (40 %) no mostraron sensibilización a Tp y en 4 (8,8 %) los datos no fueron concluyentes. Con respecto al hábitat domiciliario, 26 pacientes (57,7 %) vivían en ambiente urbano y 19 (42,2 %) en vivienda rural. Se realizó la determinación de IgE específica a Tp en 25 pacientes, siendo positiva en 12, de los cuales 7 presentaron valores superiores a 2 kU/L. No se encontró correlación significativa entre los títulos de IgE a Dpt y Tp. El experimento de RAST inhibición confirmó la baja reactividad cruzada entre ambos ácaros en los sueros analizados y sólo en un caso Dpt logró inhibir parcialmente la unión de IgE al extracto de Tp.                 Conclusiones: Tp es el segundo ácaro de almacén más identificado en las viviendas de los pacientes alérgicos a Dpt en la provincia de Huelva. Sin embargo, sólo la mitad de los pacientes expuestos son sensibles a dicho ácaro y viven en su mayoría en un ambiente urbano. No se ha encontrado una correlación significativa entre los títulos de IgE específica a Dpt y Tp y mediante RAST inhibición se confirma la baja reactividad cruzada entre ambos ácaros</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);33(4): 214-220, jul. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038910</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición y sensibilización a Tyrophagus putrescentiae en una población de alérgicos a Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus en Huelva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22205^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12551^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12551^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36539^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36535^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4450^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
