<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106219</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence-based nutritional recommendations for the prevention and treatment of overweight and obesity in adults (FESNAD-SEEDO consensus document). The role of diet in obesity prevention (II/III)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Se presenta un consenso de la Federación Española de Sociedades de Nutrición, Alimentación y Dietética (FESNAD) y la Sociedad Española para el Estudio de la Obesidad (SEEDO) sobre la dieta en la prevención del sobrepeso y la obesidad, tras efectuar una revisión sistemática de los datos de la literatura médica desde el 1 de enero de 1996 al 31 de enero de 2011. Las conclusiones obtenidas se han catalogado según niveles de evidencia. Se establecen unas recomendaciones clasificadas según grados que pueden servir de guía y orientación en el diseño de pautas alimentarias dirigidas a la prevención de la obesidad o el sobrepeso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Breton Lesmes, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basulto Marset, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiles Izquierdo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Formiguera Sala, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Salvadó, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gargallo Fernández Manuel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">This study is a consensus document of two Spanish scientific associations, FESNAD (Spanish Federation of Nutrition, Food and Dietetetic Associations) and SEEDO (Spanish Association for the Study of Obesity), about the role of the diet in the prevention and of overweight and obesity in adults. It is the result of a careful and systematic review of the data published in the medical literature from January 1st 1996 to January 31st 2011 concerning the role of the diet on obesity prevention. The conclusions obtained have been classified according several evidence levels. Subsequently, in agreement with these evidence levels, different degree recommendations are established. These recommendations could be potentially useful to design food guides as part of strategies to prevent overweight and obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(3): 800-832, mayo-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106219</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones nutricionales basadas en la evidencia para la prevención y el tratamiento del sobrepeso y la obesidad en adultos (consenso FESNAD-SEEDO). La dieta en el tratamiento de la obesidad (II/III)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
