<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77265</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical assessment of alcohol use and diagnosis of drinking pattern</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives. Alcohol misuse is associated with significant health and mental problems as well as with social and personal problems. Numerous clinical decisions will depend on the assessment of this consumption, regarding both the treatment of alcohol related disease and the management of alcohol use disorders. For these reasons it is important to make a proper assessment of alcohol consumption and determine the drinking pattern. Material and methods. We present a clinical case of a 28 year-old male patient admitted to our hospital due to acute pancreatitis. We review the history of alcohol consumption, the screening and diagnostics tests for alcohol depence, the proper terminology and the diagnostic criteria. Results. Alcohol dependence is assessed. We review alcohol-related disease and we perform a brief intervention to promote abstinence and patient&#146;s follow up after discharge. Conclusions. Quantification of alcohol consumption and diagnosis of drinking pattern is essential in clinical practice. It allows the identification of patients with risky consumption, to assess with drawl syndrome risk, and to perform a brief intervention aimed to decrease or cease alcohol use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosón Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silla Stoel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El consumo de alcohol se asocia con importantes problemas de salud, tanto físicos como mentales, así como con problemas sociales y personales. De la valoración que se realice de este consumo dependerán numerosas decisiones clínicas, tanto en lo referente al tratamiento de la patología asociada como al manejo del propio uso de alcohol. Por estos motivos es importante realizar una correcta valoración del consumo de alcohol y determinar el patrón de consumo. Material y métodos. Se presenta un caso clínico de un paciente de 28 años ingresado en nuestro centro por pancreatitis aguda. Se describe la historia clínica desde el punto de vista del uso del alcohol y se revisan los métodos y test de detección, la terminología más adecuada y los criterios diagnósticos. Resultados. Se explora la dependencia del alcohol. Se revisan las patologías relacionadas con el consumo y se realiza una intervención breve para conseguir abstinencia y seguimiento del paciente en un centro especializado tras el alta hospitalaria. Conclusiones. La cuantificación del consumo de alcohol y el diagnóstico del patrón de consumo es esencial en la práctica clínica, permite identificar aquellos pacientes con consumo de riesgo, valorar el riesgo de desarrollo de abstinencia o patología relacionada con el consumo de alcohol y realizar una intervención dirigida al cese de consumo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;11(3): 191-199, jul.-sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del consumo de alcoholy diagnóstico de patrón de consumo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
