<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140800</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New oral anticoagulants in dentist: Dabigatran</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Anticoagulation therapy is used in different conditions to prevent or treat thromboembolism. Anticoagulant drugs have also been associated with an increase in the risk of postoperative hemorrhage. The uS Food and Drug Administration and the European Medicines Agency recently recommended dabigatran etexilate as a possible treatment to prevent stroke and systemic embolism in people with atrial fibrillation. There is no need for routine coagulation monitoring in the same way as classic oral anticoagulants. The disadvantage is that dabigatran have no antidotes. Conclusions: The number of patients taking dabigatran is increasing. It is important that the dentist understands the mechanism of action of these drugs and how they may affect management of dental patients. As healthcare professionals we should also be aware of how and when to report adverse drug reactions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Curto Aguilera, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guinaldo Gil, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El tratamiento con anticoagulantes se aplica en diferentes condiciones para prevenir o tratar el tromboembolismo. Los fármacos anticoagulantes se asocian con un incremento en el riesgo de hemorragia postoperatoria. La uS Food and Drug Administration y la Agencia Europea del Medicamento recientemente han indicado el uso de dabigatran etexilato como posible tratamiento para prevenir los accidentes cerebrovasculares y las embolias sistémicas en pacientes con fibrilación auricular. No precisan la realización de estudios periódicos de monitorización en comparación con los clásicos anticoagulantes. un inconveniente es que dabigatran no presenta antídotos. Conclusiones: El número de pacientes a los que se les administra dabigatran se está incrementando. Es importante que los odontólogos comprendan el mecanismo de acción de estos fármacos y cómo pueden repercutir en el manejo de los pacientes. Como profesionales sanitarios deben ser conscientes de cómo y cuándo reportar las reacciones adversas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 51-54, ene.-abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos anticoagulantes orales en odontología: Dabigatran</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1752^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23521^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
