<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108316</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between quality of life, physical activity and cardiorespiratory fitness in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to explore the relationship between some domains of health related quality of life (HRQoL) in children with cardiorespiratory fitness, physical activity level, sedentary lifestyle (screen time) and the body mass index of a population of 302 children eleven and twelve years of age to determine whether physical fitness (cardiorespiratory fitness) is a key factor, to ensure the future quality of life of children. Children&#146;s health and Illness profile - Child edition - Parent Report Form - Spanish Edition - (CHIP-CE / PRF-Spanish edition) was used to measure HRQoL, the 20m run test for cardiorespiratory fitness, and the School Health Action, Planning and Evaluation (SHAPES) physical activity module was used to measure weekly physical activity and screen time. Parents reported height and weight. The results show a strong correlation between cardiorespiratory fitness and HRQoL, and screen time with HRQoL, but no correlation between HRQoL and physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borràs, Pere A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palou, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantallops, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponseti, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue explorar la relación entre algunos dominios de la calidad de vida, relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en niños, con el estado cardiorrespiratorio, el nivel de actividad física, el sedentarismo (tiempo de pantalla) y el índice de masa corporal de una población de 302 niños de once y doce años de edad, para determinar si la condición física (Fitness cardiorrespiratorio) es un factor clave en lugar de la actividad física, para garantizar la futura calidad de vida de los niños. El cuestionario sobre salud infantil y calidad de vida (CHIP-CE / PRF- edición española) se utilizó para medir la CVRS, El test de 20m de ida y vuelta para el fitness cardiorrespiratorio, El cuestionario de Salud Escolar de Acción, Planificación y Evaluación (SHAPES), módulo de actividad física, se utilizó para medir la actividad física semanal y el tiempo de pantalla. Los padres reportaron altura y peso. Los resultados muestran una fuerte correlación entre el fitness cardiovascular y la CVRS, y el tiempo de pantalla con la CVRS, pero no existe correlación entre CVRS y la actividad física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(2): 393-398, jul.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones entre calidad de vida, actividad física, sedentarismo y fitness cardiorrespiratorio en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
