<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048396</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stage pT= cystectomy: a review of our serie</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate the data of progression and survival in 43 patients who underwent cystectomy with stage pT0 according        to classification TNM-2002.        Matherials and methods: between 1988 and 2003 in our center had realized 420 cystectomies, 43 patients (10.2%) had not tumor        in the cystectomy specimen.        Results: In these 43 cases the initial clinical stage (in the transuretral resection of bladder) was T1 in 10 cases (23,3 %), T2 in        31 cases (72%) and T3 in 2 cases. As far as the degree 24 patients presented G2 (55.8%) and 19 (44.2%) were G3.        Median time from the transuretral resection to the cistectomy was of 44 days at a median follow-up of 89.3 months. Progressionfree        survival in the 43 patients was of 180,6 months, but during the follow-up it appeared progression in 7 patients, with disease        free survival at 36 months (3-126) ,since the date of the cistectomía.        During the follow up, 5 patients died. When we analyzed the cancer-specific survival according to tumor stage, for the T2 with        an average cancer-specific survival is of 180 months, decreasing to 35 months considerably for T3. Similar it happens with the        degree of differentiation, significantly diminishing as it advances the degree, with an average of cancer-specific survival for the        G3 at 122.6 months. In the same way it happens with pathological positive lymph nodes in the radical cistectomy , with a cancer-        specific survival of 188 months when it is N0 and of 54 months if the adenopathy was positive (N+).        Conclusion: In our experiencie urothelial carcinoma pT0 present a prolonged free period of disease (medium of 180 months). The        associated factors of risk to a smaller free period of disease are high degree of differentiation (G3, 116 months), the infiltration of        deep layers in the transuretral resection(T3, 32 months) and the ganglionary affectation (pN+ 45 months)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mallén Mateo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Martínez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Sanz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rioja Sanz, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Serrano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Regueriro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estudiar los datos de progresión y supervivencia en los 43 pacientes cistectomizados y catalogados de pT0 según        la clasificación TNM-2002.        Material y Métodos: Entre 1988 y 2003 se han realizado en nuestro centro 420 cistectomías, en 43 casos(10,2%) no se halló        tumor en la pieza anatomopatológica siendo éstos el núcleo de nuestro análisis.        Resultados: En estos 43 casos el estadio clínico inicial (en la resección transuretral de tumor vesical previa a la cistectomía)        fue T1 en 10 casos (23,3%), T2 en 31 casos (72%) y T3 en 2 casos. En cuanto al grado 24 pacientes presentaron G2 (55,8%) y        19 (44,2%) fueron G3. La mediana entre la de resección transuretral de tumor vesical diagnóstica (RTU de TM vesical) y la cistectomía        fue de 44 días y la mediana del seguimiento fue de 89,3 meses.        Progresión. La supervivencia libre de progresión en los 43 pacientes fue de 180,6 meses, pero durante el seguimiento apareció        progresión en 7 pacientes con una mediana de supervivencia libre de progresión desde la fecha de la cistectomía de 36 meses        (3-126).        Supervivencia cáncer-específica (SCE). Durante el seguimiento, 5 enfermos fallecieron, cuatro por la enfermedad y el quinto        por un cáncer de pulmón. Si analizamos la SCE, según la anatomía patológica de la RTU de tumor vesical previa, para los T2 la        media de SCE es de 180 meses, disminuyendo considerablemente para T3 hasta 35 meses. Similar ocurre con el grado de diferenciación        tumoral, disminuyendo significativamente a medida que avanza el grado, con una media de SCE para los G3 de122,6        meses. Del mismo modo ocurre con la afectación ganglionar en la pieza de la cistoprostatectomía radical, con una SCE de 188        meses cuando es N0 y de 54 meses si los ganglios son positivos (N+).        Conclusiones: En nuestra experiencia los tumores uroteliales pT0 presentan un periodo libre de enfermedad prolongada        (mediana de 180 meses).        Los factores de riesgo asociados a un menor periodo libre de enfermedad (PLE) son alto grado de diferenciación (G3, 116        meses), la infiltración de capas profundas en la RTU de tumor vesical(T3, 32 meses) y la afectación ganglionar (pN+) 45 meses</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(8): 763-771, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores de vejiga pT0 tras cistectomía radical: análisis de nuestra serie</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30423^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2971^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3063^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15152^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
