<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156611</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthy infant, with a feather on the scalp; the simplest explanation is usually the most likely</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present images of a healthy infant who was brought to our emergency department by his worried parents, who consulted concerned because 'a feather has grown in his head'. Physical examination was all normal, except from a small feather of approximately 3-4 mm, located on the right occipital- temporal region. No local inflammation, edema or erythema was appreciated in the area. After cleaning the area, the feather was removed entirely using tweezers. Evolution was good and the small wound healed without complications. It is possible that small feathers from duvets or pillows, may penetrate the baby skin or may be aspirated. Feathers may have sharp edges that easily penetrate the skin and can also cause different infections. This simple case highlights the importance of advising parents about the use of appropriate materials in the environment of the baby bedding (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Galarraga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Montero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos las imágenes de un lactante sano que acude a Urgencias traído por sus padres preocupados porque 'le ha salido una pluma en la cabeza'. La exploración física es normal, salvo por una pluma de aproximadamente unos 3-4 mm de longitud en región occipitotemporal derecha. No presenta inflamación local, edema ni eritema en la zona. Tras la limpieza y desinfección, mediante pinzas se extrae entera y sin incidencias. La evolución es buena y la herida cicatriza sin complicaciones. Es posible que pequeñas plumas de los rellenos de edredones o almohadas se fracturen y salgan al exterior, clavándose en el cuerpo del niño o pudiendo ser aspiradas. Las plumas pueden tener extremos afilados que penetran fácilmente en la piel del bebé, pudiendo además provocar infecciones. Este sencillo caso remarca la importancia de aconsejar a los padres sobre el uso de materiales adecuados en la ropa de cama del entorno del bebé (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;18(71): 263-265, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156611</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lactante sano con una pluma en el cuero cabelludo; la explicación más sencilla suele ser la más probable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4263^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
