<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040101</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: We present the activity of Preventive Medicine in the program of Tuberculosis and the quality of the tuberculosis contact investigation, using process management. Methods: We designed the process with 3 parts: a) flow chart a) responsibilities of the professionals, the documents and the protocols, and c) indicators to do the evaluation. We revised the activity of PM since 1995 to 2003. Results: We designed the flow chart with 3 levels: a) identification of cases of TB, b) identification of contacts and c) study of contacts. We selected indicators of identification of cases and contacts, time between identification of the case and notification to Public Health, time between first consult and Tuberculin skin test and chest radiograph, follow-up, and effectiveness. Main results: a) identification of cases: 100%; b) median of time to notification: 0 days; c) study of contacts of patients with sputum smear positive: over 90%; d) frequency of patients who completed treatment for latent TB infection: 93,3%; e) frequency of failure of follow-up has increased in the last two years, as the frequency of immigrant people (15,9% and 18,3% ). Conclusions: Management processes enabled doing a systematic analysis of the sequence of activities, identifying weak points, redesigning the work flow adapted to the needs, and doing a systematic evaluation of the quality of the activities. Main achievements: We have improved the Identification of cases (since 75% to 1005%), the median of the time of notification to Sanidad and the rate of study of contacts of patients with sputum smear positive (since: 60% to over 90%), and we have obtained a good rate of patients who completed treatment for latent TB infection (over 90%). The main improvement opportunities have been that we need to improve the coordination with Primary Health Care in order to improve the adherence to treatment for latent TB infection, over all to patients who probably will not finish the treatment, especially immigrant people</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la actividad de Medicina Preventiva (MP) en el programa de TB y la calidad del estudio de contactos, empleando como herramienta la gestión por procesos. Material y métodos: Se diseña el proceso en tres partes: a) diagrama de flujo; b) responsabilidades de los profesionales, documentos y protocolos; y c) indicadores a emplear para la evaluación. Se revisó la actividad de MP desde 1995 hasta el año 2003. Resultados: Se diseña el diagrama de flujo en tres niveles: a) captación de casos; b) captación de contactos; y c) estudio de contactos en MP. Se seleccionaron indicadores de cobertura de casos y contactos, demora en la declaración a Salud Pública, demora en la realización de estudios médicos, seguimiento, y efectividad. Principales resultados: a) captación de casos: 100%; b) mediana de retraso en la declaración: O días desde el año 2000; c) estudio de contactos de pacientes bacilíferos: mayor del 90%; d) porcentaje de pacientes que cumplen el tratamiento de infección tuberculosa latente (TIL): 93,3%; e) los porcentajes de pacientes perdidos en la consulta han aumentado en los 2 últimos años, coincidiendo con una mayor frecuencia de población inmigrante (15,9% y 18,3% respectivamente). Conclusiones: La gestión de procesos nos ha permitido un análisis sistemático de las actividades, detectar áreas de mejora, rediseñar el flujo de trabajo según las necesidades y realizar una evaluación sistemática de la calidad de la actividad. Principales logros obtenidos: mejora en la captación de casos (75% al 100%), así como la rapidez de la declaración a Sanidad, la tasa de estudios de contactos de casos bacilíferos (de 60% a más del 90%) y una buena tasa de cumplimento de TIL (superior al 90%). La mayor oportunidad de mejora detectada ha sido la coordinación con Atención Primaria para mejorar la adherencia al TIL de determinados grupos con riesgo de incumplimiento, especialmente población inmigrante</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;11(1): 17-24, ene.-mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040101</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La actividad del Servicio de Medicina Preventiva en tuberculosis como una gestión de procesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28897^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10112</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
