<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121025</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activity of albendazole and essential oils of peppermint (Mentha piperita) and chamomile (Matricaria chamomilla) against Anisakis type I</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: We have studied the possible synergistic activity of the essential oils of Mentha piperita and Matricaria chamomile against Anisakis type I. Materials and methods: the larvicidal activity of the mixture of essential oils was tested in vitro and in vivo, using as a reference the drug Albendazole and effectiveness measured through a statistical model. Results: The in vitro and in vivo experiments both evidenced that the larvicidal activity of essential oils, was higher than the Albendazole activity. In the in vitro assay, at concentrations of 250 and 187.5 &amp;#956;g/ml, the mortality was 100% with the mixture of essential oils while albendazole was ineffective at the concentrations studied. In the in vivo assay, the mixture of essential oils, was significantly more effective in the reduction of numbers of lesions with rats in comparison to albendazole treatments and control. Albendazole did not significantly reduce the percentage of lesions caused by larvae vs. control. Conclusion: Considering the results, we have come to the conclusion that the mixture of peppermint essential oils and chamomile could be used in the treatment/prophylaxis of human Anisakis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero López, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sánchez, Joaquina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Moll, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero López, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estudiar la posible actividad sinérgica de los aceites esenciales de Mentha piperita y Matricaria chamomilla frente Anisakis tipo I. Material y métodos: Se ensayó tanto in vitro como in vivo, la actividad larvicida de la mezcla de los aceites esenciales utilizando albendazol como fármaco de referencia y midiéndo su eficacia mediante un modelo estadístico. Resultados: En los ensayos in vitro, a las concentraciones de 250 y 187.5 &amp;#956;g/ml, la mortalidad de las larvas fue del 100% mientras que albendazol no mostró eficacia. In vivo, la mezcla de aceites esenciales fue más eficaz, reduciendo las lesiones en ratas en comparación con las tratadas con albendazol y control. Albendazol no redujo de forma significativa el porcentaje de lesiones producidas por las larvas frente al control. Conclusión: La mezcla de aceite esencial de menta y manzanilla podría ser candidata para su uso en el tratamiento/profilaxis de la anisakiasis humana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;55(1): 45-49, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad de albendazol y los aceites esenciales de menta (Mentha piperita) y manzanilla (Matricaria chamomilla) frente Anisakis tipo I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22585^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35856</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30848^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24511^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30847^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4417</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
