<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112355</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cecal perforation after paralytic ileus following a cesarean section: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cecal perforation following paralytic ileus after cesarean section is a rare but urgent complication. Familiarity with this complication is important. We report a case of cecal perforation following paralytic ileus after cesarean section. A 30-year-old primigravida who underwent cesarean section for breech presentation and severe oligohydramnios at 37+2 weeks&#146; gestation developed gastrointestinal symptoms diagnosed as paralytic ileus early in the postoperative period. The symptoms improved with conservative treatment. The patient subsequently showed worsening of the symptoms, with fever, abdominal pain and the presence of pneumoperitoneum on imaging studies. Emergency surgery was performed, confirming cecal perforation. The cecum was resected, with favorable outcome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lure Berregui, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobas Lozano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larraza Zandueta, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ferradas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasa Alvarado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La perforación cecal por íleo paralítico tras cesárea es un cuadro raro pero urgente que debemos conocer. Presentamos el caso de una perforación cecal tras íleo intestinal poscesárea. Primípara de 30 años a la que se realizó una cesárea por oligoamnios severo y presentación nalgas en la semana 37+2 y comenzó en el postoperatorio con un cuadro de clínica digestiva diagnosticado de íleo paralítico que mejoró con tratamiento conservador. Posteriormente empeoró, presentando fiebre, dolor abdominal y presencia de neumoperitoneo en las pruebas de imagen. Se intervino de urgencia confirmando la perforación cecal y procediendo a resecar el ciego. La evolución posterior fue favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);40(3): 131-133, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perforación cecal tras íleo paralítico poscesárea: caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2468^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7579^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
