<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164919</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lithium poisoning and a urinary tract infection due to Acinetobacter baumannii: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Even though it has been used in the treatment of bipolar affective disorder for more than 50 years lithium is a chemical element for which exact mechanism of action is still not clearly understood. Lithium poisoning is rare and mostly accidental, and its intensity varies from milder to more severe forms. There is a significant neurological involvement that depends on the total body burden of lithium and the initial clinical status of the patient. A clinical case is presented of a 63 year-old patient diagnosed with schizoaffective disorder and treated with lithium carbonate, who was admitted to hospital due to lithium poisoning with significant neurological repercussions. He also had a urinary infection due to an atypical microorganism with febrile peaks and impaired renal function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tudela Torras, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Longás, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomares Martínez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrós Roselló, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escandell García, Agustí</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El litio es un ion cuyo mecanismo de acción no está claro, pese a que se viene usando desde hace más de 50 años para el tratamiento de los trastornos afectivos. La intoxicación por litio es un cuadro poco frecuente, y en la mayor parte de los casos accidental, que va desde sus formas más leves a cuadros severos en los que se produce una afectación neurológica destacable, dependiendo de las cifras de litemia y del estado clínico inicial del paciente. En este artículo se presenta el caso clínico de un paciente de 63 años diagnosticado de trastorno esquizoafectivo y en tratamiento crónico con carbonato de litio que presenta como motivo de consulta e ingreso una intoxicación por litio con importante repercusión neurológica, a propósito de una infección urinaria por un microorganismo atípico, que cursa con picos febriles y afectación de la función renal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);24(2): 78-80, mayo-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección urinaria por Acinetobacter baumannii e intoxicación por litio. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55917^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8267^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8267^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36585^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36585^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
