<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77252</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The course of dissociation in the general population: a 3-year follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: There have been no previous general population studies on the stability of dissociative symptoms. The aim of this study was to examine the course of and the changes in dissociative symptoms and factors associated with these changes during a 3-year follow-up of a Finnish general population sample. Methods: The general population sample included a cohort of 1497 subjects. Dissociative symptoms were assessed with the Dissociative Experiences Scale (DES) and the DES-taxon (DES-T). Depressive symptoms and suicidal ideation were measured with the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI). The sample was categorized into low dissociators with DES scores less than 20 and high dissociators with DES scores of 20 or more. Results: At baseline, 98 subjects were high dissociators. On follow-up, 28 of them were still high dissociators, whereas among 70 subjects, the DES score declined below the cutoff score. During the follow-up period, 28 of 1399 subjects became new high dissociators, and constantly low dissociators consisted of 1371 of 1399 subjects. Dissociative taxon membership was detected in 39 subjects either at baseline or at follow-up, but only 4 of them met the criteria at both assessments. Stable high dissociation was associated with an increase in the BDI score on follow-up, baseline suicidal ideation, a younger age, a reduced working ability, and smoking. Risk factors for becoming a new high dissociator were an increase in the BDI score, a younger age at baseline, and a reduced working ability. Among the baseline high dissociators, recovery from high dissociation was associated with a decline in the BDI score at follow-up and with no suicidal thoughts, older age, and a good working ability at baseline. Conclusions: Only a small proportion of the general population had constantly high levels of dissociative symptoms. The stability of dissociative taxon membership was weaker than the stability of the continuous variables of dissociation. The dissociative experiences had a tendency to change, and these changes were associated with changes in the BDI scores. Further studies are needed to reveal the factors associated with the changes in dissociative symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Haatainen, Kaisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Honkalampi, Kirsi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Koivumaa-Honkanen, Heli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maaranen, Päivi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viinamäki, Heimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tanskanen, Antti</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hintikkaa, Jukka</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: No se han efectuado estudios previos en la población general sobre la estabilidad de los síntomas disociativos. El objetivo del presente estudio es examinar el curso y los cambios de los síntomas y factores disociativos relacionados con dichos cambios durante un seguimiento de 3 años de una muestra de la población general finlandesa. Método: La muestra de la población general incluyó una cohorte de 1.497 individuos. Los síntomas disociativos se evaluaron con la escala de experiencias disociativas (Dissociative Experiences Scale [DES]) y la categoría taxonómica DES-taxón (DES-t). Los síntomas depresivos y la ideación suicida se evaluaron con el cuestionario de depresión de Beck (Beck Depression Inventory [BDI]). La muestra se clasificó en disociadores bajos con puntuaciones obtenidas en la escala DES &lt; 20 y disociadores altos con puntuaciones &amp;#8805; 20. Resultados: En el periodo basal, 98 individuos eran disociadores altos. En el seguimiento, 28 de ellos seguían siendo disociadores altos, mientras que, entre 70 individuos, la puntuación DES disminuyó por debajo del punto de corte. Durante el periodo de seguimiento, 28 de 1.399 individuos llegaron a ser nuevos disociadores altos, y los disociadores constantemente bajos fueron 1.371 de 1.399 individuos. Los pertenecientes a la categoría taxonómica disociativa se detectaron en 39 individuos en el periodo basal o en el seguimiento, pero sólo 4 de ellos cumplieron los criterios en ambas evaluaciones. La disociación alta estable se asoció con un aumento de la puntuación obtenida en el BDI en el seguimiento, ideación suicida en el periodo basal, y una disminución de la capacidad para trabajar. Entre los disociadores altos en el periodo basal, el restablecimiento de la disociación alta se asoció con una disminución de la puntuación BDI en el seguimiento y con la ausencia de pensamientos suicidas, una edad más avanzada y una capacidad satisfactoria de trabajar en el periodo basal. Conclusiones: Sólo se identificaron niveles constantemente altos de síntomas disociativos en una proporción reducida de la población general. La estabilidad en la categoría taxonómica disociativa fue más débil que la de las variables continuas de disociación. Las experiencias disociativas tuvieron tendencia a cambiar, y estos cambios se asociaron con variaciones en la puntuación obtenida en el BDI. Se requieren estudios adicionales que revelen los factores relacionados con los cambios de los síntomas disociativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);16(2): 47-53, mar.-abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Curso de la disociación en la población general: estudio de seguimiento de 3 años de duración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
