<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-29455</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant middle cerebral artery infarction: medical or surgical treatment?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Post-ischemic brain edema occurs in 10-20% of cases of infarction of the middle cerebral artery and is the main cause of early death following a completed stroke. This complication, which is known as malignant middle cerebral artery infarction (MMCI), has a mortality rate of 78% when treated medically and thus requires a different management, such as a decompressive craniectomy. The main aim of this study is to review this procedure. Development. We conducted a search in the literature published over the last 20 years on this subject. Most of the studies are series of clinical cases with very favourable surgical outcomes. In non-random case-control studies the mortality rate was seen to decrease in the surgical group, and more so if the intervention was carried out early, as compared to the group that underwent medical treatment. Another study that compared decompressive craniectomy with hypothermia showed a higher survival rate in the surgical group. The post-surgery morbidity rate has not been determined, although it seems to be lower in infarction of the non-dominant hemisphere and in younger patients. Conclusions. The low degree of conclusiveness of the studies published to date only enables us to offer one practical opinion concerning this issue: decompressive craniectomy should be evaluated on an individual basis in patients with MMCI who do not respond to medical treatment. The final decision and the most appropriate moment to operate on the patient following the stroke must be based on the family&#146;s opinion and on the clinical features of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El edema cerebral posisquémico se presenta en el 10-20 por ciento de los infartos de la arteria cerebral media y es la principal causa de muerte precoz tras un infarto cerebral. Esta complicación, denominada infarto maligno de la arteria cerebral media (IMCM), tiene una mortalidad con terapia médica del 78 por ciento; por ello, requiere un abordaje distinto, como podría ser la craniectomía descompresiva. El objetivo principal de este trabajo es la revisiónde este procedimiento. Desarrollo. Realizamos una búsqueda bibliográfica de los artículos publicados en los últimos 20 años. La mayoría de ellos son series de casos clínicos con resultados quirúrgicos muy favorables. En los estudios de casos y controles no aleatorizados se observó una disminución de la mortalidad en el grupo quirúrgico, mayor si la cirugía era precoz, con respecto al de tratamiento médico. Otro trabajo, que comparó la hemicraniectomía descompresiva con la hipotermia mostró una mayor supervivencia en el grupo quirúrgico. No se ha establecido cuál es la morbilidad posquirúrgica, aunque ésta parece ser menor en infartos del hemisferio no dominante y pacientes más jóvenes. Conclusión. Actualmente, el bajo nivel de evidencia de los estudios publicados sólo nos permite dar, con respecto a este tema, una opinión práctica: la craniectomía descompresiva debe valorarse de forma individual en pacientes con IMCM que no responden al tratamiento médico. La decisión final y la elección del momento idóneo para operar al paciente tras el infarto deben basarse en la opinión de la familia y en las características clínicas del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(2): 145-150, ene. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infarto maligno de la arteria cerebral media: ¿tratamiento médico o quirúrgico?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Serrano Castro, PJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardado Santervás, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta Labrador, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arjona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-29455</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d34251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
