<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146020</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and public health implications of the CARDIORISC project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Adequate control of hypertension is known to be low in population and medical settings. However, physicians frequently misclassify patients&#146; blood pressure (BP) status at the office compared with ambulatory BP monitoring (ABPM). Information from ABPM is important for better knowledge of BP management in clinical practice, as well as for public health purposes. In this article, we present the burden of underestimation and overestimation of BP control, respectively, revealed by ABPM, by using the Spanish Society of Hypertension ABPM Registry, based on a large-scale network of Spanish physicians trained in ABPM (CARDIORISC project). Approximately 24% of treated hypertensive patients (with indications of ABPM) had BP controlled in the office, and approximately 52% were controlled according to daytime ABPM. These findings convey an important clinical implication, an encouraging message to clinicians, namely, that they are actually doing better than evidenced by office-based data. Furthermore, ABPM revealed that, at the office, BP control is underestimated by physicians in one out of every three hypertensive patients and is overestimated in one out of every 20 patients. In other words, the burden of undetected controlled and uncontrolled hypertension is substantial. Moreover, based on data from the CARDIORISC project, approximately 4 million hypertensives are estimated to be truly controlled (ABPM-based) instead of 2 million (office-based), while a further 4 million are actually uncontrolled instead of 6 million. Hence, physicians should be aware that assessment of BP control may well be inadequate if based on office BP measurement alone. Furthermore, knowledge of these data may contribute to more efficient planning of health resources, since many hypertensive patients previously believed to be uncontrolled are in fact controlled. However, the use of ABPM also identifies previously undetected uncontrolled hypertensive patients, who are at higher cardiovascular risk than estimated by office-based methods, thereby implying additional costs. ABPM is rarely available at clinics, and an effort is thus needed to extend its use and indication in the future. Fortunately, in general, ABPM is more cost-effective than office BP in the follow-up of hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Banegas, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Roca, GC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Es bien conocido que el control adecuado de la hipertensión arterial (HTA) es bajo en la población y en ámbitos clínicos. Sin embargo, los médicos con frecuencia clasifican mal la presión arterial (PA) de sus pacientes en la consulta si lo comparamos con la medición mediante monitorización ambulatoria de la PA (MAPA). Esta información es importante para el mejor conocimiento del manejo de la PA en la práctica clínica y también para la salud pública. En este artículo presentamos la carga de subestimación y de sobrestimación del control de la PA descubierta al utilizar MAPA basándonos en datos del proyecto CARDIORISC, que incluye una amplia red de médicos españoles entrenados en MAPA. Cerca del 24% de los hipertensos tratados (con indicaciones de MAPA) tenía su PA controlada en la consulta, y el 52% estaba controlado de acuerdo con la MAPA diurna. Esto permite deducir una importante implicación clínica, un mensaje estimulante para los clínicos: que lo están haciendo mejor de lo que se concluye de los datos procedentes de encuestas convencionales. Además, la MAPA reveló que, en la consulta, el control de la PA es subestimado en 1 de cada 3 hipertensos y sobrestimado en 1 de cada 20 pacientes. En otras palabras, la carga de HTA controlada y no controlada no detectada es notable. Además, CARDIORISC estima aproximadamente unos 4 millones de hipertensos realmente controlados (basados en MAPA), en vez de 2 millones (basados en la medición en la consulta), y otros 4 millones de hipertensos realmente no controlados, en vez de 6 millones. Por ello, el médico debería ser consciente de su posible valoración inadecuada del control de la PA cuando sólo utiliza medios convencionales en la consulta. Asimismo, el conocimiento de estos datos puede orientar la planificación más eficiente de los recursos del Sistema Nacional de Salud, ya que muchos hipertensos que previamente eran etiquetados como &#147;no controlados&#148; están de hecho controlados. Sin embargo, el uso de la MAPA también hace que emerjan sujetos hipertensos no controlados que se creían controlados, y estos pacientes están en un riesgo cardiovascular mayor que el estimado en la consulta e implican costes adicionales. La disponibilidad de la MAPA es escasa en la clínica y parece justificado extender su uso. Afortunadamente, en el seguimiento de la hipertensión, la MAPA parece ser, en general, más coste-efectiva que las determinaciones convencionales de la PA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;27(supl.1): 19-25, ene. 2010. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones clínicas y de salud pública del proyecto CARDIORISC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
