<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120162</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-123X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Defining the individual risk of caries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A method of classification of caries risk in children from 6 to 14 years old attending follow-up appointments at the Program of Oral Dental Health in Asturias, Spain. This classification provides tools that will assist clinical decision making. It also classifies the children as being in high, moderate, or low risk of experiencing caries which is an approximation to the individual as a whole, not only based on the dental status. It establishes preventive measures to be followed by all oral and dental health clinics in our health system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Barrero, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Grandgirard, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Arranz Monje, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco González, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Rodríguez, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Campos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el método de clasificación del riesgo de caries de los niños y niñas de 6 a 14 años que acuden a la revisión estomatológica prevista en el Programa de Salud Bucodental de Asturias, como herramienta de ayuda a la toma de decisiones clínicas. Esta clasificación en niños/as de riesgo alto, moderado o bajo de caries intenta una aproximación a la situación del individuo en su conjunto, no sólo a su situación dental, y establece unas actuaciones  preventivas y de seguimiento uniformes en todas las consultas desalud bucodental de nuestro sistema de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>RCOE;16(2): 115-121, jul. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120162</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Definición del riesgo individual de caries</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5593^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
