<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038283</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organic matter in comets and cometary dust</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Comets are primitive conglomerates of the solar system containing amixture of frozen gases, refractory grains, and carbonaceous particles rich in biogenicelements. The dramatic display of comets is mostly caused by a cloud of micrometer-sized dust particles that leave the comet nucleus when frozen gases sublimateas they approach the Sun. Analyses of cometary dust captured in the stratospheretogether with data obtained from space missions to comets have revealed the presence of a great variety of organic molecules. Since substantial amounts of cometary dust were gently deposited on Earth, their organic content could have played a major role in prebiotic processes prior to the appearance of microorganisms. This review discusses the description and implications for life of the organic content of comets and cometary dust</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorca, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cometas son conglomerados primitivos del sistema solar que contienen una mezcla de gases helados, granos refractarios y partículas carbonáceas ricas en elementos biogénicos. La apariencia espectacular de los cometas se debe principalmente a una nube de partículas micrométricas de polvo que abandonan el núcleo del cometa a medida que los gases helados se subliman al acercarse al Sol. Tanto el análisis de polvo cometario capturado en la estratosfera como las misiones espaciales a cometas han demostrado la presencia de una gran variedad de moléculas orgánicas. Dado que una cantidad importante de polvo cometario se depositó con suavidad en la Tierra, su contenido orgánico pudo desempeñar un papel importante en los procesos prebióticos previos a la aparición de microorganismos.  Esta revisión se centra en la descripción de los compuestos orgánicos de cometas y polvo cometario, así como su posible relación con el origen de la vida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(1): 5-12, mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Materia orgánica en cometas y polvo cometario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33153^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5218</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
