<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037207</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiofrequency catheter ablation of ventricular tachycardia in patients with an implantable defibrillator. Long-term follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The frequent occurrence of ventricular tachycardia can be a serious problem for patients with an implantable defibrillator, and may necessitate adjuvant antiarrhythmic therapy or radiofrequency catheter ablation. We analyzed the long-term results obtained with this latter therapy in patients suffering from frequent or continuous ventricular tachycardia. Patients and method. Eighteen ablation procedures were performed in 11 patients who had a defibrillator implanted because of previous syncopal ventricular tachycardia. All were men, aged 67.64 (5.87) years; 10 patients had had a myocardial infarction 15.50 (5.08) years earlier, and one suffered from arrhythmogenic right ventricular dysplasia. Results. Electrophysiologically, treatment was initially successful in 8 patients (72.73%). After a follow-up period of 39.10 (24.70) months, the number of defibrillator discharges decreased significantly in all patients, from 52.82(35.73) to 0.64 (1.03) (P=.001). During follow-up, ventricular tachycardia occurred in nine patients. In five, it took the same form as the ablated ventricular tachycardia. Six patients needed additional ablation procedures: two because of initial failure, three because of recurrence, and one because a different ventricular tachycardia occurred. In addition to the good electrophysiological results obtained, long-term clinical evolution was favorable in all patients. Conclusions. Radiofrequency ablation successfully disrupts frequent or continuous ventricular tachycardias and significantly reduces the defibrillator discharge rate even when ablation has failed electrophysiologically. It is particularly useful in these latter critical situations, in which other therapies are not sufficiently effective. Because our patients mainly had ischemic heart disease and were highly susceptible to new arrhythmias during follow up, ablation complemented rather than replaced the implantable defibrillator (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Teresa Galván, Eduardo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alzueta Rodríguez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montijano Cabrera, Ángela M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robledo Carmona, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrera Cordero, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La aparición de episodios frecuentes de taquicardia ventricular es un problema para los pacientes portadores de un desfibrilador implantable y en ocasiones requiere la combinación de un tratamiento antiarrítmico o una ablación con radiofrecuencia. Hemos analizado los resultados de esta técnica en el grupo de pacientes portadores de desfibrilador por taquicardia ventricular sincopal previa que presentaron taquicardia ventricular frecuente o incesante. Pacientes y método. Se realizaron 18 procedimientos de ablación en 11 varones de 67,64 ± 5,87 años con estas características; 10 pacientes habían presentado un infarto de miocardio 15,50 ± 5,08 años antes y otro tenía una displasia arritmogénica del ventrículo derecho. Hasta la ablación se produjeron 591,67 ± 1.020,34 episodios de taquicardia ventricular (rango, 7-2.604).Resultados. El éxito electrofisiológico inicial fue del72,73% (n = 8). Tras un seguimiento de 39,10 ± 24,70meses, el número de descargas del desfibrilador disminuyó significativamente en todos los pacientes y pasó de52,82 ± 35,73 (rango, 7-130) a 0,64 ± 1,03 (rango, 0-3)(p = 0,001); 9 pacientes presentaron posteriormente alguna taquicardia ventricular; 6 enfermos necesitaron nuevos intentos de ablación (2 por fracaso inicial, 3 por recurrencia y 1 por una taquicardia diferente). Con independencia del resultado electrofisiológico, todos los pacientes presentaron buena evolución clínica a largo plazo. Conclusiones. La ablación con radiofrecuencia interrumpe de manera eficaz la situación de taquicardia ventricular incesante o muy recurrente y reduce significativamente las descargas del desfibrilador, incluso tras el fracaso electrofisiológico, y es especialmente útil en estas situaciones críticas, cuando otras terapias resultan ineficaces o insuficientes. Dado que nuestros pacientes son mayoritariamente isquémicos y muy proclives a presentar nuevos eventos arrítmicos durante su seguimiento, la ablación no se consideró sustitutiva, sino complementaria del desfibrilador implantable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(5): 491-498, mayo 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037207</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento a largo plazo tras la ablación con radiofrecuencia de taquicardias ventriculares en pacientes portadores de un desfibrilador automático implantable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
