<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165794</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection and management of fetal growth disorders in Spain. National survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Knowing the current situation at the national level on different issues related to fetal growth restriction; specifically reference tables for percentile calculation and allocation, screening programs or diagnostic and management protocols. Material and methods: A Consensus Survey was conducted between SESEGO and SEMEPE, endorsed by SEGO and published on its official website for four months in 2015. It was possible to analyze the total of 171 forms representing all Communities and 41 provinces of Spain. In terms of the profile of the survey, we can establish that it reflects the behavior of large and teaching hospitals (80% with more than 1000 births/year, 85% with 11 or more specialists and 77% with MIR teaching). Hospitals belong to public system (91%) of the whole national territory (82%). Results: The survey allows the recognition of a wide variability in the clinical practice in matters as fundamental as the tables of fetal weight to be used, the allocation of the percentile for the evaluation of the fetal growth, the reference tables for the Doppler indices, the realization or not of a population growth restriction screening. How and at what gestational age should be programmed that screening or what types of interventions can optimize maternal and fetal prognosis. Conclusions: It seems inevitable and a priority that we must accept as a challenge the unification of criteria and recommendations in this field. Responders pronounce in a forceful and unequivocal manner that this role must be assumed and led by our Scientific Societies: SEGO, SESEGO, SEMEPE, etc (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puerto Navarro, Bienvenido</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina García, Francisca Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Astorquiza, Txantón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas Ramírez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la situación actual a nivel nacional sobre diferentes cuestiones relacionadas con el crecimiento intrauterino restringido, específicamente sobre tablas de referencia para el cálculo y asignación de percentil, programas de cribado o protocolos de diagnóstico, de manejo, etc. Material y métodos: se realizó una encuesta consensuada entre SESEGO y SEMEPE, avalada por SEGO y publicada en su web oficial durante cuatro meses en el año 2015. Fue posible analizar el total de los 171 formularios que representan a todas las Comunidades y 41 provincias de España. A la vista del perfil de la encuesta podemos establecer que refleja la manera de actuar de los hospitales grandes y docentes (80% con más de 1.000 partos/ año, 85% con 11 o más especialistas de plantilla y 77% con docencia MIR) del sistema público (91%) de todo el territorio nacional (82%). Resultados: permiten reconocer una amplia variabilidad en la práctica clínica en cuestiones tan fundamentales como las tablas de peso fetal a utilizar, la asignación del percentil para la evaluación del crecimiento fetal, las tablas de referencia para los índices Doppler, la realización o no de un cribado poblacional, cómo y a qué edad gestacional debería programarse, o qué tipo de intervenciones pueden optimizar el pronóstico materno y fetal. Conclusiones: parece ineludible y prioritario que debemos aceptar como un reto la unificación de criterios y recomendaciones en este campo. Los encuestados se pronuncian de manera contundente e inequívoca con que este papel debe ser asumido y liderado por nuestras Sociedades Científicas: SEGO, SESEGO, SEMEPE, etc (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);60(4): 306-313, jul.-ago. 2017. mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección y manejo de las alteraciones del crecimiento fetal en España. Encuesta nacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38859^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
