<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113459</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence and susceptibility of Campylobacter jejuni in pediatric patients: involvement in bacteremia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Invasive disease as a result Campylobacter spp. is rarely reported. Bloodstream infections have been reported in patients with immune deficiency or other serious underlying conditions. We conducted a prospective study to know the incidence of Campylobacter jejuni bacteremia in pediatric patients and its susceptibility to erythromycin and ciprofloxacin. Methods. The identification of Campylobacter isolates was based on routine culture methods. Antimicrobial susceptibility was performed using a disk diffusion method. Results. During April 2010-June 2012, at Hospital Niño Jesús of Madrid, Campylobacter spp. was isolated from 171 stool specimens in 154 patients. The median age was 2 years (3 months-21 year). One hundred and one (66%) isolates were identified as C. jejuni. Nine patients with enteritis due C. jejuni (9%) were immunocompromised. Erythromycin resistance was observed in 5% of the isolates. The resistance to ciprofloxacin was 88%. Blood cultures were obtained of 19 patients infected with C. jejuni (19%). Of these, one had C. jejuni bacteremia. During the study period, other episode of C. jejuni bacteremia was detected in one patient different without positive stool culture for C. jejuni (0.34% of all bloodstreams infections). Both patients were immunocompromised. Conclusions. Campylobacter spp. is an uncommon cause of bloodstream infection in our serie occurring in pediatric patients with immune deficiency as predisposing factor. In our institution, empirical use of fluoroquinolones for Campylobacter infections should not be recommended by the high rate of resistance. Moreover in our study the resistance to erythromycin is low, however is advisable its surveillance(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Abad, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Sanz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La infección por Campylobacter spp. raramente se asocia con enfermedad invasora, sucediendo en pacientes con enfermedad subyacente o inmunodeficiencia. Nuestro objetivo es conocer prospectivamente la incidencia de bacteriemia por Campylobacter jejuni así como su sensibilidad a eritromicina y ciprofloxacino en pacientes pediátricos. Métodos. La identificación de las cepas se realizó según métodos convencionales. La sensibilidad a eritromicina y ciprofloxacino se determinó mediante el método de difusión en disco. Resultados. Entre abril 2010 y junio 2012, en el Hospital Niño Jesús de Madrid, Campylobacter spp. fue aislado de 171 heces de 154 pacientes. Mediana de edad de 2 años (rango 3 meses-21 años). Ciento un aislados (66%) fueron identificados como C. jejuni. Nueve pacientes con aislamiento de C. jejuni (9%) eran inmunodeficientes. Cinco cepas de C. jejuni (5%) fueron resistentes a eritromicina y 89 a ciprofloxacino (88%). Se obtuvieron hemocultivos de 19 pacientes con aislamiento de C. jejuni en heces (19%). De éstos, uno tuvo bacteriemia por C. jejuni. En el periodo estudiado se aisló asimismo C. jejuni a partir sólo del hemocultivo en un paciente diferente. Estos dos bacteriemias por C. jejuni constituyen el 0,34% de las contabilizadas durante el periodo estudiado. Ambos pacientes eran inmunocomprometidos. Conclusiones. En nuestra serie, Campylobacter spp. es una causa infrecuente de bacteriemia, sucediendo en pacientes pediátricos con inmunodeficiencia como factor predisponente. En nuestro centro, el uso empírico de fluoroquinolonas para el tratamiento de la campilobacteriosis estaría desaconsejado dada la elevada tasa de resistencia. La resistencia a eritromicina es baja, sin bien es aconsejable su vigilancia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;26(2): 92-96, jun.2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y sensibilidad de Campylobacter jejuni en pacientes pediátricos: implicación en bacteriemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28882^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28882^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31182^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28027^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31182^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
