<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113914</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using montelukast in pediatric population: a study in three community pharmacies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of this paper is to analyze, from 3 community pharmacies, the use that is being made of montelukast in pedia tric population. Method: Observational study of montelukast prescriptions in children (&amp;#8804;15 years). A survey was done in 3 community pharmacies when dispensing this drug to collects patients&#146; data (age, dosing regimen, pathologies, duration of treatment, associated medication). Referral to doctor was done, when inappropriate treatment was detected, for review of drug treatment. Results: There were a total of 75 medical prescriptions. Children diagnosis of asthma was in only 36% and of those, 70% were receiving montelukast as initial therapy; 45% of them were not following the recommendations of the Spanish Guidelines for Asthma Management. 64% of children were not asthmatic and are receiving &#147;off-label&#148; montelukast (44% allergic rhinitis, 56% bronchiolitis): 21% of them were in a monotherapy regimen, and the rest, in combination with other drugs. Conclusions: A use of &#147;off-label&#148; montelukast is being made in children with allergic rhinitis or bronchiolitis, without asthma diagnosis, with no evidence of effectiveness in bronchiolitis. Inappropriate use could result in security issues for the patients. This study shows the need to provide independent information on the role of montelukast in therapeutic practice to health professionals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peris Molina, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Estrela, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D&#146;Ocon Navaza, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Úbeda Pascual, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar, desde tres farmacias comunitarias, el uso que se está haciendo de montelukast en la población pediátrica. Método: Estudio observacional de prescripción de montelukast realizado en tres ofi cinas de farmacia en niños (&amp;#8804;15 años) a los que se dispensó el fármaco; la recopilación de datos de los pacientes (edad, patologías, régimen de dosifi cación, duración del tratamiento, medicación asociada) se hizo a través de encuesta. Se remitió al médico cuando se detectó un tratamiento inadecuado, para su revisión. Resultados: Se recogieron un total de 75 prescripciones médicas. Sólo el 36% de los niños eran asmáticos; de ellos, al 70% se les pautó montelukast como terapia inicial, y el 45% no seguían las recomendaciones de la Guía Española para el Manejo del Asma. El 64% de los niños no eran asmáticos y estaban recibiendo montelukast fuera de indicación (off-label) (44% rinitis alérgica, 56% bronquiolitis), el 21% de ellos en monoterapia y el resto en combinación con otros fármacos. Conclusiones: Se está haciendo un uso fuera de indicación de montelukast en niños no asmáticos con rinitis alérgica o bronquiolitis, y en este último caso no existe evidencia de efectividad. El uso inadecuado podría acarrear problemas de seguridad para los pacientes. Se evidencia la necesidad de proporcionar información independiente a los profesionales sanitarios sobre el papel de montelukast en la terapéutica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;15(3): 88-94, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de montelukast en población pediátrica: estudio en tres farmacias comunitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d321^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28158^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33820^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
