<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60689</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and secular trend of Down syndrome in Asturias (Spain), 1990-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Down syndrome (DS) is the most frequent chromosomal abnormality and bears a severe associated morbidity. Our goal was to describe trends in the prevalence of DS in Asturias (Spain). Material and methods: Data from the Registry of Congenital Defects were analyzed, including births and induced abortions, between 1990 and 2004. Results: Out of a total 103 452 births, 356 chromosomal anomalies had been registered (176 births and 180 induced abortions) and there were 210 DS (119 live births, two stillbirths and 89 induced abortions). Total prevalence assessment showed an important upward trend over time in both cases. The prevalence of total chromosomal abnormalities increased from 22 cases per 10 000 births in 1990 to 48,6 in 2004 and the DS prevalence increased from 13 to 29,1. Furthermore, 63% of DS births presented one or more associated defects, cardiac and digestive tract defects being the most frequent. Conclusions: Changes in maternal age and prenatal screening have influenced DS prevalence and trends (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Toral, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riaño Galán, Isolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza Hevia, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Tenreiro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Dehli, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El síndrome de Down (SD) es la cromosomopatía más frecuente y se asocia a importante morbilidad. El objetivo de este estudio fue conocer la frecuencia de SD y otras cromosomopatías en Asturias y su evolución temporal. Material y método: Se analizaron los datos del Registro de Defectos Congénitos de Asturias (RDCA), de base poblacional, incluidos los casos diagnosticados en nacidos y abortos inducidos (AI) entre 1990 y 2004. Resultados: En 103.452 nacidos se registraron 356 cromosomopatías (176 nacidos y 180 AI), con una prevalencia total de 22 casos por 10.000 nacidos en 1990 y 48,6 en 2004. El SD fue la más frecuente, con 210 casos y una prevalencia total de 13 casos/10.000 en 1990 y 29,1 en 2004. Un 63% de los nacidos con SD presentaron anomalías asociadas. Conclusiones: Los cambios en la edad materna y los programas de diagnóstico prenatal han influido en la evolución temporal de prevalencia de SD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(15): 580-584, abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia del síndrome de Down en Asturias y tendencia temporal, 1990-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
