<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133326</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the toxic effects of phthalates on natural populations of Chironomus riparius (Diptera): implications for ecotoxicity studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chironomids, a genus of non-biting midges, are considered sentinel organisms for the evaluation of water quality and an outstanding model in Ecotoxicology for studying the effects of environmental pollutants. In contrast to its widespread use in studies with laboratory cultures, the use of natural populations (chronically exposed to complex mixtures of pollutants in their environment) is still uncommon to assess the usefulness of molecular biomarkers in studying the health of populations under multiple stress conditions. In Chironomus riparius, our results show that both bis (2-ethylhexyl) phthalate (DEHP) and benzyl butyl phthalate (BBP) cause rapid alterations in the activity of GST enzyme as well as in the expression profile of various genes related to cell stress response (hsp70 and hsc70), to the hormonal route (EcR and ERR) and to detoxification mechanisms (CYP4G). Both compounds cause different responses to these targets, especially in longer exposures, and have the ability to produce delayed toxicity. The alteration of the ecdysone hormone pathway in our experiments has special relevance, since it proves that both compounds are endocrine disruptors in insects. Finally, this study shows differences with previous data obtained with laboratory cultures in both the toxicity of these phthalates and the behavior of some targets, which emphasizes the need of carrying out studies with different populations to get a more realistic approach to the effects of contaminants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planelló, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morcillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Sande, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aquilino, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quironómidos, un género de mosquitos no picadores, son organismos centinela en la evaluación de la calidad de las aguas y un modelo de relevancia ecotoxicológica para el estudio de los efectos de contaminantes ambientales. Son todavía muy escasos los trabajos con poblaciones naturales de este organismo en los que se valore la utilidad de biomarcadores moleculares en el análisis de la salud de individuos expuestos a múltiples variables de estrés. Nuestros resultados muestran que exposiciones de larvas de poblaciones naturales de Chironomus riparius a di (2-etilhexil) ftalato (DEHP) y butil bencil ftalato (BBP), dos compuestos incluidos por la ECHA en la lista de sustancias de muy alta preocupación, provocan alteraciones rápidas en la expresión de diferentes genes relacionados con la respuesta celular de estrés (hsp70 y hsc70), la ruta hormonal (EcR y ERR) y los mecanismos de destoxicación (CYP4G), así como en la actividad enzimática de GST. Ambos compuestos provocan respuestas diferentes en estas dianas, especialmente en las exposiciones más prolongadas, y tienen la capacidad de producir efectos tóxicos retardados. Son de especial relevancia los resultados que muestran la alteración de la ruta hormonal de la ecdisona, confirmando la capacidad disruptora endocrina en insectos de estos ftalatos. Por último, existen diferencias respecto a datos previos obtenidos con larvas de laboratorio, tanto en la toxicidad de DEHP y BBP como en el comportamiento de algunas dianas, lo que acentúa la necesidad de llevar a cabo análisis con diferentes poblaciones para conseguir una aproximación más realista a los efectos de contaminantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;31(2): 176-186, jul.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de los efectos tóxicos de ftalatos sobre poblaciones naturales de Chironomus riparius (Diptera): implicaciones en estudios de ecotoxicidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38365^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4865^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38365^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11399^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2729^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11399^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11399^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38365^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2729^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25091^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4232^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25790^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
