<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043411</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical status, adherence to HAART and quality of life in HIV-infected patients receiving antiretroviral treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Quality of life is one of the most frequently used subjective measures in chronic health problems. The aim of this study is to analyze the association between clinical and therapeutic parameters, and 11 quality of life domains in HIV-infected patients. Methods. A cross-sectional survey of 320 patients on antiretroviral treatment was conducted in four Andalusian hospitals (Spain). A semi-structured questionnaire was administered by health care professionals. Health-related quality of life was assessed with the MOS-HIV questionnaire, an instrument designed specifically for HIV-infected patients. Results. Almost three-quarters of the population were men (73.4%); 35.6% had developed aids, and 88.1% were considered adherent to treatment. Patients with greater viral load presented lower quality of life scores for all the domains, except cognitive functioning. Patients who had developed aids showed poorer quality of life for 10 of the 11 domains. Patients with adequate adherence to antiretroviral treatment showed better quality of life for 10 domains. No statistically significant differences in the domain scores except for quality of life were found between patients with a treatment regimen including protease inhibitors and those without. Conclusion. The patient's clinical status and adherence affect not only survival, but also quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Causse-Prados, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Baño, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Pérez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Rico, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arco-Jiménez, Alfonso del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Gómez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada-Pardal, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ruz, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olry de Labry-Lima, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre-Lima, Javier de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasquau-Liaño, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La calidad de vida es uno de los métodos de evaluación subjetiva más utilizados en enfermedades de carácter crónico. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la asociación entre parámetros clínicos y terapéuticos y las 11 dimensiones de calidad de vida en pacientes infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). Métodos. Se realizó un estudio transversal con 320 pacientes en tratamiento antirretroviral de 4 hospitales andaluces. Se utilizó un cuestionario semiestructurado administrado por personal sanitario. La calidad de vida relacionada con la salud se midió a través del cuestionario MOS-HIV (Medical Outcomes Study HIV Health Survey), que es un instrumento específico para pacientes con VIH. Resultados. El 73,4% de los entrevistados eran varones, el 35,6% tenían sida y el 88,1% fue considerado adherente al tratamiento. Los pacientes con una mayor carga viral presentaron puntuaciones más bajas en todas las dimensiones de la calidad de vida, a excepción de la función cognitiva. Los pacientes con sida mostraron una peor calidad de vida en 10 de las 11 dimensiones. Aquéllos con una adherencia adecuada al tratamiento antirretroviral mostraron una mejor calidad de vida en 10 dimensiones. No se detectaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en las medias de las dimensiones del cuestionario MOS-HIV entre pacientes cuya combinación farmacológica incluía inhibidores de la proteasa y aquellos que no, a excepción de la dimensión de calidad de vida. Conclusión. El estado clínico y la adherencia del paciente no sólo afectan a su supervivencia, sino también a diferentes dimensiones de su calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(10): 581-585, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado clínico, adherencia al TARGA y calidad de vida en pacientes con infección por el VIH tratados con antirretrovirales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32319</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
