<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054615</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of warning against procrastination of thrombolysis in ischemic stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Fibrinolysis in stroke should be carried out as soon as possible, but delays occur for various reasons.    In the first 17 ischemic infarcts treated in our center we confirmed a tendency to exhaust the therapeutic window. We look now    at whether warnings against this tendency, without other logistical or organizational modifications, have had an impact on    delays. Patients and methods. Neurologists were encouraged to avoid procrastination. When we reached 51 treated patients,    we compared features and delay times between the first 17 (February, 2002 to June, 2004) and the 17 most recent cases    (October, 2005 to April, 2006). Non-parametric tests were used (significant if p &lt; 0.05). Results. Both groups were similar    clinically and demographically. The onset-arrival time lengthened (46 min vs. 75 min; p = 0.01) and scattered. The CTtreatment    time halved (57 min vs. 30 min; p = 0.001), with consequent shortening of the &#145;door-to-needle&#146; period (121 min vs.    90 min; p = 0.002). The arrival-CT time had remained constant (50 min vs. 53 min; p = 0.9), thus the total delay from onset    did not change significantly (165 min vs. 170 min; p = 0.7), and the inverse linear correlation between the onset-CT time and    the CT-treatment time weakened. Conclusions. Warnings against procrastination appear to be important in terms of shortening    the delays. The time used for clinical-radiologic evaluation (arrival through CT) &#150;about which there had been no action    taken&#150; had not been modified, but the time employed in the decision to treat (CT-treatment) and the &#145;door-to-needle&#146; time had    decreased appreciably. This effective compensatory reduction permitted treatment of late-arriving patients, such that although    the overall time from onset to treatment apparently was not modified, the actual treatment rate increased</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Pérez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestre-Moreno, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feria-Vilar, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saz-Saucedo, P. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiel-Navarro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Creus-Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnáiz-Urrutia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vatz, K. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La fibrinólisis del ictus isquémico debe llevarse a cabo cuanto antes; conocer las causas de retraso    permite su eventual corrección. En los primeros 17 casos que tratamos comprobamos que tendía a agotarse el período de ventana    terapéutica; evaluamos si las advertencias frente a ello, sin otras modificaciones logísticas u organizativas, han tenido    impacto en las demoras. Pacientes y métodos. Se estimuló la celeridad en el tratamiento. Con 51 pacientes tratados, comparamos    características y tiempos de demora en los primeros 17 casos (febrero de 2002 a junio de 2004) y en los 17 más recientes    (octubre de 2005 a abril de 2006), utilizando tests no paramétricos (significación si p &lt; 0,05). Resultados. Ambos grupos    son similares demográfica y clínicamente. El tiempo inicio-puerta se alargó (46 min frente a 75 min; p = 0,01) y dispersó. El    tiempo entre tomografía axial computarizada (TAC) y tratamiento se redujo a la mitad (57 min frente a 30 min; p = 0,001),    con el consecuente acortamiento del período &#145;puerta-aguja&#146; (121 min frente a 90 min; p = 0,002). El tiempo puerta-TAC se    mantuvo constante (50 min frente a 53 min; p = 0,9), y la demora total desde el inicio tampoco se modificó significativamente    (165 min frente a 170 min; p = 0,7); la correlación lineal inversa entre tiempo de inicio-TAC y tiempo TAC-tratamiento perdió    intensidad. Conclusiones. Las advertencias contra la procrastinación parecen haber sido eficaces para abreviar la toma    de decisión de tratar (TAC-tratamiento) y el tiempo &#145;puerta-aguja&#146;, mientras que el tiempo utilizado en la evaluación clinicorradiológica    (puerta-TAC), sobre el que no había habido actuaciones, no se modificó. Ello ha permitido realizar fibrinólisis    a pacientes que llegan más tarde; así, aunque el tiempo inicio-tratamiento aparentemente no cambió, se incrementó la    tasa de fibrinólisis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(11): 643-646, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de las advertencias contra la procrastinación sobre las demoras en la trombólisis del ictus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30438^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
