<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128249</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alteplase treatment for acute stroke 2007: an effective therapeutic option at our disposal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The greatest progress has been made in the research field based on the early arterial recanalization strategy in cerebral ischemia. Aim. To carry out a revision of stroke treatment with intravenous thrombolysis during the therapeutic window period covering the first three hours of evolution. The revision focuses on information provided by clinical trials, meta-analysis and open-label reports studies. Development. Clinical trials that study the use of alteplase in the acute stroke treatment, especially the two phase III clinical trials carried out by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke rt-PA Stroke Study Group, are described. A great deal of useful information has been provided through systematic revisions that analyze data on these treatment clinical trials jointly. Meta-analysis studies are described: the Pooled Analysis of ATLANTIS, ECASS and NINDS t-PA Stroke Trials, Cochrane Meta-analysis: Thrombolysis for Acute Ischemic Stroke. Community based studies, especially the SITS-MOST study, were revised, and their findings were compared with other open-label t-PA studies. Conclusions. t-PA is effective when administered in the first three hours of evolution of stroke in selected patients and under ideal conditions, and it may be beneficial, using the same selection criteria, in a therapeutic window of four and a half hours. The treatment is effective when applied as part of the daily clinical practice in our environment. This effectiveness does not disappear when extending its use to a large number of qualified hospitals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carneado Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saber, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El campo de investigación basado en la estrategia de la recanalización arterial temprana en la isquemia cerebral es en el que más se ha avanzado. Objetivo. Realizar una revisión sobre el tratamiento del infarto cerebral con trombólisis intravenosa en el período de ventana terapéutica de las tres primeras horas de evolución. Centrada en la información generada por los ensayos clínicos, los metaanálisis y los estudios poblacionales.  desarrollo. Describimos los ensayos clínicos que estudian el empleo de alteplasa en el tratamiento del infarto cerebral agudo, en especial los ensayos clínicos en fase III del National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke rt-PA Stroke Study Group. Se ha generado mucha información útil a través de revisiones sistemáticas que analizan de forma conjunta los datos de los ensayos clínicos sobre este tratamiento. Describimos los estudios de metaanálisis: el Pooled Analysis of ATLANTIS, ECASS and NINDS t-PA Stroke Trials, y el Cochrane Meta-Analysis: Thrombolysis for Acute Ischemic Stroke. Revisamos también los estudios poblacionales, en especial el estudio SITS-MOST, y comparamos sus hallazgos con los de estudios poblacionales previos. Conclusiones. El t-PA es eficaz administrado en las tres primeras horas de evolución del infarto cerebral en pacientes seleccionados y en condiciones idóneas, y pudiera ser beneficioso, utilizando los mismos criterios de selección, en una ventana terapéutica de cuatro horas y media. Es un tratamiento efectivo cuando se aplica como parte de la práctica clínica diaria en nuestro medio. Esta efectividad no se pierde al extender su uso a un número mayor de hospitales debidamente cualificados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;45(1): 42-52, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con alteplasa en el infarto cerebral agudo 2007: una opción terapéutica efectiva a nuestro alcance</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2586^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30438^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
