<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052762</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interpretation mistakes in statistical methods: their importance and some recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prior research has identified some of the most common misconceptions on how researchers interpret the results of significance tests. In this study, we examine the scope of these misconceptions in a sample of university professors and researchers from Spain on the basis of a short questionnaire. The obtained results provide important information: i) to prevent wrong interpretation from the data, ii) to correct the wrong use of statistical testing, iii) to suggest new ways of examining the data, and iv) to propose some modifications on the editorial criteria to publish scientific work</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monterde i Bort, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Llobel, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frías Navarro, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Trabajos empíricos previos han identificado las opiniones de los investigadores respecto de las pruebas de significación y de otros recursos estadísticos, algunas de estas opiniones resultan totalmente inaceptables. En esta investigación comprobamos el grado en que estos errores aparecen en una muestra española de profesores e investigadores de universidad mediante la aplicación de un cuestionario. Los datos obtenidos son importantes para: a) la prevención de interpretaciones inadecuadas; b) la corrección de usos incorrectos; c) el análisis de alternativas posibles; y d) proponer cambios editoriales en los criterios de publicación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(4): 848-856, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Errores de interpretación de los métodos estadísticos: importancia y recomendaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
