<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105986</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of dancing on Parkinson&#146;s disease patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Motor skill disorders are one of the most important symptoms and that which most affect the quality of life of Parkinson&#146;s Disease patients. Dance, as artistic and therapy activity, can help in the rehabilitation of neuromuscular disorders and motor skills. This review has aimed to make a comprehensive assessment of studies investigating whether dance favors the rehabilitation of Parkinson&#146;s Disease patients. A total of 13 trials with 384 participants were included. Four different styles of dance were evaluated. They showed favorable results on parameters such as physical function, balance, gait, fall risk and quality of life. Although there are few clinical trials, the analysis of the results suggest that dance can improve the rehabilitation of motor disorders since a decrease in the risk of falls because balance and gait are improved is observed. All of this help entail an improvement in the quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flórez García, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde Guijarro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones motoras son uno de los síntomas más importantes y que más afectan a la calidad de vida de los enfermos de Parkinson. La danza como práctica artística y terapéutica puede ayudar en la rehabilitación de alteraciones neuromusculares y motoras. El objetivo de esta revisión fue realizar una evaluación exhaustiva de estudios que investigaran acerca de si la danza favorece la rehabilitación de los enfermos de Parkinson. Se incluyeron 13 ensayos con 384 participantes y se evaluaron 4 estilos diferentes de danza, los cuales mostraron resultados favorables en parámetros como: función física, equilibrio, marcha, riesgo de caída y calidad de vida. A pesar de existir pocos ensayos clínicos, el análisis de los resultados surgiere que la danza puede mejorar la rehabilitación de alteraciones motoras, ya que se aprecia una disminución del riesgo de caída al mejorar el equilibrio y la marcha. Todo ello conllevaría una mejor calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(5): 216-224, sep. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105986</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la danza en los enfermos de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34318^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3633^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
