<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055241</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of hidden renal failure calculated through formulas on the degree of renal function in hypertense patients over 60 referred to out-patients for blood pressure monitoring</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To validate the Cockroft-Gault and the abbreviated Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formulas in a hypertense population aged over 60 and with blood pressure monitored in out-patients. To evaluate the prevalence of various stages of hidden chronic kidney disease in this population.                 Design. Descriptive study of validation of diagnostic tests.                 Setting. Urban primary care centre.                 Participants. A total of 113 patients over 60 (53.8% female) with hypertension and no history of chronic kidney disease, on whom blood pressure could be monitored in a 24-hour session.                 Main measurements. Calculation of the glomerular filtration rate. Validity parameters of diagnostic tests.                 Results. Renal clearance estimated in the Cockroft-Gault and MDRD equations was similar (77.9 mL/min and 76.9 mL/min, respectively). There was 37.3% prevalence of chronic kidney disease, using the Cockroft-Gault equation; and 27.0%, using the MDRD. The degree of agreement between the two equations was excellent in classifying patients with stage-2 chronic kidney disease (kappa index =0.9) and it was acceptable for stage-3 (kappa index =0.5). In both equations, validity indexes were acceptable for the presence of microalbuminuria as a manifestation of renal damage.                 Conclusions. There is a high prevalence of hidden chronic kidney disease in the hypertense population over 60 years old. Glomerular filtration should be determined systematically in these patients, even when their plasma creatinine figures are normal</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozuelos Estrada, Gerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Perera, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Herrera, Natalio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañón Barroso, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buitrago Ramírez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Martínez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Validar las fórmulas de Cockcroft-Gault y la abreviada del estudio Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) en la población hipertensa mayor de 60 años en la que se realiza medición ambulatoria de la presión arterial, y conocer la prevalencia de diferentes estadios de enfermedad renal crónica oculta en ese grupo de población.                 Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, de validación de pruebas diagnósticas.                 Emplazamiento. Atención primaria. Centro de salud urbano.                 Participantes. Un total de 113 pacientes mayores de 60 años (el 53,8% mujeres), hipertensos, sin historia de enfermedad renal crónica conocida y a quienes se les realizó una sesión de medición ambulatoria de presión arterial durante 24 h.                 Mediciones principales. Estimación del grado de filtración glomerular. Parámetros de validez de pruebas diagnósticas.                 Resultados. El aclaramiento renal estimado por las fórmulas de Cockroft-Gault y MDRD fue similar (77,9 y 76,9 ml/min, respectivamente). Se encontró una prevalencia de enfermedad renal crónica del 37,3% en la ecuación de Cockroft-Gault y del 27,0% en la de MDRD. El índice de concordancia de ambas ecuaciones fue excelente en la catalogación de los pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica en estadio 2 (kappa = 0,9) y aceptable (kappa = 0,5) para el estadio 3. Los índices de validez de las 2 ecuaciones son discretos frente a la presencia de microalbuminuria como manifestación de daño renal.                 Conclusiones. Hay una alta prevalencia de enfermedad renal crónica oculta en la población hipertensa mayor de 60 años. La estimación del filtrado glomerular debería realizarse sistemáticamente en esta población, aunque sus cifras de creatinina plasmática sean normales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;39(5): 247-253, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055241</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de insuficiencia renal oculta estimada mediante fórmulas de cálculo del grado de función renal en hipertensos mayores de 60 años, remitidos para medición ambulatoria de la presión arterial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
