<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166481</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prorenin and its receptor: the role of direct renin inhibition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent discovery of a (pro)renin receptor that binds both prorenin and renin has renewed interest in prorenin. Prorenin is the precursor of renin and is synthesized mainly in the juxtaglomerular apparatus, although it is also produced outside the kidney. In clinical conditions such as diabetes mellitus, high plasma levels of prorenin are observed to occur in association with microvascular damage. After binding to its receptor, prorenin undergoes nonproteolytic activation, which involves separation of the prosegment. Through this process the molecule acquires the ability to catalyze the production of angiotensin I from angiotensinogen. On the other hand, the binding of (pro)renin to its receptor induces the activation of a number of kinases involved in the differentiation of neuronal cells and in the production of fibrogenic cytokines and other mediators of tissue damage. As well as having an effect on the renin-angiotensinaldosterone system (RAAS), the (pro)renin receptor binds to vacuolar ATPase, which is involved in intracellular acidification and other processes vital for cell viability. Experimental studies with a synthetic peptide which is similar to part of the prorenin prosegment and which prevents prorenin binding with its receptor have produced conflicting findings. In some cases, the peptide has been effective in preventing or reducing diabetic nephropathy and cardiac fibrosis, while in others it has not. Direct renin inhibitors (DRIs) are able to bind to receptor-bound (pro)renin, thereby blocking its catalytic activity. Most studies have found no evidence that DRIs are able to suppress the noncatalytic (i.e. non-angiotensin-II-dependent) effects of the (pro)renin-receptor complex. There are still many unanswered questions about the role of prorenin in the production of both tissular and intracellular angiotensin II, about the intracellular effects induced by the binding of prorenin to its receptor, and about the importance of the (pro)renin receptor beyond its effect on the RAAS. Similarly, many questions have arisen about drugs that can block the (pro)renin receptor and about the effect of DRIs on the cellular implications of the interaction between (pro)renin and its receptor, whether dependent on or independent of angiotensin II (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles, Nicolás, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fernández, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El reciente descubrimiento de un receptor de (pro-)renina, al que se unen pro-renina y renina, ha renovado el interés por la pro-renina. Esta es el precursor de la renina sintetizada en el aparato yuxtaglomerular y se produce también extrarrenalmente. En situaciones clínicas como la diabetes, hay valores elevados de prorenina en plasma que se asocian a daño microvascular. Tras unirse al receptor, la pro-renina experimenta una activación no proteolítica que consiste en la separación del prosegmento, lo que le confiere capacidad catalítica para generar angiotensina I a partir del angiotensinógeno. Por otra parte, la unión de (pro-)renina al receptor induce la activación de cinasas que intervienen en la diferenciación celular (neuronal) y en la formación de citocinas fibrogénicas y otros mediadores de lesión tisular. Además de ejercer efectos relacionados con el sistema renina-angiotensina-aldosterona (SRAA), el receptor (pro-)renina se une a la ATPasa vacuolada, implicada en la acidificación intracelular y en otras importantes funciones para la viabilidad celular. El uso de un péptido similar a una parte del prosegmento de la pro-renina que impide la unión de pro-renina al receptor ha dado resultados discrepantes en modelos experimentales. En algunos casos, ha sido eficaz para prevenir o atenuar la nefropatía diabética y la fibrosis cardiaca y en otros no. Los inhibidores directos de la renina (IDR) tienen capacidad de unirse a la (pro-)renina ligada al receptor e impedir su acción catalítica. La mayoría de los estudios no evidencian la capacidad de los IDR para suprimir los efectos no catalíticos (no dependientes de la angiotensina II) del complejo (pro-)renina-receptor. Todavía hay muchos interrogantes sobre el papel de la pro-renina en la generación tisular e intracelular de la angiotensina II, los efectos intracelulares inducidos por la unión pro-renina-receptor y sobre la relevancia de la función del receptor (pro-)renina no relacionado con el SRA. Asimismo, surgen muchas cuestiones sobre posibles agentes que bloqueen el receptor (pro-)renina y sobre el efecto de los IDR en las consecuencias celulares, dependientes e independientes de la angiotensina II, de la interacción (pro-)renina-receptor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);11(supl.D): 8d-12d, 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166481</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La pro-renina y su receptor. Papel de la inhibición directa de la renina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12506^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22640^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38788^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29553^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
