<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044647</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of different pharmacological agents in the ex vivo proliferation of mesothelial cells obtained from the peritoneal effluent of patients treated with peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mesothelial cells (MC) are the first peritoneal membrane barrier in contact with    dialysate. The aim of this study was to analyze the in vitro capacity of different    pharmacological agents to modify the ex vivo proliferation of MC obtained from    the peritoneal effluent of patients treated with peritoneal dialysis (PD).    Material and Methods: Thirty cultures of MC taken from nocturnal peritoneal    effluent were performed. After identification, MC are subcultured in 24 multi-well    plates, adding the different exogenous agents. Proliferative capacity and cell morphology    were estimated on day 16th of culture. The agents evaluated were insulin,    IGF-1, tamoxifen, labetalol, carvedilol, enalapril and losartan.    Results: Insulin shows a dose-dependent effect on MC growth, with a limit that is    stimulated by the addition of fetal bovine serum (FBS). Concentrations higher than 100    &amp;#956;g/ml, are not associated with further growth, even with cell damage. In contrast, the    wide range of IGF-1 dose used did not affect to MC proliferation. Tamoxifen causes    negative effects on MC growth just a very high doses, not resembling doses in clinical    practice. Labetalol does not modify MC proliferation used under therapeutic calculated    range. However, concentrations higher than 40 &amp;#956;g/ml showed a negative influence    on growth, behaving as lethal doses that over 100 &amp;#956;g/ml. The addition of FBS    attenuates this effect. These effects were very similar to that caused by carvedilol addition.    Enalapril and losartan act as antiproliferative agents for MC. This effect is potentiated    with angiotensin II, reaching lethal concentrations increasing the dose.    In conclusion, mesothelial cell growth ex vivo taken from nocturnal peritoneal    effluent on PD patients is an useful tool to explore the effects of any pharmacological    agent on the biology of the cell of the peritoneum. The agents used had    any influence in the proliferation capacity of mesothelial cells</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Chacón, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vara, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selgas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Tomero, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrocha, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cirugeda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peso, G. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las células mesoteliales (CM) constituyen la primera barrera de la membrana    peritoneal con lo que contacta el líquido de diálisis. El objetivo de este estudio    es explorar in vitro la capacidad de determinados agentes farmacológicos de modificar    la proliferación ex vivo de las CM procedentes del efluente peritoneal de    pacientes tratados con diálisis peritoneal (DP).    Material y Métodos: Se han realizado 30 cultivos de CM procedentes de efluente    peritoneal nocturno. Las CM tras su identificación se subcultivan en placas de    24 pocillos a las que se añadieron los agentes seleccionados. La capacidad proliferativa    mesotelial se estimó en el día 16º a la vez que se evaluó la morfología    celular. Los agentes fueron seleccionados por su potencial influencia en las CM    y por ser utilizados en pacientes en DP. Se analizaron los efectos de la insulina,    IGF-1, tamoxifeno, labetalol, carvedilol, enalapril y losartán.    Resultados: La insulina ejerció un efecto dosis respuesta sobre el crecimiento    de CM aumentado por la concentración de suero bovino fetal (SBF). Este efecto    cesa a concentraciones de 100 &amp;#956;g/ml, observándose posteriormente un efecto negativo.    El IGF-1 no afectó a la proliferación mesotelial. El tamoxifeno solamente    afectó a la capacidad proliferativa mesotelial a concentraciones muy elevadas. El    labetalol no modifica el crecimiento mesotelial dentro del rango terapéutico, pero    a concentraciones de 40 &amp;#956;g/ml muestra una influencia negativa protegida por el    incremento en la concentración de SBF y a partir de 100 &amp;#956;g/ml produce un efecto    letal sobre la CM. Estos efectos se reproducen con el carvedilol. El enalapril y el losartán se comportaron como agentes antiproliferativos a nivel mesotelial. Este    efecto se acentúa en presencia de angiotensina II, siendo letal con dosis crecientes.    En conclusión el estudio de los cultivos de CM tomadas del efluente peritoneal    de pacientes en DP es útil para analizar los efectos sobre la proliferación celular    que pueden tener diferentes agentes administrados a estos pacientes. Los    agentes exógenos analizados influyen de diferente manera en la capacidad de proliferación    de las células mesoteliales, siendo recomendable investigar la relación    de estos hallazgos con lo que realmente ocurre in vivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(3): 243-251, mayo-jun. 2003. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044647</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de factores exógenos en la capacidad de proliferación ex vivo de las células mesoteliales obtenidas de efluente de pacientes tratados con diálisis peritoneal crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4926^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10719^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2512^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33405^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2490^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23324^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22114^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2487^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2487^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
