<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160209</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adopted children&#146;s emotion regulation: The role of parental attitudes and communication about adoption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Acknowledgement/rejection of adoption related differences and communication about adoption are two of the most important features of adoptive family dynamics. The present study focuses on the role played by these two variables on the adoptees&#146; emotion regulation. Method: The adoptive parents of 70 school-aged children participated in the study. Results: Data showed that participant parents perceived their adopted children&#146;s emotion regulation as adequate. In relation to family dynamics, acknowledgment of the adoption specificities significantly predicted the emotional lability/negativity of the adoptees, simultaneously mediated by the emotional quality of and the parental satisfaction with the communication about adoption. Furthermore, there was an indirect effect of early adversity on the adopted child&#146;s emotional lability. Conclusions: These findings provide new insight into adopted children&#146;s emotional development, highlighting the importance of the family environment and pre-adoption experiences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pacheco, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa-Ducharne, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la aceptación/rechazo de las características específicas de la adopción y la comunicación en torno a la adopción son dos de los rasgos más relevantes de la dinámica familiar adoptiva. En este estudio se analiza la relación entre el ambiente familiar adoptivo (definido en términos de esas dos variables) y la regulación emocional de niñas y niños adoptados. Método: se estudió a 70 madres o padres de niños adoptados, actualmente en edad escolar. Resultados: los datos indican que los adoptados de esta investigación, según la percepción de sus padres, presentan adecuadas puntuaciones en regulación emocional. Respecto a la dinámica familiar, el reconocimiento de diferencias predice de forma significativa la labilidad/negatividad emocional infantil a través de la mediación simultánea de la calidad emocional de y la satisfacción parental con la comunicación sobre la adopción. Además, se observó un efecto indirecto de la adversidad temprana sobre la labilidad emocional de los adoptados. Conclusiones: los resultados aportan nueva información sobre el desarrollo emocional de los adoptados, destacando la importancia del entorno familiar y de las experiencias pre-adoptivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(1): 49-54, feb. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160209</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regulación emocional en adoptados: el papel de las actitudes parentales y la comunicación sobre adopción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
