<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77160</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indoor air and bathing water pollution in indoor swimming pools in Guipúzcoa (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe levels of pollutants found in indoor swimming pools in Guipúzcoa (Basque Country, Spain), both in the bathing water and in the air, and to study the association between these pollutants and other variables related to ventilation systems and the use of installations.Methods: Of the 35 indoor swimming pools registered in Guipúzcoa, the 20 most frequently used by swimmers were studied. Each installation was sampled on two nonconsecutive days. Free and combined chlorine and trihalomethane levels were measured in the water, while total chlorine and chloroform levels were measured in the air. Carbon dioxide (CO2) was measured as an indicator of air renewal.Results: The average chlorine level in the air was 0.4mg/m3 and that of chloroform was 22¼g/m3. In all the swimming pools, free and combined chlorine levels were within the permitted values. The average chloroform level in bathing water was 13.7¼g/l. Chloroform levels in the air could be reasonably predicted (R2=0.85), the predictive factors being chloroform levels in the water, CO2 concentrations, and the number of bathers on the day of measurement.Conclusions: Levels of pollutants in the water and in the air of swimming pools in Guipúzcoa were lower than those reported in other studies. However, 20% of the installations exceeded the concentration of total chlorine in the air proposed as a reference value to protect swimmers carrying out intense activities (0.5mg/m) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goñi, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterrechea, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ulibarrena, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orruño, Ibai</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarluzea, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santa Marina, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artieda, Juncal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los niveles de contaminantes presentes en las piscinas cubiertas de Guipúzcoa, tanto en el agua de baño como en el aire, y estudiar la relación entre estos contaminantes y otras variables relacionadas con los sistemas de ventilación y el uso de las instalaciones. Métodos: De las 35 piscinas cubiertas registradas en Guipúzcoa se estudiaron las 20 más utilizadas por nadadores. Cada instalación se muestreó 2 días no consecutivos y se midieron los niveles de cloro libre y combinado y trihalometanos en el agua, así como los de cloro total y cloroformo en el aire. Como indicador de la renovación del aire se midió el dióxido de carbono (CO2).Resultados: El nivel medio de cloro en el aire fue de 0,4mg/m3 y el de cloroformo de 22¼g/m3. Los valores de cloro libre y combinado de todas las piscinas se mantuvieron dentro de los valores reglamentarios. El nivel medio de cloroformo del agua de baño fue de 13,7¼g/l. El valor del cloroformo del aire puede predecirse razonablemente (R2=0,85), y las variables predictoras son el cloroformo del agua, el CO2 y el número de bañistas del día.Conclusiones:Los niveles de contaminantes en el agua y en el aire de las piscinas de Guipúzcoa son inferiores a los descritos en otros estudios. Sin embargo, utilizando la concentración de 0,5mg/m3 de cloro total en aire, propuesta como valor de referencia para la protección de los nadadores con actividad intensa, un 20% de las instalaciones superarían dicho valor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(2): 115-120, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contaminación del aire interior y del agua de baño en piscinas cubiertas de Guipúzcoa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15280^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15097</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
