<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90328</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up programme dropouts in very low weight newborns before two years of age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The increase in survival rates of very low weight newborns (VLWN) and their neurodevelopmental morbidity has led to the implementation of follow-up programmes. The withdrawal from follow up limits the achievement of care goals and the validity of studies in this field. Goals: To assess the neurodevelopmental status, morbidity, social and economical data in the VLWN seen in our Neonatal Care Unit between 2002 and 2005 and lost in the follow up programme before the age of two, and compare these findings with the group who completed follow up. Patients: A total of 318 VLWN were included, of 53 had died. At the age of two, 215 had completed the monitoring visits (group S) and 50 had quit (group A).Methods: Using the SEN 1500 data base, and telephone interview of those parents who quit the programme. Results: A total of 30 cases were interviewed (Group R). Six patients had e been admitted to hospital due to respiratory illness; 26.7% had neurodevelopmental impairment (1 case, severe;1 case, moderate; 6 cases, mild) compared to 14% in group S (P &lt; 0.05). In group R, compared with group S, included more immigrants (40 vs. 14%), parental education level was lower and distance between home and hospital was greater (P &lt; 0.05). In group R, 57% of families had a low socioeconomic standard. Conclusions: The telephone interview allowed the clinical status of 60% of VLWN lost to follow up to be determined. Sequelae rate, mainly mild, was higher in the lost-to follow-up group. Some unfavourable social, economical and cultural factors could have influenced the interruption. It is advisable to develop strategies to prevent loss in the follow up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poó, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Krauel, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agut, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriondo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El aumento en la supervivencia de recién nacidos de muy bajo peso (RNMBP) y su morbilidad neuroevolutiva obliga a implementar programas de seguimiento, cuyo abandono limita la consecución de los objetivos asistenciales y la validez de los estudios. Objetivos: De los RNMBP asistidos entre 2002-2005 en nuestra unidad neonatal y perdidos en seguimiento antes de 2 años, se pretende conocer su neurodesarrollo, morbilidad post-alta y situación sociocultural y compararlos con los seguidos. Pacientes: Se asiste a 318 RNMBP, de los cuales 53 (16,6%) fallecen. A los 2 años completan el seguimiento 215 (grupo S) y 50 lo abandonan (grupo A).Métodos: Revisión de historias y bases de datos. Entrevista telefónica sistematizada a padres que abandonan seguimiento. Resultados: Se entrevista a 30 casos (grupo R) del grupo perdido. De ellos, 6 pacientes ingresan por patología respiratoria; el 26,7% (8 casos) presenta secuelas neuroevolutivas (1 grave; 1moderada; 6 leves) frente al 14% en el grupo S (p &lt; 0,05). El grupo R, comparado con el grupo S, presenta una mayor tasa de inmigración (14 vs 40%), menor nivel de estudios parental y mayor distancia casa-hospital (p &lt; 0,05). En el grupo R, el 57% tiene nivel socioeconómico bajo. Conclusiones: La entrevista telefónica ha permitido conocer la situación clínica del 60% de RNMBP perdidos en seguimiento. Hay una mayor tasa de secuelas en el grupo perdido, aunque en su mayoría son leves. Una serie de factores sociales, económicos y culturales desfavorableshan podido influir en el abandono. Conviene elaborar estrategias para evitar en lo posible pérdidas en el seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);74(5): 309-316, mayo 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abandonos en el seguimiento de recién nacidos de muy bajo peso antes de los 2 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32719^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
