<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048080</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural training in partner communication and correct condom use skills</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study assessed the effects of sexual communication and condom use skills training on 50 sexually active college students&#146; consistent condom use. In vivo sexual communication and condom use skills postintervention assessments showed that intervention group participants acquired the skills trained and were significantly better than control group participant in openly talking about sex (p&lt;.01), negotiating condom use (p&lt;.01) and correctly using it (p&lt;.001). The condom use indirect measures showed an increment on intervention group in condom use in the last sexual intercourse and consistent condom use, however, there was no statistical significance between groups in condom use for general sexual relationship (p=.869), the last sexual intercourse they recalled (p=.311), and consistent condom use (p=.082). Neither of the three trained target behavioral skills were correlated with any of the self-report condom use measures. Based on these findings this paper questions the validity of indirect measures of condom use and highlights the need to include behavioural measures and training of correct condom use and its relation to condom negotiation skills as part of any intervention program related to HIV/AIDS prevention</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barroso Villegas, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Montijo, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Pozo, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Campuzano, María de Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz González y Anaya, Eugenio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cervantes, Martha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frías Arroyo, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Rodríguez, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio evalúa los efectos de un entrenamiento conductual en habilidades de comunicación sexual en la pareja y uso correcto del condón sobre la consistencia en el uso del condón en una muestra de 50 estudiantes universitarios sexualmente activos. En la postevaluación de las variables medidas a través de la observación directa se encontró una ejecución significativamente más alta en el grupo de intervención que la obtenida en el grupo control en la habilidad para iniciar y mantener una conversación sobre sexualidad (p&lt;.01), negociar el uso del condón (p&lt;.01) y uso correcto del condón (p&lt;.001); en las medidas indirectas del uso de condón hubo un incremento intragrupo para el grupo experimental en el uso del condón en la última relación sexual y en su uso consistente, pero no hubo diferencias entre grupos en el uso del condón en las relaciones sexuales en general (p=.869), uso del condón en la última relación sexual (p=.311) y consistencia en el uso del condón (p=.082). Ninguna de las habilidades conductuales entrenadas se correlacionó con las medidas de autoinforme del uso del condón. Se cuestiona la validez de las medidas indirectas del uso del condón y se plantea la necesidad de incluir en los programas de prevención del VIH/SIDA la evaluación y entrenamiento de la habilidad conductual para usar correctamente el condón y su vinculación con la habilidad para negociarlo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;22(1): 60-71, jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento conductual en habilidades de comunicación sexual en la pareja y uso correcto del condón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
