<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106230</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alcoholic ketoacidosis and reversible neurological complications due to hypophosphataemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 57-year-old man with chronic alcoholism was admitted to our hospital due to disturbance of consciousness and polyradiculitis. Laboratory examination revealed metabolic acidosis, hypokalemia and hypophosphataemia. Alcoholic ketoacidosis is a common disorder in alcoholic patients. All patients present with a history of heavy alcohol misuse, preceding a bout of particularly excesive intake, which had been terminated by nausea, vomiting and abdominal pain. The most important laboratory results are: normal or low glucose level, metabolic acidosis with a raised anion GAP, low or absent blood alcohol level and urinary ketones. The greatest threats to patients are: hypovolemia, hypokaliemia, hypoglucemia and acidosis. Alcohol abuse may result in a wide range of electrolyte and acid-base disorders including hypophosphataemia, hypomagnesemia, hypocalcemia, hypokalemia, metabolic acidosis and respiratory alkalosis. Disturbance of consciousness in alcoholic patients is observed in several disorders, such drunkenness, Wernicke encephalopathy, alcohol withdrawal syndrome, central pontine myelinolysis, hepatic encephalopathy, hypoglucemia and electrolyte disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mato Mato, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández López, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bargo, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz Fernández, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Luis, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Vázquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un paciente varón de 57 años alcohólico ingresó en nuestro hospital por alteración del nivel de conciencia y polirradiculitis. En el estudio analítico aparecía acidosis metabólica, hipopotasemia e hipofosfatemia. La cetoacidosis alcohólica es frecuente en estos pacientes. Todos ellos se presentan con una historia de abuso del alcohol, con cese del consumo los días previos por la aparición de náuseas, vómitos y dolor abdominal. Los datos básicos de laboratorio son: glucemia normal o baja, acidosis metabólica con anión GAP elevado, ausencia de alcohol en sangre y cetonuria. Los mayores peligros son la hipovolemia, hipopotasemia, hipoglucemia y acidosis. El abuso del alcohol puede provocar un amplio rango de trastornos electrolíticos y del equilibrio ácido-base, incluyendo hipofosfatemia, hipomagnesemia, hipocalcemia, hipopotasemia, acidosis metabólica y alcalosis respiratoria. El deterioro del nivel de conciencia puede observarse en relación con intoxicación etílica aguda, encefalopatía de Wernicke, síndrome de abstinencia, mielinolisis central pontina, encefalopatía hepática, hipoglucemia y trastornos electrolíticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(3): 936-939, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106230</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cetoacidosis alcohólica y complicaciones neurológicas reversibles de la hipofosfatemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11565^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7186^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7830^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
