<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054078</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of nocturia and its impact on quality of sleep and quality of life in patient with benign prostatic hyperplasia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Nocturia is the main cause of insomnia or sleep interruption in adult men, which has a negative impact on        daily activities, quality of life (QoL) and quality of sleep (QoS).        The assessment of nocturia and its impact on QoL and QoS in patients suffering from benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) has        been poor in terms of clinical research, moreover there is a lack of specific methods to assess this impact.        Objetives: The objectives of BPH treatment should include the improvement of patient&#146;s QoL by controlling both diurnal and        nocturnal symptoms. In order to assess how nocturia affects QoL and also QoS, some specific tools, such as N-QoL questionnaire        or the number of Hours of Undisturbed Sleep (HUS), have been recently developed. Therefore, it would be interesting to        assess how nocturia reduction due to LUTS/BPH treatment can impact on some objective parameters such as HUS and also how        nocturia reduction improves QoS and QoL . This assessment should be developed during the application of pharmacological treatments        in clinical practice by means of these specific tools.        With the aim of tackling nocturia as an urologic problem in patients with LUTS/BPH, as well as knowing the physiology of        sleep and the effect of nocturia on the sleep and QoL, a meeting of expert urologists, that gathered about fifty specialists of all        around Spain, was held in Madrid. This article presents the main ideas and concepts exposed in this meeting.        Conclusions: Nocturia is a symptom with a high prevalence in older patients with STUI/BPH. The PreNoc study has showed        a Nocturia prevalence in Spain of 83% in patients &amp;#8805;60 years old diagnosed of BPH. Nocturia is the most bothersome symptom        in patients with STUI/BPH</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ristol Pont, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estivill, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batista Miranda, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Aramburu, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nocturia es la principal causa de insomnio o de interrupción del sueño en varones adultos, ello se traduce        en un efecto negativo sobre la actividad diaria, la calidad de vida y la calidad del sueño.        La valoración de la nocturia y su impacto en la Calidad de Vida (CdV) y en la Calidad del Sueño (CdS) en el paciente con HBP ha        sido escasa desde el punto de vista de la investigación clínica, además de la falta de métodos específicos que evaluasen dicho impacto.        Objetivos: Entre los objetivos del tratamiento de la HBP debería procurarse la mejora de la calidad de vida del paciente        mediante el control de los síntomas tanto de día como de noche.        Recientemente se han desarrollado instrumentos específicos para valorar la afectación de la nocturia en la CdV, como es el        cuestionario N-QoL, así como la afectación en la CdS, por medio de las horas de sueño ininterrumpido (HUS). Sería interesante        evaluar cómo la reducción de la nocturia originada por el tratamiento sobre los STUI/HBP puede influir en parámetros objetivos        como las HUS, y cómo se traduce en una mejora de la calidad del sueño y de la calidad de vida. Esta valoración debería realizarse,        con la ayuda de estas herramientas específicas, durante el desarrollo clínico de los tratamientos farmacológicos.        Con objeto de abordar la nocturia como problema urológico en los pacientes con STUI/HBP, así como de conocer la fisiología        del sueño y el efecto de la nocturia sobre el sueño y sobre la calidad de vida, se celebró en Madrid una reunión de expertos        urólogos que congregó a una cincuentena de profesionales de toda España. Este artículo presenta los principales conceptos        expuestos en esta reunión.        Conclusiones: La nocturia es un síntoma de alta prevalencia en la población masculina de edad avanzada con STUI / HBP.        El estudio PreNoc mostró una prevalencia de nocturia en España del 83% en pacientes &amp;#8805;60 años diagnosticados de HBP. La nocturia        es el síntoma más molesto en los pacientes con STUI/HBP</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(3): 262-269, mar.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la nocturia y su impacto en la calidad del sueño y en la calidad de vida en el paciente con hiperplasia benigna de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11582^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
