<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110281</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do anesthetic techniques influence postoperative outcomes? Part II</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The knowledge of the influence of anesthetic techniques in postoperative outcomes has opened a large field of research in recent years. In this second part, we review some of the major controversies arising from the literature on the impact of anesthetic techniques on postoperative outcomes in 6 areas: postoperative cognitive dysfunction, chronic postoperative pain, cancer recurrence, postoperative nausea/vomiting, surgical outcomes, and resources utilization. The development of protective and preventive anesthetic strategies against short and long-term postoperative complications will probably occupy an important role in our daily anesthetic practice. Dynamic postoperative pain control has been confirmed as one of the basic requirements of accelerated postoperative recovery programs («fast-track surgery»), and it is also a preventive factor for development of chronic postoperative pain. The weight of anesthetic technique on postoperative immunosuppression is to be defined. The potential influence of anesthesia on cancer recurrence, is a highly controversial area of research. The classic pattern of perioperative fluid therapy may increase postoperative complications. On the other hand, the maintenance of normoglycemia and normothermia was associated with a decreased postoperative morbidity. The high volume of surgical procedures means that the adequacy of human, organizational and technological resources have a major impact on overall costs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conocer hasta qué punto nuestras técnicas anestésicas pueden modificar los resultados postoperatorios ha abierto en los últimos años un gran campo de investigación. En esta segunda parte, revisamos las principales controversias que plantea la literatura sobre el impacto de las técnicas anestésicas en los resultados postoperatorios, en 6 áreas principales: disfunción cognitiva postoperatoria, dolor crónico postoperatorio, recurrencia oncológica, náuseas/vómitos postoperatorios, resultados quirúrgicos y consumo de recursos. El desarrollo de estrategias anestésicas protectoras y preventivas frente a complicaciones postoperatorias a corto y largo plazo ocupará probablemente un papel importante en nuestra práctica anestésica diaria. El control del dolor dinámico postoperatorio es uno de los requisitos básicos de los programas de recuperación postoperatoria acelerada (cirugía fast-track). Además es un factor preventivo del desarrollo de dolor crónico postoperatorio. El peso de la técnica anestésica en la inmunosupresión postoperatoria está pendiente de definir. La posibilidad de que la anestesia influya en la recurrencia oncológica, es un área de investigación muy controvertida. Las pautas clásicas de fluidoterapia pueden incrementar las complicaciones postoperatorias. Por otro lado, el mantenimiento de la normoglucemia y de la normotermia se relaciona con una disminución de la morbilidad postoperatoria. El gran volumen de intervenciones quirúrgicas hace que la adecuación de los recursos humanos, organizativos y tecnológicos tenga un gran impacto en los costes totales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(2): 93-102, feb. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110281</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Influyen las técnicas anestésicas en los resultados postoperatorios? Parte II</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33763^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33763^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33763</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
