<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108601</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to treatment, emotional state and quality of life in patients with end-stage renal disease undergoing dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: A low rate of adherence to treatment is a widespread problem of great clinical relevance among dialysis patients. The objective of the present study is to determine the relationship between adherence, emotional state (depression, anxiety, and perceived stress), and healthrelated quality of life (HRQOL) in renal patients undergoing dialysis. Method: Two patient groups (30 in hemodialysis and 31 in peritoneal dialysis) participated in this study. We evaluated aspects of adherence, depression, anxiety, perceived stress, and HRQOL with self-report and standardized instruments. Results: Peritoneal dialysis patients reported significantly higher levels of adherence to treatment and better HRQOL in Physical Function and Bodily Pain domains. Depression level is associated with HRQOL indicators. We did not find any differences regarding specifi c adherence to antihypertensive and phosphate binder drugs or in psychological variables depending on the modality of dialysis. Patients with adherence to antihypertensive drugs show better physical HRQOL. The predictors of HRQOL in dialysis patients were: work, gender and depression. Conclusions: Our results suggest that the modality of dialysis does not differentially affect the emotional state or specific adherence to drugs, but it is nevertheless related to their overall adherence to treatment and to their HRQOL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Selgas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remor, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Llana, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la escasa adhesión al tratamiento y un estado psicológico negativo constituyen potenciales factores de riesgo para la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) de los pacientes en diálisis. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue estudiar las relaciones entre adhesión, estado emocional (depresión, ansiedad y estrés percibido) y CVRS en pacientes en hemodiálisis y diálisis peritoneal. Método: participaron dos grupos de pacientes (30 en hemodiálisis y 31 en diálisis peritoneal). Evaluación mediante autoinformes e instrumentos estandarizados. Resultados: los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal informaron de niveles significativamente más altos de adhesión y mejor CVRS en función física y dolor corporal. La depresión se relaciona de manera signifi cativa con la CVRS. No encontramos diferencias en adhesión específica a fármacos hipotensores y quelantes del fósforo ni en las variables psicológicas en función de la modalidad de diálisis. Al analizar la muestra en conjunto los pacientes adherentes a los hipotensores tienen mejor CVRS física. Los predictores de CVRS en pacientes en diálisis fueron: trabajo, género y depresión. Conclusiones: nuestros resultados sugieren que la modalidad de diálisis no afecta al estado emocional ni a la adhesión específica a fármacos, pero sí está asociada al grado de adhesión global al tratamiento y CVRS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(1): 79-86, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adhesión al tratamiento, estado emocional y calidad de vida en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica en tratamiento con diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
