<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047773</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of an educational programme for the use of inhalation devices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the work presented in this article was to set up a patient education programme in a hospitalon the use of inhalation devices and to evaluate their efficacy after completion of the programme.Methodology: A survey was carried out for each inhalation model, evaluating the degree of understandingof each and one of the stages on the use of the inhaler and the degree of compliance witheach of these stages. Follow up visits were performed at 1, 3 and 6 months from the procedure. Asatisfaction survey was administered at the end of the study.Results: 42 patients were included in the study, of which 18 completed the entire follow up period.69% (n=29) used the pressurised cartridge case. 78% (N=33) had a single inhaler during the therapy.Mean time using the inhalation device was 2.7 years.95% (n=40) of the patients used the device incorrectly at admission. The inhalation technique waseven worse in cases where the pressurised cartridge case inhaler was used. 95% (n=17) of thepatients that completed the follow up period were applying the right technique at the end of thetraining period.Conclusions: The incorrect use of this type of inhalers is rather high in our setting, making nursingintervention for patient teaching purposes necessary. Patient education has been shown to be effectiveto improve the application technique of the inhaler and to improve the understanding and controlthe patient has over the treatment. It is important to include the main carer into the education programme</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego Maniques, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escriba Sanchos, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del trabajo que se presenta en este artículo fue poner en marcha en un hospital un programade educación de los pacientes sobre el uso de los inhaladores y evaluar su efectividad al finalizarel mismo.Metodología: se utilizó una encuesta según modelo de inhalador en la que se valora el grado de conocimientosde cada una de las etapas del uso del inhalador y el grado de cumplimentación con cadauna de ellas. El seguimiento se realizó al mes, tres y seis meses de la intervención. Al final del estudiose pasó encuesta de satisfacción.Resultados: participaron 42 pacientes y terminaron el seguimiento completo 18. El 69% (n=29) utilizabael inhalador de Cartucho Presurizado. El 78,6% (n=33) tenía un único inhalador en el tratamiento.La media de años de utilización del tratamiento vía inhalatoria era de 2,7.El 95% (n=40) de los pacientes realizaba la técnica de forma incorrecta al ingreso. Se dio una peortécnica inhalatoria con el uso del Cartucho Presurizado. El 95% (n=17) de los pacientes que hicieronel seguimiento completo realizaron la técnica correctamente al final del programa de entrenamiento.Conclusiones: el uso incorrecto de este tipo de inhaladores es muy elevado en nuestro medio, lo quehace necesaria la intervención enfermera de educación sanitaria de los pacientes. Ésta se demuestraeficaz para mejorar la técnica de aplicación del inhalador y mejora los conocimientos y el control deltratamiento en el paciente. Es importante integrar al cuidador principal en el programa educativo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(6): 10-14, jul. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa educativo para el uso de dispositivos inhalatorios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19256^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
