<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91767</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conduct disorders in children and adolescent. Clinical, social and school interventions, and improvement proposals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Problematic behavior generates a strong demand for attention by child and juvenile mental health services. This paper presents the results obtained by a multidisciplinary work group created with two objectives. To discuss current clinical, social and school approaches in Tarragona concerning conduct disorders in childhood and adolescence, and to agree on proposals for future interventions so as to improve clinical evolution, prognosis and psychosocial adoptions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrufat, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Griñó, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alet, Dolor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Záforas, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, Jana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masana, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralba, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canela, Asumpció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Mª Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferran, Josep Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casaus, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La problemática conductual supone una parte significativa de la demanda de atención en salud mental infantil y juvenil. Presentamos los resultados de la experiencia de creación de un grupo de trabajo multidisciplinar que se constituyó con dos objetivos. Discutir sobre el abordaje clínico, social y escolar en Tarragona de los trastornos de conducta en la infancia y en la adolescencia: así como consensuar propuestas de intervención futuras que podrían mejorar tanto evolución como pronóstico de la psicopatología y las situaciones de riesgo social presente en estos menores y sus familias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(17): 93-99, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno de conducta en niños y adolescentes. Abordaje clínico social, escolar y propuestas de mejora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
