<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93841</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of the incidence of bacteraemia related to the haemodialysis catheter: bioconnectrs versus direct connection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare hemodialysis catheterrelated bacteremia rate between bioconectors use and direct connection. Methodology: Comparative, retrospective and cross-sectional study over 2 consecutive years (one year with direct connection &#150; 2009 February to 2010 February - and 1 year using bioconectors Tego® -2010 March to 2011 March-) in hemodialysis patients in our unit with a permanent catheter as vascular access. Catheters connection and disconnection protocol was the same during the study period, except for the disinfecting solution used: iodine povidone was using in direct connection, and 2% chlorhexidine was using with bioconectors. Catheterrelated bacteremia was defined as onset of fever with a positive blood culture in the absence of another infection source. Results: 69 patients were studied: 36 during direct connection period and 33 during use bioconectors period. Six patients were studied during both periods. Bacteremia rate during direct connection period was 24.6/1000 catheters-day (9 bacteremia), while during the using bioconectors period, bacteremia rate was 5.47/1000 catheters-day (2 bacteremia) (p = 0.036). Staphylococcus aureus (3 patients) and staphylococcus coagulase negative (3 patients) were the most common infectious agents during direct connection period. Conclusions: Use of bioconectors significantly decreases the rate of bacteremia catheter-related in hemodialysis patients versus direct connection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente Jiménez, M. Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelayo Alonso, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo Sánchez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz Alonso, Rosa Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarguren Rodríguez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Begines Ramírez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menezo Viadero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Garmilla, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola García, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Nates, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepa García, Hortensia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Tordable, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar la tasa de bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter de hemodiálisis entre el uso de bioconectores y la conexión directa. Metodología: Estudio retrospectivo comparativo transversal durante un periodo de 2 años consecutivos (1 año con conexión directa &#150; Febrero 2009 a Febrero 2010- y 1 año utilizando bioconectores Tego® -Marzo 2010 a Marzo de 2011- ) en los pacientes en hemodiálisis de nuestra unidad que portaban un catéter como acceso vascular permanente. El protocolo de conexión y desconexión de los catéteres durante el periodo de estudio fue el mismo, a excepción de la solución de desinfección empleada: povidona iodada en la conexión directa y clorhexidina al 2% usando bioconectores. Se definió como bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter la aparición de fiebre junto con un hemocultivo positivo, en ausencia de otro foco de infección. Resultados: Se estudiaron 69 pacientes: 36 durante el periodo de conexión directa y 33 durante el periodo del uso de bioconectores. Seis pacientes fueron estudiados durante ambos periodos. La tasa de bacteriemia durante el periodo de conexión directa fue de 24,6 bacteriemias/1000 catéteres-día (9 bacteriemias), mientras que durante el periodo de uso de bioconectores fue de 5,47 bacteriemias/1000 catéteres-día (2 bacteriemias), (p= 0,036). El microorganismo causal más común durante el periodo de conexión directa fue el Staphyloccocus aureus (3 pacientes) junto con el Staphyloccocus coagulasa negativo (3 pacientes). Conclusiones: El uso de bioconectores disminuye de forma significativa la tasa de bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter de hemodiálisis frente a la conexión directa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;14(4): 230-235, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93841</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de incidencia de bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter de hemodiálisis: bioconectores frente a conexión directa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11644^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2755^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
