<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150815</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing interventions for patients with erectile dysfunction after radical prostatectomy: an integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to identify nursing interventions for patients undergoing radical prostatectomy. This is an integrative review, guided by the question 'What are the nursing interventions directed to patients with erectile dysfunction after radical prostatectomy?', held on the databases PubMed, Web of Science, CINAHL, SCOPUS, Cochrane Library, LILACS and on the list of references of selected articles. The final sample was comprised of 10 papers; 43 nursing interventions were identified and grouped in 10 categories. The nursing interventions for patients with erectile dysfunction after radical prostatectomy focused on the education regarding the nature of erectile dysfunction, treatment and sexuality; besides strengthening the involvement of partners during the process of coping with and treating the dysfunction. These interventions may be useful so that nurses can act during the follow-up of these patients, providing better quality of life and well-being (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Apoloni Eduardo, Aline Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves Napoleão, Anamaria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos de Carvalho, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo identificar las intervenciones de enfermería en pacientes sometidos a prostatectomía radical. Se trata de una revisión integradora guiada por la pregunta '¿Cuáles son las intervenciones de enfermería dirigidas a pacientes con disfunción eréctil después de una prostatectomía radical?' buscado en PubMed, Web of Science, CINAHL, Scopus, Cochrane Library, LILACS y en la lista de las referencias de los artículos seleccionados. Compusieron la muestra final 10 artículos y 43 intervenciones de enfermería fueron identificadas y agrupadas en 10 categorías. Las intervenciones de enfermería para pacientes con disfunción eréctil después de prostatectomía radical se centraron en la educación sobre la naturaleza de la disfunción eréctil, el tratamiento y la sexualidad; además de fortalecer el compromiso de las esposas durante el proceso de abordaje y tratamiento de la disfunción. Estas intervenciones pueden ser útiles para que las enfermeras puedan actuar durante el seguimiento de estos pacientes, proporcionando una mejor calidad de vida y bienestar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(42): 424-439, abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones de enfermería en pacientes con disfunción eréctil después de prostatectomía radical: una revisión integral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
