<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109750</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SpaceAnalysis of breast and cervix cancer morbimortality. Villa Clara. Cuba. 2004-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Breast and cervix cancers continues being a problem of health, in spite of the existence of prevention and precocius diagnosis programs, and for not existing in our county similar studies, its decide to realized this investigations to identify space and temporal space conglomerate that allow us the analysis of breast and cervix cancer morbimortality in Villa Clara. Methods: observational descriptive study to detection space and temporal space of incidence andmortality, using the statistical technique of temporal-space exploration (SatScan programs v .7.01), the sample embraced the entirety of patients diagnosed during the year 2004, to those that were carried out pursuit in the 5 serial years to the diagnosis, until the closing of the year 2009. Results: the breast cancer showed agreement in the results so much space as temporal-space with a risk of suffering the illness of 1.63 and 1.91 respectively, the municipalities that conformed significant conglomerates, were located toward the center and northeast of the county, headed by Santa Clara the municipality provincial head. The cervix cancer evidenced from the temporary point of view the diagnosis of prospective 100 cases of 68.8 during themonths ofMarch to July of the 2004. The study temporal-space showed a conglomerate of incidence in the municipalities located to the northeast of the county, the women that live in these areas have 3.46 times more risk of presenting this illness that those of the rest of the county. Conclusions: the presence of significant conglomerates so much was shown space as temporal-space, of the areas of more risk of to make sick for breast and cervix cancers. Not existing of mortality and late diagnosis conglomerates(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Batista Hernández, Norma E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Fleites, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegret Rodriguez, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El cáncer de mama y el de cérvix continúan siendo un problema de salud, a pesar de la existencia de programas de prevención y de diagnóstico precoz. Por no existir en nuestra provincia estudios similares, se decidió realizar esta investigación, con el objetivo de identificar conglomerados espaciales y/o espacio-temporales que permitan el análisis de la morbimortalidad por cáncer de mama y cérvix en la provincia Villa Clara. Métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo, focalizado en la detección de conglomerados espaciales y espacio-temporales de la incidencia y mortalidad del cáncer de mama y cérvix en Villa Clara, utilizando la técnica estadística de exploración espacio-temporal (programa SatScan v .7.01). La muestra abarcó la totalidad de mujeres diagnosticadas durante el año 2004 y de ellas las fallecidas hasta el cierre del año 2009. Resultados: El cáncer de mama mostró concordancia en los resultados tanto espaciales como espacio-temporales con un riesgo de padecer la enfermedad de 1,63 y 1,91 respectivamente, los municipios que conformaron conglomerados significativos se ubicaron hacia el centro y noreste de la provincia, encabezados por Santa Clara, cabecera provincial. El cáncer de cérvix evidenció desde el punto de vista temporal el diagnóstico de 100 casos frente a 68,8 esperados durante los meses de marzo a julio del 2004. El estudio espacio-temporal mostró un conglomerado de incidencia en los municipios ubicados al noreste de la provincia. El riesgo relativo de presentar la enfermedad para las mujeres que vivían en estas zonas fue 3,46 frente a las del resto de la provincia. Conclusiones: Se mostró la presencia de conglomerados estadísticamente significativos tanto espaciales como espacio-temporales en las áreas de mayor riesgo de enfermar por estos cánceres. No hubo conglomerados de muertes y diagnósticos tardíos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(1): 49-57, ene.-feb.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109750</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis espacial de la morbimortalidad del cáncer de mama y cérvix. Villaclara. Cuba. 2004-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27804^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
