<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90288</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compliance with antiretroviral treatment in HIV/AIDS patients on a methadone maintenance program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent advances in &#147;Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapies&#148; (HAART), aimed at controlling and preventing the spreading of HIV/AIDS, have improved the quality of life and life expectancies of many patients with this fatal disease. Nevertheless, a significant number of difficulties persist, such as the existence of individuals from disadvantaged groups, that traditionally have had difficulty accessing high-quality health care in some countries, who have not benefited from these treatments. Adverse drug reactions and non compliance with treatment regimens increase the problems for the control of the disease. This work reviews studies on compliance with antiretroviral treatments regimens in injection drug users. We briefly went over the changes and improvements in HIV/AIDS and specialized drug addiction management services in the developed world and analyzed the relationship between HAART compliance and some psychosocial and clinical variables: anxiety, depression, stress, social support, self-efficacy, self-effort, and drug use. Finally, our review study suggests broad future intervention and research lines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almendros, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ladero, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrobles, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orejudo, Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances recientes observados en los &#147;Tratamientos Antirretrovirales de Gran Actividad&#148; (TARGA), destinados a controlar e impedir el avance del VIH/SIDA, han supuesto una mejora importante en la calidad y expectativas de vida de muchos pacientes con dicha enfermedad. A pesar de ello, persisten algunas dificultades para conseguir el control de la enfermedad, tales como las limitaciones de acceso a los tratamientos en algunos países, las inherentes al consumo de cualquier fármaco (problemas de absorción, toxicidad...) y el abandono del tratamiento por parte de los pacientes. En este trabajo se lleva a cabo una revisión sobre la adhesión a la terapia antirretroviral en población drogodependiente. Se realiza un somero análisis de los cambios y mejoras experimentados en el mundo occidental en relación con el VIH/SIDA y en los servicios de atención especializada a las adicciones y se analizan las relaciones existentes entre la adhesión a la TARGA y algunas variables psicosociales y clínicas: ansiedad, depresión, estrés, apoyo social, autoeficacia, autoesfuerzo y consumo de drogas. Finalmente, se extraen determinadas conclusiones y se sugieren algunas líneas de intervención y de investigación futuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(2): 302-310, mayo-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La adhesión al tratamiento antirretroviral en pacientes VIH+ en programa de mantenimiento con metadona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
