<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049230</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New aspects on inflammation in allergic diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Allergic disease has currently reached epidemic proportions, with a high percentage of individuals in the developed world exhibiting an allergic response after exposure to some common environmental factors. Although new strategies for the treatment and management of allergic diseases have decreased the mortality rate, a high percentage of affected persons still require frequent hospitalization and experience decreased quality of life.         Methods: An internet-based literature search was performed for recent contributions on the underlying mechanisms provoking an allergic response and their potential for therapeutic approaches.         Results: Novel concepts on allergic responses have emerged: allergic disease may result from an imbalance between allergen activation of regulatory T cells and effector T helper 2 cells (Th2), a process in which dendritic cells are key players. Cytokines such as interleukin (IL)-6, IL-21, IL-25, and human thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP) seem to be important contributors in allergic processes. New data on IgE effector responses and on the IgE-independent mechanisms involved in allergic reactions have resolved some unanswered questions about these reactions.         Conclusions: These new findings on allergic diseases have important implications for diagnosis and management, with potential improvements in prevention and treatment, which could provide a cure in the future</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero Vega, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Las enfermedades alérgicas han alcanzado proporciones epidémicas, con un alto porcentaje de individuos en el mundo desarrollado que presentan una respuesta alérgica después de la exposición a algún factor ambiental común. Aunque las nuevas estrategias terapéuticas y de control de la enfermedad han conseguido disminuir la tasa de mortalidad, un alto porcentaje de personas afectadas todavía requieren hospitalización y sufren un deterioro de la calidad de vida.         Métodos: Búsqueda por Internet de publicaciones recientes sobre los mecanismos que intervienen en la respuesta alérgica y su potencial contribución a la terapéutica.         Resultados: Ha surgido un nuevo concepto de la enfermedad: la enfermedad alérgica es el resultado de un equilibrio inapropiado entre la activación por el alergeno de las células T reguladoras y las células efectoras Th2, un proceso en el que las células dendríticas juegan un papel clave. Citocinas tales como la IL-6, IL-21, IL-25 y la linfopoyetina estromal tímica humana (TSLP) parecen ser contribuidos importantes en el proceso alérgico. Nuevos datos sobre los mecanismos de la respuesta IgE y sobre los independientes de la IgE implicados en las reacciones alérgicas, han resuelto algunas de las incógnitas de la enfermedad.         Conclusiones: Estos nuevos hallazgos sobre la patología alérgica tienen implicaciones importantes para el diagnóstico y control de la enfermedad, y prometen una mejora en su prevención y tratamiento, lo que en un futuro podría con tribuir a la curación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);34(4): 156-170, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049230</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos aspectos de la inflamación en las enfermedades alérgicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32318^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22205^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8579^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32004^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7292^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32005^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22205^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
