<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61600</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">-1131 T&gt;C polymorphism of the apolipoprotein A5 gene promoter alters the binding of NRF2 (nuclear respiratory factor 2) and decreases promoter activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Postprandial triglycerides (TG) have been established as an independent risk factor for atherosclerosis, even though the role of fasting TG in the pathogenesis of this disease remains controversial. Recently, apolipoprotein AV (ApoAV) has been identified as a key player in TG metabolism. The ¿1131 T&gt;C polymorphism in the ApoA5 gene promoter has been associated with changes in plasma triglyceride and ApoAV levels. Our objective was the functional analysis of the SNP ¿1131 T&gt;C located on ApoA5 promoter to clarify his effect on ApoA5 expression. Material and methods. In order to test if this SNP influences promoter function, we have performed reporter gene assays. Our results indicated that the promoter carrying the T allele is stronger than its C- allele variant. Additionally electrophoretic ¿ mobility shift assays showed that the variant also produces a change in a NRF-2 binding site. Conclusions. Together, these results suggest that a change in the activity of ApoA5 promoter could be responsible for the increases in plasma TG levels associated with the C allele (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rey, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordovás, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pampín, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bailo, Bibiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El papel que desempeñan los triglicéridos (TG) ingeridos en la dieta en la aparición de aterosclerosis es controvertido. Sin embargo, recientemente se ha descrito que los valores de TG en estado posprandial son un factor de riesgo independiente para la aparición de esta enfermedad. Recientemente, se ha identificado la apolipoproteína (Apo) AV como una proteína clave en la regulación del metabolismo de los TG. El polimorfismo ¿1131 T&gt;C del gen de la ApoA5 se ha asociado con cambios en los valores plasmáticos de TG y de ApoAV. El objetivo de este trabajo fue determinar el papel del polimorfismo ¿1131 T&gt;C en la expresión del gen ApoA5. Material y métodos. Con el fin de estudiar la influencia de este single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) en la expresión de este promotor, se han utilizado construcciones de genes reporteros de ambos alelos. Mediante experimentos de retardo en gel se demostró que este polimorfismo también altera la secuencia de unión a NRF-2. Conclusiones. Nuestros resultados indicaron que la actividad del promotor de ApoA5 que porta la variante T del SNP ¿1131 T&gt;C es mayor que la del promotor que lleva el alelo C. Además, este cambio de nucleótido se traduce en un cambio de afinidad proteínas-ácido desoxirribonucleico. Estos resultados indican que un cambio en la actividad del promotor del gen ApoA5 podría ser la causa del incremento de los valores plasmáticos de TG asociados con el alelo C (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);21(3): 115-120, mayo-jun. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El polimorfismo -1131 T&gt;C del promotor del gen de la apolipoproteína A5 altera la unión de NRF2 (nuclear respiratory factor-2) y disminuye la actividad del promotor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34583^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1060^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
