<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126508</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurses of the nationalist side during the spanish civil war. An approach to the situation through the book "Princesas del martirio" (Concha Espina)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Concha Espina writes the book Princesas del Martirio at the turn of the 40s, in the last century. This is a book in honour of three nurses, who were killed during the Spanish Civil War. The three nurses, who were voluntaries of The Red Cross in Astorga (León), were called to attend the sick and injured people in Puerto de Somiedo (Asturias), in October 1936. Involuntarily, they found themselves involved in a Bolshevik incident, were taken prisoners and finally shot. In this paper, we draw the inspiration from this book, which allow us to reconstruct what we think would be the likely image of the "ideal nurse" of the nationalist side during the Spanish Civil War. The method we use is based on the presentation and analysis of the original text, were we mainly focus on the aspects related to the image of nursing. We interpret the evidence provided taking into account the socio-political situation at that time. Due to the importance that other elements might have in helping to reconstruct the image of the nationalist nurses during the Spanish Civil War -such as poems, monuments or streets with names related to the three nurses-, we have taken them into account, so that we can provide a more general and accurate idea of the relationship between ideology and professional acknowledgment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andina Díaz, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Concha Espina escribió a principios de los años cuarenta del pasado siglo un libro titulado Princesas del Martirio, para recordar la hazaña y homenajear a unas particulares "mártires de la Guerra Civil española". Sus protagonistas son tres enfermeras voluntarias de la Cruz Roja de Astorga (León) que, en octubre de 1936, acudieron al Puerto de Somiedo (Asturias) a prestar su asistencia a los heridos y enfermos del bando nacional, y viéndose envueltas en un episodio bolchevique, cayeron prisioneras y fueron fusiladas. En este artículo utilizaremos dicha fuente literaria para tratar de reconstruir la que pudiera considerarse, en nuestra opinión, imagen de la "enfermera ideal", perteneciente al bando nacional, durante dicha contienda. El método empleado se basará en la exposición y análisis del texto original, centrándonos especialmente en los aspectos relacionados con la imagen de nuestra profesión. Interpretaremos los datos teniendo en cuenta la realidad político-militar, social y profesional de aquel momento. Dado su interés, se ha estimado también oportuno tomar en consideración otros documentos hallados igualmente durante el período de búsqueda de información -poemas escritos, monumentos, nombres de calles relativas a las tres enfermeras-. Gracias a ellos se indagó las conexiones entre ideología y reconocimiento profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;13(47): 61-65, oct.-dic. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermeras del bando nacional en la Guerra Civil española  según el libro "Princesas del martirio" de Concha Espina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3161^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12431^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
