<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163355</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish funded paediatric research: Contribution of Anales de Pediatría to its dissemination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify Spanish funded paediatric research published in general paediatric journals included in the Web of Science (WoS) from 2010 to 2014) and those published in the Anales de Pediatría. To examine the relationship between funding and the prestige of the journals. To describe the journal conditions to meet the open access criteria. Material and method: Spanish funded paediatric articles (FA) were identified by using the WoS Funding Agency field, and by reviewing the original documents for the Anales de Pediatria (AP). For the FA published in AP the number and kind of funding agencies were identified. The possible differences in citations between FA and non-funded was assessed for articles published in this journal using the Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric test. For general journals, the patterns of distribution of FA and non-FA were investigated according to the quartile of the journal. The journal's self-archiving conditions were described using Sherpa/romeo database. Results: Funding was received for 27.5%, being 16.6% for those published in AP. In these, 105 funding agencies were identified, with 80% being national. The FA published in AP did not receive significantly more citations. In general journals, the presence of FA is greater in Q1 and Q2 journals. More than half (56%) of articles were published in subscription journals. All journals that publish FA allow self-archiving in repositories, but with embargos of at least 12 months. Conclusions: The role of AP in the dissemination of FA is still limited. Embargos in self-archiving permits compliance of Spanish open access mandate, but may hinder compliance in Europe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abad-García, María Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Teruel, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Sánchez, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar la investigación pediátrica española financiada publicada en revistas generales pediátricas incluidas en la WoS (2010-2014) y la de Anales de Pediatría (AP). Explorar la relación de la financiación con el prestigio de las revistas y describir sus condiciones para cumplir los mandatos de acceso abierto. Material y método: La financiación de los artículos publicados en revistas pediátricas generales se identificó utilizando el campo Agencia Financiadora de la WoS y revisando el documento original para AP. Para AP se identificaron las entidades financiadoras de los AF y se valoró la diferencia en la citación de los AF y los no financiados mediante test no paramétrico de Kruskal-Wallis. Se analizó la distribución de los AF y no financiados según cuartil de la revista. De las revistas con AF, se describió su tipo de acceso y su política de autoarchivo utilizando los datos de Sherpa/romeo. Resultados: El 27,5% de los artículos recibió financiación y el 16,6% de los publicados en AP. En estos se identificaron 105 entidades financiadoras (80% nacionales). Los AF de AP no recibieron un número significativamente mayor de citas. El 60% de AF se publicó en revistas de Q1 y Q2. Un 56% de AF se publicaron en revistas de suscripción. Todas las revistas, menos Pediatrics, permiten el autoarchivo de todos los AF pero con embargos de al menos 12 meses. Conclusiones: El papel de AP en la difusión de AF es aun escaso. El embargo de las revistas permite el cumplimiento del mandato español de acceso abierto pero no el europeo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(6): 306-313, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación pediátrica española financiada: contribución de Anales de Pediatría a su difusión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
