<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042576</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pemphigus vulgaris. A presentation of 14 cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pemphigus vulgaris (PV) is a chronic vesicular-ampullar mucocutaneous disease that almost always produces oral manifestations. The fact that blisters on the oral mucosa are sometimes the first manifestation of the disease implies that dental professionals must be sufficiently familiarized with the clinical manifestations of PV to ensure early diagnosis and treatment. We present a series of 14 patients with clinically and histologically diagnosed PV seen in the Teaching Unit of Oral Medicine of the University of Murcia (Spain) between 1981 and 2001. A thorough evaluation was made, recording patient age and sex, the location and extent of the lesions, and the signs and symptoms of the disease. Complementary studies were also carried out, with the evaluation of hematological parameters (including blood chemistry), the histology and immunohistochemical characteristics (direct immunofluorescence in 2 cases). Treatment comprised topical corticoids, in 12 cases combined with systemic corticoids, and associated to intralesional corticotherapy in one patient. A good response to treatment was observed in all cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Fenoll, Ambrosio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jornet, Pía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Alonso, Fabio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pénfigo vulgar (PV) es una enfermedad mucocutánea crónica de tipo vesículo-ampollares que casi siempre produce manifestaciones orales. El hecho de que en ocasiones sean las ampollas en la mucosa oral la primera manifestación de este desorden implica que los odontólogos deben conocer suficientemente las claves clínicas con el fin de realizar un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoces. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar una serie de 14 casos diagnosticados clínica e histopatológicamente de PV, que acudieron a la consulta de la Unidad Docente de Medicina Bucal de la Universidad de Murcia entre 1981 y 2001. Se realizó un estudio completo de estos pacientes, valorando la edad y el sexo, localización y extensión de las lesiones, así como el curso de los signos y síntomas. Se llevaron a cabo diversos exámenes complementarios, estudiándose las características hemáticas (biometría hemática y química sanguínea), histopatológicas, e inmunohistoquímicas (inmunofluorescencia directa en dos de los pacientes). El tratamiento consistió en corticoides tópicos, combinado en doce casos con corticoides sistémicos, y en uno con corticoides intralesionales. En todos los pacientes se obtuvo una buena respuesta al tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(4): 282-288, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pénfigo vulgar. Presentación de catorce casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29503^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29503^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d286</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29503^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
