<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114252</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Agenesis of callous body: a casuistic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Agenesis of the corpus callosun (ACC) is a brain malformation characterized by a great clinical and etiological heterogeneity. The isoalted forms are usually sporadic while those associate with other malformations are frequently integrated into syndromes or part of certain metabolic abnormalities, which is a negative prognostic factor. Objectives. To study the cahracteristics of the ACC in our country, the incidence of sequelae in patients with ACC and a number of risk factors related to its appearance. Patients and methods. Retrospective descriptive and comparative study of patients with ACC admitted in the last tow decades in the Neonatal Unit. Results. N=16. EG: 37.9 ± 3.6 weeks. 6 men, 10 women, 62,5% vaginal delivery, caesarean section 37.5%, weight: 2,919.4 ± 657.3 g. Two patients with a history of siblings with ACC and other two epilepsy. Prenatal sonographic diagnosis in 11 (68.8%). Complete in 13 ACC and 3 partial ACC. Reason for admission: 12 prenatal diagnosis, 3 hypotonia and distinctive phenotype, 1 prematurity. 43,8% had associated systemic malformations. A 43.75% of patients had isolated ACC 56.25% other non-isolated, and within this group, 44,4% was associated with malformations of the central nervous system (CNS), another 44,4% had both malformations neurological and genetic syndromes and association with a 11,2% associated with genetic syndromes. Overall 56,3% had a severe sequelae, 37,5% truncal altered auditory potentials and 3 were death (18.8%). We found a significant relationship between CNS malformations and syndromic forms with motor deficit (p = 0.030), cognitive (p= 0.04) and multiple disabilities (p = 0.04). Conclusions. Our results confirm that the neurological outcome of the ACC depends mainly on the presence of associated anomalies (syndromes or malformations of the CNS) having neuroimaging important role in prenatal counseling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clavero Montañés, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Santabárbara, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rite Gracia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pisón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Iñiguez, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebage Moisés, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Gil, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las agenesias del cuerpo calloso (ACC) constituyen una malformación cerebral frecuente caracterizada por una gran heterogeneidad clínica y etiológica. Las formas aisladas suelen ser esporádicas mientras que las asociadas con otras malformaciones se integran con frecuencia dentro de cuadros sindrómicos o forman parte de ciertas anomalías metabólicas, lo que constituye un factor pronóstico negativo. Objetivos. Estudiar las características de las ACC en nuestro medio, la incidencia de secuelas en los pacientes con ACC y una serie de factores de riesgo relacionados con su aparición. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo descriptivo y comparativo de los pacientes con ACC ingresados en las últimas dos décadas en la Unidad Neonatal. Resultados. N=16. EG. 37,9 ± 3,6 semanas. Varones 6, mujeres 10, parto vaginal 62,5%, cesárea 37,5%, peso: 2.919,4 ± 654,3 g.  Dos pacientes con antecedentes  de hermanos con ACC y otros dos de epilepsia. Diagnóstico prenatal ecográfico en 11 (68,6%). ACC completa en 13 y en 3 ACC parcial. Motivo ingreso: 12 diagnóstico prenatal , 3 hipotonía y fenotipo peculiar, 1 prematuridad. 43,8% presentaban malformaciones sistémicas asociadas. Un 43,75% de pacientes presentaba ACC aislada y otro 56,25% no aislada, y dentro de este grupo, en 44,4% estaba asociada a malformaciones del sistema nervioso central (SNC), otro 44,4% presentaban tanto malformaciones neurológicas como asociación con síndromes genéticos y un 11,2% asociada a síndromes genéticos. Globalmente  un 56,3% presentaron secuelas graves, 37,5% potenciales auditivos tronculares alterados y 3 fueron exitus (18,8%). Encontramos relación significativa entre malformaciones del SNC y formas sindrómicas con déficit motor (p: 0,030), cognitivo (p: 0,04) y plurideficiencias (p: 0,04). Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados confirman que el pronóstico neurológico de las ACC depende fundamentalmente de la presencia de anomalías asociadas (síndromes o malformaciones del SNC), teniendo la neuroimagen papel importante en el consejo prenatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;68(5): 352-357, sept.-oct. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las agenesias de cuerpo calloso: revisión casuística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9614^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
