<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046143</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of BCL-2 expression as a new basal cell marker in prostatic pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The diagnosis of invasive adenocarcinoma of the prostate is often difficult in needle        prostatic cores, where, additionally, the assessment of the presence of basal cells has demonstrated to be of        paramount importance. Currently, the immunohistochemical expression of 34betaE12 antigen and p63 protein        are the most utilized markers. In our study, we analyzed comparatively the expression of 34betaE12, p63, bcl-2        and alpha-methylacyl-CoA racemase in order to evaluate the usefulness of bcl-2 as a new marker of the basal cells        in prostatic pathology.        Methods and results: This study comprises radical prostatectomy specimens from 48 patients which were studied        in order to determine the lack of staining of basal cells in invasive tumor areas together with the expression        of racemase. Likewise, the presence of basal cells in areas of atrophy, hyperplasia, adenosis, and high-grade prostatic        intraepithelial neoplasia (PIN) was also examined. Within the areas of adenosis and PIN a discontinuous pattern        of basal cell expression was found in some cases. In 2 out of 48 cases (4,2%) of invasive carcinoma a weak        bcl-2 expression without a basal cell distribution was found. Moreover, the expression of bcl-2 in the stromal        lymphocytes appeared to be essential as an internal positive control of the technique.        Conclusions: In addition to classical markers, we demonstrated the diagnostic value of bcl-2 as a new basal        cell marker</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calatayud Blas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Briones, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Soler, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayordomo Aranda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llombart Bosch, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solsona Narbón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El diagnóstico de adenocarcinoma invasor de próstata es con frecuencia difícil en        biopsias cilíndricas, siendo fundamental en estos casos la determinación de la presencia de células basales. En        la actualidad, la expresión inmunohistoquímica del antígeno 34betaE12 junto con la proteína p63 son los marcadores        más utilizados. En nuestro estudio, se analizó comparativamente la expresión de 34betaE12, p63, bcl-2        y alfa-metilacil-CoA racemasa para valorar la utilidad de bcl-2 como nuevo marcador de células basales en patología        prostática.        Métodos y resultados: El estudio incluía piezas de prostatectomía de 48 pacientes en los que se analizó la        ausencia de marcaje inmunohistoquímico en el compartimento basal de áreas de adenocarcinoma invasor junto        a la expresión de racemasa. Se comprobó también la presencia de células basales en áreas de atrofia, hiperplasia,        adenosis y neoplasia intraepitelial prostática (PIN) de alto grado, observándose en ocasiones una expresión        discontinua de dichos marcadores en las áreas de adenosis y PIN. En 2 de los 48 casos (4,2%) de carcinoma se        obtuvo no obstante una expresión débil de bcl-2 aunque sin un patrón de distribución basal. Además, la expresión        de bcl-2 en los linfocitos del estroma resultó esencial como control interno positivo de la técnica.        Conclusiones: Nuestro estudio demuestra el valor diagnóstico de bcl-2 como nuevo marcador de células basales        añadido a los marcadores clásicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(4): 345-352, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de Bcl-2 como nuevo marcador de expresión de células basales en patología prostática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
