<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160752</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bleeding risk in endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography. Impact of the use of antithrombotic drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To analyze the risk factors for hemorrhage during endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography and the impact of antithrombotic drugs. Material and methods: Data sources: papers indexed in PubMed have been reviewed, as well as those found during the analysis of the bibliography of meta-analysis and reviews. Selection criteria: the references have been firstly evaluated by review of the abstract. After selecting the most significant articles (mainly randomized trials and well-designed case series) these have been deeply analyzed. Evaluation of the studies and synthesis: criteria by the Oxford Centre for Evidence-Based Medicine have been used for the analysis of the references and elaboration of evidence levels. Results: Seven hundred and sixty-five references were found, 753 in PubMed and the Cochrane Library. Twelve studies were selected during the analysis of other published articles (systematic reviews, meta-analysis and clinical practice guidelines). After analyzing the title or the abstract, 655 studies were excluded. Finally, 83 high quality trials or descriptive studies have been included in the analysis. Conclusion: Seven conclusions regarding the risk factors for bleeding and the impact of antithrombotic drugs have been defined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Egea Valenzuela, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberca de las Parras, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Álvarez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar los factores de riesgo de hemorragia en la colangiopancreatografía retrógrada endoscópica así como el impacto sobre la misma del uso de los fármacos antitrombóticos. Material y métodos: fuentes de datos: valoración de los artículos indexados en PubMed así como de los detectados en el análisis de la bibliografía de metaanálisis y revisiones. Criterios de elegibilidad del estudio, participantes e intervenciones: se valoraron los artículos por los abstracts y, al detectar los más significativos (principalmente ensayos clínicos aleatorizados y series de casos bien diseñadas), se analizaron los estudios completos. Métodos de evaluación del estudio y síntesis: para el análisis de la bibliografía y la elaboración de los diferentes niveles de evidencia se han utilizado los criterios establecidos por el Centro de Medicina Basada en Evidencia de Oxford. Resultados: se han encontrado 765 referencias, de las cuales 753 fueron obtenidas de la búsqueda en PubMed y Cochrane Library. Doce trabajos fueron seleccionados a partir del análisis de otros estudios publicados (revisiones sistemáticas, metaanálisis y guías clínicas). Después de analizar el título o el resumen de los estudios, fueron eliminados 655 trabajos. Definitivamente, se han incluido en el análisis final 83 ensayos clínicos o estudios descriptivos de calidad. Conclusiones: se han definido siete conclusiones con referencia a los factores de riesgo de sangrado y al impacto de los fármacos antitrombóticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;109(3): 202-210, mar. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de sangrado en la colangiopancreatografía retrógrada endoscópica: impacto del uso de fármacos antitrombóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29813^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29813^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
