<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122182</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extrahepatic visualization in the distribution of falciform artery in posttreatment Bremsstrahlung images after radioembolization with 90Y microspheres</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 39-year-old female with metastatic colorectal cancer. Pretreatment SPECT/CT imaging revealed extrahepatic tracer accumulation along the falciform artery distribution. Prior to the administration of 90Y microspheres, hepatic arterial anatomy was evaluated angiographically. It was not possible to identify the hepatic falciform artery so that no coil-embolization was performed. The patient tolerated the treatment well with only mild pain around the umbilicus during the procedure that spontaneously abated. As far as we know, this is the first report of Bremsstrahlung SPECT/CT images that has clearly shown that the microspheres accumulation in the anterior abdominal wall corresponds to hepatic falciform artery distribution on CT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sofocleous, CT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasquillo, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beylergil, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una paciente de 39 años con cáncer de colon metastatizado al hígado. La imagen SPECT/TC pretratamiento mostró acumulación extrahepática del radiotrazador a lo largo de la distribución de la arteria falciforme. Previa a la administración de las 90Y- microesferas, la anatomía arterial hepática fue evaluada angiográficamente, pero la arteria falciforme no fue identificada y, por tanto, no se realizó embolización de la misma. La paciente toleró bien el tratamiento mostrando solamente dolor periumbilical durante la realización de la técnica que cedió espontáneamente. En nuestro conocimiento esta es la primera publicación que muestra la visualización en imágenes de Bremsstrahlung de depósito extrahepático de 90Y- microesferas en la arteria falciforme (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);33(3): 178-179, mayo-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visualización extra hepática en la distribución de la arteria falciforme en las imágenes de Bremsstrahlung después de radioembolización con 90Y microesferas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6652^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
