<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60777</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Facial rash in a 4-year-old girl</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 4-year-old girl with skin lesions which began in the forehead and progressively extended to the eyelids and cheeks. These lesions improved temporary with the use of topic corticosteroids worsening afterwards. A fungal culture was conducted before the clinical suspect of ringworm facial (tinea faciale); Microsporum canis grew in the culture. The lesion disappeared after a 1-month treatment with oral grisovin. The facial ringworm (tinea faciale) is a superficial skin infection caused by dermatophytes fungi. In most of the cases the facial ringworm (tinea faciale) is diagnosed too late, especially because it is treated inadequately with topic corticoids. The choice treatment in these cases is with griseofulvine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balbín Carrero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chavarría Mur, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauleón Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una niña de 4 años de edad con lesiones cutáneas que comenzaron en la frente y luego fueron extendiéndose a los párpados y las mejillas. Mejoraron transitoriamente con la administración de corticoides tópicos, pero empeoraron con posterioridad. Con la sospecha clínica de tiña facial se realizó un cultivo de hongos. En el cultivo creció Microsporumcanis. La lesión desapareció tras un mes de tratamiento con griseofulvina oral. La tiña facial es una infección cutánea superficial por hongos dermatofitos. En la mayoría de los casos se diagnostica de forma tardía, sobre todo porque se trata inadecuadamente con corticoides tópicos. El tratamiento de elección en estos casos es la griseofulvina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(5): 220-222, mayo 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Erupción cutánea facialen una niña de 4 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9052^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6268^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
