<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143871</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of a nutrition education intervention in teachers, preschool and basic school-age children in Valparaiso region in Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the impact of a nutrition education program for teachers in the nutritional status, food knowledge and food consumption of their pre basic and basic students, and in the controls. Materials and methods: A nutrition education intervention was conducted in pre basic and basic teachers in a school year, with a pre-post evaluation of their students, compared with a control group. Subjects were 817 students (389 men and 428 women) from pre kindergarten to the second grade. The 465 students of the intervened group were distributed in two schools (Liceo 1 = 283; Liceo 2 = 182) and 352 in the control school. The nutrition intervention consisted in 9 interactive workshops for teachers with the utilization of Information and Communication Technologies (ICT). The pre post evaluation consisted in a nutritional status assessment, and a food and nutrition survey with questions related with food knowledge and food consumption, at the beginning and at the end of the school year. Results: There were no significant differences in nutritional status between the beginning and the end of the intervention. In one of the experimental schools (Liceo 2) there was a significant decrease in obesity, in women and in the age-group 7-9 years. In the experimental group there was a significant improvement in food knowledge and a decrease in non-healthy food consumption. In the control group, consumption of non-healthy food was stable, with a decrease in fruits and vegetables consumption. Conclusions: As it was demonstrated in similar studies, a short interactive nutrition education intervention with utilization of ICT in pre basic and basic teachers can produce positive changes in nutritional status of their students, improving food knowledge and healthy food consumption and decreasing non-healthy food consumption, compared with the control group. However, a strategy to incorporate parents in school nutrition education programs is still a pending issue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vio, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Carmen Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, Judith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montenegro, Edith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lera, Lydia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el efecto del programa educativo realizado en profesores, en el estado nutricional, conocimiento y consumo de alimentos saludables de alumnos de prekinder a segundo básico intervenidos y sus controles. Material y Método: Se trata de una intervención en educación nutricional en profesores de prebásica y básica, durante un año escolar, con una evaluación antes y después de sus alumnos, comparado con un grupo control. La muestra quedó constituida por 817 alumnos (389 hombres y 428 mujeres) de prekinder, kínder, 1º y 2º básico, 465 en los dos colegios intervenidos (Liceo 1 = 283 y Liceo 2 = 182) y 352 en el control. La intervención consistió en 9 talleres participativos y con uso de Tecnologías de la Información y Comunicación (TIC) a los profesores y en una evaluación de estado nutricional y encuesta de conocimiento y consumo de sus alumnos, al inicio y final del año académico. Resultados: En estado nutricional no se produjeron diferencias significativas entre el inicio y final de la intervención. En uno de los colegios intervenidos se observó una disminución significativa de la obesidad, en mujeres y en el grupo de 7 a 9 años. En los colegios intervenidos hubo una mejoría significativa en conocimiento y disminución en el consumo de alimentos poco saludables con respecto al control, en el cual se mantuvo la alimentación poco saludable y disminuyó el consumo de verduras y legumbres. Conclusiones: Al igual que en otros estudios, queda demostrado que una intervención educativa participativa, con uso de TIC y de corta duración en profesores y alumnos de prebásica y básica, puede producir cambios positivos en el estado nutricional, mejorando significativamente el conocimiento y consumo de alimentos saludables y disminuyendo el consumo de alimentos no saludables, lo que no sucede en el grupo control. Sin embargo, queda pendiente una estrategia de como implicar a los padres en esta tarea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(6): 1298-1304, jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de una intervención educativa en alimentación saludable en profesores y niños preescolares y escolares de la región de Valparaíso, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
