<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94328</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of functional dependence among elderly people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most immediate consequence of aging is the dependent population growth. For this purpose, the aim of this study is to show the prevalence of dependence on basic and instrumental activities of daily living among the population older than 60 years old, depending on the gender, the marital status and the age, in a total sample of 1.222 people. The dependency level is higher among women, in nearly all basic activities, being the widow people who have shown the highest average dependency rate and for both, basic and instrumental activities. We have observed that there is a positive correlation between the increase of aging and the increase of dependence, except in the basic activity of eating. We can know the groups and features of dependant people, so it leads us, not only to estimate the resources needed to assist them but also the possibility of carrying out preventive work among those groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gázquez-Linares, José Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Fuentes, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercader-Rubio, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero-Jurado, M. del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La consecuencia más inmediata del envejecimiento de la población actual, es el incremento de la dependencia. Así, el objetivo de este trabajo, es dar a conocer la prevalencia del nivel de dependencia para las actividades básicas e instrumentales en la población mayor de 60 años, en función del género, estado civil y la edad, seleccionando una muestra total de 1.222 personas. El nivel de dependencia es mayor entre las mujeres para casi todas las actividades básicas, siendo también las personas viudas las que mayores niveles medios de dependencia presentan y para todas las actividades, tanto básicas como instrumentales. Se observa una correlación positiva entre el aumento de la edad y el aumento de la dependencia, salvo en la actividad básica relacionada con comer. Podemos conocer los grupos y las características de las personas dependientes, lo que permite, no sólo la estimación de los recursos necesarios para su atención, sino también la posibilidad de trabajar en esos grupos con carácter preventivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 871-876, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la dependencia funcional en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
