<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155286</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients with autism spectrum disorder in pediatric dentistry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Autism Spectrum Disorders cover a range of developmental brain disorders that can cause significant problems at the level of socialization, communication and behavior. The American Psychiatric Association classifies them as: autistic disorder, Asperger's syndrome, childhood disintegrative disorder, pervasive developmental disorder not specified and Rett&#146;s syndrome. The etiology is multifactorial with interaction of genetic and environmental factors. Currently, it is unknown which they are and how they interact with potential environmental elements on genetic susceptibility. The autism spectrum disorders are difficult to diagnose; and for this, the behavioral assessment and development of the child is required. They are usually detected around 18 months and males are being affected to a greater extent. Early detection is important because the results of early therapy provide greater and more rapid improvement than later intervention. These disorders, by themselves, do not have different oral characteristics to those found in patients without this pathology, however, the risk increases due to the limited capacity of understanding and assuming responsibilities in oral health, which can severely heighten index of caries and periodontal disease. Moreover, a higher incidence of parafunctional habits and self-harm have been found. The dental management of these patients is complex and demand proper interaction between the patient and the dentist. Because they are patients who require specialized care and monitoring is essential that professionals have a proper training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Real Benlloch, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Gutiérrez, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mourelle Martínez, María Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musa Herranz, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno del espectro autista engloba una serie de trastornos del desarrollo cerebral que pueden causar problemas importantes a nivel de socialización, comunicación y conducta. La Asociación Psiquiátrica Norteamericana los clasifica en: trastorno autista, trastorno de Asperger, trastorno desintegrativo infantil, trastorno generalizado del desarrollo no especificado y trastorno de Rett. La etiología es multifactorial; con interacción de factores genéticos y ambientales. Actualmente se desconocen cuáles son y cómo interactúan los posibles elementos ambientales sobre la susceptibilidad genética. Los trastornos del espectro autista no son fáciles de diagnosticar; y para ello se precisa la evaluación de la conducta y el desarrollo del niño. Por lo general, se detectan en torno a los 18 meses, siendo el sexo masculino el afectado en mayor proporción. La detección temprana es importante ya que los resultados de la terapia precoz proporcionan una mayor y más rápida mejoría que una intervención tardía. Estos trastornos, por sí mismos, no comprenden características orales diferentes a las encontradas en pacientes sin esta patología, no obstante, el riesgo aumenta debido a la capacidad limitada de comprensión así como de asumir responsabilidades en la salud oral, lo que puede aumentar severamente el índice de caries y enfermedad periodontal. Además, se ha encontrado una mayor incidencia de hábitos parafuncionales y autolesiones. El manejo odontológico de estos pacientes es complejo y demanda de una adecuada interacción entre el paciente y el odontólogo. Debido a que son pacientes que requieren de una atención y seguimiento especializado, es imprescindible la formación adecuada de los profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);13(2): 123-128, mayo-ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pacientes con trastorno del espectro autista en odontopediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30941^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24868</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29822^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2704</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
