<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112357</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prenatal diagnosis of an adrenal mass: Intra-abdominal pulmonary sequestration, an entity to consider in diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital lung sequestrations are uncommon but are well recognized. Recently, the incidence of these anomalies has increased due to routine ultrasound scans in pregnant women. Although these anomalies represent only 0,15% to 6,45% of all pulmonary malformations, they constitute between 8% and 23% of the prenatal diagnosis of lung abnormalities. Extralobar pulmonary sequestration is an extremely rare congenital infradiaphragmatic anomaly. Most of these lesions are located in the left abdomen and differential diagnosis with adrenal masses is essential. Pulmonary sequestration should be considered in any infant with an upper abdominal or adrenal mass, especially when diagnosis is prenatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Veiras, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Somoza Argibay, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Palacios, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los secuestros pulmonares son anomalías congénitas infrecuentes pero bien reconocidas. En los últimos años han mostrado un aumento de su incidencia en relación a los controles ecográficos rutinarios a los que son sometidas las gestantes. Por ello y a pesar de que representan tan solo entre el 0,15-6,45% de todas las malformaciones congénitas pulmonares constituyen entre el 8 y el 23% de los diagnósticos prenatales de anomalías pulmonares. El secuestro pulmonar extralobar infradiafragmático es una anomalía congénita extremadamente rara. La mayoría de estas lesiones se localizan en el hemiabdomen izquierdo siendo importante el diagnóstico diferencial con masas suprarrenales. El secuestro pulmonar debería ser considerado en todo neonato con masa abdominal superior o suprarrenal, sobre todo en casos de diagnóstico prenatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);40(3): 136-138, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112357</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico prenatal de masa suprarrenal: secuestro pulmonar intraabdominal, una entidad a tener en cuenta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28310^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
