<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140874</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periprosthetic femoral fractures after hemiarthroplasty. An analysis of 17 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. To describe the characteristics of patients with periprosthetic femoral fractures after hemiarthroplasty and analyze their treatment. Material and method. An observational, longitudinal, retrospective study was conducted on a series of 17 patients with periprosthetic femoral fractures after hip hemiarthroplasty. Fourteen fractures were treated surgically. The characteristics of patients, fractures and treatment outcomes in terms of complications, mortality and functionality were analyzed. Results. The large majority (82%) of patients were women, the mean age was 86 years and with an ASA index of 3 or 4 in 15 patients. Ten fractures were type B. There were 8 general complications, one deep infection, one mobilization of a non-exchanged hemiarthroplasty, and 2 non-unions. There were 85% consolidated fractures, and only 5 patients recovered the same function prior to the injury. At the time of the study 9 patients had died (53%). Discussion. Periprosthetic femoral fractures after hemiarthroplasty will increase in the coming years and their treatment is difficult. Conclusion. Periprosthetic femoral fractures after hemiarthroplasty are more common in women around 90 years-old, and usually occur in patients with significant morbidity. Although the Vancouver classification is reliable, simple and reproducible, it is only a guide to decide on the best treatment in a patient often fragile. The preoperative planning is essential when deciding a surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Barrio, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mencía-Barrio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roces-Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Huerta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Pascua, LR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir las características de los pacientes y las fracturas femorales periprotésicas sobre hemiartroplastias, y realizar un análisis del tratamiento a partir de sus resultados. Material y método. Estudio observacional, longitudinal y retrospectivo de una serie de 17 pacientes con fracturas femorales periprotésicas sobre hemiartroplastias de cadera. Catorce se trataron quirúrgicamente. Se analizaron las características de los pacientes y de las fracturas y los resultados del tratamiento en términos de complicaciones, mortalidad y funcionalidad. Resultados. El 82% de los pacientes fueron mujeres, la edad media fue de 86 años y el índice ASA de 15 de ellos fue 3 o 4. Diez fracturas fueron de tipo B. Se registraron 8 complicaciones generales, una infección profunda, una movilización de la hemiartroplastia no recambiada y 2 seudoartrosis. Consolidaron el 85% de las fracturas y solo 5 pacientes recuperaron la función previa al traumatismo. Al final del estudio habían fallecido 9 pacientes (53%). Discusión. El tratamiento de las fracturas periprotésicas sobre hemiartroplastias, cuya frecuencia aumentará en los próximos años, es difícil. Conclusiones. Las fracturas femorales periprotésicas sobre hemiartroplastias son más frecuentes en mujeres próximas a los 90 años y suelen ocurrir en pacientes con importante morbilidad. La indicación de su tratamiento no debe basarse solo en la clasificación de Vancouver que, aunque fiable, simple y reproducible, no deja de ser una guía para decidir el mejor tratamiento en un paciente a menudo frágil. Cuando aquel sea quirúrgico, la planificación preoperatoria es fundamental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(5): 333-342, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas periprotésicas de fémur sobre hemiartroplastia. Análisis de una serie de 17 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55039^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53566^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53566^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53566^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53566^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
