<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156109</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of a PCR for the detection and quantification of parasitism by Demodex folliculorum infestation in biopsies of skin neoplasms periocular area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To standardize the relative quantification by mass of tissue parasitism by Demodex folliculorum infestation from neoplastic skin biopsies periocular using molecular amplification to study the possible relationship of the appearance of eyelid basal cell carcinoma with the presence and density of the mite in later works. Methods. A quantitative PCR was developed real-time probes TaqMan. PCR was tested in a pilot 46 actual biopsy samples nodular basal cell carcinoma series. Results. The sensitivity was placed with a detection limit of between 1 and 10 copies / &amp;#956;l. 50% (23/46) of the biopsies were positive for D. folliculorum. The specificity was 100% confirmed by sequencing. Conclusion. The technique shows good results for sensitivity and specificity that can make it useful as a tool for studies of cause and effect D. folliculorum and basal cell carcinoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tenorio-Abreu, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz-Frutos, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-España, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo-Grass, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naranjo-González, Ligia Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Gallego, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estandarizar la cuantificación relativa por masa de tejido de la parasitación por Demodex folliculorum procedente de biopsias neoplásicas cutáneas de la zona periocular mediante técnicas de amplificación molecular con el objetivo de poder estudiar la posible relación de la aparición de carcinoma basocelular palpebral con la presencia y densidad del ácaro en trabajos posteriores. Material y métodos. Se desarrolló una PCR cuantitativa a tiempo real con sondas TaqMan. La PCR se probó en una serie piloto de 46 muestras reales de biopsias de carcinoma basocelular de tipo nodular. Resultados. La sensibilidad se situó con un límite de detección de entre 1 y 10 copias/&amp;#956;l. El 50% (23/46) de las biopsias fueron positivas a D. folliculorum. La especificidad fue del 100% confirmado mediante secuenciación. Conclusión. La técnica muestra buenos resultados de sensibilidad y especificidad que la pueden hacer útil como herramienta para estudios causa-efecto de D. folliculorum y basalioma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(4): 220-223, ago. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156109</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de una PCR para la detección y cuantificación de la parasitación por Demodex folliculorum en biopsias de neoplasias cutáneas del área periocular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9113^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35408^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9114^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
