<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157549</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of biological nurturing in breastfeeding effective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim is to evaluate the effectiveness of the various positions of breastfeeding postpartum in four temporal periods in the new born child&#146;s life with women without previous experience, and that have given natural birth (eutectic delivery). Design: Experimental study with post-test measure and blind research, with control group and experimental group random assignment. Area of study: Hospital Universitario Fundación Alcorcón of Madrid and 7 affiliated medical centres. Subject of study: The subject of study will be formed by 190 first- time and expectant women. 95 women will be randomly assigned to the control group, and 95 to the experimental group. Main variables: Dependent: effective breastfeeding. Independent: position in post-partum breastfeeding (biological nurturing position and lateral decubitus position). Tools: The data collection will be performed through a validated scale LACTH, 2 hours following the child birth, in the puerperium unit, 48 hours later and in the midwife office of the primary health assistance after 7-10 and 40 days. Data analysis: The effect of the position of biological nurturing on the effective breastfeeding and the differences between the control group and the experimental group will be studied. For the data analysis, the latest version of the statistic program SPSS will be used. Limitations: There will be different schools of thought among the professionals. The midwives at specialized assistance and primary health assistance and interbranch organizations will cooperate. It might be monitoring lost (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coria Postigo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Parra, Ana Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirado Sánchez, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Yuste, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Parejo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad del tipo de posición de amamantamiento en el posparto inmediato sobre la lactancia materna eficaz en cuatro momentos de la vida del recién nacido en mujeres gestantes sin experiencia previa en lactancia materna y con parto eutócico. Diseño: Estudio experimental con medidas en el post-test y simple ciego, con asignación aleatoria al grupo control y al grupo experimental. Ámbito de estudio: Hospital Universitario Fundación Alcorcón de Madrid y siete centros de atención primaria adscritos. Sujetos de estudio: La muestra de estudio estará formada por 190 gestantes primíparas, que serán asignadas de forma aleatoria 95 al grupo control y 95 al grupo experimental. Variables principales: Dependiente: lactancia materna eficaz. Independiente: posición de amamantamiento posparto (postura de crianza biológica y decúbito lateral). Instrumentos: La recogida de datos se realizará mediante una escala LACTH validada, tras el parto en la sala de dilatación a las 2 horas, en la unidad de puerperio a las 48 horas y en la consulta de matrona de atención primaria a los 7-10 y los 40 días. Análisis de datos: Se estudiará el efecto de la postura de crianza biológica sobre la lactancia materna eficaz y las diferencias entre el grupo control y el experimental. Se utilizará la última versión disponible del programa estadístico SPSS. Limitaciones: Es de prever que entre los profesionales haya distintas formas de pensamiento y algunos de ellos no deseen participar. Para llevar a cabo el estudio se precisará la colaboración de las matronas de atención especializada y atención primaria, así como coordinación interprofesional. Es posible que se produzcan pérdidas de seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;17(3): 108-114, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la postura de crianza biológica en la lactancia materna eficaz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12439^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
