<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60559</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secondary effects of treatment with maraviroc and other CCR5 antagonists. Potential impact of the CCR5 blocker</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Maraviroc is the first inhibitor of CCR5 co-receptors to bemarketed as an antiretroviral. The pre-clinical studies andphase III trials have shown that it has a very favourablesafety profile. No characteristic adverse effect of maravirochas been identified. Unlike with aplaviroc, where itsclinical development was stopped due to serious hepatoxicity, no increase in liver toxicity has beendemonstrated in patients treated with maraviroc even ifthey are co-infected by hepatotropic virus. Nor was thereany evidence of an increase in the incidence of neoplasmsor serious infections in patients treated with maraviroc. Ina study on naive patients, maraviroc produced nonsignificantchanges in total cholesterol, LDL, HDL andtriglycerides.Although CCR5 co-receptors play a role in the immuneresponse of the body, it has not been shown whetherindividuals homozygote for its deletion (delta-32 mutation)have an increased risk of serious infections, with thepossible exception of encephalitis due to the West Nilevirus. However, long-term follow up is required onpatients treated with to be able to rule out any increasedsusceptibility to infections or neoplasms(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arribas López, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Maraviroc es el primer inhibidor de los correceptores CCR5comercializado como antirretroviral. Los estudiospreclínicos y los ensayos de fase 3 han demostrado que superfil de seguridad es muy favorable. No se ha identificadoun efecto adverso característico de maraviroc. Encontraste con aplaviroc, cuyo desarrollo clínico fueinterrumpido por hepatotoxicidad grave, no se hademostrado un incremento de toxicidad hepática enpacientes tratados con maraviroc incluso si estáncoinfectados por virus hepatotropos. Tampoco se haevidenciado un incremento en la incidencia de neoplasiaso infecciones graves en pacientes tratados con maraviroc.En un estudio de pacientes naive, maraviroc causócambios no significativos en colesterol total, lipoproteínasde baja densidad, lipoproteínas de alta densidad ytriglicéridos.Aunque los correceptores CCR5 desempeñan un papel enla respuesta inmunitaria del organismo, no se hademostrado que los individuos homocigotos para sudeleción (mutación delta-32) tengan un riesgoincrementado de infecciones graves, con la posibleexcepción de la encefalitis por el virus del Nilo occidental.Sin embargo, es necesario un seguimiento a largo plazo delos pacientes tratados con maraviroc para poder descartaruna susceptibilidad incrementada a infecciones o neoplasias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.11): 23-27, oct. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos secundarios asociados al tratamiento con maraviroc y otros antagonistas de CCR5. Impacto potencial del bloqueo del receptor CCR5</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36265^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33498^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
