<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054106</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alterations of P300 wave in occipital lobe in depressive patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The objective of this work is to assess neurofunctional alterations in patients with depression, analyzing the neurophysiological activity of P300 wave in bilateral occipital areas during visual attention and visual memory cognitive tasks.    Method. The study was made up of a group of 40 individuals, 21 in the control group and 19 in the group with depression. Visual stimulation was made by means of Cognistin system (ATI). The person is placed at one meter from the screen and remains seated, with no external visual stimulus if possible. All individuals were subjected to two different tasks: visual «oddball» paradigm and visual memory.        Results. A delay exists in latency of the P300 wave, in a global manner, both in visual task discrimination and memory task in patients with depression in the occipital areas. There is negative correlation between the P300 amplitude and severity of the depression, so that greater amplitude in the P300 component implies reduced severity of depression and vice versa. The reaction time in visual discrimination task correlates significantly with severity of depression; greater reaction time reveals greater severity in the depression.        Conclusions. The conclusions of this study reveal neurofunctional alterations in the occipital lobe during visual discrimination and memory task in patients with depression</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coullaut-Valera García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coullaut-Valera García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbaiza Díaz del Río, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es valorar las alteraciones neurofuncionales en pacientes depresivos, analizando la actividad neurofisiológica de la onda P300 en áreas occipitales bilaterales durante tareas cognitivas de atención visual y memoria visual.    Método. El estudio se realizó con un grupo de 40 sujetos, de los cuales 21 sujetos formaban el grupo control y 19 el grupo depresivo. La estimulación visual se realizó mediante el sistema Cognistin (ATI). El sujeto se sitúa a un metro de la pantalla y permanece sentado, a ser posible, sin estímulos visuales externos. A todos los sujetos se les aplicaron dos tareas diferentes: paradigma oddball visual y tarea de memoria visual.        Resultados. Existe un retraso en la latencia de la onda P300 de forma global, tanto en la tarea de discriminación visual como en la tarea de memoria, en los pacientes depresivos en las áreas occipitales. Hemos encontrado una correlación negativa entre la amplitud P300 y gravedad de la depresión, de tal manera que a mayor amplitud del componente P300, menor gravedad de la depresión y viceversa. El tiempo de reacción en la tarea de discriminación visual es el que se correlaciona de manera estadísticamente significativa con la gravedad de la depresión, a mayor tiempo de reacción mayor gravedad de la misma.        Conclusiones. Las conclusiones de este estudio ponen de manifiesto la existencia de alteraciones neurofuncionales en el lóbulo occipital durante una prueba de discriminación y memoria visual en pacientes depresivos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(4): 243-248, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones en la onda P300 en el lóbulo occipital en pacientes depresivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32754^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
