<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132792</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Weaning: a crucial period in baby nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The greatest changes of a child feeding habits take place during the first year of life. This is the period known as weaning, and it&#146;s of great significance in the life of a child. The kind of baby feeding, duration of breastfeeding and starting of solid feeding have been considered important items in the pathogenesis of some diseases. This is the reason why it is of fundamental importance to analyse the feeding recommendations at this crucial period of life, the weaning. The key to understand feeding infant&#146;s rules is the knowledge of the scientific basis on the age of solid diet introduction. Early complementary feeding has immediate effects on baby&#146;s health; moreover, continuously it is emerging more evidence about the influence that baby&#146;s diet may have on health during childhood and adulthood. International recommendations support exclusive breastfeeding six months and WHO in may 2001 recommended it as a public health global politic. Nevertheless, considering some circumstances we should be flexible in this peace of advise, but there should not be introduced any complementary food before the end of the fourth month (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vitoria Cormenzana, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El primer año es el momento en el que se realizan los mayores cambios en la alimentación durante la vida de un niño. Es el período que se conoce como el &#147;destete&#148;, el weaning de los anglosajones, y constituye un período de gran trascendencia en la vida del niño. El tipo de lactancia, la duración de la lactancia materna y el momento de introducción de los sólidos en la dieta se han considerado como puntos importantes en la patogenia de algunas enfermedades, por lo que es fundamental analizar las recomendaciones acerca de la alimentación en este período crucial de la vida que es el destete. La clave para entender las normas que rigen la alimentación infantil es el conocimiento de las bases científicas sobre las que se apoyan las recomendaciones para la edad de introducción de los sólidos en la dieta. La alimentación complementaria precoz tiene unos efectos inmediatos sobre la salud de los niños; además, cada día existen mayores evidencias de que la dieta del lactante puede tener un efecto sobre la salud durante la infancia y la edad adulta. Las recomendaciones internacionales apoyan la lactancia materna exclusiva hasta los 6 meses y la OMS en mayo de 2001 recomendó esta pauta como una política global de salud pública. No obstante, por diversas circunstancias debemos ser algo flexibles con este consejo, pero no se debe introducir ningún alimento complementario antes de finalizar el cuarto mes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(supl.5): s69-s81, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132792</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El destete: un período crucial en la nutrición del niño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7401^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15288</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1927^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16558</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
