<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125276</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Pediatric Cardiology and Cardiac Surgery Units of the University and Polytechnic Hospital La Fe</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatric Cardiology is the specialty that is in charge of the comprehensive care of the child with congenital or acquired heart disease of the cardiovascular system. It applies cardiologic medical-surgical knowledge in an extensive period of human life, with has been extending towards the fetal period, on the one hand, and beyond adolescence, on the other, as the survival of patients with heart disease increases. The University Hospital La Fe has a Pediatric Cardiology and Cardiac Surgery medical-surgical unit, with more than 40 years of experience in the care of these patients with heart disease. Both sections, as reference units, receive patients from the entire Valencian Community (the population of the Valencian Community has almost 5 million inhabitants including 762,538 children between 0 and 14 years (INE, January 2013). As a tertiary center, it has equipment and personnel that are prepared to carry out all the current diagnostic and treatment techniques. Both pediatric cardiologists and heart surgeons as well as the rest of the Hospital services, especially Neonatology, Intensive Care and Anesthesia as well as Arrhythmias and Adult Congenital health Disease units are involved in this task. Beginning with the description of the activity of the Cardiology and Child Cardiac Surgery Sections of the Hospital La Fe, this article reviews the area of action of Pediatric Cardiology and some of its aspects that have undergone significant changes in recent decades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Insa, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boni, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Cardiología Pediátrica es la especialidad que se encarga de la asistencia integral al niño con enfermedad congénita o adquirida del sistema cardiovascular, aplicando el conocimiento médico-quirúrgico cardiológico en un amplio periodo de la vida humana, que se ha ido extendiendo hacia el periodo fetal, por un lado y, más allá de la adolescencia, por otro, al verse incrementada la supervivencia de los pacientes con cardiopatía. El Hospital Universitario La Fe cuenta con una unidad médico-quirúrgica de Cardiología y Cirugía Cardiaca Pediátrica, con experiencia de más de 40 años en el cuidado de estos pacientes con cardiopatía. Ambas secciones, como unidades de referencia, reciben enfermos de toda la Comunidad Valenciana (la población de la Comunidad Valenciana es de casi 5 millones de habitantes y contaba con 762.538 niños entre 0 y 14 años (INE, enero 2013). Como centro terciario dispone de equipamiento y personal preparados para realizar todas las técnicas actuales de diagnóstico y tratamiento. En esta tarea están implicados tanto cardiólogos y cirujanos cardiacos infantiles, como el resto de servicios del hospital, especialmente los de Neonatología, Cuidados Intensivos y Anestesia, además de las unidades de Arritmias y de Cardiopatías Congénitas del Adulto. En este artículo se repasan, a partir de la descripción de la actividad de las secciones de Cardiología y Cirugía Cardiaca Infantil del Hospital La Fe, el ámbito de actuación de la Cardiología Pediátrica y algunos de los aspectos del mismo que han sufrido cambios significados en las últimas décadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;70(2): 87-92, mar.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las Unidades de Cardiología Pediátrica y Cirugía Cardiaca Infantil del Hospital Universitario y Politécnico La Fe</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33586^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13884^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
