<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114611</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epicardial adipose tissue: More than a simple fat deposit?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity increases the risk of development of atherosclerosis. However, this risk significantly depends on adipose tissue distribution in the body and ectopic accumulation of visceral adipose tissue (VAT). Recent evidence suggests that each visceral fat deposit is anatomically and functionally different. Due to proximity to the organ, each visceral fat deposit exerts a local modulation rather than a systemic effect. Because of its unique location and biomolecular properties, a &#147;non-traditional&#148; fat depot &#150; the epicardial adipose tissue &#150; has been considered to play a causative role in atherosclerosis. Epicardial adipose tissue may be measured with imaging techniques and is clinically related to left ventricular mass, coronary artery disease, and metabolic syndrome. Therefore, epicardial fat measurement may play a role in stratification of cardiometabolic risk and may serve as a therapeutic target (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lima-Martínez, Marcos M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iacobellis, Gianluca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blandenier, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad aumenta el riesgo de desarrollar arteriosclerosis; sin embargo, el riesgo depende significativamente de la distribución del tejido adiposo en el cuerpo y la acumulación ectópica de tejido adiposo visceral (TAV). Evidencia reciente indica que cada depósito de grasa visceral es anatómica y funcionalmente diferente. Dada la proximidad al órgano, cada depósito de TAV ejerce una modulación local más que un efecto sistémico. Debido a su peculiar localización y sus propiedades biomoleculares, un tejido adiposo no tradicional, el tejido adiposo epicárdico, se ha abierto campo como causante de arteriosclerosis. Este tejido puede ser medido con técnicas de imagen y está clínicamente relacionado con la masa del ventrículo izquierdo, la enfermedad arterial coronaria y el síndrome metabólico. Por tanto, la medición de la grasa epicárdica puede tener un papel en la estratificación del riesgo cardiometabólico y servir como blanco terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(6): 320-328, jun.-jul. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114611</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tejido adiposo epicárdico: ¿más que un simple depósito de grasa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10686^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
