<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154065</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient satisfaction as a component of quality in dialysis units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The quality of any service involving objective factors such as the characteristics of the materials and facilities used, and subjective elements such as user satisfaction about the service, understood as obtaining a satisfactory response to the expectations that had been raised. The patient-health system relationship has evolved to place the patient at the heart of the system, and their satisfaction has become an important component of quality, considering itself an outcome; and determine satisfaction rates periodically, it is consolidating as an essential tool to assess the evolution of the quality of service. Objectives. General: n Know the overall satisfaction of patients in the nephrology unit. Secondary: n Determine any differences in satisfaction between different units within the clinical management unit (CMU). n Identify areas for improvement in the care of our patients. Patients / Method. Cross-sectional, observational study of all patients seen in the three dialysis units in our CMU. We used to collect data a self-administered questionnaire, SERVQHOS, which was distributed to patients by nurses not employees of the units where these patients were dialyzing. They explained the objectives of the study, requested verbal consent for participation, and asked that once completed, this must be deposited anonymously in a letterbox placed in each unit. Results. The sample was of 89 patients, with a mean age of 65.1 ± 14.9 years (22-93), of which 30% were women and 70% men. 29 patients (32%) were dialyzed in the Hospital Unit (HU), 45 (49%) at a non-Hospital Unit and 17 (19%) were on peritoneal dialysis (PD). When comparing the sociodemographic variables per centers were observed only slight differences in educational level and employment status of patients. Overall assessment of the questionnaires: - 98.8% of patients were satisfied or very satisfied with the service. - 97.7% say they would recommend the service without hesitation. Best rated aspects: -Transmitting -Security personnel. -Friendliness. -Interest In Patients. -Personalized. Worst rated aspects: -Punctuality of medical consultations. - State of facilities. - Time waiting to be seen by a doctor Regarding the open question of the questionnaire, 22 patients have suggested some area of improvement. When comparing the results between the three centers of the UGC, it emphasizes that PD patients are those that show the greatest degree of satisfaction, being a slight difference between patients in the two units of HD, showing more satisfied whose at the HU than those at the non-HU. Conclusions. With this study we have found that patients receiving dialysis treatment in our CMU, they are recognized very satisfied with the service, with slight differences depending on the unit where they receive treatment, and has also allowed us to know improvable aspects that are addressing to increase patient satisfaction and therefore the quality of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez López, Victoria Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Cuesta, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Montero, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Toledano, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Cantarero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En la calidad de cualquier servicio, intervienen elementos objetivos como las características de los materiales e instalaciones que se emplean, y elementos subjetivos como la satisfacción del usuario del servicio, entendida esta como la obtención de una respuesta satisfactoria a las expectativas que se había planteado. La relación paciente-sistema sanitario ha evolucionado hasta situar al paciente como eje del sistema, y su satisfacción se ha consolidado como un importante componente de calidad, al considerarse en sí misma una medida de resultado; y determinar los índices de satisfacción de forma periódica, se está consolidando como una herramienta imprescindible para valorar la evolución de la calidad del servicio. Objetivos. -Estado de instalaciones. -Tiempo de espera para ser atendido por un médico. Respecto a la pregunta abierta del cuestionario, 22 pacientes han sugerido alguna área de mejora. Al comparar los resultados entre los tres centros de la UGC, destaca que los pacientes en DP son los que muestran el mayor grado de satisfacción, encontrándose una ligera diferencia entre los pacientes de las dos unidades de HD, mostrándose más satisfechos los de la UH que los del CPD. Conclusiones. Con este estudio hemos constatado que los pacientes que reciben tratamiento de diálisis en nuestra UGC, se reconocen muy satisfechos con el servicio, con ligeras diferencias según la unidad en la reciben tratamiento, y además nos ha permitido conocer aspectos mejorables, que se están abordando para aumentar la satisfacción del paciente y por consiguiente la calidad asistencial. General: n Conocer el grado de satisfacción global de los pacientes con el servicio de Nefrología. Secundarios: n Determinar eventuales diferencias en la satisfacción entre las diferentes unidades que integran la unidad de gestión clínica (UGC). n Detectar aspectos mejorables en la atención a nuestros pacientes. Pacientes/Método. Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal sobre todos los pacientes atendidos en las tres unidades de diálisis de nuestra UGC. Utilizamos para la recogida de datos el cuestionario autoadministrado SERVQHOS, que fue distribuido a los pacientes por enfermeras ajenas a las unidades donde se estaban dializando, las cuales explicaron los objetivos del estudio, solicitaron el consentimiento verbal para su participación, y pidieron que una vez cumplimentado lo depositaran de forma anónima en un buzón colocado en cada unidad. Resultados. La muestra fue de 89 pacientes, con una edad media de 65,1±14.9 años (22-93), de los cuales (30%) mujeres y (70%) hombres. 29 pacientes (32%) se dializaban en la Unidad Hospitalaria (UH), 45 (49%) en el Centro Periférico de Diálisis (CPD) y 17 (19%) estaban en Diálisis Peritoneal (DP). Al comparar las variables sociodemográficas por centros, solo se observan ligeras diferencias en el nivel de estudios y en la situación laboral de los pacientes...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;19(2): 125-133, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La satisfacción del paciente como componente de la calidad en las unidades de diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
