<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117825</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification of human papillomavirus in benign and malignant nonmelanoma skin lesions by molecular methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The human papillomavirus (HPV) establish a latent infection of the skin as normal flora and can develop skin lesions on some situations. Objectives: Identify the HPV types which exhibit tropism for cutaneous epithelium and analyse its possible association with benign skin lesions and nonmelanoma skin cancer. Materials and methods: Prospective study was carried out in the Department of Dermatology at the Centenario Provincial Hospital from June 2007to November 2008. Samples were collected by swabs from the following areas: sun-exposed (FE), non-sun-exposed (NFE), perilesional (PL), lesion area(SL) and biopsy of lesions for histopathological study. We included patients referred to surgical removal of a skin lesion for histopathological study. Detection of HPV by PCR.Results:67 patients were recruited, 41 men and 26 women, median age of 51 years (range, 19-89 years). 300 samples were suitable for amplification by PCR. HPV DNA was present in 58% of the analyzed samples (176/300), and 75% in FE, 39% in NFE, 75% in PL, 66% in SL and 35% in biopsies. 69 (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quattrocchi, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giri, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorosito, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bussy, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Squeff, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bergero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piccirilli, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bussy, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chouhy, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los virus papiloma humano (PVH) están presentes en la piel como flora normal, donde permanecen en forma latente, pudiendo desarrollar en ciertas oportunidades, lesiones cutáneas. Objetivo: Identificar los tipos de PVH con tropismo por epitelios cutáneos y analizar su posible asociación con lesiones cutáneas benignas y carcinomas cutáneos no melanoma. Materiales y métodos: Estudio prospectivo realizado en el servicio de dermatología del Hospital provincial del Centenario, desde Junio de 2007 a Noviembre de 2008. Se obtuvieron muestras mediante hisopados de regiones: fotoexpuesta (FE), no fotoexpuesta (NFE), perilesional (PL), superficie de lesión (SL) y biopsias de lesiones para estudio histopatológico. Se incluyeron pacientes derivados para estudio histopatológico de las lesiones antesreferidas. Detección de PVH mediante PCR. Resultados: Participaron 67 pacientes, 41 hombres y 26 mujeres, edad promedio de 51 años (rango: 19-89 años). 300 muestras resultaron idóneas para la amplificación por PCR. La frecuencia de ADN de PVH hallado fue del 58% (176/300) (Figura 1), encontrándose 75% en FE, 39% en NFE, 75%en PL, 66% en SL y 35% en las biopsias. Se identificaron 69 tipos diferentes de HPV, siendo más frecuentes el 2, 21, 20 y 6. Se detectó un nuevo PVH,el 115. No se identificó PVH en muestras de carcinomas. En queratosis seborreicas se detectó en un (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;41(3): 97-102, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación de papilomavirus humanos en lesiones cutáneas benignas y malignas no melanoma por métodos moleculares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30677^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
