<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85697</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Could malaria and dengue reappear in Spain?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent increase in immigration to Spain has facilitated the importation of many tropical diseases. Among these diseases, those of vectorial origin are among the most difficult to study. Some of the reasons for this difficulty are the complexity due to the variety of hosts involved in the transmission cycles and the need to know all the physiological, bioecological and biogeographic parameters related to the vector in order to infer the actual possibilities of the emergence or reemergence of these diseases. This article provides information on imported diseases of unquestionable epidemiological interest for the population in Spain due to the presence of several species of culicid mosquitoes (Diptera, Culicidae) capable of transmitting these diseases in our country.AbstractParasitic diseases such as malaria, which was highly endemic in Spain until 50 years ago, and other arboviral infections such as dengue and yellow fever, are analyzed in these terms. Various aspects related to the health system, as well as the different ways of tackling these issues, are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Peydró, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Marí, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aumento de la inmigración durante los últimos años en España ha facilitado la importación de numerosas enfermedades tropicales. Entre ellas, las de transmisión vectorial son algunas de las más complicadas de estudiar por la complejidad que conlleva la participación de diversos hospedadores en los ciclos de transmisión, así como por la necesidad de conocer todos los parámetros fisiológicos, bioecológicos y biogeográficos relacionados con el organismo vector para poder inferir las posibilidades reales de la emergencia o la reemergencia de las enfermedades pertinentes. En estas circunstancias, el presente trabajo aporta información acerca de enfermedades importadas de incuestionable interés epidemiológico para la población residente en España, por albergar nuestro país diversas especies de mosquitos culícidos (Diptera, Culicidae) potencialmente transmisoras de éstas. Enfermedades parasitarias como la malaria, que fue altamente endémica en España hasta hace apenas 50 años, y otras de tipo arbovírico como el dengue y la fiebre amarilla, son analizadas en estos términos. También se exponen diferentes aspectos inherentes al sistema sanitario y a las distintas formas de hacer frente a estas cuestiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(4): 347-353, jul. -agos. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85697</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Pueden la malaria y el dengue reaparecer en España?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3727</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
