<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152664</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Corneal toxicity after Ozurdex® migration into anterior chamber</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe a case of corneal toxicity after migration of a dexamethasone implant into the anterior chamber. Case report: A 62-year-old man with aphakia and a history of vitrectomy received a dexamethasone implant for a refractory Irvine-Gass syndrome. Thirty days later, the implant migrated into the anterior chamber causing endothelial contact with secondary corneal oedema that justified the removal of the implant without resolution of the oedema. Discussion: Clinical tolerability to dislocated implant is poor in cases with pre-existing corneal oedema, and because of this, it must be removed early. In cases of aphakia and vitrectomy, the increased risk of Ozurdex®dislocation justifies performing a prior endothelial count (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernal, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentamos un caso de toxicidad corneal tras migración de un implante de dexametasona (Ozurdex®) hacia la cámara anterior. Caso clínico: Varón de 62 años afáquico y vitrectomizado, recibe un implante Ozurdex® por síndrome de Irvine-Gass refractario. Treinta días después el implante migra hacia la cámara anterior produciendo edema corneal por contacto endotelial, que justificó la retirada del dispositivo, sin resolución del edema. Discusión: La tolerabilidad endotelial del implante es escasa en casos con edema preexistente, por lo que debe retirarse precozmente. En caso de vitrectomía y afaquia, el mayor riesgo de dislocación de Ozurdex®justifica el recuento endotelial previo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(6): 292-294, jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxicidad corneal tras migración de Ozurdex® a cámara anterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
