<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122214</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of the characteristics of induced pluripotent stem cells in vitro in administrative regime of their lines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently achieved techniques in the field of stem cell research have permited the development of human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs). The characteristics of these cells and their appearance after the passage of Order SCO/393/2006, of 8 February, on Functioning and Organization of a National Bank of Cell Lines and Act 14/2007, of 3 July, on Biomedical Research raise the questions of the legal regime of their deposition at the National Bank of Cell Lines and their control by the Commission of Guarantees for the Donation and Use of Human Cells and Tissues. Drawing on a wider legal frame, the author defends these requirements on the grounds that the legal classification comes from the origin and potentiality of the cells rather than from the techniques employed to obtain them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bobo Ruiz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas recientemente logradas en el ámbito de las células madre han permitido el desarrollo de células madre de pluripotencia inducida humans (hiPSCs). Las particularidades de estas células y su aparición en escena con posterioridad a la Orden SCO/393/2006 de 8 de febrero, por la que se establece la organización y funcionamiento del Banco Nacional de Lineas Celulares y a Ley 14/2007, de 3 de julio de investigación Biomédica plantean dudas sobre el régimen jurídico de las mismas en cuanto al deber de depósito en el Banco Nacional de Líneas Celulares y su control por la comisión de Garantías para la Donación y Utilización de Células y Tejidos Humanos. En el contexto de un marco normativo más amplio el autor defiende dichos requisitos basándose en que la clasificación legal atiende al origen y potencialidad y no a la técnica empleada para su obtención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(39): 61-82, jul.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de las características de las células madre de pluripotencia inducida in vitro en el régimen administrativo de sus líneas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37583^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54271^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31619^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
