<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166872</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The automatic implantable defibrillator: preventing sudden death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Technical improvements in automatic implantable defibrillators (AID) and accumulating data from a series of clinical trials have led to an exponential increase in indications for these devices. However, among developed countries, Spain has seen one of the weakest levels of growth in their use and has a low rate of implants per million inhabitants. In addition to this difference from other countries, there are significant variations in indications for these devices between the different Spanish regions. There is a need for studies specifically designed to find a better way of stratifying the risk of sudden death in patients with heart disease to ensure more appropriate candidate selection, to improve cost-effectiveness in some indications, and to provide greater consistency between the various clinical practice guidelines on recommendations for device implantation. In parallel, there is also a need for more arrhythmia units and for increased human and technical resources for these units to enable them to respond both to ongoing technological developments in the field and to the growing number of indications and concomitant treatments and to reduce the substantial geographical variability in device implantation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peinado Peinado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo tecnológico del desfibrilador automático implantable y la evidencia acumulada por sucesivos ensayos clínicos han dado lugar a que las indicaciones de estos dispositivos hayan tenido un crecimiento exponencial. Sin embargo, España es uno de los países desarrollados con menor crecimiento y menor número de implantes por millón de habitantes. Además de las diferencias con otros países, existe una significativa variabilidad en las indicaciones entre las distintas comunidades autónomas. Son necesarios estudios encaminados a mejorar la estratificación de riesgo de muerte súbita en pacientes con cardiopatía que permita una mejor selección de candidatos, una mejor relación coste-efectividad en algunas indicaciones y una mayor coherencia en las recomendaciones de implante en las distintas guías de práctica clínica. Al mismo tiempo, es necesario un mayor número de unidades de arritmias con mejor dotación de recursos humanos y técnicos para dar respuesta, junto con el constante desarrollo tecnológico en este campo, a un crecimiento en el número de indicaciones y terapias concomitantes y reducir la importante variabilidad geográfica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.A): 32a-39a, 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El desfibrilador automático implantable. Evitando la muerte súbita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
