<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128047</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of freezing on the &#147;creamatocrit&#148; measurement of the lipid content of human donor milk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine, by the creamatocrit measurement, the effect on the fat content of raw and pasteurized donor milk of freezing during 3 months at &amp;#8722;20 °C. Methods: The evolution of the creamatocrit measurement (following Lucas technique) on frozen (&amp;#8722;20 °C), raw and pasteurized human milk, was analyzed during 3 months. Results: The fat content of raw milk (n=44) was 3.19 g/dl at the beginning and 2.86 g/dl after 3 months frozen (p=0.02). In pasteurized milk (n=36) fat content at the first determination was 2.59 g/dl and 2.20 g/dl after 1 month frozen (p=0.01). Afterwards there were no significant changes up to 3 months frozen. Variability was observed in the intermediate values. Conclusions: A reduction on the fat content measurement of raw and pasteurized donor human milk after freezing was observed. Freezing does not inactivate the milk lipase but does destroy the fat globule. Creamatocrit measurement may not be the best method to determine the fat content of processed human milk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Díaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallás-Alonso, C. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escuder-Vieco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Román, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Lara, N. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar, mediante crematocrito, las modificaciones del contenido graso de la leche materna cruda y pasteurizada a lo largo de 3 meses de congelación. Método: Se analizó la evolución del crematocrito (fórmula de Lucas) en leche cruda y pasteurizada a lo largo de 3 meses de congelación a &amp;#8722;20°C. Resultados: La grasa en leche cruda (n=44) fue 3,19g/dl al inicio y 2,86g/dl a los 3meses de congelación (p=0,02). En leche pasteurizada (n=36), al inicio fue 2,59g/dl y 2,20g/dl al mes de congelación (p=0,01), posteriormente, hasta los 3 meses, no hubo cambios significativos. Se observó variabilidad en los valores intermedios. Conclusiones:  Se observó una disminución en la medida de la grasa tras congelación en leche cruda y pasteurizada. La congelación no impide la acción de la lipasa y también afecta al glóbulo de grasa. Probablemente, el crematocrito no sea el método óptimo para cuantificar la grasa en leche ya procesada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);81(3): 185-188, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medida por crematocrito del contenido calórico de la leche materna donada congelada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37778^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9083^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
