<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95595</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The medicalized rationality. Outline of nursing as a government agent knowledge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The contextualization of the infirmary professional exercise in the medicalizated sanitary system, characterized by the influence of the market's logic and political calculus that belong to hegemonic powers let's us; develop a historical and narrative description of the leading traits and characteristics surrounding the thought, it's logic and rationalities that substain the exercise of nursing as a government agent. An approximation to the discursive practice from where the biomedical hegemony, the reductionism to which the phenomenological tendencies of the main theories and the influence of a liberal ideology in the nursing knowledge are questioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irigibel-Uriz, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La contextualización del ejercicio profesional de la enfermería en los sistemas sanitarios medicalizadores, caracterizados por la influencia de las lógicas de mercado y los cálculos políticos de las fuerzas hegemónicas, permite desarrollar una descripción, narrativa e histórica de los principales rasgos y características del contorno del pensamiento, las lógicas y racionalidades que sustentan el ejercicio de la enfermería policiaca. Una aproximación a las prácticas discursivas desde donde se cuestiona la hegemonía biomédica, el reduccionismo al que remiten las tendencias fenomenológicas de las principales teorías y la influencia de la ideología liberal en el conocimiento de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(2/3): 182-186, sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Racionalidad Medicalizadora. Contornos del pensamiento de la enfermería policíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
