<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141237</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Catalonia's primary healthcare accreditation model: a valid model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are few experiences of accreditation models validated by primary care teams (EAP). The aim of this study was to detail the process of design, development, and subsequent validation of the consensus EAP accreditation model of Catalonia. An Operating Committee of the Health Department of Catalonia revised models proposed by the European Foundation for Quality Management, the Joint Commission International and the Institut Català de la Salut and proposed 628 essential standards to the technical group (25 experts in primary care and quality of care), to establish consensus standards. The consensus document was piloted in 30 EAP for the purpose of validating the contents, testing standards and identifying evidence. Finally, we did a survey to assess acceptance and validation of the document. The Technical Group agreed on a total of 414 essential standards. The pilot selected a total of 379. Mean compliance with the standards of the final document in the 30 EAP was 70.4%. The standards results were the worst fulfilment percentage. The survey target that 83% of the EAP found it useful and 78% found the content of the accreditation manual suitable as a tool to assess the quality of the EAP, and identify opportunities for improvement. On the downside they highlighted its complexity and laboriousness. We have a model that fits the reality of the EAP, and covers all relevant issues for the functioning of an excellent EAP. The model developed in Catalonia is a model for easy understanding (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gens, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pareja, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallès, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquet, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Davins, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay pocas experiencias de modelos de acreditación validados para equipos de atención primaria (EAP). El objetivo de este estudio fue detallar el proceso de diseño, elaboración, consenso y posterior validación del modelo de acreditación para equipos de atención primaria de Catalunya. Un Comité Operativo del Departament de Salut de Catalunya revisó modelos propuestos por la European Foundation for Quality Management, la Joint Commission International y el Institut Català de la Salut, y propuso 628 estándares a un grupo técnico de 25 expertos en atención primaria y calidad asistencial, para consensuar estándares esenciales para acreditar EAP. Con el documento consensuado se realizó una prueba piloto en 30 EAP, con el propósito de validar contenidos, probar los estándares e identificar evidencias. Finalmente se pasó una encuesta para valorar la aceptación y la validación del documento. El Grupo Técnico consensuó un total de 414 estándares esenciales. La prueba piloto seleccionó un total de 379. La media de cumplimiento de los estándares del documento definitivo en los 30 equipos fue del 70,4%. Los estándares con peor porcentaje de cumplimiento fueron los correspondientes a criterios de resultados. La encuesta realizada objetivó que el 83% de los equipos lo encontró útil y el 78% encontró adecuado el contenido del manual de acreditación como herramienta para evaluar la calidad de los EAP e identificar oportunidades de mejora. Como aspecto negativo destacó su complejidad y laboriosidad. Disponemos de un modelo que se ajusta a la realidad de los EAP, y contempla todos los aspectos relevantes para el funcionamiento de un equipo excelente. El modelo elaborado en Catalunya es un modelo de fácil comprensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(supl.1): 74-80, jul. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El modelo de acreditación de atención primaria de Catalunya: un modelo válido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6418^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
