<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051389</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usual practices of midwives in the management of labor in public hospitals of Barcelona, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the activities and practices of midwives according to the level of complexity of the hospital: level l (regional hospital), level ll (referral hospital) and level lll (high-technology hospital).        Design: A cross-sectional, descriptive study.        Subjects and method: Midwives at public hospitals in the province of Barcelona, Spain, who work in the delivery room.        For the data collection tool, a questionnaire was designed and distributed to all the hospitals between December 2004 and February 2005. The major study variables were concerned with sociodemographic information, the activities of the midwives and the self-perception of their role.        Results: 135 midwives from 18 hospitals were studied The mean age was 44.6 years (standard deviation [SD] = 8.45) and the mean length of their professional experience was 19.9 years (SD = 10.24). In all, 43.6% (58) of the normal deliveries were performed by midwives and in level l hospitals, they managed 81.1 % (30). The number of cases in which the diagnosis of the onset of labor and monitoring of dilation were performed by the midwife differed significantly depending on the level of the hospital (p&lt;0.001). With respect to those activities that are carried out according to protocol (dilation monitoring, establishment of cardiotocographic monitoring windows), no differences were observed among the different levels of hospital facilities. In terms of health care activities and education during the puerperium, the limited presence of midwives in maternity wards was notable. The midwives defined their role as professionals who perform both autonomous and assigned tasks (63.4%) (83). There were no significant differences between the types of hospitals in this respect.        Conclusion: The activities of midwives in terms of diagnosis, management of normal deliveries and postpartum monitoring differ from one level of hospital to another, and are fewer as the level of the hospital increases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corchs, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer cuáles son las actividades y prácticas realizadas por las matronas, según el nivel de complejidad hospitalario nivel I (hospital comarcal), nivel II (hospital de referencia) y nivel III (de alta tecnología).        Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal.        Personas y método: Matronas de hospitales públicos de la provincia de Barcelona que trabajaban en sala de partos.        Como instrumento de recogida de datos se diseñó un cuestionario distribuido a todos los hospitales entre diciembre de 2004 y febrero de 2005. Las principales variables del estudio fueron sociodemográficas, actividades realizadas por las matronas y percepción del propio rol.        Resultados: Se estudiaron 135 matronas procedentes de 18 hospitales. La media de edad fue de 44,6 años (DE= 8,45), Y la media de experiencia profesional de 19,9 años (DE= 10,24). Los partos eutócicos son atendidos por las matronas en un 43,6% (58) Y en los hospitales de nivel I con un 81,1 % (30). El hecho de efectuar el diagnóstico de parto y el control de dilatación ejercido por la matrona fue distinto según el nivel de hospital (p &lt;0,001). Respecto a las actividades protocolizadas (control de la dilatación, realización de ventanas de monitorización cardiotocográfica), no se reflejaron diferencias entre los distintos niveles de atención hospitalaria. En cuanto a las actividades y la educación sanitaria en el puerperio, destaca la poca presencia de las matronas en las salas maternoinfantiles. Las matronas definieron su rol como profesionales que ejercen por igual tareas autónomas como delegadas (63,4% (83), no existiendo variabilidad entre tipos de hospitales.        Conclusión: Las actividades realizadas por las matronas en el diagnóstico, atención al parto eutócico y control puerperal difieren entre los distintos niveles de atención hospitalaria, siendo menores cuanto mayor es el nivel del hospital</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;7(3): 5-11, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas habituales de las matronas en el parto de los hospitales públicos de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
