<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141801</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Verifying the elimination of measles and rubella in the WHO European Region: the case of Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Like some other countries in the Region, Spain has recently experienced multiple but small measles outbreaks resulting from several importations and in which health care professionals were also infected. The European Regional Verification Commission (RVC) for Measles and Rubella Elimination, an independent panel of experts, conducted an annual review of the reports submitted by the National Verification Committees (NVC) and a country visit to assess the status of interruption of endemic transmission of these diseases in Spain. Essential criteria supporting interruption included absence of endemic transmission in the presence of high-quality surveillance system and genotyping evidence. High vaccination coverage with the first dose of measles -and rubella-containing vaccine (MRCV1) has been maintained above 95% at national level. The figure is based on the number of doses administered to children aged 12-24 months. However, there are two autonomous regions, namely Cataluña and Castilla y Leon with low (&lt;90%) vaccination coverage. In the autonomous regions of Murcia and Melilla, although the coverage with MRCV1 was above 95%, that of the second dose of measles -and rubella-containing vaccine was below 90. On the basis of the evidence provided, with only two imported cases of rubella in 2013, the RVC concluded that endemic transmission of rubella had been interrupted in Spain, but there is a risk of re-establishing transmission due to the sub-optimal population immunity in at least four regions as the coverage with two doses of measles- and rubella- containing vaccines was below the required minimum of 95% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Preciado, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Al igual que algunos otros países de la Región, España ha experimentado recientemente múltiples aunque pequeños brotes de sarampión resultantes de varias importaciones en los que también se infectaron profesionales de la salud. La Comisión Regional Europea de Verificación (RVC) de Eliminación de sarampión y de rubéola, un comité de expertos independiente, llevó a cabo una revisión anual de los informes presentados por el Comité Nacional de Verificación (NVC) y una visita a España para evaluar la situación de la interrupción de la transmisión endémica del estas enfermedades. Criterios esenciales que apoyan la interrupción incluyen la ausencia de transmisión endémica en presencia de un sistema de vigilancia de alta calidad y pruebas de genotipado. De la primera dosis de la vacuna contra el sarampión y la rubéola (MRCV1) se ha mantenido un cobertura por encima del 95% a nivel nacional. Este dato se basa en el número de dosis administradas a niños de edades comprendidas entre los 12 y 24 meses. Sin embargo, hay dos regiones autónomas, a saber, Cataluña y Castilla y León con baja cobertura de vacunación (&lt;90%). En la comunidad autónoma de Murcia y en la ciudad autónoma de Melilla, aunque la cobertura con MRCV1 estuvo por encima del 95%, la cobertura de la segunda dosis de la vacuna contra el sarampión y la rubéola fue inferior al 90%. Sobre la base de las pruebas presentadas, con solo dos casos importados de rubéola en 2013, el RVC concluyó que la transmisión endémica de la rubéola se ha interrumpido en España, pero persiste el riesgo de que se restablezca debido a la baja inmunidad de la población, por debajo de los niveles óptimos en al menos cuatro regiones en las que la cobertura con dos dosis de vacuna para sarampión y rubeola está por debajo 95%, mínimo requerido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(4): 353-355, jul.-sept. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Verificación de la eliminación del sarampión y la rubéola en la región europea de la OMS: el caso de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12784^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12784^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
