<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122450</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Posterior tibial tendon dysfunction: what other structures are involved in the development of acquired adult flat foot?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the association of posterior tibial tendon dysfunction and lesions of diverse ankle structures diagnosed at MRI with radiologic signs of flat foot. Material and methods: We retrospectively compared 29 patients that had posterior tibial tendon dysfunction (all 29 studied with MRI and 21 also studied with weight-bearing plain-film X-rays) with a control group of 28 patients randomly selected from among all patients who underwent MRI and weight-bearing plain-film X-rays for other ankle problems. In the MRI studies, we analyzed whether a calcaneal spur, talar beak, plantar fasciitis, calcaneal  bone edema, Achilles&#146; tendinopathy, spring ligament injury, tarsal sinus disease, and tarsal coalition were present. In the weight-bearing plain-film X-rays, we analyzed the angle of Costa-Bertani and radiologic signs of flat foot. To analyze the differences between groups, we used Fisher&#146;s exact test for the MRI findings and for the presence of flat foot and analysis of  variance for the angle of Costa-Bertani. Results: Calcaneal spurs, talar beaks, tarsal sinus disease, and spring ligament injury were significantly more common in the group with posterior tibial tendon dysfunction (P&lt;.05). Radiologic signs of flat foot and anomalous values for the angle of Costa-Bertani were also significantly  more common in the group with posterior tibial tendon dysfunction (P&lt;.001). Conclusion: We corroborate the association between posterior tibial tendon dysfunction and lesions to the structures analyzed and radiologic signs of flat foot. Knowledge of this association can be useful in reaching an accurate diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez de la Vega Fernández, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez de la Peña, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carracoso Arranz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recto Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Alonso, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herráiz Hidalgo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la asociación entre disfunción del tendón tibial posterior (DTTP), las lesiones de diversas estructuras del tobillo diagnosticadas por RM, y los signos radiológicos del pie plano. Material y método: Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo comparando 29 pacientes con DTTP, todos examinados por RM (21 de ellos con un estudio radiológico en carga) y un grupo control de 28 pacientes elegidos aleatoriamente entre aquellos estudiados por otras afecciones del tobillo  mediante RM y estudio radiológico en carga. En los estudios de RM revisamos la existencia de espolón calcáneo, pico talar, fascitis plantar, edema óseo calcáneo, tendinopatía del Aquiles, lesión del ligamento Spring, afección del seno del tarso y coalición tarsiana. En los estudios radiológicos en carga se valoraron el ángulo de Costa-Bertani y los signos radiológicos de pie plano.  Analizamos las diferencias entre los grupos en los hallazgos con RM y presencia de pie plano mediante el test exacto de Fisher y del ángulo de Costa-Bertani mediante el análisis de lavarianza. Resultados: La presencia de espolón calcáneo, pico talar, afección del seno del tarso y del ligamento  Spring fue más frecuente en el grupo con DTTP, de forma estadísticamente significativa (p &lt; 0,05). También existieron diferencias significativas en la presencia del pie plano radiológico y valores anómalos en el ángulo de Costa-Bertani, más frecuentes (p &lt; 0,001) en el grupo con DTTP. Conclusión: Corroboramos la asociación entre la lesión de estas estructuras diagnosticada por RM y los signos del pie plano radiológico con DTTP. Conocer esta asociación puede ser de utilidad para establecer un diagnóstico preciso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(3): 247-256, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción del tendón tibial posterior: ¿qué otras estructuras están implicadas en el desarrollo del pie plano adquirido del adulto?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37269^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23249^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37270^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23245^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
