<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140908</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Precarious employment in undocumented immigrants in Spain and its relationship with health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the characteristics of precarious employment in undocumented immigrants in Spain and its relationship with health. Methods: A qualitative study was conducted using analytic induction. Criterion sampling, based on the Immigration, Work and Health project (Inmigración, Trabajo y Salud [ITSAL]) criterion (current definitions of &#145;legal immigrant&#146; in Spain and in the literature) was used to recruit 44 undocumented immigrant workers from four different countries, living in four Spanish cities. Results: The characteristics of precariousness perceived by undocumented immigrants included high job instability; disempowerment due to lack of legal protection; high vulnerability exacerbated by their legal and immigrant status; perceived insufficient wages and lower wages than coworkers; limited social benefits and difficulty in exercising their rights; and finally, long hours and fast-paced work. Our informants reported they had no serious health problems but did describe physical and mental problems associated with their employment conditions and legal situation. Conclusions: Our results suggest that undocumented immigrants&#146; situation may not fit the model of precarious employment exactly. However, the model's dimensions can be expanded to better represent undocumented immigrants&#146; situation, thus strengthening the general model. Precarious employment in this group can be defined as «extreme», as it affects their working and social lives. If these workers continue to be exposed to such precarious conditions, the impact on their health may increase (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Porthé, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavides, Fernando G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudelo-Suárez, Andrés A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Frutos, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benach, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ahonen, Emily</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características de la precariedad laboral en inmigrantes irregulares en España y su relación con la salud. Métodos: Estudio cualitativo que utiliza los principios de la inducción analítica. Se definió una submuestra del proyecto ITSAL, cuya muestra teórica se identificó a partir de la definición de inmigrante en España y de la literatura. Las áreas de estudio fueron 4 ciudades de España. La muestra final fue de 44 trabajadores inmigrantes irregulares, de 4 nacionalidades. Resultados: Algunas características de la precariedad laboral percibidas por los inmigrantes irregulares fueron: elevada inestabilidad laboral; ausencia total de empoderamiento en tanto no cuentan con un marco de protección legal; elevada vulnerabilidad agudizada por su situación legal y su estatus de inmigrante; nivel de ingresos insuficiente y más bajo que el del resto de los compañeros; ausencia total de derechos laborales y escaso poder para exigir mejores condiciones; y finalmente un tiempo de trabajo extenso y a un ritmo acelerado. Reportaron no haber tenido problemas de salud graves, aunque destacan problemas de salud física y mental que relacionan con sus condiciones de empleo y situación legal. Conclusiones: Los resultados sugieren que la situación de los inmigrantes irregulares, si bien no se ajusta exactamente al constructo de precariedad laboral, ha permitido adaptarlo, ampliando sus dimensiones y robusteciendo el modelo general. La precariedad laboral en este colectivo podría definirse como «extrema» en tanto afecta a su vida laboral y social. Si estos trabajadores continúan expuestos a tales condiciones de precariedad, las repercusiones sobre su salud podrían ser mayores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(supl.1): 107-114, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La precariedad laboral en inmigrantes en situación irregular en España y su relación con la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9209^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12758^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4727^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4727^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4552^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12831</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14877^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
