<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77003</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stroke-psychosis. Description of two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The presence of neuropsychiatry symptoms (hallucinations, delusions and agitation) as stroke-related guideline symptoms, thus forming an acute psychosis of organic cause, are extremely uncommon and often correlate with strategic infarcts (caudate nucleus, striatum and thalamus). Clinical case. We report two cases of stroke-psychosis. Case  1. A 67 year-old man with sudden-onset delusions of persecution and complete recovery in three months. The brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed infarctions in both head of the caudate nucleus and body of right caudate nucleus. Case 2. A 49 year-old man with sudden-onset delusions of persecution and gustative hallucinations that disappeared in three months. The brain MRI revealed small infarction in the left thalamus. Discussion. The possible vascular origin of the psychosis in both cases (sudden onset, complete recover, demonstration of acute ischemic lesion in strategic territory) and the underlying psychopathogenic mechanism (dysfunction of prefrontal cortico-subcortical circuits) is discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corbalán, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberti, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortina, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La presencia de manifestaciones neuropsiquiátricas (alucinaciones, ideación delirante, agitación psicomotriz) como síntomas guías de un evento vascular, configurando por tanto una psicosis aguda de causa orgánica es excepcional en la práctica clínica y obedece mayoritariamente a infartos estratégicos (caudado, estriado, tálamo).Caso clínico. Se presentan dos casos de psicosis ictal. Caso 1. Varón de 67 años de edad con ideación delirante de perjuicio de instauración brusca y remisión completa en el plazo de 3 meses. La RM cerebral demostró isquemia a nivel de ambas cabezas de núcleo caudado y cuerpo de caudado derecho. Caso 2. Varón de 49 años de edad con ideación delirante de perjuicio y alucinaciones gustativas de instauración brusca y remisión completa en 3 meses. En la RM cerebral se objetivó infarto lacunar talámico izquierdo. Discusión. Se discute el probable origen vascular de la psicosis en ambos casos (instauración brusca, recuperación completa, demostración de lesión isquémica aguda en territorio estratégico) así como el mecanismo fisiopatogénico subyacente (disfunción de los circuitos prefrontales córtico-subcorticales) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(4): 240-242, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicosis ictal. Descripción de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7398</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
