<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045169</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of the use of metformin among the risk population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To perform a follow-up of the use of metformin inorder to ensure the appropriate prescription of the drug amongthe population with the highest risk of adverse reactions.Method: A prospective follow-up was conducted of the use ofmetformin during a four-month period. In the patients recruitedfor the study, the following data were recorded: age, sex, weightand height, cause of hospitalization, pharmacotherapeutic profile,origin of the prescription (prior to hospitalization or during thehospital stay), glycemia, renal function, side effects and cause ofthe discontinuation of the treatment, if appropriate.Results: The mean number of patients hospitalized each dayduring the study period was 352 (standard deviation ± 36,8), themean age was 73 years (33-102) and the total number of patientsstudied was 135, with 46% of males.Since prescription of metformin is contraindicated in patientswith creatinine values &gt; 0.132 mMol/L, renal function was monitored.Based on the data of 20 patients, six pharmaceutical interventionswere performed in order to recommend the discontinuationof the treatment, which was accepted in 83% of the cases.Side effects and glycemia were also recorded.Conclusions: During the follow-up period, we did not observeany severe side effects such as associated lactic acidosis, althoughin some cases metformin was prescribed to patients inwhich it was not recommended. However, the follow-up ofpatients is important, since we have observed side effects (diarrhea)that require reduction of the dose of metformin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garriga Biosca, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Capafons, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pla Poblador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar un seguimiento de utilización de metforminapara comprobar la adecuada prescripción del medicamento en lapoblación con mayor riesgo de desarrollar reacciones adversas.Método: Se ha realizado un seguimiento prospectivo de utilizaciónde metformina durante un periodo de cuatro meses. En lospacientes seleccionados se ha registrado: edad, sexo, peso y talla,motivo del ingreso, perfil farmacoterapéutico, origen de la prescripción(anterior al ingreso o durante la estancia hospitalaria),glucemia, función renal, efectos adversos y el motivo de interrupcióndel tratamiento, si procede.Resultados: La media diaria de pacientes ingresados duranteeste periodo fue de 352 (desviación estándar ± 36,8), la edadmedia fue de 73 años (33-102), el total de pacientes estudiadosfue de 135, siendo un 46% hombres.La prescripción de metformina está contraindicada en pacientescon valores de creatinina superiores a 0,132 mMol/L, por ellose controló la función renal. Con los datos de 20 pacientes, serealizaron seis intervenciones farmacéuticas para aconsejar la suspensióndel tratamiento, aceptadas en un 83% de los casos. Tambiénse registraron efectos adversos y glucemia.Conclusiones: Durante el periodo de seguimiento no hemosobservado ningún efecto adverso grave como la acidosis lácticaasociada, aunque en ocasiones la prescripción de metformina seha realizado en pacientes en los que no estaría recomendada. Sinembargo, consideramos interesante el seguimiento de estospacientes puesto que hemos observado efectos adversos (diarrea)que han requerido la disminución de la dosis de metformina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;29(6): 364-366, nov.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de la utilización de metformina en la población de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
