<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130336</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serum levels of alanine aminotransferase and sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to compare alanine aminotransferase (ALT) serum levels in patients with sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (SAHS) respect patients without SAHS. Patients and methods: We studied 69 patients referred to our Sleep Unit. Sleep was studied using overnight polysomnography. Patients with hepatotoxic medication, chronic diseases or excessive alcohol consumption were excluded. Serum ALT levels in patients with SAHS, apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) &amp;#8805; 5, were compared with ALT levels from subjects without SAHS (AHI &lt; 5). Results: we included 46 patients with SAHS (AHI 49 ± 32.1) and 23 subjects without SAHS (AHI 3 ± 0.9). No significative differences in age, gender and body mass index were observed. Serum ALT levels increased significantly in SAHS patients respect control group. There were not correlation between ALT levels and nocturnal SpO2 parameters. Nevertheless, 8-hydroxyguanosine values showed significative correlation with ALT levels (rho = 0.494; P = 0.001). In multivariate lineal regression, the 8-hydroxyguanosine was the only parameter that independently associated to ALT values (p = 0.012). Conclusions: in patients with SAHS, serum ALT level is significantly increased respect control group. In our study, intermittent hypoxemia doesn&#146;t explain the variability of ALT, while 8-hydroxyguanosine could play an important role at ALT elevation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jurado Gámez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Marín, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feu Collado, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Zafra, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casáis Juanena, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: comparar en pacientes con síndrome de apneas-hipopneas del sueño (SAHS) los valores séricos de alanino-aminotransferasa (ALT) respecto a un grupo sin SAHS. Pacientes y métodos: se estudiaron 69 sujetos remitidos a la unidad del sueño, a los que se les realizó una polisomnografía. Se excluyeron aquellos pacientes con enfermedad crónica, excesiva ingesta de alcohol o medicación hepatotóxica. Los valores séricos de ALT de los pacientes diagnosticados de SAHS (índice de apneas-hipopneas, IAH &amp;#8805; 5) se compararon con los de un grupo sin SAHS (IAH &lt; 5). Resultados: se incluyeron 46 pacientes con SAHS (IAH = 49 ± 32,1) y 23 sujetos sin SAHS (IAH = 3 ± 0,9). No se observaron diferencias significativas en edad, género e índice de masa corporal. Los pacientes mostraron un incremento significativo de los valores séricos de ALT respecto al grupo control. En los enfermos con SAHS no se observó correlación entre las cifras de ALT y los parámetros relacionados con la SapO2 nocturna. Al contrario, el valor de la 8-hidroxiguanosina mostró correlación significativa con la ALT (rho = 0,494; P = 0,001) y, en el modelo de regresión lineal multivariante, fue la única variable que se asoció independientemente a las cifras de ALT (p = 0,012).Conclusiones: en pacientes diagnosticados de SAHS, el valor sérico de ALT se encuentra significativamente elevado respecto el grupo control. En nuestro estudio, la hipoxemia intermitente no explica la variabilidad de la ALT, mientras que la 8-hidroxiguanosina puede jugar un papel importante en la elevación de la ALT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;26(3): 155-160, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cifras séricas de alanino aminotransferasa y síndrome de apneas-hipopneas del sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d413^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
