<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68656</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intoduction: The abuse and inappropriate use of antibiotics has raised genuine concerns for public health. As a result of this concern there have been annual campaigns in Bizkaia since 1997 directed at the correct use and dispensing of antibiotics. Objective: To know and evaluate, once various campaigns have been carried out, that pharmacies in Bizkaia fullfill the demand for a prescription for the dispensing of antibiotics. Methods: An observational, cross-sectional study was made using a random sample of 202 of the 426 pharmacies in Bizkaia. This was performed by means of the use of false patients who requested, without a prescription, one of the two best-known brands of amoxycillin for a supposed minor sore throat. Results: 11 pharmacies (5,45%) dispensed the antibiotic without a prescription. 186 (97,38%) of those that refused to dispense it informed the false patient that it was essential to have a prescription. 49 (25,65%) suggested a non-antibiotic treatment and 69 (36,13%) recommended that the patient consult a doctor. Conclusions: Although in almost every pharmacy in Bizkaia the correct action of not dispensing antibiotics without prescription was performed, it is necessary to continue the campaigns to tighten dispensing and rational antibiotic use. On the one hand, to maintain and improve that level of demand for prescriptions, and on the other, to optimise the pharmacist&#146;s role. The behaviour of not dispensing of pharmaceuticals can be transformed to right pharmaceutical suggestions by following clinical guidelines and protocols that deal with the different reasons for why those accustomed to asking for antibiotics without prescription may consult a pharmacist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arco, Juan del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortes, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blas, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La utilización abusiva e inadecuada de antibióticos ha supuesto verdaderos problemas para la salud pública. Partiendo de esta preocupación, desde 1997 y con periodicidad anual se han realizado en Bizkaia campañas encaminadas a la dispensación y uso correcto de antibióticos. Objetivo: Conocer y evaluar el cumplimiento de exigencia de receta médica para la dispensación de antibióticos en las oficinas de farmacia de Bizkaia una vez realizadas varias campañas. Métodos Se realizó un estudio observacional y transversal en una muestra aleatoria de 202 farmacias de las 426 de Bizkaia en las que mediante falsos pacientes se solicitó sin receta una de las dos marcas de amoxicilina más conocidas para un supuesto dolor leve de garganta. Resultados: En 11 farmacias (5,45%) se dispensó sin receta el antibiótico solicitado. 186 (97,38%) de las que no lo dispensaron informaron al falso paciente que es imprescindible la receta, 49 (25,65%) propusieron un tratamiento no antibiótico y 69 (36,13%) recomendaron acudir al médico. Conclusiones: Aunque en casi todas las farmacias de Bizkaia se actúa correctamente a la hora de no dispensar antibióticos sin receta, es necesario continuar con las campañas de potenciación de la dispensación y uso racional, por una parte para mantener y mejorar ese nivel de exigencia de la receta y por otra para optimizar la actuación del farmacéutico, transformando estas no dispensaciones en indicaciones farmacéuticas correctas a través de guías clínicas o protocolos que contemplen los distintos motivos de consulta en la farmacia para los que suelen pedirse antibióticos sin receta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;8(4): 160-166, sept.-dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68656</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
