<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164584</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties from the 32nd ECTRIMS Congress, 2016, presented at the 9th Post-ECTRIMS Meeting (I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For the ninth year in a row the Post-ECTRIMS Meeting has been held in Madrid (Spain) with the aim of presenting and discussing the hottest issues debated at the ECTRIMS Congress by renowned specialists in multiple sclerosis in our country. One outcome of this scientific activity, endorsed by the Spanish Neurology Society, is this review article, which is published in two parts. This first part addresses family planning, pregnancy management and the role of breastfeeding in women with multiple sclerosis. Attention is drawn to the paediatric population, to magnetic resonance imaging features and to the genetic-environmental risk factors for developing the disease in children, without neglecting the risk factors for development in adults. The review updates the epidemiology of cognitive deterioration in patients with multiple sclerosis, the advantages and disadvantages of available assessment tools, and current management approaches, while also insisting on the importance of cognitive involvement during the course of the disease. Furthermore, the concept of individualised, precision medicine is introduced, from the diagnosis of the disease until its treatment, with the controversies that inevitably arise in patient management, above all with regard to the change of treatment and the handling of associated risks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ginés, M Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramió-Torrentà, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginestal, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Nacarino, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brieva, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Merino, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles-Hernández, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja-Guevara, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comabella, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca-Lallana, José E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oterino, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Delicias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Pinel, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendibe-Bilbao, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova-Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Por noveno año consecutivo se ha celebrado en Madrid (España) la Reunión Post-ECTRIMS con el objetivo de presentar y discutir los temas más debatidos en el congreso ECTRIMS de la mano de reconocidos especialistas en esclerosis múltiple de nuestro país. Fruto de esta actividad científica, avalada por la Sociedad Española de Neurología, se genera este artículo de revisión que sale publicado en dos partes. Esta primera parte aborda la planificación familiar en las mujeres con esclerosis múltiple, el manejo del embarazo y el papel de la lactancia. Se dirige la atención a la población pediátrica, a las características de la resonancia magnética y a los factores de riesgo geneticoambientales para el desarrollo de la enfermedad en niños, sin olvidar los factores de riesgo de progresión en los adultos. Se actualiza la epidemiología del deterioro cognitivo en los pacientes con esclerosis múltiple, las ventajas e inconvenientes de las herramientas de evaluación disponibles, y los enfoques actuales de manejo, y se insiste en la importancia de la afectación cognitiva en el curso de la enfermedad. Además, se introduce el concepto de medicina individualizada y de precisión, desde el diagnóstico de la enfermedad hasta el tratamiento, con las polémicas que inevitablemente surgen en el manejo de los pacientes, principalmente en lo relacionado con el cambio de tratamiento y el manejo de riesgos asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(1): 31-40, 1 jul., 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las novedades del XXXII Congreso ECTRIMS 2016, presentadas en la IX Reunión Post-ECTRIMS (I)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53692^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
