<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66253</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To investigate the changes in sexual hormones in a selected male population older than 50 years of age. To assess the frequency of biochemical hypogonadism and which factors are related to testosterone levels. Patients and methods: A Cross-sectional study was carried out on 230 Spanish men older than 50 years of age. Blood tests were performed including: total testosterone, SHBG, calculated free testosterone, dehidroepiandrosterone sulfate, androstendione, estradiol, bioavailable estradiol, FSH, LH, and prolactin. Clinical and socio-demographic backgrounds were investigated. The frequency of biochemical hypogonadism was established using total and free testosterone levels as diagnostic criteria. Factors that may influence testosterone levels were evaluated by univariate and multivariate statistical analysis, and a logistic regression model was used to determine which factors can predict biochemical hypogonadism according to free testosterone levels. Results: Age was associated with a significant decrease (p&lt;0.05) in total testosterone (0.6% per year), free testosterone (1.3% per year),dehidroepiandrosterone sulfate (1.8% per year) and bioavailable estradiol (0.69% per year). Moreover, an increase in SHBG, LH, and FSH was observed (p&lt;0.05). According to total testosterone levels, 4.8% of the men were hypogonadal, whereas 24.8% were hypogonadal when free testosterone was considered. In the univariate analysis, obesity, diabetes mellitus and hyperlipemia were related to lower total testosterone levels, while free testosterone levels were lower in men with sedentary life, lower levels of education, obesity or diabetes mellitus. In the multivariate analysis age, diabetes mellitus and obesity were inversely related to total and free testosterone levels. Free testosterone was also inversely related to hyperlipemia. For biochemical hypogonadism, simple logistic regression analysis selected age, sedentary life, obesity and diabetes mellitus. In the multivariate analysis age, obesity and diabetes mellitus had significant independent prognostic value. Conclusions: Starting from 50 years of age, a significant age-related decrease in total testosterone, free testosterone, dehidroepiandrosterone sulfate and bioavailable estradiol is observed. The frequency of biochemical hypogonadism is higher when free testosterone levels are used for diagnosis. Total testosterone levels were related to age, diabetes mellitus and obesity. Free testosterone was related to age, diabetes mellitus, obesity and hyperlipemia. The probability of suffering low free testosterone levels increases with age, diabetes mellitus and/or obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Salom, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queipo Zaragoza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrandis Cortes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jabaloyas, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chuan Nuez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queipo Zaragoza, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar los cambios en las hormonas sexuales en una población masculina mayor de 50 años, conocer la frecuencia de hipogonadismo bioquímico y qué factores se relacionan con los niveles de testosterona. Pacientes y método: Estudio transversal en 230 varones sanos mayores de 50 años. Se realizaron determinaciones de testosterona total, testosterona libre, testosterona biodisponible, sulfato de de hidroepiandrosterona, estradiol total y biodisponible, LH, FSH y prolactina y se averiguaron los antecedentes clínicos y sociodemográficos. Determinamos la frecuencia de hipogonadismo bioquímico. Analizamos los factores que podían influir en los niveles de testosterona total y libre mediante análisis uni y multivariante y realizamos un análisis de regresión logística para conocer los factores que pueden predecir el hipogonadismo bioquímico en base a la testosterona libre. Resultados: A medida que incrementa la edad de los sujetos evaluados, se observan niveles significativamente más bajos (p&lt;0,05) de los niveles de testosterona total (0,6% anual), testosterona libre (1,3% anual), sulfato de de hidroepiandrosterona (1,8% anual) y estradiol biodisponible (0,69% anual), mientras que se observó un incremento de la SHBG, la LH y la FSH (p&gt;0,05).La prevalencia de niveles bajos de testosterona total fue del 4,8%, alcanzando el 24,8% cuando utilizamos como referencia la testosterona libre. La media de los niveles plasmáticos de testosterona total fue significativamente inferior en los varones con obesidad, diabetes mellitus o dislipemia, mientras que la de los niveles de testosterona libre fue menor en aquellos con estilo de vida sedentario, bajo nivel de estudios, obesos o con diabetes mellitus. En el análisis multivariante, la edad, la diabetes y la obesidad se relacionaron inversamente con los niveles de testosterona total. Con la testosterona libre se relacionan los mismos factores además de la dislipemia. En el análisis de regresión logística multivariante para el hipogonadismo bioquímico, la edad, la obesidad y la diabetes fueron las variables con valor predictivo independiente. Conclusión: A partir de los 50 años se produce un descenso significativo de testosterona total, testosterona libre, sulfato de de hidroepiandrosterona y estradiol biodisponible relacionado con la edad. La prevalencia de hipogonadismo bioquímico es mayor si utilizamos la testosterona libre. Los niveles de testosterona total se relacionan además de con la edad, con la diabetes y la obesidad, añadiéndose la dislipemia para la testosterona libre. La probabilidad presentar niveles bajos de testosterona libre aumenta con la edad y es mayor cuando existen antecedentes de diabetes mellitus y/u obesidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(6): 603-610, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66253</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
