<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101698</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endocrinological sequels after cranial radiotherapy due to Cushing´s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The treatment of the tumors of central nervous system consist of surgery, radiation or chemotherapy, which has significantly increased survival rates, but associating in Exchange, multiple complications. Of them, a significant proportion is endocrinological. We present a case of microadenoma hipofisario producing ACTH (Cushing´s disease) and its evolution after 7 years of control post cranial radiation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cid Paris, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alija Merillas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Jiménez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Bustos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriola Pereda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de los tumores del sistema nerviosos central consta de cirugía, radioterapia y/o quimioterapia, lo que ha aumentado significativamente los índices de superviviente, pero asociando, a cambio, múltiples complicaciones. De ellas, una proporción importante son de tipo endocrinológico. Presentamos un caso de microadenoma hipofisario productor de ACTH (enfermedad de Cushing) y su evolución tras 7 años de control post radioterapia craneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;67(2): 105-107, mar.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Secuelas endocrinológicas tras radioterapia craneal por enfermedad de Cushing</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38634^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12271^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50470^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
