<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145696</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug-related acute renal failure in hospitalised patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The information available on the incidence and the characteristics of patients with acute renal failure (ARF) related to drugs is scarce. Objectives: To estimate the incidence of drug-related ARF in hospitalised patients and to compare their characteristics with those of patients with ARF due to other causes. Material and methods: We selected a prospective cohort of patients with ARF during hospital admission (July 2010-July 2011). Information on patients&#146; demographics, medical antecedents, ARF risk factors, ARF severity according to the RIFLE classification and hospital drug administration was collected. We analysed the relationship of drugs with the ARF episodes using Spanish Pharmacovigilance System methods and algorithm. Results: A total of 194 cases had an episode of hospital-acquired ARF. The median age of patients was 72 years [IQR 20]; 60% were men. The ARF incidence during hospitalization was 9.6 per 1,000 admissions. According to the RIFLE classification, a risk of kidney damage or kidney injury was present in 77.8% of cases. In 105 (54.1%) cases, ARF was drug-related; the drugs most frequently involved were diuretics, agents acting on the renin-angiotensin system, immunosuppressants, &amp;#946;-blocking agents, calcium channel blockers, contrast media and non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs. Patients with drug-related ARF had more multi-morbidity, fewer ARF risk factors and lower mortality. Conclusions: Half of ARF episodes during hospitalisation were drug related. Patients with drug-related ARF had higher cardiovascular morbidity than those with ARF related to other causes, but they had a lower frequency of ARF risk factors and mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Guitart, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustí Escasany, Antònia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cereza García, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iavecchia, Lujan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, Judith de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segarra Medrano, Alfons</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Terrades, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté Gallego, Mònica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La información sobre la incidencia de insuficiencia renal aguda (IRA) intrahospitalaria relacionada con medicamentos y las características de los pacientes es escasa. Objetivo: Estimar la incidencia de IRA relacionada con medicamentos en pacientes hospitalizados y comparar sus características con las de los pacientes con IRA relacionada con otras causas. Métodos: Cohorte prospectiva de pacientes con IRA intrahospitalaria (julio de 2010-julio de 2011). Se recogió información sobre características y antecedentes de los pacientes, factores de riesgo y gravedad de la IRA según la clasificación RIFLE, y medicación durante la hospitalización. El análisis de la imputabilidad de los fármacos y la evaluación de la relación causal se realizó siguiendo los métodos y el algoritmo del Sistema Español de Farmacovigilancia. Resultados: Un total de 194 casos presentaron un episodio de IRA intrahospitalaria. La edad mediana de los pacientes fue de 72 años (RI 20); el 60% eran hombres. La incidencia de IRA intrahospitalaria fue de 9,6 por cada 1.000 ingresos. Un 77,8% de los casos presentaron riesgo o daño renal según la clasificación RIFLE. En 105 (54,1%) casos, la IRA se relacionó con medicamentos; principalmente diuréticos, medicamentos que actúan sobre el sistema renina-angiotensina, inmunosupresores, bloqueadores &amp;#946;-adrenérgicos, bloqueantes de los canales de calcio, medios de contraste y antiinflamatorios no esteroideos. La morbilidad cardiovascular fue mayor y la frecuencia de factores de riesgo de IRA y la mortalidad menores en los pacientes con IRA relacionada con medicamentos. Conclusiones: La mitad de los episodios de IRA intrahospitalaria se relacionaron con medicamentos. Los pacientes con IRA relacionada con medicamentos presentaron más antecedentes patológicos cardiovasculares, pero menos factores de riesgo de IRA y una menor mortalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;35(6): 523-532, nov.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia renal aguda relacionada con medicamentos en pacientes hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
