<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146761</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation of the restriction in the use piroxicam in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. A retrospective economic evaluation was performed on the restriction of the use of piroxicam in Spain, a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug, with a proven higher risk of serious gastrointestinal complications compared to other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs with the objective of putting the relevance of these activities into context. Methods. A retrospective cost-effectiveness analysis and a budget impact analysis were performed. Costs and cases of serious gastrointestinal complications were compared in the non-intervention (use of piroxicam) and the intervention scenarios (use of other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs). The cost of serious gastrointestinal complications was obtained from the Diagnosis Related Groups and the cost of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs from usage data in the Spanish national health system. The risk of serious gastrointestinal complications was obtained from epidemiological studies. Results. The regulatory intervention was the dominant option. In that sense, 0.81 euros per treated patient were saved, 2.75 cases of serious gastrointestinal complications were avoided per 10,000 patients and 578,608 euros were saved in total in Spain in the first year following the intervention. Conclusions. It is possible to perform complete economical evaluations on pharmacovigilance actions. The intervention performed by the Spanish Agency for Medicines and Medical Devices, AEMPS on piroxicam not only achieved the objective of preventing adverse drug reactions but also resulted in significant economical savings even under conservative assumptions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maciá Martínez, Miguel-Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Se ha realizado una evaluación económica retrospectiva de la restricción llevada a cabo en España en el uso de piroxicam, debido a un riesgo constatado de complicaciones gastrointestinales graves mayor que el de los otros antiinflamatorios no esteroideos, con el fin de poner en contexto la relevancia de las actividades de farmacovigilancia. Métodos. Se realizaron análisis de coste-efectividad y de impacto presupuestario retrospectivos. Se compararon costes y casos de complicaciones gastrointestinales graves en el escenario sin intervención (uso de piroxicam) y con intervención (uso de otros antiinflamatorios no esteroideos). Se ha obtenido el coste de complicaciones gastrointestinales graves mediante los Grupos Relacionados por el Diagnóstico del conjunto mínimo básico de datos y el de los antiinflamatorios no esteroideos con los datos de consumo en el Sistema Nacional de Salud. El riesgo de complicaciones gastrointestinales graves se estimó a partir de estudios epidemiológicos. Resultados. La intervención reguladora resultó la opción dominante, con un ahorro de 0,81 euros por paciente y 2,75 casos de complicaciones gastrointestinales graves evitados por 10.000 pacientes y un ahorro estimado en toda España de 578.608 euros en el primer año tras la intervención. Conclusiones. Es posible realizar evaluaciones económicas completas sobre actuaciones en farmacovigilancia. La intervención realizada por la Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios sobre piroxicam, además de cumplir con su objetivo de prevenir reacciones adversas, supuso un ahorro significativo, incluso bajo supuestos conservadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(6): 345-352, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146761</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica de la restricción del uso de piroxicam en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27765^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30176</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
