<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154977</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advisory board recommendations on the products Restylane® Skinboosters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Related to the 10th anniversary of Restylane Skinboosters&#153; an advisory board was carried out. It gathered a group of Spanish physicians with the aim of increasing the safety standards, improve treatments, encourage good practice, increase safety and enable better results using this product range. An exhaustive review of published clinical studies demonstrates that Restylane Skinboosters&#153; improve firmness and quality of the skin, reduce roughness, provide long-term hydration and reduce acne scars. It also stimulates creation of collagen type I. Finally, doctors summarized main indications and the most appropriate protocols with these products based on their clinical experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anido, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz De-Cueto, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milotich, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarne, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreu, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ulecia, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Pérez, M Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Félix, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con motivo del 10º aniversario de Restylane Skinboosters® se llevó a cabo una reunión de consenso entre un grupo de médicos españoles con el objetivo de aumentar el estándar de seguridad, mejorar y dar coherencia a los tratamientos, favorecer la buena praxis, posibilitar mejores resultados y aumentar la seguridad con esta gama de productos. Se realizó una revisión exhaustiva de los estudios clínicos publicados que demuestran cómo Restylane Skinboosters® mejora la calidad de la piel, disminuyendo la rugosidad, aumentando la firmeza e hidratación a largo plazo y reduciendo las cicatrices de acné, así como estimulando la creación de colágeno tipo I. Por último, los participantes pusieron en común su experiencia clínica para realizar un resumen de las indicaciones y los protocolos más empleados con esta gama de tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;42(2): 187-195, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reunión de consenso para recomendaciones sobre la gama de productos Restylane Skinboosters®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29169</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23818^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
