<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61431</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of breastfeeding in the population attending Evolution of breastfeeding in the population attending</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to estimate the prevalenceand duration of breastfeeding, and how this has variedin the population attending the Mendillorri health centrebetween the years 2002 and 2006. We studied two cohortsof neonates (born in 2002 and 2006, respectively),who attended our centre, through a revision of theircomputerised clinical history. The prevalence figures ofthe different lactation categories were compared, with amonthly periodicity from the time of maternity dischargeuntil the first year of life. Home visits by nurses werealso registered where these occurred.The conclusion drawn from the results is that thepanorama of maternal lactation has changed substantiallyin this area following hospital discharge; theresults show that the prevalence figures over the firstyear of life are significantly higher in 2006 comparedwith 2002(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barace, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baztán, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armendáriz, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tiene como objetivo estimar cuál es laprevalencia y duración de la lactancia materna y cómoha variado en la población que atiende al centro de saludde Mendillorri entre los años 2002 y 2006. Se estudiarondos cohortes de neonatos (nacidos en 2002 y nacidosen 2006), que acudían a nuestro centro, medianterevisión de la historia clínica informatizada. Se comparanlas cifras de prevalencia de las diversas categoríasde lactancia en el momento del alta de la maternidad, ycon periodicidad mensual, hasta el primer año de vida.Se registra también si se realizó la visita domiciliaria deenfermería.De los resultados obtenidos se puede concluir queel panorama de la lactancia materna ha cambiado sustancialmenteen esta zona tras al alta hospitalaria, demostrándoseque las cifras de prevalencia a lo largo delprimer año de vida son significativamente superioresen 2006 versus 2002(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(1): 43-49, ene.-abr. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61431</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la lactancia materna en la población que atiende el Centro de Salud de Mendillorri</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
