<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113358</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of Armeo ®Spring during the chronic phase of stroke. Study in mild to moderate cases of hemiparesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of a gravity-supported, computer-enhanced device (Armeo®Spring) for upper limb rehabilitation in chronic stroke patients. Material and methods: We included 23 chronic hemiparetic patients (chronicity: 328 ± 90.8 days; distribution: 17 men and 6 women) aged 54.6 ± 9.5 years, who had sustained ischaemic stroke (n = 12) or haemorrhagic stroke (n = 11). All patients completed 36 one-hour sessions using the Armeo®Spring system. Arm movement was assessed at the beginning and end of the treatment programme and once more 4 months later. Main outcome measurements covered structure, activity, and function, as per the International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health: Modified Ashworth Scale, Motricity Index (MI), Fugl-Meyer Assessment Scale (FM), Motor Assessment Scale (MAS), Manual Function Test (MFT), and Wolf Motor Function Test (WMFT). Results: Repeated measures ANOVA showed significant improvement (time effect) for all function scales (P &lt; .01 for FM and MI) and activity scales (P&lt;.01 for MAS, MFT and WMFT-ability, and P &lt; .05 WMFT-time) without significant changes in muscle tone. The post-hoc analysis (Bonferroni) showed different evolutionary patterns for function and activity measurements, and clear benefits related to Armeo®Spring training, especially on activity scales. Conclusions: Armeo®Spring is an effective tool for rehabilitating the affected arm in patients with hemiparesis secondary to ictus, even in the chronic stage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torromé, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moliner, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baldoví, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la eficacia del sistema Armeo®Spring para la rehabilitación del miembro superior en pacientes crónicos que han presentado un ictus. Material y métodos: Veintitrés pacientes (17 varones y 6 mujeres), con una edad media ± desviación estándar de 54,6 ± 9,5 años, que presentaban una hemiparesia crónica  (cronicidad de 328 ± 90,8 días) secundaria a ictus isquémico (n = 12) o hemorrágico (n = 11), se incluyeron en este estudio. Todos los pacientes completaron 36 sesiones de una hora de duración con el sistema Armeo®Spring y fueron valorados al inicio, al fin y 4 meses después de completar el tratamiento con escalas dirigidas a los dominios de estructura, función y actividad de la Clasificación Internacional del Funcionamiento, de la Discapacidad y de la Salud (CIF) incluyendo: Ashworth Modified Scale, Motricity Index (MI), Fugl-Meyer  ssessment Scale (FM), Motor Assessment Scale (MAS), Manual Function Test (MFT) y Wolf Motor Function (WMFT). Resultados: Un ANOVA de medidas repetidas mostró una mejoría significativa (efecto tiempo)  en todas las escalas de función (p &lt; 0,01 en FM y MI) y actividad (p &lt; 0,01 en MAS, MFT, WMFT Habilidad y p &lt; 0,05 en WMFT-tiempo), sin que se apreciaran cambios significativos en el tono muscular. El estudio post hoc (Bonferroni) mostró un patrón de evolución diferente entre las escalas de función y las de actividad, con un beneficio directamente ligado al entrenamiento, especialmente en las escalas de actividad. Conclusiones: El Armeo®Spring constituye una herramienta eficaz para la rehabilitación del miembro superior afectado en pacientes con una hemiparesia debida a un ictus, incluso en estadios crónicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(5): 261-267, jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del sistema Armeo ®Spring en la fase crónica del ictus. Estudio en hemiparesias leves-moderadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
