<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95588</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The conflict in nurses management practice: An analysis of scientific production brazilian</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to identify and analyze the scientific production's Brazilian Nursing about conflicts in nursing, including among the publications that was searched the conflict in nurse's management practice. This is a bibliographical review of the theses and dissertations' abstracts compiled by the Studies and Research in Nursing Center of the Brazilian Nursing Association. One hundred forty-five studies were localized with the word conflict in the abstract's title or body. The content analysis was used to classify the works into three social universes that reveal the presence of conflict in nursing work: one related to education, another patient care team and the last, to the user community. Thirteen studies boarded the conflicts in the nurse's management exercise. It proposes a reflection on the phenomenon of conflict with finalidea to interpret it in the management practice of nurses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Teresinha Guerra, Soeli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Horto Fontoura Cartana, Maria do</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedes dos Santos, José Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giacomelli Prochnow, Adelina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo tuvo como objetivos identificar y analizar la producción científica de la enfermería brasileña sobre los conflictos, destacando las investigaciones acerca de los conflictos en la gerencia de enfermería. Se trata de una investigación bibliográfica de los resúmenes de las tesis de maestría y doctorado compiladas por el Centro de Investigaciones en Enfermería de la Asociación Brasilera de Enfermería. Se encontraron 145 estudios con la palabra conflicto (en la búsqueda, se utilizó la palabra en portugués: conflito) en su título o en el cuerpo del resumen. Se utilizó el análisis de contenido para clasificar los trabajos en tres universos sociales que demuestran la presencia de conflictos en el trabajo de enfermería: uno relacionado con la enseñanza; otro, con el equipo de asistencia; y, el último, con la comunidad usuaria. Trece estudios abordaban el tema conflicto en la gerencia de enfermería. Se propone una reflexión sobre el fenómeno del conflicto con la finalidad de interpretarlo en el ejercicio gerencial del enfermero (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(2/3): 147-151, sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El conflicto en la gerencia de enfermería: un análisis de la producción científica brasileña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4723</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
