<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92484</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Limbal stem cell deficiency following multiple intravitreal injections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 68 year-old male with idiopathic choroidal polypoidal vasculopathy receivedseven intravitreal injections of bevacizumab in the supero-nasal quadrant. He later developeda localized limbal stem cell deficiency which required limbal transplantation from thesame eye. Two months after surgery, a slight improvement of visual acuity was noted, alongwith an intact ocular surface, clear cornea and decreased inflammation.Discussion: Repeated surgical trauma on the limbus and surrounding areas may damage thelimbal stem cells, giving rise to a corneal epitheliopathy due to iatrogenic limbal deficiency.Repeated intravitreal injections may be considered as one of the possible causes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz, M. F. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capella, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez de Toledo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 68 años con vasculopatía polipoidea coroidea idiopática que requirió7 inyecciones intravítreas de bevacizumab en el cuadrante nasal-superior. Posteriormentedesarrolló una insuficiencia limbar localizada que requirió un autoinjerto limbar homolateral.A los dos meses de la cirugía, existía una discreta mejoría de la agudeza visual,observándose una córnea más transparente, un epitelio íntegro y una notable mejoría en laalteración de la superficie ocular.Discusión: Los traumatismos quirúrgicos repetidos sobre la región limbar o zonas próximas aella pueden ocasionar una alteración de las células madre limbares originando una epiteliopatíacorneal por insuficiencia limbar yatrogénica, entre cuyas causas deben considerarselas inyecciones intravítreas frecuentes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(3): 89-92, mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92484</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia limbar secundaria a múltiples inyecciones intravítreas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54215^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30006^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30006^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
