<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121129</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of proximal radioulnar synostosis using a posterior interosseous antegrade flow pedicled flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to determine the different therapeutic options described for the treatment of radioulnar synostosis, and report our experience with posterior interosseous antegrade flow pedicled flap with technical amendments. Two patients, who were treated with the designed flap, and with more than one year of follow-up, were reviewed. The technical innovations, end result and complications are described. In the two cases described, there was no recurrence of synostosis, which is the most frequent complication described in this condition, and no postoperative complications were observed. In the literature, many filler materials, from artificial to biological, free or vascularized, have been used the radioulnar space after excision of synostosis. The technique that provides the best results is the interposition of muscle or vascularized adipofascial flaps. The interosseous posterior antegrade flow pedicled flap is reliable, with a low morbidity, and is an effective alternative for the treatment of proximal radioulnar synostosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illan-Franco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo-Santiago, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es estudiar las diferentes opciones terapéuticas descritas para el tratamiento de la sinostosis radiocubital y, aportar nuestra experiencia con las modificaciones técnicas introducidas con posterioridad. Hemos revisado 2 pacientes con más de un año de evolución, que fueron operados con el colgajo reseñado; describimos las novedades técnicas, el resultado final y las complicaciones. En los 2 casos descritos existe ausencia de recidiva de sinostosis, complicación más frecuente descrita en esta enfermedad, con ausencia de complicaciones postoperatorias. En la literatura se han empleado numerosos materiales interpuestos en el espacio radiocubital tras la exéresis de la sinostosis, desde artificiales hasta biológicos libres o vascularizados; siendo la técnica de interposición de colgajos musculares o adipofascial vascularizados, la que ofrece los mejores resultados. El colgajo interóseo posterior pediculado de flujo anterógrado es una alternativa fiable, de poca morbilidad y, efectiva para el tratamiento de la sinostosis radiocubital proximal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(2): 120-124, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121129</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la sinostosis radiocubital proximal mediante la interposición de colgajo interóseo posterior de flujo anterógrado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12318^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13961^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14856^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
