<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167207</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicenter registry on inflammatory myositis from the Rheumatology Society in Madrid, Spain: descriptive analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze clinical characteristics, survival and causes of death of patients diagnosed with autoimmune inflammatory myositis in the REMICAM registry from the Society of Rheumatology in the Community of Madrid (SORCOM). Methods. Multicenter cohort of patients diagnosed with autoimmune inflammatory myopathy with follow-up between January 1980 and December 2014. A total of 313 variables concerning demographic, clinical and morbidity data were collected, and a comparison was performed between clinical subgroups. Results. A total of 479 patients were recruited from 12 centers, with 14% of patients lost to follow-up. Seventy-four percent of cases were women, age at diagnosis of 44±23 years and a mean follow-up period of 10±8 years. The most frequent clinical subgroups were primary myositis (PM 29%, DM 22%), followed by overlap myositis (20.5%), juvenile myositis (18%), myositis associated with cancer (8%), immune-mediated necrotizing myositis (1%) and inclusion body myositis (1%). During the follow-up period, a total of 114 deaths (28%) were registered, the main causes being cancer (24%), infections (23%) and cardiovascular events (21%). Conclusions. A total of 479 patients were recruited in the REMICAM registry of inflammatory myopathies. Including sociodemographic, clinical and prognostic information, it represents the largest Spanish multicenter registry to date in rheumatology, and constitutes an important source for conducting further substudies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-de la Peña, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomero, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbadillo, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almodóvar, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, Indalecio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo-Ibáñez, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moruno, Henry</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Robledillo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuño, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreira, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado, Valentina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Longo, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lojo, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-De Yébenes, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joven, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larena, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir las características clínicas, mortalidad y causas de muerte de una serie de pacientes diagnosticados de miositis inflamatoria idiopática del registro REMICAM de la Sociedad de Reumatología de la Comunidad de Madrid (SORCOM). Métodos. Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo multicéntrico de una cohorte de pacientes con diagnóstico de miositis inflamatoria idiopática en seguimiento en servicios de reumatología de hospitales de la Comunidad de Madrid entre enero de 1980 y diciembre de 2014. Se han recogido hasta un total de 313 variables acerca de aspectos demográficos, clínicos y de morbimortalidad, y se ha realizado una comparación entre subgrupos clínicos. Resultados. Se han reclutado 479 pacientes procedentes de 12 centros, con un 14% de pérdidas durante el periodo de seguimiento. El 74% de los casos eran mujeres, una edad al diagnóstico de 44±23 años, y una media de seguimiento de 10±8 años. Los subgrupos clínicos más frecuentes fueron las formas primarias (PM 29%, DM 22%), seguidas de síndrome de solapamiento (20,5%), miopatías juveniles (18%), miopatías asociadas a cáncer (8%), miopatías necrosantes inmunomediadas (1%) y miositis por cuerpos de inclusión (1%). Durante el periodo de seguimiento se produjeron un total de 114 fallecimientos (28%), siendo las principales causas el cáncer (24%), las infecciones (23%) y los eventos cardiovasculares (21%). Conclusiones. En el registro REMICAM de miopatías inflamatorias de la Comunidad de Madrid se han reclutado 479 casos de miositis inflamatoria idiopática con datos sociodemográficos, clínicos y pronósticos, suponiendo el mayor registro multicéntrico español en el ámbito de la Reumatología hasta la fecha, y constituyendo una fuente importante para la realización de posteriores subestudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);13(6): 331-337, nov.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167207</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro de pacientes con miopatía inflamatoria de la Sociedad Madrileña de Reumatología: análisis descriptivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
