<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30460</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Studying marine microorganisms from space</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microorganisms are but a few micrometers in diameter and are not visible to the naked eye. Yet, the large numbers of microorganisms present in the oceans and the global impact of their activities make it possible to observe them from space. Here a few examples of how microorganisms can be studied from satellites are presented. The first case is the best known: the main pigment used in photosynthesis (chlorophyll a) can be determined from satellites. These kinds of studies have contributed a tremendous amount of understanding about the distribution and dynamics of primary production in the oceans. Two other examples will concern analysis of heterotrophic prokaryotic production and estimates of dimethyl sulfide (DMS) concentration and flux to the atmosphere. These three processes are of fundamental importance for the functioning of the biosphere. Marine microbes carry out about half of the total primary production in the planet. A substantial fraction of the respiration in the oceans is due to the activity of heterotrophic prokaryotes. Finally, the flux of DMS to the atmosphere is believed to constitute one of the mechanisms by which the biota can regulate climate. The global implications of microbial processes in the oceans can only be addressed with the help of satellites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Springer-Verlag Ibérica</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los microorganismos no miden más que unos micrómetros de diámetro y no son visibles a simple vista. Sin embargo, el gran número de microorganismos presentes en los océanos y el impacto global de sus actividades hacen posible su observación desde el espacio. Este estudio presenta algunos ejemplos de cómo pueden estudiarse los microorganismos desde los satélites. El primer caso es el más conocido: el principal pigmento utilizado en la fotosíntesis (la clorofila a) puede determinarse desde un satélite. Este tipo de estudios han contribuido de forma espectacular a la comprensión de la distribución y dinámica de la producción primaria en los océanos. Otros dos ejemplos tienen que ver con la producción de los procariotas heterótrofos y con las estimaciones de la concentración de sulfuro de dimetilo (DMS) y de su flujo hacia la atmósfera. Estos tres procesos son de enorme importancia para el funcionamiento de la biosfera. Los microorganismos marinos llevan a cabo aproximadamente la mitad de la producción primaria total del planeta. Una parte importante de la respiración en los océanos se debe a la actividad de los procariotas heterótrofos. Por último, el flujo de DMS hacia la atmósfera constituye uno de los mecanismos por los cuales la biota puede regular el clima. La implicación global de los procesos microbianos en los océanos sólo puede estudiarse con ayuda de los satélites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;5(4): 195-200, dic. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El estudio de los microorganismos marinos desde el espacio</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Simó, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrós-Alió, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30460</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13827^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22347</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11820</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2784</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19132</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32022</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
