<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80648</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acceptance of a soy proteína</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the acceptance of a soy proteína drink in accordance organoleptic characteristics. Methodology: The study was carried out in 172 individuals, of both gender among 14-85 years, non smokers, of diverse socio-economic strata. The sample was distributed in 4 groups of ages: adolescents (14 to 20 years), young adults (21 to 40 years), contemporary adults (41 to 60 years) and old adults (+ 60 years) who participated voluntarily for taste testing the drinks. They tasted three beverages: soy reconstituted; cow milk with soy in equal´s parts and cow milk reconstituted. Results: showed that for the flavour and scent, the soy drink had rejection of 60,5% and 45% respectively in comtemporary and adolescent adults, of both sexes, while in the old adults had good acceptance. At level of high education and higher economic entrance the cow milk had mayor acceptance, while the soy drinks and combination cow milk-soy had acceptance to technical, primary level and strata IV and V. We conclude that the soy drink, in spite of the rejection, possesses a tendency to the acceptability and consumption on the part of an old population of adults and people of low economic income(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morón Salim de, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arpaia Manfredi, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oviedo, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano, Liseti</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la aceptación de una bebida a base de proteína de soya de acuerdo a  sus características organolépticas. Metodología: Participaron 172 individuos voluntarios de ambos sexos entre 14-85 años de edad, no fumadores, de diversos estratos socio-económicos. Los participantes fueron distribuidos en 4 grupos de edades: adolescentes (14 a 20 años), adultos jóvenes (21 a 40 años), adultos contemporáneos (41 a 60 años) y adultos mayores (+ 60 años), quienes participaron voluntariamente en la degustación de las bebidas. Se prepararon tres bebidas: soya reconstituida; leche de vaca con soya en partes iguales y leche de vaca reconstituida. Resultados: Para el sabor y olor, la bebida de soya fue rechazada en adultos contemporáneos y adolescentes con 60,5% y 45% respectivamente, sin diferencia por sexo, mientras que en adultos mayores hubo buena aceptación. En personas con educación superior y mayor ingreso económico, la leche de vaca tuvo mayor aceptación, mientras que las bebidas de soya y combinación soya-leche de vaca tuvieron mejor aceptación en individuos con nivel técnico, primario y estratos IV y V. Conclusión: La bebida de soya, a pesar del rechazo en ciertos grupos, tiene buena aceptabilidad en los adultos mayores y las personas de menor ingreso económico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;15(3): 118-122, jul.-sep.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceptación de una bebida a base de proteína de soya</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5556</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33047^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51395</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
