<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17778</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-efficacy in eating management. The Spanish version of the Eating Self-Efficacy Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyses the factorial structure and psychometric properties of the Eating Self-Efficacy Scale (ESES; Glynn y Ruderman, 1986), an instrument developed to measure self-efficacy in relation to food intake. Two hundred and ninety-eight Spanish subjects participated, distributed in two groups: normal-weight group (n= 193), and overweight and obese group (n= 105). The findings reveal evidence of two situational factors (Negative Affect and Soccially Acceptable Circumstances). The confirmatory factor analysis corroborated the two-factor model on an independent sample (N= 345). The results show a high level of internal consistency. Significant correlations were found between the ESES scores and other variables that we hypothesised would be related to them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrocal, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio analiza la estructura factorial y las propiedades psicométricas de la Eating Sel-Efficacy Scale (ESES; Glynn y Ruderman, 1986), un instrumento desarrollado para medir la autoeficacia en relación a la ingesta alimentaria. En el estudio han participado 298 sujetos distribuidos en dos grupos: con normopeso (n=193) y con exceso de peso (n=105). Los análisis factoriales exploratorios apoyan la existencia de una estructura bidimensional, con los factores Afecto Negativo y Circunstancias Socialmente Aceptables. El análisis factorial confirmatorio corrobora este modelo de dos factores con una muestra independiente (N=345). La escala y sus subdimensiones muestran un elevado nivel de consistencia interna. Por último, se han encontrado asociaciones entre las puntuaciones a la ESES y otras variables con las que hipotéticamente estarían relacionadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(1): 36-40, feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoeficacia en el control de la conducta de ingesta. Adaptación al castellano de la Eating Self-Efficacy Scale</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
