<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167584</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost associated with malnutrition prior to disease and disease-related malnutrition in the elderly: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Malnutrition is a health problem which affects a high percentage of old people since the physical and psychosocial changes common to this period of life favor it in this group. In addition, aging population has a high prevalence of chronic illnesses and acute pathologies which can affect their nutritional state negatively, leading to malnutrition related to illness. Objective: The aim of this systematic revision was to analyze the economic costs related to malnutrition in old people and to discover whether there were differences between economic costs of pre-existing malnutrition prior to illness and malnutrition because of disease. Method: A bibliographic search was carried out in the databases of Pubmed, Web of Science and Scopus, for the period between 2000 and 2016. Results: A total of 1,001 articles were found and 19 were selected using inclusion criteria. Of these, eleven analyzed the costs of pre-existing malnutrition prior to illness, seven analyzed the costs of malnutrition related to illness and one, both situations. Conclusions: In general, malnutrition increased health costs as a result of hospital admissions, greater number of readmissions and greater demand on health resources. Moreover, in the studies analyzed, pre-existing malnutrition prior to illness implied greater costs than those related to the actual illness; therefore, it would be convenient to establish selection and preventive policies on malnutrition in old people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo-García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amo-Saus, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Valero, Ana Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano-Sotos, Ana Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la desnutrición es un problema de salud que afecta en un elevado porcentaje al colectivo de ancianos, ya que los cambios físicos y psicosociales propios de esta etapa de la vida favorecen la aparición de la misma. Además, la población anciana presenta una elevada prevalencia en enfermedades crónicas y patologías agudas que pueden afectar negativamente al estado nutricional, provocando desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad. Objetivo: el propósito de esta revisión sistemática fue analizar el coste económico relacionado con la desnutrición en personas mayores y si existen diferencias entre los costes de la desnutrición previa a la enfermedad y la desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad. Método: se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica en las bases de datos Pubmed, Web of Science y Scopus, para el periodo comprendido entre 2000 y 2016. Resultados: se encontraron un total de 1.001 artículos y, utilizando los criterios de inclusión, se seleccionaron 19. De ellos, once analizaron los costes de la desnutrición previa a la enfermedad; siete, los costes de la desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad, y uno, ambas situaciones. Conclusiones: la desnutrición en general incrementa el gasto sanitario debido al aumento de estancias hospitalarias, al mayor número de reingresos y a la mayor demanda de recursos sanitarios. Además, en los estudios analizados, la desnutrición previa a la enfermedad implicó mayores costes que la relacionada con la enfermedad, por lo que sería conveniente establecer políticas de cribado y prevención de la desnutrición en los ancianos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(5): 1215-1225, sept.-oct. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costes asociados a la desnutrición previa a la enfermedad y la desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad en ancianos: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16672</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
