<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33792</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis and phenytoin. Factors linked to a higher risk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Stevens-Johnson syndrome (SJS) and toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN) are severe, although not very common, clinical skin pictures that are usually related to the use of medication. Several antiepileptic drugs, including phenytoin, have been linked to SJS/TEN. Some authors have described an increased risk for SJS/TEN when phenytoin is associated to radiotherapy, while others report the possibility of an increased risk when it is associated to corticoids. Development. This work includes a review of the spontaneous reports of suspected cases of phenytoin-linked SJS/TEN recorded in the database of the Pharmacovigilance Department at Pfizer-España between October 2000 and December 2003. Nine cases compatible with SJS/TEN were found; four occurred in cancer patients that had received radiotherapy, three of whom were also treated with corticoids. Discussion and conclusions. After reviewing the spontaneously reported cases in the database of the Pharmacovigilance Department at Pfizer-España as well as the cases in the literature, it can be concluded that when it comes to indicating a prophylactic antiepileptic treatment for cancer patients with cerebral metastasis, the clinician must take into account the existence of a greater risk of SJS/TEN if the patient is going to receive radiotherapy. If the patient already presents a history of skin rashes following administration of an antiepileptic drug, care must be taken in choosing another because phenytoin together with carbamazepine, phenobarbital and lamotrigine have all been linked to SJS/TEN. Cross-sensitivity of carbamazepine and barbiturates with phenytoin has been observed. Gabapentin and valproic acid could be considered as therapeutic options in such cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Stevens-Johnson (SSJ) y la necrólisis epidérmica tóxica (NET) son cuadros cutáneos graves, aunque poco frecuentes, que en la mayoría de los casos se relacionan con el consumo de fármacos. Varios antiepilépticos se han asociado a SSJ/NET, entre ellos la fenitoína. Algunos autores han descrito un aumento del riesgo de SSJ/NET cuando la fenitoína se asocia a radioterapia, y otros han informado de la posibilidad de un mayor riesgo cuando se asocia al empleo de corticoides. Desarrollo. En este trabajo se realiza una revisión de las notificaciones espontáneas de sospecha de SSJ/NET asociados a fenitoína registradas en la base de datos del Departamento de Farmacovigilancia de Pfizer-España, desde octubre de 2000 hasta diciembre de 2003.Se han recogido nueve casos compatibles con SSJ/NET; cuatro ocurrieron en pacientes oncológicos que habían recibido radioterapia y, además, tres de ellos se trataron también con corticoides.Discusión y conclusiones. Tras revisar los casos de notificación espontánea de la base de datos del Departamento de Farmacovigilancia de Pfizer-España, y tras revisar los casos de la literatura, se concluye que a la hora de indicar un tratamiento antiepiléptico profiláctico en pacientes oncológicos con metástasis cerebrales, debería valorarse la existencia de un mayor riesgo de presentar SSJ/NET si el paciente va a recibir radioterapia. Si el paciente ya presenta antecedentes de reacción cutánea con un antiepiléptico, la elección de otro debe realizarse con precaución, ya que tanto la fenitoína, como la carbamacepina, el fenobarbital y la lamotrigina se han asociado a SSJ/NET, y se ha observado sensibilidad cruzada de la carbamacepina y los barbitúricos con la fenitoína. La gabapentina y el ácido valproico podrían considerarse como opciones terapéuticas en estos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(11): 1056-1060, jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Stevens-Johnson, necrólisis epidérmica tóxica y fenitoína. Factores asociados a un aumento del riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Reneses, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayani, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Colombo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Criado, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33792</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10867</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
