<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134204</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The provision of occupational risk during pregnancy is in order to protect the health of the working mother and the child. This feature exists in Spain since 1999 and has been considered as a professional contingency since 2007. In order to improve the management of this provision, a descriptive study of requests and complaints in our Provincial Office in the last 4 years has been performed. Maternal age was between 25 and 46 years with an average age of 34 years. The gestational age at which the risk was mostly recognized (65.93%) was above the 24th week of pregnancy. 89.5 % of requests were from health workers of Andalusian Health Service, so that the alleged risk was mainly biological. However, the risks for which provision were recognized were predominantly ergonomic (56%) followed by psychosocial (38%), biological (21%), physical agents (6%) and chemicals agents (3%). The total number of applications remained stable in these 4 years, but the number of complaints decreased significantly due to an increasing of specificity in the criteria of physician evaluating and workers information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toscano Niebla, Francisca Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez Granados, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabuchola Moreno, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gallego, Mª Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes López, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dirección Provincial en los últimos 4 años. La edad materna estuvo comprendida entre 25 y 46 años con una media de edad de 34 años. La edad gestacional a la que se reconoció el riesgo fue mayoritariamente (65,93%) por encima de la semana 24 de embarazo. El 89,5% de las solicitudes correspondieron a trabajadoras sanitarias del Servicio Andaluz de Salud, por lo que el riesgo principalmente alegado fue el biológico. Sin embargo los riesgos por los que se reconoció la prestación fueron predominantemente ergonómicos (56%) seguidos de psicosociales (38%), biológicos (21%), agentes físicos (6%) y agentes químicos (3%). El número total de solicitudes ha permanecido estable en estos 4 años, mientras que el número de reclamaciones ha disminuido significativamente al aumentar la concreción en los criterios del médico evaluador y la información a las trabajadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(supl.1): 229-233, 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión y análisis descriptivo de la prestación económica por riesgo laboral en el embarazo gestionada por el INSS en la Dirección Provincial de Málaga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
