<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131247</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunomodulatory properties of stem mesenchymal cells in autoimmune diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Autoimmune diseases are a cluster of disorders characterized by a failure of the immune tolerance and a hyperactivation of the immune system that leads to a chronic inflammation state and the damage of several organs. The medications currently used to treat these diseases usually consist of immunosuppressive drugs that have significant systemic toxic effects and are associated with an increased risk of opportunistic infections. Recently, several studies have demonstrated that mesenchymal stem cells have immunomodulatory properties, a feature that make them candidates to be used in the treatment of autoimmune diseases. In the present study, we reviewed the role of this therapy in the treatment of systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjögren's syndrome, systemic sclerosis, Crohn's disease and multiple sclerosis, as well as the potential risks associated with its use  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Alonso, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Díaz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Berná, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades autoinmunitarias son un grupo de trastornos en los que existe un fallo en la tolerancia inmunitaria y, con ello, una hiperactivación del sistema inmunológico, de lo que se deriva un estado de inflamación crónica y un potencial daño multiorgánico. Los fármacos empleados en la actualidad para el tratamiento de este grupo de enfermedades son agentes con mayor o menor efecto inmunodepresor, con importante toxicidad sistémica y potencial riesgo de infecciones oportunistas. Se han descrito, en distintos estudios, las propiedades inmunomoduladoras de las células madre mesenquimales, características que las hacen candidatas a ser empleadas en el tratamiento de las enfermedades autoinmunitarias. Realizamos una revisión de la situación actual de esta línea terapéutica en lupus eritematoso sistémico, síndrome de Sjögren, esclerosis sistémica, enfermedad de Crohn y esclerosis múltiple, así como de los potenciales riesgos derivados de su empleo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);144(2): 88-91, ene. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acción inmunomoduladora de las células madre mesenquimales en las enfermedades autoinmunitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34204^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34204^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34204^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
