<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150213</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social cognition interventions for persons with schizophrenia: evidence and clinical practice guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although most of the research conducted up to now has shown that interventions in social cognition are effective in the rehabilitation of persons with schizophrenia, there are still no clinical practice recommendations on the topic. Their development could facilitate the clinical work, resource management and the care provided to persons with such a disorder. This article addresses this need and performs a systematic review of the identified high-quality scientific evidence and develops clinical practice recommendations. A total of 40 clinical trials and 1 meta-analysis evaluating the effects of social cognition interventions for persons with schizophrenia were selected for the present study. Taking into account the evidence available and its quality, the authors developed three clinical practice recommendations on the positive effects of these interventions. The analysis of the evidence of the quality of the studies shows that more randomized controlled trials with larger sample sizes and longer follow-ups are needed in order to establish more accurately the efficacy and effectiveness of social cognition interventions and therefore to favor the generalization of the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villegas-Miranda, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mas-Expósito, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amador-Campos, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lalucat-Jo, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque la mayoría de la investigación llevada a cabo hasta el momento ha mostrado que las intervenciones en cognición social son eficaces para la rehabilitación de las personas con esquizofrenia, todavía no se han establecido recomendaciones de práctica clínica. Su desarrollo podría facilitar el trabajo clínico, la gestión de recursos y la atención que reciben las personas con este trastorno. El presente trabajo aborda esta necesidad; se hace una revisión sistemática de las evidencias científicas de alta calidad identificadas y se formulan recomendaciones de práctica clínica a partir de estas evidencias. Se han seleccionado para el presente estudio un total de 40 ensayos clínicos y 1 metanálisis que tratan sobre los efectos de las intervenciones en cognición social en personas con esquizofrenia. Teniendo en cuenta la evidencia disponible, y su calidad, se desarrollan tres recomendaciones de práctica clínica relacionadas con los efectos positivos de este tipo de intervenciones. El análisis de las evidencias de calidad de los estudios ha puesto de manifiesto que son necesarios más ensayos controlados y aleatorizados, con mayores muestras y seguimientos más largos, para establecer, de manera más precisa, la eficacia y efectividad de las intervenciones en cognición social y, por tanto, favorecer la generalización de resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;44(1): 30-43, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones en cognición social para personas con esquizofrenia: evidencias y recomendaciones para la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
