<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143220</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dual antiplatelet therapy for 6 months vs 12 months after new-generation drug-eluting stent implantation: matched analysis of ESTROFA-DAPT and ESTROFA-2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The recommendation for dual antiplatelet therapy following drug-eluting stent implantation ranges from 6 months to 12 months or beyond. Recent trials have suggested the safety of a 6-month dual antiplatelet therapy regimen, yet certain caveats to these studies limit the applicability of this shorter duration dual antiplatelet therapy strategy in real world settings. Methods: A registry was constructed with consecutive recruitment of patients undergoing new-generation drug-eluting stent implantation and prescribed 6 months of dual antiplatelet therapy. Propensity score matching was undertaken with a historical cohort of patients treated with second-generation drug-eluting stents who received 12 months of dual antiplatelet therapy from the ESTROFA-2 registry. The sample size was calculated using a noninferiority basis and the primary endpoint was the combination of cardiac death, myocardial infarction, revascularization, or major bleeding at 12 months. Results: The analysis included 1286 patients in each group, with no significant differences in baseline characteristics. The primary endpoint occurred in 5.0% and 6.6% in the 6-month and 12-month groups, respectively (P = .001 for noninferiority). The incidence of definite or probable stent thrombosis was 0.5% and 0.7% in the 6-month and 12-month groups, respectively (P = .4). Major bleeding events were lower in the 6-month group than in the 12-month group (0.8% vs 1.4%; P = .2) Conclusions: In selected patients in this large multicenter study, the safety and efficacy of a 6-month dual antiplatelet therapy regimen after implantation of new-generation drug-eluting stents appeared to be noninferior to those of a 12-month dual antiplatelet therapy regimen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Recalde, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Navarro, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Moreno, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosa, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Prado, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oteo Domínguez, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Crespo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diarte de Miguel, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrebola Moreno, Antonio L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Camarero, Tamara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Menchero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abdul-Jawad Altisent, Omar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tizón Marcos, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andraka, Leire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Hernández, José M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zavala, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Palop, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cascón, José D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El periodo de uso recomendado del tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble tras implante de stents farmacoactivos va de los 6 a los 12 meses o más. Ensayos recientes indican que es seguro utilizar un tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble durante 6 meses, si bien ciertas limitaciones de estos estudios hacen que sea escasa la aplicabilidad de esta estrategia de tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble de menor duración en la práctica clínica real. Métodos: Se puso en marcha un registro con la inscripción de pacientes consecutivos a los que se había implantado stent farmacoactivo de nueva generación seguido de una prescripción de 6 meses de tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble. Se realizó una igualación por puntuación de propensión con una cohorte histórica de pacientes tratados con stentsfarmacoactivos de segunda generación que recibieron luego 12 meses de tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble del registro ESTROFA-2. El tamaño muestral se calculó para el criterio de no inferioridad y el objetivo principal fue la combinación de muerte cardiaca, infarto de miocardio, revascularización o hemorragia mayor a los 12 meses. Resultados: Se incluyó en el análisis a 1.286 pacientes de cada grupo, que no presentaban diferencias significativas en sus características basales. Se produjeron episodios del objetivo principal en el 5,0 y el 6,6% de los pacientes en los grupos de 6 y de 12 meses respectivamente (p = 0,001 para no inferioridad). La incidencia de trombosis del stent definitiva o probable fue del 0,5 y el 0,7% en los grupos de tratamiento de 6 y 12 meses respectivamente (p = 0,4). Los episodios de hemorragia mayor fueron menos en el grupo de 6 meses que en el de 12 (el 0,8 y el 1,4%; p = 0,2). Conclusiones: En pacientes seleccionados de este amplio estudio multicéntrico, la seguridad y la eficacia de 6 meses de tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble después del implante de stents farmacoactivos de nueva generación fueron no inferiores a las observadas con 12 meses de tratamiento antiagregante plaquetario combinado doble (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(10): 838-845, oct. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia antiplaquetaria doble de 6 o de 12 meses tras implante de stents farmacoactivos de nueva generación: análisis emparejado de los registros ESTROFA-DAPT y ESTROFA-2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54164^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
