<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-11772</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of chronic pain among the elderly: management</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Seoane de Lucas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Chronic pain is a worldwide problem that has a particular significance, prevalence and relevance among the elderly, since it is associated to chronic diseases that incre ase with age. Pain is suffered by 50-80 por ciento of the population older than 65. Chronic pain, also in the elderly, becomes a tiring experience linked to a psychological suffering associated to anxiety and depression that determines and increases pain perception. Despite the above, a high perc e n t age of patients do not receive an appropriate tre a t m e n t . Management of chronic pain among the elderly is based on the WHO analgesic scale: NSAIs, opiates, coadjuvant drugs (antidepressants, anticonvulsants...) and psychological support, the latter being very important, since pain and d e p ression are symptoms frequently associated and overlapped, thus being very difficult to differentiate between both symptoms, and determining not only the type of treatment, but also its outcomes El dolor crónico es un problema universal que tiene especial importancia y prevalencia en el anciano ya que se asocia a enfermedades crónicas que aumentan con la edad. En t re un 50-80 por ciento de la población mayor de 65 años pre s e nta dolor. El dolor crónico, también en el anciano, es una experiencia agotadora, unida a un sufrimiento psicológico con síntomas de ansiedad y depresión que condicionan y aumentan la percepción dolorosa. A pesar de ello un gran núm e ro de pacientes, no recibe el tratamiento adecuado. El tratamiento del dolor crónico en el anciano se basa en la escalera analgésica de la OMS: AINEs, opiáceos, medicación coadyuvante (antidepresivos, anticonvulsivantes, etc.) y apoyo psicológico, punto este muy importante puesto que el dolor y depresión son síntomas que se asocian y se solapan con gran frecuencia, siendo muy difícil diferenciar un síntoma de otro, condicionando no sólo el tipo de tratamiento sino también sus resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;8(1): 29-38, ene. 2001. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-11772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características del dolor crónico en el anciano: tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
