<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102213</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment with TOBI (Tobramycin Inhalation) in patients over 18 years old with cystic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic fibrosis (CF) is a genetic disease, authosomic recesive, caused by more than 1.000 mutations, being the most known F508del (70%). The pulmonary disease is one of the cause of morbility and mortality related to CF. It is very common they are colonized by several microorganims, being one of the most important P. aeruginosa. Once, patients present chronic infection, they are treated with aerosolized antibiotics, using more colistin and free-preservative tobramicin (TOBI®). There are few studies that they are analized the last antibiotic in our country, so we have proponed to observe the functional and clinic evolution of the patients older than 18 years, who have used it. We have studied 13 patients, 7 males and  6 females, with and age of 28.0 ± 11.0 years, with a BMI of 20.84 ± 1.99 and 11.0 ± 4.0 years of colonization due to P. aeruginosa. The pulmonary function was studied since 6 months before (FEV1: 37.7 ± 9.98%, FVC: 57.10 ± 8.97%, FEV1/FVC: 56.20 ± 12.90) until six months later the begining of using TOBI® (FEV1: 36.50 ± 10.70%, FVC: 55.57 ± 13.69%, FEV1/FVC: 56.0 ± 11.70%), as well as the number of exacerbations and hospitalizations in this period of time. The number of exacerbations was significatively higher during the period analized before starting with TOBI® (p &lt; 0.05). We have not seen other significative findings in the other studied variables. The secundary effects have been very little.  We think that more works could carry out between aur patients to know the efficacy and security of this antibiotic administered by inhaled way adjusting the periods on-off (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sala, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Carrera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prados, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrosis quística (FQ) es una enfermedad autosómica recesiva causada por mutaciones, siendo la más conocida la delección F508del (70%). Se han descrito más de 1.000 mutaciones asociadas a esta enfermedad. La enfermedad pulmonar es una de las causas más importantes de morbilidad y mortalidad relacionadas con la FQ. Es muy frecuente que se colonicen por determinados gérmenes, siendo uno de los más importantes la P. aeruginosa. Una vez que existe una infección crónica, los enfermos se tratan con antibioterapia en aerosol, empleando con más frecuencia la colimicina y la tobramicina libre de  conservantes (TOBI®). Son pocos los estudios que han analizado este último antibiótico en nuestro país, por lo que nos hemos propuesto observar la evolución funcional y la clínica de los pacientes mayores de 18 años que lo están empleando. Hemos estudiado a 13 enfermos, 7 hombres y 6 mujeres, con una edad media de 28,0 ± 11,0 años, con un IMC medio de 20,84 ± 1,99 y 11,0 ± 4,0 años de colonización por P. aeruginosa. Se comprobó la función pulmonar desde 6 meses antes (FEV1: 37,7 ± 9,98%, FVC: 57,10 ± 8,97%, FEV1/FVC: 56,20 ± 12,90) hasta los 6 primeros meses tras iniciar el TOBI®  (FEV1: 36,50 ± 10,70%, FVC: 55,57 ± 13,69%, FEV1/FVC: 56,0 ± 11,70%), así como el número de exacerbaciones e ingresoshospitalarios, en este espacio de tiempo. El número de exacerbaciones fue significativamente mayor en el período  analizado antes de empezar con TOBI® (p &lt; 0,05). No hemos encontrado otros hallazgos significativos en el resto de las variables analizados. Los efectos secundarios han sido muy escasos. Creemos que se podrían realizar más trabajos entre nuestros enfermos para conocer la eficacia y la seguridad de este antibiótico administrado por vía inhalada y ajustar los períodos on-off (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;11(2): 56-60, abr.-jun. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con TOBI en pacientes con fibrosis quística mayores de 18 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11989^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14419^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
