<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045583</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complementary therapies in the cares: humour and laugh</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Related to complementary therapies, humour and laugh contribute to enhance health status and diminish illness situations. Humour as a therapy is an inexpensive tool in the patient care and it has not secondary effects in most cases. Current tendencies, either about natural ways to health or believes on health care of popular cultures, and who recommendations to patients in the use of traditional and complementary methods to improve population health, make humour and laugh an alternative therapy as an optional care tool. We have reviewed the literature with the aim of recognize the application of humour therapy on health and more specifically on nurse cares.On the basis of the review we can state that humour is utilized and applied in several professional environments, apart from the health one. This therapy is widely spread in the communication area. We have found few publications on nurse literature although they are high valuable since they work in the fields of research and education. It would be interesting that nurse professionals use this complementary therapy that enhance the quality of cares and offers an independent field favourable for research</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Pascual, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Pascual, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Navascués, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros García, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Gómez, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de las terapias complementarias, la utilización de la risoterapia aporta beneficios tanto en la salud como en las situaciones de enfermedad, siendo un "instrumento de cuidados" barato y sin efectos secundarios. La tendencia actual hacia todo lo natural, las corrientes sobre cuidados de salud de las distintas culturas, unidas a las recomendaciones de la OMS a los enfermeros sobre la necesidad de utilizar los "métodos tradicionales y complementarios" para conseguir mejorar la salud de la población, hacen que la risoterapia sea una alternativa como instrumento opcional de cuidados. Planteamos una revisión bibliográfica con el objetivo de conocer la aplicación de la risoterapia en la salud y más concretamente en los cuidados enfermeros.Del análisis de los resultados podemos concretar que la risa se trabaja en diferentes ámbitos profesionales, no sólo en el sanitario. Es en el campo de la comunicación donde más se divulga esta terapia. Hemos encontrado pocas publicaciones de enfermería, pero muy valiosas ya que trabajan en el terreno de la investigación y de la docencia. Sería interesante que los profesionales de enfermería utilizaran esta terapia que mejora la calidad de los cuidados y ofrece un campo independiente propicio para la investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(48/49): 37-41, ene.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapias complementarias en los cuidados: humor y risoterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36277^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
