<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039866</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The reverse venous flow of the sural flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The reverse venous flow of the sural flap has not  been clearly reported previously. The aim of the  following study is to determine the course that this  reverse flow follows. Fifty pelvic extremities of  twenty &#150; five corpses were dessected, ind, was injected  in a reverse manner in the lesser saphenous vein  and its course was followed. In all the corpse dissections  done, only one had a valve that was located two  cm proximal from the lateral melleolous, which  diverts the reverse flow towards the deep peroneal  veins (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ugalde Vitelli, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haddad, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores García, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El flujo venoso reverso del colgajo sural no ha sido  estudiado anteriormente con claridad. El presente  estudio tiene como objetivo determinar el trayecto  que sigue dicho flujo reverso. Se disecaron cincuenta  extremidades pélvicas en veinticinco cadáveres, se  inyectó colorante de forma retrógrada en la vena safena  externa y se siguió su trayecto. Se encontró que en  el 100% de las disecciones, sólo había una válvula a  dos centímetros proximal al maléolo lateral, la cual se  encarga de desviar el flujo invertido hacia las venas  peronéas profundas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;31(1): 67-71, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El flujo venoso inverso del colgajo sural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8047^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13878^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29778^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12461^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
