<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72176</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9503</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study the enzymatic action of serum trehalase in chronic diffuse liver disease (hepatic cirrhosis). Methods. A total of 242 subjects were studied, 182 controls of both sexes and 60 patients with hepatic cirrhosis. The diagnosis was carried out taking into account the etiology and the serum, biochemical and histopathological criteria. The functional level was assessed according to the Child-Pugh score. Serum trehalasa was determined following the method of Van Handel. Results. Serum trehalase in controls was 397.9±14.7units of trehalase. Differences between controls and patients were statistically significant (p&lt;0.001). There were no differences among the different types of cirrhosis although there were according to the functional level. Conclusions. Serum trehalase activity was decreased in hepatic cirrhosis, specially when the functional worsening was more acute (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pleguezuelo Díaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cuartero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos.- Estudiar la actividad enzimática de la trehalasa sérica en hepatopatías crónicas difusas  (cirrosis hepáticas). Casuística. Métodos.- Se estudian 242 sujetos; 182 controles normales de ambos sexos y 60 enfermos de cirrosis hepática. El diagnóstico se realizó atendiendo a la etiología, criterios serológicos, bioquímicos e histopatológicos. El grado funcional se evaluó según los criterios de Child-Pugh. La trehalasa sérica se determinó según el método de Van Handel. Resultados.- La trehalasa sérica en normales fue de 397.9 +/- 14.7 UT, sin diferencias entre sexos, en los enfermos cirróticos fue de 224.3 +/- 14.2 UT, siendo las diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los normales y los cirróticos (p&lt;0,001); no hubo diferencias entre los distintos tipos etiológicos de cirrosis, aunque si según el grado funcional. Conclusiones.- La actividad de la trehalasa sérica está descendida en las cirrosis hepáticas y tanto más cuanto más severo es el deterioro funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Invest. clín. (Granada);10(1): 1-3, ene.-mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72176</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14590^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
