<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119092</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing social anxiety through five self-report measures, LSAS-SR, SPAI, SPIN, SPS, and SIAS: a critical analysis of their factor structure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment of social anxiety through self-report measures tends to involve the more widely used questionnaires at international level: SPAI, LSAS-SR, SPIN, SPS, and/or SIAS. In this study, these questionnaires have been applied to university students, with an examination made of their factor structure, reliability and internal consistency. The best factor solutions for these self-report measures have been as follows: SPAI, six factors; LSAS-SR Anxiety subscale, five factors; SPIN, three factors; SPS, three factors, and SIAS, three factors. The reliability and internal consistency of these questionnaires is adequate. A comparison is made between the different solutions obtained by the various questionnaires, and a critical analysis is conducted of the factor results recorded in the light of the dimensional structure of social anxiety established for a new self-report measure, namely, the &#147;Social Anxiety Questionnaire for Adults&#148; (SAQ-A30). Finally, consideration is given to the relevance of these analyses for a more efficient assessment of social anxiety both in terms of the general population and at clinical level</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irurtia, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Isabel I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballo, Vicente E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nobre, Larissa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la ansiedad social por medio de medidas de autoinforme suele utilizar alguno de los cuestionarios ampliamente conocidos a nivel internacional: el SPAI, la LSAS-SR, el SPIN, la SPS y/o la SIAS. En el presente estudio dichos cuestionarios se han aplicado a estudiantes universitarios, prestando especial atención a su estructura factorial y, en menor medida, a su fiabilidad y a su consistencia interna. Las mejores soluciones factoriales para estas medidas han sido las siguientes: para el SPAI, seis factores, para la subescala de ansiedad de la LSAS-SR, cinco factores, para el SPIN, tres factores, para la SPS, tres factores y para la SIAS, tres factores. La fiabilidad y la consistencia interna de estos cuestionarios son adecuadas. Se han comparado las diferentes soluciones obtenidas por los distintos cuestionarios y se ha realizado un análisis crítico de su estructura factorial a la luz de la estructura dimensional de la ansiedad social establecida por una nueva medida de autoinforme, el &#147;Cuestionario de ansiedad social para adultos&#148; (CASO-A30). Finalmente, se ha planteado la relevancia de estos análisis para una evaluación más eficiente de la ansiedad social tanto a nivel de la población general como a nivel clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;21(3): 423-448, sept.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluando la ansiedad social por medio de cinco medidas de autoinforme, SPAI, LSAS-SR, SPIN, SPS y SIAS: un análisis crítico de su estructura factorial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
