<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141085</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integrated models of care delivery for the frail elderly: international perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Interest is growing in integrated systems of care for the frail elderly. Few such systems have been both documented and evaluated in a rigorous manner. The present article provides an international review of such systems. Methods: The literature on integrated care covered the period from 1997 to 2010, inclusive. Some 2,496 citations were identified from Age Line, PsycINFO, CINAHAL and MedLine and were reviewed. To be included in this paper, articles had to provide a good description of the care delivery system and good quality evaluations. Only nine articles were retained. Most of the articles reviewed described some form of coordinated care without evaluation. Results: There were essentially two types of models of integrated care delivery for the frail elderly. One was a smaller, community-based model that relied on cooperation across care providers, focused on home and community care, and played an active role in health and social care coordination. The second type of model was a large-scale model that could be applied at a national/provincial/state, or large regional health authority, level, had a single administrative authority and a single budget, and included both home/community and residential services. Discussion: Integrated care delivery can be achieved in various ways. Irrespective of which model is adopted, some of the key factors to be considered are how care can be coordinated effectively across different types of services, and how all the care provider organizations can be coordinated to ensure continuity of care for frail elderly persons (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Béland, François</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hollander, Marcus J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los sistemas integrados de asistencia para los ancianos frágiles suscitan cada vez más interés. Hay pocos sistemas de este tipo que hayan sido documentados y evaluados de forma rigurosa. Este trabajo presenta un estudio internacional de estos sistemas. Métodos: Correspondientes al periodo de 1997 a 2010, se identificaron y revisaron 2496 referencias bibliográficas de Age Line, PsycINFO, CINAHL y MedLine. Para ser incluidos en el estudio, los artículos debían ofrecer una buena descripción del sistema de asistencia sanitaria y unas buenas evaluaciones de calidad. Sólo se seleccionaron nueve artículos; la mayoría de ellos describían algún tipo de asistencia coordinada sin evaluación. Resultados: Principalmente se han encontrado dos tipos de modelos de atención sanitaria integrada destinada a los ancianos frágiles. Uno era un modelo comunitario pequeño basado en la cooperación entre profesionales sanitarios, se centraba en la asistencia domiciliaria y comunitaria, y tenía un papel activo en la coordinación de la asistencia sanitaria y social. El segundo era un modelo a gran escala que podía ser aplicado por autoridades sanitarias nacionales/provinciales/estatales/regionales, que tenía una autoridad administrativa única, un solo presupuesto e incluía tanto servicios domiciliarios/comunitarios como residenciales. Discusión: Hay varios modos de lograr una asistencia sanitaria integrada. Algunos de los factores clave a tener en cuenta, independientemente de cuál sea el modelo que se adopte, son cómo coordinar la asistencia entre los diferentes tipos de servicios de forma eficaz y cómo asegurarse de que todas las organizaciones asistenciales trabajan juntas para garantizar la continuidad de la asistencia para las personas mayores frágiles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(supl.2): 138-146, dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos integrados de asistencia para ancianos frágiles: perspectiva internacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32782^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37681</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
