<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81763</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence, clinical characteristics and risk of myocardial infarction in patients with cocaine-related chest pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To investigate the frequency of recent cocaine use in patients attending an emergency department for acute chest pain, to describe the clinical characteristics of these patients, and to estimate the incidence of acute coronary syndrome in this population. Methods. Observational cohort study using a standard questionnaire that includes items on recent cocaine consumption. Results. During a 1-year period, 1240 patients aged under 55 years presented with chest pain. Of these, 63 (5%) had cocaine-related chest pain (7% of men and 1.8% of women). These patients were younger (35±10 years vs. 39±10 years; P=.002), were more frequently male (87% vs. 62%; P &lt; .001), and were more frequently smokers (59% vs. 35%; P &lt; .001). Patients who had used cocaine recently had a higher incidence of acute myocardial infarction (16 vs. 4%; P &lt; .001), especially ST-segment-elevation myocardial infarction (11.1% vs. 1.6%; P &lt; .01). After adjusting for coronary risk factors, history of cardiovascular disease and previous treatment, the odds ratio for myocardial infarction with recent cocaine consumption was 4.3 (95% confidence interval, 2-9.4). Conclusions. Cocaine-related chest pain is often encountered in emergency departments, especially in men aged under 55 years. It is associated with a four-fold increase in the risk of acute myocardial infarction. All male patients aged under 55 years with acute chest pain should be asked about cocaine use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guasch, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, José T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loma-Osorio, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Analizar la prevalencia de consumo reciente de cocaína entre los pacientes atendidos en urgencias por dolor torácico, estudiar las características clínicas de los pacientes y estimar la incidencia de síndromes coronarios agudos en esta población. Métodos. Estudio de cohortes observacional en el que se utilizó un cuestionario estándar que incluía el interrogatorio sobre consumo de cocaína. Resultados. Durante un periodo de 1 año, 1.240 pacientes de menos de 55 años consultaron por dolor torácico. De ellos, 63 (5%) lo sufrieron en relación con consumo de cocaína (el 7% de los varones y el 1,8% de las mujeres). Estos pacientes eran más jóvenes (35 ± 10 frente a 39 ± 10 años; p = 0,002) y más frecuentemente varones (el 87 frente al 62%; p &lt; 0,001) y fumadores (el 59 frente al 35%; p &lt; 0,001). Los pacientes consumidores de cocaína tuvieron una mayor incidencia de infarto de miocardio (el 16 frente al 4%; p &lt; 0,001), especialmente con elevación del ST (el 11,1 frente al 1,6%; p &lt; 0,01). Tras ajustar por los factores de riesgo coronario, los antecedentes cardiovasculares y el tratamiento previo, el consumo reciente de cocaína se asoció a una odds ratio de infarto de 4,3 (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 2-9,4). Conclusiones. El dolor torácico asociado al consumo de cocaína es un problema frecuente en los servicios de urgencias, especialmente en los varones de menos de 55 años, y se asocia a un riesgo 4 veces mayor de infarto de miocardio. Se debería preguntar sobre el consumo de cocaína a todos los varones de menos de 55 años con dolor torácico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(9): 1028-1034, sept. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia, características clínicas y riesgo de infarto de miocardio en pacientes con dolor torácico y consumo de cocaína</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3346^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
