<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050970</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The evaluation of lower limb arteriopathy by multidetector computed tomography compared with digital subtraction angiography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the diagnostic efficacy of multidetector computed tomography angiography (MDCTA) in lower limb arteriopathy (LLA) by comparing it with digital subtraction angiography (DSA). Material and methods. Twenty-four patients with LLA were studied. All patients underwent MDCTA (four detectors) and DSA, with double reading between the two techniques. Vascular territories were divided to facilitate analysis. Sensitivity (S), specificity (Sp), prevalence, positive and negative predictive values (PPV, PNV), and concordance (Kappa test) were evaluated. In third-portion arteries, the diagnostic performance of MDCTA was evaluated using an ROC curve. Results. MDCTA study to evaluate arterial pathology showed: Lower sensitivity in the study of the internal iliac artery (S: 0.65 and 0.71) with Sp 0.94 and 1. In the other vascular territories, S approached 1, with a slight decrease in Sp. Concordance with DSA was very high (kappa between 0.62 and 1) in all of the territories studied. MDCTA showed greater vessel longitude than DSA. In the third portion, the best diagnostic performance (ROC) was obtained in the reading of pathological vessels. Conclusion. MDCTA was highly reliable in the study of LLA, with high concordance with DSA. In tortuous vessels, MDCTA depicted the lesions poorly; however, in straight vessels and third-portion vessels, MDCTA showed more vascular segments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mollá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revert, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallardó, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jornet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar la eficacia diagnóstica de la angiografía por tomografía computarizada multidetector (ATCM) en la arteriopatía de miembros inferiores (MMII), comparándola con angiografía por sustracción digital (ASD). Material y métodos. Se estudiaron 24 pacientes con arteriopatía de MMII. Se realizaron ATCM (4 detectores) y ADS realizando doble lectura entre las dos técnicas. Los territorios vasculares se dividieron para facilitar el análisis. Se calcularon sensibilidad (S), especificidad (E), prevalencia, valor predictivo positivo y negativo (VPP, VPN) y concordancia (test de Kappa). En arterias de tercera porción se estudió el rendimiento diagnóstico del ATCM realizando una curva ROC. Resultados. El estudio ATCM para la evaluación de la patología arterial mostró: una S menor en el estudio de la arteria ilíaca primitiva y arteria ilíaca interna (S: 0,65 y 0,71) con E de 0,94 y de 1; en los demás territorios vasculares obtuvimos S próximas a 1, disminuyendo algo la E. La concordancia fue muy alta (kappa entre 0,62 y 1) en todos los territorios estudiados. La ATCM mostró más longitud de vaso que la ASD. En la tercera porción el mejor rendimiento diagnóstico (ROC) se obtuvo en la lectura de vasos patológicos. Conclusión. La ATCM presentó alta fiabilidad en el estudio de la arteriopatía de MMII, con alta concordancia respecto a la ASD. En vasos tortuosos la ATCM visualiza mal las lesiones, en cambio en vasos rectos y en tercera porción el estudio con ATCM visualiza más segmentos vasculares</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(6): 369-374, nov. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la arteriopatía de los miembros inferiores por tomografía computarizada multidetector comparada con la angiografía por sustracción digital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
