<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94638</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Child sexual abuse an parental alienation syndrome. Differential criteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Child sexual abuse and those cases of parental interferences are severe situations with negative consequences for children suffering them. Moreover, these situations are not easy to tackle regarding the diagnosis and professional approach. To distinguish when the professional is in front of one of the above mentioned situations is a complex task for which are needed a strong, solid training and trustworthy criteria. The main aim of the present work is to suggest some criteria, gathered from the publications in the field, which would be able to differentiate between actual child sexual abuse and parental interference. The analysis of the child&#146;s report, as well as different clinical indicators that are present in many victims of sexual abuse can help the professional to take the right decision. The effects of a diagnostic mistake in any of these cases would imply harm for the child, his or her family and the social system. It is very important that the professional avoid taking part actively in an evaluation of this type if he or she does not have enough training and experience on this controversial field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereda, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arch, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abuso sexual infantil y los denominados casos de interferencias parental son situaciones de especial gravedad  para los menores que las padecen, así como de evidente dificultad para su adecuado diagnóstico y abordaje profesional. Discernir cuando el profesional se encuentra ante uno u otro caso entraña una complejidad para la que son necesarios una formación adecuada y unos criterios fiables. El presente trabajo tiene como objetivo aportar algunos de los criterios recogidos de las publicaciones al respecto, que pretenden facilitar la diferenciación entre ambas situaciones. El análisis del relato del menor, así como diferentes indicadores clínicos presentes en una parte importante de las víctimas de abuso sexual pueden ayudar al profesional a tomar una decisión al respecto. Los efectos de un error diagnóstico en cualquiera de estos casos conllevaría un gran perjuicio para el menor, su familia y el sistema social, siendo fundamental que el profesional evite participar activamente en una evaluación de este tipo si no se dispone de la adecuada formación y experiencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;15(58): 279-287, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso sexual infantil y síndorme de alienación parental: criterios diferenciales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52949^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13300^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
