<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161601</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Restless legs syndrome in patients diagnosed with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Restless legs syndrome (RLS) is a common neurological disease. RLS has been linked to various psychiatric disorders, especially with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). Aims. The main objective was to describe the frequency of RLS in pediatric patients diagnosed with ADHD. Secondary objectives of the study were describe other sleep disorders in ADHD patients. Patients and methods. A multicentre prospective study was conducted in nine Spanish centers. We included children aged 6-18 years diagnosed with ADHD between January and June 2015. Data were collected by 13 researchers doctors through an interview with the parent/caregiver and with the child. To assess the degree of functioning of patients with ADHD we used the Children&#146;s Global Assessment Scale. The Sleep Disturbance Scale for Children was applied to screening sleep disorders in childhood. Results. A sample of 73 patients was collected. Five patients (6.8%) met diagnostic criteria for RLS: four of them definitive and one probable. Conclusions. RLS is a frequent condition in adulthood but also in adolescence and childhood. ADHD patients have an increased risk of an RLS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons-Rodríguez, Monserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto-Insuga, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Acero, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño-De la Mota, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Villena, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Del Valle, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Fernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada-Del Pozo, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de piernas inquietas (SPI) es una patología neurológica común. Se ha relacionado con diferentes trastornos psiquiátricos, especialmente con el trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH). Objetivos. El objetivo principal fue describir la frecuencia del SPI en pacientes pediátricos diagnosticados de TDAH. Los objetivos secundarios del estudio fueron describir otros trastornos del sueño en pacientes con TDAH. Pacientes y métodos. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo prospectivo multicéntrico en nueve centros españoles de niños de 6-18 años con diagnóstico de TDAH entre enero y junio de 2015. Los datos fueron recogidos por 13 médicos investigadores mediante entrevista con el padre/cuidador y con el menor. Para valorar el grado de funcionamiento de los pacientes con TDAH se utilizó la Children&#146;s Global Assessment Scale. Se aplicó la Sleep Disturbance Scale for Children de Bruni para el cribado del trastorno de sueño de la infancia. Resultados. Se recogió una muestra de 73 pacientes. Cinco pacientes (6,8%) cumplen criterios diagnósticos de SPI: cuatro de ellos definitivos y uno probable. Conclusiones. El SPI es una entidad frecuente en la edad adulta, pero también en la adolescencia y en la infancia. Los pacientes con TDAH tienen un riesgo aumentado de presentar de manera concomitante un SPI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(7): 299-304, 1 abr., 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de piernas inquietas en pacientes diagnosticados de trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
