<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154819</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Construction and validation of a risk factor scale for complications of pre-eclampsia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective:  To construct and validate a risk factor scale to help predict the complications of preeclampsia in the population attended by the Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital (HGO) of the Maternity Institute of Mexico (IMIEM). Patients and method :A case-control study was conducted between January 1, 2012 and March 31, 2013 in patients with pre-eclampsia with or without complications. We performed a bivariate analysis and a multivariate analysis with the risk factors obtained to create and validate a tool able to predict the complications of pre-eclampsia. Emergency department and intensive care unit of the Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital. We reviewed 345 records. There were 115 patients with complications and 230 with uncomplicated pre-eclampsia. Primary endpoints: Maternal death, HELLP syndrome, eclampsia, acute kidney injury, thrombocytopenia, coagulopathy, hemorrhage, pulmonary edema, pulmonary embolism, and cerebral vascular events. Results: The following 12 variables able to predict complications of preeclampsia were obtained: maternal age &lt;20 years, gestational age at diagnosis of preeclampsia, headache, dyspnea, oliguria, thrombocytopenia, mean platelet volume, international normalized ratio (INR), serum creatinine, uric acid, glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase and lactic dehydrogenase. These risk factors were used to construct the scale. Sensitivity was 93% and specificity was 80%. LR+ was 4.65 and the LR- 0,09. Conclusion: The application of this risk factor scale can predict the complications of preeclampsia  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Téllez-Becerril, GE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Aceves, LJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizalde-Valdés, VM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo:  Construir y validar una escala de factores de riesgo que sea útil en la predicción de complicaciones de preeclampsia en la población del Hospital de Ginecología y Obstetricia (HGO) del Instituto Materno Infantil del Estado de México (IMIEM). Pacientes y método: Se realizó un estudio de casos y controles, entre el 1 de enero de 2012 y el 31 de marzo de 2013, en pacientes con diagnóstico de preeclampsia y que cursaron o no con complicaciones. Se realizó análisis bivariado y multivariado con los factores de riesgo obtenidos para crear y validar un instrumento capaz de predecir complicaciones de preeclampsia en el Servicio de Urgencias y en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos del HGO del IMIEM. Se analizaron los expedientes de 345 pacientes con diagnóstico de preeclampsia: 115 pacientes con complicaciones y 230 pacientes que no las tuvieron. Variables de interés principales:  Muerte materna, síndrome HELLP, eclampsia, lesión renal aguda, trombocitopenia, coagulopatía, hemorragia, edema pulmonar, tromboembolismo pulmonar, evento vascular cerebral. Resultados: Se obtuvieron 12 variables capaces de predecir complicaciones de preeclampsia: edad materna &lt;20 años; edad gestacional a la que se realizó el diagnóstico de preeclampsia, cefalea, disnea, oliguria; trombocitopenia, volumen plaquetario medio, índice normalizado internacional (INR), creatinina sérica, ácido úrico, transaminasa glutámico oxalacética y deshidrogenasa láctica. Se construyó una escala con esos factores de riesgo cuya sensibilidad fue del 93%, especificidad de 80%, LR+ 4,65 y LR&amp;#8722; 0,09. Conclusión: La aplicación de esta escala de factores de riesgo puede predecir complicaciones de preeclampsia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);43(3): 110-121, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Construcción y validación de una escala de factores de riesgo para complicaciones de preeclampsia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11662^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
