<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99406</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Left atrial appendage as a source of stroke: to close (and how), or not to close (and why)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Left atrial appendage is considered the main source of emboli in stroke for patients with atrial fibrillation. Oral anticoagulant therapy significantly reduces the risk of cerebral embolic events as compared with aspirin, but it is associated with bleeding complications, and it is not considered an standard of care. Closure of the left atrial appendage reduces the rate of thromboembolic events, and currently it is recommended in patients with atrial fibrillation submitted to mitral valve surgery. However the formation of emboli in those patients may be due to other causes and the roll of the atrial appendage currently has not very well defined. Moreover, neither all patients are candidates for oral anticoagulation, nor patients with oral anticoagulant maintain a adequate therapeutic range, which could be justify the formation of atrial thrombi. There are several methods to perform the closure of the appendage: endocavitary suture in concomitant mitral surgery, epicardial exclusion by stapling or clips, or endovascular occlusion by percutaneous devices. However the results seem inconclusive in regards of their effectiveness for complete occlusion of the appendage, safety, and efficacy to prevent cerebral embolic events. To increase the confusion, some authors reveal no clear benefit in suture closure, and even more others described an increased risk of thromboembolism. We present a review of the left atrial appendage closure for prevention of stroke and the different procedures as previously described(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rábago, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Levy, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Estefanía, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La orejuela izquierda se considera la principal fuente de émbolos en los accidentes cerebrovasculares que se producen en pacientes con fibrilación auricular. El tratamiento con anticoagulantes orales reduce significativamente el riesgo de accidentes embólicos cerebrales en relación con la aspirina, pero se asocia a riesgo de complicaciones hemorrágicas, por lo que no siempre son utilizados. Se ha descrito que el cierre de la orejuela izquierda reduce la tasa de accidentes tromboembólicos y en la actualidad se recomienda en pacientes en fibrilación auricular sometidos a cirugía mitral, pero la formación de émbolos en estos pacientes puede deberse a otras causas, y la implicación de la orejuela podría ser menor de la que se presupone. Además, no todos los pacientes son candidatos para la anticoagulación oral, y no todos se mantienen en un rango terapéutico adecuado, lo que podría justificar la formación de trombos auriculares. Existen diversos métodos para el cierre de la orejuela: sutura directa, exclusión epicárdica mediante grapadora o clip, u oclusión mediante los recientes dispositivos endovasculares de aplicación percutánea. Pero, según la bibliografía, la efectividad de estos métodos para ocluir completamente la orejuela, así como su seguridad y eficacia para la prevención de accidentes embólicos cerebrales, pueden presentar resultados dispares. Para aumentar la controversia, algunos métodos de cierre con sutura no revelan un claro beneficio e, incluso, en algunos se describe un aumento del riesgo de tromboembolismo. Se presenta una revisión sobre la necesidad de cierre de la orejuela izquierda para la prevención de accidentes vasculares cerebrales, así como los diversos procedimientos descritos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;35(1): 87-98, ene.-abr. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La orejuela izquierda como fuente de accidentes cerebrovasculares: cerrar (y cómo), o no cerrar (y por qué)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35394^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34046^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
