<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048485</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of dermoid ovarian cysts: laparoscopy vs laparotomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare the results of laparoscopy and laparotomy in teh treatment of ovarian dermoid cysts (cystectomy, oophorectomy and adenectomy, mainly those related with complications (intraoperative spillage). Subjects and methods: We analize retrospectively a case series of 91 patients with dermoid cysts treated al Hospital Severo Ochoa in Madrid, from January 2001 to Decembre 2004. Data were obtained from the pathology register and from the hospital charts, and were analized with the software EpiInfo 6.0 version. Results: 79% laparoscopic approaches, same complications rate, same intraoperative spillage risk, lower hospital stay in laparoscopic group, lower operating time in case of oophorectomy/anexectomy by laparotomy. Conclusions: Laparoscopic management of ovarian teratomas is as safe as laparotomic one. The same complications rate is observed in both groups, and lower hospital stay is achieved in laparoscopic surgery. If cystectomy is recommended intraoperative spillage risk should not contraindicate laparoscopy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Tórtola, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Petrement Briones, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Amigo, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Pascual, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Castaño, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmeán, Javier M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Mondejar, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar los resultados de la cirugía del quiste dermoide de ovario (quistectomía, ooforectomía y anexectomía) mediante laparotomía y laparoscopia, especialmente relacionados con las complicaciones (rotura del quiste). Sujetos y métodos: Estudio analítico, descriptivo y retrospectivo de 91 casos de quistes dermoides operados en el Hospital Severo Ochoa de Madrid entre enero de 2001 y diciembre de 2004. Los casos se recogieron de la base de datos del servicio de anatomía patológica, los datos de éstos, de la revisión de las historias clínicas de las pacientes, y los resultados se analizaron estadísticamente mediante el paquete informático EpiInfo versión 6.0. Resultados: El 79% de las intervenciones realizadas por laparoscopia, igual tasa de complicaciones, igual riesgo de rotura del quiste en casos de quistectomía, menor estancia media en el acceso laparoscópico, menor duración de la intervención por laparotomía en casos de ooforectomía/anexectomía. Conclusiones: El tratamiento quirúrgico mediante acceso laparoscópico de los quistes dermoides de ovario es seguro, no aumenta la tasa de complicaciones y permite disminuir la estancia media. Durante la realización de la quistectomía el riesgo de rotura del quiste es igual por laparoscopia que por laparotomía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(9): 479-484, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de los quistes dermoides de ovario: laparoscopia frente a laparotomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12794^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10226^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3904^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
