<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155784</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemoglobin kinetics and long-term prognosis in heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The influence of hemoglobin kinetics on outcomes in heart failure has been incompletely established. Methods: Hemoglobin was determined at the first visit and at 6 months. Anemia was defined according to World Health Organization criteria (hemoglobin &lt; 13 g/dL for men and hemoglobin &lt; 12 g/dL for women). Patients were classified relative to their hemoglobin values as nonanemic (both measurements normal), transiently anemic (anemic at the first visit but not at 6 months), newly anemic (nonanemic initially but anemic at 6 months), or permanently anemic (anemic in both measurements). Results: A total of 1173 consecutive patients (71.9% men, mean age 66.8 ± 12.2 years) were included in the study. In all, 476 patients (40.6%) were considered nonanemic, 170 (14.5%) had transient anemia, 147 (12.5%) developed new-onset anemia, and 380 (32.4%) were persistently anemic. During a follow-up of 3.7 ± 2.8 years after the 6-month visit, 494 patients died. On comprehensive multivariable analyses, anemia (P &lt; .001) and the type of anemia (P&lt; .001) remained as independent predictors of all-cause mortality. Compared with patients without anemia, patients with persistent anemia (hazard ratio [HR] = 1.62; 95% confidence interval [95%CI], 1.30-2.03; P &lt; .001) and new-onset anemia (HR = 1.39; 95%CI, 1.04-1.87, P= .03) had higher mortality, and even transient anemia showed a similar trend, although without reaching statistical significance (HR = 1.31; 95%CI, 0.97-1.77, P = .075). Conclusions: Anemia, especially persistent and of new-onset, and to a lesser degree, transient anemia, is deleterious in heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antonio, Marta de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boldó, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayes-Genis,  Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez López, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lupón, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troya, Maria Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santesmases, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La influencia de la cinética de la hemoglobina en la insuficiencia cardiaca no se ha establecido por completo. Métodos: Se determinó la hemoglobina en la primera visita y a los 6 meses. La anemia se definió según los criterios de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (hemoglobina &lt; 13 g/dl los varones y &lt; 12 g/dl las mujeres). Según los valores de hemoglobina, se estableció una clasificación de los pacientes como sin anemia (ambas determinaciones normales), con anemia transitoria (anemia en la primera visita, pero no a los 6 meses), con anemia de nueva aparición (inicialmente sin anemia, pero con anemia a los 6 meses) o con anemia permanente (anemia en ambas determinaciones). Resultados: Se incluyó en el estudio a 1.173 pacientes consecutivos (el 71,9% varones; media de edad, 66,8 ± 12,2 años). Se consideró sin anemia a 476 pacientes (40,6%), con anemia transitoria a 170 (14,5%), con anemia de nueva aparición a 147 (12,5%) y con anemia persistente a 380 (32,4%). Durante un seguimiento de 3,7 ± 2,8 años después de la visita realizada a los 6 meses, fallecieron 494 pacientes. En los análisis multivariables generales, la anemia (p &lt; 0,001) y el tipo de anemia (p &lt; 0,001) continuaron siendo factores independientes predictivos de mortalidad por cualquier causa. En comparación con los pacientes sin anemia, aquellos con anemia persistente (hazard ratio [HR] = 1,62; intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%], 1,30-2,03; p &lt; 0,001) o con anemia de nueva aparición (HR = 1,39; IC95%, 1,04-1,87; p = 0,03) presentaron más mortalidad, e incluso los pacientes con anemia transitoria mostraron una tendencia similar, aunque sin alcanzar significación estadística (HR = 1,31; IC95%, 0,97-1,77; p = 0,075). Conclusiones: La anemia &#151;en especial la persistente y la de nueva aparición y, en menor medida, la anemia transitoria&#151; tiene efectos nocivos en la insuficiencia cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;69(9): 820-826, sept. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cinética de la hemoglobina y pronóstico a largo plazo en insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
