<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135765</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protocol for diagnosis and treatment of soft tissue sarcomas at the hospital of Basurto</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The preservation of the function in the treatment of Soft Tissue Sarcomas (STS) has been achieved by means of marginal resections, reconstruction of soft tissues and adjuvant therapy without it implies an increase in the rates of local relapse, metastasis or mortality. It demands a multidisciplinary orientation for what is necessary to coordinate, under the form of Commission, the different specialists that take part in the diagnostic and therapeutic phases. This is a review article of the diagnosis and treatment of soft tissues sarcomas because of the protocol presentation settled down in the Hospital of Basurto (Bilbao, España), effective from February of 2001, that tries to assure patient&#146;s benefit with optimal care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Egilior, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oleaga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puertas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrones,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Legorburu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La preservación de la función en el tratamiento de los sarcomas de tejidos blandos (STB) se consigue por medio de resecciones marginales, reconstrucción de tejidos blandos y terapia adyuvante sin que ello implique un aumento en las tasas de recidiva local, de metástasis o de mortalidad; exigen un abordaje multidisciplinario por lo que es necesario coordinar, bajo la forma de Comisión, a los diferentes especialistas que intervienen en las fases diagnóstica y terapéutica. Este es un artículo de revisión del diagnóstico y tratamiento de los sarcomas de tejidos blandos con motivo de la presentación del protocolo establecido en el Hospital de Basurto (Bilbao, España), vigente desde febrero de 2001 que intenta asegurar que los pacientes se beneficien de un tratamiento óptimo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;30(4): 287-294, oct.-dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo para diagnóstico y tratamiento de sarcomas de tejidos blandos del hospital de Basurto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55365^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32861^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7252^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55365^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
