<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163844</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia with topical cidofovir: a case report and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN) is a precursor of invasive vulvar carcinoma. Although the standard treatment is surgery, new medical therapies are under investigation to maintain the sexual anatomy and function of the vulva. Our objective was to describe the usefulness of topical cidofovir in VIN. We report a case of VIN resistant to photodynamic therapy and topical imiquimod, which was treated with topical cidofovir with complete response in the vulvar area and partial response in the perineal and perianal area. Cidofovir may be a therapeutic option in the management of VIN. Future trials are needed to investigate its efficacy and recommended dosage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura Palacios, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Morano, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Repiso Jiménez, Juan Bosco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troya Martín, Magdalena de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ortiz, Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Bernier, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neoplasia vulvar intraepitelial (VIN) es una precursora del carcinoma vulvar invasivo. Aunque la cirugía es el tratamiento estándar, se están investigando nuevas terapias médicas con el fi n de mantener la anatomía y función sexual de la vulva. Nuestro objetivo es describir la utilidad del cidofovir tópico en la VIN. Presentamos una paciente con una VIN resistente a terapia fotodinámica e imiquimod tópico, que fue tratada con cidofovir tópico con respuesta completa a nivel vulvar y respuesta parcial a nivel perineal y perianal. El cidofovir puede ser una opción terapéutica en el manejo de la VIN. Se necesitan más ensayos futuros para investigar la eficacia y la posología más recomendada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(2): 87-90, mar.-abr. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la neoplasia vulvar intraepitelial con cidofovir tópico: presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d708^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
