<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131202</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PAPP-A and fBhCG levels in dichorionic twin pregnancies conceveid by assisted reproductive technologies (IVF-AIH) and their implications to calculate the prenatal risk on first trimestry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Evaluation of levels of PAPP-A and fßhCG in dichorionic twin pregnancies conceived by Assisted Reproductive Technology, i.e. In Vitro Fertilization (IVF) and Artificicial Insemination (AI) in our population. Calculate the necessary correction factors for first trimester screening in pregnancies conceived by IVF. Study population: One hundred seventyone twin pregnancies were considered within this study. One group was composed by 71 dichorionic twin pregnancies  conceived by IVF with an average maternal age of 36.6 years. The control group was composed by 76 dichorionic twin pregnancies conceived spontaneously with an average maternal age of 31.8. A third group was composed by 24 dichorionic twin pregnancies conceived by AI with an average maternal age of 32.9 years. Results: Dichorionic twin pregnancies conceived by IVF present statistically significant lower values for PAPP-A than the control group (2.17 MoM versus 2.41 MoM, p&lt;0.008) and higher values of fßhCG though this difference is not significant (2.33 MoM versus 2.05 MoM, p=0.144). In the other hand, average nuchal translucency (NT) does not show statistical differences between these two groups (p=0.178). Twin pregnancies conceived by AI present these same results tendencies for PAPP-A, fßhCG, and NT, with a lower number of patients not significant. Conclusions: Women with twin pregnancies conceived by Assisted Reproductive Technology (ART) have undergone treatments to induce ovulation. These treatments are proposed as one of the causes that may justify lower PAPP-A values and higher (though not significant) fßhCG values, when twin pregnancies conceived by ART are compared to spontaneously conceived twin pregnancies. Construction of normality curves for twin pregnancies conceived by IVF or calculation of correction factors is advised, in order to decrease this effect in the studied biochemical parameters. Applying these correction factors to our population data, the rate of false positives in first trimester screenings in dichorionic twin pregnancies conceived by IVF is decreased from a 4.22% to a 1.41%; this consequently implies a reduction of chorion biopsies, which are specially complicated in twin pregnancies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramis, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagalá, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gris, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Serra, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aulesa, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los niveles de proteína plasmática placentaria (PAPP-A) y fracción libre de la &amp;#946;hCG (fßhCG) en gestaciones gemelares bicoriónicas concebidas mediante técnicas de reproducción asistida tipo fertilización in vitro (FIV) o inseminación artificial (IA) en nuestra población. Posterior cálculo de los factores de corrección necesarios a aplicar para el screening de primer trimestre en gestantes gemelares concebidas mediante FIV. Población en estudio: Se han estudiado 171 gestantes gemelares. Un grupo compuesto por 71 gestaciones bicoriónicas concebidas mediante FIV, con una edad media de 36,3 años; un grupo control de 76 gestaciones bicoriónicas concebidas por gestación espontánea, con una edad media de 31,8 años; y un último grupo de 24 gestaciones bicoriónicas concebidas por IA, con una edad media de 32,9 años. Resultados: Las gestantes gemelares bicoriónicas concebidas mediante  FIV respecto el grupo control, concebidas espontáneamente, presentan unos niveles estadísticamente inferiores de PAPP-A (2,17 MoM versus 2,41 MoM, p&lt;0,008) y valores superiores no significativos de fßhCG (2,33 MoM versus 2,05 MoM, p=0,144). Las medias de la translucencia nucal (Tn) entre ambos grupos tampoco muestran diferencias significativas (p=0,178). Esta misma tendencia se observa en los valores de PAPPA y fßhCG para las gestaciones concebidas mediante IA, pero con un número menor de gestantes no significativo. Conclusiones: Las mujeres con gestaciones gemelares concebidas por técnicas de reproducción asistida han sido sometidas a tratamientos para la estimulación de la ovulación. Este hecho se ha postulado como una de las causas que podrían explicar la presencia de valores de PAPP-A significativamente inferiores y de fßhCG superiores, aunque no significativos, a las gestantes gemelares espontáneas. Por ello se aconseja la elaboración de curvas propias con gestantes gemelares FIV, o en su defecto, el empleo de factores de corrección para disminuir este efecto. Se comprueba que con la aplicación de estos factores de corrección la tasa de falsos positivos de los gemelares bicoriónicos concebidos por FIV baja de 4,22% a 1,41% en nuestra población, con la consecuente disminución de biopsias de corion que son especialmente complejas en gestaciones gemelares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;30(4): 34-41, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de PAPP-A y fßhCG en gestantes gemelares bicoriónicas concebidas por técnicas de reproducción asistida (FIV-IAH) y sus implicaciones en el cálculo del riesgo del cribado prenatal del primer trimestre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
