<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118158</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cuban program for cardiac rehabilitation. Results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cardiovascular diseases have been the leading cause of death in Cuba for over 40 years, with a high prevalence and very negative socio-economic impact. A national communitybased comprehensive cardiac rehabilitation program has been implemented all over the country since 1989. Objectives: The principal aim of this study was to evaluate the behavior and results of this program over a 3-year period. Methods: All patients with acute myocardial infarction, unstable angina pectoris or after coronary angioplasty and aorto-coronary or valvular surgery discharged alive in the 23 hospitals of the National Heart Network were included in this study. The cardiac rehabilitation program covered its three common phases. These included modification of risk factors and measures to change style of life. Physical exercises were also included with an intensity necessary to achieve the training heart rate identified by previous ergometric tests. The convalescence phase lasted eight weeks and the maintenance one continued until at least the first year of evolution. Chi-square test was used for the comparison of qualitative data. Results: In this study, 40,738 patients, 79.1% of who underwent the hospital rehabilitation phase, were included. In the last year, 62.5% were incorporated into the convalescence phase, this representing an increase of 13.5% in relation to the previous year. A total of 58.5% of infarction patients, 34.4% of those with angina or after coronary angioplasty and 94.5% of patients after coronary artery or valvular surgery were incorporated. The majority of patients rehabilitated in the last year (56.4%) belonged to the Western region of the country, an area where a higher number of ergometric tests (58.3%) were performed and which also had specialized rehabilitation consultations and psychological interventions. Conclusions: Although the implementation of the cardiac rehabilitation program in Cuba still remains to be improved, particularly in some regions of the countryside, our results are at the same level of many countries with an appropriate socio-economic development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Nande, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrera-Sarduy, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kesser-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sixto-Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Estany, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las enfermedades cardiovasculares constituyen la primera causa de muerte en Cuba desde hace más de 40 años, con una elevada prevalencia y una muy negativa repercusión socioeconómica. Un programa de rehabilitación cardíaca integral se ha desarrollado a nivel de la comunidad en todo el país desde 1989. Objetivos: El propósito principal de este estudio ha sido evaluar el comportamiento y los resultados de dicho programa durante un período de 3 años. Métodos: Fueron incluidos todos los pacientes con infarto miocárdico, angina inestable o después de angioplastia y cirugía coronaria o valvular, dados de alta en los 23 hospitales de la Red Nacional de Cardiología. El programa de rehabilitación cardíaca abarcó sus 3 fases habituales que incluyeron modificación de los factores de riesgo y medidas para cambios en el estilo de vida, así como ejercicios físicos con una intensidad necesaria para alcanzar el pulso de entrenamiento determinado en pruebas ergométricas previas. La fase de convalecencia tuvo una duración de 8 semanas y la de mantenimiento duró por lo menos hasta el primer año de evolución. La prueba de la chi al cuadrado fue empleada para la comparación de los datos cualitativos. Resultados: Fueron incluidos en el estudio 40.738 pacientes, de los cuales se le realizó la fase hospitalaria de la rehabilitación al 79,1%. En el último año evaluado, fueron incorporados a su fase de convalecencia el 62,5%, con un incremento de un 13,5% con relación al año interior; se incorporaron el 58,5% de los pacientes infartados, un 34,4% de aquellos con angina o después de la angioplastia coronaria y el 94,5% de los pacientes después de la cirugía coronaria o valvular. La mayoría de los pacientes rehabilitados en el último año (56,4%) pertenecían a la región occidental del país, donde también se hizo mayor cantidad de pruebas ergométricas (58,3%), así como consultas especializadas de rehabilitación e intervenciones psicológicas. Conclusiones: Aunque debe aun mejorarse la aplicación del programa de rehabilitación cardíaca en Cuba, particularmente en algunas zonas del interior del país, nuestros resultados están a la altura de muchos países con un adecuado desarrollo socioeconómico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(4): 238-244, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa cubano de rehabilitación cardíaca. Resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30118^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30118^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24519^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
