<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148383</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rural medical practice at the beginning of the 20th century. Martínez Saldise (1855-1937), honorary member of Paediatric Society of Madrid in 1927</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: On the centenary of the foundation of the Paediatrics Society of Madrid, a tribute is presented to rural medical practice of that time, although there are few documents on the history of rural medicine. The main objective is to describe the context of the rural medical practice in the late 19th and beginning 20th century, while presenting a historical biographical review of Manuel Martínez Saldise, who was medical specialist from Cazalegas (Toledo). He was appointed an Honorary Member by the Paediatrics Society of Madrid in 1927. Material and methods: A search was carried out in repositories of digitized media, web portals of history of medicine, PubMed, IME files of local councils and medical colleges. The family archives were reviewed with the collaboration of his descendants. Results: The hiring of rural doctors was carried out by the municipalities, and the salary largely depended on private practice as well as &#147;retainers&#148;. Specialist physicians took part in epidemics, legal medicine, and in hygiene measures. They also had disputes with mayors, chiefs, with colleagues and with protectionism. A summary of the biography and occupational activity of Manuel Martínez Saldise is presented. Comments: Rural doctors were subjected to the society of their time, with the issues that arose, denouncing the shortcomings of the local administrations, dedicated efforts to their family and the most disadvantaged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flores Martín, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil García, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Durán, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra Anta, Miguel Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponte Hernando, Fernando Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduccion: En el centenario de la Sociedad de Pediatría de Madrid se quiere realizar un homenaje a la medicina rural de aquella época. Hay escasez documental sobre la historia de la medicina rural. El objetivo es describir el marco del ejercicio médico rural a finales del XIX y principios del XX en tanto que se desarrolla una revisión histórica biográfica de Manuel Martínez Saldise, que fue médico titular de Cazalegas (Toledo). En 1927 fue nombrado socio de honor por la Sociedad de Pediatría de Madrid. Material y métodos: Búsqueda en repositorios de prensa digitalizada, portales web de historia de la medicina, pubmed, IME, archivos locales de diputaciones y colegio de médicos. Se revisó el archivo familiar con la colaboración de uno de sus descendientes. Resultados: La contratación de los médicos rurales se realizaba por los ayuntamientos, el sueldo en gran parte dependía además del ejercicio privado, de las «igualas». Los médicos titulares participaban en las epidemias, en medicina legal, en las medidas de higiene; también tenían conflictos con alcaldes, caciques, con colegas y con el intrusismo. Se hace un resumen de aspectos biográficos y laborales de Manuel Martínez Saldise. Comentarios:Los médicos rurales se entregaban a la sociedad de su época, ante los problemas que surgían, denunciaban las carencias de la administración local, dedicaban esfuerzos a su familia y a los más desfavorecidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(1): 54-62, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148383</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La medicina rural a principios de siglo XX. A propósito de Martínez Saldise (1855-1937), socio de honor de la Sociedad de Pediatría de Madrid en 1927</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17561^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17561^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2936</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
