<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119817</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antifungal susceptibility of clinical isolates of Scopulariopsis species</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Scopulariopsis is a common soil saprophyte. In the last years the infections caused by Scopulariopsis species have increased, included superficial and invasive mycoses. This fungi has been reported resistant in vitro to some antifungal agents, although there is little information about this. The aim of the study was to establish in vitro antifungal susceptibility of clinical isolates of Scopulariopsis species against to broad-spectrum antifungal agents. Methods. A total of 28 Scopulariopsis strains (10 S. brevicaulis, 7 S. koningii, 3 S. acremonium, 3 S. candida, 3 S. flava, 1 S. brumptii and 1 S. fusca) were tested using Sensititre YeastOne and broth microdilution methods to determine the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) to amphotericin B, fluconazole, itraconazole, posaconazole, voriconazole and 5-fluorocytosine, and minimun effective concentration (MECs) to anidulafungin, caspofungin and micafungin. Results. Our data confirm the high in vitro resistance of Scopulariopsis to antifungal agents. Anidulafungin, caspofungin, micafungin (MICs &amp;#8805;8 mg/L), 5-fluorocytosine (MICs &amp;#8805;64 mg/L), and fluconazole (MICs &amp;#8805;128 mg/L) were inactive in vitro in all species. MICs of amphotericin B (range 2 to &amp;#8805;8 mg/L) and itraconazole (0.5 to &amp;#8805;16 mg/L) were high. The best antifungal activity was observed for posaconazole and voriconazole (0.5 to &amp;#8805;8 mg/L). With Sensititre YeastOne method MICs obtained slightly lower. Scopulariopsis candida, S. flava and S. fusca were the most resistant species, while S. acremonium and S. brevicaulis showed the lowest MICs. Conclusions. MICs of all tested antifungal agents for Scopulariopsis were very high. Infections caused by Scopulariopsis species may not respond to antifungal treatment. Voriconazole is the drug of choice for treatment. We consider it appropriate to add amphotericin B in serious infections (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Martos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Agudo, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odero, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Iglesias, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Scopulariopsis es un hongo saprofito del suelo. En los últimos años se ha incrementado el número y diversidad de las infecciones causadas por este hongo, incluyendo micosis superficiales e invasoras, y se ha descrito resistencia in vitro a antifúngicos, aunque existe escasa información al respecto. Nuestro objetivo fue establecer la sensibilidad in vitro de especies de origen clínico frente a un amplio número de antifúngicos. Material y métodos. Veintiocho cepas de Scopulariopsis (10 S. brevicaulis, 7 S. koningii, 3 S. acremonium, 3 S. candida, 3 S. flava, 1 S. brumptii y 1 S. fusca) fueron ensayadas mediante el método Sensititre YeastOne y el de microdilución en caldo, para determinar las concentraciones mínimas inhibitorias (CMIs) frente a anfotericina B, fluconazol, itraconazol, posaconazol, voriconazol y 5-fluorocitosina, y las concentraciones mínimas efectivas (CMEs) frente a anidulafungina, caspofungina y micafungina. Resultados. Nuestros datos confirman la alta resistencia in vitro a los antifúngicos de Scopulariopsis. Anidulafungina, caspofungina, micafungina (CMIs &amp;#8805;8 mg/L), 5-fluorocitosina (CMIs &amp;#8805;64 mg/L) y fluconazol (CMIs &amp;#8805;128 mg/L) fueron inactivas para todas las especies. Las CMIs para anfotericina B (rango 2 a &amp;#8805;8 mg/L) e itraconazol (0,5 a &amp;#8805;16 mg/L) fueron altas. La mejor actividad se observó para posaconazol y voriconazol (0,5 a &amp;#8805;8 mg/L). Con el método Sensititre YeastOne se obtuvieron CMIs ligeramente inferiores. Scopulariopsis candida, S. flava y S. fusca, fueron las especies más resistentes; S. acremonium y S. brevicaulis las de CMIs más bajas. Conclusiones. Las CMIs de todos los antifúngicos ensayados fueron elevadas para Scopulariopsis, lo que demuestra que las infecciones causadas por especies de Scopulariopsis podrían no responder al tratamiento. En infecciones graves, voriconazol sería una buena elección para el tratamiento, asociado a anfotericina B (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;27(1): 17-21, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad a antifúngicos de especies de Scopulariopsis de origen clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54448^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
