<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124738</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Leptomeningeal metastases (carcinomatous meningitis): Different cases with the same results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Carcinomatous meningitis is observed in 5% of the patients with cancer. This complication is more frequent in hematological processes that in solid tumors, and of theses infiltrating lobular breast cancer is the most common. Clinical cases: We present three different clinical cases of leptomeningeal metastases with different management, but obtaining the same results. Discussion: A meticulous anamnesis and clinical examination is essential to arrive at a diagnosis. Of the diagnostic tests, nuclear magnetic resonance has a sensitivity of 40-50%, the cytology of the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) is essental for a differential diagnosis (particulary infectious diseases) and finally the study of the CSF flow by radionuclide cisternogram to confirm the diagnosis. The treatments are directed at the relief of the symptoms, improving the neurological (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mowbray, Jose Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomez-Ulla Astray, Jacobo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macias Montero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La carcinomatosis meníngea se observa en un 5% de los enfermos con cáncer. Es más habitual en procesos hematológicos que en tumores sólidos, y de estos el que con más frecuencia lo desarrolla es el carcinoma lobulillar infiltrante de mama. Casos clínicos Exponemos 3 casos clínicos de pacientes con carcinomatosis meníngea en los que se realizó una estrategia terapéutica diferente que evolucionó con el mismo resultado. Discusión Para llegar al diagnóstico son fundamentales una anamnesis y exploración clínica meticulosas. Entre las pruebas complementarias más rentables destacan: la resonancia magnética (RMN) (con una sensibilidad del 40-50%), la citología del líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR) y el estudio del flujo del LCR mediante cisternograma con radionucleóticos. Los tratamientos están encaminados a la paliación de síntomas, mejorar la función neurológica del paciente y prolongar la supervivencia. Existen distintos manejos de esta complicación neurológica sin que ninguno de ellos haya demostrado ningún beneficio sobre los otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;21(3): 121-125, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinomatosis meníngea: distintos casos con los mismos resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8748^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53057^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
