<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052649</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of the Why worry? questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study presents the validation of Spanish version of Why worry? Questionnaire which assesses a variable of process related to the overestimation of the positive and negative consequences of the excessive and uncontrollable worry that is characteristic of Generalized Anxiety Disorder. 833 participants from Tenerife (Canary Island) completed this questionnaire among other psychological measures. The exploratory factor analysis yielded a two-factors structure that explained 41.34% of the total variance; both of them showed adecuate internal consistency (&amp;#945;1= 0.86 and &amp;#945;2= 0.85) and test-retest (r1= 0.70 and r2= 0.75) reliability coefficients. A confirmatory factor analysis confirmed two-factor structure. As expected, concurrent validation uncovered substantial correlation with anxiety and mood disorders. The results support a good discriminate validity. The Spanish version of why worry questionnaire provides a reliable and valid instrument, which we can use in cross-cultural studies on worry as a GAD characteristic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Arquímedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fumero, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bethencourt, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta la validación de la versión española del cuestionario Why worry? (¿Por qué preocuparse?, ¿PP?) para evaluar una variable de proceso relacionada con la sobrestimación de las consecuencias tanto positivas como negativas de la preocupación excesiva e incontrolable que es una característica del Trastorno de Ansiedad Generalizada (TAG). 833 personas de la isla de Tenerife cumplimentaron dicho cuestionario, entre otras medidas psicológicas. El análisis factorial exploratorio aisló una estructura bifactorial que explica el 41,34% de la varianza total. Ambos factores muestran adecuada consistencia interna (&amp;#945;1= 0.86 y &amp;#945;2= 0.85) y fiabilidad test-retest (r1= 0.70 y r2= 0.75). La estructura bifactorial se confirmó mediante un análisis factorial confirmatorio. Como se esperaba, la validación concurrente descubrió correlaciones importantes con los trastornos de ansiedad y del estado de ánimo. Los análisis diferenciales para las variables anteriores proporcionaron evidencia sobre la validez discriminante. La versión española del Why worry? proporciona un instrumento fiable y válido que puede ser usado en estudios transculturales sobre la preocupación como una característica del TAG</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(2): 313-318, mayo 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación española del cuestionario ¿por qué preocuparse?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4252</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33531^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37587</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
