<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131663</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of introducing an enterovirus polymerase chain reaction in the management of aseptic meningitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The diagnosis of aseptic meningitis, based on an enterovirus PCR (EV-PCR) in cerebrospinal fluid, is a rapid and sensitive test. Objective: To assess the impact of introducing EV-PCR on the use of antibiotics and hospital length of stay in aseptic meningitis. Material and methods: A prospective study that included children with aseptic meningitis during one year. The patients prior to the introduction of the test formed the control group. Results: The performance of the PCR test was associated with less use of antibiotics compared to the control group (16.2% vs 41.4%, P = .029) and with fewer days of administration (.54 vs. 2 days, P=.014). A non-significant decrease in length of stay (3.57 vs. 4.21 days, P=.376) was also observed in the study group. Conclusion: The introduction of the EV-PCR test decreases the use of antibiotics and hospital length of stay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alados Arboledas, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Tardío, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Fernández, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Pastrana, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El diagnóstico de meningitis aséptica basado en la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa (PCR) frente a enterovirus en líquido cefalorraquídeo es un método rápido y sensible. Objetivo: Valorar la influencia de la implantación de la PCR a enterovirus en el uso de antibióticos y la estancia hospitalaria en meningitis aséptica. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de ni&#152;nos con meningitis aséptica durante un a&#152;no, utilizando como grupo control a pacientes previos a la implantación de la técnica. Resultados: La realización de la PCR se asoció a un menor uso de antibióticos respecto al grupo control (16,2% vs. 41,4%; p = 0,029), a un menor tiempo de administración (0,54 vs. 2 días; p = 0,014) y a una disminución no significativa de la duración del ingreso (3,57 vs. 4,21 días; p = 0,376). Conclusión: La implantación de la PCR a enterovirus disminuye la utilización de antibióticos y la estancia hospitalaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e26-e29, ene. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131663</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la implantación de la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa a enterovirus en el manejo de la meningitis aséptica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
