<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88741</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rupture of the superficial vein of penis: therapeutic options</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report an uncommon clinical case of spontaneous rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of penis.METHOD: A 27-year-old male patient attended the emergency room following spontaneous occurrence of a large hematoma and deformity in the penis. Rupture of cavernous bodies was initially suspected.RESULTS: Surgical examination revealed rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of penis, which was ligated. The patient was admitted to hospital for 24 hours, and showed total cosmetic and functional recovery at 2 weeks.CONCLUSIONS: Rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of penis is an uncommon condition considered in differential diagnosis of penile hematoma. Doppler ultrasound of the penis may allow for its diagnosis and for excluding rupture of corpora cavernosa. Although conservative management appears to be of choice, surgical examination, providing good cosmetic and functional postoperative results, is indicated when a reasonable doubt exists about diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toucedo Caamaño, Valentin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villasenín Parrado, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortegoso González, Melisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puñal Pereira, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fentes, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Parra, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar un caso clínico poco frecuente de rotura de vena dorsal superficial del pene, producida de forma espontánea.MÉTODO: Paciente de 27 años que acude a urgencias tras la aparición espontánea de gran hematoma y deformidad peneana. La sospecha diagnóstica inicial fue rotura de cuerpos cavernosos.RESULTADOS: Se realiza exploración quirúrgica, evidenciando la rotura de la vena dorsal superficial del pene, que se liga. Ingreso hospitalario de 24 horas. Completa recuperación estética y funcional a las 2 semanas.CONCLUSIONES: La rotura de la vena dorsal superficial del pene es una entidad poco frecuente, incluida dentro del diagnóstico diferencial de los hematomas peneanos. La ecografía-doppler peneana puede permitir su diagnóstico y excluir la rotura de cuerpos cavernosos. Aunq-ue el tratamiento conservador parece de elección, ante la duda diagnóstica razonable, está indicada la exploración quirúrgica, la cual ofrece buenos resultados postoperatorios estéticos y funcionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(10): 871-873, dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88741</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura de la vena superficial del pene: opciones terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
