<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052783</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of emotional intelligence and other individual difference variables in predicting emotional labor relative to situational demands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study found a significant positive relationship between emotional intelligence (MSCEIT) and deep    acting (making an effort to feel emotions that are required in interpersonal interactions) in a sample of    service workers. Surface acting (faking displayed emotions and hiding personal feelings) was positively    associated with emotional awareness. Emotional intelligence did not add to the prediction of variance    in emotional labor beyond situational demands, nor did it moderate the relationship between situational    demands and emotional labor. Thus, workers&#146; level of emotional intelligence did not appear    to influence the nature of the emotional labor that was performed given situational demands. Rather,    the key role of emotional intelligence seemed to be as a predictor of the perceived situational demands,    which, in turn, predicted the nature of emotional labor that was performed. Workers with higher levels    of emotional intelligence were found to be more likely to perceive the need to frequently display emotions    as part of their work role and perform deep acting in response to these situational demands</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brotheridge, Celeste M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio encontró una relación positiva significativa entre la inteligencia emocional (MSCEIT) y el comportamiento profundo (hacer un esfuerzo para sentir las emociones que requieren las interacciones interpersonales) en una muestra de asistentes sociales. El comportamiento superficial (fingir las emociones que se muestran y ocultar los sentimientos personales) se asoció positivamente con la conciencia emocional. La inteligencia emocional no predijo la varianza del trabajo emocional por encima de las demandas situacionales, ni moderó la relación entre las demandas situacionales y el trabajo emocional. Así, el nivel de inteligencia emocional de los trabajadores no parece influir en la naturaleza del trabajo emocional realizado en las demandas situacionales. Más bien, el papel clave de la inteligencia emocional parece ser el de predictor de las demandas situacionales percibidas, las cuales a su vez predijeron la naturaleza del trabajo emocional realizado. Los trabajadores con niveles más altos de inteligencia emocional fueron los más propensos a percibir la necesidad de mostrar frecuentemente emociones como parte de su trabajo y realizar un comportamiento profundo en respuesta a estas demandas situacionales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(supl.1): 139-144, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052783</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la inteligencia emocional y otras variables de diferencias individuales en la predicción del trabajo emocional relacionado con las demandas situacionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10112</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
