<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164845</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A descriptive study of Hafnia alvei isolated from stool samples: an approach to its clinical assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The importance in human diarrhoeal disease of Hafnia alvei is unclear. The objective of the study was to describe the population which was isolated H. alvei in stool cultures and the therapeutic management of these cases in our Health Area. Material and methods. A descriptive retrospective study was carried out in 2014 and 2015. Epidemiological, clinical, treatment and evolution variables were collected in the computerized clinical history. Result. A collection of 7,290 stool specimens were processed, 3,321 in 2014 and 3,969 in 2015, of which 58 (1.7%) and 53 (1.3%) were positive for H. alvei, respectively. A 60.4% of samples were isolated in women. The mean age was 38.68 years. A 68.5% of samples were from primary care. In 71.2% there was related clinic, diarrhoea in 57.7%. In 75.7% of the cases there was not associated underlying disease. A 43.2% of the cases received treatment. A 66.7% of treated patients came from Primary Care. The mean duration of treatment was 8 days. The evolution was favourable in 85.4% of the cases treated. All strains were susceptible to ciprofloxacin and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole. Conclusions. More evidence is needed to support H. alvei as a cause of gastroenteritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Gil, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Urrutia, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eiros, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñuela, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos, Mónica de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcinuño, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El papel de Hafnia alvei en la etiología de diarrea en humanos es todavía muy controvertido; el objetivo del estudio fue describir la población en cuyos coprocultivos se aisló H. alvei y el manejo terapéutico de estos casos en nuestro Área de Salud. Material y métodos. Para ello se realizó un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de 2014 y 2015. Se recogieron en la historia clínica informatizada, variables epidemiológicas, clínicas, tratamiento y evolución. Resultados. Se procesaron 7.290 coprocultivos, 3.321 en 2014, 58 (1,7%) en los que se aisló H. alvei y 3.969 en 2015, 53 (1,3%) positivos. El 60,4% de las muestras fueron aisladas en mujeres. La edad media fue de 38,68 años. El 68,5% provenían de Atención Primaria. En el 71,2% se recogió clínica asociada, siendo el más frecuente la diarrea en el 57,7%. En el 75,7% de los casos no existía patología de base asociada. El 43,2% de los casos recibió tratamiento de los cuales el 66,7% de los pacientes procedían de Atención Primaria. La duración media del tratamiento fue de 8 días. En el 85,4% de los casos tratados, la evolución fue favorable. Todas las cepas fueron sensibles a ciprofloxacino y trimetoprim/sulfametoxazol. Conclusiones. Faltan estudios que establezcan de forma concluyente la enteropatogenicidad o no de H. alvei (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;30(4): 280-284, ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descriptivo de Hafnia alvei aisladas en coprocultivo: aproximación a su valoración en clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34116^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13807^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34116^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14697^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
