<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156435</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dissemination of an odontogenic infection to the periorbital space secondary to malpractice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Odontogenic infections of the head and neck derived pulpar pathology not adequately handles may be aggravated. One of the possible complications are the orbital infections, that in turn, can trigger a thrombosis of the cavernous sinus and the patient´s death, combined with systemic compromise, such as pregnancy, requiring the modification of certain aspects of endodontic treatment. A 31 year old female patient with a 35 week pregnancy was admitted to the emergency Hospital General Manuel GEA González due to a severe buccal, malar y periorbital abscess deriving from an incorrect dental management. The approach was pharmacological treatment, cesarean and drainage. She was then remitted to the Division de Studios de Postgrad e Investigation UNAM Endodontic Graduate Department. The diagnosis was: chronic dentoalveolar abscess of left lateral incisor, canine and first premolar. The treatment focused on neutralization the septic content and a comprehensive treatment including different dental specialties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lazo García, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sadek González, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Flores, Hilda Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones odontogénicas de cabeza y cuello derivadas de patologías pulpares mal manejadas pueden agravarse. Una de las posibles complicaciones son las infecciones orbitarias que a su vez, pueden desencadenar trombosis del seno cavernoso y la muerte del paciente; si aunado a esto el paciente presenta compromiso sistémico, requerirá la modificación de ciertos aspectos del manejo endodóncico. Paciente femenino de 31 años de edad con embarazo de 35 semanas acude de urgencia al Hospital General Manuel GEA González por mal manejo dental, desencadenando absceso bucal, malar y periorbitario izquierdo por lo que se realiza tratamiento farmacológico, apertura y drenaje. A su egreso del hospital acude a la División de Estudios de Posgrado e Investigación UNAM Posgrado de Endodoncia, se realiza diagnóstico de abscesos dentoalveolares crónicos de incisivo lateral, canino y premolar superior izquierdo, se plantea un manejo para la neutralización del contenido séptico y tratamiento integral con diferentes especialidades odontológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(2): 73-82, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseminación de una infección odontogénica a espacios periorbitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5626^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5626^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53767</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5626^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53767^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52600^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34259^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30529^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5626^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30529^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52600^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
