<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106436</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Budgetary impact of COPD treatment in II, III and IV with tiotropium versus ipratropium, in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the budgetary impact of the approach of the pathology with tiotropium compared to ipratropium from the perspective of the National Health System (NHS), in conditions of optimal diagnosis and treatment of the disease and considering the intervening intermediate products. Material and method: prospective descriptive study, with analytical intent, after implantation in the market (ex-post) of the therapeutic alternatives compared, carried out on the basis of previous studies, the costs of which, were adjusted by the current Consumer Price Index (CPI) within the field of health economics, in which a decision tree with three decisional branches was elaborated (moderate, severe and very severe stages of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease-COPD-). The analysis included direct healthcare costs of treatment in stable phase, treatment of exacerbations, and health resource utilization. Results: treatment with tiotropium strategy had a financial repercussion on the last available figure of 2,7% of health spending, while the ipratropium strategy had a 1,5% repercussion. This showed a difference of 1,2% between strategies, which resulted in 841,1 million euros. Conclusions: although the effectiveness of tiotropium results in lower probability of exacerbation, high costs dependent on the high price of the baseline treatment discourage it use compared to ipratropium, and therefore decreasing its cost-effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pablos Heredero, Carmen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinagre Romero, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Gabriel, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar el impacto presupuestario que produciría el abordaje de la patología con tiotropio comparado con ipratropio desde la perspectiva del Sistema Nacional de Salud (SNS), en condiciones de óptimo diagnóstico y tratamiento de la enfermedad y considerando los productos intermedios intervinientes. Material y método: estudio descriptivo y prospectivo, con intención analítica, tras la implantación en el mercado (ex-post) de las alternativas terapéuticas comparadas, realizado sobre la base de estudios anteriores cuyos costes han sido ajustados por el índice de precios al consumo (IPC)actual dentro del ámbito de la economía de la salud, en el que se elaboró un árbol de decisión con tres ramas decisionales (estadios moderado, severo y muy severo de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica &#150;EPOC&#150;).En el análisis se incluyeron los costes directos sanitarios del tratamiento estable, del tratamiento de la exacerbación y de la utilización de recursos sanitarios. Resultados: la estrategia de tratamiento con tiotropio supuso una repercusión económica sobre la última cifra de gasto sanitario disponible del 2,7%, mientras que la estrategia de tratamiento con ipratropio, un1,5%. Esto arrojaba una diferencia entre estrategias de un 1,2%, lo que se traducía en 841,1 millones de euros. Conclusiones: si bien la efectividad del tiotropio redunda en una menor probabilidad de exacerbación, los altos costes dependientes del elevado precio del tratamiento base desaconsejan su utilización frente a ipratropio disminuyendo, por tanto, su coste-efectividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(9): 69-77, nov. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto presupuestario del tratamiento de la EPOC en estadios II, III y IV con tiotropio versus ipratropio en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30917^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
