<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90655</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Construction and validation of a self-efficacy scale for physical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The estimation by standardized tests on belief in personal capacity to practice regular physical activity (self-efficacy for physical activity) allows us to make predictions about the actual practice of this behavior. We do not have measuring instruments suitable for this purpose, therefore, we propose to construct and validate a scale to determine levels of self-efficacy of adult users of the Primary Health Care Services for regular physical activity. Methods: Phases: 1) Develop and review the scale by expert judges. 2) A pilot study. 3) Determination of reliability and validity of the test. The sample was 388 adult users (18-65 years) of health centres from the province of Seville selected by cluster sampling (health centres) and quotas (town size, age and sex). Concurrent validity was found by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) and discriminant validity by Beck Depression Inventory (BDI). Results: The results reported adequate content validity and high reliability (Cronbach Alpha &gt; 0,9 in all factors and Beta = 0,96). Exploratory factor analysis showed three factors explaining 52,569% of the variance. The scale was sensitive to activity levels assessed by the IPAQ (F (1)= 4.131; p &lt;0.05) and negatively correlated with BDI (r = -0,127; p &lt;0,05). Conclusions: The psychometric properties of the scale are appropriate for measuring the efficacy of adult users of Health Services to practice regular physical activity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>María Herrera Sánchez, ISabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Méndez, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Del Olmo, Aarón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cabrera, Thais</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Anzano, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La estimación con pruebas estandarizadas de la creencia en la capacidad personal para practicar con regularidad actividad física (autoeficacia para la actividad física) nos permite establecer predicciones sobre la práctica real de esta conducta. El objetivo del trabajo es validar una escala que determine los niveles de autoeficacia de los usuarios adultos de los servicios de salud de atención primaria para realizar actividad física regular. Métodos: Fases: 1) Construcción de la escala y revisión por expertos, 2) Estudio piloto, 3) Determinación de su fiabilidad y validez. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 388 personas de 18 a 65 años usuarias de Centros de Salud de la provincia de Sevilla seleccionadas mediante muestreo por conglomerados (centros de salud) y cuotas (tamaño del municipio, edad y sexo). La validez concurrente fue hallada con el Cuestionario Internacional de Actividad Física (IPAQ) y la discriminante con el Inventario de Depresión de Beck (BDI). Resultados: Validez de contenido y fiabilidad: &amp;#61541; de Cronbach&gt;0,9 en todos los factores y Beta = 0,96. El análisis factorial mostró tres factores que explicaron el 52,569% de la varianza. La escala fue sensible a los niveles de actividad medidos con el IPAQ F (1)= 4.131; p &lt;0,05 y correlacionó negativamente con el BDI (r=-0,127; p &lt;0,05). Conclusiones: Las propiedades psicométricas de la escala son adecuadas para medir la autoeficacia de las personas adultas usuarias de los servicios de salud para practicar actividad física(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(4): 405-417, jul.-ago.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Construcción y validación de una escala de autoeficacia para la actividad física</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
