<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98581</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aortoenteric fistula due to a vascular prosthesis as the cause of gastrointestinal bleeding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aortoenteric fistulas are very rare, but because of the urgent and sometimes life-threatening nature of this complication, its possibility should be taken into consideration, especially if patients have undergone vascular surgery. In such situations, aortoenteric fistula should be included in the differential diagnosis for gastrointestinal bleeding. We report the case of a man who came to the emergency department with hematemes is and rectal bleeding. Diagnosis and treatment are analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caldevilla Bernardo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguía Almansa, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalver Pardines, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fístula aorto-entérica es una entidad muy infrecuente, pero dada la situación urgente y en algunas ocasiones vital que supone su diagnóstico, es importante recordar su existencia, sobre todo en aquellos pacientes que han sido sometidos a una cirugía vascular previa. Por tanto, la hemos de tener en cuenta a la hora de hacer un diagnóstico diferencial con otras causas de hemorragia digestiva. Presentamos el caso de un paciente que acude a urgencias por hematemesis y rectorragia, y analizamos su diagnóstico y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(1): 44-46, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula aorto-entérica secundaria a prótesis vascular como causa de hemorragia digestiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29432^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28066^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1017^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
