<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84941</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous treatment of a dysfunctional aortic bioprosthesis with the coreValveW prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently, percutaneous aortic valve replacement has emerged as a therapeutic option for patients with severe symptomatic aortic stenosis and a high surgical risk. We report our initial experience in four patients with percutaneous implantation of a CoreValve aortic prosthesis to treat aortic bioprosthesis dysfunction involving aortic stenosis or regurgitation. In-hospital and medium-term outcomes were analyzed. The procedure was performed under local anesthesia and guided by angiography. The prosthesis was implanted successfully in all patients, although a second prosthesis was required in one case because the first was positioned too high. There were no major complications. After a mean followup of 7 months (SD, 4.7), all patients remained asymptomatic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Bailón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teresa-Galván, Eduardo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-García, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Franco, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Briales, Juan H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Navarro, Manuel F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-García, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olalla-Mercadé, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El implante valvular aórtico percutáneo ha surgido recientemente como alternativa terapéutica para pacientes con estenosis aórtica severa sintomática y alto riesgo quirúrgico. Se presenta la experiencia inicial en el tratamiento de la disfunción de la bioprótesis aórtica mediante el implante percutáneo de prótesis aórtica CoreValve en 4 pacientes, tanto con estenosis como con insuficiencia aórtica, y se analiza los resultados hospitalarios y a medio plazo. El procedimiento se realizó con anestesia local y guiado por angiografía. Se implantaron con éxito en todos los casos, si bien uno precisó una segunda prótesis por posicionamiento alto de la primera. No hubo complicaciones mayores. Tras un seguimiento medio de 7±4,7 meses, todos los pacientes se encuentran asintomáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(2): 155-158, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento percutáneo de las bioprótesis aórticas disfuncionantes con la prótesis CoreValve®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
