<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140297</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of iron deficiency anemia in a population of different ethnic groups under 6 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Due to the high prevalence of ferropenic diseases and the increase of different immigrant populations with their own eating habits, a population-based study was considered necessary in order to evaluate the nutritional status and document possible iron deficiencies secondary to each food culture. Study purpose: To evaluate the anthropometric parameters, the hemoglobin and ferritin plasmatic concentrations and the sideremy values in each ethnic group. Population and methods: Prospective study carried out from 2008 to 2010, in a paediatrician consultation working area. Population: 307 children from Salt (Girona) under the age of 6, Caucasian (n= 85; 27.4%), Moroccan (n= 87; 28%), Sub-Saharan African (n= 101; 32.5%), Central American (n= 20; 6.4%) and Indian-Paquistan (n= 14; 4.5%). Biochemical parameters: blood count, sideremy and ferritin values. Results: Analysis of anthropometric parameters did not show any relevant difference between the native and the immigrant population. The biochemical data showed a sideremy deficiency (&lt;50 µg/dL) (Caucasian population 38.5%, Moroccan 51%, Sub-Saharan African 43%, Central American 35%, Indian-Paquistan 79%), a ferritin deficiency (&lt;20 ng/mL) (Caucasian population 10.5%, Moroccan 49%, Sub-Saharan African 29%, Central American 15%, Indian-Paquistan 85%) and an hemoglobin deficiency (&lt;10.5 mg/mL) (Caucasian population 3.7%, Moroccan 7%, Sub-Saharan African 15%, Central American 5%, Indian-Paquistan 21%).  Conclusions: No auxologic malnutrition was detected in the studied population; however, there was a clear deficiency in sideremy, ferritin and hemoglobin in the child populations from Morocco and Sub-Saharan Africa, this being even more evident among the Indian-Paquistan population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Audí Parera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Lezcano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muro, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yeste Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cancio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La alta prevalencia de ferropenia en nuestro medio, así como el número elevado de población inmigrante con hábitos y culturas alimentarias diferentes, fundamentan un estudio para evaluar el estado nutricional y documentar la presencia de ferropenias secundarias a las diversas pautas de alimentación.  Objetivos: Evaluar los parámetros antropométricos y las concentraciones plasmáticas de hemoglobina, ferritina y sideremia de cada etnia. Población y métodos: Estudio prospectivo realizado durante los años 2008-2010 en una consulta de pediatría de atención primaria, en una población de 307 niños de Salt (Girona), con una edad inferior a 6 años, de diferentes etnias: caucásicos (n= 85; 27,4%), magrebíes (n= 87; 28%), subsaharianos (n= 101; 32,5%), centroamericanos (n= 20; 6,4%) e indopakistaníes (n= 14; 4,5%). Los parámetros bioquímicos estudiados fueron la hematimetría, la sideremia y la ferritina.  Resultados: El análisis de los parámetros antropométricos no demuestra diferencias significativas entre la población autóctona y la inmigrante. En el análisis bioquímico se pone de manifiesto un déficit de hierro (sideremia &lt;50 µg/dL) (caucásicos 38,5%, magrebíes 51%, subsaharianos 43%, centroamericanos 35%, indopakistaníes 79%), un déficit de ferritina (&lt;20 ng/mL) (caucásicos 10,5%, magrebíes 49%, subsaharianos 29%, centroamericanos 15% e indopakistaníes 85%) y un déficit de hemoglobina (&lt;10,5 mg/mL) (caucásicos 3,7%, magrebíes 7%, subsaharianos 15%, centroamericanos 5% e indopakistaníes 21%).  Conclusiones: No se ha detectado desnutrición con repercusión auxológica en las poblaciones evaluadas. Pero se aprecia un déficit de hierro, ferritina y hemoglobina en las poblaciones infantiles magrebí, subsahariana y, de forma más acusada, indopakistaní (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(5): 120-125, mayo 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la anemia ferropénica en niños menores de 6 años de edad de diferentes etnias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22189^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22189^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
