<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123126</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Capacity analysis of health food choice by reference to consumers in two models of nutritional labeling: crossover study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of this study was to compare two models of nutrition labeling front-of-pack, in reference to the ability of consumers to choose a diet closer to nutritional recommendations. Methods: Randomized crossover design in 32 adults (18-65 years) of both sexes. Participants were randomly exposed to two experimental conditions using nutritional traffic light system (S-SN) or monochrome system (SM). Participants had to choose options from a closed menu for five days on the basis of the experimental front-of-pack labelling. For each meal, three food options with different nutritional compositions were given to the participants. The total energy and fat, saturated fat, sugar and salt of the chosen options were calculated. Results: No significant differences at baseline socio-demographic and anthropometric characteristics were shown between individuals regardless of the experimental condition in which they started. The subjects tended to choose a diet with a lower, but not significant energy content of 23.0 ± 67.5 (P = 0.063) and a significantly lower sugar content of 3.5 ± 9.2 g, P &lt; 0.001 and 0.6 ± 1 g, P &lt; 0.003 for salt. Conclusions: Compared to the to the monochrome system, the multiple traffic-light system probably can help make food choices with less sugar and salt in a situation similar to the usual purchase in which there is a time limitation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salas-Salvadó, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Babio, Nancy</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del presente estudio fue comparar dos modelos de etiquetado nutricional en la parte frontal del envase alimentario, en referencia a la capacidad de los consumidores de realizar elecciones alimentarias más cercanas a las recomendaciones nutricionales. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio aleatorizado cruzado en 32 adultos (18 a 65 años) de ambos sexos. Los participantes fueron aleatorizados a realizar dos condiciones experimentales utilizando el sistema semáforo nutricional (S-SN) o el sistema monocromo (S-M), en las que debían escoger sus elecciones de alimentos dentro de un menú cerrado según la información del etiquetado nutricional. Para cada alimento, el participante tenía tres opciones con diferente composición nutricional. Se calculó el promedio de energía, grasa total y saturada, azúcar y sal a partir de las opciones elegidas por cada participante. Resultados: No se observaron diferencias significativas con respecto a sexo, edad, IMC ni nivel socioeconómico en función del orden de inicio de la condición experimental. Los sujetos tendieron a escoger una dieta con un menor, pero no significativo contenido en energía de 23,0 ± 67,5 kcal (P = 0,063) y un significativo menor contenido en azúcares de 3,5 ± 9,2 g; P &lt; 0.001 y de 0,6 ± 1 g; P &lt; 0, 003 en sal. Conclusiones: En comparación con el sistema monocromo, el sistema del semáforo nutricional puede ayudar probablemente a realizar elecciones alimentarias con menor cantidad en azúcares y sal en una situación similar a la habitual de compra en la que existe una limitación de tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(1): 173-181, ene.-feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la capacidad de elección de alimentos saludables por parte de los consumidores en referencia a dos modelos de etiquetado nutricional: estudio cruzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5654</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
