<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74081</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary closure in GBR. Mucogingival flaps and grafts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Guided Bone Regeneration (GBR) is the process by which we try to induce the regeneration of bone tissue in an area that has suffered bone loss. It is based on the cellular exclusion principle, the objective of which is to keep epithelium cells and the cells of gingival connective tissue away from bone defects. The colonisation of these cells occurs much more rapidly than by osteoblasts. Keeping the cells away allows this "empty" area to be filled with bone tissue and not with epithelium and gingival connective tissue. The cellular exclusion principle requires a series of conditions including the primary closure of the wound. To guarantee closure, there are a series of guidelines that must be followed to ensure the passive approximation of the edges of the wound: a specific way of making the incisions, specific designs of flaps and grafts, and specific ways to suture them. Compliance with these guidelines shall ensure the success of the GBR treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Plaza Julián, Antonio de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rosado Castrillo, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La regeneración ósea guiada (ROG), es el proceso mediante el cual intentamos inducir la regeneración del tejido óseo en una zona que ha sufrido una pérdida del mismo. Se basa en el principio de exclusión celular cuyo objetivo es mantener al margen de un defecto óseo a las células del epitelio y el conectivo gingival. La colonización de estas células ocurre de forma mucho más rápida que la llevada a cabo por los osteoblastos. Mantener dichas células al margen permite que esa zona "vacía" se rellene de tejido óseo y no de epitelio y conectivo gingival. El principio de exclusión celular exige una serie de condiciones entre las que se encuentra el cierre primario de la herida. Para garantizar dicho cierre, tenemos una serie de pautas a seguir que garanticen la aproximación pasiva de los márgenes de la herida: una forma determinada de realizar las incisiones, unos diseños concretos de colgajos o injertos y formas de suturarlos específicas. Es el cumplimiento de dichas pautas, lo que hace de la ROG un tratamiento de éxito predecible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);6(1): 49-60, ene.-abr.  2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74081</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cierre primario en ROG. Colgajos e injertos mucogingivales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6032^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1886</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
