<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054568</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The metabolic regulation of cerebral microcirculation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse the mechanisms involved in the microvascular metabolic regulation of cerebral blood flow. The    article outlines the neuronal metabolism and mechanisms involved in functional hyperaemia and examines the contractile    properties of brain microvasculature. It also discusses the role played by ion channels in pericytes and vascular smooth    muscle and describes the signalling pathways involved in arteriolar and capillary vasodilatation or vasoconstriction.    Development. The blood-brain barrier and the close functional relations between neurons and astrocytes give rise to nerve    tissue properties such as functional hyperaemia. In this mechanism the astrocytes act as a structural and functional &#145;bridge&#146;    between neurons and brain capillaries, and respond to synaptic activity by releasing vasoactive compounds, above all    vasodilators. The metabolites derived from arachidonic acid, such as prostaglandins and epoxyeicosatrienoic acids, as well as    the compounds that have traditionally been involved, such as nitric oxide and prostacyclin, are especially important. These    substances are capable of extending to the capillaries and arterioles, where they alter the membrane potential and the    contractibility of the pericytes and the smooth muscle of vessels. Conclusions. The functional interaction among neurons,    astrocytes and capillaries in the central nervous system (called the &#145;neurovascular unit&#146;) is essential for the regulation of    cerebral blood flow, since it links neuron-glial cell metabolic activity to the supply of energetic substrates from the microcirculation.    Within this functional unit, astrocytes play a vital role by releasing vasoactive substances that are derived from or    produced by neuronal activity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tamayo-Orrego, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque-Parra, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar los mecanismos implicados en la regulación metabólica microvascular del flujo sanguíneo cerebral.    Se describe el metabolismo neuronal y los mecanismos implicados en la hiperemia funcional, se examinan las propiedades    contráctiles de la microvasculatura cerebral, se plantea el papel de los canales iónicos en los pericitos y el músculo liso    vascular y se describen las vías de señalización implicadas en la vasodilatación o vasoconstricción arteriolar y capilar. Desarrollo.    La barrera hematoencefálica y las estrechas relaciones funcionales entre neuronas y astrocitos generan propiedades al    tejido nervioso, como la hiperemia funcional. En este mecanismo, los astrocitos actúan de &#145;puente&#146; estructural y funcional    entre neuronas y capilares cerebrales, respondiendo a la actividad sináptica mediante la liberación de compuestos vasoactivos,    principalmente vasodilatadores. Son de especial importancia los metabolitos derivados del ácido araquidónico, como    prostaglandinas y ácidos epoxieicosatrienoicos, además de los compuestos tradicionalmente implicados, como óxido nítrico    y prostaciclina. Estas sustancias tienen la capacidad de difundir hasta los capilares y las arteriolas, donde alteran el potencial    de membrana y la contractilidad de los pericitos y el músculo liso vascular. Conclusiones. La interacción funcional entre    neuronas, astrocitos y capilares del sistema nervioso central (denominada &#145;unidad neurovascular&#146;) resulta esencial en la regulación    del flujo sanguíneo cerebral, ya que asocia la actividad metabólica neurona-glía al suministro de sustratos energéticos    desde la microcirculación. En esta unidad funcional, los astrocitos desempeñan un papel vital liberando sustancias vasoactivas    derivadas o producidas a consecuencia de la actividad neuronal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(7): 415-425, abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regulación metabólica de la microcirculación cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9022^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33891^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2485^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7120^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28252^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2599^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
