<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135247</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Other pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors: glucagonomas, vipomas, somatostatinomas, nonfunctioning tumors and ectopic hormonesecreting tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endocrine tumors of the pancreas are infrequent, representing between 1 and 2% of pancreatic tumors. These tumors are usually solitary, but may occur in association with other tumors within multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN-1) syndrome or Von Hippel-Lindau syndrome. Nonfunctioning endocrine tumors represent approximately 30 to 40% of endocrine tumors of the pancreas, manifesting as compression symptoms or invasion of surrounding structures. Diagnosis of these tumors is based on determination of general tumoral markers such as chromogranin A. Functioning endocrine tumors other than gastrinoma and insulinoma (glucagonomas, vipomas, somatostatinomas) are extremely infrequent and are usually accompanied by a characteristic clinical syndrome. The diagnosis of these tumors is based on determination of specific peptides segregated for each tumor. Pancreatic endocrine tumors can sometimes release peptide hormones characteristic of other endocrine glands, which are not present in pancreatic tissue under normal conditions (ectopic hormone secretion). These tumors are usually large and easy to localize. However, highly specific techniques are sometimes required for their localization (endoscopic ultrasonography, octreotide scintigraphy, angiography). Diagnosis is usually made late and metastases are common. Despite the presence of disseminated disease, a subgroup of patients show prolonged survival. Of the multiple treatments available (chemoembolization, radiofrequency, chemotherapy, somatostatin analogs, interferon-alpha), the only curative therapy is complete tumoral resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aller, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos son poco frecuentes y representan entre el 1 y el 2% de los tumores pancreáticos. Habitualmente se presentan de forma aislada, pero pueden hacerlo asociados a otros tumores dentro del síndrome de neoplasia endocrina múltiple tipo 1 (MEN1) o el síndrome de Von Hippel-Lindau. Los tumores neuroendocrinos no funcionantes suponen aproximadamente el 30-40% de los tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos, se presentan con síntomas derivados de la compresión o invasión de estructuras cercanas y su diagnóstico se basa en la determinación de marcadores tumorales no específicos, como la cromogranina A. Los tumores endocrinos funcionantes distintos de gastrinoma e insulinoma (glucagonomas, VIPomas, somatostatinomas) son extremadamente raros y suelen acompañarse de un síndrome clínico muy característico. Su diagnóstico se basa en la determinación de los péptidos específicos segregados por cada tumor. En ocasiones, los tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos pueden liberar hormonas peptídicas características de otras glándulas endocrinas, no presentes en el tejido pancreático en condiciones normales (secreción hormonal ectópica). Estos tumores generalmente son de gran tamaño y fáciles de localizar, pero en ocasiones son necesarias técnicas muy específicas para su localización (ecografía endoscópica, gammagrafía con octreótida, angiografía). El diagnóstico suele realizarse de forma tardía, y es frecuente la presencia de metástasis. A pesar de la existencia de enfermedad diseminada un subgrupo de pacientes presentan una supervivencia prolongada. De los múltiples tratamientos disponibles (quimioembolización, radiofrecuencia, quimioterapia, análogos de somatostatina, interferón &amp;#945;) ninguno, salvo la resección completa del tumor, puede curar la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(supl.1): 31-37, ene. 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Otros tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos: glucagonomas, VIPomas, somatostatinomas, no funcionantes y tumores con secreción ectópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6886^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54000^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13388^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31819^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6079^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
