<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168084</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of animal-assisted therapy in patients with dementia: A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the effectiveness of animal-assisted therapy on the symptoms of dementia as shown in previous studies. Material and methods: A search strategy was developed using the PUBMED, DIALNET, PEDro and CSIC databases to capture all clinical trials published between 2003 and 2015 in English and Spanish. Search terms included the combination of the keywords: 'dog therapy, dementia, pet therapy, mental illness, animal assisted, elderly patients, animal assisted therapy, animal assisted therapy, dementia, Alzheimer's.' Three records were selected from the 157 located after applying the inclusion criteria. Conclusions: The dog is the most commonly used in animal-assisted therapy in dementia. This therapy produces an improvement in behaviour, mood, quality of life, activities of daily living, and mental stress of people with dementia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido Ardila, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López-Arza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Palomares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Sánchez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mansilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Sintetizar la efectividad presentada por estudios originales previos de la terapia asistida con animales en la sintomatología de personas con demencia. Material y métodos: Se desarrolló una estrategia de búsqueda en las bases de datos PUBMED, DIALNET, PEDro y CSIC con el fin de captar todos aquellos ensayos clínicos publicados entre 2003 y 2015 en inglés y español. Los términos de búsqueda incluyeron la combinación de las palabras clave: «dog therapy, dementia, pet therapy, mental illnes, animal assisted, ederly patients, animal assisted therapy, terapia asistida con animales, demencia, Alzheimer». Se seleccionaron 3 registros de los 157 localizados tras aplicar los criterios de inclusión. Conclusiones: La terapia más utilizada a la hora de llevar a cabo terapia asistida con animales en demencia es la canina. Esta terapia produce una mejora en el comportamiento, estado de ánimo, calidad de vida, actividades de la vida diaria y en el estrés mental de personas que padecen demencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(6): 242-249, nov.-dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la terapia asistida con animales en pacientes con demencias, una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53694^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53694^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
