<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144625</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical skills training in the third course of Medicine. Sequential evaluation of five cycles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. There are very few studies regarding the clinical skills training of a particular matter. In the present study the experience in clinical training in the matter &#145;Semiology and Clinical Propedeutics&#146; from the Faculty of Medicine in the University of Barcelona is presented. The results of surveys from five consecutive cycles are compared. Materials and methods. The period of study represents five cycles (2011-2014) since the matter is developed twice a year. The clinical period training in the matter spent seven weeks (28 days) and the number of students for each of the seven different facilities ranged from 4-8. When arriving, the students are informed about the objectives to be achieved through their training period, and at the end they are asked about the voluntary and anonymous survey complementation. Results. A total of 95% (n = 477) of the requested surveys were collected. A very good global qualification was assessed (median: 5; first quartile: 4, in 1-5 scale), without significant differences among the different evaluated periods of time (p = 0.658). Conclusions. Clinical skills training in this matter is considered near excellent without significant variations through the five consecutive periods analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antúnez, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobos, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existen pocos estudios que de forma selectiva valoren la docencia clínica de una determinada asignatura. En este artículo se presenta la experiencia en docencia clínica de la asignatura &#145;Semiología General y Propedéutica Clínica&#146; en tercer curso del Grado de Medicina en la Facultad de Medicina de la Universitat de Barcelona. Materiales y métodos. Se han analizado los cursos 2011-2012, 2012-2013 y 2013-2014, representando un total de cinco &#145;cursos&#146;, ya que la asignatura es semestral y se imparte dos veces en cada curso académico. El período de docencia clínica de la asignatura es de siete semanas (28 días) y el número de alumnos oscila entre cuatro y ocho por cada una de las siete unidades/centros distintos. A su llegada se les informa de los objetivos de la estancia clínica y al final del período se les invita a cumplimentar una encuesta anónima y voluntaria en la que valoran distintos ítems. Resultados. Se han recogido 477 encuestas (95%). Se constató una muy buena valoración global del período de docencia clínica (mediana: 5; primer cuartil: 4, en escala de 1 a 5), sin variaciones significativas entre los distintos períodos evaluados (p = 0,658). Conclusiones. La docencia clínica en esta asignatura está muy bien valorada de forma global, sin detectar variaciones relevantes en los cinco cursos analizados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(5): 331-335, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la docencia clínica en tercer curso del Grado de Medicina. Estudio secuencial de cinco cursos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
