<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134419</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of exercise on the body composition and aerobic capacity of elderly with obesity through three models of intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of this study was to analyze the influence of aerobic exercise on body composition and aerobic capacity of a sample of older, sedentary adults with obesity rates by three different models of intervention(recommendation, prescription at home and monitoring).Material and Methods: A total of 76older adults with a mean age 67.1+/-1.2years, sedentary, with a BMI&gt; 30 kg/m2 were randomized in to four groups: Control (CON)recommendation (REC), prescription home (PRES) and monitoring in a sports center (MON). The same program of aerobic exercise for groups of home and sports center for 24 weeks, 3 days a week was developed. It was determined before and after the intervention BMI, Waist Hip-index(ICC), the% fat (&amp;#931; folds) and aerobic capacity(T6M) throughout the sample. Results: MON and PRES groups showed significant improvements in the ICC, &amp;#931; folds and T 6M variables, not the case in BMI. However the MON group presented significant differences from group PRES between-group analysis (p &lt;0.001). The recommendation did not get positive effects. Conclusion: Monitoring is the most effective exercise programs in adults with obesity methodology. However the exercise prescription at home since early intervention is an important approach for people with physical and/ or psychological reasons such as obesity cannot access the sports centers to participate in activities led by a monitor. Unknowns of aerobic exercise are cleared in the home that are of great impact for social policies regarding the health of the elderly population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Valle, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abelairas-Gómez, Cristian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nistal, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcala-Furelos, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la influencia del ejercicio aeróbico en la composición corporal y la capacidad aeróbica de una muestra de adultos mayores, sedentarios y con índices de obesidad, mediante tres modelos diferentes de intervención (recomendación, prescripción en el hogar y monitorización).Material y método: Participaron 76 adultos mayores con una edad media 67.1 + / - 1.2 años, sedentarios, con un IMC &gt; 30 kg/m2 que se distribuyeron aleatoriamente en cuatro grupos: Control (CON) recomendación (REC),prescripción en el hogar (PRES) y monitorización en un centro deportivo (MON). Se desarrolló un mismo programa de ejercicio físico aeróbico para los grupos de hogar y centro deportivo durante 24 semanas, 3 días a la semana. Se determinó antes y después de la intervención el IMC, el Índice-Cadera-Cintura (ICC), el % graso (&amp;#931; Pligues) y la capacidad aeróbica (T 6M) en toda la muestra. Resultados: Los grupos MON y PRES mostraron mejoras significativas en las variables ICC, &amp;#931; Pliegues y T6M, no siendo así en el IMC. Sin embargo el grupo MON presentó diferencias significativas respecto al grupo PRES en el análisis entre-grupos (p&lt;0.001). La recomendación no obtuvo efectos positivos. Conclusión: La monitorización es la metodología más eficaz para los programas de ejercicio físico en población adulta con obesidad. Sin embargo la prescripción del ejercicio en el hogar desde la atención temprana supone un importante enfoque para personas que por motivos físicos y/o psicológicos como es el caso de la obesidad no pueden acceder a los centros deportivos a participar en actividades dirigidas por un monitor. Se despejan incógnitas del ejercicio aeróbico en el hogar que son de gran repercusión para las políticas sociales con relación a la salud de la población adulta mayor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(3): 1217-1224, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Repercusión del ejercicio físico en la composición corporal y la capacidad aeróbica de adultos mayores con obesidad mediante tres modelos de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27892</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
