<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99384</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant retroperitoneal sarcoma: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report a new case of giant retroperitoneal mass with silent beginning. METHODS: We present the case of a 36 year old man with a giant retroperitoneal liposarcoma 35 x 15 cm in size. The only symptom was a one month history of minimal abdominal pain. CONCLUSION: Liposarcoma is the most frequent retroperitoneal mass. In most of the cases clinical symptoms are silent, being this the reason why diagnosis is late and the size is large. The best image options are CT scan or MRI but final diagnosis is based on pathology results. Its treatment is surgery and relapse is very usual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Carral, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuervo, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemany, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Pello, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Villamil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar un nuevo caso de masa retroperitoneal gigante. MÉTODOS: Se presenta el caso de un varón de 36 años con un liposarcoma retroperitoneal gigante de 35 x 15 cm cuyo único síntoma actual es una molestia abdominal de un mes de evolución. CONCLUSIÓN: El liposarcoma supone la masa retroperitoneal más frecuente, dando lugar en la mayoría de los casos a una sintomatología silente, lo que implica un retraso en su diagnóstico y un gran incremento en su tamaño. Las pruebas de imagen más concluyentes son la Tc o la Rmn pero el diagnóstico de certeza es histológico. Su tratamiento es quirúgico, el objetivo es la exéresis completa pero la recidiva es la norma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(4): 492-495, mayo 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Liposarcoma retroperitoneal gigante: presentación de un nuevo caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
