<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85441</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender and self-perceived health in childhood and adolescence in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo describe gender differences in self-perceived health and health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in childhood and adolescence in Spain, to compare the results in distinct studies using different HRQoL instruments, and to analyze the influence of sociodemographic factors and reported morbidity on self-perceived health and HRQoL according to gender.MethodsWe analyzed data from previous studies of HRQoL: the Child Health and Illness Profile (child and adolescent editions, n=2451), the KIDSCREEN (n=908), and Vecú Perçue et Santé de l&#146;Adolescent (n=1,242). Logistic regression models of worse perceived health (good/fair/poor vs. excellent/very good) and worse HRQoL (less than 0.8 standard deviations from the mean vs. the remaining distribution) were adjusted to analyze gender differences. A summary measure of differences in perceived health according to gender was obtained.ResultsThe response rates varied among the studies (total sample n=4.601). Girls showed a higher odds ratio (OR) than boys for perceiving worse overall health and physical and emotional health, but a lower OR in school environment dimensions. The overall OR for worse perceived health was 1.28 (95% confidence interval [95%CI]: 0.97&#150;1.68) in younger girls and was 2.17 (95%CI: 1.88&#150;2.51) in adolescent girls.ConclusionsGirls were twice as likely as boys to perceive worse health, as well as worse HRQoL in the physical and emotional dimensions. Gender perspective should be taken into account when implementing preventive and health promotion measures for children and adolescents(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Aguilà, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez Galárraga, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rajmil,  Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDescribir las diferencias de género en salud autopercibida y en calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en la infancia y la adolescencia en España; comparar los resultados entre estudios que utilizaron diferentes instrumentos de medida; y analizar la influencia de factores sociodemográficos y de la morbilidad declarada en la salud percibida y la CVRS según el género.MétodosSe analizaron datos de estudios previos de CVRS: el Child Health and Illness Profile (versiones infantil y de adolescentes, n=2451), el KIDSCREEN (n=908), y el Vecú et Sante Perçue de l&#146;Adolescent (n=1.242). Se construyeron modelos de regresión logística de peor salud percibida (buena/regular/mala frente a excelente/muy buena) y peor CVRS (menos de 0,8 desviaciones estándar de la media frente al resto de la distribución) para analizar las diferencias de género. Se obtuvo una medida resumen de las diferencias en salud percibida según el género.ResultadosLa proporción de respuesta fue variable entre los estudios (n total=4.601). Las chicas presentaron odds ratio (OR) mayores que los chicos para percibir peor salud general, física y emocional, pero menores en el ámbito escolar. La OR global de peor salud general fue de 1,28 (intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]: 0,97&#150;1,68) en niñas y de 2,17 (IC95%: 1,88&#150;2,51) en chicas.ConclusionesSer chica condiciona el doble de probabilidades de percibir peor salud y CVRS en los aspectos físicos y emocionales que los chicos. La perspectiva de género se debería tener en cuenta en la implementación de medidas de prevención y promoción de la salud infantil y adolescente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(5): 433-439, sep. -oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Género y salud percibida en la infancia y la adolescencia en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
