<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121755</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervical rib in the differential diagnosis of supraclavicular mass</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cervical rib is a supernumerary rib arising from the seventh cervical vertebra and ends freely in the tissue of the neck or articulates with the first rib. It can be diagnosed as an asymptomatic incidental finding on a chest radiograph or presented with supraclavicular pain or complications as thoracic outlet syndrome. The differential diagnosis often poses malignant tumor masses, because of their characteristics in the physical exam. The management is often conservative reserving surgical intervention for highly symptomatic or complicated cases. We report a case of symptomatic cervical rib and its approach from Primary Care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros Lara, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Sala, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Montes, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La costilla cervical consiste en una costilla supernumeraria que surge de la séptima vértebra cervical y termina libremente en el tejido del cuello o se articula con la primera costilla. Puede ser asintomática y diagnosticarse como hallazgo casual en una radiografía de tórax, o bien presentarse con dolor en la región supraclavicular o como complicación en forma de síndrome del desfiladero torácico. A menudo plantea diagnóstico diferencial con masas tumorales malignas, por sus características en la exploración. El manejo suele ser conservador y la intervención quirúrgica se reserva para casos muy sintomáticos o complicados. Presentamos un caso clínico de costilla cervical sintomática y su abordaje desde Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(61): 45-48, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costilla cervical en el diagnóstico diferencial de una masa supraclavicular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53415^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53415^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53415^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53415^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
