<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048175</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an immunoassay kit to measure free testosterone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objetives: The best indicators to the diagnosis of hypogonadism are free and bioavailable testosterone    circulating levels. Free and bioavailable testosterone measurements are complex. However, simple kits for direct    measurement of free testosterone by analog immunoassay are available. We examined the utility of an enzymoimmunoassay    kit for free testosterone measurement.    Material and method: One hundred thirty-three healthy males were included. Total testosterone, SHBG, albumin and    free testosterone was measured. We used two different methods to free testosterone estimation: direct measurement by    enzymoimmunoassay and mathematical calculation with Vermeulen&#146;s formula, which uses albumin concentration, total    testosterone and SHBG to calculate free testosterone (method recommended by the International Society for the Study of    the Aging Male). We compared the two methods means values and a linear regression study was performed.    Results: Mean age was 37 ± 11 years. Mean serum concentration for total testosterone was 21.43 ± 6.8 nm ol/L. The    mean value for free testosterone measured by direct and mathematical method was 0.0508 ± 0.0118 nmol/L and    0.474±0.123 nmol/L respectively. In linear regression study exists a positive correlation between both methods (p&lt; 0.05),    although correlation coefficient is very low (r = 0.25).    Conclusions: There are significant statistical differences between the measurements of free testosterone by direct and    mathematical methods. Although certain correlation is observed, this is very low. In conclusion, free testosterone measurement    by enzymoimmunoassay is not reliable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Salom, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jabaloyas, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chuan Nuez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queipo Zaragozá, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los mejores indicadores bioquímicos para el diagnóstico del hipogonadismo son la testosterona    libre y la biodisponible. La determinación de ambas fracciones de testosterona es compleja, aunque se han desarrollado    técnicas de inmunoanálisis que permiten la determinación de la testosterona libre de manera directa y sencilla.    Valoramos la utilidad de una técnica no evaluada de enzimoinmunoanálisis para la determinación de testosterona libre.    Material y métodos: En el estudio se incluyeron 133 varones sanos en los que se determinó la testosterona total, la    SHBG, la albúmina y la testosterona libre. La testosterona libre fue determinada mediante 2 métodos diferentes: determinación    directa mediante enzimoinmunoanálisis (DSL 10-49100 ACTIVE(R) Free Testosterone EIA, Diagnostics System    Laboratories) y mediante cálculo matemático utilizando la fórmula desarrollada por Vermeulen, que utiliza la concentración    de albúmina, testosterona total y SHBG para calcular la testosterona libre (método recomendado por la    'International Society for the Study of the Aging Male'). Comparamos los valores obtenidos mediante un test de comparación    de medias y realizamos un análisis de regresión para observar el grado de correlación existente entre ambos tipos    de determinaciones.    Resultados: La edad media fue de 37 ± 11 años. Los niveles medios de testosterona total fue de 21,43 ± 6,8 nmol/L    y los de testosterona libre de 0,0508 ± 0,0118 nmol/L para el método directo y de 0,474 ± 0,123 nmol/L para el método    matemático (p&lt;0,05). En el estudio de regresión lineal se observa que aunque existe una correlación positiva entre    ambos métodos (p&lt;0,05) el coeficiente de correlación es bajo (r = 0,25).    Conclusiones: Existen diferencias significativas entre los valores de testosterona libre determinados por el método    directo de enzimoinmunoanálisis y la testosterona libre calculada. Aunque se observa una cierta correlación, esta es tan    baja que hace poco fiable la utilización del enzimoinmunoanálisis para la determinación de la testosterona libre</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(6): 598-601, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de una técnica de inmunoanálisis para la determinación de testosterona libre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d740^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d740^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
