<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62127</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The unstable knee prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prosthetic instability is the third most frequent cause for the failure of total kneereplacement (TKR), which leads to between 10% and 22% of surgical revisions. In additionto individual factors such as previous instabilities or deformities, an associatedneuromuscular condition, rheumatoid arthritis or obesity, the main causes for prostheticinstability are related to errors in selecting the primary prosthesis or mistakes in thesurgical technique, i.e. inadequate bone resections, failure to obtain an appropriatejoint balance with symmetrical fl exion and extension gaps, causing a iatrogenic laxity,etc. &#150; all of them easily preventable. In order to successfully correct these instabilities,it is indispensable to identify its causes so as to be able to address and thereby avoidrepeating the same mistakes that provoked them in the fi rst place. As, the majority ofcases will require surgical treatment and prosthetic revision, in this study we carry outan analysis of the different models available. As a general rule, we recommend the useof a prosthetic model with the minimum constraint necessary to achieve stability, takinginto account that a posterostabilized prosthesis may be able to address a fl exioninstability, although it cannot compensate for a medial-lateral instability, and that evenif a highly constrained prosthesis can compensate for both instabilities initially, in thelong term it can lead to mechanical complications(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Merchán, E. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Tovar, O. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La inestabilidad protésica es la tercera causa más frecuente de fallo de una prótesis totalde rodilla (PTR). Entre el 10 y el 22% de las revisiones quirúrgicas se deben a esta causa.Además de factores individuales, como inestabilidades o deformidades previas, afecciónneuromuscular concomitante, artritis reumatoide u obesidad, las principales causas se deben a errores en la selección de la prótesis primaria o a defectos en la técnica quirúrgica,como inadecuadas resecciones óseas, no obtener un apropiado balance con espaciosimétrico en extensión y fl exión o producir una laxitud iatrogénica, por lo que pueden serprevenibles. Para obtener un buen resultado en su corrección es imprescindible identifi -car la causa de la inestabilidad a fi n de actuar sobre ella y no repetir los errores que laprodujeron. La mayor&#155;´a de los casos requerirán tratamiento quirúrgico y recambio protésico,por lo que en este artículo realizamos un análisis de los distintos modelos disponibles.Como regla general recomendamos utilizar un modelo de prótesis con la m&#155;´nimaconstricción necesaria para lograr la estabilidad, teniendo en cuenta que una prótesisestabilizada posterior puede solucionar una inestabilidad en fl exión, aunque no compensauna inestabilidad medio-lateral, y que si bien una prótesis altamente constreñidacompensa inicialmente ambas inestabilidades, a largo plazo pueden producir complicacionesmecánicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);53(2): 113-119, mar.-abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62127</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La prótesis total de rodilla inestable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7895^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7895^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7895^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
