<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146163</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status and biochemical markers of deficiency or excess of micronutrients in 4 to 14 year-old Chilean children: a critical review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of obesity in Chilean children has been increasing steadily for the last two decades. The first study to determine nutritional status and food intake in a representative sample of this population was carried out in 1960. Recently the National Food Consumption Survey (ENCA) carried out in 2012 was released by the Ministry of Health. However, this study did not include biochemical determinations of micronutrients which would allow a better diagnosis of nutritional status in children. Objective: to review the literature available from 2004 to 2014 in food intake and nutritional status in Chilean children aged 4 to 14 years. Method: a total of 362 references published between 2004 and 2014 were obtained through searches in the databases PubMed, Lilacs, Embase and Scielo. From these, 40 articles were selected for a thorough review. Results: food intake by children is characterized by a high-energy intake, a low consumption of fruits and vegetables and a high consumption of bread. The ENCA showed that 95% of the Chilean population has a deficient diet. A high prevalence of obesity is observed from very early in life. There is a dearth of data available on plasma indicators of vitamin and mineral status since 1960, which would provide more reliable information on nutritional assessment. Conclusion: It is imperative to implement a representative nutrition survey of children in Chile that includes biochemical indicators to get reliable information in order to develop strategies aimed to correct micronutrient malnutrition from excess or deficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Díaz, Diego F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruchet Muñoz, Sylvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozowski Narkunska, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Bravo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gotteland Russel, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Valenzuela, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figari Jullian, Nicole</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weisstaub Nuta, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de obesidad en niños chilenos ha aumentado consistentemente en las últimas dos décadas. El primer estudio que determinó el estado nutricional y la ingesta de alimentos efectuado en una muestra representativa de la población fue llevado a cabo en 1960. Recientemente el Ministerio de Salud publicó la Encuesta Nacional de Consumo Alimentario (ENCA), efectuada en el año 2012. Sin embargo, este estudio no incluyó mediciones bioquímicas de nutrientes que permitan un diagnóstico integral y representativo de la condición nutricional del niño en Chile. Objetivos: revisar la literatura disponible entre los años 2004 y 2014 sobre ingesta de alimentos y estado nutricional en niños chilenos de 4 a 14 años de edad. Método: un total de 362 referencias publicadas en ese período se obtuvieron de las bases de datos PubMed, Lilacs, Embase y Scielo. De estos, 40 artículos fueron seleccionados para una revisión completa. Resultados: la ingesta de alimentos se caracteriza por una ingesta calórica alta; un bajo consumo de frutas, verduras y productos lácteos y un alto consumo de pan. La ENCA concluyó que un 95% de los chilenos presenta una dieta deficiente. Se observa una alta prevalencia de obesidad desde edades tempranas. Desde 1960 no ha habido un estudio representativo de la población que incluya niveles plasmáticos de micronutrientes, que proveerían información más confiable sobre el estado nutricional de los niños, además de encuestas de consumo de alimentos. Conclusión: los niños chilenos presentan un estado nutricional y una alimentación deficientes; sin embargo, no hay evidencia representativa de los niveles plasmáticos de nutrientes, por lo que es imperativo desarrollar un estudio representativo que incluya indicadores bioquímicos de micronutrientes con objeto de desarrollar estrategias para mejorar el estado nutricional de los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2916-2925, dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146163</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional y marcadores bioquímicos de deficiencia o exceso de micronutrientes en niños chilenos de 4 a 14 años de edad: una revisión crítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
