<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97768</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequency transposition. Impact on identification skills, auditory comprehension, and voice quality in young adults with profound hearing loss</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Based on the need to enhance perception of more high-pitched acoustic features of speech phonemes, we present this study on the changes observed in a group of young people with severe-profound hearing impairment after trialling the frequency transposition technology of the Mind440-19 hearing aid, using the Audibility Extender. The sample of the study was a group of 7young people with ages ranging from 13 to 25years, divided into two groups based on their audiometric configuration. The first group consisted of 4subjects with a mean pure tone of 99dB. The second group had more profound hearing loss, with a mean pure tone of 105dB in both ears. Frequency transposition benefit was measured through a test battery including Ling's test, an identification test and a word recognition test. Tests were administered after 4, 8, and 12weeks of hearing aid use, and compared with results from the previous hearing aids used by the participants, with their Audibility Extender off(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gou, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero-Garcia, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Smith, Jane</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir de la necesidad de facilitar la percepción de los rasgos acústicos más agudos de los fonemas del habla, se presenta un estudio sobre los cambios observados en un grupo de jóvenes con discapacidad auditiva severa-profunda, después de utilizar la transposición frecuencial proporcionada por unos audífonos digitales Mind440-19, mediante el extensor de audibilidad. La muestra del estudio la constituyó un grupo de 7jóvenes con edades comprendidas entre los 13 y los 25años, divididos en dos grupos, en función de su configuración audiométrica. El primer grupo estuvo formado por 4participantes con una pérdida auditiva promedio de 99dB. El segundo grupo presentó una pérdida mayor, con un promedio de 105 dB para ambos oídos. El beneficio de la transposición frecuencial se comprobó mediante una batería de pruebas que incluía el test de Ling, un test de identificación y otro de reconocimiento de palabras. Las pruebas fueron administradas después de 4, 8 y 12semanas de emplear los nuevos audífonos y se compararon con los resultados obtenidos con los anteriores audífonos empleados por los participantes en este estudio, sin el extensor de audibilidad activado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);32(1): 7-13, ene.-mar.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97768</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La transposición frecuencial. Incidencia en las habilidades de identificación y el reconocimiento auditivo en jóvenes con pérdidas auditivas profundas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d168^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3656^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3656^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1305^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
