<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14178</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Binge drinking in Galician adolescents: Prevalence, implications and related variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The phenomenon of botellón (binge drinking) among adolescents has contributed to the expansion and consolidation of a worrying pattern of alcohol consumption. However, there are few studies that analyze it, being this the objective of the paper. The results obtained with a sample of 3,419 adolescents aged between 12 and 18 years (M= 14.94, SD= 1.89) put the prevalence of botellón at 38.4%. Its practice involves consumption rates of other substances significantly higher, being up to 16 times higher in the case of binge drinking, as well as higher risk consumption levels. Likewise, it is associated with several highrisk practices such as fights, accidents or unprotected sex. Variables such as expectations, peers consumption, curfew or spending money have been shown to be associated with this practice. All this reinforces the convenience of developing comprehensive preventive work that includes both variables of a personal nature and those more closely related to the establishment of norms and limits by the parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Isorna Folgar, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rial Boubeta, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Couto, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Salgado, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Golpe Ferreiro, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El fenómeno del botellón ha contribuido a la expansión y consolidación de un patrón de consumo de alcohol preocupante en forma de atracón. Pese a ello existen pocos estudios que lo analicen, siendo éste precisamente el objetivo del presente trabajo. Los resultados obtenidos con una muestra de 3.419 adolescentes de entre 12 y 18 años (M=14,94; DT= 1,89) sitúan la prevalencia del botellón en un 38,4%. Su práctica implica tasas de consumo de otras sustancias significativamente mayores, siendo hasta 16 veces superior en el caso del consumo intensivo (binge drinking), así como mayores tasas de consumo de riesgo. Asimismo, se asocia con numerosas prácticas de riesgo, como peleas, accidentes o sexo sin protección. Las expectativas, el consumo de los iguales, la hora de llegada a casa o el dinero disponible se han mostrado asociadas con esta práctica. Todo ello refuerza la conveniencia de desarrollar una labor preventiva integral que contemple tanto variables de naturaleza personal como aquellas más estrechamente relacionadas con el establecimiento de normas y límites por parte de los padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;25(3): 529-545, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La práctica del botellón en adolescentes gallegos: prevalencia, implicaciones y variables asociadas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
