<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94461</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intensity of nursing care: workloads or individual complexity?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to explore the identification of individual care complexity factors in hospitalized patients.Method: a qualitative design of participative research-action was employedwith the direct analysis method for the content of brief stories of participants and nurses of the hospitals of the Catalan Institute of Health, on casesin which they had experienced situations of complexity. Sample sufficiency was established based on the information&#146;s saturation criterion. Participants were offered the chance to participate in a series of workshops/discussion sessions that were carried out over the course of 18 months. One of the researchers collected participants&#146; opinions in written form, whilethe other one moderated the debate and asked reflexive questions on the proposal&#146;s content. Later, participants were asked to form small groups inorder discuss and record in an individual form brief stories of cases in which they had experienced situations of complexity.Results: 287 brief stories were included in the final analysis. The individualfactors of care complexity include five domains: (1) evolutionary, (2) mental and cognitive, (3) psychoemotional, (4) sociocultural and (5) comorbidity and complications. The individual complexity of care is structured insources, factors and specifications.Conclusions: of the five complexity axes identified in Safford&#146;s Vectorial Method of Complexity, four coincide in part with the analysis presented.The architecture of care complexity should include a multiperspective consideration,including the domains of individual, therapeutic-procedural and organizational complexity axes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesalles-Morredes, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soldevila-Casas, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Pérez, Hermelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anton-Riera, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Muñoz, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gías, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà-Miravete, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juvé Udina, María Eulàlia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matad Calvo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabrellas-Padres, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farrero Muñoz, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauri-Herrero, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Privat-Marce, Lluïsa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: explorar la identificación de los factores individuales de complejidad de cuidados en enfermos hospitalizados. Método: se empleó un diseño cualitativo de investigación-acción participativa con el método de análisis directo de contenido de los breves relatos de los participantes, enfermeras y enfermeros de los hospitales del Instituto Catalán de la Salud, sobre casos en los que hubieran experimentado situaciones de complejidad. La suficiencia muestral se estableció a partir del criterio de saturación de la información. Los participantes fueron invitados a formar parte de una ronda de talleres/sesiones de discusión que se hicieron durante18 meses. Uno de los investigadores recogía por escrito las opiniones de los participantes, mientras el otro moderaba el debate y realizaba preguntas reflexivas sobre el contenido de la propuesta. Posteriormente se invitaba a los participantes a organizarse en pequeños grupos para discutir y registrar en un formulario individual, breves narrativas sobre casos en los que hubieran experimentado situaciones de complejidad. Resultados: el número de relatos breves incluidos en el análisis final fue de 287. Los factores individuales de complejidad de cuidados incluye cinco dominios:(1) evolutivo, (2) mental y cognitivo, (3) psicoemocional, (4) sociocultural y (5) comorbilidad y complicaciones. La complejidad individual de cuidados se estructura fuentes, factores y especificaciones.Conclusiones: de los cinco ejes de complejidad identificados en el Modelo Vectorial de Complejidad de Safford, cuatro coinciden parcialmente con el análisis presentado. La arquitectura de la complejidad de cuidados debería incluir una consideración multiperspectiva, incluyendo los ejes de complejidad individual, terapéutica-procedimental y organizativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(8): 6-14, oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intensidad de cuidados enfermeros: ¿cargas de trabajo o complejidad individual?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10115</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
