<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86868</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dopaminergic stimulation in the non-motor symptoms of Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. The non-motor symptoms of Parkinson&#146;s disease have a great impact in terms of quality of life. They are frequently underdiagnosed and clinical experience suggests that not only is dopamine therapy ineffective but that in many cases it is also responsible for the appearance of some of these symptoms. Different studies have drawn attention to the involvement of the dopaminergic pathways in the pathogenesis of some non-motor symptoms. It has been observed that they can undergo fluctuations in relation to dopaminergic stimulation, generally in wearing off states,  while displaying a significant correlation with motor fluctuations and a clinical response with continuous dopaminergic therapy. Conclusions. Although recent reviews offer insufficient evidence for treatment of non-motor symptoms with dopaminergic therapy, involvement of the dopaminergic pathways in the aetiopathogenesis of some of these disorders and the clinical observation that such symptoms undergo fluctuations in relation to pulsatile dopaminergic stimulation may lead us to  reconsider the possible role of dopaminergic therapy in the treatment of these symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castrillo Sanz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vico, Jaime S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pueyo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrocal Izquierdo, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. Los síntomas no motores de la enfermedad de Parkinson tienen un gran impacto en términos de calidad de vida. Frecuentemente se infradiagnostican y la experiencia clínica indica que la terapia dopaminérgica no  sólo es ineficaz sino que en muchos casos es responsable de la aparición de algunos de estos síntomas. Diferentes estudios han llamado la atención sobre la implicación de las vías dopaminérgicas en la patogénesis de algunos síntomas no motores. Se ha observado que pueden experimentar fluctuaciones en relación a la estimulación dopaminérgica, generalmente en estados de wearing off, demostrándose una correlación significativa con las fluctuaciones motoras y una  respuesta clínica con terapia dopaminérgica continua.Conclusión. Aunque revisiones recientes demuestran una evidencia insuficiente para el tratamiento de los síntomas no  motores con la terapia dopaminérgica, la implicación de las vías dopaminérgicas en la etiopatogenia de algunos de estos trastornos y la observación clínica de que dichos síntomas experimentan fluctuaciones en relación a la estimulación dopaminérgica pulsátil, nos puede hacer replantear el posible papel de la terapia dopaminérgica en el tratamiento de estos síntomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(supl.2): s85-s94, feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86868</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación dopaminérgica en los trastornos no motores de la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14955^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7353^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
