<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054379</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nontuberculous mycobacterial lymphadenitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective                 To study the clinical features, epidemiology and outcome of nontuberculous mycobacterial lymphadenitis (NTML).                 Methods                 A retrospective study was performed on 54 patients under 14 years old diagnosed with atypical mycobacterial lymphadenitis between 1987 and 2004. Inclusion criteria were: (i) positive polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test or culture; (ii) positive sensitin skin test 6 mm above Mantoux; (iii) histopathologic features compatible with mycobacterial infection and/or positive direct smear for acid-fast bacilli, Mantoux reaction less than 15 mm, a normal chest radiograph, absence of exposure to an adult with tuberculosis, negative Mantoux test reactions in family members, and exclusion of other causes of granulomatous adenitis.                 Results                 Fifty-four patients were included in the study. The number of NTML cases increased notably from 1996, coinciding with a decrease in cases of tuberculous adenitis. The mean age was 35 months (range: 14 months-6 years). Submandibular nodes were involved in 22 of 63 cases of adenitis (34.9 %) and cervical nodes were involved in 21 (33.3 %). In 8/42 patients (19 %) the tuberculin skin test was larger than 10 mm. Cultures were positive in 52.9 % of the cases (18/34) and PCR in 53.3 % (8/15). The most frequently isolated mycobacteria was Mycobacterium avium (61 %).                 Therapy failed in 8/21 patients receiving antibiotics (38 %), in 10/13 patients with drainage alone (77 %) and in none of the patients who underwent surgery (8/8).                 Conclusions                 Nontuberculous mycobacterial adenitis has become more frequent in our hospital since 1996. Cultures do not always allow isolation of mycobacteria and the Mantoux test frequently yields false positive results, thus hampering diagnosis. The most effective treatment was surgical excision. Nevertheless, when the surgical approach is difficult or there is postoperative recurrence, pharmacological treatment can be useful</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Martín, F. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Echevarría, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Gómez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Miguel, M. J </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero Artigao, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves Ferreira, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo                 Estudiar las características epidemiológicas, clínicas y evolutivas de las linfadenitis por micobacterias no tuberculosas.                 Métodos                 Estudio retrospectivo de 54 pacientes menores de 14 años diagnosticados de linfadenitis por micobacterias atípicas entre 1987 y 2004. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: a) reacción en cadena de la polimerasa (PCR) o cultivo positivo; b) test de sensitinas positivo con valor superior en 6 mm al Mantoux, y c) hallazgos anatomopatológicos compatibles con infección micobacteriana, junto con Mantoux menor de 15 mm, radiografía de tórax normal, ausencia de contacto tuberculoso, Mantoux negativo en familiares directos, y exclusión de otras causas de adenitis granulomatosa.                 Resultados                 Se detectaron 54 casos de adenitis por micobacterias no tuberculosas. Estas infecciones aumentaron desde 1996 coincidiendo con una disminución de adenitis tuberculosas. La edad media de los pacientes fue de 35 meses (rango: 14 meses-6 años). La localización más frecuente fue submaxilar en 22 de 63 adenitis (34,9 %) y laterocervical en 21 adenitis (33,3 %). El Mantoux fue superior a 10 mm en 8/42 (19 %). El cultivo fue positivo en 18/34 de los casos (52,9 %) y la PCR en 8/15 (53,3 %). La micobacteria más aislada fue Mycobacterium avium (61 %).                 Se produjo fracaso terapéutico en 8 de los 21 pacientes tratados inicialmente con antibióticos (38 %) y en 10 de los 13 tratados con drenaje (77 %). En el 100 % (8/8) de los casos en los que se realizó exéresis quirúrgica se consiguió la curación definitiva.                 Conclusiones                 Los casos de adenitis por micobacterias no tuberculosas han aumentado desde 1996 en nuestro hospital. La rentabilidad de los cultivos es baja y el Mantoux presenta falsos positivos con frecuencia, lo cual dificulta el diagnóstico. La exéresis quirúrgica fue el tratamiento más eficaz. Sin embargo, en adenitis que presenten difícil abordaje quirúrgico y en recurrencias postexéresis el tratamiento farmacológico puede ser útil</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(3): 254-259, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenitis por micobacterias no tuberculosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8376^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5069^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9354^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9355^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9354^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9355^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13781^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31068^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8376^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8376^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
