<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82155</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of food advertising aimed at children and adolescents in Chilean open channel television</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Childhood obesity represents a major public health problem in Chile. Studies show that television advertising affects directly the consumption of energy-dense foods in children and adolescents. Objective: To study the nutritional characteristics of foods advertised on five Chilean television channels aimed at children in order to identify the percentage of healthy and unhealthy foods, to know their exposure to lower quality nutritional foods and to incorporate new perspectives on food and nutritional education. Method: 350 hours were recorded during the day (09:00 to 20:00 hours) in 5 Chilean television channels (July and August 2009). Of all the advertising were selected general and child food advertisements. They were analyzed by their nutritional contents: fat, saturated fat, salt and simple sugars added, considering the methodology called "light food" proposed by the National Food Agency of the United Kingdom (FSAB) and contained in a Chilean bill designed to identify healthy foods. Results: 56.6% of food advertising was targeted at children. Only 12.8% were healthy foods, 8.5 and 78.7% were respectively moderately and unhealthy. Conclusions: There is a predominance of advertising aimed at children associated with unhealthy foods, suggesting the need to regulate and to encourage food companies to develop products with enhanced nutritional quality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tur-Marí, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Lancellotti, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Castillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Santiago, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La obesidad infantil representa uno de los principales problemas de salud pública en Chile. Numerosos estudios muestran que la publicidad televisiva influye de forma directa en el consumo de alimentos de alta densidad energética en niños y adolescentes. Objetivo: Estudiar las características nutricionales de alimentos publicitados en los 5 canales chilenos de televisión abierta dirigidos a niños, e identificar el porcentaje de alimentos saludables y no saludables y conocer su exposición a alimentos de menor calidad nutricional para incorporar nuevas perspectivas en la educación alimentaria y nutricional. Método: Se grabaron 350 horas diurnas (09.00 a 20.00 horas) en los 5 canales de televisión abierta chilenos (julio y agosto de 2009). Del total de la publicidad emitida se seleccionaron anuncios de alimentos en general e infantiles. En la destinada a niños se analizó su contenido nutricional: grasas, grasas saturadas, sal y azúcares simples añadidos, considerando la metodología denominada "semáforo de alimentos" propuesta por la Agencia Nacional de Alimentos del Reino Unido (FSAB) y contenida en un Proyecto de Ley chileno destinado a identificar alimentos saludables. Resultados: Un 56,6% de la publicidad de alimentos estaba dirigida a niños; sólo un 12,8% correspondía a alimentos saludables. Un 8,5 y un 78,7% correspondían a alimentos medianamente saludables y no saludables, respectivamente. Conclusiones: Se observa un predominio de publicidad dirigida a niños asociada a alimentos y bebidas no saludables, sugiriendo la necesidad de regular su publicidad e incentivar a las empresas al desarrollo de alimentos con una mejor calidad nutricional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(2): 90-97, abr.-jun.2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la publicidad de alimentos orientada a niños y adolescentes en canales chilenos de televisión abierta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16571^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d332^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
