<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111819</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paratesticular phabdomyosarcoma: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report a case of paratesticular rhadomyosarcoma and to perform a bibliographic review. METHODS: We report the case of a 16-year-old male referred to our Department because of a left paratesticular hard tumor with progressive growth. Ultrasound examination showed a paratesticular heterogeneous mass with Internal flow on Doppler. RESULTS: The patient underwent left inguinal orchiectomy, with pathological diagnosis of rhabdomyosarcoma. He refused adjuvant chemotherapy. After being disease-free for 13 months, he presented with left colic pain. Ultrasound and CT examinations showed a left paraaortic retroperitoneal mass causing grade III ureterohydronephrosis, and lung metastases. Despite rescue chemotherapy treatment, there was no response and the abdominal mass progressed. A surgical approach was not possible since patient showed a rapid clinical worsening leading to his death a few weeks later. CONCLUSIONS: Paratesticular sarcomas are very uncommon tumors with poor prognosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorente Domenech, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Navarro, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verges Prosper, Aleixandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez Ebri, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planelles Gómez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osca García, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Salom, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar un caso de radomiosarcoma paratesticular y revisión de la literatura. MÉTODOS: Describimos el caso de un varón de 16 años remitido a nuestro servicio por masa paratesticular izquierda de crecimiento progresivo, con imagen ecográfica de tumoración paratesticular heterogénea con flujo Doppler en su interior. RESULTADOS: Se realizó orquiectomía izquierda, con diagnóstico de rabdomiosarcoma. El paciente rechazó el tratamiento quimioterápico adyuvante. Tras 13 meses libre de enfermedad, reingresó por dolor cólico izquierdo detectándose en ecografía y TC una masa retroperitoneal paraaórtica izquierda que condicionaba uréterohidronefrosis grado III, y metástasis pulmonares. A pesar de instaurarse quimioterapia de rescate, no respondió presentando rápida progresión de la masa abdominal con importante deterioro general que no permitió el abordaje quirúrgico, siendo éxitus a las pocas semanas. CONCLUSIÓN: Los sarcomas paratesticulares son tumores infrecuentes y de mal pronóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(3): 305-307, abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radomiosarcoma paratesticular: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9409^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9409^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9409^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9409^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
