<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133489</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in food intake and nutritional habits between Spanish adolescents who engage in ski activity and those who do not</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Increasing obesity among adolescents in the industrialized world may result from poor nutritional habits and inadequate exercise. Aim: To determine differences in food intake, nutritional habits, and body mass index between Spanish adolescents who engage in ski activity and those who do not. Methods: A socio-demographic survey, food frequency questionnaire, 24-hr dietary recall, and physical activity questionnaire were completed by 300 Spanish schoolchildren aged 10 to 18 yrs. Results were compared (Student&#146;st, chi-square and Fisher&#146;s exact test) between adolescents engaged (SP) and not engaged (N-SP) in skiing according to their sex. Results: SP adolescents devoted &gt; 4 h/day to physical activity versus &lt; 1 h for N-SP adolescents. No significant differences were found in nutrient intake or nutritional habits between SP and N-SP adolescents. Protein and fat intakes of both groups were above recommended levels. A higher proportion of N-SP than SP males were overweight. Logistic regression analysis showed that the maintenance of a normal weight was favored by the practice of skiing, the consumption of sugar-free drinks, and supplementation with vitamins/mineral salts and was negatively associated with body weight dissatisfaction, intake of nutritional supplements other than vitamins or minerals, and the consumption of snacks. Conclusions: The diet of this adolescent population  was poorly balanced. Engagement in physical activity appears to be a key factor in maintaining a healthy body mass index (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oleoa Serrano, Fatima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, Mª Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernandez Elizondo, Jessenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariscal Arcas, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benhammou, Samira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El aumento de la obesidad entre los adolescentes en países desarrollados puede ser consecuencia de malos hábitos alimentarios y falta de actividad. Objetivo: Determinar las diferencias en la ingesta dealimentos, hábitos nutricionales e índice de masa corporal entre adolescentes españoles que practican esquí y los que no lo hacen. Métodos: Una muestra de 300 adolescentes españoles de 10 a 18 años completó una encuesta que incluyó variables sociodemográficas, un cuestionario de frecuencia de consumo de alimentos, recordatorio de 24h y un cuestionario de actividad física. Se utilizaron test de comparación paramétricos y no paramétricos para comparar los resultados entre adolescentes que practican (SP) y no practican (N-SP) esquí, en función al sexo. Resultados: Los adolescentes SP dedicaron más de 4h diarias a la realización de actividad física mientras que los adolescentes N-SP dedicaron menos de 1 hora diaria a la actividad física. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en la ingesta de nutrientes o los hábitos nutricionales entre adolescentes SP y N-SP. La ingesta de proteínas y lípidos de ambos grupos estuvo por encima de los niveles recomendados. El sobrepeso fue más frecuente entre adolescentes N-SP. El análisis de regresión logística mostró que el mantenimiento de un peso normal se ve favorecido por la práctica del esquí, el consumo de bebidas sin azúcar y la suplementación con vitaminas/minerales y se asoció negativamente con la insatisfacción con el peso  corporal, el consumo de suplementos nutricionales distintosa vitaminas o minerales y el consumo de aperitivos. Conclusiones: La dieta de esta población adolescente fue desequilibrada. La participación en la actividad física parece ser un factor clave en el mantenimiento de un índice de masa corporal saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 936-943, feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133489</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de alimentos y hábitos nutricionales entre adolescentes españoles que practican y no practican esquí</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13246^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
