<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131719</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reversible neuropsychological deterioration associated to zonisamide in a paediatric patient with tuberous sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To document reversible cognitive deterioration associated to high doses of zonisamide, using the Reliable Change Index to control practice effects derived from repetitive neuropsychological assessments. Case report. A 11 year-old boy with tuberous sclerosis complex and left frontal refractory epilepsy, evaluated within a paediatric epilepsy surgery program. The epileptogenic zone was found to be related with a tuber situated on the left inferior frontal gyrus. The effects of high doses of zonisamide simulate a disturbance of eloquent cortex within the epileptogenic zone and the impact of uncontrolled seizures on cognitive functioning over the language-dominant hemisphere. Drug withdrawal significantly improved total intelligence index, verbal comprehension intellectual index and specific languagesustained cognitive abilities, beyond practice effects. Conclusions. The differentiation between cognitive effects of drugs and functional deficits resulting from eloquent cortex involvement within the epileptogenic zone can be of crucial importance in the ecision-making process for epilepsy surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles Bermejo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melero Llorente, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Beregaña, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fournier Del Castillo, M Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Jiménez, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Peñas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Budke, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Documentar el deterioro cognitivo reversible asociado a altas dosis de zonisamida, utilizando índices de cambio fiable para controlar los efectos de práctica derivados de evaluaciones neuropsicológicas repetidas. Caso clínico. Niño de 11 años con complejo esclerosis tuberosa y epilepsia refractaria del lóbulo frontal izquierdo, evaluado en el contexto de un programa de cirugía de la epilepsia pediátrica. La zona epileptógena se relacionó con un túber epileptógeno localizado en el giro frontal inferior del hemisferio izquierdo. Los efectos de altas dosis de zonisamida mimetizaron una afectación de la corteza elocuente en la zona epileptógena y un impacto de las crisis no controladas en el funcionamiento cognitivo asociado al hemisferio dominante para el lenguaje. La retirada del fármaco mejoró significativamente, más allá de los efectos de práctica, el cociente intelectual total, el índice intelectual de comprensión verbal y habilidades cognitivas específicas sustentadas en el lenguaje. Conclusiones. La diferenciación entre los efectos cognitivos de los fármacos y la existencia de un déficit funcional por afectación de la corteza elocuente en el área epileptógena puede ser crucial para la toma de decisiones en cirugía de la epilepsia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(2): 75-80, 16 ene., 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131719</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro neuropsicológico reversible asociado a zonisamida en un paciente pediátrico con esclerosis tuberosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13837^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13837^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14804^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14804^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
