<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117934</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relocation Stress Syndrome in Nursing Students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leaving home to start a university career may be considered a potential source of stress, described by NANDA as &#147;Relocation Stress Syndrome&#148;(RSS).Objective: to determine the prevalence of RSS in Nursing Degree students, and its relationship with socio-demographic factors, social support and personal development. Method: a descriptive study was conducted with students in the first year of their Nursing degree in the Universidad de Huelva, classified according to their having to move in order to study. A questionnaire was applied, which collects RSS indicators grouped into ten different dimensions, and the indicators for the rest of variables. Minimal and maximum scores were established for each dimension, and the cut-off point was determined in order to assign the RSS diagnostic label. Results: information was obtained from 111 students (69 moves),with a 1.45% prevalence of RSS. The most altered dimensions were sleep pattern (91.9%), difficulties in concentration (91.2%) and eating pattern (73.9%). There were significant differences between the score in the RSS scale and gender (F= 5.92, p&lt; 0.018), the self-perception of health (F= 4.26, p&lt; 0.018) and personality characteristics(F= 1.82; p&lt; 0.043). Significant differences were also observed in some of the general stress indicators between students who had moved and those living at the family home. Conclusions: overall, the prevalence of RSS is very low; but altered indicators can be observed with high frequency, which allow identifying the relocation situation as a source of discomfort for students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Padilla, Francisca María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayetano Matamoros, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Bejarano, Rafaela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abandono del hogar para comenzar los estudios universitarios puede ser considerado una potencial fuente de estrés descrita por la NANDA como el &#147;síndrome de estrés de traslado&#148; (SET).Objetivo: determinar la prevalencia del SET en estudiantes de la titulación de Enfermería y su relación con factores sociodemográficos, apoyo social y desarrollo personal. Método: se efectuó un estudio descriptivo con estudiantes de primer año de la titulación de Enfermería en la Universidad de Huelva, agrupados en función de si se habían tenido que trasladar para realizar sus estudios. Se aplicó un cuestionario que recoge indicadores del SET agrupados en diez dimensiones diferentes y los indicadores del resto de variables. Se estableció una puntuación mínima y máxima para cada dimensión y se fijó el punto de corte para adjudicar la etiqueta diagnóstica SET. Resultados: se obtuvo información de 111 estudiantes (69 trasladados),con una prevalencia de SET de 1,45%. Las dimensiones más alteradas fueron el patrón de sueño (91,9%), las dificultades de concentración(91,2%) y el patrón alimentario (73,9%). Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre la puntuación en la escala de SET y el sexo (F= 5,92, p&lt; 0,018), la autopercepción de salud (F= 4,26, p&lt;0,018) y características de la personalidad (F= 1,82; p&lt; 0,043). También se observaron diferencias significativas en algunos de los indicadores de estrés general entre los estudiantes trasladados y los que residen en el hogar familiar. Conclusiones: globalmente, la prevalencia del SET es muy baja, pero se observan indicadores alterados en una alta frecuencia, que permiten identificar la situación de traslado como una fuente de malestar en el alumnado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;16(10): 63-69, dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117934</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome del estrés de traslado en estudiantes de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16091</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
