<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109517</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraskeletal Ewing's Sarcoma Presenting as a Posterior Mediastinal Mass</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors is an uncommon group of malignant neoplasms that may be located in both skeletal and extraskeletal regions. Extraskeletal Ewing's sarcoma (EES) is quite rare and predominantly involves the soft tissues of the trunk or the extremities. Herein, we report the case of a 19-year-old female patient who complained of left arm pain. Simple chest radiography revealed an opacity occupying almost the entire left hemithorax. Diagnostic imaging techniques demonstrated a solid contrast-enhanced mass in the posterior mediastinum. There was an evident mediastinal shift, and the left lung was collapsed. Even though lymphoma was considered as an initial diagnosis, a biopsy was taken and its histopathological analysis revealed EES. In the literature, there have been only a few case reports of ESS located in the mediastinum. We conclude that, although this is an unusual location, EES should be contemplated in the differential diagnosis of mediastinal masses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesrur Halefoglu, Ahmet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La familia de tumores del sarcoma de Ewing es un grupo poco habitual de neoplasias malignas que pueden localizarse en regiones tanto óseas como extraóseas. El sarcoma de Ewing extraóseo (SEE) es poco frecuente y afecta de modo predominante a los tejidos blandos del tronco o de las extremidades. Describimos a una paciente de 19 años de edad que refirió dolor en el brazo izquierdo. La radiografía de tórax simple reveló una opacidad que ocupaba casi todo el hemitórax izquierdo y, tras realizar modalidades de diagnóstico por imagen, se demostró una lesión de masa realzada para el contraste, sólida, en el mediastino posterior. Era evidente una desviación mediastínica y el pulmón izquierdo estaba colapsado. Aunque, como diagnóstico inicial, se consideró un linfoma, la paciente se sometió a una biopsia y el análisis histopatológico reveló un SEE. Entre los estudios publicados, solo se han descrito unos pocos casos de SEE localizados en el mediastino. Concluimos que, aunque es una localización insólita del SEE, debe tenerse en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial de las masas mediastínicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(2): 82-84, feb. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presentación de un sarcoma extraóseo de Ewing como una masa mediastínica posterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31258^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31258^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8650^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8647^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8647^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8650^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
