<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108111</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">«Are we prophets only at home»? Do national otorhinolaryngologists cite papers by other Spanish ORL colleagues?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Over the last few years, the Acta Otorrinolaringológica Española (Acta ORL) has been working to improve its impact factor. A high citation rate in the Journals indexed at the Institute for Scientific Information (ISI) is needed to achieve this, particularly in the ones with a high impact factor. The objective of this study was to analyse the index of citation by other national research groups of the articles by Spanish otorhinolaryngologists published in the Acta ORL Esp. Material and methods: Retrospective descriptive-bibliometric study to analyse the publications and citations of original articles published in the Acta ORL between January 2004 and December 2008. Results: We observed that Spanish otolaryngologists had a low publication index in the Acta ORL, where only 39.1% of the Spanish biomedical production was published. Moreover, the original articles published in the Acta ORL had a low index (32%) of citation by other national authors or groups, displaying a strong self-citation tendency (18.9%). Conclusion: National otorhinolaryngologists or ORL research groups had a low tendency to cite other national (ORL) authors in their publications. In addition, national authors had low biomedical production compared with their European peers. The biomedical production and the articles published in the Acta ORL had a low citation index by ISI indexed journals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iñiguez-Cuadra, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Sprekelsen, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Langdon, Cristóbal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilaseca, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: En los últimos años la revista Acta Otorrinolaringológica Española (Acta ORL) ha hecho un gran esfuerzo de difusión científica y mejoría de su calidad con la intención primordial de conseguir el factor de impacto otorgado por el Institute for Scientific Information (ISI). Para ello, resulta imprescindible que se incremente el número de veces que sus artículos son citados en otras revistas médicas indexadas en el ISI. El presente estudio analiza la citación de los artículos publicados por los otorrinolaringólogos nacionales en el Acta ORL (Abreviación: Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp), por parte de otros grupos nacionales. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo descriptivo-bibliométrico, que analiza las publicaciones y las citaciones de los artículos publicados en el Acta ORL por los otorrinolaringólogos nacionales entre enero de 2004 y diciembre de 2008. Resultados: Se observa un bajo índice de publicación biomédica por parte de los grupos otorrinolaringológicos nacionales en el Acta ORL, donde solo se publica un 39,1% de la producción biomédica nacional. Se observa un bajo índice de citaciones provenientes de grupos nacionales (32%) y una importante tendencia a las autocitaciones (18,9%). Conclusión: Los autores nacionales citan escasamente a otros autores nacionales en sus propias publicaciones nacionales e internacionales. También observamos un bajo índice de producción biomédica en comparación con los pares europeos. Además, se constata que los artículos publicados en el Acta ORL poseen un bajo índice de citación en revistas indexadas en el ISI(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;63(6): 407-412, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«¿Solo se es profeta en su tierra?» ¿Citan los otorrinolaringólogos nacionales a otros otorrinolaringólogos españoles?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10214^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12078^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
