<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155471</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity: prevalence and relationship with educational level in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Obesity is a chronic disease considered by World Health Organization as the epidemic of the century. Several factors cause their presence and also trigger substantial pathologies. The aim therefore of this study is to determine the prevalence of obesity in Spanish adult population, relating to age and sex, in addition to knowing what kind of relationship established with the education factor. Methods: An ecological study using data from national health surveys of 2003, 2006 and 2011. Our population is composed by adults and the study variable in the questionnaires is the body mass index. Results: The percentage of obesity in Spain continues increasing along this century, from 13.62% in 2003 to 17.03% in 2011. As far as gender is concerned, men tend to be more obese than women, with special emphasis from the 45 years of age. Regarding the prevalence of obesity in the autonomous regions of the country, Andalusia, Extremadura and Castilla La Mancha lead the top positions, while Cantabria, Navarra and Castilla Leon are the last. Finally, depending on the level of study of individuals, those who have primary or lower education present a high rate of obesity, 26.7% in 2011. Discussion: Education has a positive impact on the health and welfare of the individual, as it provides the necessary knowledge to develop behaviors and healthier life styles. Thus, this fact suggests that higher levels of education, lower percentage of obesity. Currently, most of the adult population has primary education, which coincides with an increase in the number of obese Spanish. Conclusion: The relationship between obesity and educational level is inverse and very strong. However, this does not indicate causality but dependency, so it would be useful to further research on this type of association in order to reduce the rate of obesity in our country making population aware of this major health problem through the education promotion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez Díaz, Rita Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La obesidad es una enfermedad crónica considerada según la Organización Mundial de la Salud como la epidemia del siglo XXI. Son diversos los factores que provocan su aparición y también cuantiosas las patologías que desencadena. El objetivo por tanto de este estudio es el de conocer la prevalencia de la obesidad en la población adulta española, relacionándola con la edad y el sexo, además de conocer qué tipo de relación establece con el factor de educación. Métodos: Se realiza un estudio ecológico con datos procedentes de las encuestas nacionales de salud de los años 2003, 2006 y 2011. Nuestra población la conforman individuos de 18 años de edad o superior y la variable de estudio dentro de los cuestionarios es el índice de masa corporal. Resultados: El porcentaje de obesidad en España continúa incrementándose en lo que llevamos de siglo, pasando de un 13,62% en 2003 a un 17,03% en 2011. Según el sexo, los hombres tienden a ser más obesos que las mujeres, con especial hincapié a partir de los 45 años de edad. En cuanto a la prevalencia de obesidad en las Comunidades Autónomas del país, Andalucía, Extremadura y Castilla La Mancha lideran las primeras posiciones, mientras que Cantabria, Navarra y Castilla León son las últimas. Finalmente, según el nivel de estudio de los individuos, aquellos con estudios primarios o inferiores presentan un índice elevado de obesidad, 26,7% en 2011. Discusión: La educación tiene un impacto positivo en la salud y el bienestar del individuo, ya que le proporciona los conocimientos necesarios para desarrollar conductas y estilos de vida más saludables. Este hecho sugiere pues que a mayor nivel de formación, menor porcentaje de obesidad existe. Actualmente, la mayor parte de la población adulta posee estudios primarios, lo que coincide con un aumento del número de españoles obesos. Conclusión: La relación existente entre la obesidad y el nivel educativo es inversa y muy fuerte. No obstante, esto no indica causalidad sino dependencia, por lo que sería provechoso realizar nuevas investigaciones sobre este tipo de asociación para así poder reducir el índice de obesidad en nuestro país concienciando a la población de este gran problema de salud mediante la promoción de la educación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;36(3): 181-188, 2016. ^graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad: prevalencia y relación con el nivel educativo en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
