<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132990</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bone and metabolic complications of urinary diversions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hyperchloremic metabolic acidosis is a complication of urinary diversion using ileum or colon. Its prevalence ranges from 25% and 46% depending on the procedure used and renal function of the patient. It is a consequence of intestinal fluid and electrolyte exchange between intestinal mucosa and urine. The main mechanism is absorption of ammonium and chloride from urine. Long-term chronic metabolic acidosis in these patients may lead to impaired bone metabolism and osteomalacia. Regular monitoring of pH, chlorine, bicarbonate, and calcium-phosphorus metabolism is therefore essential for early diagnosis and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Golmayo Muñoz Delgado, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Megías, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La acidosis metabólica hiperclorémica es una complicación de las derivaciones urinarias que utilizan ileon o colon, y su prevalencia oscila entre el 25% y 46% de los casos, dependiendo de la técnica utilizada y de la función renal del paciente. Es una consecuencia del intercambio hidroelectrolítico entre la mucosa intestinal y la orina, siendo su mecanismo principal la absorción del amonio y cloruro de la orina. A largo plazo la acidosis metabólica crónica puede conllevar una alteración del metabolismo óseo y producir osteomalacia, por lo que la monitorización del pH, cloro, bicarbonato y metabolismo fosfocálcico es fundamental para un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;62(2): 100-105, feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones metabólicas y óseas de las derivaciones urinarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36514^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7830^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29754^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7186^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
