<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117119</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation to the dentine of an experimental mineral trioxide-based seale. Pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study was to evaluate under a SEM, the adaptation to the dentine of an experimental mineral trioxide-based sealer, with and without the use of ETA after preparing the root ducts. Material and methods. 12 single-rooted teeth were instrumented to caliber 45, randomly divided into 2 groups of 6. In group 1 (without EDTA), the ducts received a final wash with 5 mil of distilled water. In group 2 (with EDTA), the ducts were treated with EDTA at 17% for 3 minutes, followed by irrigation with 5 ml of sodium hypochlorite at 5,25% and a final wash with 5 ml of distilled water. A specimen of each group was kept without sealing as positive and negative control of the EDTA activity. For the obturation, the technique of an only cone was used, using an experimental sealer and the samples were kept al a 100% of humidity at 37º for 30 days. They were later longitudinally sectioned using chisel and hammer and the 3 apical mm were examined under a scanning electron microscopy (SEM). Results. In group 1 (without EDTA) the adaptation to the dentinal walls was like a thick continuous homogeneous cord with makes it difficult to define a joint line between the dentine, the smear layer and the endodontic seal. Group 2 (with EDTA) showed an acceptable adaptation of the sealer to the dentine, presenting a well defined joint line between them. Conclusions. The adaptation of the experimental sealer to the dentinal walls was better when no EDTA was used, leaving the smear layer, validating a possible chemical integration. The elimination of the smear layer showed an acceptable adaptation to the dentine, without presenting a chemical interaction with the dentinal walls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcelo Leonhardt, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubén Paduli, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar al MEB, la adaptación a la dentina de un sellador experimental a base del trióxido mineral, con y si la utilización de EDTA al final de la preparación de los conductos radiculares. Material y método: Doce dientes unirradiculares fueron conformados hasta el calibre 45 y divididos al azar en dos grupos de 6. El grupo 1 (sin EDTA), los conductos recibieron un lavaje final con 5 ml de agua estilada. El grupo 2 (con EDTA), los conductos fueron tratados con EDTA al 17% durante 3 minutos, seguidos por una irrigación con 5 ml de hipoclorito de sodio al 5,25% y un lavaje final con 5 ml de agua destilada. Se dejó un espécimen de cada grupo sin obturar como control positivo y negativo de la actividad del EDTA. Para la obturación se utilizó la técnica de cono único, empleando el sellador experimental y los especímenes fueron mantenidas al 100% de humedad a 37ºC por un período de 30 días. Posteriormente fueron seccionados con escoplo y martillo longitudinalmente y se examinaron los 3 mm apicales con un microscopio electrónico de barrido. Resultados. En el grupo 1(sin EDTA) la adaptación a las paredes dentinarias se presentó como un cordón denso, continuo y homogéneo, que hace difícil definir una línea de unión entre la dentina, el barro dentinario y el sellador endodóntico. El grupo 2(con EDTA) mostró una adaptación aceptable del sellador a la dentina, presentando una línea bien definida de unión entre ambos. Conclusiones. La adaptación a las paredes dentinarias del sellador experimental fue superior cuando no se utilizó EDTA dejando el barro dentinario, valorándose una posible integración química. La eliminación del barro dentinario mostró una adaptación aceptable a la dentina, sin presentar una interacción química con las paredes dentinarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);30(2): 55-59, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación a la dentina de un sellador experimental a base de trióxido mineral. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30758^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12762^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12763^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29816</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
