<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97694</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beliefs and motives associated with cannabis use in scholars of Valencia city, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the beliefs and motives significantly associated with the consumption and not consumption of cannabis among scholars in Valencia city, analyzing differences by gender. Material and methods. Transversal design. 1,324 students participated, with a mean age of 14.86 (SD = 3.17), and 47.7% are men. X2 tests and logistic regressions are used. Results. Denying the negative effects on both physical and mental, and to the social environment is associated with testing the substance, and occasional or daily consumption, and believing that consumption is good for achieving a goal is associated with occasional and daily consumption. The boys indicate more that the consumption is good to achieve an emotional state or goal. The belief "if you control, nothing happens" is associated with experimental, occasional and daily consumption, and denial, to never try. The reasons associated with current consumption are to relax, have fun, and forget the problems. The motive most indicated for hadn´t consumed it, is because it harms the physical and mental health. The boys indicate more to no consume because it´s expensive and due personal convictions of moral type; the girls, due they feel good and to be able to amuse without drugs. Conclusions. It is important to reinforce beliefs that negative effects of cannabis occurs on the physical, mental and social environment, even when it is perceived that the consumption is being controled. Reasons for reducing stress are potential for consuming occasionally and daily; it is therefore necessary to educate or provide alternatives for leisure and relaxation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales-Manrique, C. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aleixandre-Benavent, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno-Cañigral, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valderrama-Zurián, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar las creencias y motivos significativamente asociados con el consumo y no consumo de cannabis en escolares de la ciudad de Valencia, analizando diferencias en cuanto al sexo. Material y métodos. Diseño transversal. Participan 1.324 estudiantes con una edad media de 14,86 (DT = 3,17); 47,7% son hombres. Se utilizan las pruebas de X2 y regresiones logísticas. Resultados. Negar que el consumo de cannabis afecta la salud física y mental y el entorno social está asociado con probar o consumir ocasionalmente o a diario cannabis; y creer que es bueno para lograr un objetivo se asocia igualmente con el consumo ocasional o diario. Los chicos señalan más que las chicas que el consumo es bueno para lograr un estado emocional u objetivo. Creer que "si controlas, no pasa nada" se encuentra asociado con el consumo experimental, ocasional y diario; y negarlo, con no probarlo nunca. Los motivos asociados con consumir son el de relajarse, divertirse y olvidar los problemas. El motivo más señalado para no consumir es porque perjudica la salud física y mental. Los chicos señalan más que no han consumido porque es caro y por convicciones personales de tipo moral; las chicas, por sentirse bien y saber divertirse sin drogas. Conclusiones. Es relevante reforzar las creencias sobre los efectos negativos del cannabis a nivel físico, mental y en el entorno social, aun cuando se percibe que se controla el consumo. Los motivos para reducir la tensión son potenciales para el consumo ocasional o diario; es por ello necesario enseñar o facilitar alternativas de ocio y relajación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;13(4): 151-159, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97694</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Creencias y motivos asociados al consumo de cannabis en población escolarizada de la ciudad de Valencia, España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
