<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92077</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurrent ischemic stroke. Study of 605 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: To characterize the clinical factors and prognosis and identify determinants of ischemic stroke recurrence in acute stroke. Patients and methods: Recurrent stroke patterns were studied in 605 consecutive patients admitted with a second or further ischemic stroke to the Department of Neurology of the Sagrat Cor Hospital of Barcelona over a 17 year period. Demographic, risk factors, clinical, neuroimaging and outcome variables were analyzed and compared with patients with first-ever cerebral infarction (n=2.099) to identify predictors of ischemic recurrent stroke. Significant variables were entered into a multivariate logistic regression analysis. Results:Ischemic recurrent strokes accounted for 22.4% of all acute consecutive ischemic strokes. Frequency of ischemic stroke recurrence were significantly different among ischemic stroke subtypes: 26.2% in atherothrombotic, 24.4% in cardioembolic, 21.8% in lacunar stroke, 15.8% in infarcts of unusual etiology and 12% infarctions of uncertain etiology. The overall in-hospital mortality and symptom free at discharge in recurrent vs. non-recurrent stroke patients rate was 16.2 vs. 12% (p=0.005) and 17.8 vs. 27.3% (p=0.0001) respectively. Previous intracerebral hemorrhage (OR=3.07; 95% CI, 1.51-6.25), intermittent claudication (OR=1.39; 95% CI, 1.01-1.90), arterial hypertension (OR=1.32; 95% CI, 1.09-1.59), diabetes mellitus (OR=1.26; 95% CI, 1.02-1.56), age (OR=1.02; 95% CI, 1.01-1.03), female gender (OR=0.63; 95% CI, 0.52-0.77), headache (OR=0.62; 95% CI, 0.44-0.87) and bulbar topography (OR=0.21; 95% CI, 0.05-0.89) were independent clinical variables related to ischemic stroke recurrence. Conclusions: About one in every four patients with ischemic stroke had an ischemic stroke recurrence. In-hospital mortality is 16.2% and clinical profiles were different in ischemic stroke recurrence when compared to first-ever ischemic stroke patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Eroles, Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboix, Adrià</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comes, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balcells, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveres, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massons, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Analizar las características demográficas, pronósticas y el perfil clínico relacionados con los infartos cerebrales recurrentes (ICR).Pacientes y método: Estudio hospitalario descriptivo de 605 pacientes consecutivos ingresados durante un período de 17 años por presentar ICR. Se efectúa una comparación con 2.099 pacientes con un primer infarto cerebral.Resultados: Los ICR representan el 22,4% del total de infartos cerebrales. Se observaron ICR en el 26,2% de los infartos trombóticos, en el 24,4% de los cardioembólicos, en el 21,8% de los lacunares, en el 15,8% de los infartos inhabituales y en el 12% de los infartos esenciales. Los ICR tienen un peor pronóstico que los infartos no recurrentes, presentando una mayor mortalidad hospitalaria (16,2 frente al 12%; p=0,005) y una menor frecuencia de ausencia de limitación al alta hospitalaria (17,8 frente al 27,3%; p=0,0001). El perfil clínico significativamente asociado con los ICR fue: presencia de hemorragia cerebral previa (odds ratio [OR] 3,07; intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC 95%] 1,51-6,25), claudicación intermitente (OR 1,39; IC 95% 1,01-1,90), hipertensión arterial (OR 1,32; IC 95% 1,09-1,59), diabetes mellitus (OR 1,26; IC 95% 1,02-1,56), edad (OR 1,02; IC 95% 1,01-1,03), sexo femenino (OR 0,63; IC 95% 0,52-0,77), cefalea (OR 0,62; IC 95% 0,44-0,87) y la topografía bulbar (OR 0,21; IC 95% 0,05-0,89). Conclusiones: Los ICR constituyen aproximadamente una cuarta parte de los infartos cerebrales, siendo más frecuentes en los infartos trombóticos y en los cardioembólicos. Tienen un peor pronóstico, con una mayor mortalidad hospitalaria y una menor frecuencia de ausencia de limitación al alta. Presentan un perfil clínico diferenciado de los primeros infartos cerebrales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(12): 541-545, nov. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infartos cerebrales recurrentes: estudio de 605 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
