<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100068</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cannabinoid drugs for neurological diseases: what is behind?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. In recent years progress has been made in the development of pharmaceuticals based on the plant Cannabis sativa or on synthetic molecules with a similar action. Some of these pharmaceuticals, such as the mouth spray Sativex ®,have recently been approved for the treatment of spasticity in multiple sclerosis, but they are not the first and others, such as Marinol ® or Cesamet ® for the treatment of vomiting and nausea, and anorexia-cachexia syndrome, had already beenapproved. This incipient clinical use of cannabinoid drugs confirms something that was already known from fairly ancient times up to practically the last century, which is the potential use of this plant for medicinal applications &#150; somethingwhich was brought to a standstill by the abusive use of preparations of the plant for recreational purposes. In any case, this incipient clinical use of cannabinoid drugs is not backed just by the anecdote of the medicinal use of cannabis since ancient times, but instead the boost it has been given by scientific research, which has made it possible to identify thetarget molecules that are activated or inhibited by these substances. These targets are part of a new system of intercellularcommunication that is especially active in the central nervous system, which is called the &#145;endogenous cannabinoid system&#146; and, like many other systems, can be manipulated pharmacologically. The aim of this review is to probe further intothe scientific knowledge about this system generated in the last few years, as a necessary step to justify the development of pharmaceuticals based on its activation or inhibition and which can be useful in different neurological diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ruiz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. En los últimos años se han producido avances en el desarrollo de fármacos basados en la planta Cannabis sativa o en moléculas sintéticas con una acción similar. Alguno de estos fármacos, como el aerosol bucal Sativex ®, ha sidorecientemente aprobado para el tratamiento de la espasticidad en esclerosis múltiple, pero anteriormente lo fueron otros, como Marinol ® o Cesamet ® para el tratamiento del vómito y la náusea, y el síndrome de anorexia-caquexia. Este incipiente uso clínico de fármacos cannabinoides confirma algo que ya se conocía desde tiempos bastante más antiguos yhasta prácticamente el siglo pasado, que es el potencial de esta planta para uso medicinal, algo que se vio frenado por el abuso de preparados de la planta también para uso recreacional. En cualquier caso, este incipiente uso clínico de fármacoscannabinoides no tiene detrás la mera anécdota del uso medicinal del cannabis desde tiempos antiguos, sino el impulso de la investigación científica, que ha permitido identificar las dianas moleculares que son activadas o inhibidas porestas sustancias, dianas que forman parte de un nuevo sistema de comunicación intercelular especialmente activo en elsistema nervioso central, que se ha denominado &#145;sistema cannabinoide endógeno&#146;, y que, como muchos otros sistemas, es susceptible de manipulación farmacológica. Esta revisión pretende bucear en el conocimiento científico generado entorno a este sistema en los últimos años, como paso necesario para justificar el desarrollo de fármacos basados en su activación o inhibición y que puedan ser útiles en diferentes enfermedades neurológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(10): 613-628, mayo 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fármacos cannabinoides para las enfermedades neurológicas: ¿qué hay detrás?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2218^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38270</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
