<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129277</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current evidence on the motivational interview in the approach to health care problems in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The motivational interview has been widely used as a clinical method to promote behavioural changes in patients, helping them to resolve their ambivalence to obtain their own motivations. In the present article, a review is made of the main meta-analyses and systematic and narrative reviews on the efficacy of the motivational interview in the primary health care environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barragán Brun, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prados Castillejo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bóveda Fontán, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campiñez Navarro, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérula de Torres, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch Fontcuberta, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La entrevista motivacional ha sido ampliamente desarrollada como método clínico para promover en los pacientes cambios de conducta, ayudando a resolver su ambivalencia para obtener sus propias motivaciones. En el presente artículo ofrecemos una revisión de los principales metaanálisis y revisiones, tanto sistemáticas como narrativas, sobre la eficacia de la entrevista motivacional, centrándonos en el ámbito de la atención primaria de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;45(9): 486-495, nov. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia actual de la entrevista motivacional en el abordaje de los problemas de salud en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55090^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
