<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86755</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Five years&#146; experience in a paediatric epilepsy unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims. The epilepsy monitoring unit is a space inside a hospital, which objective is to reproduce epileptic seizures in order to better study of an epileptic patient. We have analysed data from all the patients admitted to our  pediatric epilepsy unit in the last 5 years. Patients and methods. 191 patients have been admitted in our unit, and we have obtained seizures in 186 admissions (monitoring efficacy, 85.9%). In this report we summarize characteristics of these children, type of seizures and treatment. Results. The most frequent cause of epilepsy in our series is cortical development malformation. Patients are often late in their admission, with a median time of 3 to 4 years from epileptic onset to admission in the epilepsy unit. After the study,22 patients underwent functional epilepsy surgery, all of them with excellent results, 9 patients underwent vagal nerve stimulator implantation and in 66 patients their previous pharmacological treatment was modified. Conclusions. The efficacy of our monitoring unit is similar to previously published, 85.9%. After the admission, we have changed diagnose in 57% of the patients and pharmacological treatment in 29%. We recommend the study in a monitoring epilepsy unit of every patient with refractory epilepsy, meaning an epilepsy that does not respond to 2-3 different appropriate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Donaire, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fructuoso, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumía, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sala, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cusí Sánchez, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio Navarro, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartí, Francesc X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turón Viñas, Eulália</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La unidad de monitorización continua videoelectroencefalográfica (video-EEG) es una zona dentro del ámbito hospitalario cuyo objetivo es intentar reproducir el mayor número de crisis en un paciente para su estudio. Hemos realizado un análisis de los datos de los pacientes ingresados en los últimos cinco años en nuestra unidad de epilepsia pediátrica. Pacientes y métodos. En total han ingresado 191 pacientes, obteniéndose crisis en 186 (eficacia de la monitorización del 85,9%). En este estudio se resumen las características de estos niños, del tipo de crisis que presentaron y de su tratamiento. Resultados. La causa más frecuente de epilepsia en nuestros niños han sido las malformaciones del desarrollo cortical. Los pacientes tardaron un promedio de 3-4 años desde el inicio de la epilepsia hasta el ingreso en la unidad. Tras el ingreso, 22 pacientes fueron sometidos a cirugía funcional de la epilepsia, con resultados excelentes, a nueve niños se les implantó un estimulador del nervio vago y a 66 se les modificó el tratamiento médico previo, con mejoría significativa de su clínica y su calidad de vida. Conclusiones. La eficacia de la monitorización en nuestra unidad es similar a estudios previos publicados, del 85,9%. Tras el ingreso, hemos modificado el diagnóstico en un 57% y el tratamiento médico en un 29%. Aún tardamos mucho tiempo  en ingresar a un paciente en la unidad de monitorización. Recomendamos el estudio en una unidad de monitorización continua video-EEG a todo paciente con epilepsia farmacorresistente, considerada como aquélla que no responde tras dos o tres tratamientos antiepilépticos adecuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(8): 451-460, oct. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de cinco años en una unidad de epilepsia pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54404^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
