<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036332</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypertransaminasemia greater than 400 U/l in adults attended in a tertiary hospital. Prospective study of etiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To investigate the frequency of distinct causes of elevated transaminase levels in the range of acute viral hepatitides in patients attended in a hospital. Patients and method: Patients attended in a tertiary hospital over a 3-month period who had elevation of transaminase levels (aspartate aminotransferase [AST] or alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) above 400 U/l were identified and their medical records were reviewed to determine etiology. Results: A total of 106 patients were studied, of which 22 had undergone liver transplantation. In these patients, the causes of hypertransaminasemia were ischemic/reperfusion injury in 6 (27%), ischemic hepatitis in 4 (18%), acute hepatitis in 2 (9%), cellular rejection in 3 (14%), chronic hepatitis C in 4 (18%) and cholestasis in 3 (14%). In the 84 patients who did not undergo transplantation, the causes were hepatic ischemia in 24 (28%), chronic viral hepatitis in 19 (22%), toxic hepatitis in 12 (14%), pancreatico-biliary disease in 11 (13%), acute viral or bacterial hepatitis in 10 (12%), liver tumor in 3 (4%), cholestasis of pregnancy in one and unknown in 4 (5%). Ischemic lesions and pancreatico-biliary disease were more frequent in hospitalized patients while acute and chronic hepatitides were more frequent in outpatients. The worst outcomes were found in ischemic lesions and pancreatico-biliary disease. Conclusion: Marked elevation of transaminase levels has multiple causes. Acute viral hepatitides were a relatively infrequent cause. In transplant recipients, the most frequent causes were ischemia/reperfusion injury, while in non-transplanted patients the most frequent causes were ischemic hepatitides and acute episodes of chronic viral hepatitides. The AST/ALT ratio did not contribute to etiologic diagnosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corradi, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruguera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrera, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar cuál es la frecuencia de las causas de elevación de las transaminasas en el rango de las hepatitis virales aguda en pacientes atendidos en un hospital. Pacientes y método: Se identificó a los pacientes atendidos en un hospital terciario durante un período de 3 meses que presentaron una elevación de las transaminasas (aspartato-aminotransferasa [AST] o alanina-aminotransferasa [ALT]) por encima de 400 U/l, y se revisaron las historias clínicas de estos pacientes para reconocer la etiología. Resultados: Se estudió a 106 pacientes, de los que 22 ha-bían sido expuestos a un trasplante hepático. En éstos las causas de la hipertransaminasemia fueron lesión de isquemia/reperfusión en 6 (27%), hepatitis isquémica en 4 (18%), hepatitis aguda en 2 (9%), rechazo celular en 3 (14%), hepatitis C crónica en 4 (18%) y colestasis en 3 (14%). En los 84 pacientes no trasplantados la etiología fue isquemia hepática en 24 (28%), hepatitis viral crónica en 19 (22%), hepatitis tóxica en 12 (14%), enfermedad pancreaticobiliar en 11 (13%), hepatitis aguda, viral o bacteriana en 10 (12%), tumor hepático en 3 (4%), colestasis gravídica en uno y de causa desconocida en 4 (5%). Las lesiones isquémicas y las enfermedades pancreaticobiliares predominaron en los pacientes hospitalizados, mientras que las hepatitis agudas y crónicas predominaron en los pacientes ambulatorios. Las primeras fueron las que comportaron peor pronóstico. Conclusión: Múltiples y variadas causas justifican una elevación acentuada de las transaminasas. Las hepatitis virales agudas son una causa relativamente infrecuente. En los pacientes trasplantados las causas más frecuentes son las lesiones de isquemia/reperfusión, mientras que en los no trasplantados fueron las hepatitis isquémicas y las exacerbaciones de las hepatitis virales crónicas. El cociente AST/ALT no contribuyó al diagnóstico etiológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;28(1): 15-19, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertransaminasemia superior a 400 U/l en adultos atendidos en un hospital terciario. Estudio prospectivo de su etiol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d650</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6676^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d650^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
