<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84441</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Keys to managing cases of severe influenza A (H1N1)v in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An outbreak of new influenza A (H1N1)v was declared in April 2009, and on Juny 11 the World Health Organization declared a level 6 pandemic. The diagnostic criteria are the same as those for seasonal influenza: the sudden onset of a high fever, cough, sore throat, and muscle pain. Symptoms are usually mild and remit within 3 days, but a small percentage of patients have fever and progressive respiratory difficulty beyond that point. Paradoxically, in contrast with seasonal flu, patients over the age of 65 years who have chronic diseases make up less than 10% of the cases of the new influenza. A minority have primary viral pneumonia and respiratory distress. The patient profile is a 35-year-old male who, after 3 days with fever, develops progressive hypoxemia requiring intubation within 24 hours of admission. Adolescents and young adults make up the largest population group affected and illness is particularly severe during pregnancy, during the postpartum period., and in obese patients. In children, this influenza often presents with croup and bronchiolitis, although the respiratory syncytial virus is the main cause of those clinical pictures. Respiratory frequency should be monitored and a rate of more than 25 breaths/min considered a warning sign of severity. Continuous monitoring with a pulse oximeter is also advised and a fall in oxyhemoglobin saturation below 95% is another marker of severity. Steps should be taken to isolate patients to prevent transmission of the virus to health care staff or other patients. If complications or risk factors are present, oseltamivir should be started promptly, even if the patient has been ill for longer than 48 hours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boqué, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rello, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En abril de 2009 se declaró un brote de gripe por un nuevo virus A(H1N1)v y el 11 de junio la OMS declaraba en nivel 6 de pandemia. Los criterios diagnósticos son identicosa gripe estacional: la aparición brusca de fiebre alta, tos, dolor de garganta y mialgias. El cuadro suele ser banal y remitir en 3 días. Un bajo porcentaje de pacientes presentan fiebre y dificultad respiratoria progresiva que va más allá de los 3 días. La paradoja con la gripe estacional es que los mayores de 65 años con enfermedades crónicas representan menos del 10%. Una minoría de los casos presentan una neumonía viral primaria y distrés respiratorio. El perfil del paciente grave es de un adulto joven que después de tres días de fiebre presenta hipoxemia progresiva que requiere intubación en 24 horas. La población más afectada es la de adolescentes y adultos jóvenes, con especial gravedad en algunas mujeres embarazadas, en el postparto y en obesos. En niños, el crup, y la bronquiolitis son formas de presentación frecuente. Hay que medir la frecuencia respiratoria(alerta si es mayor de 25x&#146;) y hacer la pulsioximetría (alerta si es menor del 95%)para identificar casos graves. Las medidas de aislamiento en el manejo de estos pacientes son esenciales para evitar la propagación entre personal sanitario y a otros pacientes. En grupos de riesgo y casos con complicaciones no hay que demorar el empleo de oseltamivir, aunque lleven más de 48 h de evolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(5): 370-375, oct. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Puntos clave para la orientación y manejo trapéuticode los casos graves de gripe A(H1N1)v en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
