<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139350</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of trigeminal neuralgia: an update and future prospects of percutaneous techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Trigeminal neuralgia is one of the most severe facial pain syndromes. The annual incidence varies between 4-13% and has a significant effect on patients&#146; quality of life. When the pain cannot be controlled by pharmacological treatment, several different surgical options can be considered. The choice of technique will be based on observational studies and its application depends on the experience of each centre. Aims. To assess the effectiveness and level of evidence of pharmacological and surgical treatment in trigeminal neuralgia, and to analyse the current role of percutaneous techniques in the treatment of this pathology. Development. The initial treatment of trigeminal neuralgia is pharmacological and carbamazepine is the only drug with a sufficiently high level of evidence. The percutaneous surgical techniques are effective and easy to apply, but the tendency for relapses to appear means there is a preference for vascular microdecompression. Yet, there are no reports of comparative studies that determine the superiority of a technique with a good level of evidence. The three most commonly used percutaneous techniques, balloon compression, glycerol rhizotomy and thermocoagulation by radiofrequency, were reviewed. This last technique is the one that has undergone the greatest development in recent years, with the emergence of neurophysiological techniques that make it possible to optimise results. Conclusions. The selection of a surgical technique for use in trigeminal neuralgia does not have much backing from randomised clinical trials. The new procedures in the application of radiofrequency can improve the treatment prospects of this pathology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Vicenç</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bescós, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Màlaga, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escosa-Bagé, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La neuralgia del trigémino es uno de los síndromes de dolor facial más graves. La incidencia anual varía entre el 4-13% y altera de forma significativa la calidad de vida de los afectados. Cuando el dolor no puede controlarse con tratamiento farmacológico, existen diferentes opciones quirúrgicas. La selección de la técnica está basada en estudios observacionales y su aplicación depende de la experiencia de cada centro. Objetivos. Evaluar la efectividad y el nivel de evidencia del tratamiento farmacológico y quirúrgico en la neuralgia del trigémino, y analizar el papel actual de las técnicas percutáneas en el tratamiento de esta patología. Desarrollo. El tratamiento inicial de la neuralgia del trigémino es el farmacológico y la carbamacepina es el único fármaco con suficiente nivel de evidencia. Las técnicas quirúrgicas percutáneas son efectivas y de fácil aplicación, pero la tendencia a la recidiva conduce a la preferencia por la microdescompresión vascular. Sin embargo, no hay estudios comparativos que determinen la superioridad de alguna técnica con buen nivel de evidencia. Se han revisado las tres técnicas percutá- neas más utilizadas, la compresión con balón, la rizotomía con glicerol y la termocoagulación por radiofrecuencia. Esta última es la que ha presentado mayor desarrollo en los últimos años, con la aparición de técnicas neurofisiológicas que pueden optimizar los resultados. Conclusiones. La selección de una técnica quirúrgica en la neuralgia del trigémino no está bien apoyada por ensayos clínicos aleatorizados. Los nuevos procedimientos en la aplicación de la radiofrecuencia pueden mejorar las perspectivas del tratamiento de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(3): 114-124, 1 ago., 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139350</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la neuralgia del trigémino: actualización y perspectivas futuras de las técnicas percutáneas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28309^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14676^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28309^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28309^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6134^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
