<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120927</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natural history of an optic disc macroaneurysm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 75-year old man with reduced vision in his left eye (0.05) presented with hypertensive retinopathy, retinal haemorrhages and cotton wool spots in the papillomacular bundle, as well as macular oedema. Fluorescein angiography showed a saccular hyperfluorescent lesion corresponding to arterial macroaneurysm on the optic disc, with the optical coherence tomography demonstrating macular oedema. At 2 months follow-up, vision had improved to 0.7 with spontaneous closure of the macroaneurysm and resolution of the macular oedema. Discussion: Arterial macroaneurysms on the optic disc are unusual and are difficult to diagnose clinically. There is no safe and effective treatment, and our case, as the few single cases reported, showed that they can spontaneously close and enable visual function to recover (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alforja, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giralt, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adan, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 76 años con agudeza visual (AV) de 0,05, que presentaba retinopatía hipertensiva, con hemorragias y manchas algodonosas en haz papilomacular y edema macular. La angiografía fluoresceínica mostró una dilatación sacular hiperfluorescente arterial correspondiente con un macroaneurisma papilar y la tomografía de coherencia óptica (OCT), edema macular. A los 2 meses, la AV mejoró a 0,7, con cierre espontáneo del macroaneurisma y resolución del edema macular. Discusión: Los macroaneurismas papilares son infrecuentes y presentan dificultades en su diagnóstico. No existe ningún tratamiento seguro y eficaz y, en concordancia con los pocos casos publicados, la involución espontánea permite la recuperación visual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(3): 113-116, mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia natural del macroaneurisma arterial de nervio óptico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10080^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
