<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69989</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Vitamix® is a dietary product composed of a hydro-alcoholic extract of cereals and pulses with honey, calciumgly cerophosphate, vitamins B and D, selenium and fluoride. The basic product, Ceregumil®, patented in 1912, was highly popular as tonic and consumers reported a feeling of health, resistance to illness, and increased predisposition to work and exercise. Material and method: In the present study we analysed the effect of Vitamix® used as dietary supplement, on several physiological parameters in laboratoryrats. We periodically performed hemograms and measured intake and weight, as well as blood levels of glucose, triglycerides, cholesterol, transaminases and malondialdehyde, a lipoperoxidation product. Physical probes were performed and a histochemical study was done in the liver. Results: Rats fed with Vitamix® displayed lower intake and body weight in adult ages, showed and increased antioxidantactivity, higher resistance in the wire hang test and lower fatigue in the Morris pool, specially those specimens considered as bad performers supplemented with Vitamix®. The rest of the measured parameters remained similar to control and no hepatic alterations were found.Conclusions: This study supports as cientific basis to know the effect of these complements over physiologicalparameters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Ávalos, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grondona, Jesús M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cifuentes, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedraza, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Arillo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares-Mira, José Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Llebrez, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, Amelia Victoria de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Palomo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Martín, MArgarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Vitamix® es un producto dietético compuesto por un extractohidroalcohólico de cereales y leguminosas con miel, glicerofosfato de calcio, vitaminas B y D selenio y flúor. El producto base, Ceregumil®, patentado en 1912, ha sido muy popular como reconstituyente, y los usuarios refieren una sensación de salud, resistencia a enfermedades o mayor predisposición para el trabajo o el ejercicio. Material y método: En el presente trabajo se analiza el efecto de Vitamix®, utilizado como suplemento alimenticio en ratas de laboratorio, en diversos parámetros fisiológicos y pruebas físicas. Periódicamente se realizaron hemogramas y se midieron la ingesta y el peso de los animales, así como las concentraciones sanguíneas de glucosa, triglicéridos, colesterol, transaminasas y malondialdehído, un producto de la lipoperoxidación. Se realizaron pruebas de resistencia física y sellevó a cabo un estudio histoquímico del hígado. Resultados: Los animales que tomaron Vitamix® tenían menor peso e ingesta en edades avanzadas, mostraban mayor capacidad antioxidante, mayor resistencia en la prueba del alambre y menor fatiga en la piscina de Morris. En este último caso, la mejoría era notable en los animales considerados de mal desempeño suplementados con Vitamix®. El resto de los parámetros medidos se mantuvieron estadísticamente similares a los de los controles y no se observaron alteraciones hepáticas de ningún tipo. Conclusiones: Este estudio supone una base científica y experimental para conocer el efecto de dichos complementos en los parámetrosfisiológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(8): 346-355, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69989</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d650^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8488^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
