<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94408</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Managing the care of a patient with adrenoleukodystrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This report describes how a community liaison nurse managed a case,whose work is carried out within the framework of case management as a practical course on advanced care on a patient diagnosed of adrenoleukodystrophy and his carer, after referral by the family nurse.An integral evaluation of the patient and the carer were carried out, followingM. Gordon&#146;s functional patterns. The nursing language taxonomies NANDA,NOC, NIC were used to support the decisions of the care plan and the results achieved.The patient presented a collaboration problem manifested as muscularataxia; nursing diagnoses included deterioration of skin integrity and low situational self-esteem. The carer was assessed as having compromised coping skills with the family.The attention to this case required the participation of a multidisciplinary team to complete the provision of care and the support needed by the patient and his carer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgos Sánchez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirado Pedregosa, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se muestra la gestión de un caso realizada por parte de un enfermero comunitario de enlace, cuyo trabajo se en marca dentro de gestión de casos como una práctica avanzada de cuidados, con un paciente diagnosticado deadrenoleucodistrofia y su cuidadora, tras la derivación realizada por su enfermero de familia.Se realizó la valoración integral del paciente y su cuidadora, siguiendo los patrones funcionales de M. Gordon y se utilizaron las taxonomías de lenguaje enfermero NANDA, NOC, NIC para reflejar las decisiones del plan de cuidados y los resultados obtenidos.El paciente presentó como problema de colaboración ataxia muscular, como diagnósticos enfermeros: &#147;deterioro de la integridad cutánea&#148; y &#147;baja autoestima situacional&#148;. La cuidadora tenía un diagnóstico de Enfermería de&#147;afrontamiento familiar comprometido&#148;.La atención del caso requirió la participación de un equipo multidisciplinar para completar la prestación de cuidados y el apoyo al paciente y su cuidadora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(1): 55-60, feb. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión del cuidado de un paciente con adrenoleucodistrofia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d328^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
