<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055868</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the situation of treatments for smoking cessation based on cognitive-behavioral therapy and nicotine patches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To examine whether cue-exposure therapy increases the effectiveness of a multicomponent smoking cessation program that combines cognitive-behavioral techniques with nicotine patches.                Method: Pre-post-follow-up quasi-experimental study of two groups, one group of 22 smokers that received a multicomponent group smoking cessation program that combined cognitive-behavioral techniques with nicotine patches and other group of 26 smokers that received a similar program that also included in vivo exposure to smoking-related cues and contexts and daily self-exposure homework.                Results: The program with cue-exposure therapy showed higher abstinence rates at post-treatment, 1-month follow-up, 6-month follow-up and one-year follow-up than those showed by the program without cue-exposure therapy (65,4%, 65,4%, 66,7% and 66,7%, respectively, versus 59,1%, 59,1%, 40,9% and 36,4%), however, the differences were not statistically significant.                Conclusions: It seems that cue-exposure therapy does not signifi cantly increase the abstinence rates of a multicomponent smoking cessation program that combines cognitivebehavioral techniques with nicotine patches. However, this conclusion should be taken with caution because the present study used a cuasi- experimental design (instead of an experimental one) and is based on a small number of smokers. In this sense, it is likely that this study lacked statistical power since differences so large as the 25-30 percentage points foundat the six-month and one-year follow-ups did not reach statistical signifi cance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vera, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Examinar si la terapia de exposición aumenta la efectividad de un programa multicomponente para dejar de fumar que combina técnicas cognitivo-conductuales con parches de nicotina.                Método: Estudio cuasi-experimental prepost- seguimiento de dos grupos, uno de 22 fumadores que recibieron un programa grupal multicomponente cognitivo-conductual con parches de nicotina y otro de 26 fumadores que recibieron un programa similar que incluía además terapia de exposición en vivo a estímulos y contextos relacionados con la conducta de fumar, incluyendo tareas diarias para casa de autoexposición.                Resultados: Aunque el programa con terapia de exposición mostró tasas de abstinencia en el postratamiento y en los seguimientos al mes, a los seis meses y al año superiores al programa sin terapia de exposición (respectivamente, 65,4%, 65,4%, 66,7% y 66,7%, frente a 59,1%, 59,1%, 40,9% y 36,4%), tales diferencias no fueron estadísticamente significativas.                Conclusiones: No parece que la terapia de exposición aumente de forma significativa las tasas de abstinencia de un programa multicomponente cognitivo-conductual con parches de nicotina. Sin embargo, esta conclusión debe tomarse con precaución dada la naturaleza cuasiexperimental del estudio y el pequeño                número de fumadores en que está basado. En este sentido, el hecho de que no alcanzaran significación estadística diferencias tan grandes como los 25-30 puntos porcentuales encontrados en los seguimientos a los seis meses y al año, probablemente indican la falta de potencia estadística del estudio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);3(2/3): 305-318, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055868</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué aportan las técnicas de exposición a la efectividad de la terapia cognitivo-conductual con parches de nicotina para dejar de fumar?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
