<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94837</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sense of smell, physiologicl ageing and neurodegenerative diseases: II. ageing and neurodegenertive diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The sense of smell, which was once studied because of its biological and evolutionary significance, is today one of the centres of interest in research on normal and pathological ageing. The latest scientific developments point to an inversely proportional relationship between age and olfactory sensitivity. In certain neurodegenerative diseases this sensory decline is one of the first symptoms of the disorder and is correlated with the progression of the disease. Development. In this work we are going to review the scientific knowledge on loss of sense of smell in ageing and in neurodegenerative diseases, with special attention given to Alzheimer&#146;s and Parkinson&#146;s diseases. Conclusions. A survey of studies that have examined the olfactory deficits in ageing and in some neurodegenerative diseases offers conclusive results about the presence of these impairments in the early stages of these disorders and even among healthy elderly persons. Although a number of causes contribute to these sensory losses in physiological ageing, a common neurological foundation has been proposed for Alzheimer's and Parkinson&#146;s diseases. Nevertheless, despite certain initial similarities, the olfactory deficits shown in these disorders seem to be qualitatively different (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fusari, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El sentido del olfato, antaño estudiado por su significado biológico y evolutivo, es hoy uno de los focos de interés en las investigaciones sobre envejecimiento normal y patológico. Los últimos desarrollos científicos apuntan a una relación inversamente proporcional entre edad y sensibilidad olfatoria. En ciertas enfermedades neurodegenerativas, este declive sensorial es uno de los primeros síntomas del trastorno y correlaciona con la progresión de la enfermedad. Desarrollo. Se revisan  los conocimientos científicos sobre las pérdidas olfatorias en el envejecimiento y en las enfermedades neurodegenerativas, incidiendo especialmente en las enfermedades de Alzheimer y de Parkinson. Conclusiones. La revisión de estudios que han investigado los déficit olfatorios en el envejecimiento y en algunas enfermedades neurodegenerativas ofrece resultados concluyentes sobre la presencia de estos deterioros en las fases incipientes de estos trastornos e incluso en población anciana sana. Aunque diversas causas contribuyen a estas pérdidas sensoriales en el envejecimiento fisiológico, se ha propuesto una base neurológica común para las enfermedades de Alzheimer y de Parkinson. Sin embargo, a pesar de ciertas similitudes iniciales, los déficit olfatorios mostrados en estos trastornos parecen ser cualitativamente diferentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(7): 363-369, oct. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94837</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Olfato, envejecimiento fisiológico y enfermedades neurodegenerativas: II. Envejecimiento y enfermedades neurodegenerativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
