<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106222</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the creation of a nutritional support team on the quality, safety and effectiveness of total parenteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Parenteral nutrition (PN) is an essential component in the treatment of many hospitalized patients; however its use is associated to severe complications. The monitoring of these patients has been demonstrated as an effective method for the success of nutrition therapy; therefore, nutritional support teams play an important role to increase the effectiveness and efficiency of the PN. In Spain, there is no data available about the situation of nutritional support teams in hospitals. Objective: Develop a nutritional support team in our hospital and analyze the interventions and outcomes in terms of quality, effectiveness and safety. Methods: Retrospective, cross-sectional study. Patients with PN were selected during two months, corresponding to the period before and after the creation of the nutritional support team (group 1 and 2, respectively). The functions of the nutritional team include: nutritional evaluation, daily monitoring of vital signs and glycemia, detailed analytical control, management of PN complications, between others. Results: 67% of patients in group 1 (n = 24) maintain the PN &lt; 7 days, versus 22% in group 2 (n = 38). In group 1, no patient had a nutritional assessment, neither daily vital signs monitoring (100% in group 2). Detailed analytical control was carried out in the 4% of group 1 and 79% of group 2. In group 2, albumin and prealbumin levels remain stable or increased in the 66% and 88% of patients, respectively. No patient reached triglyceride &gt; 400 mg/dl. 34% of patients showed glycemia &gt; 140 mg/dl (100% of them were solved), and 26% of patients underwent hepatic dysfunction (50% were solved). No refeeding syndrome was reported (thiamine was added to PN in 34% of patients). Discussion: the nutritional support team work has notably increased the quality, safety and effectiveness of PN. This study demonstrates the need to incorporate multidisciplinary nutritional teams in hospitals and the benefit obtained in the patient medical care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Faus Felipe, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Siles, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abilés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nutrición parenteral (NP) es esencial en muchos pacientes hospitalizados, no estando exenta de complicaciones. El seguimiento de estos pacientes constituye un método eficaz para el éxito de la terapia nutricional, por lo que los equipos de soporte nutricional han incrementado la eficacia y eficiencia de la NP. En España, no existen referencias sobre los equipos de soporte nutricional hospitalarios. Objetivos: Crear un equipo nutricional y analizar las intervenciones realizadas y los resultados obtenidos en términos de calidad, efectividad y seguridad en la NP. Métodos: estudio retrospectivo transversal. Se seleccionaron los pacientes con NP durante dos meses, previos y posterior a la creación del equipo (grupo 1 y 2, respectivamente). Las funciones del equipo incluyen: valoración del paciente, seguimiento diario de constantes vitales y glucemia, control analítico completo, manejo de complicaciones metabólicas, electrolíticas y hepáticas, entre otras. Resultados: La duración de la NP fue &lt; 7 días en el 67% del grupo 1 (n = 24) y en el 22% del grupo 2 (n = 38). Ningún paciente fue valorado, ni tuvo seguimiento diario de constantes vitales en el grupo 1 (100% grupo 2). El control analítico completo se realizó en el 4% del grupo 1 y 79% del grupo 2. En el grupo 2, los niveles de albúmina y prealbúmina se mantuvieron estables o aumentaron en el 66% y 88% de los pacientes, respectivamente. Ningún paciente presentó hipertrigliceridemia. El 34% presentó glucemias &gt; 140 mg/dl (100% fueron resueltas) y el 26% presentó complicaciones hepatobiliares (50% fueron resueltas). Ningún paciente presentó síndrome de realimentación (se añadió tiamina al 34%). Discusión: El equipo nutricional ha incrementado notablemente la calidad, seguridad y efectividad de la NP quedando demostrada la necesidad de dichos equipos multidisciplinares a nivel hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(3): 663-671, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la creación de un equipo de soporte nutricional en la calidad, seguridad y efectividad de la nutrición parenteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
