<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89707</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hematologic diseases: from within the heart</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fundamental relationship between blood disorders and the cardiovascular system originates within multiple points of interface, ranging from the heart and its structural constituents to include heart chambers, valves, coronary arteries, coronary veins, and the cerebrovascular and peripheral vasculature. While the cellular components of circulating blood derive their primary origin from multipotent progenitor cells, plasma-based components, which include coagulation proteins, are mostly born of hepatic synthesis and endothelial cells. Here we provide a focused overview of nononcological blood disorders and their potential impact on the arterial circulatory system as common phenotypes, including myocardial infarction, ischemic stroke and peripheral arterial occlusive events. Venous thromboembolism is employed in our discussion as a clinical template. We also provide practical steps and guidance for diagnostic testing and management in routine clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wang, Tracy Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xua, Weixian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becker, Richard C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La relación fundamental entre los trastornos sanguíneos y el sistema cardiovascular tiene su origen en múltiples puntos de contacto, que van del corazón y sus componentes estructurales, como las cámaras cardiacas, las válvulas, las arterias coronarias y las venas coronarias, a los vasos sanguíneos cerebrovasculares y periféricos. Mientras que los componentes celulares de la sangre circulante proceden inicialmente de células progenitoras pluripotenciales, los componentes plasmáticos, que incluyen las proteínas de la coagulación, se originan principalmente en la síntesis hepática y las células endoteliales. Presentamos aquí una revisión centrada en los trastornos hematológicos no oncológicos y sus posibles repercusiones en el sistema circulatorio arterial en forma de fenotipos frecuentes, como el infarto de miocardio, el ictus isquémico y los episodios de oclusión arterial periférica. En nuestro análisis utilizamos la tromboembolia venosa como patrón de referencia clínico. Presentamos también unos pasos prácticos y una guía para las pruebas diagnósticas y el manejo en la práctica clínica habitual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(7): 606-613, jul. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades hematológicas: desde dentro del corazón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6473^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12133^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32063^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5000^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33770^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
