<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96233</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary retention in immunocompetent patient: acute transverse myelitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">MODY-5 diabetes is an infrequent type of monogenic diabetes, caused by mutation in the gene of the nuclear hepatic transcription factor 1-beta (HNF-1¦Â).This mutation can be of a momentary type or it might correspond to big deletions, and, in its turn, it can appear due to spontaneous de novo mutation or it can be transmitted by hereditary with an autosomal dominant character. It is associated with a high risk of microvascular complications that appear early in affected people, as well as with characteristic renal alterations of the cyst type, and anomalies of the genital tract, which are present even before birth. That is why it is justified to carry out detection tests for HNF-1¦Â mutations in non-obese diabetics, above all when there are associated renal or genital alterations, without consideration of family antecedents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Moreno, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Canales, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes MODY-5 es un tipo de diabetes monogenica infrecuente, causada por mutación en el gen del factor de transcripción nuclear hepático 1-beta (HNF-1¦Â). Esta mutación puede ser de tipo puntual o bien corresponder a delecciones grandes, y a su vez, puede aparecer de novo por mutación espontanea o bien ser transmitida de forma hereditaria con caracter autosomicodominante. Está asociada con un alto riesgo de complicaciones microvasculares de aparición temprana en las personas afectas, así como con alteraciones renales características del tipo quistes y anomalías del tracto genital, que estan presentes incluso antes del nacimiento. Por ello, está justificado hacer pruebas de detección para las mutaciones de HNF-1Â en diabíticos no obesos, sobre todo, cuando existen alteraciones renales o genitales asociadas, sin tener en cuenta los antecedentes familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(3): 523-526, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96233</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retención de orina en un paciente inmunocompetente: mielitis transversa aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29144^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14983^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9380^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
