<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055472</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The avian middle ear (Struthio camelus). Data for the physiology of sound transmission in systems with a single ossicle in the Chain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and goals: The columella of birds, often cited in the literature, has yet to be adequately described. We aim to give an account of this transmission element, describing its anchoring systems and detailing the muscle associated to it.         Material and method: We performed microscopic dissection and obtained images of ostrich specimens (Struthio camelus), chosen because it is the bird with the largest head.         Results: We describe the columella: the osseous tripod formed on its external section (extracolumella), the conic shape of its inner section (stapedial), and links to the tympanic membrane and the oval window. We describe its anchoring system: posterior ligament and annular ligament. We conclude by describing the characteristics of the columella muscle, its insertions and the fibrous vein surrounding it.         Conclusions: The avian middle ear is a valid model for understanding the mechanical characteristics of the human ear repaired with total ossicular replacement prosthesis, ie replacement of the ossicular chain by a single element. We highlight an apparent contradiction: the existing muscle is inserted into the columella in an area close to the tympanic membrane rather than adjacent to the oval window</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Valdezate, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Carcedo Sañudo, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablos López, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Carcedo García, Luis María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Carcedo Sañudo, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La columela de las aves, citada frecuentemente en la literatura, no aparece descrita convenientemente. Pretendemos mostrar este elemento de transmisión sonora precisando sus sistemas de anclaje y fijación y detallando el músculo de que dispone.         Material y método: Realizamos una disección microscópica de especímenes de avestruz (Struthio camelus), y obtuvimos y procesamos imágenes de éstos. Escogimos este animal por ser el ave con mayor tamaño cefálico.         Resultados: Se describe la columela: el trípode óseo que se forma en su porción externa (extracolumela), la forma cónica de su porción interna (estapedial), sus relaciones con la membrana timpánica y con la ventana oval. Mostramos sus medios de anclaje: ligamento posterior y ligamento anular. Relatamos las características del músculo de la columela, sus inserciones y la potente vaina fibrosa que lo rodea.         Conclusiones: El oído medio de las aves es un modelo válido para la comprensión de las características mecánicas del oído humano, en el que se sustituye la cadena osicular por un solo elemento de transmisión sonora. Denotamos una aparente paradoja: el músculo existente se inserta en la columela en un lugar próximo a la membrana timpánica, en vez de en la proximidad de la ventana oval</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(6): 246-251, jun.-jul. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Del oído medio de las aves (Struthio camelus). Datos para la fisiología de la transmisión en sistemas de un único osículo en la cadena</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d165^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4493^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4495^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4491^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30994^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
