<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122134</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-4358</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Calcium antagonists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Calcium antagonists are a heterogeneous group of drugs. They all have the same mechanism of action, but present differences in terms of their pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics profiles, their secondary effects and, thus, their therapeutic applications. They can be classified as selective (verapamil, diltiazem, nifedipine, etc) and nonselective (flunarizine and cinnarizine) depending on their manner of blocking the entrance of calcium into the cell through the L-type channels (slow inactivation) located in the cardiac strated muscle and vascular smooth muscle. Their pharmacokinetic features (cytochrome P450 dependent metabolism) and pharmacodynamics characteristics (inotropic and chronotropic effects9 are responsible for their adverse effects (headache, edemas, facial flushing bradycardia, atrioventricular block, hypotension, dyspnea and heart failure) and interactions (enzyme inducers, antiarrhythmic agents). Among their main therapeutic applications are their use in hypertension, diabetes mellitus, angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, cardiac arrhythmias, hyperthorphic cardiomyopathy, subarachnoid hemorrhage, primary pulmonary hypertension, migraine, premature delivery in pregnancy, dementia, anal fissure and Raynaud´s phenomenon). Other more controversial indications would be diffuse esophageal spasm and achalasia, dysmenorrhea, nocturnal urinary incontinence/enuresis and benign prostatic hyperplasia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San José Arango, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casal Llorente, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Farm. aten. prim;5(4): 137-144, oct.-dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antagonistas del calcio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15068^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
