<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044321</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognosis in patients with pneumonia and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the incidence, severity, and mortality rates of pneumonia in a cohort of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients monitored over 3 years.        Patients and methods: A total of 596 patients diagnosed with COPD according to spirometric criteria were included in the study. The variables assessed were mortality and severity according to the Pneumonia Severity Index (PSI) for community-acquired pneumonia (CAP).                 Results: Of the 596 patients included in the study, 75 (12.6%) developed at least 1 episode of pneumonia during the 3 years of the study. The overall incidence of pneumonia was 55.1 per 1000 person-years. There were 88 episodes in 75 patients. COPD severity, evaluated based on percentage of predicted FEV1, was mild in 9 patients, moderate in 24, and severe in 42. Seventy-six (86.3%) episodes were CAP and 12 (13.6%) were acquired in hospital. Fourteen CAP cases corresponded to PSI group V, 28 to group IV, 20 to group III, and 14 to groups I and II. Overall mortality was 12.5% (11/88). The mortality rate was 41.7% (5/12) for nosocomial cases and 7.8% (6/76) for CAP cases (OR, 6.67; 95% confidence interval, 1.65-26.93). Assessing CAP mortality by level of severity, we found that the mortality rate was 35.7% (5/14) for group V and 3.5% (1/28) for group IV. No deaths occurred among patients in the other severity groups.                 Conclusions: The incidence of pneumonia in COPD patients is high. More than half the cases of CAP (55.2%) in our COPD patients were classified in PSI risk groups IV and V</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfageme-Michavila, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-Núñez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino-Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la incidencia, gravedad y mortalidad de las neumonías ocurridas en una cohorte de pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) seguidos durante 3 años.                 Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyó en el estudio a 596 pacientes con diagnóstico espirométrico de EPOC. Los parámetros a evaluar fueron la mortalidad y la gravedad valorada de acuerdo con el Pneumonia Severity Index (PSI) para la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC).                 Resultados: De 596 pacientes incluidos en el estudio, 75 (12,6%) desarrollaron al menos un episodio de neumonía durante el seguimiento. La incidencia global de neumonía fue de 55,1 por 1.000 personas-año. Hubo 88 episodios en 75 pacientes. El grado de la EPOC, valorado según el FEV1 como porcentaje del teórico, era en 9 pacientes leve, en 24 moderado y en 42 grave. De los episodios de neumonía, 76 (86,3%) fueron adquiridos en la comunidad y 12 (13,6%) en el hospital. Al valorar la gravedad de la NAC, 14 episodios correspondían al grupo V, 28 al grupo IV, 20 al grupo III y 14 a los grupos I y II. La mortalidad global fue del 12,5% (11/88). La mortalidad en las neumonías nosocomiales fue del 41,7% (5/12) y la mortalidad en las NAC fue del 7,8% (6/76) (OR: 6,67; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,65-26,93). Al valorar la mortalidad en las NAC según la gravedad, se encontró que la mortalidad en el grupo V fue de un 35,7% (5/14), en el grupo IV del 3,5% (1/28) y nula en el resto de los grupos.                 Conclusiones: Hay una elevada incidencia de neumonía en los pacientes con EPOC. Más de la mitad de las NAC (55,2%) ocurridas en nuestros pacientes con EPOC están dentro de los grupos de riesgo del PSI IV y V</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;41(11): 607-611, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación pronóstica de las neumonías en pacientes con EPOC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
