<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125503</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seroepidemiological study in workers exposed to Hepatitis A virus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The objective is to conduct a seroepidemiological study of workers exposed to Hepatitis A Virus ( HAV ) seroprevalence for antibodies against HAV and effectiveness of the vaccination program of hepatitis A. Methods. Cross-sectional study on the population of workers exposed to HAV in the city of Córdoba, in the period 2001-2012. A total of 144 workers were asked against HAV serology , and health information and education was performed on this biological risk. Vaccination is indicated in seronegative workers. Results. The mean age was 40.2 years. The major labor group was nurses ( 48.6 %). 110 serology (76.4% ) were performed , giving a prevalence of HAV infection of 35.5 %. The first vaccination was performed in 44 ( 62%), and they completely finished the same 31 workers . Program effectiveness was 33.3% . Conclusions. The seroprevalence obtained was lower than similar studies . The threshold below which no efficient is the pre-vaccine serology, is for workers born after 1966 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto Ballesteros, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Fernández, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vquero Abellán, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Saldana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo es realizar un estudio seroepidemiológico de los trabajadores expuestos al Virus de la Hepatitis A (VHA), para conocer la seroprevalencia de anticuerpos frente al VHA y la efectividad del programa de vacunación de Hepatitis A. Métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal sobre la población de trabajadores expuestos al VHA en el Ayuntamiento de Córdoba, en el periodo de 2001-2012. A un total de 144 trabajadores se les solicitó una serología frente al VHA, y se realizó información y educación sanitaria sobre este riesgo biológico. La vacunación se indicó en trabajadores seronegativos.  Resultados. La edad media fue de 40,2 años. El grupo laboral mayoritario fue de auxiliares de enfermería (48,6%). Se practicaron 110 serologías (76,4%), obteniendo una prevalencia de infección por VHAdel 35,5%. La primovacunación se llevó a cabo en 44 (62%), y de ellos,  finalizaron completamente la misma 31 trabajadores. La efectividad del programa fue del 33,3%. Conclusiones. La seroprevalencia obtenida ha sido inferior a los estudios similares. El umbral, por debajo del cual no resulta eficiente la serología prevacunal, es para trabajadores nacidos después de 1966 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;23(2): 300-308, jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio seroepidemiológico en trabajadores expuestos a Virus de la Hepatitis A</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6658^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35592^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35387^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37543^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
