<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165104</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of a self-administered questionnaire to assess dietary habits in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In Argentina Non Communicable Diseases are responsible for 81% of deaths and inadequate nutrition is a main risk factor. In response to this issue, the Health Stations Program (ES), which offers basic health checkups and a Nutritional Counselling Service, has been implemented in the City of Buenos Aires. An eating habits general evaluation instrument has been designed in order to expedite the Nutritional Counselling and to promote deliberation within ES users. Methods: Non experimental cross-section study for questionnaire validation. A self-administered instrument was designed in order to evaluate the construct «healthy eating», which included 18 items. Content validity was evaluated and cognitive pre-test, reliability analysis and internal consistency were carried out. Results: The cognitive evaluation results allowed for design modifications enabling the inclusion of the 18 items. The test presents adequate temporal stability (Intraclass Correlation Coefficient=0.89) and internal consistency within recommended values (Cronbach&#146;s alpha=0.68). Conclusions: The test is a quick and simple tool which can be employed in the promotion of deliberation and sensitization of people&#146;s eating habits, thus motivating attendance to the Nutritional Counselling Service offered at ES (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yomal, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruggiero, María de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antún, María Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirri, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Verónica Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En Argentina las Enfermedades Crónicas No Transmisibles representan el 81% de las muertes y la alimentación inadecuada constituye un importante factor de riesgo. Como respuesta a esta problemática, en la Ciudad de Buenos Aires surge el Programa Estaciones Saludables (ES), en el cual se ofrecen controles básicos de salud y servicio de Consejería Nutricional. Con el objetivo de agilizar la consejería y para promover la reflexión entre los usuarios de ES se decidió crear un instrumento de evaluación de hábitos alimentarios. Métodos: Estudio transversal para validación de cuestionarios. Se elaboró una herramienta autoadministrada para evaluar el constructo «alimentación saludable» que incluyó 18 ítems. Se evaluó la validez de contenido y se realizó pre-test cognitivo, análisis de fiabilidad y de consistencia interna. Resultados: Los resultados de la evaluación cognitiva permitieron hacer modificaciones de diseño y redacción permitiendo conservar los 18 ítems. El test presenta una adecuada estabilidad temporal (Coeficiente de Correlación Intraclase=0,89) y una consistencia interna cercana a lo recomendado (alfa de Cronbach=0,68). Conclusiones: El test es una herramienta simple y rápida que se puede emplear como estrategia de reflexión y sensibilización de las personas sobre sus propios hábitos alimentarios y así motivar la asistencia a la consejería nutricional brindada en ES (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;22(1): 0-0, ene.-mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de un autotest de hábitos alimentarios para la población adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16571^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
