<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120054</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anemia and iron deficiency in children with chronic respiratory diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Children with chronic respiratory disease (CRD) are at increased risk of iron deficiency and anemia, which is under-diagnosed. Aim: To describe the iron (Fe) status in children with CRD and to evaluate the effects of its prophylactic indication. METHOD: Prospective study of children with CRD and adequate Fe intake in the diet. At baseline we measured hemogram, C-reactive protein and Fe profile. Subsequently, those with normal plasma hemoglobin (Hb) were not supplemented with Fe (Group A) and those with iron deficiency anemia or at risk of developing it (group B) were supplemented. We evaluated them 3 months later and, after supplementing all, at 4th month. RESULTS: Of 40 patients, median 30 months old (0.5 to 178), 60% were male, 80% eutrophic. Ventilation or oxygen were required in 45%. Diagnoses: 50% Chronic Lung Damage, 17.5% airway diseases, 10% Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia, 7.5% Cystic Fibrosis and 13.5% other. At baseline 20% were anemic (mostly ferropenic) and 12.5% had an abnormal iron profile. At all, 25 children completed the study: in group A, serum ferritin decreased to 3(th) month (-22.9 ± 30) and incremented to 4(th)month (+12.8 ± 26) &amp;#956;g/L (p = 0.013), without difference in Hb. Group B had a rise in Hb (91 ± 12 to 102 ± 12% of the mean for age, p = 0.04).CONCLUSION: Anemia and ferropenia are frequent in children with CRD. Decrease of their iron reserves can be prevented if they are supplemented. We suggest monitoring properly and treating early or supplement them prophylactically (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Briceño, Lilian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becker, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Mireya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jakubson, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barja, Salesa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los niños con enfermedades respiratorias crónicas (ERC) tienen mayor riesgo de desarrollar anemia ferropriva, sin embargo, la ferropenia está infradiagnosticada. Objetivos: Describir el status de hierro (Fe) en niños con ERC y evaluar la respuesta a su suplementación profiláctica. Método: Estudio prospectivo de niños con ERC y adecuada ingesta de Fe en la dieta: se realizó hemograma, velocidad de eritro-sedimentación, proteína Creactiva y perfil de Fe. Posteriormente, aquellos con hemoglobina plasmática (Hb) normal no se suplementaron con Fe (Grupo A) y los que presentaban anemia ferropriva o factores de riesgo sí lo fueron (grupo B). Se evaluaron al 3º mes, después se suplementaron todos y se re-evaluaron al 4ºmes. Resultados: De 40 pacientes, con mediana de edad 30 meses (0,5 a 178), 60% eran hombres, 80% eutróficos. Requerían ventilación prolongada u oxigenoterapia 45%. Diagnósticos: 50% Bronquiolitis Obliterante post-infecciosa, 17,5% enfermedades de la vía aérea, 10% Displasia Broncopulmonar, 7,5% Fibrosis Quística y 15% otros. Basalmente 12,5% tuvo bajos depósitos de Fe y 20% anemia (la mayoría ferropriva). Completaron el estudio 25 niños: el grupo A disminuyó la ferritina sérica al 3ºmes (- 22,9 ± 30) y aumentó al 4ºmes (+12,8 ± 26) &amp;#956;g/L, (p = 0,013), sin cambio en la Hb. El grupo B tuvo ascenso de la Hb (91 ± 12 a 102 ± 12% del promedio para la edad, p = 0,04). Conclusión: La anemia ferropriva y la ferropenia son frecuentes en niños con ERC, quienes deterioran reversiblemente sus depósitos si no son suplementados. Sugerimos monitorizar con perfil de Fe y tratar precozmente, o suplementarlos en forma profiláctica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(3): 787-793, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anemia y déficit de hierro en niños con enfermedades respiratorias crónicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
