<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042658</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Artisanship of care: caregiving in the home of a relative with advanced dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Family caregiving is so common that it tends to go unnoticed and is viewed as a natural occurrence in family life. This article presents the category of Artisanship of Care that emerged during a qualitative study about family caregiving of patients with advanced dementia. Objective. To identify caregivers' strategies when providing care to their relatives. Method. The study was based on the principles and procedures of grounded theory. Data were collected from interviews with 18 primary caregivers of relatives with advanced dementia and two health professionals and from participant observation in caregivers' support groups and homes. Constant comparison analysis was used after entering data into the QSR Nvivo program. Results. The strategies found that constitute artisanship of care are: 1) creation of ruses for providing care, 2) development of a language, and 3) to build a place for caregiving. These strategies reveal caregivers' artisanship and alert health professionals to caregivers' capabilities. Conclusions. This study offers nursing professionals new perspectives on their work and provides them with information to assess needs and mobilize caregivers' capabilities and community resources</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Benjumea, Carmen de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Cuidar en la casa a un familiar es una actividad tan común que este trabajo suele pasar inadvertido y es entendido como algo natural en la vida familiar. En este artículo se presenta la categoría "artesanía del cuidado", que emergió durante un estudio cualitativo sobre el cuidado familiar de pacientes con demencia avanzada. Objetivo. El objetivo del estudio fue identificar las estrategias que realizan los cuidadores de estos pacientes. Método. El estudio se basó en los principios y procedimientos de la teoría fundamentada. Los datos se recogieron a través de entrevistas a 18 cuidadores y a 2 profesionales y por medio de la observación participante en grupos de apoyo y en los domicilios de los cuidadores. El análisis siguió los procedimientos de la teoría fundamentada y se ayudó del programa informático Nvivo. Resultados. Las estrategias que conforman la artesanía del cuidado son: 1) crear artimañas de cuidado, 2) elaborar un lenguaje y 3) construir un lugar para que habite. Estas estrategias ponen de relieve un trabajo que es artesanal, a la vez que dan cuenta a los profesionales de las capacidades de los cuidadores. Conclusiones. Este estudio ofrece nuevas perspectivas con las que trabajar. Proporciona a los profesionales de enfermería elementos para detectar necesidades, movilizar capacidades de los propios cuidadores y recursos de la comunidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(6): 335-342, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042658</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La artesanía del cuidado: cuidar en la casa a un familiar con demencia avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
