<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78519</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus Conference on Acute Bronchiolitis (I): methodology and recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recommendations of the Consensus Conference "Diagnostic and Therapeutic Management of Acute Bronchiolitis" are presented. Evidence on the frequency of bronchiolitis in the general population and risk groups, risk factors and markers of severe forms, severity scores and the clinical-etiological profile is summarized. The commonly used diagnostic tests are ineffective in the management of the disease; oxygen saturation measurement is considered necessary only in the initial assessment or to monitor changes in patients with respiratory distress. Other tests such as chest radiograph, rapid diagnostic tests for respiratory virus infection and screening tests for bacterial infection should be used only very selectively. There is sufficient evidence on the lack of effectiveness of most interventions tested in bronchiolitis. Apart from oxygen therapy, fluid therapy, aspiration of secretions and ventilation support, few treatment options will be beneficial. Only in moderate-severe bronchiolitis would it be justified to test a treatment with inhaled bronchodilators (salbutamol or epinephrine) with or without hypertonic saline solution. Heliox and non-invasive ventilation techniques could be used in cases with respiratory failure, methylxanthine in patients with apnea and surfactant in intubated critically ill patients. No treatment has proved effective in preventing persistence or recurrence of post-bronchiolitis symptoms. As for prevention of bronchiolitis, only palivizumab slightly reduces the risk of admissions for lower respiratory infections by respiratory syncytial virus, although its high cost justifies its use only in a small group of high-risk patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Sangrador, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan las recomendaciones de la Conferencia de Consenso «Manejo diagnóstico y terapéutico de la bronquiolitis aguda». Se resume la evidencia sobre frecuencia de bronquiolitis en población general y grupos de riesgo, factores y marcadores de riesgo de formas graves, escalas de gravedad y perfil clínico-etiológico. Las pruebas diagnósticas habitualmente empleadas apenas resultan útiles en el manejo de la enfermedad; solo se considera necesaria la medición de la saturación de oxígeno en la valoración inicial o en el control de cambios en los pacientes con compromiso respiratorio. Otras pruebas como la radiografía de tórax, las pruebas de diagnóstico rápido de infección por virus respiratorios y las pruebas de cribado de infección bacteriana solo deben emplearse de forma muy selectiva. Existe evidencia suficiente sobre la falta de eficacia de la mayoría de las intervenciones ensayadas en la bronquiolitis. Al margen de la oxigenoterapia, la fluidoterapia, la aspiración de secreciones y la asistencia respiratoria, pocas opciones terapéuticas resultarán beneficiosas. Solo en los casos moderado-graves estaría justificado el ensayo con broncodilatadores inhalados (salbutamol o adrenalina) con o sin suero salino hipertónico. En casos con fracaso respiratorio podría emplearse heliox y técnicas de ventilación no invasiva, en pacientes con apneas valorar el uso de metilxantinas y en pacientes graves intubados el uso de surfactante. Ningún tratamiento se ha mostrado eficaz para evitar la persistencia o recurrencia de síntomas postbronquiolitis. En cuanto a la prevención de bronquiolitis, solo palivizumab reduce discretamente el riesgo de ingreso por infecciones respiratorias bajas por virus respiratorio sincitial, aunque por su elevado coste solo se justifica su uso en un reducido grupo de pacientes de alto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);72(3): e1-e33, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conferencia de Consenso sobre bronquiolitis aguda (I): metodología y recomendaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
