<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049165</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organ-preserving resection of the pancreaticoduodenal region in the treatment of intraductal papillary mucinous tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The standard surgical procedure for intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the main duct (IPMN-M) or side branch ducts (IPMN-Br) is pancreaticoduodenectomy. IPMN-BR is a more indolent disease with a lower incidence of malignancy.  Objective. To evaluate the usefulness of organ-preserving pancreatic resections (OPPR) including duodenum-preserving pancreatic head resection (DPHR) and pancreatic head resection with segmental duodenectomy (PHRSD) in patients with IPMN-BR. Patients and method. Surgical outcomes were evaluated in eight IPMN-Br patients: DPHR was performed in 4 patients and PHRSD was performed in 4 patients. In addition, 13 IPMN patients with Whipple resections were included in the analysis.  Results. The incidence of postoperative complications was 38% after Whipple resection, 100% after DPHR and 25% after PHRSD. The mean length of hospital stay was 27 days after DPHR, 22 days after Whipple resection and 16 days after PHRSD. Invasive IPMN was found in 38% of the patients in the Whipple group, and noninvasive IPMN was found in 100% of patients who underwent organ-preserving surgery.  Conclusions. Pancreaticoduodenectomy remains the treatment of choice in patients with invasive IPMN. PHRSD appears to be a useful procedure for IPMN-Br located in the head of the pancreas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cruz, Laureano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bollo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaume Comas, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Boado, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olvera, Cristóbal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La técnica quirúrgica estándar para el tratamiento del tumor mucinoso papilar intraductal (TPMI) de las variedades del conducto dilatado (TPMI-CD) o ramificado (TPMI-R) es la duodenopancreatectomía cefálica (DPC). El TPMI-R tiene un crecimiento lento y con menor incidencia de malignidad.  Objetivo. Evaluar la utilidad de la cirugía conservadora, resección parcial de la cabeza pancreática con preservación duodenal (RPCP-PD), y la resección total de la cabeza pancreática con duodenectomía segmentaria (RTCP-DS) en pacientes con TPMI-R.                 Pacientes y método. Los resultados de la cirugía fueron evaluados en 8 pacientes, de los que a 4 se realizó la técnica RTCP-PD y a 4, la técnica RTCP-DS. También se incluyó a 13 pacientes a los que se realizó la DPC según técnica de Whipple.  Resultados. La incidencia de complicaciones postoperatorias fue del 38% después de Whipple, el 100% después de RPCP-PD y el 25% después de RTCP-DS. La estancia hospitalaria media fue 27 días después de RPCP-PD, 22 días después de Whipple y 16 días después de RTCP-DS. Un TPMI invasivo se encontró en el 38% después de Whipple y un TPMI no invasivo, en el 100% de los pacientes sometidos a cirugía conservadora. Conclusiones. La DPC es la técnica de elección para pacientes con TPMI invasivo. La RTCP-DS parece ser un procedimiento seguro y de gran eficacia en el tratamiento de pacientes con TPMI-R localizado en la cabeza del páncreas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);80(5): 295-300, nov. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resección conservadora de la región duodenopancreática en el tratamiento del tumor papilar mucinoso intraductal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
