<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040146</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety in the principal caregivers of elderly individuals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze anxiety in caregivers and its relationship with the level of dependency in elderly individuals. Method. A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional study was performed in the Tordera Health Center, in Catalonia, Spain. Ninety-six caregivers of elderly patients in the Tordera Home Care Program were chosen by random sampling. Goldberg's scale was used to measure anxiety in caregivers, while Barthel's Index was used to measure dependency in elderly patients. A custom-made questionnaire for both caregivers and old people was used to gather sociodemographic data. Results. A total of 93.2% (82) of caregivers were women and 52.3% (46) were daughters of the elderly individual requiring care. The mean age was 61.3 years old. More than half (62.5% [55]) of caregivers were housewives, and the mean caregiving time was 7.4 years. Among old people, 64.8% (57) were women, and their mean age was 84 years old. Half of these had a low dependency level and a low social risk. Fifty-eight percent (51) of caregivers showed anxiety. The patient's dependency level was related to the presence of caregiver anxiety (c2 = 8.163; gl = 2; p = 0.017). Conclusions. A high proportion of caregivers suffer from anxiety but the level found in the present study was lower than that reported in other surveys. The probability of anxiety among caregivers increases when the level of dependency among patients is greater</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rovira Font, Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camós Llovet, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Tantiñá, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la presencia de ansiedad en los cuidadores principales e identificar su relación con el nivel de dependencia de la persona cuidada. Método. Estudio descriptivo, observacional y transversal. Se realizó en el Centro de Salud de Tordera (Barcelona) a 96 cuidadores de personas mayores incluidas en el Programa de Atención Domiciliaria, elegidos por muestreo aleatorio simple. Se utilizó la escala de Goldberg para medir la ansiedad de los cuidadores, el índice de Barthel para el nivel de dependencia de la persona cuidada y una encuesta de elaboración propia para los datos sociodemográficos del cuidador principal y de la persona mayor cuidada. Resultados. El 93,2% (82) de los cuidadores eran mujeres, hijas de la persona cuidada en un 52,3% (46). La edad media era de 61,3 años. El 62,5% (55) de estas cuidadoras eran amas de casa y llevaban una media de 7,4 años cuidando. El 64,8% (57) de las personas cuidadas eran también mujeres, con una media de edad de 84 años. La mitad de ellas tenía un nivel de dependencia leve, con poca presencia de riesgo social. El 58% (51) de los cuidadores presentaban ansiedad. El nivel de dependencia de la persona mayor tenía relación con la aparición de ansiedad en el cuidador (c2 = 8,163; gl = 2; p = 0,017). Conclusiones. Se detecta una elevada proporción de ansiedad entre los cuidadores, aunque menor que la observada en otros estudios. Cuanto más alta es la dependencia de la persona cuidada más probable es que haya ansiedad en el cuidador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(5): 251-256, sept. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad en los cuidadores principales de personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
