<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151243</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Function and frailty: what do we have to measure?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is fairly widespread agreement on the distinction between frailty and disability. However, there is no validated and widely accepted concept of frailty, a condition that is frequently found in old age and which could constitute the main marker of pathological ageing. Given the absence of biological markers with good sensitivity and specificity that could be applied in practice, current approaches attempt to delimit the clinical manifestations that define vulnerable elderly individuals with a high risk of developing serious adverse events, including dependence, hospitalization, institutionalization, and death. Although the origin of frailty is multifactorial, its manifestations probably converge in an alteration in physical functioning. Early identification of the signs and symptoms related to this deterioration would contribute to the early detection of frail elderly elderly individuals who could benefit from primary and secondary prevention, thus reducing or delaying the development of the above-mentioned adverse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baztán Cortés, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe un acuerdo bastante extendido en diferenciar fragilidad de discapacidad. Sin embargo, el concepto de fragilidad, condición que frecuentemente acompaña a la vejez y que podría constituir el principal marcador del envejecimiento patológico, no tiene una definición validada y clínicamente aceptada de manera uniforme en el momento actual. Ante la ausencia de marcadores biológicos sensibles y específicos aplicables en la práctica, las líneas de trabajo actual intentan delimitar las manifestaciones clínicas que marquen el perfil de los ancianos vulnerables con mayor riesgo de desarrollar episodios adversos relevantes, entre los que se incluyen la dependencia, la hospitalización, la institucionalización y la muerte. Aunque la fragilidad tiene un origen multifactorial, probablemente sus manifestaciones confluyen en una alteración del funcionamiento físico. Observar precozmente signos y síntomas relacionados con dicho deterioro contribuiría a la detección precoz de ancianos frágiles susceptibles de prevención primaria y secundaria que redujeran o retrasasen la aparición de los acontecimientos adversos reseñados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);41(supl.1): 36-42, nov. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función y fragilidad: ¿qué tenemos que medir?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10192^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10192^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10192^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10192^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
