<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116869</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients with hemodynamic unstable pelvic fractures in extremis: Pelvic packing or angiography?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The multidisciplinary management of patients with pelvic trauma has improved prognosis, but mortality is still very high. The appropriate treatment strategy remains controversial, especially regarding the control of bleeding in patients whose clinical situation is extreme by using angiography or pelvic packing. We propose using a tool of evidence-based medicine (CAT) the benefit of the completion of pelvic packing in relation to a specific clinical question from a specific situation. What is best for the management of bleeding, extraperitoneal pelvic packing or angiography, in patients with hemodynamically unstable pelvic fracture in extremis? From this study we can conclude that angiography may improve control of bleeding in patients with arterial bleeding and hemodynamically stable but the packing has priority in patients with pelvic fractures and hemodynamic instability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lázaro-Gonzálvez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giráldez-Sánchez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liñán-Padilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Luís, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Toledano, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El manejo multidisciplinar de los pacientes con traumatismo pélvico ha mejorado su pronóstico, sin embargo la mortalidad sigue siendo muy elevada. La estrategia de un tratamiento adecuado es aún controvertida, sobre todo respecto al control de la hemorragia en pacientes cuya situación clínica es extrema mediante el uso de arteriografía o packing pélvico. Planteamos mediante una herramienta de medicina basada en evidencia (CAT) el beneficio de la realización del packing pélvico en relación a una pregunta clínica específica desde una situación concreta, ¿qué es mejor para el manejo del sangrado, packing pélvico extraperitoneal o arteriografía, en pacientes con fractura de pelvis inestables hemodinámicamente in extremis? De este estudio podemos concluir que la arteriografía puede mejorar el control de la hemorragia en los pacientes con sangrado arterial y hemodinámicamente estables, pero el packing tiene prioridad en los pacientes con fracturas de pelvis e inestabilidad hemodinámica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(6): 429-433, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116869</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pacientes con fractura de pelvis inestables hemodinámicamente in extremis ¿packing pélvico o arteriografía?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
