<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27544</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">FAB: a preliminar spanish application of the frontal assessment battery to 11 groups of patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We consider in this paper the applicability of the FAB in Spain, a battery at bedside devised to assess frontal lobe function and able to identify a dysexecutive syndrome, which takes few minutes to administer, and useful for neuropsychological diagnosis in diseases involving frontal lobe dysfunctions. Patients and methods. We study dual application of FAB and Folstein&#146;s MMSE to 195 subjects belonging to 11 subgroups (controls, neurodegenerative disorders and psychiatric conditions), and they were related to: cortical/subcortical normality, cortical/subcortical cognitive impairment, or cortical/ subcortical dementia. Statistics: mean, standard deviation, U-test (p&lt; 0.05) and Pearson&#146;s correlation index. Conclusions. Data suggest FAB reflects in Spanish environment the reality of frontosubcortical deterioration in studied groups. FAB and MMSE showed a variable grade of positive lineal correlation in different diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En este trabajo se realiza, por primera vez, una valoración preliminar sobre el funcionamiento en el ámbito español de la FAB (frontal assessment battery), una batería desarrollada para evaluar las funciones del lóbulo frontal e identificar, en especial, el síndrome disejecutivo. Lleva pocos minutos pasar dicha prueba, útil para el diagnóstico neuropsicológico de las patologías que conllevan trastornos del lóbulo frontal. Pacientes y métodos. Se estudiaron los resultados, tanto del FAB como del MMSE de Folstein, de 195 sujetos, pertenecientes a 11 grupos (controles, enfermedades neurodegenerativas y patologías psiquiátricas), y se clasificaron en las siguientes categorías: normalidad cortical/subcortical, deterioro cognitivo de tipo cortical/subcortical o demencia cortical/subcortical. Estadísticos usados: media, desviación típica, prueba U (p&lt; 0,05), e índice R de correlación de Pearson. Conclusiones. Los resultados del FAB en esta aplicación española representan, suficientemente, la realidad neuropsicológica y clínica de la afectación frontosubcortical de tales grupos. El FAB y el MMSE mostraron una correlación lineal variable y positiva entre sus puntuaciones, en función de las diferentes enfermedades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(7): 605-608, abr. 2003. Introduction. We consider in this paper the applicability of the FAB in Spain, a battery at bedside devised to assess frontal lobe function and able to identify a dysexecutive syndrome, which takes few minutes to administer, and useful for neuropsychological diagnosis in diseases involving frontal lobe dysfunctions. Patients and methods. We study dual application of FAB and Folstein&#146;s MMSE to 195 subjects belonging to 11 subgroups (controls, neurodegenerative disorders and psychiatric conditions), and they were related to: cortical/subcortical normality, cortical/subcortical cognitive impairment, or cortical/ subcortical dementia. Statistics: mean, standard deviation, U-test (p&lt; 0.05) and Pearson&#146;s correlation index. Conclusions. Data suggest FAB reflects in Spanish environment the reality of frontosubcortical deterioration in studied groups. FAB and MMSE showed a variable grade of positive lineal correlation in different diseases (AU)^ien, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">FAB: aplicación preliminar española de la batería neuropsicológica de evaluación de funciones frontales a 11 grupos de pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Catalán Alonso, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Marín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez del Álamo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27544</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33671</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
