<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81514</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence study of self-medication in a touristic population done by a community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Analyzing the practice of self-medication in a tourist town in the South of Gran Canaria. Methods: Prevalence study of self-medication in a community pharmacy in San Bartolome de Tirajana. The total during the months from February to December 2008 was 300 surveys of the persons who went to the pharmacy. Features sociodemographic information was collected (age, employment status), features self-medication (type of medication, treated symptoms, reason not going to the doctor, etc.) and general knowledge about used medications (possible adverse effects, reading the prospectuses, knowledge or potential effects with chronic medication). Results: Saw a 69.3% self-medication. The individuals less than 45 years of age and foreigners are the one of the most engaged in this type of practice. The primary symptoms treated were pain (58.2%), fever (16%) and cough (13%). For the group of analgesic drugs and NSAIDs accounted for 62% of consumption. The request was the most common way to acquire the medicine, not receiving any information on a 72% of cases by the pharmacy. The 54.3% is not necessary to see a doctor and 39.4% recommended medication and a family member or friend in a 26.9% of cases prescriptions made out by the doctor in the past. The 54.8% of respondents obtained information from the medicine through the prospectuses and 51.4% said to know the side effects. The 37% of those suffering from self chronic health problems, basically hypertension and diabetes were the most abundant. 37% of the cases suffering from health problems, 76.6% were unaware of the potential interactions between medications. Conclusions: Self-medication is a common practice among the population, especially among foreigners and persons under 45 years of age. The common symptom of self-medication is pain and NSAIDs are the common medicines most used. The direct application in pharmacies is very common and the listing of medicines, constitutes an important source of information. The most persons considered good or very good practice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bautista Castaño, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Ramos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la práctica de automedicación en una localidad turística situada en el sur de Gran Canaria. Método: Estudio de prevalencia de automedicación en una farmacia comunitaria de San Bartolomé de Tirajana. Durante los meses de febrero a diciembre de 2008 se obtuvieron un total de 300 encuestas entre las personas que acudían a la farmacia. Se recogió información sobre sus características sociodemográfi cas (edad, sexo, situación laboral...), características de la automedicación (tipo de medicamento, síntomas tratados, motivo para no acudir al médico...) y conocimientos generales sobre los medicamentos utilizados (efectos adversos, lectura de los prospectos, posibles o potenciales efectos adversos con la medicación crónica). Resultados: Se registró un 69,3% de casos de automedicación. Los individuos menores de 45 años y los extranjeros son los grupos que más realizan este tipo de práctica. Los principales síntomas tratados fueron el dolor (58,2%), la fi ebre (16%) y la tos (13%). Por grupos de medicamentos, los analgésicos y los antiinfl amatorios no esteroideos (AINE) representaron el 62% del autoconsumo. La solicitud directa fue la forma más habitual de adquirir el medicamento, sin ningún tipo de información recibida por parte de la farmacia en un 72% de los casos. El 54,3% no consideraba necesario acudir al médico, al 39,4% le recomendó el medicamento algún familiar o amigo, y en un 26,9% de los casos los pacientes recordaban prescripciones hechas por el médico en ocasiones anteriores. El 54,8% de los encuestados obtuvo la información del medicamento a través de los prospectos y el 51,4% decía conocer las contraindicaciones. El 37% de las personas que se automedicaban padecía algún problema de salud crónico, entre los cuales la hipertensión y la diabetes eran los más frecuentes. Del 37% de los casos que presentaban algún problema de salud, el 76,6% desconocía la posibilidad de que se produjesen interacciones entre ambas medicaciones. Conclusiones: La automedicación es una práctica muy importante entre la población de estudio, sobre todo entre los extranjeros y las personas menores de 45 años. El dolor es el síntoma más automedicado; los analgésicos y los AINE son los fármacos más utilizados. La solicitud directa en las farmacias es muy habitual y el prospecto de los medicamentos constituye una fuente importante de información(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;12(2): 69-78, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de prevalencia de automedicación en una población turística realizado desde una farmacia comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14587^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
