<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050894</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the PCR-based universal heteroduplex generator assay for identification of rifampicin-resistant and multiresistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis in Lima, Peru</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To validate the polymerase chain reaction-based universal heteroduplex generator (PCR UHG-Rif) assay for identifying rifampin-resistant and multidrug-resistant (MDR, resistant to isoniazid and rifampin) Mycobacterium tuberculosis in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis from communities in Lima (Peru) with a high incidence of resistant tuberculosis. Design. To compare the results of antituberculosis drug susceptibility testing in clinical samples performed by the proportion method with those obtained by the PCR UHG-Rif assay, with the aim of analyzing the diagnostic capability of PCR UHG-Rif. Results. Concordance for the identification of antituberculosis drug susceptibility was 0.95 (k 5 0.899; P &lt; .05), with a sensitivity and specificity of 0.973 and 0.922 (P &lt; .05), respectively. The positive predictive value was 0.939 (95% CI: 0.879-0.970) and the negative predictive value was 0.965 (95% CI: 0.902-0.988). Nevertheless, the probability for MDR prediction was 0.981 (P &lt; .05). PCR UHG-Rif allows the detection of mixed populations; discordant results can be explained by the presence of point mutations, missense mutations and mutations outside the rpoB "hot" region associated with rifampin-resistance. Conclusions. The PCR UHG-Rif assay detects mutations in the rpoB gene with excellent sensitivity and specificity, and suitable predictive values when compared with the standard method for determining susceptibility to antituberculosis drugs. This test can be considered an excellent tool that can contribute to tuberculosis control by correctly identifying patients infected with resistant and MDR bacilli, leading to a reduction in the cases of tuberculosis and resistant tuberculosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Nole, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asencios-Solís, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yale-Cajahuanca, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecca-García, Leonid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quispe-Torres, Neyda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón-Espinoza, Róger I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llanos-Zavalaga, Luis F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Validar el ensayo de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa basada en generador universal de heterodúplex (PCR UHG-Rif) para la identificación de Mycobacterium tuberculosis resistente a rifampicina y multirresistente (MDR, resistente a isoniazida y rifampicina) en pacientes con diagnóstico de tuberculosis pulmonar procedentes de comunidades de elevada incidencia de tuberculosis resistente en Lima, Perú. Diseño. Comparar la determinación de la sensibilidad a fármacos antituberculosos mediante el método de las proporciones y el PCR UHG-Rif a partir de muestras clínicas, y en función de eso, analizar la capacidad diagnóstica del ensayo de PCR UHG-Rif. Resultados. La concordancia en la identificación de la sensibilidad a fármacos antituberculosos fue 0,95 (k 5 0,899; p &lt; 0,05) mostrando una sensibilidad y especificidad del 0,973 y 0,922 p &lt; 0,05), respectivamente. El valor predictivo positivo fue 0,939 (IC 95%: 0,879-0,970) y el valor predictivo negativo fue 0,965 (IC 95%: 0,902-0,988). Sin embargo, la posibilidad de predicción de MDR fue 0,981 (p &lt; 0,05). Este método permite la detección de poblaciones mixtas y las discordancias pueden explicarse por la presencia de mutaciones silenciosas y no incluidas en la región "caliente" del gen rpoB asociada a la resistencia a rifampicina. Conclusión. El ensayo de PCR UHG-Rif detectó mutaciones en el gen rpoB y mostraba sensibilidad y especificidad excelente y adecuados valores predictivos en comparación con el método estándar en la determinación de la sensibilidad a fármacos antituberculosos. Por lo tanto, este ensayo puede ser considerado como una excelente herramienta cuya aplicación contribuirá al control de la tuberculosis, identificando correcta y oportunamente a los pacientes infectados con bacilos resistentes y MDR, permitiendo la reducción de casos de tuberculosis y tuberculosis resistente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(8): 495-499, oct. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa basada en generador universal de heterodúplex para la identificación de Mycobacterium tuberculosis resistente a rifampicina y multirresistente en Lima, Perú</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13568^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33874^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
