<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10050600</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Miret Mases, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García de Olalla Rizo, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vall Mayans, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Clos Guix, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casabona Barbarà, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caylà Buqueras, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To ascertain the degree to which AIDS is officially reported in Catalunya. METHOD The request for T CD4+ white blood cell counts and the prescribing of antiretroviral drugs in seven university hospitals in Catalunya from January 1, 1994 to June 31, 1994 were used as data-comparison sources. A case was considered to not have been reported when the clinical history showed a diagnosis of AIDS (according to the Europe 93 definition) and the case in question did not show up on the AIDS Registry for Catalunya. RESULTS Of the 1,370 cases studied, 50 unreported AIDS cases were found. In all, 98.6% of all cases were found to have been reported, for a 95% confidence interval (95% CI): 98.2-99.0. Most of the unreported cases were males (72%) averaging 37.3 years of age (HCA: 11.8), 52% of whom were injected drug users (IDU's), extrapulmonary tuberculosis being the disease most often diagnosed (16%), 81.4% having been found to have a T CD4+ white blood cell count of 200 WBC/mm3 or below. 92% of these cases were detected based on T CD4+ white blood cell counts. CONCLUSIONS The degree of completeness found is considered to be adequate. It is recommended that the white blood cell count records being used for this type of studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exhaustividad de la notificación de los casos de SIDA en Cataluña: un estudio basado en las solicitudes de determinaciones de linfocitos CD4 y en la prescripción de antirretrovirales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Extension of reporting AIDS cases in Catalonia: study based on requests for CD4 lymphocyte count and prescription of antiretroviral drugs].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
