<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10068758</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Charúa Guindic, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avendaño Espinosa, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Cázares, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE The aim of this study was to determine the efficacy of infrared photocoagulation in the treatment of grades I and II of hemorrhoidal disease. MATERIAL AND METHODS 60 patients with hemorrhoidal disease grades I and II were included, each one with transanal bleeding as the only symptom, without any other ano-rectal pathology. They were 30 male and 30 female patients, with 39.9 years as median age. Each had 1 to 4 photocoagulation sessions, according to the results obtained in each one. TECHNIC Each application was 1.5 seconds duration, once every two weeks, in diamond or rainbow shape; 1 to 4 sessions were required. Follow up was 24 months. RESULTS Good results were obtained in 66.6% since the second application, and in 93.4% at the end of the study; 4 (6.6%) patients were failures and had to be operated on. CONCLUSION Treatment of hemorrhoidal disease grades I and II with infrared photocoagulation is an excellent alternative; it is painless, suitable as an outpatient procedure and its cost is low.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La fotocoagulación por rayos infrarrojos en el tratamiento de la enfermedad hemorroidaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infrared photocoagulation in the treatment of hemorrhoids].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
