<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10074219</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montz, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carreras, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maldonado, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marañes, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Melgarejo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Castejón, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The value of whole body PET-FDG in the evaluation of metastases has been demonstrated in a wide variety of tumors. In this report, we present the case of a patient with antecedent of papillary thyroid carcinoma, who was operated twelve years ago, and submitted to an ablative dose of residual thyroid tissue through 131I, being the levels of thyroglobulin normals. After twelve years of evolution, the patient refers bag pain and respiratory trouble, appearing in the CT image suspicious of metastases in right pulmonary base. The levels of thyroglobulin were shown increased, being the 131I scan negative. A whole body PET-FDG study was performed in order to exclude metastases of his malignant process, showed multiple high FDG uptake focus in brain, cerebellum, neck, chest, lymphatic nodes and bone, suggestive of dedifferentiated disease These findings were confirmed subsequently in the clinic evolution. Therefore, whole-body PET-FDG is a complementary diagnostic technique for study patients with CDT (Thyroid Differentiated Carcinoma) with 131I scan negative and rising thyroglobulin levels.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La PET-FDG en el cáncer de tiroides ante niveles altos de tiroglobulina y rastro 131-I negativo. A Propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[PET-FDG in thyroid cancer with high thyroglobulin levels and negative 131-I scan. A case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
