<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10100438</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>March Fierro, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casals Caus, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Drudis Morell, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aberasturi Fueyo, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mayoral Rojals, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catá Ortells, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gregori Gubern, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miguel Magro, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baró Cabestany, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the usefulness of the cuffed oropharyngeal airway (COPA), a new device for airway control, in 45 patients scheduled for colonoscopy. PATIENTS AND METHODS The patients were anesthetized with propofol and the COPA was applied following the manufacturer's recommendations. Positive pressure ventilation was provided at first, and later the patients were allowed to breathe spontaneously. RESULTS The mean dose of propofol needed to place the COPA correctly was 2.3 +/- 0.3 mg.kg-1. "Free hands" anesthesia was possible in 43 procedures (96%). Placement had to be attempted several times in five patients (11%) before adequate ventilation was achieved. Two patients (4%) had to be switched to a smaller or larger size COPA. In two others (4%), the technique was abandoned because of inadequate ventilation. No hemodynamic changes were observed after placement, although systolic blood pressure tended to increase slightly during colonoscopy, while heart rate decreased. Spontaneous ventilation was possible in all cases and respiratory frequency and end-tidal CO2 increased significantly during colonoscopy. No cases of laryngospasm or sore throat were observed, although 10 patients (22%) coughed upon emergence from anesthesia. CONCLUSIONS The COPA is a new alternative to intubation or other methods for controlling the airway during short procedures, making "free hands" anesthesia possible in most cases. Provided contraindications are respected, the number and seriousness of complications seems to be minimal.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del COPA (cuffed oropharyngeal airway) en anestesia para colonoscopias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Utility of COPA (cuffed oropharyngeal airway) in anesthesia for colonoscopies].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
