<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10217672</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domingo-Salvany, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hartnoll, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez González, K</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION As prevalence of HIV-1 among drug users in Spain is high and it is difficult to contact them because of their hidden behaviors, emergency rooms are one of the health facilities where they can be located. A cross-sectional interview study was planned. The aims of the study were to estimate prevalence of HIV-1 and to describe risk behaviors. METHODS The sample included all patients that in spring 1992 were detected and referred by the doctor as being current opiate users, defined as any use in the 30 days prior the interview. Drug users who did not know their HIV status or were negative for more than six months were asked to provide a urine sample to test HIV serology. A descriptive analysis with simple stratification was carried out. Row and adjusted odds ratio were used to analyse association between different variables and HIV status. Logistic regression was used to examine variables associated with HIV infection and risk behaviors (injecting drug use, sharing needles, and no use of condom). RESULTS Three hundred and eighty three opiate users were interviewed. It was possible to know HIV status of 94% of the subjects. Of them, 61% were positive (219). The best adjusted logistic model to predict associated variables with HIV included being female, primary school level, sickness absence, to attend because of organic pathology, and more years of parenteral use. Seventy five percent of the sample injected drugs during the past 30 days, and among them 30% shared syringes. The variables associated with a higher probability of having injected heroin or cocaine in the last 30 days were to have completed at least primary education, to be unemployed or reliant on illegal activities, not to be in drug treatment, and a larger number of drugs used in the last 30 days. A higher probability of sharing syringes was associated with a lower educational level, not to be in drug treatment, to live alone and a higher number of drugs used during last 30 days. Twenty one percent of the subjects who were sexually active always or nearly always used condom with regular partners and 56% with casual partners. Women were more likely to use condom than men with casual partners. Subjects who shared syringes during last 30 days were nearly three times more likely not to use condom with casual partners. CONCLUSIONS Although a high prevalence of HIV-1 was estimated among opioid users seen in an emergency room, it is not higher than estimates for intravenous drug users recruited from treatment centres, prison or needles exchange programs. A high frequency of risk behavior was also observed indicating a need to develop specific prevention programs for drug users.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana y conductas de riesgo en consumidores de opioides visitados en un servicio de urgencias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of human immunodeficiency virus and risk behaviours among opioid users seen in an emergency room].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
