<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10323097</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-4355</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pinto, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cueto, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Mejía, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To estimate the effectiveness of the Asturias transfusion network in achieving self-sufficiency in plasma, derivatives, blood and blood components in the period from 1990 to 1995. MATERIAL AND METHODS A retrospective study of the indicators of blood donation, production, management and transfusion of fresh frozen plasma and of the clinical usage of plasma derivatives in 1990 and 1995 was carried out. RESULTS In 1990, 26.1% of the plasma and derivatives used were produced in Asturias (108% of the plasma transfused and 15.9% of that equivalent to the plasma derivatives). On the other hand, an estimated 112.4% of the plasma needed was used (FFP, 153%; plasma derivatives, 108.7%). In 1995, 32.2% of all the plasma and derivatives used were produced here (118% of the FFP transfused and 27.2% of the equivalent to the plasma derivatives used). The usage of the plasma necessary for clinical supplies was estimated in 149.0% of the needs (FFP, 138.9%; plasma derivatives, 149.6%). The volume of plasma-equivalent used in both years was higher for albumin than for factor VII. CONCLUSIONS The Consulting Commission of the Blood Centre, with the participation of the Services of Pharmacy, has to establish a programme aimed to monitor all the aspects related with the use of plasma and to evaluate the degree of accomplishment of the obligation of attaining self-sufficiency in plasma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la obtención, uso y necesidad de plasma y derivados plasmáticos en Asturias (1990-1995).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of the acquisition, use and needs of plasma derivatives in Asturias (1990-1995)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Sangre</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
