<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1034469</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Scicli, G G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanahuja, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sambucetti, M E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to improve the nutritive value of wheat protein, with a wheat flour, defated soybean flour and sunflower seed flour were mixed on the basis of their amino acid composition. The highest nutritive value, 86 expressed as CS, was obtained with 60% wheat flour + 28% defatted soybean flour + 12% defatted sunflower seed flour. The mixture was used to prepare: a) sea-biscuits, baked in a traditional bakery oven, and b) crackers, baked in an electric endless oven. Similar products, baked with wheat flour alone, were studied as controls. Chemical composition, total lysine, methionine, cystine, threonine and available lysine content were determine on the raw flours and mixture. Protein, fats and available lysine were determined on the bakery products. The nutritive value of the latter was assessed by their NPUop from which NPUst was calculated. The results showed an increase in the protein content of the enriched bakery products up to 60% over the controls. The nutritive value of the products was lower than the calculated figure for the raw mixture. Products b had the highest NPUst (56.4), surpassing the figures for the control (33.3) and also for product a (53.5). These values agreed with the figures for lysine availability which decreased with heat according to the cooking process. These data and the good acceptability of the crackers suggest that their enrichment with soybean and sunflowers seed concentrates asayed, could help to fulfill protein requirements in children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1976 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enriquecimiento de la harina de trigo con harinas de soja y girasol para la obtencion de productos de panaderia</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Enrichment of wheat flour with sunflower and soya flour for bakery products].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
