<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1035392</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Robles, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negroni, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Hardie, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aerobic bacterial flora of 63 cases of onicolysis 78 of paronychis and 5 of onicomadesis produced by yeast-like fungus were studied. Bacterial isolation was carried out in nutrient agar with a concentration of 10 mug/ml of nystatin. These microorganisms were identified following the Otto Bier and Bailey &amp; Scott's techniques (3, 1). Bacterial contamination was very frequent. One species or more were isolated from 93,6% of onicolysis and 97% of paronychis. The onicolysis presented the following flora: "Staphylococcus aureus" in 22 cases, "Staphylococcus epidermidis" in 21, Gram positive sporulated bacilli in 17, "Enterobacteriaceae" in 13, and "Pseudomona aeruginosa" in 6. The paronychial lesions showed the following flora: "Staphylococcus aureus" in 21 cases, "Staphylococcus epidermidis" in 26, Gram positive sporulated bacilli in 17, "Enterobacteriaceae" in 17 and "Pseudomona aeruginosa" in 3. It is important to emphasize that "Pseudomona aeruginosa" was isolated in a few cases of both types of candidal onixis, contrary to usual reports (2, 4, 9). No significant difference between the aerobic bacterial flora of the onicolysis and paronychia was found, that would give an explanation of the existence of these two clinical forms of candidal nails infection.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1976 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la flora aerobia bacteriana de las onicolisis y perionixis por Candida</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of the aerobic bacterial flora of onycolysis and paronychia caused by Candida].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina cutanea ibero-latino-americana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
