<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10365228</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fuenmayor, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuenmayor, A J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report our experiences with tachycardia-induced cardiomyopathy. Nine patients (3-56 years old) had incessant supraventricular tachycardia and congestive heart failure. The cardiac eco-Doppler evidenced a significant increase of cardiac volumes and mild tricuspid and mitral regurgitation. The ejection fraction (EF) was 0.31 +/- 0.12, the end diastolic volume was 162 +/- 48 cc and the end systolic volume, 116 +/- 54 cc. Four patients had accessory pathways, 3 atrial flutter, 1 A-V nodal reentrant tachycardia, and 1 ectopic atrial tachycardia. Two patients had Chagasic myocarditis. Only in one chagasic patient a decreased number of tachycardia episodes was achieved, this patient died. The autopsy revealed cerebellar and pulmonary emboli. In the other 8 patients the arrhythmia was well controlled. In these, the ventricular volumes decreased, the EF increased to 0.51 +/- 0.14 (p = 0.00006), and the congestive heart failure remitted. We conclude that incessant tachycardia produces a symptomatic dilated cardiomyopathy in patients with and without structural heart disease. The arrhythmia control is followed by an increase in cardiac function and a remission of heart failure symptoms.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taquicardiomiopatía en pacientes con y sin patología cardiaca subyacente. Experiencia en el Centro Cardiovascular de Mérida-Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tachycardiomyopathy in patients with and without subacute cardiac pathology. Experiences at the Cardiovascular Center of Merida, Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
