<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10368583</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garcés, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gorgojo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Artalejo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Moreno, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lasunción, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Oya, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Spain shows an important variation in the geographical distribution of ischaemic heart disease and cerebrovascular disease mortality. In this article, the primary objectives and design of the Four Provinces study are described. In this study we analyzed the contribution of environmental factors (diet, lipid profile and plasma antioxidants), acting in childhood, to explain differences in cardiovascular mortality rates between different provinces in Spain. METHODS An ecological design was projected in which the units to study were four Spanish provinces with a wide variation in cardiovascular mortality in adulthood. The design compares diet, anthropometric variables and biological markers (particularly plasma lipids and antioxidant levels) in 6-7-year-old children, between the two provinces with the highest cardiovascular mortality rates and the two provinces with the lowest. The information for each province is collected in a cross-sectional manner in a representative sample of children from each province. DISCUSSION Evidence from the literature concerning Northern European countries suggest the contribution of environmental factors during early age in the development of cardiovascular disease in adulthood. The "Four Provinces" study will provide, for the first time, information about the influence of factors in early childhood of cardiovascular risk in a Mediterranean country. The study will also offer interesting data about food intake during school age in four provinces and it will allow us to estimate values of population of the variables of interest in those provinces.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio Cuatro Provincias: principales objectivos y diseño. Investigadores del Estudio Cuatro Provincias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The 4 Provinces Study: its principal objectives and design. The Researchers of the 4 Provinces Study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
