<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10391069</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Cairo Cueto, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cisneros González, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas Ramos, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno Rodríguez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Messier L-selectin and LFA-1 in neutrophils from moderate and non atopic asthma patients, before and after stimuli with and without Sa (Staphylococcus aureus). MATERIALS AND METHOD Design Trial; experimental. We studied neutrophils from 12 moderate and non atopic asthma patients and 12 healthy subjects before and after stimuli with and without Sa. MEASURES The neutrophyls adhesion molecules, CD 62-L and CD 11 a was measured by citometric flow assays. RESULTS The median of CD 62-L molecule expression increase with the stimuli in non atopic asthma patients from 2444 (CI 1966, CS 3627, RC 1661) to 6285.5 (CI 5243, CS 7203, RC 1960), and the median of CD 11 a molecule expression decrease with the stimuli in non atopic asthma patients from 9910.5 (CI 9765, CS 9961, RC 196) to 7670 (CI 7125, CS 8291, RC 1166). The median of CD 11 a molecule expression increase with the stimuli in healthy subjects from 593 (CI 361, CS 929, RC 568) to 1113 (CI 910, CS 1240, RC 330) and the median of CD 11 a molecule expression decrease with the stimuli in healthy subjects from 9850 (CI 9741, CS 9898, RC 157) to 9808.5 (CI 9693, CS 9890, RC 197) [CI. Inferior Cuartil, CS. Superior Cuartil, RC.-Cuartil Range].</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del extracto de Staphylococcus aureus en la expresión de L-selectina y LFA-1, en neutrófilos de pacientes con asma bronquial no alérgica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of Staphylococcus aureus extract on the expression of L-selectin and LFA-1, in neutrophils from patients with allergic bronchial asthma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
