<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10413973</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Serrano, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orellana, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez de Ulzurrun, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvet, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteras, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gatell, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the paediatric prescription in a rural health district in terms of the origin and reason for consultation. DESIGN Cross-sectional descriptive study. SETTING Garraf Rural Health District, Barcelona. PARTICIPANTS The 3 basic care paediatrics units in the district. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS 1068 attendances of children of both sexes under 15 were collected. Recorded on each visit to the paediatrics clinic were: age, sex, reason for consultation (RC), and, if medicine was given, the product prescribed and the origin of the prescription. The number of children receiving treatment increased progressively with age. 87% +/- 2.8% of prescriptions originated with the paediatrician. Therapeutic groups of respiratory apparatus and systemic anti-infection drugs accounted for 69% +/- 2.9% of all prescriptions. Only 2.3% +/- 0.5% had fixed-dose associations. The most common RC was upper-tract respiratory infection, mainly treated with a single therapy (76.6% +/- 6.1%). In the case of the second most common RC, acute bronchitis, 94.6% +/- 4.2% of all cases received drugs treatment with single therapy or two simultaneous treatments. Acute tonsillitis was mainly treated with antibiotics (86.4% +/- 6.6%). CONCLUSIONS The frequencies of the pathology groups detected in the Health District correlate with other studies' findings. Analysis of the origin of prescriptions shows the high decision-making capacity of the Health District's paediatricians. The pharmacological profile employed is good, though it could be improved.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 May 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción pediátrica según origen y motivo de consulta en un área básica de salud rural.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The pediatric prescription according to its origin and the motive for the consultation in a basic rural health area].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
