<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10416240</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ladera, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perea, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVE We present a diagnostic decision tree for the correct use of neuropsychological evaluation techniques in head injury. Our aim is to avoid extensive, intensive use of unnecessary tests and measurements or lapses into diagnostic error which often accompany cognitive dysfunction when 'superficial' 'undirected' studies are done. DEVELOPMENT It is essential to select the neuropsychological, neuroconductal and psychosocial evaluation tests which are most suitable in each case and establish a reliable diagnosis of the functional, cognitive, emotional and psychosocial conditions of the patient. The decision tree for neuropsychological evaluation is a guide to assist professionals so that they may adequately examine the functional changes which can occur as a consequence of traumatic brain damage, adapted to each point in its evolution and taking into account factors which may influence neuropsychological evaluation. CONCLUSION The evaluation of consequences of trauma includes evaluation of the gravity of the head injury, and the neuropsychological, neuroconductal and functional evaluation of the patient.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 May 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arbol de decisión diagnóstica para la correcta utilización de las técnicas de evaluación neuropsicológica en el traumatismo craneoencefálico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diagnostic decision tree for the correct use of neuropsychological evaluation in head injury].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
