<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10410588</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8376</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Viniegra Velázquez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Hernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To establish clinical competence of family physicians to diagnose systemic arterial hypertension and to analyze it's associations with some variables related to working conditions and prior training. METHODS The clinical competence was established in a non probabilistic sample of 165 family physicians working in 12 units of the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social (IMSS) in Mexico City. We used questionnaire of 160 items (true/false/don't know) to evaluate clinical competence. Association of the scores were explored for work shift (morning/afternoon), working conditions (very favorable/favorable/little favorable/unfavorable) and having been trained in a familiar medicine residency of the IMSS (yes/no). RESULTS There were a general low competence to diagnose systemic arterial hypertension (median score of 36 of a possible 160). There were associations of competence with more favorable working conditions (p = 0.005 Kruskal-Wallis test) and with having been trained previously (p = 0.0123 U Mann-Whitney test). CONCLUSIONS Our results support the need to continue in this area of research to improve measuring instruments and to identify the modifiers of clinical competence to overcome the deficiencies detected in the present study.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencia clínica del médico familiar en hipertensión arterial sistémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical competence of the family doctor in systemic arterial hypertension].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de investigacion clinica; organo del Hospital de Enfermedades de la Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
