<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10427880</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Diego Rodríguez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Valle Schaan, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Correas Gómez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portillo Martín, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rado Velázquez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez Baños, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roca Edreira, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Castrillo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín García, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez García, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the efficacy of the Anderson-Hynes pyeloplasty in 47 patients with pelviureteric junction syndrome and to compare our results with the reported results for open surgery and other techniques. METHODS The records of 47 patients (21 males, 26 females) with pelviureteric junction syndrome treated at the Marqués de Valdecilla University Hospital from 1979-1997 were reviewed. Twenty-eight patients had right-sided involvement and two were bilateral. Mean age at the time of surgery was 35 years. Pain was the most common presenting feature (nephric colic, 28 pts; chronic lumbar pain, 11 pts). RESULTS The Anderson-Hynes technique was performed in 43 of the 47 patients. IVP showed good results in 74.5%. CONCLUSION In our experience the success rate achieved with the Anderson-Hynes technique is comparable to those reported elsewhere, which ranges from 65%-100%. Although currently there is considerably less experience with endoscopic and laparoscopic techniques, the results achieved to data appear to be similar to those of open surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la cirugía abierta en el síndrome de la unión pieloureteral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The results of open surgery in the ureteropelvic junction syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
