<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10420791</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Taddei-Bringas, G A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Cancio, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Téllez, M B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santillana-Macedo, M A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To explore the degree of usage of therapeutic medical plants among the patients, physicians and health workers in a local Family Medical Care Unit of the Mexican Institute of Social Security (IMSS)). MATERIAL AND METHODS A transversal descriptive study was performed. A questionnaire focusing on two variables was designed and validated. It was applied to 60 family physicians, a randomized sample of 130 health workers and another of 264 patients of the Family Mediccal Care Unit. Response percentage was 78%. RESULTS The study found that 83% of family physicians accept the therapeutic use of herbal medicine; moreover, 75% use it as a therapeutic resource. Among health workers, acceptance and use was 100%, while in patients the level of acceptance was of 92% and of use it was 90%. Differences between groups are significant (p &lt; 0.05). The more frequently used plants are Gordolobo (Gnaphalium sp.), Eucalyptus (Eucalyptus sp., probably E. globulus), spearmint (Mentha sp.), camomile (Matricaria chamomilla) and prickly pear cladodes (the vegetative parts of the prickly pear, Opuntia sp. Probably Opuntia ficus indica). CONCLUSIONS This information agrees with previous reports about Mexico, however, in this case, data were gathered in urban areas where physicians have been trained in the biomedical paradigm of medicine.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceptación y uso de herbolaria en medicina familiar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acceptance and use of medicinal plants in family medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
