<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10420921</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez-Regueira, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espí, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sierra, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zornoza, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez-Caballero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cebeiro, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast physical examination which is enormous help in clinical diagnosis of cancer of the breast is not useful in the diagnosis of early lesions. We analized in this study different complementary examinations we do for the diagnosis of the cancer of the breast. Mammography, though maintaining a 5-7% false negative results is the examination of choice of the breast. Not with standing its simplicity, its contribution with respect to breast and neoplastic biology makes it a useful investigation. The diagnosis obtained through mammography in non palpable tumors permit the use of conservative therapeutic techniques at the same time allowing improvement in curation and survival rates when we deal preferently with Stage I cancer. It is still necessary in our means an information-sensibilization of the female population about breast autoexamination and the need for early specialized medical consultation. Any abnormal breast sign should alert us that more than 2.5 months delay would suppose a difference from a T1 to a T2 tumor.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de mama: valor de distintas exploraciones en el diagnóstico de la lesión primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Breast cancer: value of various examinations in the diagnosis of the primary lesion].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de medicina de la Universidad de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
