<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10431092</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Amaya Vidal, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Herrera, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soria de la Cruz, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porcel Martín, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Macías Rodríguez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rendón Unceta, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to analyze certain epidemiological and ultrasonographic features, and the response to percutaneous treatment, of abdominal tuberculous abscesses in patients with human acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. METHODS we reviewed the clinical records and ultrasonographic findings in 7 patients with abdominal tuberculous abscesses who were treated in our service by ultrasonography-guided percutaneous drainage. RESULTS in 5 patients there was a previous diagnosis of AIDS. The abscesses (two in one patient) were located mainly in the retroperitoneum and appeared mottled at ultrasonography. Seven of the abscesses were drained via catheter, whereas in the remaining case aspiration puncture was used. Mycobacterium tuberculosis was found in the drained material in 6 patients, and 1 case presented superinfection by Enterococcus faecalis. Percutaneous drainage was effective in 6 patients, and in the remaining case it was only palliative. CONCLUSIONS the incidence of abdominal tuberculous abscesses is increasing in patients with AIDS, and in some patients it is the first symptom. Abscesses are located primarily in the retroperitoneum. They can be dealt with satisfactorily by percutaneous drainage guided by ultrasonography.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abdominal tuberculous abscesses in AIDS patients: percutaneous treatment.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
