<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10439538</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Geijo, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escribano, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosa, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To compare the results obtained by Brucella Coombs' test with those obtained by Brucellacapt. MATERIAL AND METHODS 145 serum samples from 112 patients with brucellosis or with brucellar infection suspected on clinical grounds and a history of occupational exposure were analyzed. All serum samples were tested for Rose Bengal, agglutinations whenever Rose Bengal was positive, Brucella Coombs' test and Brucellacapt. RESULTS There was a direct correlation between both methods (p &lt; 0.01). Negative serum samples and most serum samples with titers between 1/40 and 1/2,560 as tested by Brucella Coombs' test showed similar results into a range of one to two dilutions by Brucellacapt. However, serum samples with titres between 1/5,120 and 1/40,960 by Brucella Combs' test yielded also higher titres by Brucellacapt and for this reason we were unable to define a titre. CONCLUSIONS Brucellacapt is a rapid assay to exclude infection and yield results comparable to Brucella Coombs' test in range 1/40 to 1/2,560. Significantly higher and more rapid titres were obtained in acute brucellosis by Brucellacapt as compared with those obtained by Brucella Coombs' test. Titre's evolutions by Brucellacapt is similar to Brucella Coombs' test. Unfortunately it was difficult the titres definition of Brucellacapt at high titres.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo del test Brucellacapt con el test de Coombs para Brucella.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study of the Brucellacapt test versus the Coombs test for Brucella].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
