<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10472596</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez Gómez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto Campos, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calderón Osuna, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez Gutiérrez, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo Gómez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Becerra, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Castillo Otero, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The aim of this study was to prospectively evaluate the clinical and gasometric evolution and the side effects of two treatment schedules in the exacerbations of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD): 500 mg/24 h of azithromycin (AZM) for three days versus 500 mg/12 h of acetyl cefuroxime (ACF) for 10 days. PATIENTS AND METHODS Patients were randomized included into each therapeutic schedule. The patients were seen three times (days 1 and 4, and at 15-21 days) to evaluate clinical symptoms scores. Forced spirometry and arterial gasometry were performed the first and the last time the patients were seen. The number of patients requiring admission during follow up and the secondary effects of each antibiotic were quantified. RESULTS A total de 50 patients were treated with AZM and 51 with ACF. The evolution of the symptoms was similar although with a trend to greater improvement in those treated with AZM. This improvement was significant for the characteristics of expectoration (p &lt; 0.05). Functional and gasometric evolution was similar in the two schedules. Three patients treated with AZM required hospital admission, as did 5 treated with ACF. A greater number of secondary effects were observed in patients treated with ACF (18%) than in those receiving AZM (10%), with gastrointestinal side effects being the most commonly observed. CONCLUSIONS Treatment with short schedule of AZM may have the same activity as longer schedule of ACF, with fewer secondary effects thereby suggesting that AZM may be an effective alternative in the treatment of exacerbations in patients with COPD.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jul 03 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo, aleatorio entre 3 días de tratamiento con azitromicina y 10 días de tratamiento con cefuroxima en las exacerbaciones de pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A randomized comparative study of 3 days of azithromycin treatment and 10 days of cefuroxime treatment in exacerbations in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
