<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10478290</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Valencia Sánchez, J S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Enríquez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomo Villada, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arriaga Nava, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro Robles, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED We report the surgical-medical experience in left side mechanic prosthesis cardiac valve dysfunction. From January 1986 to June 1997 we included 108 consecutive patients (pts), 24 were men and 84 women, mean age 45 years, they underwent 114 surgical procedures, 104 in mitral and 10 in aortic position. RESULTS The dysfunction was due to obstruction in fixed disc in 107 pts and intermitent in 7 pts. The pathological findings were thrombosis in 92 pts, pannus in 9 pts and both in 13 pts. The time interval between valve replacement and dysfunction was from 1 to 247 months, mean 53.8 +/- 56.7. Seventy five percent of patients received inadequate anticoagulant therapy, the mean INR was 2.06 +/- 0.79. In 76% of patients the functional class was III or IV NYHA. The diagnosis was made by clinical and echocardiographic findings in 96% of patients. The surgical procedures included valve replacement in 103, and toilette in 11 pts. The time of extracorporeal circulation in patients who died us survival patients were (159.9 +/- 108.95 vs 87.32 +/- 27.53 min) and aortic cross-clamp (64.8 +/- 20.69 vs 48.28 +/- 23.71 min) respectively (p &lt; 0.001). The overall mortality was 12 pts (10.5%), all in functional class III or IV NYHA (p &lt; 0.05), five patients died during surgical procedure. In conclusion the diagnosis must be established clinically as well as by echocardiography. The risk factors associated with mortality were pulmonary edema, shock, delayed surgery, surgical time prolonged and functional class III or IV NYHA.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo médico-quirúrgico en la disfunción de prótesis valvular mecánica cardiaca izquierda por obstrucción. Once años de experiencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Medical-surgical management of left heart valve prosthesis dysfunction due to obstruction. Eleven year's experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
