<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10532143</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez García, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Trejo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solís Daun, J O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alor Guzmán, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED The adrenal myelolipoma are rare tumors that are generally asymptomatic, unilateral and nonfunctional and in the majority of the cases they are found incidentally. OBJECTIVE Is to present a clinical case of adrenal myelolipoma, associated with gallstones. CASE REPORT A 30 year old obese female with chronic abdominal pain, which underwent a GI series, having found a hiatal hernia and esophagitis. An ultrasound, of the gallbladder and bile ducts showed gallstones and incidentally a tumor of 9.3 x 8 x 7 cm was found between the right kidney and the liver. In the CT of the abdomen of observed, a little vascularized tumor of the adipose composition of 9.2 x 6 x 5 cm over the top of the right kidney. A cholecystectomy was performed and the resection of the tumor, histopathological study of the tumor reported normal adrenal tissues, mature adiposis and hematopoietic with all of its series. CONCLUSIONS The association of adrenal myelolipoma and gallstones is not common and it could be an incidental association. With the new tools available we can diagnose the adrenal myelolipoma with a greater degree of certainty.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mielolipoma adrenal vinculado a colecistitis litiásica, hernia hiatal y esofagitis.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Adrenal myelolipoma associated with lithiasic cholecystitis, hiatal hernia and esophagitis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
