<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10562673</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tur-Tur, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso-Vargas, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Valle, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo-Muñoz, A J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gasser, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bornay-Llinares, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arévalo, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quindós, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruesga, M T</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Using Sensititre (AccuMed, USA) we studied the in vitro antifungal activity of amphotericin B, fluconazole, itraconazole, ketoconazole and 5-fluorocytosine against 250 clinical yeast isolates taken from different hospitals, including Candida (151 C. albicans, 15 C. krusei, 14 C. parapsilosis, 11 C. tropicalis, 10 C. glabrata, 4 C. guilliermondii, 3 C. rugosa, 2 C. viswanathii, 2 C. famata and 2 C. kefyr), Cryptococcus (32 C. neoformans and 1 C. laurentii), Trichosporon (2 isolates) and Rhodotorula rubra (1 isolate). All the strains were susceptible to amphotericin B and showed an MIC &lt;1 mg/l. The susceptibility of C. albicans (MIC(90) &lt;256 mg/l), C. krusei (MIC(90) &lt;64 mg/l), C. glabrata (MIC(90) &lt;64 mg/l) and C. neoformans (MIC(90) 32 mg/l) to fluconazole was lower (14% isolates being resistant and 16.8% susceptible depending on the dose). The largest number of strains resistant to itraconazole was observed in C. albicans and C. glabrata (17.2% resistant and 24% susceptible and susceptible depending on the dose, respectively). Ketoconazole and 5-fluorocytosine were not effective in vitro against 12.8% and 2%, respectively, of all the isolates studied. Nine C. krusei and seven C. neoformans (12.9%) showed dose-dependent susceptibility to 5-fluorocytosine.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación mediante el sistema Sensititre de la sensibilidad in vitro a los antifúngicos de levaduras de interés médico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Determination of the in vitro antifungal susceptibility of clinically important yeasts using the Sensititre system].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
