<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10605256</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Iturralde-Torres, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kershenovich, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colín-Lizalde, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Hermosillo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several reports have demonstrated that radiofrequency catheter ablation provides effective control of a variety of tachyarrhythmias. This report details the results of radiofrequency catheter ablation in 1,000 consecutive patients with a wide variety of tachyarrhythmias treated in the Instituto Nacional de Cardiología "Ignacio Chavez". Tachyarrhythmias were associated with the presence of an accessory pathway in 700 patients (70%). Dual accessory pathways were present in 21 patients, giving a total of 722 accessory pathways. The mechanism of the arrhythmia was AV nodal reentrant tachycardia in 204 patients (20.4%). Ablation of the reentrant circuit of atrial flutter within the right atrium was attempted in 56 (5.6%) patients and a primary atrial tachycardia in five patients (0.5%). AV node ablation and permanent pacemaker implantation were performed in 17 patients (1.7%). Finally we performed radiofrequency catheter ablation in 22 (2.2%) patients with ventricular tachycardia. Radiofrequency catheter ablation was successful in 630 of 700 (90%) patients with accessory pathways with a complication rate of 9/700 (1.2%) and a recurrence rate of 73 (12.4%). AV nodal reentry was successfully abolished in 190 of 204 (93%) patients by selective ablation of the slow pathway in 168/180 (93.3%) patients and the fast pathway in 22/24 (92%) patients. The complication rate of this group was 7/204 (3.4%) with a recurrence rate of 30 patients (14.2%). The reentrant circuit of atrial flutter was ablated successfully in 41 of 56 (73%). Four/five (80%) of patients with primary atrial tachycardia were successfully ablated. Complete AV block was achieved in 17/17 patients with atrial fibrillation or flutter treated by AV nodal ablation without complications or recurrence. The procedure was successful in 17/22 (77%) of patients with ventricular tachycardia. The results of this series of patients demonstrate the safety and efficacy of radiofrequency ablation for the treatment of a wide variety of tachyarrhythmias with high rate of success 899/1,000 (89.9%) and with an 1 1.8% of recurrence, low risk of complications (1.5%) and no mortality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ablación con radiofrecuencia en el tratamiento de las taquiarritmias. Experiencia en 1000 pacientes consecutivos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Radiofrequency ablation in the treatment of tachyarrhythmias. Experience concerning 1,000 consecutive patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
