<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10619913</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Abril, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arenal, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benito, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Concejo, M P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To analyze mortality-related factors in elderly patients who were operated on for intestinal obstruction, and to determine whether advanced age worsened the morbidity and mortality rates. METHODS In this prospective study we analyzed 188 patients older than 69 years who were operated on for intestinal obstruction. Group 1 consisted of 82 patients aged between 70 and 79 years, and group 2 consisted of 106 patients aged 80 years and older. We compared the distribution of clinical features and outcomes between the two groups, and determined factors related with mortality (chi-squared test with Yates' correction, Student's t test and multiple logistic regression analysis). RESULTS The incidence of heart disease was 11% in group 1 and 35% in group 1 (p = 0.0003). There was no difference between the groups in any of the other factors analyzed. Univariate analysis identified as mortality-related factors perianesthetic risk (American Society of Anesthesiologists' Physical Status classification) (p = 0.0005), presence of metastases (p = 0.0001) and delay in surgery (t value = 3.043, p = 0.0027). CONCLUSIONS Mortality due to surgery for intestinal obstruction in elderly patients is related to perianesthetic risk and delay in surgery. Older age does not increase the morbidity or mortality rates for this type of surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intestinal obstruction in the elderly. Prognostic factors of mortality.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
