<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10618906</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-4355</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castro, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cid, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solla, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Adelantado, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Villaescusa, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castrillo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eiras, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varela, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE We have evaluated in vitro the effects of using plasma (group A) or PAS-2 (group B) in storing platelets, regarding as well the type of container (conventional polyolefin--PL732--or new oxygen permeable platelet containers--PL2410, Compoflex--), on the metabolism of platelet concentrates--PC--from pools of five buffy coats. MATERIAL AND METHODS 87, A and B pools of PCs collected in two types of bags were studied. The samples were taken on days 2, 5 and 7, and cell counts, pH, glucose, platelet activation (% CD62) and aggregation response were measured. RESULTS In group A, when we compared the two types of bags, we observed a difference (p &lt; 0.01) in values of pH and glucose on day 5. These values were more advantageous in new oxygen permeable platelet containers. The rest of the parameters analysed didn't show significant differences. When we compared the PL-2410 containers from groups A and B, we found a lower level of glucose (p &lt; 0.01) in group B, although the levels of glucose in this group on days 5 and 7 of storage were sufficient to support the platelet metabolism. CONCLUSIONS The use of new oxygen permeable polyolefin containers and additive solutions, PAS-2, allows us to obtain pools of PC with suitable metabolic parameters during storage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades de los concentrados de plaquetas almacenados: influencia del medio de suspensión y del tipo de bolsas utilizadas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Properties of stored platelet concentrates: effect of the suspension media and type of pouch used].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Sangre</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
