<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10667272</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rosado, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castañeda, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nutrient composition in foods is necessary for the determination of nutrient intake. Food composition tables used for dietary studies in Mexico do not have information of zinc, iron and copper; when present the values have been extrapolated from laboratory analysis carried out with foods in other countries and regions of the world. In this study zinc, iron, and copper content of 104 plant foods and 32 animal foods was determined. The procedure used was atomic absorption spectrophotometry for the minerals. Foods were grouped into cereals, vegetables, fruits, legumes and animal foods. Zinc content ranged from 0.018 mg/100 g for strawberry to 9.193 mg/100 g for beef. Iron content ranged from 0.113 mg/100 g for yogurt to 19.82 mg/100 g for a commercial cereal which had minerals added during processing. In some foods copper was not found and the highest content was 3.371 mg/100 g in beef liver. This study has provided information on zinc, iron and copper content of the most commonly consumed foods in Mexico.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contenido de hierro, zinc y cobre en los alimentos de mayor consumo en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Iron, zinc and copper content of foods commonly consumed in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
