<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10726181</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Puente Maestu, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz de Oña Lacasta, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Hermosa, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cubillo Marcos, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tatay Martí, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to compare two instruments for measuring dyspnea to functional capacity, defined as maximal oxygen uptake in a stress test limited by symptoms. We carried out a descriptive study to determine correlation between the methods. Subjects with severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease were enrolled and dyspnea during daily activities was evaluated using the Medical Research Council (MRC) scale and the chronic respiratory disease health perception questionnaire (CRQ). Dyspnea was also assessed on a visual analog scale (VAS) and the Borg scale. Patients performed a progressive treadmill test limited by symptoms to measure peak VO2 and VE. Correlation analysis of the two measures of dyspnea and the objective measures of functional capacity (peak VO2 and VE) showed that the clinical dyspnea measures (CRQ and MRC) correlated well with peak aerobic capacity and with maximal ventilation, whereas the VAS and Borg scale were not significantly related to the aforementioned variables. We also observed that the clinical scales for dyspnea correlated with each other, as did the VAS and Borg scale, but that there was no correlation between the two types of measurement. We conclude that clinical dyspnea indexes (CRQ and MRC) correlate well with maximal aerobic capacity and with each other. However, the VAS and Borg scale do not correlate with functional capacity measured by peak VO2 and VE.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de varias escalas de medición para valorar la disnea en las actividades diarias en los pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A comparison of several measurement scales for assessing dyspnea in their daily activities in patients with chronic obstructive lung disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
