<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10721555</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garijo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Córdoba, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Argüello, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olaso, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Viedma, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteban, R J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gobernado, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Two standardized techniques, Quantiplex (bDNA-2.0) and Amplicor Monitor have been evaluated for the quantification of virus load of HCV with these objectives: a) determinate the relationship between virus load and genotype, and b) evaluate the virus load in serial serum samples and in patients with normal or slightly increased liver enzymes in an area with a high prevalence of genotype 1. RESULTS A significant correlation of 0.7 (p &lt; 0.0001) in virus load has been observed by both methods, but the virus load is smaller by Monitor than by Quantiplex and does not depend on genotype. The relationship Monitor/Quantiplex is smaller in patients with non-1 genotype than in patients with genotype 1a (p = 0.01) and 1b (p = 0.005). Virus characteristics are similar in patients with normal or slightly increased enzymes than in patients with high enzymes. Virus load by both methods is not related to the age, sex, know duration of the infection, transmission manner of the infection neither to the histologic activity index. CONCLUSION The virus load not depends on genotype. The determination of virus load in a single serum sample adequately reflects the virus load are in several serum samples in patients with chronic HCV infection. The genotype and the virus load are similar in patients with normal enzymes than in patients with high enzymes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis comparativo de la carga viral mediante bDNA HCV RNA-2.0 y Amplicor HCV Monitor, en pacientes infectados por el virus de la hepatitis C.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative analysis of viral load by bDNA HCV RNA-2.0 and amplicor HCV monitor in patients with hepatitis C infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
