<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10758698</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rivero-Rodríguez, Z</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diaz, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cheng, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chourio-Lozano, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rucsón, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To determine the prevalence and epidemiological parameters of intestinal parasites in schoolchildren, a faecal analysis was performed in 349 individuals of both sexes, between 5 and 16 years of age. The methodology used included, a fresh test, formol-ether technique and faecal egg counts by the Kato-Katz method. Eighty three per cent of the children presented enteroparasites, with a high prevalence of polyparasitism (71.6%). There was not significative difference between parasitoses, sex and age. However, it was observed an increase of helminthiasis and protozooses in children between 7 and 10 years of age. The principal enteroparasites founded were: Trichuris trichiura (41.8%), Ascaris lumbricoides (35.2%), Blastocystis hominis (48.1%) and Endolimax nana (22.9%). When the intensity of infestation was studied by the faecal egg counts, it was observed that the highest percentage of children with T. trichiura had light infestations (84.3%), while 45.9% of the children with A. lumbricoides had severe infestations. The Abundance, Mean Intensity and Aggregation Coefficient (k) values show an over-dispersed spatial disposition of both helminths, where only few children harbour heavy burdens and eliminate a large quantity of eggs. This aggregation was higher for T. trichiura (k = 0.298) than for A. lumbricoides (k = 1.138).</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enteroparásitos en escolares de una institución pública del municipio Maracaibo, Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intestinal parasites in school children at a public institution in Maracaibo municipality, Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
