<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10752266</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Valdivia, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bastías, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In the last forty years, a sustained reduction in the gastric cancer and cerebrovascular disease mortality has been recorded. Joossens has postulated that sodium intake has an influence in the natural history of both diseases. AIM To analyze the mortality caused by both diseases in Chile. MATERIAL AND METHODS The mortality of people aged 35 to 64 years old, due to gastric cancer and cerebrovascular diseases in the period 1955-1994, was analyzed. An analysis according to regions, using temporal series and correlation techniques was performed. RESULTS In the studied period, the mortality due to gastric cancer decreased by 71.6% in men and by 79.5% in women. Mortality due to cerebrovascular diseases decreased by 56.9% in men and by 63.9% in women. There was a correlation coefficient of +0.91 between the mortality due to both diseases. Cerebrovascular disease mortality appears as a predictor of gastric cancer mortality in temporal series analysis. CONCLUSIONS Joossens theories are supported by the present data. Prospective studies should be designed to confirm the hypothesis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1999 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer gástrico y enfermedad cerebrovascular. Una historia natural con elementos comunes? Análisis de la teoría de la sal en Chile (1955-1994).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Gastric cancer and cerebrovascular diseases. A natural history with common elements? Analysis of the salt theory in Chile (1955-1994)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
