<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10785942</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Echeverría, M G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Etcheverrigaray, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pecoraro, M R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliva, G A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corva, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila Roza, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galosi, C M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An indirect enzyme linked immunosorbent assay was developed. Infected and non infected allantoic fluids precipitated with polyetilenglycol 6000 were used as antigen and control antigen, respectively. Serum samples were diluted 1/20 and a commercial horse radish peroxidase-labelled rabbit anti-equine IgG was used as second antibody. The reaction was developed using azino-diethylbenzotyazol-sulfonate (ABTS). Cut-off was determined by ratio sample (Rs). The hemagglutination inhibition test was used as a reference test for the 391 samples analyzed. Of these, 301 sera were positive by hemagglutination inhibition test and indirect ELISA, 75 were negative by both techniques, and 15 were positive by indirect ELISA and negative by hemagglutination inhibition test. Using hemagglutination inhibition test as standard, the indirect ELISA showed a relative specificity and sensitivity of 83.3 and 100%, respectively. This indirect ELISA is useful as screening test.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">ELISA indirecto para el diagnóstico rápido de Influenza Equina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Indirect ELISA for the rapid diagnosis of Equine Influenza].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
