<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10846602</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Toral Marín, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>González de Castro, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Castillo Otero, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peñafiel Colás, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carpio Muñoz, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between January 1992 and December 1998 we collected clinical, epidemiological and treatment data on all patients diagnosed of tuberculosis in our specialized unit. Five hundred sixty-seven patients (70% male and 30% female) were studied prospectively. The rate of new cases increased until 1995 and decreased during the last three years of study. Mean patient age was 38.8 years, with nearly 64% of patients under 45 years of age. Predisposing disease, mainly chronic alcoholism, was present in 36%. Fifteen percent belonged to a high-risk social group (6.5% were drug addicts and 6.3% lived inside secure institutions). The mean time elapsing from the appearance of symptoms until referral to our service was 80.4 days and the most common clinical picture at presentation was general unwellness with cough and expectoration (46%) followed by hemoptysis (18%). Cavitation was visible in 48.5% of x-rays, while alveolar infiltrates were seen in 33%, pleural effusion in 12% and lymph node involvement in 10%. Adult tuberculosis was diagnosed in 80% of cases, 10% were reactivations and 9% were primary. Bacteriological diagnosis was available for 85%. Therapy usually involved six months with hydrazide, rifampicin and pyrazinamide (81%). Therapy was generally well-tolerated, although analyses revealed some anomalies, such as transaminase alteration (18%) and hyperuricemia (19%). Therapy was changed because of toxicity in only 2.6%. Follow-up after therapy was strict and the rate of successful cure was 97.5%. We conclude that diagnosis was not prompt enough and believe that knowledge of epidemiological, clinical and evolutionary data, as well as monitoring of real rates of cure of treated patients justifies the existence of specialized centers for managing tuberculosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidad monográfica de tuberculosis: experiencia de 7 años de funcionamiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tuberculosis management unit: 7-year experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
