<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10859738</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Timoneda-Gallart, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Alvarez, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION We present a study on reading and writing difficulties after normal instruction during a year. OBJECTIVE Verifying if these patients showed a specific pattern of PASS (Planning, Attention, Sequential and Simultaneous) cognitive processing; if so, it allows us a rapid diagnosis and a useful cognitive remediation according to the PASS theory of intelligence. PATIENTS AND METHODS Thirty patients were selected from neuropediatric patients because of learning disability. They were selected according to their performance on several tests of phonological aware and a test of writing to discover errors in spelling. Patients with verbal language problems, as in dysphasia, and patients with learning difficulty not determined by reading or writing were ruled out. A control group of 300 scholars was used. The translated DN:CAS battery was administered to the study group and the control group for assessing the PASS cognitive processing. Statistical factorial analysis of the control group was performed as a validity confirmation to discriminate the four PASS cognitive processes. Cluster analysis of the study group was performed to discriminate its homogeneity. Differences between means were tested with the t-Student. RESULTS The four PASS cognitive processes were identified in the control group. The study group scored less than minus 1 SD in successive processing, the rest of the processes being clearly higher than minus 1 SD, and the mean of study group was inferior to control group (p = 0.001). CONCLUSION A kind of dyslexia may be defined by disfunction in PASS successive processing.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Apr 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La dislexia como disfunción del procesamiento secuencial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dyslexia as a disfunction in successive processing].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
