<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10851749</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Merino, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tato, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gude, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros-Dios, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey-García, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beceiro, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the relationship between self-perception of their health and mortality in a representative sample of persons over 65 in a rural community. DESIGN Survival study of population with three years observance. SETTING A non-coastal and rural borough in Galicia. PARTICIPANTS 408 people over 65, chosen by random sampling. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS The demographic, social and health (objective and subjective) parameters were determined through an initial survey, with subsequent follow-up to find the date and cause of death should this have occurred. Of the 404 elderly people observed, 67 (16%) died. The main causes of death were diseases of the circulatory apparatus (48%) followed by tumours. Mortality was higher in people who were older, unmarried, didn't drink alcohol, were seriously ill, had restricted mobility, consumed more medicines and had a perception of their health as poor. We found an association between self-perceived health and mortality, after adjustment for age, sex, marital status, educational level and consumption of medicines, only when we looked at the elderly without restricted mobility (RR = 2.3; 95% CI = 1.0-5.3). CONCLUSIONS We think that self-perception of health status can be an overall indicator of health, linked to mortality, and that in the elderly with good mobility, this association can be independent of age, sex, educational level, marital status and consumption of medicines.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Apr 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autopercepción de la salud y mortalidad en ancianos de una comunidad rural.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Self-perception of health and mortality in elderly from a rural community].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
