<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10886860</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4464</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avalos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mizdraji</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Damborsky</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oscherov</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Domestic and peridomestic triatomine colonization, T. infestans infection rate and human seropositives to Trypanosoma cruzi in rural areas of Empedrado Department, Corrientes, Argentina, were carried out. Methods used in order to search the triatomines, to determine them systematically, to obtain their infection rates and the human seropositives, were the same applied in a previous report. From 100 households characterized, 53.0% had mud walls, laminated zinc or cardboard combined with other elements were used in 37.5% of the roofs, and 83.0% had earthen floors. Presence of domestic animais sleeping inside houses was detected in 91.0% of human dwellings. Domestic infestation by T. infestans was 29.0% and 1.0% by T. sordida. Other T. infestans entomological indexes recorded were: natural infection index = 23, colonization index = 75 and dispersion index = 54,5. T. sordida was found in 12.1% of peridomestic structures while T. infestans was detected in 2.4%. General prevalence from 298 human sera analized by Indirect Hemagglutination and Indirect Immunofluorescence Antibody Tests, was 32.2%. A high percentage of positive serology (23.7%) was found among 0-10 years old, wich represent the age group of higher transmission risk.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infestación domiciliaria por triatominos y seroprevalencia humana en el Departamento Empedrado, Corrientes, Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Household infestation by triatomines and human seroprevalence in Empedrado Department, Corrientes, Argentina]</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cadernos de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
