<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10902449</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villalonga, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Metje, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arxer, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santiveri, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Plaja, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the duration of spinal block with 5% prilocaine and 2% mepivacaine in short procedures for transurethral resection and to assess possible complications in the immediate postoperative period. MATERIAL AND METHODS Fifty-seven patients scheduled for transurethral resection of the prostate or a vesical tumor. Patients were ASA I-III, over 55 years of age and randomly assigned to two groups to receive 5% prilocaine (1 mg/kg, n = 27) or 2% mepivacaine (0.8 mg/kg, n = 30). We collected data on anesthetic technique, levels of extension of motor and sensory blockades, duration of blockades and complications within the first 24 hours after surgery. RESULTS Demographic data, ASA classification and duration of surgery were similar in both groups. We found statistically significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) in duration of sensory blockade (120.92 +/- 36.21 min with prilocaine and 145.83 +/- 35.81 min with mepivacaine) and in motor blockade (106.29 +/- 38.16 min with prilocaine and 133.16 +/- 42.21 min with mepivacaine). Five cases of hypotension and 4 of bradycardia occurred in each group and one patient in the mepivacaine group suffered slight postoperative cephalea. CONCLUSIONS Both local anesthetics offer good surgical conditions with hemodynamic stability and few complications. The duration of sensory and motor blockade is shorter with prilocaine than with mepivacaine, making prilocaine more appropriate for short interventions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo entre prilocaína al 5% y mepivacaína al 2% por vía subaracnoidea en resecciones transuretrales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study between 5% prilocaine and 2% mepivacaine by the subarachnoid route in transurethral resections].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
