<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10919186</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Junqué, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mataró, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pueyo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Sánchez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vendrell, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estévez-González, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mañeru, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Anatomical and functional neuroimaging data from subjects with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) have consistently implicated a reversal of cerebral asymmetry and suggested a fronto-striatal dysfunction in this disorder. OBJECTIVE The aim of this study is to investigate the brain asymmetries in a homogeneous and non-medicated sample of adolescents with ADHD who had been previously studied in our laboratory. PATIENTS AND METHODS T1-weighted magnetic resonance images were obtained for 11 adolescents with ADHD and 19 control subjects. Frontal and posterior brain regions, caudate nucleus, and ventricular system were quantitatively measured. RESULTS A reversed pattern of asymmetry for the caudate nucleus (right &gt; left) was found in ADHD when compared to the control group. We also found a reversed pattern of asymmetry for the frontal lobe (right &lt; left) and a smaller right frontal volume (prefrontal specifically) in the ADHD subjects most severely impaired. Right caudate and frontal measures were inversely correlated. CONCLUSIONS ADHD is associated with fronto-striatal abnormalities, which may be explicable via extant neurodevelopmental theories. Enlargement of the right caudate nucleus may suggest the failure of a process of synaptic 'pruning' by which attentional functions could be improperly transferred from the basal ganglia to frontal regions during development.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 May 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad. Asimetrías cerebrales observadas en resonancia magnética.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Cerebral asymmetry observed on magnetic resonance].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
