<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10932340</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Although lung cancer is the most frequently diagnosed tumor world-wide, the real incidence of this diagnosis in Spain is unknown. To contribute to determining the incidence of lung cancer in this country, and in view of the lack of data from the community of Castilla-León, we carried out the present study. METHODS The 56 members of the lung cancer research group of the Castillian-Leonese Respiratory Disease Society (SOCALPAR) prospectively gathered data on new cases diagnosed in our community during 1997. Quality control checks were performed locally, at the central office for data management, and by way of reviews conducted at referral hospitals. RESULTS One thousand fifteen cases (95 women and 920 men) were diagnosed, giving an age-adjusted rate to world population of 21.53 cases per 100,000 inhabitants (men: 41.58; women: 4.31). The incidence of lung cancer by province of origin was 36.89 for Avila, 43.65 for Burgos, 42.07 for León, 38.88 for Palencia, 38.88 for Salamanca, 36.72 for Segovia, 29.91 for Soria, 45.90 for Valladolid, and 48.71 for Zamora. Smokers or ex-smokers accounted for 90.14% of patients with lung cancer. Diagnosis was by cytohistology for 877 patients (86.4%), with a predominance of squamous cell carcinoma (50.62%), and by clinical or radiologic assessment based on the pneumologist's or surgeon's criteria in 138 (13.6%). CONCLUSIONS The standardized incidence of lung cancer in Castilla-León in 1997 was 21.53 cases per 100,000 inhabitants (men: 41.58; women: 4.31). Diagnosis was by clinical or radiological criteria in 13.6%.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia del carcinoma broncopulmonar en Castilla-León durante el año 1997. Estudio multicéntrico de la Sociedad Castellano-Leonesa de Patología Respiratoria (SOCALPAR). Grupo de Estudio del Carcinoma Broncopulmonar de la SOCALPAR.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Incidence of bronchopulmonary carcinoma in Castilla-León in 1997. Multicenter study of the Society of Castilla-León of Respiratory Pathology (SOCALPAR). Study Group for Bronchopulmonary Carcinoma of the SOCALPAR].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
