<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>10956603</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romeo, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Salmerón, R J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guitián, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ponce De León, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Campo, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mantilla, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goicolea, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nandayapa, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pasalodos, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND AIM Gated-SPECT is a promising method to analyze myocardial viability. We have assessed the accuracy of a new protocol of rest/Dobutamine gated-SPECT, based on the evaluation of contractile reserve induced by 10 microg/kg/min of Dobutamine, to predict contractile recovery after revascularization of dysinergic myocardial territories. PATIENTS AND METHODS In a group of 36 patients submitted to percutaneous revascularization, we selected 40 vascular territories (21 left descending artery, 19 right coronary-circumflex) with severely depressed contractility (contrast ventriculography, center line method). Follow up evaluation at 6 months showed the absence of angiographic restenosis and control contrast ventriculography assessed the contractile changes of the selected territories, considering those with contractile restoration as viable. Before revascularization, rest/Dobutamine gated-SPECT study was applied and viability was defined as the presence of contractile reserve (positive or improvement [n = 21] and negative or impairment [n = 7]) with non viability being the absence of contractile reserve (n = 12). We analyzed the evolution of the ejection fraction in a group of 27 patients with impaired ventricular function and complete revascularization. RESULTS Gated-SPECT showed a sensitivity of 0.96 (95% CI 0.78-0.99) and a specificity of 0.78 (95% CI 0.48-0.94) in the diagnosis of viability. The ejection fraction (median [interquartile range]) increased after revascularization: 0.42 (0.15) vs 0.55 (0.22), Z = -3.9; p &lt; 0. 001. The diagnosis of viability by gated-SPECT (p &lt; 0.001) and the extent of severely depressed myocardium (p = 0.04) independently predicted the increase of the ejection fraction after revascularization. CONCLUSIONS The analysis of contractile reserve by rest/Dobutamine gated-SPECT is adequate to diagnose viability in territories with severely depressed contractility and independently predicts the increase of ejection fraction after revascularization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capacidad del protocolo de gated-SPECT reposo/dobutamina para predecir la recuperación contráctil posrevascularización de áreas miocárdicas disinérgicas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The capacity of the rest-dobutamine gated SPECT protocol to predict contractile recovery after revascularization of myocardial dysinergic areas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
