<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11003883</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Verdú Pérez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ureta Huertos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Lozano, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Falero Gallego, M P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tuberous sclerosis is characterized by the potential for hamartomatous growth in multiple organs. Common manifestations are hypomelanotic spots, facial angiofibromas, subependymal hamartomas, cortical tubers, cardiac rhabdomyomas, retinal hamartomas, and so on. Seizures and mental retardation are frequent. It is an autosomal dominant disease but there is a high percentage of spontaneous mutations. Neonatal diagnosis is exceptional. We report a case of a female term newborn who presented partial motor seizures at the third day of life. Physical examination revealed only a disturbance of cardiac rhythm. Echocardiography showed ventricular intramural rhabdomyomas. Magnetic resonance imaging disclosed periventricular subependymal nodules and cortical tubers. A retinal hamartoma was found in the right eye. At the age of 1 month, hypomelanotic spots were evident on the back skin. The patient had infantile spasms, followed by poorly controlled partial complex seizures together with severe psychomotor retardation. Examination of both parents was normal. We discuss the uncommon diagnosis of tuberous sclerosis during the neonatal period, as well as the exceptional mode of presentation of our patient, with seizures in the early neonatal period, a phenomenon rarely reported in the literature.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crisis parciales en recién nacido con esclerosis tuberosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Partial seizures in a newborn with tuberous sclerosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
