<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11002717</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Saludes Serra, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solsona Della, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boada Pie, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Recasens Urbez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rull Bartomeu, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bueno Izquierdo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertrophic obstructive myocardiopathy (HOM) is characterised by left ventricular hypertrophy, which causes dynamic obstruction at the exit of the chamber and diastolic dysfunction of the myocardium. The use of epidural anesthesia in patients with HOM is controversial due to the hemodynamic repercussions of reduced preloading and postloading that occur. A 28-year-old woman with HOM was scheduled for cesarean delivery at 36.5 weeks because of delayed intrauterine growth. Satisfactory epidural anesthesia was provided with 0.5% bupivacaine with prior invasive hemodynamic monitoring. Analgesic and anesthetic management of a full-term parturient with HOM is a major challenge for the anesthesiologist. Although elective cesarean under general anesthesia is traditionally suggested for such patients, vaginal delivery with epidural analgesia is currently also being used. However, experience in using epidural anesthesia for cesarean delivery is scarce. For our patient, epidural anesthesia with appropriate hemodynamic monitoring allowed surgery to take place without complications. We therefore believe that the technique might be useful for such patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cesárea electiva con anestesia epidural a una gestante con miocardiopatía hipertrófica obstructiva.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Elective cesarean section with epidural anesthesia in a pregnant woman with obstructive hypertrophic myocardiopathy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
