<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11002713</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arnau Obrer, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Granell Gil, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palanca Sanfrancisco, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguar Olba, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cantó Armengod, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grau Real, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To evaluate the effects on postoperative pulmonary function and quality of analgesia of two protocols for epidural infusion of alfentanil after lung resection. PATIENTS AND METHODS After informed consent, 30 ASA I-IV patients undergoing chest surgery (lobectomy or pneumonectomy) were randomly assigned to two groups of 15. A catheter was inserted into the epidural space at T5-7 (group T) or L2-3 (group L). After a test dose, an initial bolus of alfentanil (10 micrograms/kg) was administered. After anesthetic induction, epidural analgesia was performed with an infusion of 400 micrograms/h of alfentanil (group L) during and after surgery. Endovenous patent-controlled anesthesia (PCA) was provided with morphine. During the first 24 h after surgery, the following variables were recorded: arterial blood gas concentrations, spirometric parameters, pain on a visual analog scale (VAS) and side effects. ANOVA and Scheffé and chi-square tests were used to analyze the results (p &lt; or = 0.05). RESULTS In group T, PaO2 was significantly higher at 6 and 18 h (p &lt; or = 0.05), while FEV1 and FVC were significantly higher at 12 and 18 h. Pain assessed by VAS and PCA need for morphine was significantly less in group T. CONCLUSIONS Thoracic epidural analgesia with alfentanil and lidocaine improves postoperative lung function and reduces the need for top-up analgesia in comparison with lumbar epidural infusion of alfentanil.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función pulmonar y calidad de la analgesia tras cirugía resectiva pulmonar con alfentanilo epidural.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Lung function and quality of analgesia after lung resection with epidural alfentanyl].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
