<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11002515</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villavicencio Mavrich, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tabernero Caturla, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santomé Couto, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valentí Moreno, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To review the advantages, disadvantages and efficacy of the different therapeutic options for stage I seminoma and nonseminomatous germ cell testicular tumors. METHODS The literature on the treatment of stage I germ cell testicular tumors was reviewed. RESULTS/CONCLUSIONS Germ cell tumors of the testis constitute 1-1.5% of neoplasms in the male, accounting for 95% of testicular neoplasms, and is the most common solid tumor in men aged 20-35 years. Currently, 70% of the patients with seminoma and 50% of the patients with nonseminomatous germ cell testicular tumors are diagnosed in stage I. Radiotherapy following orchidectomy has classically been utilized in the treatment of stage I germ cell testicular tumors. Postoperative radiation therapy is currently being replaced by close patient follow-up in many centers. Retroperitoneal lymphadenectomy post-orchidectomy is the standard treatment for stage I nonseminomatous germ cell testicular tumors. Today, however, the foregoing approach is also being replaced by close postoperative follow-up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de los tumores de células germinales testiculares estadio I.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of stage I germ cell tumors of the testis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
