<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11027095</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Beltrán-Blasco, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castaño-Pérez, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medrano-Martínez, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moltó-Jordà, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arenas, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Pérez, R M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Meningiomas are primary tumours of the central nervous system. Usually they are sporadic. The occurrence in more than one member of a family is unusual. Up till now this coincidence had been related with type 2 neurofibromatosis. In this paper we comment on two siblings who did not fulfil neurofibromatosis diagnostic criteria as an example of sporadic familial meningiomas. CLINICAL CASES Two siblings (a 79 years old female and a 77 years old male) were diagnosed of a meningioma in an interval of two years, with surprising clinical and neuroimaging similarities. In sporadic meningiomas, abnormalities in the long arm of chromosome 22 have been found. Type 2 neurofibromatosis causative gene has also been found in this chromosome. Meningiomas are quite often found in this entity, and therefore, this gene was implicated as a main factor in the genesis of an important number of meningiomas. However, several studies have not found an association between these tumours and the locus for neurofibromatosis, leading to think that there may be other genes that may influence on meningiomas development.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Sep 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningiomas familiares esporádicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sporadic familial meningiomas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
