<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11055110</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Guzmán, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lomelí-Rodríguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-García, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Prenatal diagnosis of fetal ovarian cyst, spontaneously resolved in the postnatal period. INTRODUCTION Fetal ovarian cysts are an unusual entity, which is generally discovered during an ultrasonographic fetal examination. The objective of this report is to present a clinical case of a female fetus with an ovarian cysts which was diagnose by an ultrasound (US) at 36.5 week gestation which was spontaneously resolved in the postnatal period. CLINICAL CASE A 22 year old woman to whom an US was performed to evaluate the gestational age due to the fact that she was to be programmed for a cesarean due to vulvovaginal condyloma. The US reported a 36.5 week gestation, the fetus was female and a cyst of 50 x 44 mm diameter was found in the fetal pelvis, lateral to the bladder. The child was born two weeks later by cesarean section and without complications. The control pelvic US at one month of age showed that the cysts was 54 x 45 mm in diameter. It was decided and wait to see what would happen. At five months of age the pelvic US showed the absence of the cyst. CONCLUSION The diagnosis of the fetal ovarian cysts was based on three ultrasonographic criteria: 1. presence of a cystic structure of regular size which is located in the lower and lateral side of the abdomen, 2. integrity of urinary and gastrointestinal tracts, and 3. female sex of the fetus. The treatment depends on the size of the cyst and the ultrasonographic images of torsion and hemorrhage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico prenatal de quiste de ovario fetal, resolución espontánea posnatal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prenatal diagnosis of fetal ovarian cyst, postnatal spontaneous remission].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
