<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11083965</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vázquez Rueda, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moñiz Mora, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vaz Leal, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To determine the psychological response in children undergoing short-stay ambulatory surgery. PATIENTS AND METHODS &lt; psychological responses (CDS, STAIC-E); factor 2: personality (EPQ-J and STAIC-R) and adaptability (TAMAI); factor 3: anxiety and hospital fears (HFRS). Student's paired t-test was used to compare clinical variables. RESULTS &lt; 8.17 +/- 2.10). The most frequent diagnosis in boys was phymosis and that in girls was inguinal hernia. Forty-one children had previously been hospitalized, of which 29 had undergone surgery. Factorial analysis of the variables explained 46.8% of variance. STAIC-E and STAIC-R scores significantly decreased in the postoperative period. Girls had higher HFRS scores than boys. STAIC-R scores were lower in previously hospitalized children. FILE values in the previous 12 months correlated with increased STAIC-R scores. CONCLUSIONS Elective ambulatory surgery in children minimizes emotional disruption to the child. In this study no differences were observed in the STIC-R and STAIC-E scores before and after surgery. Girls had higher levels of anxiety and fear of surgery. Previously hospitalized children, with or without surgery, had lower anxiety levels. Family problems during the 12 months prior to surgery increased the children's anxiety and depression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la respuesta psicológica perioperatoria en la cirugía de corta estancia hospitalaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of perioperative psychological response to short-stay hospital surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
