<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11093841</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mora, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nogueira, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pasquau, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moltó, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escolano, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gregori, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To assess genotypic resistance mutations in patients with virological failure with highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) METHODS: Genotyping of reverse transcriptase (RT) and protease (PRO) HIV-1 genes were carried out in 33 adherent patients failing on HAART. RESULTS Resistance mutations were found in 32 of the 33; 27 of them (81.8%) being primary mutations: 26 (78.8%) in the RT gene and 60 (60.6%) in the PRO gene. Overall, 66.6% had genotypic resistance to two drugs and 60.6% showed resistance to drugs belonging to the two main classes of antiretroviral drugs. At the time of treatment failure, 72.7% had on their therapeutic regimen one antiretroviral drug to which they had resistance mutations, 48.5% had genotypic resistance to two drugs of the therapeutic regimen and 21.2% to three drugs. CONCLUSIONS Most adherent patients failing on HAART carry drug resistant genotypes. These patients may constitute a reservoir of multidrug resistant HIV that may limit treatment options in the future.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Oct 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resistencias genotípicas a los fármacos antirretrovirales en fracasos terapéuticos con pautas de alta eficacia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Genotypic resistance to antiretroviral drugs in patients with therapeutic failure to highly active antiretroviral therapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
