<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11109652</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Medina Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Asencio Marchante, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Chozas, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espino Montoro, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Martín, M C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Subacute thyroiditis is an inflammatory disorder of the thyroid caused probably by viruses. It is clinically characterized by the presence of anterior cervical pain and/or painful goiter, and rarely as fever of unknown origin or as prolonged fever syndrome. We report a case of a 49-year-old female admitted to the hospital because of fever during last month, leukocytosis and accelerated erythrocyte sedimentation rate. Following observation, slight tenderness over the thyroid gland and signs of hyperthyroidism occurred. After the laboratory studies, low thyroidal radioactive iodine uptake and fine-needle aspiration cytology (FNAC) of thyroid, she was diagnosed of subacute thyroiditis with hyperthyroidism. We believe that the etiologic agent was the Epstein-Barr virus because heterophile and Epstein-Barr virus-specific antibodies were positive. The patient was treated with acetaminophen (1.500 mg/day) with prompt and complete resolution of the clinical and laboratory abnormalities. There has been no recurrence of the disease during a 1 year follow-up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiroiditis subaguda asociada a anticuerpos positivos al virus de Epstein-Barr.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Subacute thyroiditis associated with positive antibodies to the Epstein-Barr virus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
