<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11105340</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barrueco, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soldado, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteban, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solanellas, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Sucralfate is an effective agent in the treatment of peptic ulcer, mixing up the fibrinous exudate of duodenal ulcer to form a protective barrier promoting its healing. Similarly the deprived muscle in the tonsillar bed results protected and consequently bring down the post-surgical morbidity. OBJECTIVE The aim of this study has been to ascertain the suitability of sucralfate in alleviating symptoms after tonsil's removal. MATERIAL AND METHODS 205 children were included in the study and randomly postoperative treated with sucralfate. A lot of different parameters were controlled afterwards such as days with pain, taken of analgesics, return to normal diet, fever, bloody saliva, halitosis or vomits. RESULTS There was a significant association between the use of sucralfate and less days with sore throat, less pain and analgesia required. CONCLUSIONS The use of sucralfate means and efficient measure in order to alleviate the pain and postoperative discomfort associated with tonsils removal, being a cheap drug and without having topical after-effects.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del sucralfato en la mejora del posoperatorio de la amigdalectomía infantil.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The usefulness of sucralfate in postoperative improvement of children's tonsillectomy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales otorrinolaringologicos ibero-americanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
