<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11131858</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Millán-Guerrero, R O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tene-Pérez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trujillo-Hernández, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE After reviewing the existing literature on the subject, a therapeutic, symptomatic alternative in the treatment of hemifacial spasm is proposed. MATERIAL AND METHOD Three patients, all with a 5-year history of hemifacial spasm, were given one 25/250-mg tablet of Levodopa/carbidopa every 12 h. In a cross-over study, the patients were their own controls. The initial treatment phase lasted 1 month, at the end of which treatment was suspended. For an equal amount of time, the patients were given a placebo, after which they were again given Levodopa. RESULTS After a 2-week period of treatment with Levodopa, the symptomatic aspect of the spasm disappeared in the patients. Upon replacing the drug with the placebo, the spasm reappeared. The patients have since been receiving the treatment with Levodopa, one tablet every 12 h, for a period of 4 years and the reduction of the hemifacial spasm has oscillated at 75%. CONCLUSION We suggest the use of Levodopa/carbidopa in the treatment of hemifacial spasm as a therapeutic alternative. This treatment is within the patients' economic reach and more importantly allows them to once again lead normal lives.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Levo dopa en espasmo hemifacial. Una alternativa terapéutica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Levodopa in hemifacial spasm. A therapeutic alternative].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
