<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11141415</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández de la Puebla Giménez, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ceballos, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carmona, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Miranda, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Perepérez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Martínez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Jiménez, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The coagulant activity of factor VII increases with age and is a risk factor in middle aged subjects. Its role in elderly people is still unknown. The aim of this study was to evaluate whether or not FVIIc is a risk factor in such population. STUDY DESIGN cases and controls study. The group of cases consisted of 79 subjects fulfilling the following criteria: a) age between 65 and 85 years, and b) admission in the Valle de los Pedroches Hospital of Pozoblanco (Córdoba, Spain) due to a myocardial infarction and/or unstable angina, 2 or 6 months before their enrollment. The control group consisted of 81 subjects of similar age, chosen at random from the municipal registry, and excluding those with coronary heart disease. Factor VIIc was measured by conventional methods. Plasma samples were diluted with deficient plasma in FVIIc, and coagulation times were measured after adding thromboplastin and calcium. The measures were compared with a &lt;control&gt; plasma and the results were presented as a percentage. RESULTS There were no significant differences in the FVIIc between cases (118.3 [SD 22.2]) and controls (116.5 [24.4]; p = 0.630) in the total group. When classified according to their age, it was observed that within the group of more than 75 years old, cases had a higher FVIIc than controls (124.1 [18.2] vs 113.3 [23.5]; p &lt; 0. 05). When the classification was carried out according to sex, male presented similar results than the total group. Bivariable analysis showed, in subjects with coronary diseases, that FVIIc was related to total cholesterol, cLDL, apoprotein B, body mass index, HbA1c, and age. Factors related to FVIIc in the multivariable analysis were basal glucose serum level, body mass index; cHDL was negatively related. CONCLUSIONS FVIIc is higher in very old subjects with coronary diseases so it may be a significant coronary risk factor in this age group.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov 18 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad coagulante del factor VII (FVIIc) en ancianos con cardiopatía isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Coagulant activity of factor VII (FVIIc) in the elderly with ischemic heart disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
