<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11153202</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Reina, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galmes, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mari, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ballesteros, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Munar, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To prospectively evaluate the efficacy of the saline dextran extraction method in the human cytomegalovirus (CMV) pp65 antigenemia assay (Ag-pp65). MATERIAL AND METHODS In a 2 months period we studied all the blood samples from immunodepressed patients. The extraction of leukocytes polymorphonuclear (LPMN) was obtained with a 6% dextran solution in 0.9% saline. The total leukocytes population was counted and the percentage of LPMN obtained was established. Simultaneously the LPMN were cultivated into the MRC-5 cell line by the shell vial method (SVC). RESULTS The 144 blood samples studied were divided in three groups depending of the positivity in the pp65-AG and/or in the SVC. The patients with both assays positive presented the lower overall leukocyte and LPMN counting, with a difference statistically significance with the pp65-Ag negative. No statistically difference was observed in the overall count of leukocytes in the pp65-Ag negative group. The overall percentage of LPMN obtained was 87%. The median value of pp65-Ag positive samples was 48/100,000 LPMN, this value would be 51/100,000 LPMN with the application of the real percentage of LPMN obtained (p &gt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS The saline dextran extraction method presented a high efficacy in the majority of blood samples studied. The immunological status and the presence of a CMV infection or disease in the patient were the principal factors that influence the extraction method. In general there is no need to adjust the pp65-Ag value obtained with this method to the real one.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rendimiento del método de extracción con dextrano salino en la prueba de la antigenemia pp65 frente al citomegalovirus humano.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Efficiency of the extraction method with saline dextran in the pp65 antigenemia assay against human cytomegalovirus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
