<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11178802</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín Martínez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alió Y Sanz, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mahiques Bujanda, M M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fouad Sakla, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mulet Homs, M E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To evaluate the efficacy and tolerance of ADAL-1(R), a new adhesive in strabismus surgery. METHODS Three groups of 10 eyes each of 30 albino rabbits underwent superior rectus muscle recession 4 mm, 1(st) group of 10 eyes using the new adhesive, sacrified after one week, 2(nd) group of 10 eyes also with ADAL-1(R), sacrificed after one month and the 3(rd) group (control) of 10 eyes using Dexon 6/0 suture, sacrificed after one month. Clinical evaluation was done at the 1(st) postoperative day, at one week and at one month. The presence of residue of the adhesive, its hardness and the condition of the muscle were all studied after sacrificing the animal. Descriptive study was done for the 1(st) and the 2(nd) group, within the 2(nd) group significant changes along the follow up period were studied using the Friedman test and also differences between the 2(nd) and the suture group were examined using the Fisher's Exact Test. RESULTS The inflammatory reaction was evaluated between absent and mild in 80% of the cases, both in the 2(nd) and the control group. In the ADAL-1(R) group there were significant statistical differences between 1(st) and 4(th) week (p=0.0002). In the 2(nd) group, 80% of the muscles were attached to the planed position and 20% were slightly displaced, while in the control group 90% of the muscles were attached to the planed position, and 10% were slightly displaced, however there is no significant difference between the two groups p=0.5 (Fisher's Exact Test). CONCLUSION ADAL-1(R), a new adhesive, could replace sutures in strabismus surgery, giving rise to a rapid and efficient adhesion between muscles and sclera and well tolerated by the ocular tissues.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">ADAL-1(R): Nuevo adhesivo sintético de uso en cirugía del estrabismo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[ADAL-1(R): a new synthetic adhesive for use in strabismus surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
