<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11181193</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ariceta Iraola, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez do Forno, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND There are many therapeutic options against enuresis. OBJECTIVE To evaluate several therapies introduced progressively to treat monosymptomatic nocturnal enuresis. METHODS Eighty-four patients, aged 6 to 14 years old, were studied. The 67 year olds were treated with desmopressin and oxybutynin was added in nonresponders. If enuresis persisted, Alarm was given. Children over 7 years of age were randomly divided and treated with Alarm or Alarm plus desmopressin. Nonresponders were treated with desmopressin alone. RESULTS In children aged 6-7 years the cumulative response was 72%. Those who wetted themselves less responded to desmopressin. In children over 7 years of age, response to Alarm was 73.3% and response to Alarm plus desmopressin was 58.6%. In nonresponders the cumulative response after desmopressin treatment increased to 80% and 62% respectively. CONCLUSIONS In the group of 6 to 7 year-olds desmopressin was indicated as first line therapy. Treatment efficacy was increased by adding oxybutynin especially in the children who wetted themselves the most. In children over 7 years of age Alarm was the most effective treatment and relapses were fewer. No advantages were observed with the combination of Alarm and desmopressin in our protocol.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de una estrategia terapéutica frente a la enuresis nocturna monosintomática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Results of a therapeutic strategy against monosymptomatic nocturnal enuresis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
