<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11195956</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Río de la Loza, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carranza-Lira, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Celis, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Chéquer, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murillo-Uribe, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the effectiveness in the control of climacteric symptoms, the tolerability and the uterine bleeding pattern between two types of hormone replacement therapy. MATERIAL AND METHODS 81 postmenopausal women between 40 and 60 years age with vasomotor symptoms were studied. Randomly it was administered: I. Conjugated equine estrogens (CEE)-Medroxyprogesterone acetate (MPA): 21 tablets with 0.625 mg of CEE and 10 tablets with 5 mg of MPA which were taken with the last ten tablets of CEE in each cycle (n = 3 7). II. E2V-CPA: 11 tablets with 2 mg of E2V and 10 tablets with 2 mg of E2V and 1 mg of CPA (n = 44). Each cycle comprised 28 days. The treatments were compared with squared Chi and Mann-Whitney U test. RESULTS The hot flushes presence was significantly greater in the group with CEE-MPA (p &lt; 0.03). Severe throbs at the end of the study had a trend to be more frequent in the group with EC-MPA (p &lt; 0.06). At the end of the study there was a greater frequency of breast tenderness in the group with CEE-MPA (P = 0.009). CONCLUSIONS Both treatments have good effectiveness, tolerability and same bleeding pattern. Only the frequency of hot flushes, the presence of severe throbs and breast tenderness were lower in the group with E2V-CPA, that makes this preparation an option that can have a better acceptance by the women.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo entre la combinación valerianato de estradiol-acetato de ciproterona y estrógenos conjugados equinos-acetato de medroxiprogesterona como terapia hormonal de reemplazo en el climaterio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study between estradiol valerate combined with cyproterone acetate, and conjugated equine estrogens combined with medroxyprogesterone acetate as hormone replacement therapy in climacteric].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
