<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11190968</identifier>
<setSpec>1020-4989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Honorio Martínez, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santamarina Mijares, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Pacheco, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In June 1996 in the state of Oaxaca, Mexico, larvae of the mosquito species Aedes aegypti were exposed to infective preparasites of the nematode Romanomermis culicivorax, Ross and Smith, in the laboratory and in the field. For the laboratory experiments larvae in instars I-IV were used; they had been collected in natural reservoirs. The laboratory experiments were carried out in triplicate, with 100 larvae of each larval stage per experiment. Three preparasite application dosage ratios were tested: 5, 10, or 15 preparasites per mosquito larva. For the field studies 13 A. aegypti outdoor breeding sites were used, with larvae in instars I-IV and a 15:1 preparasite dosage ratio. With the laboratory experiments, an increase was observed in the average infestation of the larvae as the preparasite application ratio was increased from 5:1 to 15:1. With a 10:1 ratio, the rates of parasitism were 100%, 100%, 85%, and 74% in the larvae in instars I, II, III, and IV, respectively; for the 15:1 preparasite ratio, parasitism rates were 100%, 100%, 90%, and 79%, respectively. The field tests with the 15:1 preparasite dosage ratio in the 13 outdoor reservoirs produced parasitism rates of 80% to 98%, thus demonstrating the susceptibility of this species of mosquito to parasitism by R. culicivorax in Oaxaca, Mexico.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Susceptibilidad de las larvas de Aedes aegypti al parasitismo por Romanomermis culicivorax en condiciones de laboratorio y de campo en Oaxaca, México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Susceptibility of Aedes aegypti larvae to parasitism by Romanomermis culicivorax in laboratory and field conditions in Oaxaca, Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
