<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11198337</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carlón López, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Varela, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Houghton, R F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Suárez Gil, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Suárez, M M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study the understanding, attitudes and practice of primary care doctors in the prescription of hormonal post-coitus interception, along with the social and demographic, educational, legal and ethical variables associated with this prescription. DESIGN Cross-sectional descriptive study. SETTING Area IV de INSALUD in Asturias. PARTICIPANTS Family doctors, excluding locums (n = 178). MEASUREMENTS AND RESULTS An anonymous self-administered questionnaire with 33 questions, re-sent once, between November 1999 and February 2000. The association-independence of variables was contrasted through the chi 2 test (a statistically significant association if p &lt; 0.05). 77% responded, 51% of whom were men. Average age was 43 (SD = 6.69), with professional experience of 17 years worked (SD = 6.87). 47% were family doctors and 39% general practitioners. 85% worked in health centres; 46% in urban settings. 71% were catholics, 73% (95% CI: 66%-80%) had been asked on at least one occasion in the previous six months for the post-coitus pill (PCP), with demand greater in the urban environment (83%). 18% considered the PCP an abortion method. 88% said they would prescribe it (95% CI: 82.5%-93.5%), of which 30% (95% CI: 16%-44%) did so according to WHO recommendations. 100% of the "non-prescribers" were catholics. CONCLUSIONS Most doctors receive requests for the PCP and prescribe it on demand, though prescription varies with age, categories and, in particular, religious belief. Only a third prescribes according to WHO recommendations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intercepción poscoital hormonal: estudio sobre actitudes y prescripción de los médicos de atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Postcoital hormonal contraception: study on the attitudes and prescription of primary care physicians].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
