<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11213391</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallo Rolanía, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the appropriate technique for each case of urethral stricture, according to its length, depth, localization, etiology and age of the patient. METHODS 83 urethroplasties for urethral stricture performed from 1992-1998 were reviewed. The strictures involved different levels of the urethra. The techniques utilized were analyzed (substitution urethroplasty with pedicle skin graft and free grafts using buccal mucosa and extragenital skin, excision and anastomotic repair, regeneration techniques with internal urethrotomy and placement of intraluminal prosthesis, and two-stage repair procedures). RESULTS The overall functional results were good in 93% of the cases (78 good, 5 poor), but the morphological results demonstrated by the radiological findings were not as good in 24% of the cases, which corresponded to those that had received preputial pedicle grafts and buccal mucosa free grafts. CONCLUSION Using the appropriate urethroplasty technique is essential to achieve good functional results. The substitution techniques require well-vascularized grafts and/or recipient sites. The foregoing must be taken into account in the selection of the appropriate graft and deciding on the stricture length and localization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de 83 uretroplastias por estenosis uretral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of 83 urethroplasties for urethral stenosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
