<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11247290</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alvarez Calatayud, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín de Argila, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boixeda, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bermejo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gisbert, J P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Defarges, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To study the influence of Helicobacter pylori eradication on basal gastrin and pepsinogen I and II levels in patients with gastric ulcer over a 1-year follow-up period, and to assess the usefulness of these values in confirming H. pylori eradication after treatment. METHODS Fifty-six patients with gastric ulcer and H. pylori infection were prospectively studied. At the beginning of the study, endoscopy with biopsies for histologic examination and urease testing was carried out, as were 13C-urea breath test and blood samples for determination of gastrin and pepsinogen I and II values by radioimmunoassay and serology. Histologic study, 13C-urea breath test and laboratory determinations were repeated at months 1, 6 and 12 after completion of eradication treatment. RESULTS H. pylori infection was eradicated in 82.1% of patients. In patients with successful H. pylori eradication, the initial mean gastrin value was 75.5 +/- 39.1 pg/ml, while at 1 month after treatment this value decreased to 49.2 +/- 21 pg/ml (p &lt; 0.0001). No further reductions were noted. Initial pepsinogen I and II values were 104 +/- 58 and 15.8 +/- 10 ng/ml, respectively, whereas at month 1 after treatment these values were 77 +/- 42 and 7.3 +/- 4 ng/ml, respectively (p &lt; 0.0001) and were 72 +/- 41 and 6.7 +/- 3 ng/ml respectively at month 6 (p &lt; 0.01); no further variations were observed thereafter. The area under the ROC curve which reveals eradication through reductions in hormonal values was 0.70 for gastrin, 0.78 for pepsinogen I, 0.93 for pepsinogen II and 0.92 for the pepsinogen I/II ratio. At months 6 and 12 after treatment completion, differences in mean gastrin and pepsinogen I and II values between the patients with normal histologic findings and those with chronic gastritis were significant (p &lt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS a) H. pylori eradication is associated with an early fall in basal gastrin values and a progressive decrease in basal pepsinogen I and II values. b) In patients with gastric ulcer, determination of the decrease in basal pepsinogen II levels is a useful and early non-invasive method for confirming eradication. c) Determination of gastrin and pepsinogen I and II values may be useful for assessing improvement in gastritis 6 months after treatment completion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones basales de gastrina y pepsinógeno I y II en la úlcera gástrica: influencia de la infección por Helicobacter pylori y utilidad en el control de la erradicación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Basal concentrations of gastrin and pepsinogen I and II in gastric ulcer: influence of Helicobacter pylori infection and usefulness in the control of the eradication].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
