<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11262264</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mateo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcorta, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estella Aguado, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toll, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) or Moschovitz' syndrome is rare and is even rarer in childhood. Clinically, it is characterized by microangiopathic hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, neurologic abnormalities, fever and renal dysfunction. The etiology is still unknown, although different factors such as large von Willebrand factor multimers and prostacyclin have been implicated. The acute form is more frequent, and in most cases the course is fulminant if treatment is not initiated. Laboratory data typically reveal hemolytic anemia, with schistocytes on the peripheral smear, diminished serum haptoglobin, and thrombocytopenia. MATERIAL AND METHODS We present the clinical cases of two children, aged 4 and 7 respectively, with TTP, but with different evolution and treatment. Evolution was favorable in both patients. The first child recovered spontaneously. In the second plasmapheresis was required and produced remission of all the symptomatology. Normality has been maintained for 36 and 24 months respectively, and the children have presented no clinico-biological alterations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anemia hemolítica microangiopática ytrombocitopenia. ¿Púrpuratrombótica trombocitopénica?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia and thrombocytopenia. Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
