<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11322035</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero Sanz, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Shum Funk, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>López García, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andrada Becerra, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carratalá Torregrosa, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Hidalgo, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) is a rare, serious, chronic disease whose etiology is unknown and which affects young women almost exclusively. It produces typical clinical and radiological characteristics. Diagnosis is confirmed on finding histological evidence of irregular proliferation of the smooth muscle cells of the lungs. Treatment is not usually effective and there is rapid worsening of the pulmonary function leading to serious respiratory failure which often results in the patients death. We present two cases of LAM in women, one of whom was 33 and the other 38. In the first case the patient had all the pulmonary findings described in the literature, while the second also had bilateral renal angiomyolipomas. We discuss the histological, radiological and clinical characteristics and evolution of both cases, as well as the treatment given. We also review the literature. It is concluded that LAM should be suspected in young women who have dyspnea, cough and/or hemoptysis and an interstitial radiological pattern, especially when associated with a pleural effusion or pneumothorax.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfangioleiomiomatosis pulmonar. Descripción y evolución de dos casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary lymphangioleiomyomatosis. Description and course of 2 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
