<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11338975</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-9402</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Matinella, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pino, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Six lots of 18 B. glabrata from: La Victoria, Turmero, Cagua in Aragua state; Caserío El 25 in Carabobo state, Chabasquén in Portuguesa state and Humocaro Bajo in Lara state, were experimentally infected with miracidia of SM, C5 and C6 strains of Schistosoma mansoni (18 snails/Schistosoma mansoni strain). The averages of the intramolluscal period (IMP) obtained for the S. mansoni strains were very similar and comprised between 35.4 and 36.1 days. No significative statistical differences in the IMP were found according to the S. mansoni strain and the size of snails: &lt; 7 mm and &gt; 7 mm. However, significative statistical differences in the IMP were found, in relation to the B. glabrata strain and between the snails classified in two groups according to the S. mansoni dose (5 miracidia/snail and 10 miracidia/snail). The higher percentages of infection (PI) were found for the following parasite-snail combinations: C6-Cas. El 25 (80.7%), SM-La Victoria (73.1%) and C5-Cagua (62%). No significative statistical differences were found for the PI a) between the snail classified in two groups according to the size (&lt; 7 mm and &gt; 7 mm), b) in relation to the miracidium dosification (5 and 10 miracidia/snail and c) in accord to the S. mansoni strain. However, significative statistical differences were found for the PI obtained with different strains of the snail.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Jul-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación hospedador--parásito entre tres cepas de Schistosoma mansoni y seis cepas de Biomphalaria glabrata de áreas endémicas y no endémicas venezolanas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Host parasite relationship among 3 Schistosoma mansoni and 6 Biomphalaria glabrata strains from epidemic and no epidemic Venezuelan areas is studied].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin chileno de parasitologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
