<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11339115</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Migliazza, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gámez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrauri, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Santamaría, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murcia, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frauca, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Vicente, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarriá, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jara, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quijano, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nuño, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tovar, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Polanco, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prieto, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED We present the first case of intestinal transplant (IT) performed in Spacin. CASE REPORT 28 months old boy with secretory diarrhea since the first month of life, diagnosed of microvillous inclusion disease (MID). He is on total parenteral nutrition (TPN) and had suffered of multiple episodes of catheter related sepsis with lost of standard venous access. An isolated small bowel transplant from a cadaveric donor was performed at the age of 3 years. The native ileocaecal valve and colon were not removed. RESULTS Enteral feeding was started in the 2nd. week after the IT. On the 25th day he was off TPN. Since the 77th day, he eats regular foods by mouth. At the 6th month post IT the ileostomy was closed. Among the complications, he suffered a rotavirus infection on the 38th post IT day and an episode of mild rejection responsive to methil-prednisolone bolus. CONCLUSIONS The IT is a therapeutic option that can be already offered with possibilities of success in our country. Although the colonic enterocytes express MVD, the recipient ileocaecal valve and colon can be preserved.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante intestinal. Primera experiencia en España.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intestinal transplantation. First experience in Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
