<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11373705</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Abelenda Pose, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrer Jaureguizar, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Ulla De Irazazábal, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco Rivera, M C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To define the findings of an indocyanine green angiographic study of angioid streaks and compare them with the ophthalmoscopic and fluorescein angiographic findings. PATIENTS AND METHODS Twelve eyes of six patients with bilateral angioid streaks were examined by ophthalmoscopy, fluorescein angiography, and indocyanine green angiography. RESULTS In the ophthalmoscopy, the streak colors ranged from brown in the early phases to orange in severe stages. The streaks already presented a hyperfluorescent pattern from the arterial phases in all of the eyes with the fluorescein angiography. Using the indocyanine green angiography filling of the choroidal veins, a hyperfluorescent pattern was observed in eight eyes with severe lesional changes and a hypofluorescent pattern in four eyes with an early stage of the disease. The angioid streaks were more clearly visualized by indocyanine green angiography. CONCLUSION The indocyanine green angiography contributes to the diagnosis of angioid streaks. The indocyanine patterns seems to be correlated with the ophthalmoscopic features and degree of evolution of the disease. The indocyanine green angiography allows for the early detection of angioid streaks and diagnosis in young patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angiografía verde indocianina en las estrías angioides.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Indocyanine green angiography in angioid streaks].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
