<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11413994</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sotomayor, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Naveas, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sotomayor, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Not all the techniques for the correct use of metered dose inhalers are used by patients and health care professionals. AIM To assess the techniques and errors in the use of metered dose inhalers among patients and health care professionals. MATERIAL AND METHODS Evaluation of the inhaling technique, using a validated questionnaire, used by 68 patients, 30 physicians and 30 nurses working in a hospital at Concepción, Chile. RESULTS The "closed mouth" technique is used by 84% of patients, 40% of physicians and 73% of nurses. The rest uses the "open mouth" technique. The aerochamber is used by 12% of patients, 37% of physicians and 27% of nurses. The most frequent inhaling errors detected were not shaking the inhaler (26% of patients, 30% of physicians and 7% of nurses), not applying the puff at the start of inspiration (28% of patients, 7% of physicians and 13% of nurses), and not maintaining an apnea after the inhalation (41% of patients, 7% of physicians and 10% of nurses). Sixty percent of patients, 67% of physicians and 40% of nurses have not received instructions about the inhaler use. CONCLUSIONS There is a high frequency of errors in the use of inhalers and most users have not been trained in its use.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las técnicas y errores en el uso de los inhaladores de dosis medida en el paciente adulto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of techniques and errors in the use of metered dose inhalers in the adult patient].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
