<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11413990</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Méricq, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cassorla, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinoza, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Carvallo, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iñiguez, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar, T E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Circulating concentrations of the high affinity growth hormone binding protein (GHBP) may be a marker of GH receptor density as well as GH sensitivity. GOAL To determine values of GHBP for a normal Chilean pediatric population. METHODS We determined GHBP levels in 73 males and 73 females between 4 to 15.5 years and 4 to 16.8 years respectively, divided in 7 groups according to age and puberal status. RESULTS The population was normally distributed in weight, height and body mass index (BMI). GHBP activity increased up to Tanner IV in males and Tanner III in females, and decreased slightly thereafter in Tanner V and IV respectively. There was a significant difference between GHBP levels of preschool children and those found in Tanner II to V in both sexes (p &lt; 0.05). In addition, we found a positive correlation between GHBP vs weight, height and BMI (p &lt; 0.001) in males and females. CONCLUSION The availability of this methodology allows us to establish the normative value of GHBP in our population and provides useful information to interpret GH circulating levels in children with growth disorders.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia para proteína transportadora de hormona de crecimiento en una población pediátrica normal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reference values of growth hormone binding protein (GHBP) for a normal pediatric population].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
