<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11424059</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zambran-Toledo, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Speech therapy treatment on patients who have a neurogenically induced dysphagia begins at hospital, in the intensive rehabilitation units. This study shows some of the difficulties found dealing with and orienting the family and the patient from a therapy point of view, mainly during his return to home surroundings. DEVELOPMENT To better understand the dysphagic situation, normal swallowing steps (oral, pharyngeal and esophageal) steps have been described. These were then related to the dysphagic problems, with their evaluation, classification and characteristics. Under dysphagia rehabilitation the therapeutic guidance should be lead by the appropriate nutritional demands, and prevent aspirations. Some of the therapeutic procedures for treating and controlling neurogenic dysphagia have been described (head posture control, tactile and thermal stimuli, etc.). The author questions the difficulties found controlling orientation and maintaining conduct outside the hospital environment, principally with patients at risk from aspirations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Congresses</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 May 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El mantenimiento de las orientaciones logopédicas en el paciente con disfagia orofaríngea de origen neurogénico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Maintenance of logopedic orientation in a patient with oropharyngeal dysphagia of neurogenic origin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
