<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11459535</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Sesma, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zabalza Ollo, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The care provided by nurses to potential organ donors is essential to ensure the optimal utilization of transplant organs. With the aim of providing a reasoned description of such care, this article outlines the physiopathological changes produced in donors after brain death and identifies the nursing care required by these changes until the donor is taken to the operating room. The method used was a literature review. This study is structured according to the various physiological changes in the following sections: nursing care in the maintenance of (i) cardiovascular function, (ii) respiratory function, (ii) thermoregulation, (iv) hydroelectrolytic balance and endocrine-metabolic function, (v) renal function, (vi) corneas, (vii) prevention of infection, and (viii) other nursing care. The aim of all nursing care acts is to maintain the donor in optimum conditions in order to conserve the functioning of the maximum number of organs and thus ensure their successful transplantation. Finally, Annex I of the Royal Decree of December 30, 1999 is reproduced. This decree presents the protocols for the diagnosis and certification of death for organ extraction from donors in irreversible coma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados de enfermería en el mantenimiento del donante potencial de órganos en muerte encefálica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Nursing care in the maintenance of potential donors in brain death].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
