<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11476020</identifier>
<setSpec>1020-4989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castillo Lizardo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerrero-Romero, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Morán, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine, for the teaching of basic health concepts to school-age children, the effectiveness of an educational strategy based on traditional children's games. METHODS Intervention study carried out in the city of Durango, Mexico, in June 2000 with 300 children from 9 to 11 years old. The children were randomly divided into two groups. The children in Group A used a modified version of a Mexican popular game called Serpientes y Escaleras (Snakes and Ladders) that included messages on basic health concepts; the children in Group B made up the control group and did not play the modified game. RESULTS At baseline there were no significant differences between the two groups in terms of age, grade level, or their scores on a knowledge test of basic health concepts. After the educational intervention, the health concepts test scores, out of a maximum possible of 10, were 9.3 +/- 0.8 for Group A and 7.5 +/- 1.1 for Group B (P &lt; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS Using games that include health and hygiene messages can be an alternative for teaching basic health concepts.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El juego como alternativa para la enseñanza de conceptos básicos de salud.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Games as an alternative for teaching basic health concepts].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
