<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11475679</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García de Lorenzo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casimiro, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Usán, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate nutritional status and blood glucose level according to type of diet followed by elderly (&gt; 65 years old) institutionalised patients with non insulin dependent diabetes mellitus (NIDDM). METHODS A data collection questionnaire was administered to the staff of 80 Spanish geriatric facilities participating in this one-day cross-sectional study. Data collected included: age, gender, history of previous glucose control, type of antidiabetic treatment, body mass index (BMI), nutritional risk index (NRI), type of diet with patient's preference, nutritional status evaluation and biochemical parameters. RESULTS Data from a total of 486 institutionalised elderly people (66.5% female) were collected with a mean +/- SD age of 80.8 +/- 7.5. Had a diabetic diet 93.3% of patients with no gender differences 55.7% were on oral antidiabetic treatment (53.9% females and 58.9% males, ns) and 24.7% on insulin therapy (24.5% females and 26.4% males, ns). Physical activity was presented in 86% of people with no gender differences. Exercise was practiced by people younger, 78.8 +/- 7.9 years, versus walking, 80.4 +/- 7.6 years or resting 82.1 +/- 7.3 years, p &lt; 0.05. Both nutritional indexes, BMI and NRI, were equivalent in men and in women; 28.5 +/- 10.7 vs 28.1 +/- 7.6 and 103.5 +/- 12.9 vs 104.1 +/- 11.4, respectively. History glucose control was good in 68.8% of the sample with a trend towards significance between sexes (62.7% males, 71.7% females, p = 0.07) and significant differences according to type of diet; 70.7% diabetic versus 37.0% free diet, p = 0.0006). Eating behaviors (appetite and meal completeness) were similar in both males and females and in diabetic or free diet groups. Also, no differences were observed in patient preferences about diet according to type of diet (71% of diabetic patients always or almost always liked their food versus 82% of free diet patients) and either nutritional status (9.3% vs 15.6% in status I, 10.9% vs 12.5% in level II and 79.9% vs 71.9% in status III, respectively). The NRI, cholesterol, albumin and triglyceride levels were significantly higher in patients with high fat rate supplemented dietary intake than other supplemented diets. CONCLUSIONS A high proportion of patients on a diabetic diet was observed in this study with no gender differences. Elderly NIDDM institutionalised patients on a diabetic diet showed a greater good history glucose control than patients on a free diet. Diabetic diet preference by these subjects is similar than free diet. A better nutritional risk control was shown in patients with high fat rate supplemented diet.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional y metabólico y valoración dietética en pacientes ancianos, institucionalizados, con diabetes mellitus no insulino dependiente (DMNID).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Nutritional and metabolic status and dietetic evaluation in institutionalized elderly patients with non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
