<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11494714</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>pascual del Pobil Moreno, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Gómez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campoy Martínez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina López, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales López, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Congregado Ruiz, C B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To present the results of a descriptive analysis of 267 surgically treated renal tumors. METHODS From January 1986 to October 1999, 267 patients (153 males and 114 females) with renal tumor were treated in our department. All data were introduced into the Access data base program and analyzed using the SPSS software. Descriptive analysis was performed and life expectancy was calculated with the Kaplan-Meier survival curve. Mean follow-up was 42.72 months. RESULTS 56.4% were in the right and 43.6% were in the left kidney. 41.2% of the cases were incidentally discovered. In the symptomatic patients, the most common presenting feature was hematuria (51.8%). Radical nephrectomy was performed in 94.2%, partial in 3.1% and tumor resection in 2.7%. The lumbar approach was used in 75.5% of the cases. In regard to the histology, 88.7% were carcinomas. Clear cell was the most frequent cell type (91.5%). By grade, 55.8% were GI, 32.9% GII and 11.3% were GIII. By stage (according to the 1992 TNM classification), 64.3% were stage I, 15.4% stage II, 17% stage III and 3.3% stage IV. 80.5% showed no vascular involvement. The 5-year overall survival was 71.93% (mean 114 months; median 167 months). Currently, 76% of the patients are alive. CONCLUSIONS Distribution by sex in our series was different to that reported in most of the studies. The tumor was incidentally discovered in a high proportion of the cases. The lumbar access was the most widely used surgical approach. The overall survival is similar to that reported by other groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer renal: análisis descriptivo de una serie de 267 casos intervenidos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Renal cancer: descriptive analysis of a series of 267 intervened cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
