<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11496556</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hinojosa Mena-Bernal, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zurro Muñoz, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Sarmiento, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ergueta Martín, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Martínez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zurro Hernández, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determinate the influence of the acarbosa and microalbuminuria on metabolic parameters in patients diabetics type 2. RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS We are studied 92 patients with diabetes type 2, treated with Acarbose alone or with insuline or oral anti-diabetics We are determined the values of HbA1c, total cholesterol, HDL, LDL, triglycerides and microalbuminuria, before and after or the treatment with acarbose. RESULTS The patients presented globally a statistically significant improvement in the levels of Hb A1 c, triglycerides and microalbuminuria. In the group treatise with 300 mg/day of acarbose it was observed a significant decrease of the values of Hb A1c and triglycerides independently of the associated treatment. In the group treated with 150 mg/day the improvement only it was statistically significant for the levels of Hb A1c. CONCLUSIONS The treatment with acarbose produces an improvement in the levels of Hb A1c independently of the administered dose and of the triglycerides in patients treated with 300 mg/day without relation to associated treatments. Therefore, he acarbose win be considered an effective medication to improve the metabolic control to prevent the cardiovascular risk in those patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modificación de los parámetros metabólicos y microalbuminuria en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 tratados con acarbosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Changes in metabolic parameters and microalbuminuria in patients with type 2 diabetes treated with acarbose].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
