<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11563168</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rocha, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarto, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Capmany, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pasqualini, R S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quintans, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Donaldson, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Geller, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acquired and inherited thrombophilia are associated with recurrent pregnancy loss (RPL). Antithrombotic therapy could restore hemostatic balance and improve early placentation and gestational outcome. We evaluated the efficacy of enoxaparin adapted to the fertility program for prevention of pregnancy loss in 35 women (W) with early RPL and thrombophilia. Previous to the diagnosis of thrombophilia, they had had a total of 105 gestations of which 89 (85%) ended in early pregnancy loss. After diagnosis of thrombophilia, 35 subsequent pregnancies were treated with enoxaparin. In 5 cases assisted reproductive techniques were necessary to achieve pregnancy due to couple infertility. In 17 W who had had at least one preclinical pregnancy loss, enoxaparin (20 mg/d/s.c.) was started previous to conception and adapted to the fertility program. All the women continued with the gestational regime. Eighteen W with only clinical pregnancy loss started enoxaparin (20 mg twice per day s.c.) after biochemical pregnancy diagnosis. During gestations heparin dose was adjusted with anti Xa test, maintaining a range between 0.3 at 0.6 u/ml. With antithrombotic therapy, 30/35 (85%) of the pregnancies ended in live birth versus 16/105 (15%) of the pregnancies without treatment (p &lt; 0.001). These results suggest that enoxaparin adapted to the fertility program can be effective in the prevention of preclinical and clinical abortion in women with thrombophilia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con enoxaparina adaptado a los programas de fertilidad en mujeres con aborto recurrente y trombofilia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment with enoxaparin adapted to the fertility programs in women with recurrent abortion and thrombophilia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
