<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11565360</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Plaza Hernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montoya Guerrero, A S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes Cisneros, F A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Farell Campa, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ledesma Velasco, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomo Villada, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abundes Velazco, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We reviewed our work and evaluated clinical and angiographic results, as well as the follow up of young adult patients &lt; 40 years that were subject to percutaneous trans-clinical coronary angioplasty (PTCA) with an endovascular prostheses (stent). From January 1995 to December 1999, 896 PCTA's performed using stents in 770 patients. Only one selected group of 30 patients (with 32 procedures, and an average of 1.06 stents per patients. Patients age ranged from 21 to 39 years old with an average of 32.8 + 52, 2, 29 (96%) were male and only one woman (3.3%). Nine patients (30%) had a severe angina, class III Braunwald and 21 (70%) had a previous history of myocardial infarcts. The average percent of arterial obstruction was 90.88 +/- 5.22 and the expulsion fraction. (EF) had a percent of 46.8 +/- 4.3 with ranges of 35 to 60%. Immediate angiographic success was 93.75% in only two patients (6.25%) with a 100% occlusion, and more than twelve weeks. There was no mortality, nor infarct, and no patient was sent to an urgent revascularization surgery. Clinical follow up lasted 50 weeks in all patients with the effort test using the electric Bruce type and for nuclear medicine. Only in 3 patients EF was reported, and tHalium with a slight septal ischemia. Angiographic control was included in 27 (90% patients between the 4th and 6th month. PTA with stent is a successful angiographic and clinical procedure in young adults &lt; 40 years old; it constitutes a complete and efficient therapeutical revascularization procedure, and is an excellent option before undertaking an aortocoronary revascularization surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento clínico y angiográfico en adultos jóvenes post ACTP más stents intracoronarios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical and angiographic follow-up of young adults after PTCA plus intracoronary stents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
