<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11575244</identifier>
<setSpec>1020-4989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yépez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barreto, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santander, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abad-Franch, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To develop, apply, and evaluate an educational model for the primary prevention of sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) and acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) that was based on the sexual knowledge, attitudes, and practices (KAPs) of adolescents and on their perceptions and behaviors in this area, with the ultimate goal of helping develop educational tools to prevent infection with STDs and the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). METHODS An STD/HIV/AIDS primary prevention model was applied with adolescent schoolchildren (12 to 15 years old) in the canton of Santo Domingo de los Colorados, Ecuador. Two groups with similar characteristics were formed: the experimental group, with 358 students, and the control group, with 288 students. Schools were selected according to inclusion criteria, and adolescents at each school were chosen at random. A discussion guide was applied with 16 focus groups, and the resulting information was used to prepare a KAP survey. After being validated, the KAP survey was applied to the experimental group and to the control group. A prevention education program geared to students and teachers was implemented with the experimental group. Eight months later a second KAP survey was done with the experimental group and the control group. The differences in KAPs before and after the intervention were evaluated using the chi-square test. RESULTS There were no statistically significant differences between the two groups before the intervention, but afterwards the differences were statistically significant (P = 0.012), with an increase in the knowledge of sexuality and STDs/AIDS in the experimental group, even though the long-term behavior changes have not been evaluated. CONCLUSIONS This study validated a multifactorial STD/AIDS prevention model adapted to the reality of adolescents, and it suggests the possibility of extrapolating this experience more broadly to contexts similar to those of this Ecuador population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un modelo de prevención primaria de las enfermedades de transmisión sexual y del VIH/sida en adolescentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A model of primary prevention of sexually transmitted diseases and HIV/AIDS in adolescents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
