<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11588810</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz-Sánchez, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Peón, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendoza-González, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tay-Zavala, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Vega, J T</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to determine the presence of unspecific vaginosis and their causes, 700 vaginal smears were obtained from patients assisting to the Clinical Laboratory of the Familiar Medicine Unit No. 28 "Gabriel Mancera" of the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, during 6 months. The patients age was from 18 to 55 years old. To establish the infectious etiology of these pathologies the vaginal smears were observed freshly and stained by Gram's method. Specific test for differentiate Gardnerella vaginalis and Candida albicans were also performed. From 700 vaginal smears, 160 were positive to Candida albicans (22.86%); 150 to Gardnerella vaginalis (21.43%); and 14 to Trichomonas vaginalis (2%). The most frequent association were Candida albicans with Gardnerella vaginalis in 14 women, who 12 had a reduced number of pregnancy, and 7 had only one pregnancy (58.3%). The age groups most affected were between 18 and 35 years old, corresponding to the reproductive stage of the woman. Gardnerella vaginalis predominated in the 30-35 years old group.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de vaginosis producida por Gardnerella vaginalis y su asociación con otros patógenos causantes de infección genital en la mujer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Frequency of Gardnerella vaginalis vaginosis and its association with other pathogens causing genital infections in the female].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
