<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11674948</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Millán Vázquez, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Cid, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosado Muñoz, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuente Juárez, A I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Simón García, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blesa Malpica, A L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barroso Díaz, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing workloads form the basis for the appropriate provision of nursing personnel. In this study we used the nine equivalents of nursing manpower use score (NEMS) to determine and evaluate the use of nursing staff in our unit. In the first phase we determined the actual workload in the various shifts and diagnostic areas. Statistically significant differences were found among diagnostic areas but not among shifts. Then, to compare our situation with that of other European intensive care units (ICUs), dynamic parameters of the management and efficiency of the use of nursing staff were analyzed following the multicentric EURICUS-I study, which was performed over 4 months in 100 ICUs in 12 European countries. For the comparison, indexes such as the work utilization ratio (WUR), the level of care planned (LOC p) and the level of care operative (LOC op) were used. The results obtained reveal that although our workload is equivalent to the European average, efficiency is greater. Thus, the situation in our unit differs from the downward trend of the data obtained in other European countries.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del uso de los recursos humanos enfermeros en una unidad de cuidados intensivos polivalente. Situación con el resto de UCIs europeas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of the use of nursing personnel in a general intensive care unit. Situation in other european ICUs].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
