<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11674982</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echevarría, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hachero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alamo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caba, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Merino, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the influence that bispectral index (BIS) monitoring of hypnosis might have on need for analgesia during surgery under total intravenous anesthesia provided by bolus administration of fentanyl. PATIENTS AND METHOD Prospective, randomized and partially double-blind study of 40 patients undergoing major gynecological surgery under total intravenous anesthesia with propofol and fentanyl. In the BIS group (n = 20) propofol administration was adjusted to maintain BIS between 40 and 60. In the control group (n = 20) standard doses were given: 10 mg/kg-1/h-1 after anesthetic induction and for 5 minutes, 8 mg/kg-1/h-1 over the next 5 minutes and 6 mg/kg-1/h-1 throughout the rest of the operation. All patients received intravenous bolus administration of 150 or 75 microg of fentanyl to maintain analgesia whenever systolic blood pressure and heart rate increased 20% over baseline. We compared propofol and fentanyl requirements, intraoperative changes in BIS, and awakening from anesthesia. RESULTS Patient and surgical characteristics were similar in both groups. BIS monitoring allowed propofol administration to be decreased a mean 24% during maintenance of anesthesia, and this in turn was associated with a significant increase in mean dose of fentanyl (415 microg versus 253 microg in the BIS and control groups, respectively; p = 0.01). Mean values of BIS were higher in the BIS group (46.4 versus 42.2; p = 0.04) and patients in the BIS group awoke sooner (in 7.7 min versus 11.1 min; p = 0.01) and tended to report less pain upon arrival at the postanesthetic recovery room, although the difference was not statistically significant. CONCLUSIONS BIS monitoring of depth of hypnosis can influence requirements for fentanyl during total intravenous anesthesia by bolus dosing for maintenance of analgesia. This is probably due to changes in the administration of propofol made possible by BIS monitoring.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la monitorización BIS en los requerimientos de fentanilo durante la anestesia intravenosa total en cirugía mayor ginecológica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of bispectral index monitoring on fentanyl requirements during total intravenous anesthesia for major gynecological surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
