<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11676908</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moreno Madrid, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Fernández, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Forte, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Diego Fernández, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last few years, granulocyte colony stimulating factors (G-CSF), or hematopoietic growth factors, have created new possibilities for treating severe neutropenias, with high clinical efficacy and minimal adverse effects. Moreover, due to genetic recombinant techniques, the therapeutic use of these glycoproteins is increasing. We report the case of a 4-year-old girl who was diagnosed with glycogenosis IB at the age of 7 months. From the age of 2 years, she presented severe established neutropenia secondary to the main disease. Subcutaneus G-CSF therapy was started. The patient has shown no serious infections, has maintained normal growth and development, and has not required hospitalization. Adverse effects have been minimal. The therapeutic efficacy demonstrated by this case justifies the continuous use of G-CSF, although the lack of long-term perspectives should not be forgotten.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento continuo con factores estimulantes de colonias (G-CSF) de la neutropenia asociada a la glucogenosis tipo Ib.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continuous treatment with colony stimulating factors (G-CSF) for neutropenia associated with type Ib glycogenosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
