<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11685678</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Del Nozal, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marcos, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manzanas, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE Several antioxidant substances have been included in intraocular solutions for vitrectomy in order to reduce oxidative stress. The objective of this work is to evaluate the antioxidant effect of BBS plus(R) (with oxidized glutathione) by means of determining scores of Malondialdehyde (MDA) in retinal tissue at different post vitrectomy time-periods. MATERIAL AND METHODS Thirty pigmented rabbits distributed in three groups (n=10). Group I: Control (no surgery); group II: Vitrectomy adding BSS plus(R), scoring of malondialdehyde at 3 hours post surgery; group III: Vitrectomy adding BBS plus(R), analysis of malondialdehide at 48 hours after vitrectomy. Retinal samples were used to determine the score of malondialdehyde using ion-pairing high performance liquid chromatography. Statistical analysis was performed using ANOVA-Scheffé test (p&lt;0.05). RESULTS Scores of free MDA (microgram of retinal tissue) were: group I (n=8): 1.080 S.D. 0.389 microgram group II (n=8): 1.273 S.D. 0.710 microgram and group III (n=10): 0.639 S.D. 0.374 microgram. CONCLUSIONS BSS plus(R) showed antioxidant effects in retinal tissue which were observed better at a later rather than early stage after a vitrectomy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inhibición de la lipoperoxidación retiniana durante la vitrectomía. Efecto de la solución de irrigación intraocular BSS plus.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inhibition of lipid peroxidation in retinal tissue during vitrectomy. Effect of intraocular irrigating solution BSS plus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
