<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11714453</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crespo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Lara, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>León, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rejas, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villasante, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Dyspepsia affects about 25 % of the population and may cause an important decrease in quality of life. The aim of this work was to perform a Spanish validation and adaptation of the questionnaire DRHS (Dyspepsia Related Health Scale), a tool that assesses dyspepsia-related quality of life. PATIENTS AND METHOD The study was carried out in 234 subjects, 163 with symptoms of dyspepsia and 71 health volunteers. Two rheumatologists, 2 general practitioners, 1 gastroenterologist, 1 clinical pharmacologist, 1 pharmacoepidemiologist and 1 psychologist were involved in the work. The process of adaptation and validation included translation and re-translation, pilot study in 16 patients, dimensionality, reliability and validity (of content, of construct, convergent, predictive and discriminative). RESULTS The mean age was 49.1 years (SD: 18) and 60.7 % were females. The between-judges agreement rate of Hambleton and Rovinelli, which evaluates the content validity, was lower than 0.41. The construct validity assessed by the factorial analysis of responses showed that each subscale may be considered unidimensional in both health volunteers and individuals with dyspepsia. Reliability was satisfactory (Cronbach's alpha = 0.92) and stability of measures (test-retest) was excellent with a correlation coefficient of 0.95. The convergent validity, assessed by means of the EuroQoL, was only moderate with a correlation coefficient of 0.54 (p &lt; 0.001). The predictive validity, assessed by administering the questionnaire 12 days after treating dyspepsia, showed a correlation coefficient of 0.47 between the two measures (p &lt; 0.001). There was also a relationship between scores variation and outcome. CONCLUSIONS The Spanish version of the DRHS, so-called QoL-PEI (questionnaire of quality of life related with problems of stomach and intestine), displays good metric properties and is able to predict the evolution of dyspepsia. The results of this study show that this tool is essentially unidimensional, yet it can be used on a multidimensional form to perform a differentiated assessment of each evaluated case.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Nov 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionario sobre calidad de vida asociada a dispepsia. Adaptación española y validación del cuestionario Dyspepsia Related Health Scale.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dyspepsia-related quality of life. Spanish adaptation and validation of the questionnaire Dyspepsia-Related Health Scale].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
