<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11727243</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramos-Estébanez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valle, H A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Hérnandez, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz-Arrondo, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Although an increasing quantity of information concerning risk factors for stroke have been developed lately, the relationship between alcohol consumption and cerebral ischemic infarction, unlike at coronary sites, remains unclear. This review highlights the main pathogenic mechanisms of alcohol in the development of ischemic stroke, as it intends to be an update of this possible association. DEVELOPMENT A critical literature review has been performed regarding this association to study its pathogenic mechanisms and the possible confounding factors present in the current design of epidemiological reports. CONCLUSIONS There is an increasing evidence about the effect of light to moderate alcohol consumption and prevention of ischemic stroke. On the other hand it seems that heavy drinking, and particularly binge drinkers, are exposed to a higher risk for cardioembolic stroke. The growing incidence of acute heavy alcohol consumption highlights the necessity of considering a cardioembolic source when managing ischemic stroke, specially in young adults.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Sep 16-30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alcohol e ictus isquémico: asociación controvertida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Alcohol and stroke: a controversial association].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
