<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11727220</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sedó, M A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Examination of the special bilingual student (5% of the bilingual student population of the USA) permits us to use not only (1) the statistical reports of the population coefficients and percentages), (2) measurements of progress or performance (age in years or grades of progress at school) and (3) the neuropsychological dimensions of the brain (left and right, anterior and posterior, inferior and superior). DEVELOPMENT It is possible to put into parenthesis the statistical norms, either national, local, regional or even Hispanic national, given the great disparity seen in the results. At the present time the Hispanic population is made up mainly of young persons, recent immigrants with limited education. So it is logical that there are three major sources of error for students who do an exam in a foreign language when they are already disadvantaged and handicapped. Alternatively, we may pay attention to ipsative comparisons (of the same subject regarding different aspects of his behavior), which are almost free of any norm but comparison between themselves. CONCLUSIONS Here we list a series of comparisons connected with concrete and abstract conduct, asynchrony between knowledge and operations, hand work (unilateral and bilateral), linguistic and academic performance, in one language or the other. The comparisons observed help us to understand, in a new, relevant manner, the cognitive and academic function of the child who is handicapped, disadvantaged and bilingual . It also allows us to describe the basic dimensions of his cognitive and academic progress.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Sep 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Siete claves ipsativas para la comprensión del estudiante 'hispano' urbano con discapacidades de aprendizaje en Estados Unidos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Seven ipsative keys to understanding the poor 'Hispanic' student in the USA].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
