<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11730616</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Muñoz Núñez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez Arias, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villanueva Pavón, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olcoz Goñi, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Gundín, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera Abian, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jorquera Plaza, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vivas Alegre, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez Carbajo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Morejón, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Linares Torres, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinel Díez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda Castañón, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To determine the current status of endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) and the effects of the introduction of magnetic resonance cholangiography (MRC) on ERCP and to evaluate the diagnostic yield of MRC since its introduction in obstructive biliary disease. MATERIAL AND METHODS We performed a retrospective analysis of the ERCP carried out between January 1998 and December 2000 and of the MRC performed for suspected obstructive biliary disease from May 1999 to December 2000. When both techniques were performed, the diagnostic yield of MRC was evaluated. RESULTS We performed 927 ERCP. A total of 45.3% of the patients were men. Mean age was 69.2 14.6 years. Treatment was performed on 688 occasions (77%), mainly sphincterotomy (69.9%) and placement of polyethylene (21.8%) or self-expanding (9.9%) prostheses. The number of ERCP performed each year was 261, 330 and 336 in 1998, 1999 and 2000, respectively; of these 76.6%, 80% and 76.9% were therapeutic. MRC was performed in 63 patients with suspected biliary disease. In 27 of 59 patients (45.8%) MRC was sufficient for diagnosis, avoiding the need for ERCP. In the 35 patients in whom both techniques (MRC and ERCP) were performed, the diagnostic yield of MRC compared with that of ERCP was: sensitivity 100%, specificity 50%, positive predictive value 87.1%, negative predictive value 100% and overall value 89%. The cases responsible for the low specificity (all due to choledocholithiases) were analyzed and a significant time lapse was found between the performance of MRC and ERCP (range: 7-35 days) during which choledocholithiasis probably resolved spontaneously. CONCLUSIONS a) Contrary to what could be expected, the number of ERCP seems to be increasing with a high percentage of endoscopic treatment; b) Because of its diagnostic sensitivity, MRC is the ideal technique for eliminating the need for diagnostic ERCP, thus allowing greater development of the therapeutic aspect of ERCP.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual de la CPRE. Cómo se refleja la introducción de la colangiorresonancia magnética?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Current status of endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography. What is the effect of the introduction of magnetic resonance cholangiography?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
