<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11730620</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garrido Serrano, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lepe Jiménez, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerrero Igea, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomo Gil, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hepatocellular carcinoma mainly affects patients with liver disease and rarely develops in healthy liver. Cirrhosis greatly increases the risk of developing this malignancy and consequently these patients are candidates for close follow-up and surveillance. The most commonly used screening programs are abdominal ultrasonography and serum alpha-fetoprotein determination. Without treatment, the prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma is poor and mortality continues to be significant even in patients with small tumors detected during follow-up. We present the case of a 71-year-old male patient with alcoholic cirrhosis. The patient was diagnosed during follow-up of a single hepatocellular carcinoma of 4 cm in diameter. Although he refused all treatment, evolution was favorable, serum alpha-fetoprotein levels returned to normal and ultrasonographic images compatible with hepatocellular carcinoma disappeared. Three years after diagnosis, the patient was completely asymptomatic.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regresión espontánea de carcinoma hepatocelular en paciente cirrótico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Spontaneous regression of hepatocellular carcinoma in a cirrhotic patient].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
