<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11784982</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Reiber, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dorta Contreras, A J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Díaz, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robinson Agramonte, M A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The intrathecal response of IgG, is the most frequent neuropathological sign in multiple sclerosis (MS) patients beside the detection of oligoclonal IgG bands in cerebrospinal fluid. At the same time the observation of an intrathecal antibody synthesis (antibody index&gt; 1.4) against neurotropic viruses like measles, rubella, varicella zoster or herpes simple shows a higher frequency in MS than any other chronic disease (MRZH reaction). We report the intrathecal, polyspecific and oligoclonal immune response in patients with definitive MS. PATIENTS AND METHODS CSF and serum were tested for Albumin, IgG, IgM and IgA by standard immunochemical nephelometry assay while virus specific antibodies in CSF and serum samples were evaluated by ELISA and calculated as antibody index. RESULTS Oligoclonal IgG by, isoelectric focusing was detectable in all patients. A differential pattern of combined antibody index against neurotropic virus was observed. The largest frequency of a single species in the oligoclonal immune response was for measles antibodies, while the antibody response was found as a combination with increased rubella antibody index and VZ antibody index, respectively. CONCLUSION Our results although preliminary for our country, enrich the criteria about that MRZH reaction provide a major neuroimmunological support to MS diagnosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Nov 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta inmune intracraneal oligoclonal y poliespecífica en la esclerosis múltiple.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intrathecal oligoclonal and polyspecific immune response in multiple sclerosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
