<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11789369</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Burgos Revilla, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saenz Garrido, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vallejo Herrador, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To review the indications and complications of the use of endourological catheters in the treatment of urinary lithiasis and choice of catheter based on its physical and hydrodynamic characteristics and biocompatibility. METHODS Data from our experimental and clinical studies, as well as those published in the literature are summarized. RESULTS Polyurethane, C-flex and Percuflex catheters have the highest retaining capacity, while the silicone, Urosoft and Wiruthan catheters have the lowest. The tensile strength of polyurethane and copolymers is superior to that of silicone. The friction coefficient, which varies within the same material, influences the facility of catheter insertion. The number and size of the side vents are essential to catheter hydrodynamic behavior. Silicone is the most biocompatible material, followed by Urosoft. The polyurethanes and C-flex catheters cause important urothelial hyperplasia and edema of the lamina propia. CONCLUSIONS The choice of endourological catheter should be individualized and based on the clinical indication. For prevention of obstruction from steinstrasse post-lithotripsy, a catheter with a high extraluminal flow and high retaining capacity is indicated to facilitate passage of stone fragments and to avoid catheter migration.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los catéteres endourológicos en el tratamiento de la litiasis urinaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Usefulness of endourologic catheters in the treatment of urinary lithiasis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
