<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11803778</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Bengoechea, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Lasierra, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romeo Extremar, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millán Serrano, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To communicate a technical modification of urethrocystopexy which consist in the suspension of the urethropelvic ligaments to the posterior pubic bone with using bone fixations inserted with the In-Fast system. MATERIAL AND METHODS Between August 2000 and January 2001, thirteen patients with an mean age of 56.1 years were operated with this technic. Using a transvaginal approach and after great opening of the endopelvic fascia we insert one fixation screw in each side of the symphisis pubic bone, later we give two or three stitches to the urethropelvic ligament with the polypropylene no. 1 suture that each screw have joined to their end. RESULTS The mean stay has been 5.1 days. The cystostomy has been remained for a mean of the 10.1 days. We didn't observe any complication neither intra nor postoperatives. With a mean follow-up of 5.3 months all the patients present a disappearance of their stress incontinence. CONCLUSIONS Lack of confirm with a larger following and more cases, the suspension of the urethropelvisc ligaments with screw fixations directly situated into the pubic bone per vaginal approach, has been a simple method, safe and highly comfortable for the patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uretrocistopexia con anclajes óseos: modificación técnica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Urethrocystopexy with bone anchors: technical modification].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
