<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11834192</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Durán, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Durán, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chacón, J R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To evaluate the antipsychotic efficacy of olanzapine (OLZ) in patients with Parkinson's disease (PD) and drug-induced psychosis (DIP) and its repercussion on the motor function. METHODS Ten patients (5 women and 5 men) diagnosed of PD and DIP, aged 67 years (range: 50-81), with PD duration of 11.1 years (range: 6-23), treated chronically with levodopa per day, received a dose of 2.5 or 5.0 mg OLZ daily. Data concerning improvement of psychosis and worsening of motor function was based on Positive And Negative Symptoms Scale (PANSS) and Unified Parkinsons Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) motor. RESULTS Psychotic symptoms were improved in all patients. In most of them the improvement was almost total. Seven patients increased levodopa dose on OLZ, but significant worsening of motor function was reported just in one patient. None of the patients had agranulocytosis in the blood monitoring. Two patients presented weight gain. Seven patients improved their cognitive status. CONCLUSIONS We conclude that OLZ at the doses studied may have efficacy for DIP which appears in PD and does not induce worsening of motor function in most of the patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la olanzapina en la psicosis inducida por levodopa en pacientes parkinsonianos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Usefulness of olanzapine in the levodopa-induced psychosis in patients with Parkinson's disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
