<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11844438</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Maimo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soro, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de La Peña, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Agustí, A G N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Togores, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bosch, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abad, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Lung function has been shown to deteriorate after laparoscopic cholecystectomy (LC). The present study evaluated 1) the rate of recovery after LC, and 2) the pathogenic role of postoperative pain in functional deterioration. DESIGN Lung function was measured 24 hours before LC, upon hospital discharge (48-72 h after LC), and 10 days later. All patients received metamizol after LC until discharge (2 g every 6 h i.v.). Half the patients (analgesia group) received tramadol (150 mg i.m.) 30 minutes before lung function testing on the day of hospital discharge. The remaining patients constituted the control group. PATIENTS Twenty healthy subjects (53 4 years old) undergoing LC for gall bladder removal. All signed informed consent forms. Measures and outcomes: Patient characteristics and preoperative lung function results were similar in both groups. LC duration and postoperative course were also similar in both groups. All were discharged without complications within 72 hours after LC. Lung function upon discharge (FVC, FEV1, TLC, PaO2 and AaPO2) had deteriorated in both groups (p&lt;0.001). Deterioration was less marked in the analgesia group (p &lt; 0.05). Ten days later, lung function had normalized for all subjects. CONCLUSIONS These results indicate that after LC, 1) lung function is still abnormal when the patient is discharged from hospital, 2) lung function has fully recovered within 10 days, and 3) postoperative pain contributes significantly to temporary deterioration in lung function.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recuperación de la función pulmonar tras colecistectomía laparoscópica: papel del dolor postoperatorio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Recovery of lung function after laparoscopic cholecystectomy: the role of postoperative pain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
