<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11893287</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Páez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nieto, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguayo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Atriano, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robles-García, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Hopelessness, anhedonia and automatic thoughts have all been related to major depression and depressive symptoms. Few research has been done on these constructs in children, specially together. AIM The aim of this study was to translate into Spanish and validate the hopelessness scale for children, the pleasure scale for children, the automatic thoughts scale and the Kovak's child depression inventory, and then to relate the cognitive constructs to depressive symptoms in a sample of normal children. METHODS Children were recruited from the Federal Primary School Mexican Air Forces of Mexico City. All Children from the 3rd to 6th grades were included. RESULTS 256 children were included, 53% male and 46% female, mean age 9.8 1.15 years. Internal consistencies for instruments were as follows: anhedonia scale 0.91, hopelessness scale 0.63, automatic thoughts 0.87 and depression 0.80. The factor structures of the translated versions were similar to those reported by their original authors. Interinstruments correlations ranged from 0.17 to 0.39. Automatic thoughts and depressive symptoms reached the highest significant value (r= 0.39). 6th graders rated significantly lower in all instruments than their 5th and 3rd peers. CONCLUSIONS All measures studied demonstrate moderate to high internal reliability and the factor structures predicted. Depressive symptoms among normal children related weakly but significantly to the cognitive constructs studied, just as seen in normal adults.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de constructos cognitivos relacionados con la depresión en niños.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cognitive constructs related to depression in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas espanolas de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
