<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11933694</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Estañol, Bruno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mondragón, Benita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Infante, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinosa-Sierra, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Ramos, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corona Figueroa, Marco Vinicio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Memije, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Lomelí, María Magdalena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Plascencia-Alvarez, Noel Isaías</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evaluation of heart rate variability is an important tool to study several diseases. The most important tests include the variability of the heart rate as a function of time and as function of frequency, variability of blood pressure and pulsatile cutaneous blood flow (PCBF). We studied the effect of a sustained contraction of the quadriceps muscle on the instantaneous heart rate and pulsatile cutaneous blood flow in 10 healthy subjects. We measured the R-R interval and the instantaneous heart rate, in the time domain, 10 beats before the contraction, the R-R interval that coincided with the onset of the contraction, and the 30 R-R intervals after the beginning of the contraction. To measure the PCBF we used a photopletismograph designed for this purpose. We recorded the surface electromyographic activity (EMG) of the quadriceps muscle to determine the onset and end of the muscle contraction, and measured respiratory movements with a belt. We found an increase of the instantaneous heart rate at the first and second beats after the onset of the contraction. There was a decrease of the pulsatile cutaneous blood flow of the finger pad immediately after the contraction, which lasted for approximately eight beats. The findings support the idea of a central command and co-activation of the motor and sympathetic nervous systems. This efferent sympathetic activity seems to act not just on the contracting muscle but also on the heart and the cutaneous blood vessels of the extremities. These findings imply that it is quite likely that the sympathetic efferent effect has a supraspinal origin. This is a test that could be used to study cardiovascular control by the sympathetic nervous system.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la contracción muscular en la frecuencia cardiaca y en el flujo sanguíneo cutáneo. Resultados preliminares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of muscle contraction on heart rate and skin blood flow. Preliminary results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
