<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11965858</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Grutadauria, Sergio L</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, Juan J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gendelman, Héctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bustos, Dolores A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pavan, Jorge V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yacci, María R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carricart, Silvia E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nates, Silvia V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper was to assess the prevalence of antibodies to HHV-6 in the general population and study the virus circulation among individuals with cancer, in order to analyze HHV-6 involvement in lymphoproliferative disorders. A total of 200 sera from the general population and 67 from patients with neoplasia were studied. The latter were divided in 3 groups: lymphoma/myeloma, leukemia and non-immune solid tumors. HHV-6 antibodies (IgG and IgM) were assayed by IFA and viral genomes were detected using nested PCR. The prevalence of the infection in the healthy population was 63.5% with a titer geometric mean (TGM) of 48.67 +/- 1.23. A control group was obtained by systematic sampling of the healthy population. Among the patients with neoplasia, the prevalence was 95.5%. In the lymphoma/myeloma group, TGM was 268.73 +/- 1.62; in the leukemia group it was 151.1 +/- 1.88 and in the non-immunogenic solid tumors group it was 95.67 +/- 1.57. Statistically significant differences were observed (p &lt; 0.01) between the control group and the lymphoma/myeloma and leukemia groups. Serum IgM or free viral genomes were not detected in any serum sample. The antibody prevalence found in the general population documents the high circulation of this lymphotropic virus which could indirectly contribute to the pathogenesis of the lymphoproliferative disorder.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Circulación del virus Herpes 6 humano en adultos normales y en pacientes oncológicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Human herpesvirus-6 circulation in healthy adults and oncologic patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
