<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>11987673</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cases, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Gómez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dialysis patients constitute a high-risk subset of patients for developing cardiovascular disease, which accounts for nearly 50% of deaths. After stratification for age, race and gender, cardiovascular mortality is 10-20 times higher in dialysis patients than in the general population. Cardiovascular disease in this population cannot be fully explained by the high prevalence of classical cardiovascular risk factors (age, hypertension, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, smoking, etc.). Thus, the involvement of "new" cardiovascular risk factors (hyperhomocysteinemia, hyperfibrinogenemia, high lipoprotein (a) levels, oxidative stress, inflammation, etc.), and uremia-related factors (anemia, impaired calcium-phosphorus metabolism, hyperparathyroidism, accumulation of endogenous inhibitors of nitric oxide synthesis, etc.) has been also invoked to play a role in the increased cardiovascular risk in these patients. Endothelial dysfunction is the initial event in the development of atherosclerosis. Uremic patients exhibit an endothelial dysfunction, even before starting dialysis, which persists o is even aggravated under dialysis treatment. Uremic patients must be considered at high risk of developing cardiovascular disease. Thus cardiovascular risk factors in these patients should be managed early, aggressive and multifactorially in order to reduce their high cardiovascular morbidity and mortality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo cardiovascular en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica. Pacientes en tratamiento sustitutivo renal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiovascular risk in patients with chronic renal failure. Patients in renal replacement therapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
