<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12012560</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rached de Paoli, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Azuaje Sanchez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Henriquez Pérez, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To analyze the behavior of the anthropometric measures during gestation in teenagers and adults pregnant women. The study group was formed by 81 well nourished, healthy pregnant women, 14 teenagers and 67 adults. They were evaluated at Centro de Atención Nutricional Infantil "Antímano". The anthropometric criteria included at least five anthropometric evaluations: one in the first trimester of pregnancy, two in the second and two in the third. The anthropometric variable mean was obtained from each one of the pregnant women in each of their corresponding visits during the first, second and third trimester. The descriptive statistics of the studied anthropometric variables were calculated. Student' t test was applied. There were significant changes during pregnancy in weight, wrist, waist, abdomen, waist-hip, hip-gluteal, thigh and calf circumferences and body mass index in teenagers and adults. There were significant changes during gestation in a lying down position height in teenagers and mid-arm circumference in adults. There was significant difference in change from the first to the third trimester of gestation, between teenagers and adults in the calf circumference. The studied anthropometric variables presented the same behavior during gestation in adolescents and adults, unless the mid-upper arm circumference.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en las variables antropométricas durante la gestación en mujeres eutróficas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Changes of the anthropometric variables during gestation in well-nourished women].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
