<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12056255</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Tresguerres Hernández, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endocrine system hormonal secretion decreases during aging. The reduction of estrogens and GH exert a very important influence on cardiovascular and central nervous system functions, both systems being nowadays the most frequent responsible for illnesses and death in our society. To investigate the therapeutical effects of GH and estrogens on aging induced morphological and functional changes on vascular and cerebral tissues, young (5 months) and old (22 months) rats were compared. Male and female animals were used; some of the female rats were castrated to study the role of estrogens. Old rats exhibited thicker arterial wall than young animals, but GH and estrogens treatment was able to recover young morphological aspect. Vasodilatory reactivity to Isoprenaline and acetilcholine was reduced in old rats as compared to young ones, recovering the function when treated both with GH or GH and estrogens. Vasoconstrictory response to angiotensin was more marked in old rats especially in the castrated females, but GH and estrogens treatment reverted this effect. At cerebral level concentration of glutamine, arginine and aspartate was diminished in old male rats in the hypothalamus, the diencephalon and the temporal area, recovering young values when treated with GH; increased values of citruline in old rats considerably decreased when treated with GH. GH treatment seems to exert a beneficial effect on vascular and cerebral functions in old rats.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Envejecimiento vascular y cerebral: prevención con GH.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Vascular and cerebral aging: prevention with GH].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de la Real Academia Nacional de Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
