<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12053779</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Méndez-González, Rosa María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cervera-Montejano, María Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare vaginal delivery hospital and traditional care systems to identify resources and practices, as well as maternal and neonatal complications related to each system. MATERIAL AND METHODS Between 1989 and 1990, a cross-sectional study was conducted in three hospitals of Merida City and four municipalities of the state of Yucatan. The study sample consisted of 205 women who had a normal vaginal delivery. Delivery procedures were observed and a questionnaire to identify complications was applied 15 days after childbirth. Data analysis consisted in comparison of proportions with the chi-squared test. RESULTS Maternal and neonatal complications were identified in both systems; however, maternal complications were more frequent in hospital care, whereas neonatal complications were more frequent in traditional delivery care. The total number of complications was similar in the two systems. CONCLUSIONS No difference was found in the quality of care between the hospital and the traditional systems. Observed complications may be attributable to resources and practices of each system. Additional studies should be conducted to evaluate the advantages and disadvantages of each system, as well as to improve the quality of maternal and child care. The English version of this paper is available at: http://www.insp.mx/salud/index.html.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la atención del parto normal en los sistemas hospitalario y tradicional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison of normal delivery care in the hospital and traditional care systems].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
