<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12070895</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de la Rosa López, Jorge Humberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias Cruz, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Díaz, Sandra Nora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canseco González, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The MDI's are widely used in the treatment of asthma and are relatively easy to use. The response to this medicament is influenced by several facts that include the physical characteristics of the container and the technique used by the patient. OBJECTIVE To identify the mistakes made by asthmatic children and teenagers in the use of the MDI's. MATERIAL AND METHODS This paper was a descriptive and observational study in 57 asthmatic patients who were between 5 to 17 years. For the evaluation of the inhalation technique we used a placebo without a spacer. There are 5 steps for the correct use of the inhaled medications: 1) opening, 2) agitation, 3) coordination between inhalation and the shoot of the MDI's, 4) a deep breath and holding it for at lest 6 seconds. RESULTS 20 of the 57 patients (35%) followed all the steps correctly. The most frequent mistake was to take the deep breath, which was perform only by 20 (35%) out of the children. The second mistake we found in this study was the up holding inspiration at least for 6 seconds, which was done properly only by 31 patients (54%). CONCLUSIONS The implantation of inhaled therapy programs directed and performed by specialists is recommended.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Errores en la técnica de uso de inhaladores de dosis medida en niños y adolescentes asmáticos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Errors in the technique of using measured-dose inhalers in asthmatic children and adolescents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
