<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12090058</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alkiza, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bujanda, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballeros, C H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Stampa, M A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To determine the frequency of symptoms sugestive of functional gastrointestinal disorders and their relation to parasite infections in a developing nation. MATERIAL AND METHODS 174 consecutive patients was seen in a gastroenterology clinic in Solola (Guatemala). RESULTS Symptoms suggestive of irritable bowel syndrome was diagnosed in 37 patients (21%), irritable bowel syndrome with dyspeptic syndrome in 26 (15%) and dyspeptic syndrome in 24 (14%). Forty-two patients (24%) had been diagnosed of parasitation in the past. Such patients had a higher risk of suffering symptoms suggestives with functional gastrointestinal disorder (OR 6,335 CI 95% 2.72-14-75). Fifty-nine patients (34%) were subjected to parasite examination in stools; of these, 13 proved positive. In this same group of patients the risk of functional gastrointestinal problems was likewise higher among the subjects with parasite infection (p &lt; 0.05). In turn, 41 patients (49%) with symptoms suggestives of gastrointestinal functional disorders were or had previously been diagnosed of parasite infection. CONCLUSIONS Symptoms suggestives of functional gastrointestinal disorders are frequent in developing regions and its was in relation to intestinal parasites.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Corrected and Republished Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos gastrointestinales en Guatemala y su relación con infecciones parasitarias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Gastrointestinal disorders in Guatemala and their relation with parasitic infections].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
