<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12106516</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carrasco Perera, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Iglesias, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Urdaniz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina Ramos, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Borderline personality disorder (BPD) is the most common personality disorder in clinical settings, however, this disorder presents diagnostic difficulties because of the own heterogeneous character. The purpose of this study was to describe and examine the possible relationship between clinic-psychobiographical aspects of the patients and diagnoses of BPD. METHOD A transversal study was assessed in 73 psychiatric outpatients, by protocol of data collection about social and demographic aspects, psychobiographic aspects about childhood, sexual history and psychiatric earlier. International Personality Disorders Examination (IPDE) was used to evaluate the personality disorder. RESULTS Borderline patients self-reported of traumatics experiences, physical and/or sexual abuse in childhood in more percentage than the group without BPD. Sexual identity disturbance and homosexual relations were associated with BPD. Psychiatry earlier of hospitalization, suicide attempts and substance use disorders were more frequent in BPD patients. CONCLUSIONS These results suggest a profile that can be use to suspect a BPD and help to do precocious diagnoses.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados al diagnóstico de trastorno límite de la personalidad en pacientes psiquiátricos ambulatorios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors associated to the diagnoses of borderline personality disorder in psychiatric out-patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas espanolas de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
