<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12123130</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera-Sempere, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moll, J L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the clinical and pathological characteristics of a 49 year-old heterozygous female carrier of Anderson-Fabry's disease. Light microscopy and ultrastructural study of a renal biopsy showed the presence of foam cell nephropathy and galactosylceramide deposits affecting podocytes, the parietal epithelium of Bowman's capsule and the distal tubular cells, endothelial cells and medullary interstitial elements. Retrospectively, the presence of storage disease was confirmed in a hysterectomy specimen obtained two years previously. Our observation shows that heterozygotes for this disorder can not only carry and transmit the disease but may also develop pathological deposits in various organs. A renal biopsy from these carriers allows precise identification of the disease, facilitates adequate genetic counseling and gives the option of enzyme replacement therapy in patients who have pathological deposits.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefropatía de células espumosas en mujer heterozigota portadora de la enfermedad de Fabry.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Foam cell nephropathy in heterozygous female with Fabry's disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
