<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12140596</identifier>
<setSpec>1609-722X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vildósola, Herman</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colichón, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio Md, María del Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Weil, John</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of Hepatitis A Virus (HAV) in a country largely reflects its standards of hygiene and socio-economic conditions. In The 80's, it was reported 98% positive anti-HAV in adults and 82% in children; the rate increased with age, from 30% in thosed aged 1 year old to 100% in those of 8 years old.From October to December 1999, we performed a Sero-epidemiologic survey to evaluate the presence of Hepatitis A antibody (anti-HAV) in 859 subjects (518 were children and 341 adults), aged fron 1 to 39 years old, divided in two groups according to their socio-economic status (high and very high, low and very low).Adults older than 20 years old had 84% positives (288/341). Children (between 1 to 14 years old) had 46.3% positives (163/352): 35.6% (57/160) from socio-economic group AB and 55.2% (106/192) in level CD.We concluded that in the last 15 years was performed as significant decrease in the prevalence of Hepatitis A virus infection in children and adolescent polpulation of Lima-Peru, forming an intermediate endemicity as epidemiological pattern.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de anticuerpos contra Hepatitis A(Anti-HVA IgG)en una población de 01 a 39 a os de Lima.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[ANTI-HAV IgG PREVALENCE IN A POPULTION BETWEEN 1 AND 39 YEARS OLD IN LIMA,PERU]</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
