<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12373668</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Llaves-Estévez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Fernández, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burguera-Hernández, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valero, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chacon-Peña, J R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Hemifacial spasms consist in tonic clonic, involuntary, asymmetrical and asynchronous contractions in the territory innerved by the facial nerve. Several different causes may give rise to this disorder, the most frequent of which are vascular abnormalities in the cerebellopontine angle. Its clinical features and electrophysiological studies are commonly used in diagnosis and its etiological diagnosis is most frequently performed by means of magnetic resonance imaging. Symptoms are treated using local injections of Botulinum toxin Type A in the affected muscles. AIMS To review our experience in the handling of this pathological condition and to determine the results of employing Botulinum toxin. PATIENTS AND METHODS We describe the cases of bilateral hemifacial spasms that have been diagnosed in the Virgen Macarena Hospital in Seville and La Fe in Valencia since 1980, as well as the follow up after treatment with Botulinum toxin. RESULTS We describe eight cases of this pathological condition in which patients were treated with Botulinum toxin, and in all cases there was an improvement in the symptoms. CONCLUSIONS Treatment with Botulinum toxin is considered to be satisfactory and provides a marked improvement in the patients quality of life.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Sep 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espasmo hemifacial bilateral. A propósito de ocho casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bilateral hemifacial spasm: eight personal case reports].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
