<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12396943</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Nogales Aguado, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Vallejo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido Elustondo, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To find professionals' suggestions for training contents, the value they place on various options, the difficulties they detect for attending activities and their preferences for time-table and format of courses. DESIGN Cross-sectional, descriptive study. SETTING Primary Care Area 7 in Madrid. PARTICIPANTS Medical and office workers from the area (n=1,053). MAIN MEASUREMENTS An anonymous self-filled questionnaire. RESULTS 39% replied (46% nurses; 42% administrative assistants, and 40% doctors). The subjects for courses most often requested by doctors were dermatology, minor surgery and radiology; by nurses, emergency, functional bandages and computer skills; and by administrative assistants, computers, management of health service delivery and Internet. The continuing education options valued most highly were courses/workshops in the area's continuing education programme, self-training sessions and rotations. The main difficulties for attending courses were the lack of budget for cover and time-tables outside working hours. 42% preferred mornings; and 35%, courses lasting more than 20 hours. CONCLUSIONS The training needs expressed by doctors and nurses are mainly clinical in content, whereas those of office staff are mainly computer-related. The most highly valued training options are the courses/workshops in the area's continuing education programme. The main difficulty for attending courses is the lack of cover for their job.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Oct 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación continuada en atención primaria: necesidades formativas de sus profesionales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continuing education in primary care: the educational needs of its professionals].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
