<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12404925</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández, Paula C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wasserman, Moisés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caldas, María Leonor</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The reconstruction of Giardia lamblia life cycle in vitro is an excellent tool for the study of the parasite's molecular biology. The present work describes techniques developed that better define parasite differentiation. An encystation protocol is presented along with a method for isolation and purification of the produced cysts. The cyst morphology at the light microscopy level is identical to that of in vivo cysts. A two-dimension protein map obtained by high-resolution electrophoresis indicated that most of the parasite's proteins are acid. Based on this result, the two dimension gel electrophoresis used a pH 4-7 gradient in the first, isoelectric focusing dimension. Differences in protein expression during the stages of encystation were clearly discerned, as well as images of the parasite obtained by light and by transmission electron microscopy that describe the morphological and the ultrastructural changes that occur as the cysts are produced in vitro.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enquistación in vitro de Giardia lamblia: análisis por electroforesis bidimensional de proteínas expresadas diferencialmente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[In vitro encystation of Giardia lamblia: analysis with two-dimensional electrophoresis of differentially expressed proteins].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
