<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12425889</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carril, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guede, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quirce, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Bonilla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Banzo, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pena, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Allende, R H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Attenuation correction (AC) and scatter compensation (SC) techniques are recent developments of myocardial perfusion SPECT. Our aim was to evaluate the effect of AC + SC on the myocardial distribution of 99mTc-MIBI in a population without coronary artery disease. MATERIAL AND METHODS A multiarray of Gd-153 linear sources was used for simultaneous transmission/emission 99mTc-MIBI myocardial perfusion SPECT in 27 patients without coronary artery disease. A visual analysis and polar map quantification was performed. Changes between non-corrected (NC) and corrected (AC + SC) studies were compared. RESULTS AC + SC produced an increase in liver activity and better visualization of the right ventricle. Intestinal activity increased in six patients. Myocardial homogeneity was increased by AC + SC. No differences by gender were observed after AC + SC. In females AC + SC led to a decrease of uptake in the anterior wall, apex and apical segments of the lateral wall and septum, and an increase in the inferior wall. In males AC + SC caused an increase of uptake in the inferior wall and in the basal segments of septum and a decrease of uptake in apex and apical segments of anterior and lateral walls. AC + SC generated false defects in the anterior wall of five patients. CONCLUSIONS Our results show the usefulness of AC + SC for compensating the interferences produced by attenuation on the myocardial distribution of 99mTc-MIBI. Because AC + SC may introduce false defects, it must not be applied to normal perfused myocardium.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la corrección de la atenuación y de la radiación dispersa en la SPET de perfusión miocárdica con 99mTc-MIBI de pacientes sin cardiopatía isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of attenuation correction and scatter compensation on the 99mTc-MIBI myocardial perfusion spect in patients without coronary artery disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
