<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12447795</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz-Heijtz, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a complex neurodevelopmental disorder, which is very common among the school aged population. Its core symptoms are inattention, hyperactivity, and impulsivity. Currently, three principal subtypes of ADHD are recognized: ADHD predominantly inattentive type, ADHD predominantly hyperactive/impulsive type or ADHD combined type. Affected individuals have increased comorbidity risks, often followed by cognitive, emotional and/or social impairments as adults. Stimulants drugs such methylphenidate (Ritalin) or D amphetamine (Dexedrine) represent the first line drugs for the treatment of ADHD. DEVELOPMENT The clinical features of ADHD were first described by Dr. George Frederick Still for Lancet in 1902, and in spite of the investigations carried out since then, the precise cause is still not clear. The purpose of this review is to describe recent advances of the neurobiological basis of ADHD. CONCLUSIONS Recent neuroimaging studies in humans indicate a dysfunctions of the frontal striatal circuits in patients with ADHD, which can be improved by pharmacological treatment. Both pre and clinical studies implicate a dysregulation of the dopaminergic and noradrenergic systems, which are known to regulate the functions of these circuits. More recent evidence indicate that some features of ADHD could be linked to alterations in the posterior inferior vermis. These studies also stress the importance of taking into consideration factors such as age, gender and duration of pharmacological treatment when interpreting the results.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases bioquímicas e investigaciones en el trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Biochemical bases and research in attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
