<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12455285</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Amón Sesmero, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Sagarra, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Toves, Luis Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estebanez Zarranz, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manzanas, Manolo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conde Redondo, Consuelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso Fernández, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To emphasise a case of splenic hematoma secondary to ESWL. METHODS We report the case of a 69 year old patient with the diagnosis of left kidney stone who underwent ESWL. The treatment was performed with an electric lithotripter after pre-treatment antibiotic prophylaxis; 2000 shock waves of 18 Kv were given to the patient. RESULTS Patient presented abdominal pain and hematocrit descent after lithotripsy. The diagnosis of splenic hematoma was established after abdominal ultrasound and CT-scan and the patient was treated conservatively. He required a posterior emergency splenectomy secondary to infection of the hematoma, with the result of death secondary to septic shock. CONCLUSION Splenic lesion is an exceptional complication after ESWL. There are no studies about the effect of shock waves on the spleen, having been reported only four cases. It is believed that extreme care should be taken in cases with splenic pathology: leukaemia, lymphoma, etc.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hematoma de bazo tras litotricia extracorpórea: a propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Splenic hematoma after extracorporeal lithotripsy: apropos of a case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
