<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12466077</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Verrillo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cilveti Portillo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estivill Sancho, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) in children is a frequent and potentially serious respiratory disorder, it has a reliable diagnosis and treatment is highly effective. OSAS is a respiratory sleep-related disorder that forms part of sleep apnea-hypoapnea syndrome. The syndrome affects between 1 % and 3 % of children. In addition to its cardiopulmonary complications, it can retard growth and increase the risk of hyperactivity and learning difficulties. It has also been associated with attention deficit disorder and hyperactivity. When OSAS is suspected, up-to-date nocturnal polysomnography is the gold standard for the diagnosis and quantification of severity of childhood OSAS. In most children the treatment of choice is adenotonsillectomy, which has a success rate of more than 85 %. We provide an up-to-date review of the evidence on the clinical features, etiology, complications and treatment of OSAS in children. The main objective of this review is to alert pediatricians to their essential role in the early detection of this syndrome, especially among children who snore, and to provide a clinical practice guideline for the diagnosis and definitive treatment of these children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de apnea obstructiva del sueño en el niño: una responsabilidad del pediatra.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome in children: the responsibility of pediatricians].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
