<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12487947</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Santos Diez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llinares Pellicer, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palau Muñoz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albiach Catalá, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE This paper aims to study the predictive potential of the stage of change, type of treatment followed and other variables regarding adherence to therapy. METHODOLOGY A longitudinal and multicentre study has been carried out in three drug-addiction treatment centres within the Valencia Region, Spain. The sample included 172 alcohol-addicted clients (152 men and 20 women). Adherence to treatment was measured at one, 3, 6, 9, 12, 18, and 24 months. RESULTS The most successful variable predicting treatment adherence is the type of program followed associated to all the time cutoffs. The fact of attending the centre with some relative or friend is a sign of potential adherence to treatment at the 3 and 6 months. The longer the withdrawal period previous to treatment, the greater the chances of adherence at the 6, 9 and 12 months of treatment. CONCLUSIONS Those variables directly associated with treatment are potentially better predictors of adherence than the stage of change. We have found it necessary to assess it throughout the therapeutic process.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables predictoras de adherencia al tratamiento en pacientes alcohólicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Predictive variables of adherence to treatment in alcoholics].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas espanolas de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
