<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12529774</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fantini, M G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dios Seoane, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rossi, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goyanes, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodiño, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amaro, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dios García, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The anterior sacral meningocele is the congenital hernia of the thecal sac into the pelvis through a bone defect of the anterior wall of the sacrum. The association of anorectal anomaly, anterior sacral defect and presacral mass, known as Currarino's triad, can be diagnosed during the first decade of life in the eighty per cent of the cases However, in the incomplete syndrome, the symptoms appear in adults. In order to avoid late complications and due to the clear genetic origin of this uncommon pathology, the investigation of the family is of paramount importance for the early diagnosis and treatment. We review the literature and add two cases of anterior sacral meningocele with rectal fistula and incomplete Currarino's syndrome. In one of the cases the pathology is also present in another member of the same family and is complicated with meningitis. The importance of early diagnosis and treatment of these malformations and the need for fammily genetic investigation are discussed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningocele sacro anterior en pacientes con síndrome de Currarino: aportación de dos casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Anterior sacral meningocele with Currarino's syndrome: report of two cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
