<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12599150</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mosqueda-Betancourt, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva-AdAn, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vega-Basulto, S D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montejo-Montejo, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Genetic etiology in suggested in intracranial aneurysms. Such hypothesis is supported on familial aggregation, ocurrence in identical twins or associated to genetic diseases like adult polycystic renal disease. OBJECTIVE To identify biological features in familial aneurysms different to sporadic ones. PATIENTS AND METHODS Camag ey province is one of the most ancient in Cuba. Motionless population at the beginning had its sources in Spanish and African people. It has 800,000 inhabitants. 497 patients with intracranial aneurysms were operated at Manuel Ascunce Domenech Hospital between January 1982 and August 2001. We identified 15 families with intracranial aneurysms. RESULTS 31 patients were operated on of 42 intracranial sacs at the carotid territory. There were 34% of multiplicity ant three mirror aneurysms. Three patients (9.7 %) have adult polycystic renal disease. 87 % of patients present aneurysms rupture and mortality was 32 %. This last figure was related to poor admission clinical grade. CONCLUSIONS Frequency of familial aneurysms was 6.2% Familial aggregation, aneurysms between twins associated with genetic linked disease, early age rupture, high frequency between women, posterior communicating and middle cerebral artery bifurcation preference, mirror aneurysms and high general mortality associated to massive intracranial bleeding identified this clusters of familial aneurysms and would justify imaginological screening of high risk patients before the rupture.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Feb 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurismas intracraneales familiares en Camagüey.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Familial intracranial aneurysms in Camagüey].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
