<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12607014</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Canut Blasco, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abásolo Osinaga, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abecia Inchaurregui, L C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ulibarrena Sanz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hermosilla Nájera, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE Antimicrobials are a mayor part of hospital pharmacy budgets and must be considered in resource planning and spending projections. This study describes the profile of antibiotic use at a medium-sized hospital (by examining the ICU separately) and analyses its evolution over the period 1996-2000. METHODS Descriptive and retrospective study. Pharmacy records were reviewed to identify oral and parenteral antimicrobial agents administered to inpatients. Results were expressed in Daily Defined Doses (DDD) per 100 stays and day. RESULTS During the five-year study period 176.162 DDD / 100 s-d of antibiotics were consumed in the ICU, whereas in the rest of the hospital usage was much lower (54.540 DDD / 100 s-d). Aminoglycosides, cephalosporins, penicillins, glycopeptides and carbapenems were the most commonly used groups of antimicrobials in the ICU, and penicillins, cephalosporins, trimethoprim/sulfonamide combinations, aminoglycosides and quinolones in the rest of the hospital. CONCLUSIONS ICUs have some special features which make them different to the rest of inpatient areas. Because of that fact we consider important to study this specific patient-care area separately.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la utilización de antimicrobianos durante los años 1996-2000 en un hospital general. Estudio pormenorizado de la UCI.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evolution of antimicrobial use during the years 1996-2000 in a general hospital. A detailed ICU study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
