<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12609111</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Piñol Moreso, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez Pérez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mèlich Teruel, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Folch Pujol, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aragonès Benaiges, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labad Alquézar, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence and forms of clinical expression of depressive disorders in primary care patients. To analyse the under-detection of depression by primary care doctors. DESIGN Descriptive and transversal study, with two-stage sampling. Setting. Primary care consultations in the Camp de Tarragona area. PARTICIPANTS 1000 consecutive patients visiting their doctor for any reason will make up the first-stage sample. Of these 350 go on to the second stage (all the positive results in the screening for depression test plus a random one-seventh of the negative results). MAIN MEASUREMENTS The first stage will consist of the screening of the sample for depressive disorders with Zung's Self-Rating Depression Scale. In the sub-sample that will go on to the second stage, the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Disorders will be used to establish diagnoses of depressive disorders and other co-morbid psychiatric disorders. There will also be a range of specific questionnaires to find reasons for consultation and the form of presentation of an eventual depressive disorder, medical co-morbidity, medication taken, use of health services, the functional and vital repercussions of depression. A questionnaire for the patient's G.P. will assess and detect depression. DISCUSSION The study will enable us to check the validity for our patients of pre-suppositions on depression in primary care obtained from studies in other countries with different health structures and social and cultural conditioners, and to find diverse information extrapolated from specialist studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Feb 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia, expresión e impacto de los trastornos depresivos en atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence, expression and impact of depressive disorders in primary care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
