<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12601963</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barrientos Fernández, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Crespo Izquierdo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luque Mialdea, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED The stress leak point pressure is the lowest bladder pressure at which leakage occurs during increases in intra-abdominal pressure. Our goal was the study of the stress leak point pressure in children to determine if it is a useful method of evaluation of incontinence and how it can be applied to pediatric clinical practice. We prospectively studied 68 consecutive incontinent children: Group 1 included 50 children neurologically normal. Group 2 included 18 children with myelodysplasia. RESULTS 1) No correlation was found between stress leak point pressure and leak point pressure values. 2) The difference between the volumes at which the stress and rest leak were obtained was not statistically significant. 3) Study of stress leak point pressure: Group 1; Leakage during stress only occurs in 16%. Stress leak point pressure was greater than 100 cm of H2O in these children. Group 2; Leakage during stress occurs in all children (positive test in 100%). Stress leak point pressure was less than 100 cm of H2O, indicating intrinsic sphincter deficiency. These results suggest the stress leak point pressure is a diagnostic test that provide information about the function of proximal urethra and bladder neck in pediatric population, and an useful tool to despite of intrinsic sphincter deficiency.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor predictivo de la presión vesical de escape en estrés en la incontinencia urinaria en el niño.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Predictive value of stress leak bladder pressure in urinary incontinence in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
