<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12622958</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz-Salmerón, Rafael J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goicolea, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Araujo Martins-Romeo, Daniela</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocaranza, Raymundo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanmartín, Marcelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Campo, Víctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saa, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castellanos, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mantilla, Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guitián, Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Gated-SPECT simultaneously evaluates perfusion and ventricular function and could provide important prognostic information in ischemic cardiomyopathy. Our aim was to study the value of gated-SPECT performed before revascularization in a cardioischemic population to predict the outcome of revascularization. METHODS One hundred and ten patients who had undergone percutaneous (n = 100) or surgical revascularization were included. Patients underwent sestamibi gated-SPECT before revascularization. After revascularization, they were followed-up for at least 12 months (mean 23.7 months, maximum 44 months). We recorded deaths and a combined clinical event of death, non-fatal infarction, and hospital re-admission for cardiac reasons. We analyzed the prognostic value of clinical, angiographic, and gated-SPECT variables. RESULTS During follow-up, there were 14 deaths (6.4%/ year) and 36 cases of combined events (16.5%/year). Multivariate analysis showed that depressed gated-SPECT ejection fraction (threshold 0.30) was the only variable independently related to death (OR = 4.8; 95%CI, 1.6-14.6) and combined event (OR = 2.5; 95%CI, 1.2-4.8). Survival analysis showed that patients with ejection fraction &lt; or = 0.30% had a significantly shorter period of time free of death (33 months [28-38] versus 42 months [40-44]; p = 0.002) and combined events (28 months [23-32] versus 36 months [33-39]; p = 0.007). CONCLUSIONS Gated-SPECT, due to the information it provides about left ventricular function, predicts the prognosis of patients after coronary revascularization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor del gated-SPECT para definir el pronóstico tras la revascularización en una población con cardiopatía isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Value of gated-SPECT in defining the post-revascularization prognosis of patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
