<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12647249</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mayo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Arumí, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giraldo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez de la Rúa, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aragón, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanabria, R M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To identify clinical risk factors for development of postoperative PVR, to determine the incidence of this complication and its time of onset by a prospective multicentric study. METHODS A multicentric and prospective study of 223 patients with rhegmatogenous retinal detachment (RD) was conducted. Logistic regression analysis was used to identify risk factors for PVR among 83 variables related to preoperative, intraoperative and postoperative characteristics. RESULTS 22 out of 223 RD developed PVR (incidence 9.9%, confidence interval 95%: 5.9-13.9). After logistic regression analysis, four variables showed an odds ratio higher than 1.0 (RD affecting 4 quadrants, cryopexy, aphakia/pseudophakia and those RD in which an encircling band was implanted). None of these factors showed a &lt;p&gt; value lower than 0.05. Most of postoperative PVR (77.2%) appeared in the first month after surgery. CONCLUSIONS This study establishes the incidence of PVR, and its time of onset, but it was not effective to identify clinical risk factors with a high level of confidence.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores clínicos de riesgo para el desarrollo de la vitreorretinopatía proliferante (VRP) postquirúrgica. Estudio prospectivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical risk factors for postoperative proliferative vitreoretinopathy (PVR). A prospective study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
