<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12645376</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domínguez Domínguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arroyo Maestre, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quintero Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibáñez Suárez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camacho González, J E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The radical nephrectomy is considered to be the optional treatment for renal carcinoma. In the last years, the good results with partial resection shows conservadora surgery the most suitable treatment for well-localized bilateral renal tumours. In this cases dialysis is avoided, and the subsequent risk of immunological deficit and the higher possibility of metastasic illness are minimized. Nowadays, however, there seems to be some controversy over conservative surgery, concerning applications and technique of surgery to practice (partial resection vs. enucleation). We have a case of bilateral synchronic renal cell carcinoma where radical surgery on the left kidney was put into practice, as it presented a great tumour with multiples points corticals confirmed by PAAF and conservative surgery on the right kidney with enucleation of localized mass in the lower renal. The patient held normal renal function with a good quality of life for five years, finding out then, in one of the radiological tests, carcinoma relapse in the only kidney, that forced to radical surgery and to his inclusion in dialysis programme.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de células renales bilateral sincrónico. Presentación de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bilateral synchronous renal cell carcinoma. Report of a case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
