<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12677467</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fresán, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Loyzaga, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nicolini, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ulloa, R E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Apiquian, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION There are two phenotypes proposed for the psychotic disorders based on premorbid functioning and probably related with the duration of untreated psychosis (DUP). The aim of this study was to compare the clinical features, premorbid functioning and its relationship with DUP by gender in a group of first episode psychosis patients. METHODS We included 77 patients in their first admission to a psychiatric facility. A clinical evaluation was performed with the PANSS, Calgary Depression Scale,Hamilton Depression Scale and Mania Rating Scale. Premorbid functioning was rated with the Premorbid Adjustment Scale. RESULTS There were no clinical differences between men and women. Men had greater impairment in their premorbid functioning. Patients with short DUP (&lt; 28 weeks) showed better premorbid functioning compared to those with long DUP (&gt; 28 weeks). CONCLUSION Duration of untreated psychosis is determined by premorbid functioning and it is possible that male patients, who show a higher frequency of poor premorbid functioning, have a longer delay in seeking treatment, that conditions a longer duration of untreated psychosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funcionamiento premórbido por género y su relación con la duración de la psicosis no tratada (DPNT) en el primer episodio psicótico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Premorbid functioning by gender and its relationship with duration of untreated psychosis in first psychotic episode].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas espanolas de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
