<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12696403</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morillo, Carlos A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vesga, Boris E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Federico A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán, Juan Camilo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grubb, Blair P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years increased interest has focused on the nature and pathophysiology of orthostatic intolerance and syndromes associated with autonomic disorders. Understanding the pathophysiology underlying these syndromes has led to the recognition of several distinct clinical entities with overlapping features and the associated need to reclassify many of the previously unrecognized syndromes. Among the clinical manifestations, syncope and near syncope are frequently associated with orthostatic intolerance. In addition, however, a wide spectrum of symptoms have been described ranging from chronic fatigue to recurrent neurally mediated vasodepressor reactions. The present review focuses on the pathophysiology and classification of syndromes of autonomic dysfunction associated with orthostatic intolerance. Primary and secondary causes of dysautonomia as well as therapeutic approach to these frequently unrecognized syndromes is presented.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndromes de disfunción autonómica asociados con intolerancia ortostática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Autonomic dysfunction syndromes associated with orthostatic intolerance].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
