<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12717562</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Solá Uthurry, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fontana Raspanti, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To adapt the DA inverted exclamation mark der methodology to identify and resolve drug related problems (DRP) in pediatric inpatients by disigning a normalized work procedure (NWP). To establish a pilot plan of pharmacotherapeutic follow-up to evaluate the NWP created. METHODS The DA inverted exclamation mark der methodology is taken as a base adapting it to the characteristics and needs of pediatric inpatients and a NWP for their pharmacotherapeutic follow-up is created. A pilot plan consisting in a prospective longitudinal follow-up study is designed. The population and setting of the study are all the inpatients during one month in a room at the Municipal Childrenâs Hospital. RESULTS The NWP is composed by the following steps: Previous phase: patient selection; follow-up phase: data compilation, information analysis (situation state, study phase, global evaluation), pharmaceutical intervention; results; clinical sessions; record documents. Pilot plan: 21 patients were studied; 71.4% of them presented at least 1 DRP during hospitalization period and 27 DRP were identified in all studied cases; 51.9% of DRP were effectiveness problems, 37.0% were related to safety and 11.1% to necessity; 55.6% of the health problems were resolved. CONCLUSIONS The elaboration of the NWP allowed to adapt the DA inverted exclamation mark der methodology at the hospital setting. The pilot plan was very useful in carrying out the pharmacotherapeutic follow-up of pediatric inpatients thus showing the necessity of pharmacistâs participation in the health team to improve the quality of the inpatientâs pharmacologic treatments.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento farmacoterapéutico en pacientes pediátricos hospitalizados: adaptación de la metodología Dáder.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pharmacotherapeutic follow-up in hospitalised paediatric patients: adapting Dáder methodology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
