<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12766872</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Gentili, L I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salgado, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kremenchutzky, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION With the aim of integrating clinical thinking and obtaining epidemiological and biostatistical results in long series of patients who present balance disorders, we have developed a neuro otological protocol and its corresponding database. This offers answers to the questions of how to assess the patient, how to conduct a clinical interview correctly, and which complementary studies should be requested and how. RESULTS The information from the protocol is stored and analysed in our database, which was designed in the Epi Info software application, produced by CDC (NIH, USA), in collaboration with the WHO Global Program on AIDS. The application, which we call ENO LK, has already been used to store data concerning 1,100 patients whose average age is 54.5 years old and 62.8% of which were females (SD 18, range 4 93). 69.1% were diagnosed as suffering from vertigo, 12.7% displayed instability, 1.9% syncope and 16.3% had other causes (37% psychogenic and 28% disorders affecting the central integrator). Of the 760 patients with vertigo, in 55% it was positional (60% of these were idiopathic benign), 6.3% were sustained (peripheral causes accounted for 74% and a vascular aetiology was predominant in the central causes), 26.6% were recurring and 12.1% otolithic (in this series the vertigos all had a central aetiology). CONCLUSIONS With this application the user has the possibility of obtaining epidemiological and diagnostic conclusions efficiently and effectively, as well as aiding to follow up all patients who present balance disorders.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 May 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Base de datos para pacientes con trastornos del equilibrio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Data base for patients with balance disorders].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
