<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12778876</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Praga, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espejo, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valentín, M O</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrero, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bueno, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The commonest clinical presentation of both immunoalergic interstitial nephritis (IIN) and atheroembolic renal disease (ATD) is an acute renal failure accompanied by skin lesions and eosinophilia. As a consequence, differential diagnosis between both entities is often very difficult. We have performed a comparative retrospective study of those patients diagnosed as having IIN or ATD in our Hospital in the period 1980-2000. A total of 42 patients have been diagnosed of IIN and 16 of ATD. Demographic data, as well as clinical and laboratory parameters and outcomes of every studied patient were analysed. We found a significantly higher prevalence of male sex (100% vs 57%, p &lt; 0.01), previous history of hypertension (100% vs 55%, p &lt; 0.01), chronic renal insufficiency (56% vs 17%, p &lt; 0.01), ischemic heart disease (56% vs 14%, p &lt; 0.001), peripheral ischemic disease, endovascular procedures (87% vs 7%, p &lt; 0.001) and anticoagulant treatments (25% vs 5%, p &lt; 0.001) among patients with ATD as compared with IIN, respectively. On the contrary, previous infections (45% vs 12%, p &lt; 0.01) and exposure to new drugs (100% vs 40%, p &lt; 0.001) were significantly more frequent among IIN patients in compare with ATD. ATD patients showed skin lesions consisting of livedo reticularis and digital infarcts (63% vs 31%, p &lt; 0.05) accompanied by blood pressure increase (100% vs 24%, p &lt; 0.001), whereas IIN patients showed fever (41% vs 19%, p &lt; 0.05) and cutaneous rash as significant clinical manifestations, respectively. The number of ATD patients with proteinuria &gt; 1 g/24 h was significantly higher, but no differences between both groups in the prevalence of urinary sediment abnormalities were observed. The prevalence of absolute eosinophilia was high in both groups (88% among ATD patients, 64% among IIN patients; pNS). Prognosis of both entities was clearly different: Almost all patients with ATD died (69%) or evolved to end-stage renal failure, whereas most patients with IIN showed a recovery of renal function after withdrawal of responsible drugs and steroid treatment. In summary, the analysis of clinical and laboratory data allows an initial differential diagnosis in patients suspected as having IIN or ATD.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefritis intersticial inmunoalérgica vs ateroembolismo de colesterol. Características diferenciales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Immunoallergic interstitial nephritis vs. cholesterol atheroembolism. Differentiating characteristics].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
