<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12793020</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aguayo-Godínez, Arnoldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Venegas Ochoa, Urbicio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro Núñez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñiz Gómez, Arnoldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Toro-Equihua, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the prevalence of anemia among rural pregnant women living at 540 meters above sea level in Colima, Mexico. MATERIAL AND METHOD A cross-sectional studied was carried out, we included women attending antenatal clinic between January 1996 and December 2000, who are not receiving prenatal iron and folato supplements previously. Blood samples were examined for hemoglobin (Hb) concentration. Information on date of examination, name, private residence, age, gestational age, marital status, educational status, work, menarche, parity, cesarean sections, miscarriages, intergestation lapse, and hemoglobin levels was recorded. The information was confirmed by visit at private residence. Altitude was derived from official maps. Our measures to diagnose anemia were gestational age and low hemoglobin concentration. Three groups were integrated with the following criterions: GROUP I: Gestational age 1st to 5th week, Hb less than 12.0 g/dL. GROUP II: Gestational age 6th to 15th week, Hb less than 11.0 g/dL. GROUP III: Gestational age 16th to 40th week, Hb less than 10.4 g/dL. We calculated percentages, frequencies, and prevalence. RESULTS We found 35 women, 25.7% showed anemia, the higher Hb concentration was of 14.6 g/dL and the lower was of 9 g/dL. CONCLUSIONS The prevalence of anemia was of 0 x 1000 women in-group I, 117 x 1000 women in-group II, and 437 x 1000 women in-group III.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anemia en embarazadas residentes en área rural a 540 metros de altitud.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Anemia among rural pregnant women living at 540 meters above sea level].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
