<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12825306</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tisner Madrid, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanjoaquín Mur, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Diego Fernández, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrerizo Torrente, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES The purpose of this study was to compare two 27-gauge anesthesia needles with different points (a Whitacre-type point and a Quincke-type point) and to assess the incidences of postdural puncture headache (PDPH), puncture difficulty and failed anesthesia. MATERIAL AND METHODS This prospective, randomized and double-blind trial enrolled 1,555 patients receiving spinal anesthesia for lower abdominal surgery. No age limits were established. A 27-gauge Whitacre-point needle was used in group I (n = 748) and a 27-gauge Quincke-point needle was used in group II (n = 774). RESULTS The incidences of PDPH were significantly different in groups I (0.53%) and II (1.85%) (p &lt; 0.01). Puncture was easy in 84.89% of the procedures in group I and in 78.81% in group II (p &lt; 0.01). The number of cases in which a puncture could not be accomplished was similar in the two groups (2.41% in group I and 2.07% in group II). The number of failed anesthetic procedures was also similar (0.96% in group I and 1.45% in group II). CONCLUSIONS When a 27-gauge Whitacre-point needle is used, fewer cases of PDPH develop and the puncture is easier to accomplish than when a Quincke-point needle is used. The number of failed anesthetic procedures is similar with both needles. Whitacre-point 27-gauge needles are preferable to Quincke-point 27-gauge needles.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de dos agujas de calibre 27G para anestesia raquídea. Estudio sobre 1.555 pacientes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison of two 27-G-caliber needles for spinal anesthesia. Study of 1,555 patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
