<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12825340</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferré Rey, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morelló-Castro, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION With the development of medical technology, human life expectancy has increased. This has increased the incidence of senile pathologies and the associated problems for this people. In the field of otolaryngology, one of these pathologies is presbyacusis. This study attempts to find relationships between presbyacusis and different parameters related to it. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross sectional study was carried out with 59 volunteers aged between 50-89 from different homes for the elderly in the city of Reus. The subjects presented with or without symptoms of deafness. An AOE test was then performed to determine the different parameters. Significant response criteria were: otoemissions with a signal-noise ratio of 3 dB or greater or 65% reproducibility in &lt; 2 bands. The results obtained were analyzed through a computer statistics program (SPSS) and Microsoft Excel for the graphics. RESULTS The results of the characteristics of the test are within the acceptable limits of quality. The prevalence of subjects with AOE was 22%, with an average age of the subjects of around 69 years. We did not find statistical differences in the presbyacusis group with respect to the parameters of intensity and reproductability, but there was a correlation in the duration of the test. In the analysis of frequencies in the reproductibility parameters we observed a fall in the 5 KHz. The ratio signal-noise showed a similar tendency. It is necessary to emphasize the worst results in the different parameters from the right ear the left one. CONCLUSIONS The AOE offers information in frequencies of 1 and 2 KHz, where we can see a reduction in the reproducibility in the presbyacusis group. We see a longer test time, in the presbyacusis group and this may be used to control the development of the disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de las otoemisiones acústicas en la presbiacusia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Validation of the otoacoustic emissions in presbyacusis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
