<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12833678</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Famiglietti, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casellas, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pasterán, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quinteros, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutkind, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kovensky Pupko, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goldberg, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soloaga, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nicola, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Couto, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galas, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bantar, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Radice, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corso, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Predari, S C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lopardo, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial susceptibility testing is mainly performed in Argentina by disk diffusion method, following National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards (NCCLS) recommendations. We worked out new recommendations for the reporting and interpretation of this test when dealing with gram-positive cocci, in accordance to local trends and epidemiology. General considerations for performing the diffusion assay, quality control, and an update on susceptibility testing for gram-positive cocci are reported in this first document. The present update should be considered as a group of recommendations summarized by Argentinean experts and as the result of a consensus meeting coordinated by the Subcomisión de Antimicrobianos of the Sociedad Argentina de Bacteriología Clínica (Asociación Argentina de Microbiología). Experts in antimicrobial agents were convened in order to prepare this final document. These recommendations take into account local needs, affordability and availability to be used in current practice, tending to contribute to the correct antimicrobial treatment election, according to the particular microorganism and the infection sites.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso sobre las pruebas de sensibilidad a los antimicrobianos en cocos gram-positivos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Consensus on antimicrobial sensitivity tests in gram-positive cocci. Subcommittee on Antimicrobials, SADEBAC (Argentinian Society of Clinical Bacteriology), Argentinian Association of Microbiology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
