<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12872564</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cárdenas, Rocío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferro, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera, Olga L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Munstermann, Leonard E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of PCR (polymerase chain reaction) was evaluated for its effectiveness as a tool in the detection of transmission of Leishmania chagasi to a hamster host, Mesocricetus auratus, by insect vector bite. Two pairs of uninfected and anesthetized hamsters were introduced into cages containing infected females of the typical phlebotomine sand fly vector, Lutzomyia longipalpis. The flies were experimentally infected with Leishmania chagasi and the infection was verified by dissection of subsamples. At 37 and 51 days after exposure to the infected flies, biopsies of each hamster's liver and spleen were subjected to direct histopathological and PCR examination. DNA was extracted with Chelex 100; for PCR amplification, primers specific to Leishmania minicircle DNA were used. PCR product was separated on agarose gels and visualized with UV. A band of approximately 120 base pairs was observed in 3 of the 4 biopsies, corresponding to the expected minicircle size. PCR was the only method that detected presence of the parasite. The results demonstrated that the sensitivity of PCR greatly expedites the confirmation process of a particular phlebotomine species as a vector of leishmaniasis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PCR para la confirmación de transmisión experimental de Leishmania chagasi a hámster sano por picadura de Lutzomyia longipalpis (Diptera: Psychodidae).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[PCR as a tool in confirming the experimental transmission of Leishmania chagasi to hamsters by Lutzomyia longipalpis (Diptera:Psychodidae)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
