<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12883595</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vairo, María Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dabi, Eugenia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matusevich, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Finkelsztein, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Faccioli, José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine, in older suicide attempt inpatients, differences between leaving a suicide note and not leaving it as regards age, sex, marital status, religion, living alone, level of education, present psychiatric treatment, severity of suicidal attempt, previous suicidal arousal, afterwards suicidal arousal, suicidal ideation, hopelessness, depression, dementia, narcissistic personality disorder, physical pain, previous suicide attempt, familiar history of suicide or suicide attempt. MATERIAL AND METHODS This is a comparative, prospective, observational, transversal, single blind study. RESULTS We studied 31 patients. Statistical significant associations were found between leaving a suicide note and hopelessness (p=0.03;OR=8.57;IC=1.19-95.33) and severe suicide attempt (p=0.022;OR=8.40;IC=1.28-63.88). DISCUSSION Although associations between writing suicide notes and hopelessness have not been reported, our results are not surprising because, on one side, the severity of the suicide attempt is more related to hopelessness than to any other depressive parameter and, on the other side, leaving a suicide note is associated to severe suicide attempts. Finally, to feel hopeless and to leave a suicide note are associated to severe suicide attempts.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jun-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Notas suicidas en pacientes mayores de 65 años: estudio comparativo (datos preliminares).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A comparative study of suicide notes in over 65 years old patients (preliminary data)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
