<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12891393</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sola, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Elso, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chueca, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oyarzábal, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of congenital Hypothyroidism is estimated at one case per 3,000-4,000 newly born. It is a proven fact that early diagnosis and treatment of this problem prevents mental retardation, which has led to the design and utilisation of methods of systematic detection in the newly born. The implantation of the screening program is relatively recent and progressive in some autonomous communities. With respect to the achievements that are being obtained by the program outstanding is the shorter time with respect to initiation of the treatment, but there still remain some shortcomings such as that of carrying out a longitudinal follow up of these infants, with respect to the evaluation of the development quotient, hence the need to have available hospital psychologists to carry out these evaluations. The expectations of achieving a mental development within normality in the children affected by congenital Hypothyroidism detected by the neonatal screening is a fact confirmed by many authors, for which reason it is highly encouraging to view the results of early detection of this neonatal screening.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Sep-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Screening neonatal del Hipotiroidismo congénito: resultados del programa en Navarra.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neonatal screening of congenital Hypothyroidism: result of the Navarra program].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
