<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12891447</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díez, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Expósito, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belzunegui, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gurrea, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present paper is a retrospective descriptive study, carried out in the Special Casualty Service (Servicio Especial de Urgencias) of Pamplona. It evaluates 8,411 cases of calls from homes, extracted from an aleatory sample stratified by day of the week and season of the year, with a N=647. The diagnoses were codified according to the ICHPPC-2 of the WONCA and the statistical study with SPSS/PC+V 4.0. The monthly average was 701 calls from homes, with a daily average of 19 (from Monday to Friday), with 38 on Sundays and holidays. With respect to distribution by time, on working days 66.5% were distributed between 15.00 and 22.00 hours, while on Sundays and holidays 51% fell between 8.00 and 13.00 hours. The overall rate of use was situated at 32.71/1,000 inhabitants and year (with extreme rates in Mendillorri=7.42 and II Ensanche=57.35). In 74% of the cases a doctor or nurse visited the home. The most frequent cause for home care are illnesses of the respiratory apparatus with 23.5%. Some 40.9% of the patients attended were over 75 years of age. The conclusions are: 1. There is a low rate of home care. 2. Those requiring such visits are of an advanced age. 3. Illnesses of the respiratory apparatus are the most frequent cause of demand. 4. The zones of most demand are those where a Health Centre has not been set up as such.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la demanda de atención domiciliaria en 1995 del Servicio de Urgencias Extrahospitalario de Pamplona.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of the demand for home care by the Pamplona Extrahospital Emergency Services in 1995].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
