<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12891443</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz de Rada, M O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santamaría, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lecumberri, J J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to study meniscal regeneration, and the behaviour of different autologous plasties used as meniscal substitutes, the knees of 45 adult White New Zealand rabbits were operated on. The 45 knees were divided into three groups with fifteen knees in each group. The meniscectomy group was given the letter M, the patellar group R, and the cartilage group C. In group M a total medial meniscectomy was performed; in group R, after the total medial meniscectomy, a strip of the patellar tendon, harvested from the same rabbit, was implanted on the site of the original meniscus; in group C, after the total medial meniscectomy, a fragment of cartilage, also harvested from the same animal, was implanted on the site of the original meniscus. We reviewed 5 knees from each group 6, 12 and 24 weeks after surgery, and the newly formed menisci were histologically studied. Twenty-four weeks after surgery we found fibrocartilaginous menisci in the three groups; the metaplasiant sequence from fibrous tissue to fibrocartilage was similar in the three groups. We therefore conclude that: 1. Meniscal regeneration occurs. 2. The autografts we have used could be valid meniscal substitutes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la regeneración meniscal tras meniscectomía total y de la sustitución del menisco por distintas plastias autólogas. Trabajo experimental desarrollado en la rodilla del conejo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of meniscal regeneration following total meniscectomy and the replacement of meniscus by different autologous plasties].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
