<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12894486</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Hernández, José A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escalante-Acosta, Bruno A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zúñiga-Sosa, Leonor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Mendoza, M Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastelín-Hernández, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Ayala, Sonia O</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nitric oxide and cytochrome P450 arachidonic acid metabolites participate in blood pressure regulation. The synthesis of these autacoids leads to arterial hypertension. However, it is not known whether there is an interaction between them. Therefore, we studied the modulatory effect of nitric oxide and cytochrome P450-arachidonic acid metabolites, their interaction on blood pressure, and the renal content of cytochrome P450. Male Wistar rats were divided: 1) control, 2) L-NAME (100 mg/kg/d p.o.), 3) L-NAME + SnCl2 (10 mg/kg/d i.p.), and 4) L-NAME + dexamethasone (1 mg/kg/d s.c.). We measured blood pressure and collected urine and blood for nitric oxide measurement. NO2 was quantified by HPLC. Blood pressure was: control, 97 +/- 7 mmHg; L-NAME, 151 +/- 4.6 mmHg; L-NAME + SnCl2, 133 +/- 3 mmHg, and L-NAME + dexamethasone 152 +/- 4.5 mmHg. Urine nitrite concentration was: 1) 1.832 +/- 0.32, 2) 1.031 +/- 0.23, 3) 1.616 +/- 0.33, and 4) 1.244 +/- 0.33 mumol/mL, while the concentration in blood was: 1) 0.293 +/- 0.06, 2) 0.150 +/- 0.05, 3) 0.373 +/- 0.13, and 4) 0.373 +/- 0.07 mumol/mL. L-NAME + SnCl2 decreased cytochrome P450 renal content, and L-NAME + dexamethasone showed a similar response. In conclusion, both, nitric oxide and CYP-arachidonic acid metabolites play a role in the regulation of blood pressure. Nitric oxide also partially regulates renal cytochrome P450 content.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Participación del óxido nítrico y los metabolitos del ácido araquidónico vía citocromo P450 en la regulación de la presión arterial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Participation of nitric oxide and arachidonic acid metabolites via cytochrome - P450 in the regulation of arterial blood pressure].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
