<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>12934269</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-6722</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Frede, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hliba, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martellotto, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED These ovarian neoplasm derive from the ovarian stromal component constituting around the 5 to 12% of all ovarian tumors. OBJECTIVE To examine the histopathological and ultrastructural morphologic characteristic of the neoplastic cells and the patognomonic element of these tumors: Call Exner's Bodies MATERIALS AND METHODS The materials corresponded to 2 women of 52 and 55 years. The syntomatology was abdominal tumor that went in increase. The materials were fractioned for the histopathological conventional study and for ultrastructural analysis. For this last one, they were fixed in Karnovsky, refix in osmio and included in Araldita. RESULTS By means of the different observations it was determined in both cases the nuclear atipia, indentations nuclei and prominent nucleoli. In one of the cases the presence of Bodies of Call-Exner was detected, and ultrastructurally was compound by whirled fibrils and amorphous material, with dense structures electron to its around. It was interest the infiltrated of plasmatic cells around the tumors cells. These neoplasms are of interest due to their impredictible behavior and to the hormonal production that can originate alterations in other organs of the genital apparatus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores de células de la granulosa: análisis estructural y ultraestructural.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Granulosa cell tumors: structural and ultrastructural analysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
