<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1300852</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Currás, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olmos, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zalar, A E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nadales, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Magnanini, F L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peralta, C G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gorzelewsky, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During 2 years (1988-1990) 373 patients were studied by ERCP in order to establish the etiology of cholestasis. Biliary duct stones were found in 190. Thirty-nine were treated surgically and 151 by endoscopic sphincterotomy and different extraction techniques. In 12 patients of the last group (9 women, 3 men, mean age 71 years, 9 had undergone cholecystectomy and 3 has their gallbladders in situ), ESWL was used as additional treatment to fragment the stones that could not be removed with the Dormia basket or with mechanical lithotripsy. Four patients had only one stone in their biliary ducts, 5 had two, and 3 had more than two stones. The size of the stones was greater than 2.5 cm. in 11 patients, only 1 patient had a 1 cm. diameter stone. In each session between 1200 and 5000 shock waves were administered (mean 1400). In 8 patients (66%), the fragmentation was successful to achieve their spontaneous passage or their extraction with a basket. In 4 who received only one session of ESWL, the procedure failed to break the stones. Side effects were observed in 3 cases: mild haemobilia in 1, skin petechiae and pain in 2 patients. No complications were observed in the long term follow-up. We conclude that ESWL is useful in the treatment of biliary duct stones which cannot be extracted through sphincterotomy with a basket or mechanical lithotripsy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con ondas de choque extracorporeas (ESWL) en la litiasis de la viá biliar principal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment with extracorporeal shockwave (ESWL) in lithiasis of the common bile duct].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta gastroenterologica Latinoamericana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
