<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1340901</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mileo Vaglio, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Litwak, L E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutman, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fried, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Althabe, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Sancho, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A total of 35 pregnancies in 28 Pregestational Diabetic Patients (PDP) were followed with the goal of achieving and maintaining near normoglycemia (as many pre-postprandial glycemias as possible between 60-140 mg/dl); 13 patients (16 pregnancies) were assigned to Subcutaneous Continuous Preprogrammed Insulin Infusion (SCII) because of high risk pregnancies (HRP) (at least one of the following: former history of spontaneous abortions, stillbirths, premature deliveries and/or sterility). The remaining 12 PDP's (15 pregnancies with no past history of the above nature) were treated with Multiple Conventional Insulin Injections (MCII). Both groups were comparable regarding the following clinical parameters: age, time of onset and class of diabetes. All patients were instructed in performing 3 to 7 daily Self Capillary Blood Glucose controls (SCBG). Mean follow-up observation period was (mean +/- SEM) 28.5 +/- 2.5 weeks for SCII and 3.2 MCII and 28.8 +/- 3.2 weeks for MCII. All the 3 PDP drop out's (4 pregnancies) belonged to the CMII group. No drop out's were recorded in the SCII group. Both insulin therapy approaches were similarly effective in improving metabolic control in that comparable levels of mean blood glucose (MBG) and HbA1 were attained by SCII and MCII (Fig. 1). Compliance, as evidenced by average of daily SCBG was also similar in both groups (Fig. 2). Such satisfactory metabolic control was achieved mostly because of an increase in the percentage (65%) of "fair" glycemias (60-139 mg/dl) and not because of an increase in hypoglycemias (&lt; 60 mg/dl) which could have canceled out an undesirable degree of hyperglycemias thus rendering "false satisfactory" MBG's and HbA1 (Fig. 1). With the above degree of metabolic control obtained there occurred no severe hypoglycemic episodes requiring medical intervention. All newborns to the PDP's who remained under treatment showed an adequate APGAR (X +/- SEM, 9.5 +/- 0.2) regardless of the modality (SCII or MCII) of insulin delivery used (Tables 1, 2). The single malformed baby found in this series was born to a patient on SCII who happened to start on the intensified insulin treatment rather late in her pregnancy (21st week) and, in addition, the patient self medicated with high doses of chlorpromazine because of recurrent vomiting episodes. Incidence of neonatal hypoglycemia (HY) or macrosomy (MS) was comparable in both groups (Tables 1, 2). It is to be pointed out, however, that PDP's who bore the babies with no HY or MS had presented a larger number of low glycemic values than mothers who bore the babies with HY and/or MS.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 400 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insulinoterapia intensificada en el manejo de la diabetes pregestacional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intensified insulin therapy in the management of gestational diabetes].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
