<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14508946</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vila i Vidal, Dalmau</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author creates a systematic, ordered and standardized nursing treatment methodology for the use of hyperbaric chambers as a up-to-date, simple, practical tool which can be individualized to fit the needs of our patients. The author bases his method on the theoretical-practical knowledge acquired during his years of professional treatment experiences and on a study of the articles published about how nurses work with hyperbaric chambers. The author has not found any bibliographical references on any study which specifically describes standardized nursing procedures related to hyperbaric chambers. The author describes the materials and the functioning of hyperbaric chambers: the human and material resources involved, basic materials in a hyperbaric chamber, and systems to administer oxygen therapy. The author also plans out nursing treatment procedures; therapeutic protocol before entering a hyperbaric chamber; maintenance or standard treatment, that is the protocol working procedure sequence; medical prescriptions; monitoring and vigilance techniques; and how to detect diagnostic and nursing problems. To this end, the author has developed a clinical report check sheet for related nursing procedures as well as a scheme-guide for the most probable problems and diagnoses on which symptoms, causes objectives working procedures and evaluation information are included; these are: risk of a lesion, risk of intoxication, deterioration of a patient's mobility, pain and anxiety.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cámara hiperbárica. Planificación estandarizada de cuidados de enfermería.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hyperbaric chamber. Standardized planning of nursing care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
