<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14574752</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sotelo-Cruz, Norberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In Mexico, we do not know the exact number of cases and the magnitude of health damage conditioned by poisonous rattlesnake bites, and little relative information exists in pediatric population. OBJECTIVE To inform on continued follow-up of 55 patients at a children's hospital, and to propose a therapeutic sequence adequate for children. MATERIALS AND METHODS We reviewed clinical records and variables were origin, age, sex, time of year, previous care measures, time passed, hospital treatment complications and care cost. RESULTS Rattlesnake bite occurred around the home at times and at times inside the home in rural areas; we did not observe any noticeable difference in gender; snake variety most involved was Crotalus atrox, anatomic site most injured were the lower extremities in 78%. Prior to admission, 50% received insufficient antivenom serum doses; the most frequent complication was hematologic in 69%. One patient died with multiple organ failure and disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC). The treatment protocol that we have recommended since 1986 at the Hospital Infantil del Estado de Sonora, revised and modified in 1996, reduced hospital stay from 15 to 5 days. CONCLUSION The protocol used avoided further complications and had a favorable influence on cost reduction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Envenenamiento por mordedura de serpiente de cascabel, daños a la salud y su tratamiento en edad pediátrica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rattlesnake bite poisoning, health damage and treatment in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
