<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1457705</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández Echegaray, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Pérez, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benítez Bocanegra, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno Sánchez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Navarro, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valles Casado, L M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez Puente, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna del Castillo, J D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cejas Hermoso, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés Martínez, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the frequency and characteristics of post-vaccination reactions, between on the one hand the simultaneous administration of the Oral Antipolio (OP), the Triple Virus (TV) and the Anti-Diphtheria and Anti-Tetanus (DT) vaccines; and on the other hand, their administration in sequence. DESIGN Prospective study with interventions, with a non-random, non-blind determination. SITE. Survey covering the mothers of infants vaccinated at 24 vaccination centres in Mála province. PARTICIPANTS 490 infants vaccinated during their second year of life. 263 had the vaccines administered simultaneously and 227 in sequence. INTERVENTIONS Simultaneous administration of the TV, OP and DT vaccines at 15 months; as against the administration of TV at 15 months, followed by OP and DT at 18 months. MAIN RESULTS 78 infants (29.66%) suffered a reaction that could be attributed to the vaccination after the simultaneous administration of TV, OP and DT; and 86 infants (37.88%) after one of the two occasions of vaccination in the administration in sequence: 27.31% after the TV, 17.18% after the OP-DT and 6.62% after both. CONCLUSIONS The safety of simultaneous administration, taken together with data coming from other studies on its immunogenic effectiveness, reaffirms the usefulness of simultaneous administration of TV, OP and DT vaccines at 15 months, as a strategy to improve vaccine coverage of infants in their second year of life.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 Oct 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacciones posvacunales tras la administración simultánea de vacunas triple vírica y antipolio oral-difteria-tétanos, frente a su administración secuencial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Postvaccinal reactions to simultaneous administration of the triple viral, oral polio and diphtheria-tetanus vaccines compared with their administration in sequence].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
