<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14588229</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bello, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castel, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Velasco, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cañete, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hervás, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Cabezas, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Langerhans cell histiocytosis (LCH) is a granulomatous disease which can involve multiples sites of the body. Diagnostic imaging is of utmost importance in the management of these patients. Up to now radiographic skeletal survey and bone scintigraphy (BS) have been used to assess bone involvement (both with low specificity). Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and CT have been used to assess visceral involvement but with the limitation that they cannot give information about the functional status. Recently somatostatin receptor scintigraphy (SSRS) has been proposed to detect active lesions and to monitor response to treatment. The aim of this study is to assess bone and somatostatin receptor scintigraphy in the detection of bone involvement in LCH in children. Twenty scintigraphies (12 SSRS and 8 BS) were performed in seven patients (3 girls and 4 boys) aged at diagnosis: 18 month-12 years (mean age 6 years). The findings obtained in the scintigraphies were compared with clinical evolution and other imaging techniques. Bone scintigraphy detected all the LCH bone lesions, and discovered one unknown lesion. SSRS scintigraphy visualised the active lesions in 3 patients (clinical and other imaging techniques were also positive). SSRS was negative in one patient classified as disease free and another in clinical remission. SSRS detected 2 new unknown bone lesions, but could not detect LCH bone lesions confirmed in other imaging techniques in 2 patients. Somatostatin receptor and Bone scintigraphy can be used to detect active LCH bone lesions in children and can help to monitor response to treatment. Further studies with more patients are needed to confirm the diagnostic usefulness of these techniques.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gammagrafía ósea y gammagrafía de receptores de la somatostatina en pacientes pediátricos con histiocitosis de células de Langerhans ósea.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bone scintigraphy and somatostatin receptor scintigraphy in pediatric patients with bone involvement in Langerhans cell histiocytosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
