<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14606379</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mato, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Antonio, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, L M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES We aimed to determine whether early termination of sevoflurane administration lowers the incidence of postanesthetic shivering. MATERIAL AND METHODS Eighty ASA I-III patients were randomized to two groups of 40 (Group A and Group B). All were premedicated with oral bromazepam. Fentanyl (2 micrograms/Kg), propofol (2.5 mg/Kg) and atracurium (0.5 mg/Kg) were used for induction. Anesthesia was maintained with sevoflurane in 60% N2O in oxygen at 1 maximum alveolar concentration, with boluses of fentanyl and atracurium on demand. Sevoflurane administration was terminated 30 minutes before awakening in group A and 10 minutes before awakening in group B. After termination, 60% N2O in oxygen was used in both groups. Mean blood pressure, heart rate and peripheral and core temperatures were measured at 5 minutes intervals during surgery. Postoperative shivering was recorded until one hour after awakening. RESULTS Patient characteristics and duration of anesthesia were similar in both groups. The incidence of shivering was significantly lower in group A (4%) than in group B (57%). No significant differences were observed in other variables. CONCLUSIONS The important observation in this study was that the incidence of postoperative shivering in group A was lower than in group B and lower than the incidences reported in other similar studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2002 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de escalofríos postquirúrgicos en relación al tiempo de suspensión del sevoflurano.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Incidence of postoperative shivering in relation to the time of sevoflurane discontinuation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
