<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14635480</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jerjes-Sánchez Díaz, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solís Olivares, Carlos Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Archondo Arce, Tamara</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Our current knowledge on the prognosis of systolic left ventricular dysfunction has been obtained through multicentric trials performed at third level health care institutions, which usually include patients based on strict inclusion criteria. OBJECTIVE To establish in systolic left ventricular dysfunction patients, evaluated at a community hospital, a risk profile for adverse cardiovascular events and to know their survival. METHODS Prospective study with 4 years follow-up. INCLUSION CRITERIA a) Symptomatic patients with systolic left ventricular dysfunction, b) any NYHA functional class or etiology, c) ejection fraction &lt; 40%. EXCLUSION CRITERIA a) Asymptomatic patients, b) acute coronary syndrome in the last 6 weeks, c) ventricular dysfunction secondary to pulmonary arterial hypertension, d) severe systemic illness or neoplasms causing disability &lt; 6 months. STATISTICS Student's test, Chi-square, Yates and Mantel-Haenszel. Unvariant and multivariant logistic regression analysis. Cox and Kaplan-Meier method. Significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. RESULTS From January 1997 to January 2001, 110 patients were studied, 61% men and 39% women, their age were 61 +/- 13.1 years. Ischemic etiology in 46% and 54%, 68% in III/IV NYHA class and 32% in I/II NYHA class. Basal left ventricular ejection fraction was 28 +/- 6.9%. Patients were followed for 30.11 +/- 18.7 months, with 26% of global mortality. Through lineal, logistic and multivariate regression analysis, the high clinical risk profile was identified, corresponding &gt; 65 years, female gender, hypertension, diabetes mellitus II, ischemic heart disease, III/IV NYHA class and ventricular tachycardia (p = 0.00001). CONCLUSION In the "real world" of systolic left ventricular dysfunction, the identified risk profile allows stratify high priority subgroup of patients to be enrolled in a cardiac transplant program.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de riesgo y supervivencia en pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca por disfunción sistólica. Estudio prospectivo con seguimiento a cuatro años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk profile and survival in patients with heart failure caused by systolic function. Prospective study with 4-year follow-up].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
