<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14636533</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Corral Gudino, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Arellano, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreiro Barroso, Maite</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Pino Montes, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guijo Hernández, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Pulmonary embolism (PE) is a frequent and severe condition. Although clinical models do exist, many patients are wrongly diagnosed. Our objective was to evaluate the clinical characteristics of patients with PE who are admitted at a hospital without initial clinical suspicion of it. We also evaluated the sensitivity of three clinical models in order to categorize the pre-test probability of PE. PATIENTS AND METHOD Retrospective review of clinical cases of PE diagnosed in a teaching hospital during one year. We compared the clinical features of patients whose PE was not initially suspected with those of patients in whom PE was a first diagnosis. The three clinical models were applied in all cases. RESULTS 58 patients were identified. In 15 out of them (26%), PE was not an initial diagnosis. Patients without an initial PE suspicion were older, and previous surgery was less frequent among them. The clinical models exhibited sensitivities (60, 85, 89%) which were lower than those previously reported but higher than the doctor's initial clinical suspicion (74%). The models showed bad agreement between them (kappa = 0.06-0.1). CONCLUSIONS An initial misdiagnosis of PE is not justified by atypical clinical characteristics. The use of clinical models would improve the clinical suspicion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Nov 08 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tromboembolia pulmonar: análisis de los casos sin sospecha inicial y sensibilidad de tres modelos clínicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary embolism: analysis of cases without initial suspicion and sensitivity of three clinical models].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
