<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14964087</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Nogueira March, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros Rodríguez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez López, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez García, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Alonso, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Iglesias, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso Rodrigo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benavente Delgado, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ojea Calvo, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fournier's gangrene is a skin infectious-necrotising process in the peri-neogenital area affecting males, usually in their sixties or seventies. Isolated flora from cultures of the necrotic lesion is commonly multi-microbial. In a majority of cases both aerobic and anaerobic micro-organisms are found in the cultures, Escherichia coli being the most commonly identified germ. Although considered in the past an idiopathic condition, in most patients today a genitourinary, anorectal or dermal triggering factor can be identified. There are a series of systemic host debilitating disorders such as diabetes mellitus, chronic alcohol abuse, and malignant neoplasia that are associated to this condition and may be considered risk factor to suffer this disease. Fournier's gangrene in children show specific bacteriological, pathogenic, clinical, therapeutic and prognostic features that distinguish it from that in adults. The most extensively accepted management for this condition includes therapy with broad-spectrum parenteral antibiotics and early and aggressive surgical debridement of the necrotic areas. Mortality continues to be high, ranging between 10-80% in the various series. Finally, a group of 7 patients with Fournier's gangrene is analyzed (1991-1998) aiming to establish a comparison between our results and those seen in recent series.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2000 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gangrena de Fournier: aspectos anátomo-clínicos en el adulto y en el niño. Actualización terapéutica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fournier's gangrene: anatomo-clinical features in adults and children. Therapy update].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
