<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>14968985</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Burnes, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prado Lobato, Simón Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero Rico, Frida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos Díaz, Aidee del Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales González, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez Nava, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Asthma is a chronic disorder of the airways that modify behavior response of persons and affect family function. OBJECTIVE To determine if there is a disorder of the familial dynamics in asthmatic patients of Tamaulipas. MATERIAL AND METHODS An observational, comparative, open and cross-sectional study was performed to determine: family categorization, family function and evaluation of conjugal subsystem. We included 300 persons who were 30 to 50 years old, male and female: 100 subjects with asthma diagnosis, 100 with diabetes type 2 and 100 healthy people. RESULTS The asthmatic subjects' age average was of 45.67 years, complete nuclear family was documented in 15% of sick persons, women were the family head in 50% of the cases, we appreciated great family dysfunction in relation to: adaptability function (50%), participation (63%), family grow-up (61%) and feeling manifestations (64%). In 53% of the conjugal couple cases of the patients, do not carry out her family functions like: communication 59%, share out functions 59%, sexual satisfaction 60%, and making decision 59%. CONCLUSION It is only feasible to treat these patients when there is an active participation of the family members.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paciente asmático y su dinámica familiar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The asthmatic patient and his/her family dynamics].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
