<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15011151</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Muñoz Yunta, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernandez Lucas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salvado Salvado, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palau Baduell, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maestu, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Autistic spectrum disorders (ASD) is a term that is not included in DSM IV or in ICD 10, which are the diagnostic tools most commonly used by clinical professionals but can offer problems in research when it comes to finding homogenous groups. DEVELOPMENT From a neuropaediatric point of view, there is a need for a classification of the generalised disorders affecting development and for this purpose we used Wing's triad, which defines the continuum of the autistic spectrum, and the information provided by magnetoencephalography (MEG) as grouping elements. Specific generalised developmental disorders were taken as being those syndromes that partially expressed some autistic trait, but with their own personality so that they could be considered to be a specific disorder. ASD were classified as being primary, cryptogenic or secondary. The primary disorders, in turn, express a continuum that ranges from Savant syndrome to Asperger's syndrome and the different degrees of early infantile autism. MEG is a functional neuroimaging technique that has enabled us to back up this classification.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio mediante magnetoencefalografia de los trastornos generalizados del desarrollo. Nueva propuesta de clasificacion.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A magnetoencephalographic study of generalised developmental disorders. A new proposal for their classification].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
