<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1502407</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pedromingo Marino, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guardiola Pereira, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bigorra Llosas, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Rivera, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At the end of 1989 a transversal study to know the availability of glycosylated hemoglobin as a control parameter in diabetic patients was done. Two hundred and three physicians-specialists in diabetes-provided information on the fraction, technique and reference interval used in their clinical practice. 90 +/- 4% of the participants were able to obtain, in their settings, the determination of glycosylated hemoglobin. Regarding work-places it is outstanding that 36 +/- 15% of the physicians in primary care did not have the possibility to get this parameter determined. Fraction and technique more widely used were, respectively, HbA1 and Ionic Interchange Chromatography performed with HPLC. There was no homogeneity in the reference intervals for HbA1 and HbA1c, considering different methodologies. The possibility to obtain different glycosylated hemoglobin determined, depends on the setting where the health care is being provided. It is important to know the reference interval of the Center where the determination is being done, in order to correctly interpret the glycosylated hemoglobin values of each patient.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La determinación de hemoglobina glucosilada en la práctica clínica asistencial de la diabetes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Determination of glycosylated hemoglobin in clinical practice care of diabetes].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
