<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15022399</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fiorentino, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, María Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saavedra, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quijano, Sandra M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orozco, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The expression of heat shock proteins (HSP70) in tumor cells or virus infected cells is important for the induction of specific cellular immune response. They are implicated in transport of immunodominants peptides in the endoplasmic reticulum, activation of antigen presenting cells and cross priming of CD8 T cells. AIM To analyze the expression of HSP70 protein in its constitutive (HSP73) and inducible forms (HSP72) in Hodgkin's lymphoma (HL), infected or not by Epstein Barr virus (EBV) and to assess its relationship with pathological subtype, clinical stages and treatment response. MATERIAL AND METHODS The analysis of HSP73 and HSP72 was done by immunoperoxidase on routinely processed paraffin sections with prior antigen retrieval. RESULTS Sixty seven cases were studied. The expression of HSP73 and HSP72 was detected in 19.4 and 17.9% of samples respectively. The infiltrating lymphocytes expressed HSP72 in 58% of cases. The pathological subtypes with the higher expression in lymphocytes were mixed cellularity and nodular sclerosis. No differences in HSP70 expression were observed, according to clinical stage, treatment response or the presence of EBV. CONCLUSIONS The expression of HSP72 on lymphocytes suggests that this protein plays an important role in the induction and amplification of antitumor immune response.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión de proteínas del choque térmico HSP72 y HSP73 en casos colombianos de linfoma de Hodgkin positivos y negativos para virus de Epstein Barr.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Expression of heat shock proteins HSP72 and HSP73 in Colombian patients with Hodgkin lymphoma positive and negative for Epstein Barr virus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
