<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1504207</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ortiz de Lejarazu, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eiros Bouza, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias Mayorga, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Pozo Pérez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marañón Cabello, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We described an 18 old homosexual man who after 5 days developed a neurologic picture associated with Human Immunodeficiency Viruses (HIV) seroconversion. The patient had developed a dissociative psychiatric disorder 6 months before, and after resolution of the acute neurologic disease a mild neuro-psychiatric disorder remained. After mononucleosis-like syndrome of three weeks, the patient developed a meningo-encephalitic process 48 h post admission. He evolved with tonic seizures and twilight state and was admitted into Intensive Care Unit because of epileptic status and deep coma. Evolution was favourable after 72 h of treatment with acyclovir and antiepileptic drugs. Laboratory data showed an inverted T4/T8 ratio and seroconversion to HIV-antibodies and p24-antigen both in serum and CSF. These observations confirm the existence of psychiatric as well neurological alterations in acute HIV infection, and also the significance of p24-antigen and Western-Blot in serum and CSF in showing the seroconversion profile.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno disociativo psiquiátrico previo y status epiléptico en un caso de infección aguda por VIH.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Previous dissociative psychiatric disorder and status epilepticus in a case of acute HIV infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
