<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15074782</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cabrera Pérez, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Miñón, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Cardoso, Juan Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Enguita, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calahorra Fernández, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vela Navarrete, Remigio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To determine the long-term efficacy and complications of contact laser prostatectomy in the treatment of the benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH). METHODS 32 patients in a prospective clinical trial of contact laser prostatectomy were followed for 5 years. Patients were assessed by physical examination, International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS), uroflowmetry, post void residual urine, transrectal ultrasound and PSA. RESULTS From the initial cohort, three patients had died from concomitant diseases. Three patients (9%) had undergone reoperation (TURP). Seven Patients (22%) received alpha blockers for irritative symptoms. IPSS and maximum flow improved significantly and remained stable at five years. There were not statistically significant differences in prostate volume or PSA level. CONCLUSIONS Contact laser prostatectomy is a safe and effective treatment for BPH in the long-term. It has minimal morbidity and durable therapeutic effects. Nevertheless, in our experience postoperative irritative voiding symptoms (22%) are the major disadvantage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">HBP: seguimiento a cinco años de los pacientes tratados mediante vaporización por láser de contacto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Benign prostatic hyperplasia: five year follow-up in patients who underwent contact laser vaporization].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
