<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15087047</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-7411</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bross-Soriano, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Schimelmitz-Idi, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arrieta-Gómez, José R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate efficacy of the conventional technique of adenoidectomy by means of transoperative endoscopic revision of the nasopharynx and to evaluate the need for including telescopes as part of usual instruments used in adenoidectomy. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective, open, comparative, and transversal study. We included the first 150 patients with absolute indication for adenoidectomy. We did 150 adenoidectomy procedures by conventional technique using Beckman adenotomes, and La Force adenotomes, using a laryngeal mirror to observe condition of nasopharynx once the surgeon thought the procedure was completed, we did a revision of adenoid area with Hopkins telescopes of 0 and 30; if we founded residues of adenoids, these were eliminated with Guggenheim forceps, adenotomes, or curved 40 degrees microdebrider tip, all after endoscopic viewing, which also helped in control of area bleeding. MEASURED PARAMETERS: Presence or absence of adenoids residue location, and presence or absence of active bleeding. RESULTS Total removal of adenoids was carried in 43 patients, our finding adenoid residues in 107 of cases. Of these, 45.3% were occluding pharyngeal part of Eustachian tubes. CONCLUSIONS Conventional technique for adenoidectomy was effective in &lt; 30%; therefore, it is imperative to use endoscopic revision in each case.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenoidectomía endoscópica, uso o abuso de la tecnología?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endoscopic adenoidectomy; use or abuse of the technology?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
