<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15098040</identifier>
<setSpec>1022-5129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Caffo-Mendo, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yan-Quiroz, Edgar Fermín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burgos-Chávez, Othoniel Abelardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Plasencia, Juan Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vilela-Guillén, Edwin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas-Vergara, Adrián Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santillán-Medina, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To identify the clinical and pathological characteristics and prognosis factors for five-year survival in patients with advanced gastric carcinoma in the proximal third and half of the stomach undergoing gastrectomy with limited and extended lymphadectomy. MATERIAL AND METHODS This retrospective study analyzed information from 39 patients with histological diagnosis of advanced gastric adenocarcinoma in the upper third and half of the stomach (U-M) who underwent gastrectomy with limited (D0-D1) and extended (D2-D3) lymphadectomy at the Belén Hospital in Trujillo between January 1, 1966 and December 31, 2000. RESULTS The mean age of the U-M group was 55.56+/-16.24 years. There were 27 males (69.2%) and 12 females (30.8%) (M:F ratio was 2.3:1). The most frequent symptoms were abdominal pain (94.9%) and weight loss (61.5%). The most common evidence was pallor (61.5%). The independent prognosis factors statistically related to survival were: depth of T2 invasion (p=0.017), presence of remote metastasis (p=0.013), clinic stage I-II (p=0.005), Borrmann lesions I-II (p=0.05) and surgery with healing intention (p=0.003). The actuarial 5-year survival rate for all the series reached 13.6%. CONCLUSIONS Early detection and the feasibility of gastrectomy with preservation of the pancreas tail should be considered in patients with advanced gastric carcinoma in the proximal third and half of the stomach in order to improve their survival.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma avanzado del tercio proximal-medio del estómago: cuadro clínico-patológico y factores pronósticos de sobrevida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Advanced gastric carcinoma in the proximal third and half of the stomach: clinical and pathological characteristics and survival prognosis factors].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
