<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15109285</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Raya Sánchez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brito Barroso, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Salazar, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Nieto, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso Socas, M M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary effusion lymphoma (PEL) is a recently individualized form of non-Hodgkin lymphoma (WHO classification) that mainly develops in HIV infected males, more frequently in homosexuals and advanced stages of the disease (total CD4+ lymphocyte count below 100-200/mL). Occasionally, it appears in others immunodepressive states (such as solid organs postransplant period) and even, although very rarelly, in immunocompetents patients. From a pathogenetic point of view, PEL has been related to Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpes virus (also named human herpesvirus 8) and to the clinical antecedent of Kaposís sarcoma. Relative unfrequency of this disease, the absence of wide casuistics allowing a better characterization, and its unfavorable outcome, support the need of a deeper knowledge. We present here the clinical-biological findings of three patients that were diagnosed of pleural PEL in our institution in the last two years.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HIV-associated primary body-cavity-based lymphoma: clinico-biologic features in three patients diagnosed at the same institution.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
