<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15104971</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García de Albéñiz, Xabier Adrián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-González, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega-Martínez, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerra-Gutiérrez, Félix</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Villegas, Almudena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective of this study was to assess the association between employment, educational level, marital status, and smoking in a large cohort of Spanish university graduates (3- and 5-year degrees), with a predominance of health professionals. METHODS A cross-sectional analysis of the baseline data of the first 7,508 participants in the follow-up study of the University of Navarre (SUN Project) was performed. The subjects were classified according to their smoking status. Independent variables were: employment, marital status, highest educational level attained, number of children, alcohol consumption (g/day), body mass index, and age. In the multivariate analysis, 3 non-conditional logistic regression models were built using the following outcomes: a) smokers vs never-smokers plus ex-smokers; b) smokers vs never-smokers; c) smokers of 15 or more cigarettes a day vs smokers of less than 15 cigarettes a day plus never-smokers and ex-smokers. RESULTS Among men, no association was found between employment and smoking status in any of the comparisons. In contrast, among women, being a nurse was associated with a higher prevalence of smoking. The prevalence of current smokers among nurses was 48.5%. Female students were also more likely to smoke and had a higher risk of being heavy smokers (OR = 1.81; 95% CI, 1.28-2.57). A lower prevalence of smoking was found among participants of both sexes who had completed a doctorate. CONCLUSIONS Among a large Spanish collective with higher education, the prevalence of smoking was higher in women with a shorter college degree. The prevalence of smoking among nurses was higher than the average among women graduates, which is a cause for concern.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de tabaco en titulados universitarios. El Proyecto SUN (Seguimiento Universidad de Navarra).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Smoking among a cohort of Spanish university graduates. The SUN Project].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
