<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15125083</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yañez, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarroel, Mario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Biolley, Edith</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acevedo, Carol</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Characterization of functional properties of Sphagnum magellanicum fiber were investigated. Water absortion (WAC) and water retention (WRC) capacities, swelling capacity (SC); organic molecule absortion capacity (OMAC) and cationic interchange capacity (CIC) were evaluated, as well as its incorporation as fiber source to bakery produts. Diferent particles sizes were selected to evaluate their effects on the functional properties of moss fiber: T1(1.4 mm);T2(1.0 mm); T3(0.42 mm); T4(0.18 mm). Best results of CAA, CRA; SC and OMRC were obtained with T3, whereas best values of CIC were attained with T1. An optimized formulation of fiber enriched bread was developed analizing simultaneously the effect of four independent variables (yeast, moss fiber, fluffy agent and shortening) on the sensory quality of products. Shelf life studies were carried out by storing samples of fiber enriched breads at 20 degrees C and 6 degrees C. At the end of the study, refrigerated samples showed better sensory quality stability.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades funcionales de la fibra del musgo Sphagnum magellanicum y su utilización en la formulación de productos de panadería.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Functional properties of Sphagnum magellanicum fiber and its direct use in formulation of bakery products].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
