<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15142492</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aller de la Fuente, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Hernández, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Luis Román, D A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Calle Valverde, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arranz Santos, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Salazar, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Olmo Martínez, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Analyze the presence of dysplasia in colonoscopy visualized colonic polyps, and the predictive factors for high grade dysplasia. MATERIAL AND METHODS We studied the polyps observed in the colonoscopies carried out during the year 2001. Colonoscopies carried out in 2,144 patients were analyzed, with demonstration of polyps in 326 patients (average age: 67 12,6 years, 63,5% males). 732 polyps were analyzed, with average of 2.27 2 polyps by patient. RESULTS 72% polyps were located distally to splenic flexure, and sigmoid colon was the most frequent location (34.7%). Most of the polyps (86%) were sessile. Only 3% were &gt; 2 cm, and the majority (88%) was &lt; 1 cm. The most prevalent histological type was tubular adenoma (36%). Dysplasia was observed in 42.2% (low grade in 40% and high grade in 2.2%) Size &gt; 1 cm and location proximal to splenic flexure were the only variables with indendent significant association to high grade dysplasia. CONCLUSIONS The presence of high grade dysplasia in the colonic polyps was related in our cohort both to the location of the polyps in the colon and to its size, so that greater risk was for proximal polyps and for polyps &gt; 1 cm.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pólipos de colon: factores predictivos de displasia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Colonic polyps: dysplasia predictive factors].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
