<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15175126</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-7411</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zambrano, Víctor H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias-Fuenmayor, Euro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Al-Awad, Adel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valderrama-Landaeta, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chow-Lee, Gladys</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate hepatic resections in patient with benign and malignant lesions during the years 1997 to 2002 at the Autonomous University Hospital Service of Maracaibo, Venezuela. MATERIALS We carried out 18 hepatic resections for benign and/or malignant lesions; traumatic and infectious lesions were excluded. RESULTS The female sex prevailed with 77.7% and age ranged between third and fourth decade. Three asymptomatic patients (16.6%) and 83.3% symptomatic; pain in upper hemiabdomen 80%. Ultrasonography was employed in 94.4% of cases, CT 83.3%, FNAB 27.7%, arteriography 22.2%, Echo-Doppler 16.6%, laparoscopy 11.1%, hepatic scintigraphy and ERCP, 5.5%. Minor resections represented 61.1%. Major hepatic resections represented 38.8%, with prevalence of left hepatectomy (33.3%). Blood loss was greatest in major hepatic resections with average of 1,242.9 +/- 827.8 ml. Pringles maneuver was carried out in 90% with duration average of 8.5 min; morbidity was 16.6%. Benign tumours prevailed with 66.6%. CONCLUSION The technique of resection with intraparenchymatous identification of pedicles makes it the most successful technique for hepatic resections.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las resecciones hepáticas en pacientes con lesiones benignas y malignas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of hepatic resections in patients with benign and malignant lesions].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
