<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15228015</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramos Pérez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tlapanco Barba, Rubén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cérbulo Vázquez, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velázquez Ramírez, Norma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro Eguiluz, Denisse</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Guerrero, César Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the immunology kind of response Th1 (cytotoxic) or Th2 (humoral) prevailing at peripheral and peritoneal environment at endometriosis women (ENW). STUDY DESIGN Observational, transverse, analytical, retrospective, cases and controls. MATERIAL AND METHODS Cooperative and cytotoxic lymphocytes obtained from peritoneal fluid (PF) and peripheral blood (PB) were used to determine IFN-gamma and IL-2 intracellular synthesis at ENW. IFN-gamma, IL-2, IL-4 and IL-10 concentration were determined at PF, PB at ENW and fertile women (FERW). Results were analyzed by ANOVA, t student and Mann-Whitney tests, accepting p &lt; 0.05, as a statistic difference. RESULTS Peritoneal environment of ENW shows a smaller intracellular synthesis of IFN-gamma and IL-2 at cooperative and cytotoxic T lymphocytes, as in the PF at ENW. The decrease is associated to a smaller percentage of activated, cooperative T lymphocytes and NK cells (p &lt; 0.05, at all the variable), versus FERW. This phenomenon is observed more stressed at the III and IV pathology degree. CONCLUSIONS ENW show a peritoneal environment with a smaller immunology cytotoxic capacity, versus FERW. The discouragement of the immunology cytotoxic capacity increases associated to the pathology intensity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis y abatimiento de las características de la respuesta inmunológica citotóxica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endometriosis and discouragement of immunology cytotoxic characteristics].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
