<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15228897</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mosquera, María del Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echevarría, Juan Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guisasola, María Eulalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Ory, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The comparison of serological methods used by the laboratories participating in the Network for the Elimination of Measles to diagnose measles virus infection as well as differential diagnosis with other exanthematic diseases are compared. MATERIALS AND METHODS One panel of 20 serum samples including measles (12), rubella (4), parvovirus B19 (2) and dengue (2) infections was established. All cases were diagnosed by detection of specific IgM. The panel was sent to the laboratories of the Network. The results were compared with those obtained at the reference laboratory. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION Regarding measles, IgM response from 20 laboratories (19 by ELISA and 1 by indirect immunofluorescence) was obtained, with an agreement of 91.5%. Related to rubella IgM, replay from 6 laboratories, using ELISA, was received, with an agreement of 98.7%. With respect to parvovirus B19 IgM, response from 10 laboratories (8 by ELISA and 2 by indirect immunofluorescence) was obtained, with an agreement of 94.6%. Results about dengue virus were not reported by any laboratory. CONCLUSION Some laboratories from the network should review the methods used for the diagnosis of measles and other exanthematic diseases. The results reassert the need for a reference laboratory to support confirmation of the results.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de los procedimientos serológicos de los laboratorios del Plan para la Eliminación del Sarampión en el diagnóstico de exantemas víricos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison of serological procedures used for the diagnosis of viral exanthema in laboratories participating in the measles elimination plan].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
