<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15243654</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez, Fernando Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurosciences have contributed to give support to the significance objects (mother, father, among others), affects, environment and different early experiences have in the unfolding and development of the child's mental structure and in this manner to throw light on intersubjective and intrapsychic relationships. This review focused on the impact of early mothering experiences and of the environment on molecular events linked to the processes of neurogenesis, synaptogenesis and the construction of circuits of processing and signalling, mainly in the hippocampus (structure connected with the processes of learning, memory and the control of response to stressors). Therefore, normal development,as well as mental pathology, is not the mere result from the action of present stressors (synchronic view), but its deepest roots lie in the matrix generated by the early experiences between mother and child and the environment inputs (diachronic view). Therefore, early experience, as well as secure attachment, can modulate the individual resilience in the face of future adversity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jun-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencias tempranas y entorno: su impacto en el neurodesarrollo y la creación de los procesos mentales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Early experiences and environment: their impact on neurodevelopment and the creation of mental processes].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
