<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15253340</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morera, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fontes, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernáldez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gorospe, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gavilán, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study in an animal model the local healing process after partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis. MATERIAL AND METHODS Partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis was performed in 17 New Zealand rabbits. Experimental animals were gradually sacrificed and the laryngotracheal complex was removed to proceed to a histopathological study. RESULTS An acute inflammatory response followed by a chronic inflammatory process was found in the surgical site. Normal tissue architecture was established after an eight week period. Anteroposterior and transverse diameters at all levels of the upper respiratory tract were not significantly altered at any time along the healing process. Experimental animals remained free from symptoms during the follow-up period. CONCLUSIONS These results support that partial cricoid resection with thyrotracheal anastomosis is a safe procedure for the treatment of severe laryngotracheal stenosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios histopatológicos en la unión quirúrgica en animales de experimentación sometidos a resección cricoidea parcial y anastomosis tirotraqueal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Histopathological changes at the surgical site in experimental animals following partial cricoid resection and thyrotracheal anastomosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
