<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15282060</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanz, Ginés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuppoletti, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roig, Eulalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrer, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, Wladimiro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Villa, Félix</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llancaqueo, Marcelo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVE In patients with congestive heart failure, neurohormonal activation plays an important role in disease progression and prognosis. The aim of this study was to document the evolution of neurohormonal activation after heart transplantation. PATIENTS AND METHOD Thirty-seven patients on the waiting list for heart transplantation were included in the study. Plasma levels of angiotensin II, aldosterone, endothelin, atrial natriuretic peptide and adrenomedullin were measured before heart transplantation and again 1, 4, 9 and 12 months afterwards. Plasma levels of norepinephrine and renin were measured before and 1 month after heart transplantation. RESULTS The levels of angiotensin II, norepinephrine and renin showed a nonsignificant trend towards reduction. The levels of aldosterone were unchanged, and an increase in endothelin levels was seen 9 and 12 months after transplantation. Plasma levels of atrial natriuretic peptide and adrenomedullin were significantly lower 1, 4, 9 and 12 months after heart transplantation compared to pretransplant levels. CONCLUSIONS During the first several months after heart transplantation there were no significant reductions in plasma levels of angiotensin II, aldosterone and endothelin, and there were significant reductions soon after surgery in peptides with a predominantly vasodilator effect (atrial natriuretic peptide and adrenomedullin). This unfavorable neurohormonal profile may contribute to the development of posttransplant complications such as edema, arterial hypertension and endothelial dysfunction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Activación neurohormonal en la insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva: se normaliza después del transplante cardíaco?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neurohormonal activation in congestive heart failure: does it normalize after heart transplantation?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
