<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15332374</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morales de Sétien, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sepúlveda, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallardo-Zurita, Paola</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Medical and surgical teams consult psychiatrists when abnormal behavior or psychopathological traits are observed in their patients. AIM To describe the experience of liaison psychiatry teams in public hospitals. MATERIAL AND METHODS Analysis of 128 consultations, involving 110 patients. Eighty eight patients were subjected to the structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV-TR Axis I Disorders--Patient Edition, the Mini Mental State score and to a search for personality disorders. RESULTS The most commonly consulted problems were depression in 44 patients, substance abuse in 29 and suicidal behavior in 21. The psychiatric study detected that 8% of patients were asymptomatic, 8% had stress reactions, 16.5% had substance abuse, 14.6% had alcohol abuse, 11% had a major depression, 10% had delirium or dementia, 9% had anxiety disorders, 4% schizophrenia, 18% personality disorders and 19% had suicidal behaviors. CONCLUSIONS Psychiatric consultations in medical and surgical services are common and have a wide variety of severity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psiquiatría de enlace en servicios médico-quirúrgicos de dos hospitales de Santiago.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Liaison psychiatry in two public hospitals of Santiago].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
