<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15338970</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Swieszkowski, Sandra P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez de la Hoz, Ricardo A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Gabriela B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poyatos, Maria E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Martínez, José A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brito, Viviana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lakowsky, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sampo, Eduardo A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The exercise testing is still the most common test used to stratify the patients's risk of new events following an acute myocardial infarction, but about 20 to 40% of the patients can not perform it appropriately. Since the electrocardiographic test with dobutamine has proved to be easy and safe, our aim was to evaluate its capacity to predict the results of the exercise testing on patients after an acute myocardial infarction. A total of 210 patients (average of age 60.5+/-11.7 years old and 23.3% females) recovering from a first uncomplicated myocardial infarction, were consecutively included. An electrocardiographic test with dobutamine was performed during the fifth day of admission, and an exercise test during the sixth. The development of chest pain and/or a descending ST segment &gt; or = 1 mm during a test qualified it as positive for ischemia. The sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predictive values of both tests were determinated, as well as the congruence on their results, a p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significative. Whereas 91 patients achieved a positive result on the electrocardiographic dobutamine tests, 54 patients were positive during exercise. On the other hand, both tests came up positive in 49 patients, and negative in 114 patients. The hemodynamic variables were similar during both tests, except in those patients with negative results with both methods, who developed a higher maximal arterial pressure and double product during exercise. Accordingly, the electrocardiographic dobutamine test showed a sensivity 90.17%, a specificity 73%, positive and negative predictive values 54% and 95.8%, respectively, to predict the results of the exercise testing, with a Kappa value of 0.52. In conclusion, the electrocardiographic dobutamine test showed not only to predict the results of the exercise testing adequately with a high negative predictive value, but also to be safe, a useful and simple diagnostic tool for the evaluation of patients after an acute myocardial infarction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor del test de dobutamina comparado con la ergometría en la evaluación de riesgo coronario.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison between electrocardiographic test with dobutamine and exercise stress testing on coronary risk stratification].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
