<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15368024</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, F A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Salazar, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Calvo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Carballal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Leal, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the surgical management of patients with trigeminal neuralgia after failed microvascular decompression. PATIENTS AND METHODS Between 1993 and 2002, exploration of the posterior fossa was performed in 60 patients with trigeminal neuralgia. Records were analyzed retrospectively for those patients who needed another surgical procedure due to recurrence of pain, describing which procedure was performed, postoperative results and complications, and also the intraoperative findings when posterior fossa reexploration was realized. RESULTS Eighteen patients had trigeminal neuralgia recurrence requiring a new surgical intervention, that consisted in a fossa posterior reexploration in nine patients and percutaneous radiofrequency termal rhizotomy in the other nine patients. Among the repeat operations, there was negative exploration in 7 patients (77%), and a partial sensory rhizotomy was performed. Most of thermocoagulations (5/9) were performed in old patients or patients with anestesic contraindication for the fossa posterior reexploration. CONCLUSION Fossa posterior reexploration is an effective and safe surgical attitude in the treatment of recurrent trigeminal neuralgia after failed microvascular decompression. Partial sensory rhizotomy is recommended when the reexploration is negative.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la recidiva de la neuralgia del trigémino tras descompresión microvascular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Management of recurrent trigeminal neuralgia after failed microvascular decompression].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
