<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15379051</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Trujillo, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acevedo, Attia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Favi, Myriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roos, Orietta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yung, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND A WHO experts committee recommended the substitution of antirabic vaccines produced in nervous tissue, by vaccines produced in tissue cultures. AIM To compare the immunogenic capacity of antirabic vaccines CRL (produced in nervous tissue) and Verorab (produced in tissue culture), used for pre-exposure prophylaxis in humans. PATIENTS AND METHODS Fifty four volunteers were immunized for this study. The first group, vaccinated with CLR was treated with a scheme of 4 subcutaneous peri umbilical doses in days 0, 3, 7 and 28. The second group, vaccinated with Verorab vaccine was treated with a scheme of 3 intramuscular doses in deltoid zone at days 0, 7 and 28. Blood samples were obtained at days 0, 7, 42 and 365 to measure neutralizing antibodies using the Inhibition of Fluorescent Focus Technique (RFFIT). RESULTS At day seven, a primary non protective immunologic response was observed in both groups, with titers significantly higher in the group vaccinated with Verorab. At day 42, no differences were observed. At day 365, all subjects vaccinated with Verorab and 50% of individuals vaccinated with CRL had protective antibody titers (p &lt;0.05). CONCLUSIONS The vaccine produced in cell breeds (Verorab) produces a better an faster immunologic response compared to the CRL vaccine.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la capacidad inmunogénica de la vacuna antirrábica tipo Fuenzalida- Palacios (CRL) y de la vacuna antirrábica de cultivo celular (Verorab) en personas con tratamiento preexposición.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Immune response of suckling mouse brain (CRL) rabies vaccine and tissue culture rabies vaccine (Verorab) in pre-exposure prophylaxis in humans].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
