<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15373989</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mesa Rubio, Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romo Peña, Elías</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Esteban, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vallés Belsué, Federico</dc:author>
<dc:author>Anguita Sánchez, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ojeda Pineda, Soledad</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz Ortiz, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES There is little information on the clinical and functional course of patients with heart failure secondary to dilated cardiomyopathy due to hypertension. The objectives of our study were to assess the clinical and functional course of these patients, and to identify possible predictors of prognosis. PATIENTS AND METHOD We evaluated a series of 49 patients with this condition diagnosed in our hospital from 1994 to 2003. Mean age was 63(11) years, and 40% were women. Left ventricular ejection fraction was 30.1(4.8)%. Follow-up was 45(23) months (median, 41 months). RESULTS Four-year survival was 0.84, the 4-year rate of hospitalization due to heart failure was 0.12, and likelihood of readmission-free survival was 0.80 at 4 years. Left ventricular ejection fraction increased from 30.1(4.8)% to 57.6(13.5)% (P&lt; .001). An unfavorable clinical and functional outcome at 4 years (death, readmission for heart failure or persistence of dilated cardiomyopathy) was recorded in only in 40% of the patients. Multivariate analysis with the Cox model showed appropriate control of blood pressure to be the only independent predictor of a favorable clinical outcome (absence of death or readmission for heart failure) (hazard ratio = 4.58; 95% CI, 1.32-9.83; P=.032). CONCLUSIONS The course of patients with severe dilated cardiomyopathy due to hypertension was favorable in 60% of cases. Adequate control of blood pressure was the only independent predictor of a favorable clinical outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución clínica y reversibilidad de la disfunción sistólica en pacientes con miocardiopatía dilatada hipertensiva e insuficiencia cardíaca crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical outcome and reversibility of systolic dysfunction in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy due to hypertension and chronic heart failure].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
