<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15455495</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Neira, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albalate, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llamas, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Oña, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caramelo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Deudero, J J P</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED The sudden interruption of recombinant human erythropoietin (rHuEPO) in end-stage renal disease (ESRD) patients leads to rapid anemization. The mechanisms of this phenomenon are, however, insufficiently understood. The present study examined the response to immediate rHuEPO withdrawal in dialysis patients. METHODS 10 chronic hemodialysis (HD) patients regularly receiving rHuEPO were studied. rHuEPO was stopped and reinitiated after 7 days. Reticulocyte profile, haemoglobin and haematocrit were measured at 0, 7 and 15 days. As a complementary study, and with the purpose of analyzying whether uremia was a relevant factor, 10 non-uremic male Wistar rats were treated with rHuEPO. After two weeks, rHuEPO was withdrawn in 5 animals, and continued for 7 additional days in the remainder. The same variables than in the human study were determined. RESULTS Changes in reticulocyte subtypes from baseline to day 7 were: total 18.2 +/- 0.9 vs 14.3 +/- 1.8% (p &lt; 0.06); high-fluorescence (HFR): 2.6 +/- 0.4 vs 0.75 +/- 0.2 (p &lt; 0.001); medium-fluorescence (MFR): 13.0 +/- 1.1 vs 6.6 +/- 0.9% (p &lt; 0.02); and low-fluorescence (LFR): 84.2 +/- 1.4 vs 92.7 +/- 1% (p NS). The baseline pattern was recovered upon 7 days of rHuEPO reinitiation (p NS). Mean hemoglobin and hematocrit decreased by day 14 (p &lt; 0.02) in spite of rHuEPO reinitiation at day 7. In non-uremic rats, changes were similar to that in the ESRD patients. CONCLUSION rHuEPO induces changes in the reticulocyte pattern, consisting in a reduction of immature reticulocytes. These changes appear to be independent of the presence of uremia. Accordingly, complete rHuEPO withdrawal in HD patients will cause a rapidly-developing anaemia due to an alteration in the reticulocyte maturation series; therefore, sudden rHuEPO interruption should be avoided whenever is possible. As a collateral application, the specific changes described herein have potential use for detecting illegal administration of rHuEPO.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta reticulocitaria tras cese inmediato de administración de eritropoyetina recombinante humana en enfermos en hemodiálisis crónica. Implicaciones en la terapia de la anemia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reticulocyte response after immediate withdrawal of recombinant human erythropoietin in chronic hemodialysis patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
