<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15467990</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jiménez-Corral, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrera-Izquierdo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocastegui-Candial, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrera-Izquierdo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morán-Sánchez, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Recio, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The damage caused to the central nervous system by lightning can be immediate or delayed. Cerebrovascular accidents are usually an infrequent complication of lightning strikes. CASE REPORT We report the case of a patient who was hit by lightning and then developed an acute bilateral intraparenchymatous haemorrhage in the basal ganglia and the left internal capsule. DISCUSSION Few cases of intracranial haemorrhages secondary to lightning strikes have been reported. We carry out a review and analysis of the literature currently available on the subject. A number of theories have been put forward that attempt to explain the mechanism behind these haemorrhages in patients who have been hit by lightning. The reason why there is a predilection for the basal ganglia is unknown, although it could be linked to the particular features of the vascularisation of the area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Sep 16-30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia intracraneal secundaria a fulguración por rayo: presentación de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intracranial haemorrhage secondary to a lightning strike: a case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
