<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1549757</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED We reviewed the clinical data of 2,726 patients from 14 different hospitals in Spain to evaluate the clinical performance of the Björk-Shiley Monostrut valve. Between January 1983 and December 1987 a total of 1,128 aortic valve replacements, 1,165 mitral valve replacements, and 433 double valve replacements, were performed. Afterwards it was necessary to perform 40 new valvular implantations to either change the prosthesis or substitute another native valve. A total of 3,199 prosthetic valves were implanted. The total follow-up was 5,457 patient-years (means: 24 months), and was complete in 97.9% of all cases. There were 181 hospital deaths (6.6%). Late mortality was 5.9% (151 patients). Actuarial 5 years survival for the whole group was 81.9 +/- 1.4%. In the different groups survival was 85.3 +/- 1.8% for aortic valve replacement, 81.9 +/- 1.9% for mitral valve replacement and 72 +/- 5.3% for double valvular replacement. Actuarial 5 year freedom from all valve-related events (hospital mortality included) was 65.8 +/- 2.2%. Without hospital mortality, this percentage increases to 70.9 +/- 2.3%. There was no reported case of valve thrombosis or structural deterioration or dysfunction. There were 47 cases of non-structural dysfunction of which 14 were fatal. CONCLUSIONS The Björk Shiley Monostrut valve can be considered a good prosthetic valvular substitute in the face of the absence of valve thrombosis and structural dysfunction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cinco años de experiencia con la prótesis de Björk-Shiley Monostrut. Estudio multicéntrico español Monostrut. Grupo Español de Estudio Monostrut.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[5 years of experience with the Björk-Shiley Monostrut prosthesis. A multicenter Spanish Monostruct study. The Spanish Monostrut Study Group].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
