<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15536958</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Ledesma, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bujons Tur, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villavicencio Mavrich, Humberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puigvert Martínez, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cetina Errando, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iglesias Guzmán, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To report a very unfrequent case of penile hematoma secondary to rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of the penis during intercourse. METHODS 35-year-old patient presenting at the emergency department with a half moon shape hematoma in the dorsal part of the penis, not much painful, developed when initiating intercourse that we believe was a rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of the penis. RESULTS In spite of the few cases of rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of the penis described, and after differential diagnosis with other causes of acute penis, conservative attitude with anti-inflammatory drugs and compressive bandage was undertaken. CONCLUSIONS The rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of the penis is an unfrequent pathology which should be taken into differential diagnosis in a patient consulting with acute penile edema, the attitude is conservative with complete recovery without sequel.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hematoma peneano secundario a rotura de la vena dorsal superficial del pene.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Penile hematoma secondary to rupture of the superficial dorsal vein of the penis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
