<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15538816</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nombela, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernáez, M L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fluconazole is one of the most useful drugs in the treatment of fungal systemic infections which frequently affect non immunocompetent individuals. However, the emergence of resistant strains in recent years may severely limit its usefulness in future. Although there are several described mechanisms involved in resistance to azoles, recent genetic studies demonstrate the role of specific genes in clinical resistance. Currently, the best characterized are the MDR1 and CDR1 genes, which code members of the MFS or ABC family of drug transporters, respectively. These proteins respond to the membrane potential (MFS) or hydrolyse ATP (ABC) thus promoting drug efflux and therefore reducing its intracellular accumulation. It has been shown that the mRNA from these genes is frequently increased in some Candida albicans resistant strains from patients receiving long term azole treatment. The development of molecular genetic tools in C. albicans is allowing characterization of their role in this and other important processes in the fungal cell.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos moleculares y genéticos de la resistencia a azoles en Candida albicans.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Molecular and genetic aspects of resistance to azoles in Candida albicans].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
