<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15554586</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cervera-Paz, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez de la Iglesia, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manrique Rodríguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES The study goal was to evaluate the hearing follow up results in patients who underwent surgery for congenital aural atresia. We studied hearing results and correlated them with Jahrsdoerfer prognostic classification. Protocols management of unilateral and bilateral atresia auris are written considering to our results and other authors. METHODS We conducted a retrospective review of 12 ears who underwent surgery for congenital aural atresia between 1989 and 2002. CT scan was used to evaluate Jahrsdoerfer prognostic classification and the correlation with the hearing results. RESULTS There are significant statistical differences (p = 0.003) in air-bone gap closure before and after surgery, also a lineal significant correlation (p = 0.016) between Jahrsdoerfer prognostic classification and air-bone gap closure. CONCLUSION Atresiaplasty surgery in individuals with congenital aural atresia can yield good hearing results in selected cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de la Atresia auris. Estudio retrospectivo de nuestros resultados y correlación con los criterios pronósticos de Jahrsdoerfer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Surgery for Atresia auris. Retrospective study of our results and correlation with Jahrsdoerfer prognostic criterium].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
