<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15559190</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lugaresi, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lavaroni, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vanzini, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguirre, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torioni de Echaide, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnosis of bovine brucellosis using PCR in blood and milk samples from two dairy herds were compared to in vitro isolation, complement fixation test (CF), competitive ELISA (C-ELISA) in serum, and indirect ELISA (I-ELISA) in milk. Samples were obtained from 99 cows vaccinated with Brucella abortus strain 19, from a naturally infected herd (A), whose cows were also vaccinated with B. abortus strain RB51 as adults, and 100 from brucellosis free herd (B). In herd A, PCR identified 14 B. abortus infected cows: nine infected with wild type, and five with wild type and RB51, B. abortus S 19 was not identified. B. abortus biotype 1 was isolated from one cow. All cows infected with a wild strain of B. abortus were positive in serologic tests. Brucella was not found in herd B using PCR. Serological test showed 100% sensitivity related to PCR. The specificity for CF, C-ELISA and I-ELISA was 100%, 99% and 95% respectively. PCR could be useful to identify Brucella biotypes and to complement serologic tests.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluaci칩n de la reacci칩n en cadena de la polimerasa para el diagn칩stico de la brucelosis en un reba침o lechero infectado con Brucella spp.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to diagnose brucellosis in a Brucella infected herd].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
