<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15563798</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ahumada, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vioque, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE We intended to estimate the prevalence of varicose veins in the mature population of the Valencia Community and to analyze its relationship with socio-demographic variables, self-reported health status, body mass index and the presence of hemorrhoids, tobacco smoking, alcohol consumption and physical activity. SUBJECTS AND METHOD Information on self-reported varicose veins was collected from 1,778 adults older than 14 years (819 men and 959 women) who participated in the Health and Nutrition Survey of the Valencia Community (Spain). We estimated the prevalence of varicose veins by age groups and sex. To explore the association between varicose veins and variables, we estimated adjusted odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (CI 95%) by multiple logistic regression. RESULTS The overall prevalence of varicose veins was 16.4%, with a much higher prevalence in women that in men (26.7% versus 5.5%) and with older age. Gender and age were the 2 strongest predictors of varicose veins in multivariate analysis. Women had seven times more risk than men (OR = 7.01; CI 95%, 4.52-10.87) and those older than 35 years almost tripled the risk with respect to those aged 15-24 years. A body mass index of 30 kg/m2, a poor self-reported health status and hemorrhoids were significantly associated with the presence of varicose veins. Employers showed higher risk than workers. A moderate alcohol consumption (&lt; or = 1 drink/day) was associated with a protective effect (OR = 0.50; CI 95%, 0.28-0.88). Tobacco smoking and physical activity were not associated with varicose veins. CONCLUSIONS Although being a woman and having an advanced age were the strongest predictors of varicose veins, other factors such as a high BMI, poor health status, hemorrhoids and some professional categories may be also important factors in their presentation. A moderate alcohol consumption seems to have a protective effect.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Nov 13 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de varices en adultos y factores asociados.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence and risk factors of varicose veins in adults].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
