<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15574285</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Benet Rodríguez, Mikhail</dc:author>
<dc:author>Apollinaire Penneni, Juan J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The association between family history of essential high blood pressure (FH of HBP) and the cardiovascular hyperactivity to the isometric exercise is not well known; that is why the aim of this study was to describe this relation and to determine whether it is independent of the presence of cardiovascular risk factors. PATIENTS AND METHOD We carried out a correlational descriptive study with a sample of 1855 people of both sexes between 18 and 70 years of age. The cardiovascular hyperactivity, expression of the cardiovascular response to the activity of the sympathetic nervous system (SNS), was determined by means of the test of the sustained weight (TSW). Comparisons of the values of cardiovascular reactivity were developed between individuals with and without FH of HBP and a model of logistical regression. The level of statistical significance was 95%. RESULTS The arterial blood pressure at the end of the TSW was higher in individuals with FH of HBP independently of the age group. The cardiovascular hyperactivity, measured by means of they systolic index of cardiovascular reactivity, was also significantly higher in subjects with FH of HBP. Finally, individuals with FH of HBP showed a higher risk (more than 5 times) of having cardiovascular hyperactivity (OR = 5.16; CI 95%, 3.51-7.59), this association being independent of other cardiovascular factors of risk. CONCLUSIONS The FH of HBP is independently related to the cardiovascular hyperactivity, to the isometric exercise, of other cardiovascular risks factors. These elements help explain the relationship between cardiovascular hyperactivity, the activity of SNS and essential high blood pressure, at least in an important group of people.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Nov 27 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperreactividad cardiovascular en pacientes con antecedentes familiares de hipertensión arterial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiovascular hyperactivity in patients with family history of high blood pressure].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
