<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15578282</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Toldos, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borras Blasco, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almiñana Almiñana, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarado Valero, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Ramos, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To study the impact of topical treatment with autologous serum on the clinical evolution of persistent corneal epithelial defects (PED) and to observe its effect on squamous metaplasia in 7 cases of dry eye. PATIENTS AND METHODS In this prospective, clinical, non-comparative case series study we evaluated a total of 17 eyes (14 patients). We analized the clinical evolution (fluorescein staining, Schirmer's I and II tests and photographic control) of PED in these patients, to whom 20% autologous serum eyedrops were applied for 28 days. Using impression cytology technique (Tseng's method) we evaluated the involution of squamous metaplasia in 7 eyes of 4 patients with ocular cicatricial pemphigoid and dry eye who were treated with autologous serum. The Wilconxon test was used for the statistical treatment of the data. RESULTS The epithelial defect healed within 2 weeks in 6 eyes (35.2%). Eight eyes (47%) healed within 2-4 weeks and 3 eyes (17.6%) did not heal after week 4. The duration of PED, before serum therapy was 36 days. Six of seven eyes treated with autologous serum presented an involution of squamous metaplasia 28 days after initiation of the serum drops. CONCLUSIONS Autologous serum treatment accelerates PED healing. Autologous serum application causes an involution of squamous metaplasia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de defectos epiteliales persistentes mediante suero autólogo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of persistent epithelial defects using autologous serum application].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
