<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15631204</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bello, Helia T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Patricia Q</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, Mariana Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trabal, Natalia F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zemelman, Raúl Z</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, Gerardo R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mella, Sergio M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Klebsiella pneumoniae is a pathogenic bacterium frequently isolated from nosocomial samples, specially the subspecie pneunonlae, with extensive antibiolic resistance profiles, including third generation cepbhalosporiis, aminoglycosides and quinolones. This is specially true for those strains producing extended spectrum beta lactamases (ESBL). AIM To investigate the susceptibility to gentamicin, amikacin and ciprofloxacin and the presence of some aminogloycoside modifying enzyme (AMEs) among nosocomial strains of K pneumoniae subspecie pneumoniae producing ESBL. MATERIAL AND METHODS The antibiotic resistant patterns and the level of resistance (minimal inhibitory concentration, MIC) of 100 strains, isoklted from sel ,eal bospitals of dcifferent Chilean cities, were deterl,in,ed. Tbe presence of some aminoglycosides modifying enzyme (AMEs) was investigated by PCR. RESULTS Sixty five percent of strains were resistant to gentamicin, 47% were resistant to amikacin, and 29% were resistant to ciprofloxacin. The most frequent AMEs genes detected were the aac(6')-Ib gene (6'N-Acetyltransferase type Ib enzyme) in 69% of strains, conferring resistance to amikacin, kanamycin, tobramycin, and nieoniycin, and the gene aac(3)-IIa (3-Acetyltransferase type 3-IIa enzyme), in 36% of strains, conferring resistance to gentamlicin. CONCLUSIONS Among nosocomial strains of K pneumoniae subspecie pneumoniae isolaterd from Chilean hospitals, there is an association between the production of ESBL and the resistance to others antimicrobial agents, especially aminoglycosides. Nevertheless, 71% of isolates are susceptible to ciprofloxacin.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resistencia a gentamicina, amikacina y ciprofloxacina en cepas hospitalarias de klebsiella pneumoniae subespecie pneumoniae productoras de beta-lactamasas de espectro extendido.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Resistance to gentamicin, amikacin and ciprofloxacin among nosocomial isolates of klebsiella pneumoniae subspecie pneumoniae producing extended spectrum beta-lactamases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
