<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15632994</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calvo-Rubal, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Laza, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Spagnuolo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sgarbi, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soria-Vargas, V R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prinzo, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is worlwide accepted that in almost 60% of cases, anatomical variants in the Circle of Willis can be found. Some of them are associated with vascular malformations such as aneurysms. The knowledge of these anatomical variants is of vital importance when facing surgery, being the aims to preserve arteries in unusual localisations, which when injured can determine invalidating sequelae. The authors have reviewed 192 cerebral hemispheres, finding three variants in the anterior Circle of Willis: Azigos anterior cerebral artery; Median artery of the corpus callosum and accessory middle cerebral artery. The authors make an anatomical description of the findings, their angiographical correlation, and describe the influence of these changes during surgery of aneurysms in the involved regions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variaciones del sector anterior del polígono de Willis. Correlación anatomo-angiográfica y su implicancia en la cirugía de aneurismas intracraneanos. (Arterias: ácigos cerebral anterior, mediana del cuerpo calloso y cerebral media accesoria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Variants of the anterior circle of Willis. Anatomic and angiografic correlation and its implications in the surgery of intracranial aneurysms. (Acigos anterior cerebral artery, median artery of the corpus callosum and accessory middle cerebral artery)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
