<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15709784</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco Santos, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Becerra, Aldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Moreno, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bioremediation is a spontaneous or controlled process in which biological, mainly microbiological, methods are used to degrade or transform contaminants to non or less toxic products, reducing the environmental pollution. The most important parameters to define a contaminated site are: biodegradability, contaminant distribution, lixiviation grade, chemical reactivity of the contaminants, soil type and properties, oxygen availability and occurrence of inhibitory substances. Biological treatments of organic contaminations are based on the degradative abilities of the microorganisms. Therefore the knowledge on the physiology and ecology of the biological species or consortia involved as well as the characteristics of the polluted sites are decisive factors to select an adequate biorremediation protocol. Basidiomycetes which cause white rot decay of wood are able to degrade lignin and a variety of environmentally persistent pollutants. Thus, white rot fungi and their enzymes are thought to be useful not only in some industrial process like biopulping and biobleaching but also in bioremediation. This paper provides a review of different aspects of bioremediation technologies and recent advances on ligninolytic metabolism research.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamientos biológicos de suelos contaminados; contaminación por hidrocarburos. Aplicaciones de hongos en tratamientos de biorrecuperación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Biological treatments for contaminated soils: hydrocarbon contamination. Fungal applications in bioremediation treatment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
