<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15709503</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sarachaga, Ignacio Herraiz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bialkowski, Jacek</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez-Balda, José I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, Ramón Bermúdez-Cañete</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kusa, Jacek</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Castro, Marta Hernández</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía, Sandra Matiz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez, Fernando Rueda</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Venous access through the superior caval vein is mandatory to study the pulmonary arteries in patients with a Glenn anastomosis. In complex congenital heart disease, repeat catheterizations may lead to iliac vein thrombosis and superior access is needed. In order to avoid the internal jugular venous puncture, we have used puncture of the antecubital vein as an elective access. MATERIAL Brachial puncture was attempted in 37 patients. Mean age: 10 years (3.1-33.5). 2.45 heart surgeries and 3.6 cardiac catheterizations per patient had been previously performed in this group. 40% of patients had bilateral iliac vein thrombosis. TECHNIQUE Axillary vein external compression, venous puncture and introduction of 4-6 F sheath. RESULTS Venous access through brachial vein was achieved in 34 of 37 pts (91.8%). Diagnostic catheterization was done in all, balloon test occlusion of the pulmonary valve in 3 and pulmonary artery branch dilation in 6 pts. COMPLICATIONS 2 late thrombosis of the right brachial vein (6%). CONCLUSIONS Antecubital venous puncture is an alternative and useful technique that allows easy catheterization of superior caval vein, pulmonary artery and right heart chambers. It is associated with minor complication rate, avoiding internal jugular vein puncture. Certain therapeutic procedures can be performed through such route.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acceso venoso percutáneo braquial: Su utilidad en el cateterismo diagnóstico e intervencionista en cardiopatías complejas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Brachial percutaneous venous access. Its usefulness in the diagnostic and interventionist catheterism of complex cardiopathies].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
