<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15747702</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López de Castro, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lucas, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sariñena, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Busquets, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Guasch, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES The aim of the present study was to consider the feasibility of Arndt-type bronchial blockers in thoracic surgery. PATIENTS AND METHODS We enrolled the first 11 patients undergoing uncomplicated thoracic surgery expected to be of short duration. The following variables were recorded: age, weight, height, diagnosis, type of surgery, side where the blocker was used, time needed for positioning, the number of times the blocker was malpositioned according to fiberoptic bronchoscopy, time of lung isolation, duration of surgery, and effectiveness of lung collapse. RESULTS Eleven blockers were placed in 5 women and 6 men aged between 25 and 81 years old (mean +/- SD, 52.73 +/- 22.12 years). Weight ranged from 45 to 88 Kg (mean 65.82 +/- 11.86 Kg). Height ranged from 157 to 175 cm (mean 166 +/- 5.76 cm). Time needed for positioning the blocker ranged from 2 to 30 minutes (median 5 minutes, interquartile range 1-12). According to fiberoptic bronchoscopy, the bronchial cuff was malpositioned, with herniation into the carina, in 1 case. Duration of surgery ranged from 30 minutes to 4 hours (median 70 minutes, interquartile range 50-210 minutes). Lung collapse was excellent in 9 cases and acceptable in 2 according to the surgeon. CONCLUSIONS Our initial experience with bronchial blockers in elective surgery has shown that time for initial positioning is acceptably short and that surgical conditions are excellent in most cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia inicial con los bloqueadores bronquiales tipo Arndt en cirugía torácica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Initial experience with Arndt-type bronchial blockers in thoracic surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
