<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15757581</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ardanza-Trevijano, Bruno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labora, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pedraz, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solinís, María Angeles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canut, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Gascón, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isla, Arantxazu</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION This study evaluates the efficacy of various antimicrobial treatments for orofacial infections on the basis of pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) criteria. METHODS A complete a literature search was undertaken to establish the MIC90 values of the five microorganisms most frequently isolated in odontogenic infections and the pharmacokinetic parameters of 13 antibiotics used in these infections. Pharmacokinetic simulations were then carried out with mean population parameters and efficacy indexes were calculated for the 47 treatment regimens analyzed. For drugs showing time-dependent antibacterial killing, the time above MIC (t &gt; MIC) was calculated. For drugs with concentration-dependent bactericidal activity, the AUC/MIC was calculated. RESULTS Amoxicillin-clavulanic (500 mg/8 h or 1000 mg/12 h) and clindamycin (300 mg/6 h) in the time-dependent killing group and moxifloxacin (400 mg/24 h) in the concentration-dependent group showed adequate efficacy indexes against the five pathogens considered to be the most commonly implicated in odontogenic infections. The spiramycin plus metronidazole combination, present in the commercial formulation Rhodogyl, did not reach satisfactory PK/PD indexes. CONCLUSION PK/PD indexes, which are useful predictors of the potential efficacy of antibacterial therapy, were used with ontogenic infections in the present study. The PK/PD simulations showed that amoxicillin-clavulanic, clindamycin and moxifloxacin were the most suitable antibiotics for this kind of infection. Clinical trials are required to confirm that this methodology is useful in these pathologic processes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis farmacocinético/farmacodinámico (PK/PD) de la antibioterapia en odontoestomatología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic analysis of antibiotic therapy in dentistry and stomatology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
