<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15768152</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Neira L, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fischer G, Sylvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres C, María Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferreiro M, Myriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Milinarsky T, Aída</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giadrosich R, Vinka</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arriagada M, Marina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arinoviche S, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND An important loss of bone mineral density, associated to pain and fractures, has been reported in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). AIM To measure bone mineral density among children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) that completed the remission induction phase with chemotherapy, that lasts 30 days. PATIENTS AND METHODS children with ALL, admitted to the oncology unit of a general hospital were considered eligible for the study. body composition and bone mineral density were measured by dual energy x ray absorptiometry (DEXA). each child with ALL was paired with a healthy control. RESULTS Fourteen children age 1 to 11 years, completed the study, Spine and femoral bone mineral densities were significantly lower than in their matched controls. No differences in total body bone mineral density or content were observed. Children with ALL had a lower fat free mass and a higher fat mass than their matched controls. There was a significant correlation between fat free mass and bone mineral content. CONCLUSIONS After one month of chemotherapy, children with ALL had a lower bone mineral density in the spine and femur and a lower fat free mass.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Densitometría ósea en niños leucémicos al completar el primer mes de quimioterapia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bone mineral density in leukemic children after completing one month of chemotherapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
