<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15782644</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Trinidad Ruíz, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Palomino, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero García, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pardo Romero, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pantoja Hernández, C G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blasco Huelva, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pino Rivero, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marcos García, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sudden deafness goes on being a clinical entity of unknown cause for which several theories and treatments have been proposed. We are reporting a comparative study of two different protocols that we have performed on 60 patients (divided in two groups of 30) diagnosed and admitted with sudden hearing loss between 1989 and 2003. The main goal is to prove if there is a statistical and significant difference among both, in respect of the audiologic improvement obtained, after two weeks of therapy at east. We have applied the normal approximation of Mann-Whitney's test and we can argue, after its result, our current protocol (piracetam, pentoxifiline, metilprednisolone), which includes 4 days of endovenous treatment another 10 days at home. The presence of vestibular symptoms darkens the prognosis since about 95% of the patients with them have not improved significantly (p&lt;0.05).</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio estadístico y resultados clínicos de la comparación de dos protocolos diferentes en el tratamiento de la hipoacusia brusca.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Statistical study and clinical results by comparison of two different protocols in the treatment of sudden hearing loss].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
