<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15849961</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Juan Carlos Martínez</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Río, Marlene Isabel Armesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Suárez, Idalia Morelia Baró</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sosa, Mayelin Mirabal</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, Francisco Domínguez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Azze, Rolando Felipe Ochoa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A randomized, controlled and double-blind study was conducted in young adults aged 18-20 aimed at evaluating the reactogenecity and immunogenecity of vaz-TyVi, a vaccine of polyssacharide Vi from Salmonella typhi. They were distributed into 3 groups: immunized with a dose of Vax-TyVi (Finlay Institute), TYPHIM Vi (Pasteur-Mérieux) or vax-TET (tetanic toxoid). Serum samples were taken before and 21 days after immunization. The immunogenecity was evaluated in 323 volunteers by an indirect ELISA. The seroconversion of those receiving vax-TyVi was 81.97% and 65.05 % for TYPHIM Vi. The postvaccine mean geometric titers were 7.41 U/mL (5.92-9.27 U/mL) and 5.41 U/mL (4.35-6.72 U/mL), respectively. The seroconversion with vax-TET was 0%. The reactogenecity of both polysaccharide vaccines was low. It was concluded that the immunogenecity of vax-TyVi was not lower than that of TYPHIM Vi and that its reactogenecity was similar.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2003 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad e inmunogenicidad de una vacuna de polisacárido Vi de Salmonella typhi en jóvenes cubanos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Safety and immunogenecity of a vaccine of polyssacharide Vi from Salmonella typhi in Cuban youths].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
