<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15846922</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pelayo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordoví, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez, F A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendoza, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobedo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A coproparasitologic study was performed on 456 children aged 1-5 years from 4 day-care centers located in San Miguel del Padrón municipality during November 1998, with the aim of finding out the behaviour of the main intestinal parasites and particularly how Giardia lamblia was affecting this child population. Three fecal specimens were collected from each child in every other day, which were processed by coproparasitologic methods such as direct testing and Ritchie's concentration technique. The most frequently identified parasite was G. lamblia with 249 positive cases for a prevalence rate of 54.6%. The second one was Blastocystis hominis (29.6%) followed by Endolimax nana(23.9%). Coccidia like Crystosporidium parvum and Cyclospora cayetanensis exhibited low frequencies, 0.6 and 1.5% respectively, being the majority of the cases located in only one day care center. These results confirmed that G. lamblia is the most prevailing parasite in day care centers, with peak frequency values in 2-4y age group and no differences between sexes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2001 Sep-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parasitosis intestinales en 4 círculos infantiles de San Miguel del Padrón, Ciudad de La Habana, 1998.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intestinal parasitic infections in 4 child day-care centers located in San Miguel del Padrón municipality, Havana City, 1998].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
