<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15871292</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Preciado, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calzada, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Preciado, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To the analyse the risk factors of voice disorders among teaching staff of La Rioja, Spain. DESIGN We carried out a transversal study of voice disorders in teaching staff of La Rioja (a random sample of 931 of 3.113 teachers). PATIENTS 527 teachers of random sample took part of study: 332 female (63%) and 195 male (37%). METHODS All teachers filled in a standard questionnaire and posteriorly they underwent an, ENT and functional vocal cord examination, videolaryngostroboscopy and acoustic analysis with MDVP. RESULTS The prevalence of voice disorders among La Rioja Teachers was 57%: 20% for organic lesions, 8% for chronic laryngitis and 29% for functional disorders. Women compared with men did not have a higher prevalence of voice disorders (p &gt; 0.05) (OR: 1.138). Professional and personal factors as well as classroom atmosphere were studied. The most relevant factors in the pathological group were previous vocal pathology, laryngeal surgery, gastroesophageal reflux and, classroom dryness and smoking habits. CONCLUSIONS The most relevant factor of voice disorders in teaching professional is the vocal overwork during their job. It is advisable to carry out a clinical evaluation of all the future teachers in their educational programs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia y factores de riesgo de los trastornos de la voz en el personal docente de La Rioja. Estudio transversal de 527 docentes: cuestionario, examen de la función vocal, análisis acústico y vídeolaringoestroscopia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Frequency and risk factors of voice disorders among teaching staff of La Rioja, Spain. Clinical study: questionnaire, function vocal examination, acoustic analysis and videolaryngostroboscopy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
