<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15880184</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gubelin, Walter</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garmendia, María Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete, Nelson</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santander, Ester</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Genital herpes, a sexually transmitted disease caused by herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV-2), is found in 3.8% of all sexually transmitted diseases (STD) in Chile. AIM To determine the seroprevalence of herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV-2) and to identify an association between HSV-2 and HIV-1, other STD, and to study its demographic characteristics. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study at two STD public clinics in Santiago was conducted among 200 consecutive patients. Samples were tested for HSV-2, HIV-1, syphilis and hepatitis B virus surface antigen. RESULTS The seroprevalence for HSV-2 was 43%. Four patients had a history of genital herpes. There was a strong association between HSV-2 infection and HIV-1 positivity (OR=8.7, 95% CI 3.4-22.4, p &lt;0.001) and the condition of being a sexual worker (OR=4.5, 95% CI 1.7-11.9, p &lt;0.01). CONCLUSIONS The high association with HIV-1 and sexual workers, emphasizes the need of having HSV-2 specific diagnostic tests, counseling on sign and symptom recognition and taking preventive measures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seropervalencia de la infección por virus herpes simplex tipo 2 en pacientes atendidos en centros de referencia de ETS de Santiago.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Seroprevalence of herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV-2) infection in two clinics for sexually transmitted diseases in Santiago, Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
