<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15899220</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-048X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Camps Herrero, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blasco Cordellat, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bayo Zaera, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sancho Salvador, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sirera Pérez, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Safont Aguilera, María José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Presence of circulating DNA in the serum of patients with cancer makes detection of tumour-specific genetic alterations feasible. OBJECTIVE To study serum DNA concentration in patients diagnosed as having advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) and to evaluate its relationship with age, histology, stage, response, time-to-progression (TTP), and survival. METHODS Serum DNA from 78 patients was purified and spectrophotometrically quantified. RESULTS No significant correlations were found between serum DNA concentration and age, histology, response and survival. There was a significant correlation with respect to stage (IIIB = 408.75 ng/ml; IV = 478.74 ng/ml; p = 0.02). When patients were grouped according to DNA concentration, significant correlation with TTP was found; establishing a cut-off point at 500 ng/ml ([DNA] &lt; 500 ng/ml TTP = 7.25 months, 95%CI: 3.5-5.25; [DNA ] &gt; or = 500 ng/ml TTP = 4.25 months, 95%CI: 2-6.5; p = 0.05). CONCLUSIONS Using the present method, DNA concentration quantification appears to be simple, but with certain deficiencies due to inter-sample variability and low specificity. This is because total DNA concentration is measured without distinguishing as to whether it is tumour-related. We suggest that there is a correlation between DNA concentration and prognosis which enables an analysis of the natural history of the disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la concentración sérica del ADN tumoral en el cáncer de pulmón no microcítico y avanzado: 'es útil como factor pronóstico?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of tumour-derived DNA in serum in advanced non-microcytic lung cancer: might it be a prognostic factor?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Clinical &amp; translational oncology : official publication of the Federation of Spanish Oncology Societies and of the National Cancer Institute of Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
