<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15909736</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Estradas, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meave, Aloha</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alexánderson, Erick</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alexánderson, E Graciela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ricalde, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Coronary artery disease (CAD) represents the principal cause of morbidity and mortality in our environment. Positron emission tomography (PET) is a new technique in our country that allows the assessment of myocardial perfusion and the absolute quantification of the coronary blood flow (CBF) through the utilization of radiotracers using the same criteria employed in conventional nuclear cardiology. CBF normal values have been determined in other populations around the world. No studies in our country assessing in a non-invasive way the CBF have been published before. The quantification of CBF in healthy population is important to establish a standard measure and determine through it, the effects of the many diseases that change the coronary blood flow. The quantification of the CBF, the calculation of coronary blood flow reserve (CFR) and the endothelium dependent vasodilatation index (EDVI) through PET is possible performing three different acquisition stages: rest, cold pressor test (CPT) and pharmacologic stress using Ammonia as radiotracer. The aim of this study was to evaluate the CBF, the CFR and the EDVI in healthy Mexican volunteers. RESULTS Global basal CBF was 0.34 (+/- 0.09) mL/g/min, during CPT increased to 0.55 (+/- 0.17) mL/g/min and during the stress increased to 1.18 (+/- 0.25). CFR was 3.5 (+/- 0.65) and EDVI was 1.55 (+/- 0.33). CONCLUSIONS CFR and EDVI values obtained in Mexican healthy population correlates very well with those reported in the literature. This values represents a reference to further research that use this technology.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del flujo coronario mediante PET en lapoblación mexicana sin enfermedad arterial coronaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of coronary flow by means of PET in the Mexican population without coronary artery disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
