<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15912215</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Akiskal, Hagop</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez, Gustavo H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED One of the major points of interest in the study of affective temperaments is the possibility of exploring the clinical significance of sub-affective traits as predictors of the development and inter-episodic manifestation of recurrent mood disorders within the bipolar illness spectrum. The TEMPS-A scale is a self-evaluation questionnaire used worldwide to assess the four basic affective temperaments (hyperthymic, depressive, cyclothymic, and irritable), and the anxious temperament. METHOD The TEMPS-A questionnaire version that includes 110 items has been locally adapted from the version used in Spain, which in turn was produced by following the translation / retro-translation method. A locally-adapted version was produced from the version used in Spain. This local version was subsequently translated into English by a bilingual translator. RESULTS A satisfactory adaptation of the version used in Spain was achieved, as confirmed by the retro-translation into English, and its subsequent approval by the authors of the scale. CONCLUSIONS The Argentine version of the TEMPS-A self-evaluation questionnaire for the assessment of affective temperaments can be considered equivalent to the original version, and used as an important instrument for the clinical investigation of affective disorders in our country.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escala de temperamento de Memphis, Pisa, París y San Diego autoaplicada, versión argentina (TEMPS-A Buenos Aires).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The temperament evaluation of the Memphis, Pisa, Paris, and San Diego autoquestionnaire, Argentine version (TEMPS-A Buenos Aires)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
