<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15946624</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montoza Aguado, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas Guerrero, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojo Hernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Felipe Jiménez-Casquet, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Aragón, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Lorenzo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Cañavate Burgos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The development of allergic pathology takes place as result of an alteration of the immunity and alteration of the corporal mechanism of protection, giving rise to an erroneous answer or exaggerated forehead to innocuous antigens, that it generates clinical symptoms with cutaneous, digestive or respiratory manifestations. The frequency and distribution of this process have undergone an increase from the 1970, which causes that a greater interest in the knowledge of the mechanisms exists that produce this clinic. The answer by immunoglobulin E is regulated by the answer of lymphocytes T-helper-1 represented by interleukin 2 and gamma-interferon that inhibits their production, and the answer of lymphocytes T-helper-2 formed by interleukin 4, interleukin 10 and interleukin 13 that stimulate the production of immunoglobulin E. METHODS AND RESULTS A study of cases and controls with a sample of 70 appears new born considering antecedent relatives of first degree of allergic disease (47 no, 23 yes). Values in umbilical cord blood were moderate of interleukins 4, 10, 13 and gamma-interferon (kit CLB, and method ELISA). Values for interleukin 4 and interleukin 13 have not been obtained. One has been greater values of interleukin 10 in children of mother or brother affection (mother affects IL 10 = 48.7 pg/ml, in front of mother does not affect IL 10 = 31.62 pg/ml, p = 0.081, no signification), (brother affection IL 10 = 72.8 pg/ml, in front of brother no affection IL 10 = 32.31 pg/ml, p = 0.0062, is significant). Difference for gamma-interferon was not obtained. CONCLUSIONS As it has already been shown in other studies, interleukin 10 increases in cord blood in children whose mother is the one who presents the disease. It emphasizes the increase of interleukin 10 in blood of umbilical cord of children with brother affection of allergic disease. Still it is left much to do and by means of later pursuit it is hoped to obtain interest results.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de interleucinas en sangre de cordón: relación con antecedentes familiares de enfermedad alérgica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Interleukin levels in umbilical cord blood: relationship with a family history of allergic disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Allergologia et immunopathologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
