<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15954034</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sastre-Garriga, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montalbán, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galán-Cartañá, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Thompson, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurorehabilitation is predominantly an educational, dynamic process based on the adaptation of the individual and his environment to the actual neurological impairment and focuses on decreasing the impact of disabling neurological conditions on the individual in order to achieve optimum quality of life. It has been suggested by some that neurorehabilitation is the only approach available to us which can improve the limitations in activity and restrictions in social participation of people with multiple sclerosis. The neurorehabilitation approach is a holistic one and is a fundamental part of neurological care; it should not be forgotten by neurologists, especially when dealing with people with chronic disabling conditions such as multiple sclerosis. Together with the social model of disability, the concept of restorative neurology, as a scientific and therapeutic attempt to minimize those impairments directly responsible for the disability presented by the person, is recently gaining ground among neuroscientists and clinicians. In this review the conceptual basis for neurorehabilitation will be presented together with a review of the literature concerning the biological aspects of neurorehabilitative therapy (neuroplasticity) and the clinical trials evaluating the effectiveness of neurorehabilitation in people with multiple sclerosis. Finally, we will consider the practical aspects of neurorehabilitation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurorrehabilitación en esclerosis múltiple.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neurorehabilitation in multiple sclerosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
