<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15982181</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodrigo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ornia, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tosca, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Olmo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serra, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lluch, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Torres, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escudero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martí, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To ascertain the epidemiological characteristics, clinical symptoms, and evolution of drug-induced hepatitis over the last 22 years. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN AND SUBJECTS: An observational, retrospective study between 1982 and 1993, and prospective study between 1994 and 2003. All patients in our department diagnosed with having drug-induced hepatitis were studied analyzing epidemiological (age, sex, cases per year, hospitalization) and clinical features (previous liver disease, hepatic symptoms, laboratory results), and follow-up (complete recovery or chronicity). RESULTS A total of 61 patients were diagnosed as having drug-induced hepatitis, 26 men and 35 women (57%), mean age 52.4 years +/- 17 years, of which 72.2% were older than 40 years. A total of 43% were admitted to hospital. In 87% of cases, two or more drugs were involved, the most frequent being antituberculosis (19 cases), psychotropic (26 cases), and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (45 cases). Evolution showed that 94% of patients recovered after the withdrawal of suspected causal drugs. CONCLUSIONS The incidence of drug-induced hepatitis is higher in patients over 40 years of age, it being more common in females. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory, psychotropic, and anti-tuberculosis agents were the main drugs involved. Most patients made a complete recovery after withdrawal of the suspected causal drug.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical evaluation of drug-induced hepatitis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
