<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15989826</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tapia Collados, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil Guillén, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orozco Beltrán, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To know the influence of mother's anxiety in the number of office visits made by the children al primary care paediatric setting. DESIGN Case control study. SETTING Primary care. 17th Health Area. Valencian Community. Spain. PATIENTS 134 mothers. Overuse was defined as number of visits higher than the average of visits in all children plus one standard deviation in a certain period. 14.89% were over users. 46 mothers (35.12%) from over user children and 85 (64.88%) from non over users. MEASURES Anxiety scale STAI (Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory) short form. Mother's job and number of mother's children. RESULTS Mother's of over user's children score higher in STAI scale. Number of children or mother's job is not associated with STAI scores. In multivariate analysis anxiety is an important factor associated to over user's children. CONCLUSIONS Mother's anxiety is associated with over user's children in primary care paediatric setting. This is a modifiable factor to influence in the number of inappropriate office visits.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jun 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la ansiedad materna en la frecuentación de las consultas de pediatría de atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of maternal anxiety on the frequency of paediatric primary care visits].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
