<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1598451</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yáñez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camba, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peleteiro, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have evaluated the analgesic effect of continuous intrathecal administration of midazolam in 4 patients using a three-level score (no change, amelioration, and marked improvement). The secondary effects of this drug were also investigated (sedation, nausea, vomiting, respiratory depression, urinary retention, motor dysfunction). In one patient midazolam was the only drug administered, whereas in three patients this drug was associated with morphine. In one patient with a peripheral arteriopathy, midazolam at a dose of 12 mg/day was unable to equal the analgesic effect achieved with 0.4 mg of morphine. The remaining three patients had carcinoma and received a continuous intrathecal perfusion of morphine at increasing daily doses up to 12; 4,8; and 6 mg/day, respectively without pain relief. In these patients the association of midazolam at respective doses of 9; 4-8; and 6 mg/day induced amelioration in one patient and marked improvement in the two other patients. Midazolam did not change the heart rate, respiratory rate, arterial blood pressure, nor body temperature. We believe that the analgesic effect of intrathecal administration of midazolam is due to its coupling with the ionophore complex GABA-spinal benzodiazepine that in turn produces an increment of the GABA amino butyric acid at this level.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Administración intratecal de morfina, midazolam y su asociación en 4 pacientes afectados de dolor crónico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intrathecal administration of morphine, midazolam, and their combination in 4 patients with chronic pain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
