<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>15989871</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Reina, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several epidemiological studies have indicated that, in all countries and in distinct epidemic years, the highest rates of influenza infection (between 15% and 42%) occur in the pediatric population, especially in school-aged children. Over various influenza seasons, the rates of annual outpatient visits attributable to influenza vary from 6-29% of children. Influenza and its complications have been reported to result in a 10-30% increase in the number of antibiotic courses prescribed to children during the influenza season. Current percentages of influenza vaccination in children are very low, although the hospitalization rates for infectious complications in children under 5 years are at least equal to those observed in individuals aged more than 65 years. The reasons for these low immunization rates are unknown, but many factors could be involved, especially the need for annual revaccination. In 2003 the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) recommended influenza immunization only in children at high risk for influenza complications and in those living with someone in a high-risk group. However, they encouraged vaccination of all children aged 6-23 months old. After a review of various epidemiological studies, in 2004 both the ACIP and the American Academy of Pediatrics recommended systematic immunization of all healthy children within this age group. However, both institutions advise that before the routine introduction of influenza immunization in all children aged 6-23 months old, immunization programs in high-risk children need to be implemented.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas indicaciones de la vacuna inactivada antigripal en la población infantil (2004-2005).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[New indications for the inactivated influenza vaccine in the pediatric population (2004-2005)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
