<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16044642</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García Saavedra, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Crespo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez Zapico, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The practice of minimally invasive surgery techniques in the retro-peritoneal space presents additional difficulties. Due to the absence of a real cavity and the presence of a dense fat tissue involving the structures, the need for an artificial space to work in is necessary. We present three cases of the retro-peritoneal superior heminephrectomy present in a 3-months, 6-months and a 6-year old children. In all cases a 1 centimeter port for the optique and two 0.5 centimeter ports for the instruments were situated, and the use of harmonic scalpel was satisfactory to remove renal tissue without bleeding. Drainages were unnecessary and all of the children left the hospital within the first 48 post-operative hours. Since 1994, when Figenhans and Clayman communicated the first laparoscopic nephrectomy in children, the technique has been used generally and their forward advances in conventional surgery are now universally accepted. Furthermore, the practice of polar retro-peritoneoscopic heminephrectomy allowed a very precise renal hiliar dissection and an excellent differentiation of each hemirenal tissue, separating the ill kidney and preserving the maximum function possible for the other half-kidney and the adrenal gland.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Heminefrectomía retroperitoneoscópica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Retroperitoneoscopic heminephrectomy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
