<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16050404</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Miranda, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oppenheimer, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spain is the leader country in cadaver kidney transplantation. However the percentage of those transplants coming from living donors represents only a 2% of the total activity. To analyze the cause of this situation the Spanish Society of Nephrology and the National Transplant Organization carried out an opinion pole between patients and health professionals including nephrologists, surgeons/urologists and nurses implicated in kidney transplantation. 60% out the patients consider that the time into the waiting list is to long and 59% don't have any information about living donor kidney transplantation. All the health professionals believe that living donor share better results than get cadaver donors and that the number of the procedure are not enough. Considering that scarcely motivation of professionals and the family of the patients are the main cause. Parents, brothers and sister were considered the best match between donor and recipients and non genetically/emotionally-related donors were accepted by only 2.5%. A 55.7% out of the health professionals considered that the nephrologists are the people that must inform the patients and family about living kidney donation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta de opinión sobre la donación de vivo renal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Opinion survey on renal donation from living donor].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
