<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16050206</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calleja Escudero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortiñas González, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivero Martínez, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Egea Camacho, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pascual Samaniego, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández del Busto, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association of a seminal vesicle cyst with ipsilateral renal agenesis was initially reported in 1914 by Zinner, and it is a very rare congenital anomaly. The association of this anomaly with an ectopic ureter entering the seminal vesicle cyst is even less common. In these cases, clinical symptoms appear in patients 15 years or older due to the distention of the seminal vesicle caused by the secretions of the reproductive tract. Perineal discomfort and recurrent epididymitis are the most often presentations. Urogenital upper tract image studies are mandatory in the management of a cystic pelvic mass and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is the best of this radiographic studies, that also reveals the ectopic ureter draining into the seminal vesicle. We report an additional case of this rare congenital anomaly where only MRI provided a correct preoperative diagnosis and a right surgical approach.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agenesia renal derecha y abocamiento ectópico del uréter en dilatación quística de la vesícula seminal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Right renal agenesis and ureter ectopic abouchement in cystic dilation of seminal vesicle].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
