<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16056181</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bermejo-Fenoll, Ambrosio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camacho-Alonso, Fabio</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Jornet, Pía</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pemphigus vulgaris (PV) is a chronic vesicular-ampullar mucocutaneous disease that almost always produces oral manifestations. The fact that blisters on the oral mucosa are sometimes the first manifestation of the disease implies that dental professionals must be sufficiently familiarized with the clinical manifestations of PV to ensure early diagnosis and treatment. We present a series of 14 patients with clinically and histologically diagnosed PV seen in the Teaching Unit of Oral Medicine of the University of Murcia (Spain) between 1981 and 2001. A thorough evaluation was made, recording patient age and sex, the location and extent of the lesions, and the signs and symptoms of the disease. Complementary studies were also carried out, with the evaluation of hematological parameters (including blood chemistry), the histology and immunohistochemical characteristics (direct immunofluorescence in 2 cases). Treatment comprised topical corticoids, in 12 cases combined with systemic corticoids, and associated to intralesional corticotherapy in one patient. A good response to treatment was observed in all cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Aug-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pemphigus vulgaris. A presentation of 14 cases and review of the literature.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina oral, patologia oral y cirugia bucal</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
