<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16053013</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morcillo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Tamajón, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marrero, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Posada, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Laynez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meneses, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alarco, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prognosis of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) patients with chronic renal failure (CRF) improves after simultaneous pancreas-kidney (SPK) transplantation. In order to evaluate the changes in cardio-vascular risk (CVR) factors after SKP, we studied nine recipients before and 6 months after SPK. There were five females and four males, with a mean age of 37 +/- 8 years, duration of diabetes of 24 +/- 5 years, three of them before starting dialysis, and six on dialysis (hemodialysis = 5; peritoneal dialysis = 1). Before SPK, all patients received anti-hypertensive therapy (1-4 drugs; mean 2.2 +/- 0.9) and eight received statins. At 6 months after SPK, all patients were under triple immunosuppressive therapy (steroids + tacrolimus + MMF) without statins. They had normal renal function (Plasma Creatinine = 1.2 +/- 0.3 mg/dl) and pancreatic endocrine function (glycemia = 80 +/- 8 mg/dl). HbA1c decreased significantly (8.4 +/- 1.2 vs 4.7 +/- 0.6%; p &lt; 0.007) with a value &gt; 7% in seven patients before SPK and in none 6 months after SKP transplantation (p &lt; 0.001). Although Body Mass Index increased (23 +/- 2 vs 25 +/- 3 kg/m2; p &lt; 0.05), plasma triglycerides decreased (130 +/- 51 vs 88 +/- 33 mg/dl; p &lt; 0.05), and total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol and HDL-cholesterol were similar. Systolic and diastolic blood pressure (BP) decreased (156 +/- 7 vs 133 +/- 15; p &lt; 0.01 and 96 +/- 7 vs 79 +/- 9; p &lt; 0.007) with only two patients on anti-hypertensive therapy (1 drug). Likewise, before transplantation all patients were hypertensive (six grade 1 and three grade 2) while this was observed in only two at the end of follow-up (both grade 1) (p &lt; 0.001). In conclusion, SPK transplantation with good renal and pancreatic function is associated with a short-term improvement in CVR profile.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución a corto plazo de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular tras el trasplante reno-pancreático.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Improved short-term cardiovascular profile after simultaneous pancreas-kidney transplantation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
