<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16075810</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ibarra, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Creydt, Virginia Pistone</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zotta, Elsa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nuñez, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Shiga toxin (Stx)-producing E. coli causing watery diarrhea, hemorrhagic colitis and hemolytic-uremic syndrome (HUS). In Argentina, HUS is the most common cause of acute renal failure in children. The purpose of the present study was to examine the cytotoxicity of Stx type 2 (Stx2) and its B subunit (Stx2B) on human renal tubular epithelial cells (HRTEC), in the presence and absence of inflammatory factors. Cytotoxic effects were assessed in terms of functionality of the epithelium, histological damage, cell viability, protein synthesis and cellular apoptosis. Results show that Stx2 regulates the passage of water through the HRTEC within an incubation period of 1h. Within longer periods, up to 72 hours, the study of morphology, viability, protein synthesis and apoptosis shows that HRTEC were sensitive to the cytotoxic action of Stx2 and Stx2B in a dose- and time-dependent manner. These effects were potentiated by lipopolysaccharides (LPS), IL-1beta, and butirate.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto citotóxico de la toxina Shiga tipo 2 y su subunidad B en células epiteliales tubulares renales humanas en cultivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cytotoxic effect of Shiga toxin type 2 and its B subunit on human renal tubular epithelial cell cultures].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
