<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16137488</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Laso, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orfao, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is well established that alcoholism is associated with imbalanced immune responses. To date, most relevant finding reported is the existence of an immunodepressed state which leads to a higher risk of suffering from severe infections in alcoholic patients. However, recent studies have shown that ethanol intake is followed by changes involving the synthesis and serum levels of specific cytokines as well as the activation of several different subsets of cytotoxic lymphocytes, that could be involved in the development of alcoholic liver disease. Accordingly, tumor necrosis factor-alpha plays a key role in the development of alcoholic liver damage through the induction of both apoptosis and necrosis of hepatocytes. This cytokine, together with interleukin (IL) 1, IL6 and several chemokines, facilitate the development of inflammation of the liver. Additionally, both transforming growth factor-beta and platelet-derived growth factor, act over stellate cells favouring hepatic fibrogenesis. The advances in the knowledge of the immunological mechanisms involved in alcoholic liver disease may lead to the discovery of new potential therapeutic targets, which may modify disease outcome in the near future.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Sep 03 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistema inmune y enfermedad hepática por alcohol.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Immune system and alcoholic liver disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
