<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16185563</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Padilla, Emma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, Olivia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reina, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz de Gopegui, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In recent years studies from various parts of the world have reported a significant increase in the number of genital infections caused by HSV-1, especially among women. METHODS We report a study of genital infections caused by HSV-1 in our geographic area from 1995 to 2003. Genital samples were inoculated in the Vero cell line and cultures were stained by monoclonal antibodies against HSV-1 and HSV-2. RESULTS During the study period, 263 samples were positive for herpesviruses: 146 for HSV-1 (55.5%) and 117 for HSV-2 (44.5%). The 20 HSV-1 isolated in the genital tract represented 7.6% of all the herpesviruses isolated in this study. Of the 146 HSV-1 isolated, 20 (13.7%) were obtained in genital samples, 15 (75%) in women and 5 (25%) in men (p &lt; 0.005). Four men (80%) were homosexual. No patient, male or female, was infected with the HIV and none worked as prostitutes. CONCLUSIONS The percentage of HSV-1 genital infections increased in the last year of the study (33%), especially among women from the general population. The herpesvirus isolated in these samples should be characterized, since, in general, HSV-1 does not usually develop latency or recurrent infections in this anatomical area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de infecciones genitales causadas por el virus del herpes simple tipo 1 (VHS-1) durante el período 1995-2003.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Incidence of genital infections caused by herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) from 1995 to 2003].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
