<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16211987</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-6722</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yorio, Marcelo A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Hernán A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Savio, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escudero Millán, Andrés E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Upper gastrointestinal bleeding--UGB-, as a complication, is well studied at intensive care units (ICU), but is less known in non ICU settings. OBJECTIVES To determine incidence and risk factors of this entity at clinical hospitalization. MATERIALS AND METHODS A case-control study of patients with gastric ulcer disease diagnosed by endoscopy who presented with melena and hematemesis. Ten controls were taken for each case, matching sex, age and prophylaxis for gastric hemorrhage. Demographic data and other know risks factors were analyzed. RESULT We found ten bleeding case among 35070 discharges (incidence: 2.8/10000 discharges). Mortality was not increased but the number of transfusion was higher in the bleeding group. We found an assocciation betwen UGB and systemic inflammatory response syndrome--SIRS-(OR: 9.22 IC 95% 2.98-28.17) and diabetes (OR: 7.8 IC 95% 2.3-26.8). The rest of the factors studied did not rich a statistical significance. CONCLUSIONS UGB during clinical hospitalization is a rare complication that requires an increased staying at hospital and a great number of transfusions. It may be probably associated in a positive way with diabetes and SIRS.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2004 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo asociados a hemorragia digestiva alta, en sala común.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors associated to upper gastrointestinal bleeding in non intensive care units].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
