<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16219280</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro Gómez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borrego Domínguez, R R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carreras Fernández, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Campderá, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Brain abscess is a rare infection in infants. Morbidity and mortality are high but have decreased due to advances in neuroimaging studies and the use of new antibiotics. We describe six cases of brain abscess diagnosed at the Gregorio Marañón Children's Hospital between January 1996 and September 2003. METHODS We performed a retrospective chart review of patients with brain abscess. The variables analyzed were age, sex, clinical symptoms and signs, radiological studies, etiology, therapy, and clinical outcome. RESULTS Age ranged from 8 to 15 years (mean age: 11 years). There were three girls and three boys. The most frequent symptoms were neurological with associated sinusitis in four patients, congenital cyanogenic cardiopathy in one patient and meningitis in one patient. Diagnosis was established through computed tomography (CT) of the brain in five patients and through magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in one patient. In five patients the abscess was located in the frontal lobe. All patients received broad-spectrum antibiotics and five underwent surgical drainage. Two patients had neurological sequelae. CONCLUSIONS Although rare, brain abscess should be considered in patients with neurological manifestations associated with otorhinolaryngological infections or congenital cyanotic cardiopathy. When suspected, a CT or MRI must be performed to rule out this diagnosis and, if confirmed, prompt therapy with broad-spectrum antibiotics should be started. Surgical drainage may be needed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso cerebral infantil.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Brain abscess in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
