<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16238958</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Formiga, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marcos, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sole, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lora-Tamayo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pujol, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valencia, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Delirium or acute confusional syndrome (ACS) is a frequent problem during hospitalization of elderly patients. We study the appearance of delirium and its characteristics in patients admitted to an internal medicine service. METHODS Prospective study of 148 patients over 64 years admitted due to medical condition (non-surgical) in the internal medicine service of the University Hospital of Bellvitge. Functionality was quantified with the Barthel index (BI) and comorbidity with the Charlson index (CI). The Confusional Assessment Method was used for the diagnosis of the ACS. RESULTS Seventy-seven (77) (52%) of the 148 patients were women, with a mean age of 78.5 years. The CI was 2.2. Mean of previous BI was 81.7. Mortality during admission was 8% (12 patients). A total of 42.5% of the patients (63) had ACS (30% prevalent). It was hyperactive in 68%, hypoactive in 16% and mixed in 16%. In 38% of the patients, the ACS had morning predominance and 62% it appeared after the evening. Advanced age was the only significant differences between patients with or without ACS (p &lt; 0.001). There were no significant differences in the ACS percentage between patients who survived or who died (p = 0.36). CONCLUSIONS Frequency of appearance of the confusional picture is high in patients admitted to acute hospitals, it being more frequent in the elderly. Measures to prevent the confusional picture in elderly patients who are hospitalized should be increased.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome confusional agudo en pacientes ancianos ingresados por patología médica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acute confusional syndrome in elderly patients hospitalized due to medical condition].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
