<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16240917</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>da Costa, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martin, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Branco Neves, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Although the aetiology of otitis media is known to be multifactorial, adenoids infections and Eustachian tube dysfunction, have been frequently associated with the incidence of middle-ear effusion. Middle-ear effusion cases are frequent in Maputo, Mozambique, and very often insertion of tympanostomy tubes and adenoidectomy alone or with amigdalectomy have been used to treat these cases and to prevent further episodes. The objective of this study is to describe the association of these factors with otitis medias with effusion in patients that visit the Otorrinolaringology department (ENT) at the Central Hospital of Maputo (HCM), as well as to describe the clinical and epidemiological profile of these patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS A cross sectional study was conducted. 4157 clinical files of all patients who made their first visit to the ENT department at the HCM, with otitis media during a period of 4 years (1995 to 1998). RESULTS 23.3% of patients who visited the ORL service of Maputo with otitis media, are children under 3 years; the major proportion of otitis media with effusion was observed in children aged from 3 to 7 years old (49.2%). In boys under, otitis media with effusion is strongly associated with the history of adenoiditis and/or Eustachian tube dysfunction (OR=9.53) and in older patients (OR=12.26). CONCLUSION The proportion of otitis media with effusion increases more evidently in patients with disfuntion tube syndrome. Other factor that can be important in patients under seven, is the presence of adenoiditis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Otitis medias con derrame: asociación con el síndrome de disfunción tubárica y las adenoiditis. El caso del Hospital Central de Maputo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Otitis medias with effusion: association with the Eustachian tube dysfunction and adenoiditis. The case of the Central Hospital of Maputo].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
