<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16245197</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Poposki, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vilaplana, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castilla, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE Long term assessment of the evolution of Idiopathic Polypoidal Choroidal Vasculopathy (IPCV) in symptomatic patients treated by laser photocoagulation. METHODS We carried out a retrospective study involving seven eyes in six patients with visual impairment, affected by IPCV, confirmed by indocyanine green angiography. All were treated by laser photocoagulation and monitored during a period of at least one year. The controls were evaluated during the first, third, sixth and twelfth month, in order to assess whether it was necessary to repeat the treatment. RESULTS Of the six patients with IPCV lesions, two were men and four were women (1:2) aged between 58 and 81 years (mean = 73 years), and monitored for a time interval of 18 and 75 months (mean = 39 months). The average initial visual acuity was 0.25, and the final was 0.15. All the patients had the other eye also affected: three had a macular disciform scar, secondary to the previous haemorrhagic episodes, two had asymptomatic polyps and in one patient we defined active bilateral IPCV which was treated by laser photocoagulation. In two eyes it appeared as a macular haemorrhage, in four eyes as a serosanguinous retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) detachment and in one eye as a serous RPE detachment. Three eyes suffered a relapse which required further laser photocoagulation treatment. CONCLUSIONS Laser photocoagulation is a palliative treatment for IPCV. Final vision achieved is poor and relapse is frequent. Other procedures should be used to treat this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fotocoagulación láser en la vasculopatía coroidal polipoidea idiopática. Seguimiento superior a un año.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Laser photocoagulation in idiopathic polypoidal choroidal vasculopathy. Over one year follow-up].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
