<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16254862</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Soriano-Ferrer, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Our current understanding of learning disabilities (LD) is essentially limited by their actual definition, the heterogeneity of the samples and the unsuitability of the control groups. AIMS This study offers an overview of the methodological aspects and the areas of research in LD. DEVELOPMENT From a bibliographical search conducted in the Psychological Abstracts database, PsycINFO, we identified and selected the studies the review was to focus on, and this was completed with previous reviews. Quantitative research methods are preferred in 99.7% of cases, whereas the remaining 0.3% opted for qualitative methods. There was in increase in the number of research reviews, as well as longitudinal studies and those aimed at determining the effectiveness of the interventions, with the resulting interest in new techniques for data analysis such as meta-analysis, path analysis and latent growth curves. The research topics that aroused most interest were LD-related problems (16.7%), difficulties in learning to read (15.82%), studies focusing on intervention (10.15%) and diagnostics in LD. CONCLUSIONS The primary objectives of the research appear to be the characterisation of LD and the problems they cause throughout the patient's life cycle, together with their identification and early treatment. Research is also extended towards other, more practical matters, with a special emphasis on the school setting.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Nov 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La investigación en dificultades de aprendizaje: un análisis documental</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Research into learning disabilities: a documentary analysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
