<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16288422</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Godes-Medrano, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pardal-Fernández, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rallo-Gutiérrez, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Polyneuropathies (PNP) result from damage to a number of nerves. They are classified according to the anatomical-functional, histological, aetiological and genetic characteristics. Here we report on the prolonged follow-up carried out on an adult male who had a chronic recurring axonal-type PNP. CASE REPORT We describe the case of a 65-year-old male who presented episodes of neurological deficit over a period of 10 years that were interspersed with prolonged, stable periods in which he was free of new symptoms. The patient's functional limitations became greater with each successive relapse and the situation is now one of extreme disability. The characteristics of the clinical picture pointed towards a diffuse peripheral nerve disorder, and the neurophysiological studies carried out revealed polyneuropathic, sensory and motor injury mediated by an axonal mechanism with no associated demyelination. A comprehensive analytical, imaging and functional study was conducted, but did not reveal any specific causes. The particular clinical process, the exclusion of other pathologies and the electrophysiological findings allowed us to reach a diagnosis of recurring or episodic chronic primary axonal PNP. CONCLUSIONS This description can be added to the few cases reported in the literature. As we see it, this is an unusual, although probably underdiagnosed, disease and it must be taken into account in the differential diagnosis of chronic recurring PNP because of the diagnostic implications and--with respect to its usually poor response to therapy--due to the prognoses.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Nov 16-30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polineuropatía crónica axonal recidivante en brotes. Caso clínico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic relapsing axonal neuropathy. A case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
