<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16324566</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Solaz-Moreno, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artero-Mora, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vallalta-Morales, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Bellés, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salavert-Lletí, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mahiques-Santos, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In the last two decades there has been a reported increase in the incidence of streptococcal toxic shock syndrome (STSS). The objective of this study was to determine the clinical and epidemiological characteristics of this infection. METHODS Retrospective study of all cases of STSS diagnosed at a single tertiary hospital over the last ten years. RESULTS We report 13 cases of STSS (8 men, mean age 62 years). The mean annual incidence was 0.19 episodes/100,000 population from 1994 to 1998 and 0.53 episodes/100,000 population from 1999 to 2003 (p = 0.059). All patients had at least one underlying disease and there were no intravenous drug users. The most common portals of entry were the skin and soft tissues (85%) and all but one patient had a positive blood culture. Two cases were nosocomial and five patients required surgery (amputation and/or debridement). There was a high mortality rate (85%) and a rapid course from onset to death; nine patients died within four days after establishing the diagnosis. CONCLUSION The incidence of SSTS has increased over the last five years at our hospital. Elderly patients with underlying medical conditions were more susceptible to acquiring this infection. Early mortality was very high.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome del shock tóxico estreptocócico: experiencia de los últimos 10 años en un hospital terciario.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Streptococcal toxic shock syndrome: ten years' experience at a tertiary hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
