<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16388295</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Saez-Yuguero, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pardo-Zamora, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo-Guirado, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM The aim of this article is to assess the efficiency of the technique for the posterior alveolar expansion and elevation of the upper maxillary alveolar ridge through the use of compressive osteotomes (Quirurgical Bontempi, España) which have been specifically designed for Osseotite NT and Osseotite NT Certain of 3i implants (Implants Innovations, USA). MATERIALS AND METHODS 24 adult patients (16 female and 12 male), who were selected according to Albrektsson's inclusion and exclusion criteria, took part in the study. All the patients presented bone deficiency in the width and height of the upper maxilla. 48 Osseotite implants were performed (four Osseotite Standard; six Osseotite NT; 38 NT Certain (3i, Implants Innovations, CA, USA)). Implant diameters were 4 mm in 44 cases and 5 mm in 4 cases with lengths varying between 11.5 (n = 4) and 13 mm (n = 44). The alveolar ridges of the 24 patients had initial widths from 1.5 mm to 5 mm and heights between 5 and 13 mm. RESULTS The data obtained were analysed using the SPSS 11.0 program. In the 48 areas treated with immediate implants, an increase in bone height of 6.75 mm -/+ 1.25 mm was achieved. In the case of the alveolar expansion for the 48 implants, the average was 3.2 mm -/+ 0.15 mm. CONCLUSIONS The technique for alveolar expansion and elevation of the upper maxilla with compressive osseotomes can lead to a 100% success rate after a 9-month follow-up of the implants and insertion of prostheses. It is a highly predictable surgical procedure which allows implants to be performed at the same time as surgery, thus reducing the number of such interventions while recovering aesthetic and functional losses in the patient.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jan 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compressive osteotomes for expansion and maxilla sinus floor lifting.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina oral, patologia oral y cirugia bucal</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
