<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16402320</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guelbenzu, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crespo-Rodríguez, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guillén-Subirán, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo-Hernández, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barrena, M R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Angulo-Hervías, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION We analysed the characteristics, progression and outcomes observed following the embolisation of 100 intracranial arteriovenous malformations (AVM) that were performed in order to achieve complete obliteration of the AVM, the elimination of associated vascular risk factors and also to reduce their size with a view to increasing the effectiveness of later treatments. PATIENTS AND METHODS The demographic and anatomical characteristics of 110 patients with AVM were analysed over a period of 13 years, and embolisation was performed in 100 of them. In all, 203 embolisation sessions were carried out with an average of 3 embolisations per patient. Of the 100 AVM that were embolised, 36 were AVM which were treated by embolisation with no later therapy, 48 required radiosurgery after the embolisation and the other 16 were submitted to surgery following the embolisation. The type of materials used included liquid adhesive embolic agents (Hystoacryl, Glubran), non-adhesive embolic agents (Onyx) and polyvinyl alcohol particles. Patients were examined clinically and arteriographically. RESULTS Of the 100 AVM that were embolised, complete eradication was accomplished with just embolisation in 27 cases of AVM (27%). Of the 48 AVM in which radiosurgery was carried out at a later date, the average rate of obliteration was 78% and of the 16 AVM in which surgery was carried out some time later, the average rate of obliteration was 70%. Of the 100 AVM that were embolised, some residue remained in 16 cases. Embolisation eliminated most of the associated vascular risk factors, as can be seen by the fact that associated risk factors disappeared in 28 (65%) out of the 43 AVM with such factors. The morbidity and mortality rates with embolisation were 8% and 2%, respectively. CONCLUSIONS Embolisation eliminated most of the vascular risk factors, with complete obliteration in 27 cases and size was satisfactorily reduced for later treatment; at the same time, morbidity and mortality rates were acceptable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jan 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución tras la embolización de 100 malformaciones arteriovenosas intracraneales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Progression following the embolisation of 100 intracranial arteriovenous malformations].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
