<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16420816</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Suárez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Sanz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueras, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balsells, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rotellar, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Noguera, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Luis, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artigas, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Güell, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olsina, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cugat, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Experience in laparoscopic liver surgery is limited, and multicenter studies with large series are required for a critical evaluation of this type of surgery. OBJECTIVE To analyze the results of the National Registry of Laparoscopic Liver Surgery. Indications, technical features, conversion rates, morbidity, and mortality were analyzed. PATIENTS AND METHOD Seventy-four patients from 10 centers who underwent surgery between February 2000 and April 2005 were included. There were 58 women and 16 men, with a mean age of 55 years. More than one lesion was present in 16 patients. Consequently, 74 patients with 156 lesions were treated. RESULTS Forty-six patients had cystic lesions (26 simple cysts, 13 polycystic disease, five hydatid cysts and two cystic adenomas). Surgical treatment consisted of 37 fenestrations, five cystopericystectomies, two atypical resections, one segmentectomy and one bisegmentectomy of segments II-III. In 28 patients the lesions were solid (four adenomas, six focal nodular hyperplasias, three hemangiomas, four hepatocarcinomas, five colorectal metastases, two lung metastases, one breast metastasis, one malignant melanoma metastasis, one pancreatic vipoma metastasis, and one lymphoma). Ten bisegmentectomies of segments II-III, 17 atypical resections and one segmentectomy of segment III were performed. Other surgery was associated in 23 patients. The mean operating time was 160.5 minutes and the conversion rate was 8%. The mean length of hospital stay was 5.6 days and was less than 5 days in 78% of the patients. Analgesia was administered for less than 48 hours in 55%. Morbidity was observed in eight patients (10.8%). Reoperations were performed in three patients. There was no mortality in this series. CONCLUSIONS Laparoscopic hepatic resection is safe and feasible in selected patients. Large, controlled series are required to determine long-term outcomes. The national registry provides a good basis for evaluating laparoscopic liver surgery in Spain.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados iniciales del Registro Nacional de Cirugía Hepática por Laparoscopia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Initial results of the National Registry of Laparoscopic Liver Surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
