<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16420850</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez-Rubio, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jurado-Jiménez, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Blanco, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Recio-Moyano, Gumersindo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lozano-Gómez, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Arcos, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The aim of this study was to analyze the influence of superspecialization in endocrine surgery on the standard of thyroidectomy, both before and after the creation of an endocrine surgery unit. PATIENTS AND METHODS We performed a retrospective, comparative study of two 7-year periods. Three hundred forty thyroidectomies (G1) were performed before the instauration of the unit, and 583 were carried out afterwards (G2). The variables of age, gender, anesthesia risk, surgeon expertise (staff vs. resident), thyroid function, pathological features, intrathoracic growth, extent of the procedure (unilateral or bilateral), neck drainage, morbidity and mortality and length of hospital stay were compared. RESULTS Age was older in G2 (G1: 44.7 +/- 15 years old, G2: 48.09 +/- 16.3 years old; p &lt; 0.001). There were no differences (p NS) between the two groups in gender, anesthesia risk, thyroid function or rate of benign/malignant disease, but there was a greater frequency of nodular (p = 0.009) and intrathoracic goiters (p = 0.0004) in the second period. Residents operated on more patients in G2 (p &lt; 0.001). Bilateral thyroidectomy was more frequent in G2 (G1: 155, G2: 315; p = 0.016) as was the rate of total thyroidectomy vs. subtotal or near total thyroidectomy (p &lt; 0.001). Neck drainage also showed statistically significant differences (G1: 75.29%, G2: 12.18%; p &lt; 0.001). No differences were found in overall postoperative complications. Although the procedures used were more aggressive in G2, similar rates of transient asymptomatic hypocalcemia (p NS) and transient symptomatic (p NS) and permanent hypocalcemia were found (G1: 1.17%, G2: 0.68%, p NS). The rate of transitory recurrent laryngeal nerve paralysis was similar with regard to patients (p NS) or nerves at risk (p NS). Permanent inferior laryngeal nerve paralysis was no different regarding patients (p = 0.083) but statistically significant differences were found with regard to nerves at risk (G1: 1.44%, G2: 0.33%; p = 0.04). One patient in G2 died (p NS). Length of hospital stay was shorter in G2 (p &lt; 0.001) and more patients in this group stayed in hospital for only one day (p &lt; 0.001) or were operated on in the outpatient setting (0 versus 71; p &lt; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS An endocrine surgical unit allows more efficient management of thyroidectomy. It increases the rate of total thyroidectomy, reduces definitive complications and improves training of resident surgeons. In addition, it reduces resource use and allows the development of programs of outpatient thyroid surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la superespecialización en cirugía endocrina en los resultados de la tiroidectomía en un servicio de cirugía general.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of superspecialization in endocrine surgery on outcomes of thyroidectomy in a general surgery department].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
