<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16446791</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alarcón, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domingo, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Brea, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Campos, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Obra, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Regañón, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clarithromycin, amoxicillin, tetracycline and metronidazole are the most frequently used antimicrobials for Helicobacter pylori infection treatment. While tetracycline and amoxicillin resistance are rare, clarithromycin and metronidazole resistance vary in different populations and are considered factors for treatment failure. The aim of this study was to determine the in vitro activity of furazolidone and nitrofurantoin in 164 H. pylori clinical isolates by agar dilution and to determine the spontaneous mutation rate. Metronidazole and clarithromycin resistance were 23.77% (CI95%: 18.96-29.14) and 16.78% (CI95%: 12.64-21.62), respectively; moreover, 1.4% (CI95%: 0.38-3.54) were intermediate to clarithromycin. All the isolates were susceptible to amoxicillin and tetracycline. Furazolidone and nitrofurantoin resistance rates were 1.82% (CI95%: 0.37-5.25) and 0.6% (CI95%: 0-3.35), respectively. The three furazolidone-resistant strains were nitrofurantoine-susceptible (MIC 4 mg/l for furazolidone and 2 mg/l for nitrofurantoin) and the nitrofurantoin-resistant strains were furazolidone-susceptible (MIC 4 mg/l for nitrofurantoin and 1 mg/l for furazolidone). These four strains were metronidazole-resistant (MIC 16 mg/l). Furazolidone or nitrofurantoin spontaneous mutants were not detected in the eight H. pylori strains tested. However, mutants with resistance to metronidazole were found with all the strains with a mutation rate of 7.4 x 10(-10) to 9.4 x 10(-10). Furazolidone and nitrofurantoin showed an excellent in vitro activity against the H. pylori clinical isolates included herein, supporting the usefulness of furazolidone as second-line antimicrobial after treatment failure or as first-line therapy in populations with low economical resources.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad in vitro de la furazolidona y la nitrofurantoína en aislamientos clínicos de Helicobacter pylori y estudio de la tasa de mutación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[In vitro activity of furazolidone and nitrofurantoin in Helicobacter pylori clinical isolates and study of mutation rate].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
