<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16454049</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peña, Evelyn</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Armando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, Nelina F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meertens, Lesbia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solano, Liseti</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The zinc intervenes in the growth and development, being of vital importance in the pregnancy. In order to determine the behavior of the serum zinc levels during the pregnancy associating it to the anthropometric nutritional status and dietary intake, 108 pregnants were assessed longitudinally, between March 1998 and December 1999, in the 12, 22 and 33 week pregnancy. Anthropometric parameters, serum zinc and albumin, and dietary intake of energy, proteins, zinc and fiber were determined. Descriptive standards and frequencies were calculated and Student's t test, Wilcoxon signed rank test, one-way analysis of variance and Pearson correlation test were made. Significant decrease of the serum zinc and albumin was observed during the gestation. The serum zinc levels in the first trimester differed significantly according to intake of oligoelement. In the second trimester, zinc concentrations differed significantly according to maternal age and weight gain, while no significant differences were found by parity, pregestational body mass index, height-for-age in none of the trimesters. Changes in the serum zinc concentrations are confirmed throughout the pregnancy, these modifications are explained partially by the decrease of serum albumin. Serum levels of zinc during gestation do not depend of parity or pregestational anthropometric nutritional status.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportamiento de los niveles séricos de zinc durante el embarazo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Behavior of serum zinc levels during pregnancy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
