<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16470299</identifier>
<setSpec>0102-311X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Botero, Waldor Federico</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, Hernán Darío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes, José Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Congolino, Mary Lily</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urrea-Giraldo, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to qualitatively evaluate sexual behaviors or practices and the incidence of sexual and reproductive health programs in adolescent and postadolescent users educated in Cali, Colombia, two quota samples were carried out, one in schools in poor neighborhoods of the city and one at Valle University (UNIVALLE). In addition, a limited number of twelve open interviews was made among two different student population groups, the schools and the university. The study addresses the sexual behaviors of adolescents and postadolescents, contraceptive methods and prevention of STDs and HIV/AIDS, and the uses of sexual and reproductive health programs by both populations, controlling for social class (socioeconomic stratum), gender, and race. Two sexual and reproductive health programs were taken as reference: that of PROFAMILIA (Pro-Wellbeing of the Colombian Family Association), and the sexual and reproductive health program of the University Medical Service of the UNIVALLE. Results show how the behaviors and responses to sexual and reproductive health programs are mediated by multiple sociological categories that orient the analysis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportamientos sexuales e incidencia de los programas de salud sexual y reproductiva en estudiantes de secundaria de sectores populares y de la universidad pública en la ciudad de Cali, Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sexual behaviors and incidence of sexual and reproductive health programs among poor secondary students and public university students in Cali, Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cadernos de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
