<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16476306</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peramiquel, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pernas, Sonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sancho, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes, M Josefina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, M Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Curell, Román</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alomar, Agustín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barnadas, M Asunción</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Post-radiotherapy cutaneous angiosarcomas have been described in different locations, including the breast. We present a case of cutaneous angiosarcoma of the breast, diagnosed 6 years after a carcinoma of the breast had been treated with radiation. The patient was a 44-year-old female with a history of ductal carcinoma (CA) of the right breast treated with tumorectomy, axillary lymphadenectomy, chemotherapy (FEC) and radiotherapy, who 6 years later presented with a violaceous, indurated plaque with a satellite nodule on the same breast. The histology of the skin biopsies showed angiomatous proliferation throughout the entire dermis, with no cellular atypia. Considering the patient's symptoms, history and the changes observed via mammography, it was decided to completely excise the lesion followed by a simple mastectomy, with the diagnosis of angiosarcoma being confirmed. The patient was later treated with paclitaxel, and the disease was apparently controlled. Despite this fact, two years and one month later, the angiosarcoma recurred on the internal area of the mastectomy scar. The patient was treated with paclitaxel, and surgical excision of the lesion area was once again performed. This complication usually appears 5-10 years after treatment with radiotherapy, so angiosarcoma should be ruled out if any angiomatous lesions later appear on skin that had been irradiated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angiosarcoma en mama irradiada: descripción de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Angiosarcoma in an irradiated breast: a case description].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
