<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16642446</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Papazian, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alfonso, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andrade, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luzondo, R J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Herpes simplex encephalitis (HSE) is a focal infectious disease of the central nervous system (CNS) acknowledged the world over as being severe. DEVELOPMENT The epidemiology is well known in developed countries. It presents in patients over the age of 3 months. The mechanism by which the virus reactivates and penetrates into the CNS is still not fully understood. A timely diagnosis is crucial so that early treatment can be established within the first four days of the infectious process. By so doing, it becomes possible to raise the chances of survival by over 50%. The physician should have a strong suspicion when faced with a patient with symptoms of encephalitis, especially if he or she has focal neurological manifestations, including manifestations in the neuropsychiatric sphere. The non-invasive diagnostic method par excellence is high-sensitivity magnetic resonance imaging studies of the brain within the first 24-48 hours following the onset of the clinical signs and symptoms. Determination of viral DNA in cerebrospinal fluid by the polymerase chain reaction method is the technique with the highest degree of sensitivity and specificity available for carrying out the diagnosis. Effective treatment is intravenous acyclovir: 30 mg/kg/day in three doses. CONCLUSIONS Encephalitis produced by the herpes virus is a disease that is dreaded because of the high mortality rate and the devastation it causes in the living conditions of survivors. Our aim is to stimulate the clinical suspicion of HSE so that pharmacological treatment can be established even while diagnostic tests are being carried out. We suggest early neuropsychological evaluation and follow-up of the manifestations of focal sequelae related to the frontotemporal regions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Apr 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las encefalitis herpéticas en niños.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of herpes simplex encephalitis in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
