<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16688291</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alarcón, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Brea, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Peñuela, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznar, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to compare the susceptibility to seven antimicrobials of Acinetobacter baumannii clinical isolates from H. U. de La Princesa of Madrid vs. A. baumannii clinical isolates from Hospital Queen Mary of Hong Kong from January 2004 to March 2005. A total of 74 strains isolated from our hospital and 30 strains attended to Hospital Queen Mary were studied. The MIC (minimal inhibitory concentration) was determined by agar dilution method. NCCLS recommended breakpoints were used against imipenem, tobramycin, amikacin, ofloxacin and ceftazidime. For sulbactam the break point for ampicillin/sulbactam was used. BSAC breakpoint was considered against colistin. Colistin showed the highest susceptibility percentage in Spanish strains (98.64%), followed by imipenem (94.59%) and tobramycin (78.37%). About 50% of the clinical isolates were susceptible to sulbactam (54.05%) and amikacin (51.35%). The majority of the strains were resistant to ofloxacin (2.7% of susceptible strains) and ceftazidime (1.35% of susceptible strains). In the Hong Kong clinical isolates, high susceptibility percentages were shown for most antimicrobials: 96.66% to colistin, sulbactam, tobramycin and amikacin; lower for imipenem (93.33%) and ofloxacin (90%). Ceftazidime presented the lowest susceptibility percentage (10%). In conclusion, higher resistant percentages in Spanish strains than Chinese strains were obtained for most antimicrobials tested. To ofloxacin, 90% of Hong Kong isolates were susceptible while 93% of Madrid isolates were resistant. Geographically remote populations (such as Madrid and Hong Kong) showed important differences according to the susceptibility patterns.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de sensibilidad de aislamientos clínicos de Acinetobacter baumannii en Madrid vs. Hong Kong.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Susceptibility pattern of Acinetobacter baumannii clinical isolates in Madrid vs. Hong Kong].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
