<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16715764</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Elsner, Boris</dc:author>
<dc:author>Curutchet, H Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Falco, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Denninghoff, Valeria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Survival at 5 years of patients with localized primary malignant melanoma is about 80%, compared with a 35% survival in case of lymph nodes involvement. Sentinel lymph node(s) from 45 subjects with diagnosis of malignant melanoma stage I or II was/were studied with hematoxylin-eosin (HE), immunohistochemistry (IHC) and molecular biology (MB) techniques. The population was divided into three groups: HE-/IHC+/MB+, where 67% patients died; HE-/IHC-/MB+, where 57% died; and HE-/IHC-/MB-, where 100% of the patients are alive, with no lymphadenectomy and a median follow-up of 60 months. Those subjects who showed negativity with all the three methods had a null recurrence rate. Data herein obtained suggest a new molecular oncological staging, which would allow the selection of patients with submicroscopic metastases for a complete treatment. Moreover, several patients with no lymph node metastases should not undergo lymphadenectomies, and overtreatment could therefore be avoided.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del ganglio centinela diagnostico y tratamiento del melanoma maligno cutaneo, estadios I y II.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of the sentinel lymph node. Diagnosis and treatment of cutaneous malignant melanoma stages I and II].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
