<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16734072</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rubio Armendariz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso Marrero, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hardisson de la Torre, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Afonso Gutiérrez, V L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero Mesa, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Weller, D M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To satisfactorily implement the critical hazards and check points analysis. SETTING Tenerife Island Subjects: 15 industries INTERVENTION visits to gofio-manufacturing industries were done with the aim of giving advice to employers and workers, and thereafter, the intervention was assessed verifying the hygiene and sanitary conditions of the industry and the correct application of the established auto-control system. RESULTS After the advising intervention, we observed that certain parameters taken into account from the hygiene and sanitary perspective have been corrected, such as modifying the facilities to adapt them to in force regulations, or asking the suppliers to certify raw materials. With regards to food production process, the intervention was effective in such a way that more than have of the industries reduced the time of those phases with higher contamination susceptibility and to carry out the control registries that were established. CONCLUSIONS All industries implemented the auto-control system by means of registration charts of each one of the elaboration phases. 86% of the industries have introduced more hygienic materials. 60% implemented a reduction in intermediate times of production phases. 26% perfmored some obsolete machinery replacement modernaizing the facilities.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación y evaluación del análisis de peligros y puntos de control críticos (APPCC) en las industrias tinerfeñas productoras de Gofio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Implementation and evaluation of critical hazards and check points analysis (CHCPA) in gofio-producing industries from Tenerife].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
