<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16759551</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García del Pozo, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ros, Antonio Aguilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zafrilla, Beatriz Pérez</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Abajo, Francisco J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE In July, 2002, observational post-authorization studies were subjected to regulation in Spain, giving rise to an uproar among sponsors and investigators. The aim of the present report was to assess the scientific and ethical quality of the studies presented during the year before the regulation came into force. In addition, we explored how many of them reached publication. MATERIAL AND METHOD We extracted information relative to administrative procedures, methods, follow-up and ethical issues from the protocol of the studies presented to the Spanish Agency for Medicines and Healthcare Products (AEMPS) during 2001. RESULTS A total of 162 studies intended to recruit 306,539 patients were registered as post-authorization studies in 2001. The most widely used design was the &lt;non-controlled prospective follow-up study&gt; (122 studies; 75%). Physicians were the only source of information in 99% of the studies. In 43% of them, the sample size was neither specified nor justified. In 83% of the studies the observation period per patient was less than 12 months. An ethical review was requested for only 13% of the studies while a procedure to inform patients was planned in 44%. Eleven studies (10% of those finalized) had been published in scientific journals (1 of them international) and 13 (12% of those finalized) were reported as a communication to a national (11) or international (2) congress. CONCLUSIONS Most post-authorization studies presented to the AEMPS in 2001 had poor methodological and ethical quality. Only a few became published, raising doubts about their scientific aims. These results give empirical support to the regulation adopted.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Apr 29 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de los estudios postautorización de tipo observacional registrados en España antes de su regulación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quality of observational post-authorization studies registered in Spain before their regulation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
