<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16756873</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González Elena, Luis Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Ortiz, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Marcos, Manuel A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Rodríguez, Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the effectiveness of an intervention on health workers, based on quality improvement through reduction of cardiovascular risk in patients with hypertension. DESIGN Quasi-experimental study. SETTING Primary care. Two urban health centres. PARTICIPANTS A thousand hypertense patients selected by stratified random sampling. One centre (500) was assigned to implement a quality improvement intervention, while at the other centre (500) "usual care" procedures were followed (control group). INTERVENTIONS The quality improvement intervention consisted of a combined program designed for the medical and nursing staff that comprised audit, feedback, training sessions, and implementation of clinical practice guidelines. MAIN MEASUREMENTS Coronary risk using the Framingham scale and cardiovascular mortality risk using the SCORE project. RESULTS Absolute coronary risk decreased from 16.94% (95% CI, 15.92-17.66) to 13.81% (95% CI, 13.09-14.52) (P&lt;.001) in the intervention group; whilst there was no significant change in the control group, which dropped from 17.63% (95% CI, 16.68-18.53) to 16.82% (95% CI, 15.91-17.74). The intervention led to a 2.28% point decrease (95% CI, 1.35-3.21) (P&lt;.001) in coronary risk. Cardiovascular mortality risk decreased from 2.48% (95% CI, 2.35-2.62) to 2.19% (95% CI, 2.07-2.31) (P&lt;.001) in the intervention group, with no significant change in the control group, which changed from 2.45% (95% CI, 2.30-2.59) to 2.52% (95% CI, 2.38-2.66). The intervention led to a 0.36% point decrease (95% CI, 0.05-0.73) (P&lt;.001) in cardiovascular mortality risk. CONCLUSIONS The quality improvement intervention was effective in decreasing coronary risk and cardiovascular mortality risk in patients with hypertension.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 May 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de una intervención de mejora de calidad en la reducción del riesgo coronario y del riesgo de mortalidad cardiovascular en pacientes hipertensos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectiveness of an intervention to improve quality care in reducing cardiovascular risk in hypertense patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
