<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16762273</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez-Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzana, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porras, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabezudo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Bernardo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Infante, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rayo, J I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Brain tumours show uptake with Thallium-201 Chloride with high target/background rate and they would benefit from radioguided surgery. We report a patient with a brain tumor that was Thallium positive in a brain SPECT. On the next day in the operating room we injected 50 MBq of Thallium-201. At 40 minutes we confirmed tumour uptake with a gamma-probe and with a biopsy sample. After brain tumor resection was completed by conventional method, we found pathologic activity in tumoral bed with the gamma probe, that showed persistence of increased activity. After a new evaluation, residual tumor tissue was located in the pathological uptake area and was removed. Control CT showed complete resection, although the Thallium SPECT carried out after surgery showed faint uptake in the anterior pole of the surgical bed. Radioguided surgery was evaluated as a useful and promising technique by the neurosurgeon.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurocirugía radiodirigida: una aplicación novedosa de la Medicina Nuclear.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Radioguided neurosurgery: a novel application of nuclear medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
