<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16786730</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Páez, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portillo, Zulay</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llovera, Daisy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velásquez, Emma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Adela Barón, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solano, Liseti</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epidemiological studies have shown that unfavorable serum lipids levels in childhood are predictors of development of atherosclerosis lesions in adulthood. We assessed the lipid profile of 297 Venezuelan preschool children (4-7 years old) from two socioeconomic levels in order to compare them by this characteristic. Their social level was determined according to modified Graffar method, and two groups were obtained: high socioeconomic status (HSES, n=103) and low socioeconomic status (LSES, n=194). Nutritional anthropometric evaluation was performed by weight to height, and NCHS/OMS cut-off point was used. Lipid profile was determined by colorimetric biochemical methods and atherogenic risks factors were calculated. Underweight for HSES was 5.8% and for LSES: 14.9%, while normal status was 78.6% and 70.1%, and overweight was 15.5% and 14.9%, respectively. Mean values for triglycerides were 0.66 +/- 0.27and 0.76 +/- 0.31 mmol/L, total cholesterol (TC): 3.61 +/- 0.65 and 2.98 +/- 0.71 mmol/L, HDL-C: 1.04 +/- 0.18 and 0.62 +/- 0.16 mmol/L, LDL-C: 2.27 +/- 0.61 and 2.01 +/- 0.71 mmol/L, TC/HDL-C: 3.5 +/- 0.78 and 5.0 +/- 1.5; LDL-C/HDL-C: 2.0 +/- 0.71 and 3.4 +/- 1.4 with significant differences between HSES and LSES as shown respectively. A significant association was found (p &lt; 0.01) between lipid values and socioeconomic status, being the LSES preschoolers those with the higher atherogenic risk. Its pattern was of lower HDL-C levels, and higher TC/HDL-C and LDL-C/HDL-C ratio. Comparisons of lipid profile by nutritional status or gender did not show significant differences. Findings indicate that children from low socioeconomic status are at a higher risk for cardiovascular disease and atherosclerosis than children from high socioeconomic status.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil lipídico en preescolares venezolanos según nivel socioeconómico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Lipid profile in Venezuelan preschoolers by socioeconomic status].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
