<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16792453</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gayoso Diz, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sueiro Benavides, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Seara, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Macenlle García, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES to determine the prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection in the general adult population of the province of Ourense. MATERIAL AND METHODS a cross-sectional study was carried out with a randomly selected populational sample. The diagnosis of Helicobacter pylori infection was reached using the 13C-urea breath test. RESULTS three hundred and eighty-three subjects were studied, with a prevalence rate of 69.1% (95% CI: 61.7-75.1%); 69.8% (95% CI: 63.2-76.6%) in males and 68.4% (95% CI: 61.5-75.4%) in females (difference not statistically significant). Prevalence increases with age up to a maximum of 88.4% in the 45-54 years age group, and decreases thereafter to a rate of 57.1% in individuals over the age of 84 years. CONCLUSION this study reveals that the prevalence rate of Helicobacter pylori infection is high in the general adult population of the province of Ourense. It increases with age until it peaks in the group of middle-aged individuals and is similar in both sexes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection in the general adult population of the province of Ourense.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
