<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16802045</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Soto S, Juan Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Concepción Ch, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yovaniniz L, Patricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vukasovic R, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sepúlveda M, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro G, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nazzal N, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garcés F, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrada K, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cavada Ch, Gabriel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Heart failure (HF) with preserved ejection fraction (EF) is a condition of growing interest due to its high prevalence and difficult management. AIM To evaluate the clinical profile of patients hospitalized with HF and preserved EF in Chilean hospitals. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective registry of 15 centers. Among 649 patients hospitalized in functional class III and IV, an echocardiogram was performed to 353. Preserved EF was defined quantitatively as an EF &gt;50%. RESULTS Out the 353 patients, 45% presented an EF &gt;50%. Mean age in patients with EF &gt;50 and -50% was 66+/-13 and 67+/-13 years, respectively. Among patients with HF and EF &gt;50%, the proportion of women was higher (73.7 and 36.3%, p &lt;0.001), the proportion of patients with a history of hypertension (76.8 and 65.5%, p &lt;0.05) and the presence of atrial fibrillation was also higher (62.3 and 47.8%, p &lt;0.01) and a history of myocardial infarction was lower (17.1 and 29.5%, p &lt;0.05). The diastolic diameter of the left ventricle was significantly lower in HF with preserved EF (51.0+10 and 63.5+10 mm respectively, p &lt;0.001). No differences in the length of hospital stay and mortality were observed between HF with depressed and preserved EF. Female gender was an independent predictor for the presence of HF with preserved EF (Odds ratio: 2.62; confidence intervals: 1.1-6.1). CONCLUSIONS HF and preserved EF is common among hospitalized patients, particularly in women and subjects with a history of hypertension and atrial fibrillation. Hospitalization length and mortality were similar in patients with either preserved or depressed EF.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la insuficiencia cardíaca en pacientes con fracción de eyección preservada: resultados del registro Nacional de insuficiencia Cardíaca, grupo ICARO.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characteristics of heart failure with preserved ejection fraction: results of the Chilean national registry of heart failure, ICARO].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
