<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16838467</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín Fernández, Jesus</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND A debate exists as to whether it is advisable to extend the influenza immunization programs to the entire population, possibly due to the economic impact of this measure. This study is aimed at analyzing the cost-benefit ratio of an influenza immunization strategy among our country's working population. METHODS Economic study from a social standpoint, including the direct and indirect costs (lost productive time, adverse effects) of the immunization. The costs avoided include the loss of productivity (from the human capital standpoint) and the health costs avoided when the infection is prevented. A costs avoided/costs incurred ratio, known as the Return Rate (RR) is constructed. The costs are converted into constant 2003 Euros. The data was compiled from published sources and a sensitivity analysis presented. RESULTS The average cost of each immunization is 13.58 (95% CI 13.54-13.62) Euros. Each case of influenza avoided saves an average expense of 374.71 (95% CI 372.59-376.83) Euros. Every 1000 immunizations would avoid an average of 29.3 influenza cases (95% CI 29.0-29.5). The net cost of immunization is 2.60 (95% CI 2.51-2.70) euros. The RR has an average value of 0.80 (95% CI 0.79-0.81), median 0.74, interquartile range (0.53-1.02) Euros. In the case of avoiding more than 36 cases of influenza per 1000 immunizations, the RR takes on values &gt;1. CONCLUSIONS The influenza immunization strategy for the working population is solely cost-effective for situations of high influence incidence and high vaccine effectiveness.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analisis de un modelo económico de una estrategia poblacional de vacunación gripal en trabajadores sanos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of a economic model of a populational influenza immunization strategy in healthy employees].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
