<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16875355</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zacarías, Rogelio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arenas, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes, Adán</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, Ramón F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Dapsone with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazol is currently the standard treatment for actinomycetoma. In select cases, amikacin, streptomycin, kanamycin, amoxicillin/clavulanic acid or phosphomycin may be also added. Imipenem has shown to be effective both in vitro and in vivo against some actinomycetes. Amikacin with Imipenem has a synergistic effect. OBJECTIVES To report our preliminary findings using imipenem alone or with amikacin for severe or multi-resistant mycetomas due to Nocardia sp. MATERIAL AND METHODS We present 5 cases of chronic mycetoma infection previously treated with anti-bacterial multidrug regimens. All patients were hospitalized and treated with imipenem 500 mg IV, three times a day for three weeks. Three patients received in addition amikacin. RESULTS We included 3 male and 2 female patients. The average length of disease duration was 7.4 years. In 3 cases mycetoma was located on the back; one of them involved the rib and the lung. One case was localized in the abdominal wall, and another one involved the posterior side of the cervical region. Two patients achieved clinical and bacteriological cure one year after treatment with Imipenem, and the remaining three displayed clinical improvement, even though grains were observed, cultures where negative. None of the 5 patients studied showed clinical evidence of adverse reactions to Imipenem. CONCLUSIONS Imipenem is a strong antibiotic and constitutes an important treatment alternative for severe or multi-resistant mycetoma especially for cases with bone and visceral involvement.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actinomicetoma por Nocardia sp. Informe de cinco casos tratados con imipenem solo o combinado con amikacina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Actinomycetoma and Nocardia sp. Report of five cases treated with imipenem or imipenem plus amikacin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
