<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16887077</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-7411</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lámbarry-Arroyo, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Morfín, Iván</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orozco-Gómez, Luis Porfirio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moguel-Ancheita, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND We undertook this study to evaluate the long-term effects of threshold retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) treatment using Argon laser under indirect ophthalmoscopy, as well as to analyze ocular diseases in those patients. METHODS This is a descriptive, observational, longitudinal and prospective study carried out from March 1991 to February 2005, including patients with threshold retinopathy of prematurity for treatment using Argon laser under indirect ophthalmoscopy. Related ocular diseases were also reported. Descriptive statistics were applied. RESULTS Follow-up was maintained for 14 years, 6.50 +/- 1.39 (CI 95%, p &lt; 0.05), and 170 patients were studied. Weight was 1216.50 +/- 152.03 g (CI 95%, p &lt; 0.05). Retinopathy was not present in 42% (72), in stage I-III, 46% (78), and threshold stage, 12% (20). Forty eyes were treated with Argon laser. After treatment, no progressive disease was found in 92.75%. We found high myopia in 20%, macular displacement 7.5%, strabismus 35%, retinal detachment (5%), optical nerve atrophy 5%, and ocular atrophy 5%. CONCLUSIONS We were able to demonstrate that Argon laser treatment under indirect ophthalmoscopy has been effective in the control of threshold disease. The most important related ocular diseases were strabismus and myopia. Long-term monitoring has permitted us to initiate timely treatment for ocular diseases related to prematurity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de los pacientes con retinopatía de prematuro en estadio umbral tratados con láser de argón mediante oftalmoscopia indirecta.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evolution of threshold retinopathy of prematurity after argon laser treatment under indirect ophthalmoscopy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
