<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16925102</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castañeda, Elizabeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Firacative, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Streptococcus pneumoniae serotype 5 is an important cause of invasive disease in Colombia where the circulation of the clone Colombia5-19, penicillin susceptible but tetracycline and chloramphenicol resistant, has been demonstrated. OBJECTIVE To establish the genetic relatedness among Colombian invasive S. pneumoniae serotype 5 isolates, recovered between 1994 and 2004, and the clone Colombia(5)-19. MATERIALS AND METHODS Eighty three isolates with penicillin, vancomycin, ceftriaxone, erythromycin, trimethoprim-sulfametoxazole, chloramphenicol and tetracycline susceptibility patterns were studied. Of these isolates, 29 were recovered from children less than 5 years of age. DNA restriction patterns of all isolates were determined for pulsed field gel electrophoresis, using the Smal enzyme. Genetic similarity among isolates and the clone Colombia(5)-19 was established according to Tenover's criteria and the Fingerprintingä II program. RESULTS All isolates were related with the Colombia(5)-19 clone and belonged to the electrophoretic pattern A, of which 17 subtypes were derived. Most of the isolates belonged to patterns A (38,6%), A8 (21,7%) and A5 (12%), the other 23 isolates belonged to 15 electrophoretic patterns. Thirty -four isolates resistant both to tetracycline and chloramphenicol were related with electrophoretic patterns A (n = 32), A16 (n = 1) and A28 (n = 1), which have a band of 340 Kb in common with the clone. CONCLUSION These results showed the continuing circulation of S pneumoniae serotype 5 isolates in the country, and which are genetically related with the clone Colombia(5)-19.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización molecular de aislamientos invasores colombianos de Streptococcus pneumoniae serotipo 5 recuperados entre 1994 y 2004.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Molecular characterization of Colombian invasive serotype 5 Streptococcus pneumoniae isolates recovered between 1994 and 2004].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
