<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16933485</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chantada Abal, Venancio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Rodríguez-Losada, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Rosado, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rois Soto, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To describe the technique of renal radiofrequency (RF) thermal ablation. Case report of a successful nephron-sparing surgery after failure of the RF thermal ablation of a renal adenocarcinoma in a patient with a single kidney. METHODS A patient presenting with a renal adenocarcinoma in a single left kidney was treated by RF thermal ablation. The failure of the technique was patent on follow-up after demonstration of a central area of necrosis surrounded by a peripheral contrast enhancing area. Nephron sparing surgery was indicated as salvage procedure. RESULTS Surgical excision of the tumor with a safety margin, without renal pedicle clamping was undertaken. Fat tissue and hemostatic synthetic material were placed in the surgical bed. Pathology report: renal adenocarcinoma with changes secondary to central necrosis. Twenty-four month postoperative follow-up: fatty renal nodule with small fibrous tracts inside in the area of the tumor. No evidence of contrast enhancing areas. Normal renal function (sCr 0.7 mg/dl, urea 24 mg/dl). CONCLUSIONS Radiofrequency thermal ablation is a relatively new technique. Its oncological efficacy greatly depends on appropriate case selection. One of its main caveats is achieving an area of tissue ablation enough to completely destroy the tumor. When the technique fails, renal surgery (nephron sparing or not) seems to be the most recommended alternative.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía renal conservadora de nefronas como tratamiento de rescate tras fracaso de la termoablación mediante radiofrecuencia en paciente monorreno con adenocarcinoma renal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Nephron sparing renal surgery as salvage treatment after failure of radiofrequency thermal ablation in a patient with a single kidney and renal adenocarcinoma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
