<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>16948989</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luburich, Patricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Xaubet, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lario, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrión, María Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Molina, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Transforming growth factor ss1 (TGF-ss1) is one of the key profibrotic mediators in the pathogenesis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF). The purpose of this study was to investigate the prognostic value of quantifying TGF-ss1 levels in patients with IPF. PATIENTS AND METHODS We conducted a prospective study of 29 IPF patients and 27 healthy controls. Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays were used to quantify TGF-ss1 levels. RESULTS Mean (SD) TGF-ss1 levels were significantly higher in the IPF patients than in the control subjects (11.1 [7.5] ng/mL vs 4 [2.4] ng/mL; P&lt; .01). Weak inverse correlations were observed between TGF-ss1 levels and both forced vital capacity and total lung capacity. Thirteen IPF patients were evaluated at 8 (1.2) months (range, 5-9 months). The mean TGF-ss1 level was 18.2 (15) ng/mL and there were no significant differences with respect to the initial measurement of 11.1 (7.5) ng/mL. No correlation was observed between changes in respiratory function and changes in TGF-ss1 levels. CONCLUSIONS Although plasma levels of TGF-beta1 were high in the patients with IPF, they do not appear to be a useful prognostic marker of disease activity or therapeutic response.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación en plasma del factor transformador del crecimiento beta1 en la fibrosis pulmonar idiopática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quantifying plasma levels of transforming growth factor beta1 in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
