<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17022307</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Schally, Andrew V</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Bárcena, David</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Early clinical trials in Mexico with analogs of luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LH-RH) also known as gonadotropin releasing hormone (Gn-RH), were reviewed. Extensive clinical studies were carried out at IMSS with agonists of LH-RH, both in men and woman. All subjects responded to LH-RH agonists with a release of LH and FSH, but repeated administration of these analogs, initially aimed at stimulation of fertility (thought to stimulate fertility), was later shown to result in inhibition due to desensitization of pituitary gland and downregulation of LH-RH receptors. Various clinical investigations with LH-RH antagonists were also carried out. This included the first demonstration that LH-RHantagonists can suppress LH and FSH and sex steroid secretion in men and women. Various studies in Mexico with early LH-RH antagonists aimed at the development of new contraceptive methods were reviewed. Modern LH-RH antagonist Cetrorelix was shown to be effective in men and women and useful in treatment of uterine leiomyomas and benign prostatic hyperplasia. Major oncological studies were also carried out with agonist D-Trp6-LH-RH and antagonist Cetrorelix in men with prostate cancer, which demonstrated therapeutic efficacy of both types of analogs. Some endocrine studies with early analogs of somatostatin were also cited and a clinical trial with somatostatin analog vapreotide in patients with relapsed prostate cancer was reviewed. All these studies played a major role in introducing analogs of hypothalamic-releasing hormones into clinical medicine.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia de los estudios clínicos con los análogos de las hormonas hipotalámicas en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[History of clinical studies on hypothalamic hormone analogs in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
