<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17078402</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peña de la Moneda, Héctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>García García, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo González, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Padrón Valdés, Froilán</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil del Valle, Yamel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lázaro Rodríguez Collar, Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To report one case of synchronic prostate cancer and bilateral renal tumors, radiologically suggestive of renal cell carcinoma. METHODS We present the case of a 63-year-old diabetic male, heavy smoker, who presents at the outpatient office complaining of right upper quadrant abdominal pain and mild obstructive voiding symptoms. Abdominal examination was negative and digital rectal examination revealed a rock hard irregular prostate. RESULTS The prostatic biopsy showed a moderately differentiated prostate adenocarcinoma. Abdominal ultrasound showed the existence of a 6 cm heterogeneous complex tumor at the lower pole and middle portion of the right kidney, and another at the upper pole-middle left kidney. CT scan confirmed the tumors, which enhanced with contrast. Chest x-ray and bone scan were negative for metastases. Two fine-needle aspiration biopsies of the right kidney tumor were unsuccessful and patient refused to undergo further diagnostic procedures. Treatment for the prostate cancer with LHRH analogues and antiandrogenic drugs was started. The three-month follow-up CT scan showed no variation. CONCLUSIONS Despite the absence of a histological diagnosis due to refusal of the patient, CT scan images are typical of bilateral renal cell carcinoma, supporting the idea that in the presence of a genitourinary neoplasia we should suspect and rule out a synchronic second tumor of the same apparatus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer prostático y tumor renal bilateral sincrónicos. A propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prostate cancer and bilateral synchronic renal tumors. Case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
