<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17099849</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Poeta, L S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosa-Neto, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is one of the most frequent disorders in childhood. According to the literature, ADHD is a syndrome produced by multiple causes that depend on genetic factors and environmental and social adversities. AIMS Our aim was to describe the biopsychosocial characteristics of schoolchildren with ADHD indicators. PATIENTS AND METHODS The sample used in our study consisted of 31 children (aged between 7 and 10 years) studying in the first and second course of primary education in state-run schools in Florianopolis (Santa Catarina, Brazil), who had ADHD indicators based on the Diagnostic and Statistic Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) and the EDAH questionnaires, which were answered by teachers and parents. The mothers and another legal guardian of these children answered a biopsychosocial questionnaire that contained questions concerning their pre, peri and postnatal history, neuropsychomotor development, family environment and questions about ADHD. RESULTS Findings showed a number of diverse risk factors that may be related with the disorder. Many of these biopsychosocial characteristics were highly prevalent in the children in this study. They cannot, however, be considered to be a cause of the disorder but they may be possible risk factors. CONCLUSIONS Knowledge of the child's history is important to be able to reach an accurate diagnosis, as well as to try to prevent and treat this syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Nov 16-30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características biopsicosociales de los escolares con indicadores de trastorno de déficit de atención e hiperactividad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The biopsychosocial characteristics of schoolchildren with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder indicators].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
