<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17147065</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rebato Ochoa, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rocandio Pablo, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salces Beti, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ansotegui Alday, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pascual Apalauza, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arroyo Izaga, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess diet quality and to examine the association between diet quality and overweight and obesity in a group of university students. SUBJECTS Our simple consisted of 749 volunteer students of the State University of the Basque Country (68% females and 32% males). Mean age was 21.52 +/- 2.50 years old. METHODS Dietary intake data were obtained from food frequency questionnaire. This questionnaire was validated using a 24 hour recall technique. From these data the diet quality index score was calculated. The total diet quality index score ranges from 0 to 50. Body mass index was used as criteria to identify overweight and obesity. Demographic data (age, sex), smoking status and alcohol use were also registered. The statistical analyses were performed with SPSS vs 13.0. Significance level P &lt; 0.05. RESULTS Prevalence of overweight and obesity for the total sample was 17.5% (25% in males and 13.9% in females). The mean diet quality index was 31.93 +/- 5.62. The diet quality index score was higher in women and among individuals who have a consumption of alcohol lower than 3 times per week. The mean diet quality index was significantly lower among obese and overweight subjects compared to the normal weight individuals in total sample and in men. CONCLUSIONS Our results suggest that diet quality is associated with overweight and obesity in this population, and that this association varied across sex groups and groups according to alcohol consumption. Since the diet quality index is based on the Dietary Guidelines, the use of these guidelines as a way to improve health should be emphasized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de la dieta, sobrepeso y obesidad en estudiantes universitarios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diet quality, overweight and obesity in university students].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
