<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17140052</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Avila Escobedo, Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerrero Hernández, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Méndez, Eric</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Portal hypertension is associated with splanchnic vasodilatation and baroreceptors activation with secondary renal vasoconstriction. OBJECTIVE To measure the pulsatility and resistance index in the renal arteries: Segmentaries and arcuates of both kidneys in cirrhotic patients Child-Pugh A, B, C classes and compared them with healthy controls. PATIENTS AND METHODS Thirty patients with cirrhosis were included: Ten patients Child A, 10 were Child B and 10 Child C class and 10 healthy patients, we measured the resistance index (RI = [systolic peak velocity-minimum diastolic velocity]/systolic peak velocity) and the pulsatility index (PI = [systolic peak velocity-minimum diastolic velocity]/medium velocity) with Doppler spectral analysis. RESULTS The RI in controls had an average of 0.55 +/- 0.11. In child A: 0.79 +/- 0.114, in Child B 0.77 +/- 0.104 and in Child C 0.85 +/- 0.037. For the pulsatility index the values were: 0.98 +/- 0.21, 1.4 +/- 0.105, 1.72 +/- 0.206, and 2.04 +/- 0.346, respectively. The resistances and pulsatility index were higher in patients with cirrhosis at the time to be compared with healthy controls, which represent a diminishment in blood flow. At the time to compare each one of the Child stages with controls, both index resulted higher in cirrhotic patients, but when we compared the cirrhotic patients between them, only difference for RI in child B vs. C was evident. The differences in PI were evident between each one of the Child classes. DISCUSSION The present study proved that a non invasive method like Doppler ultrasound is useful in the evaluation of the renal hemodynamic changes in cirrhotic patients with a good correlation between Child class and IP.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemodinámica renal y su correlación con el estadio de Child-Pugh en pacientes cirróticos y controles sanos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Renal hemodynamics and its correlation with the Child-Pugh stage in cirrhotic patients and their controls].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
