<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17169287</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Luis, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aller, Rocío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zarzuelo, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertension has a high prevalence and worldwide distribution, secondary to economics, social, cultural and ethnics factors. The prevalence increases with the age, over 50 year a 50% of the population has hypertension. No pharmacological approach is an important device in the treatment of these patients, salt restriction is one of the main dietary treatment. A lot of studies and designs have been realized in this topic area with controversial results. In summary, restriction in salt intake improves blood pressure (BP). However, other nutritional interventions such as DASH diet (Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension) have been usefull. This diet is low in saturated fat, total fat and cholesterol, and it has high levels of fruit, vegetable, pulses and semiskimmed dairy products. In a recent metaanalysis, it has been demonstrated the improvement in BP with different interventions: aerobic exercise, 4.6 mmHg, reducing alcohol intake, 3.8 mmHg, decreasing salt intake, 3.6 mmHg and using supplements of fish oil, 2.3 mmHg. In conclusion, restriction in salt intake is important in the prevention and treatment of hypertension. However this treatment has another piece in the integral approach of this entity with weight reduction programs, suppression of coffe, alcohol and smoking habit, and a right source and type of fats.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Nov 04 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sal en la dieta en la era de los antihipertensivos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dietary salt in the era of antihypertensive drugs].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
