<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17175932</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cabello Benavente, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Fernández, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herranz Amo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monzó, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Subirá Ríos, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Salamanca, J I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To undertake a cost comparison (cost minimization) between transperitoneal laparoscopic and opened nephrectomy in renal adenocarcinoma treatment. METHOD Retrospective study on the first 26 patients submitted to LN without intra or postoperative complications in the period 2002-2003, using as control 22 patients treated with ON with the same characteristics and in the same period. Demographic variables were evaluated (age, sex, tumor size, etc.), intraoperative (operative time and fungible material used) and postoperative (length of stay in Postanaesthesic Care Unit, Acute Pain Unit needs and hospital stay). Our Hospital costs plus those imputed during year 2003 to the Urology Service, as well as the cost of fungible material for the same year were applied, carrying out a comparison of costs between both groups. RESULTS There were no differences between the demographic variables between both groups except in the tumor, bigger size in the opened nephrectomy (p=0,001). Transperitoneal laparoscopic was 29,4% globally more expensive than opened nephrectomy. The transperitoneal laparoscopic intraoperative cost (operating room, anesthesia and fungibles) the exceeded in 151,6% to that of the opened nephrectomy, whereas in the opened nephrectomy the postoperative cost was a 63 % higher than in the transperitoneal laparoscopic cases. CONCLUSIONS Transperitoneal laparoscopic in our Center is more expensive than opened nephrectomy due to a major occupation of operating room and that the specific fungible material used at the surgical act has a very high cost. It would be necessary to drastically reduce surgical time and decrease fungible material expenses, thus transperitoneal laparoscopic procedure could be competitive in our Hospital.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de costes entre la nefrectomía radical laparoscópica y la abierta en el adenocarcinoma renal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Opened vs. laparoscopic radical nephrectomy in renal adenocarcinoma cost comparison].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
