<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17173812</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villa-Barragán, Juan Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Constantino-Casas, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes-Morales, Hortensia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Cuevas, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Arreola, Laura Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vladislavovna Doubova, Svetlana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the health needs of the eligible public population of the Mexican Institute of Social Security (IMSS). DESIGN Observational, descriptive, transversal study. SETTING Family Medicine Unit number 8 of the IMSS, in the city of Tlaxcala, Mexico. PARTICIPANTS A sample of 1200 families using multi-stage sampling, between October 1999 and March 2000. MAIN MEASUREMENTS The designed and validated questionnaire on "Family health diagnosis" was used. RESULTS A 19.2% of the families had a very low socio-economic level, and 14.9% of subjects were not entitled to Social Security. Functional illiteracy in at least one member was found in 12.6% of the families. According to the family Apgar, 93% of families were functional and two-thirds of the families were classified as nuclear. About 51.1% and 36.9% of women used programs for detection of cervical/uterine and breast cancer, respectively. Only 25% of the adult population underwent the detection tests for diabetes mellitus and hypertension and 10.9% had a chronic disease. 56.4% of families considered the quality of health care good, and only 18.13% were satisfied with the care received. CONCLUSIONS Identification of health needs through diagnosis of family health is useful as a basis for establishing a hierarchy of problems as well as for developing health programs that may facilitate greater equity in attention.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Oct 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las necesidades de salud en atención primaria mediante el diagnóstico de salud de la familia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of primary care health needs through family health diagnosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
