<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17184010</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ortega, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Carcedo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vallejo, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrero, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Carcedo, L M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Carotid body paragangliomas (CBP) are relatively rare tumors arising from the carotid body paraganglion. Clinical signs and images are necessary to establish the diagnosis. Surgery is the preferred method of treatment, paying special attention to the carotid artery. Nine patients with carotid body tumors were identified, three of them with complicated diagnosis. One patient is treated with radiotherapy. Out of the eight surgical patients, three preserved the whole arterial structure, the external carotid artery is resected in two patients, the carotid artery is replaced (safen graft, gore tex prosthesis) in other two patients, and the common carotid was tied in the remaining patient. Our objective is to show the decisions taken in the patients from our casuistic, comparing them to the literature data. We conclude that the diagnosis may be deceptive, and that the attitude forward the carotid is variable, always being prepared to do arterial replacement techniques.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento de los paragangliomas carotídeos. Presentación de nueve casos y revisión de la literatura.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diagnosis and treatment of carotid body paragangliomas. Presentation of 9 cases and review of the literature].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
