<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17192219</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Monjero Ares, Inmaculada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado Plasencia, Luciano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Rabelo, Juan Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torregrosa-Gallud, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuesta, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For the last two decades, general and digestive surgeons have attempted to improve the postoperative course of surgical patients. Classical perioperative treatment can be described as a period of preoperative dehydration caused by fasting and intensive colon preparation followed by fluid overload generally due to excessively prolonged serum therapy. There is also perioperative surgical stress, the trauma of surgery itself, and a long period of drainage and nasogastric tubes. The patient is thus literally confined to bed and mobilization is, at the very least, difficult. Moreover, the use of opiates delays intestinal peristalsis and consequently oral nutrition. All together, these factors prolong the length of hospital stay and hamper recovery. All these perioperative treatment modalities have been questioned by Kehlet, resulting in a set of new, more realistic and evidence-based modalities, currently known as the fast-track program. The aim of this program is to decrease perioperative stress, reduce organ involvement produced by surgical trauma and hasten the patient's general recovery. Major advantages of this program consist not only of shorter length of hospital stay but also of a concurrent improvement in patients' quality of life and a reduction in mortality. The present review article analyzes all these modalities, with special emphasis on laparoscopic colorectal surgery. This approach is presented as one of the elements of the fast-track program.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programas de rehabilitación multimodal (fast-track) en cirugía laparoscópica colorrectal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fast-track multimodal rehabilitation programs in laparoscopic colorectal surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
