<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17211486</identifier>
<setSpec>1022-5129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Burgos Chávez, Othoniel Abelardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Zavala, Neyda Milagros</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yan Quiroz, Edgar Fermín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Determining the prognostic factors, clinical and pathological characteristics, surgical morbidity and mortality and actuarial survival after five (5) years of patients with obstructive and non-obstructive excisable colorectal cancer. MATERIAL AND METHODS Descriptive, correlative, longitudinal and observational study at the Belen Hospital in Trujillo of 88 patients with excisable colorectal cancer and a histological confirmation of their disease, between 1966 and 2000. RESULTS The mean age of the total series was 62.35 +/- 14.64 years; the primary tumor (p = 0.001) and regional ganglionic condition (p = 0.0001) were the factors associated with the five year survival in both groups of patients with obstructive and non-obstructive colorectal cancer. Furthermore, the size of the tumors and distance metastasis were also prognostic factors associated in patients with non-obstructive colorectal cancer. Actuarial survival at 60 months of patients with obstructive and non-obstructive colorectal cancer who had surgery for curative purposes was 65.5% and 20%, respectively (p = 0.0135). The actuarial survival rate of patients with obstructive excisable colorectal cancer was 9.5% and in patients with non-obstructive colorectal cancer it was 35.1% (p = 0.1480). CONCLUSIONS The primary tumor and regional ganglionic condition were prognostic factors in both groups. Furthermore, size of the tumors, distance metastasis and clinical stage were also prognostic factors in patients with non-obstructive colorectal cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronósticos de sobrevida en cáncer colorectal resecable obstructivo y no obstructivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prognostic factors of survival in obstructive and non-obstructive excisable colorectal cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
