<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17228642</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carreras Delgado, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Scola Yurrita, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado Bolton, R C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pasamontes Pingarrón, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo Manuel, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera Martín, M N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND This study aimed to assess the results obtained with the positron emission tomography (PET) and conventional anatomic imaging methods (CT scan and MRI) in the diagnosis of suspicion of tumor recurrence in head and neck cancers. METHODS Thirty patients with suspicion of tumor recurrence due to head and neck cancers were reviewed retrospectively. Consequently, 34 PET studies were performed. The images were obtained in the PET Institute of Madrid. They were interpreted by visual and semiquantitative analysis. The results were confirmed with clinical follow-up, response to treatment or with histological studies in some cases. RESULTS Sensitivity and specificity of the PET were 95.6% and 81.8% respectively, while it was 65% and 80% for the CT scan/MRI. CONCLUSIONS We can conclude that PET provides better results than conventional imaging techniques in the detection of head and neck cancer recurrence.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación entre la PET 18F-FDG y las técnicas de imagen convencionales (TAC y RMN) en el diagnóstico de sospecha de recurrencia de tumores de cabeza y cuello.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison between 18F-FDG PET and conventional imaging techniques (CT SCAN and MRI) in the diagnosis of head and neck tumor suspicion of recurrence].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
