<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1723277</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cruz, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zepeda, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avilés, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An analysis of the possible late effects in 15 children of mothers with Hodgkin Disease, who were given combined chemotherapy during pregnancy, including five who were in the first trimester of development, was conducted. None of the newborns were found to have congenital abnormalities during birth. The 15 children, ranging in ages between 4 to 17, are alive, showing both normal physical and psychomotor development, as well as normal laboratory and cytogenetic results. The thirteen mothers who were in complete remission as a result of the chemotherapy used at recommended dosages and at accepted intervals, are alive and without any evidence of the illness, considering them as cured. Based on these results, pregnancy should not be considered as a contraindication for the adequate treatment of Hodgkin's disease, since those fetuses who received cytotoxic agents in utero, did not show a greater incidence of congenital malformations and have not shown any evidence of side-effects due to the chemotherapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Hodgkin durante el embarazo. Estudio de efectos tardíos en los recién nacidos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hodgkin's disease during pregnancy. Study of late effects in the newborn infants].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
