<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17244496</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-7411</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cicero-Sabido, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro-Reynoso, Francisco Pascual</dc:author>
<dc:author>Páramo-Arroyo, Rafael F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pimentel-Ugarte, Lorenzo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Pleural effusion is a common clinical entity. Proper diagnosis and management are important for successful treatment. We undertook this study to evaluate immediate results of the procedures used in a group of cases with pleural effusion. METHODS Of 2589 patients at first consultation, 787 were hospitalized and 156 had pleural effusion. Diagnostic and therapeutic procedures used were evaluated. RESULTS With thoracentesis and evacuation of liquid, 23 nonneoplastic cases had resolution. Chest tube drainage with water seal was performed in 133 patients. This procedure suppressed the effusion in 109 patients, but in 24 patients another approach was necessary. In this group there were 35 neoplastic and 96 nonmalignant cases, the latter 36 were provoked by iatrogenic management. Twenty two cases of pneumothorax considered as gaseous effusion and 10 cases of chronic empyema sequelae of pleural effusions were also studied. Proportion comparison demonstrated significant differences between neoplastic and nonneoplastic effusions (p =0.001) and in cases managed with minimally invasive procedures and chest tube drainage (p =0.001). The performance of pleurodesis and thoracoscopy is discussed. In chronic cases, indications of open window thoracostomy and myoplasty are elucidated. CONCLUSIONS In pleural effusion, opportune diagnosis and proper management are essential. Drainage tube can solve the majority of cases. Pneumothorax must be treated in the same way. In chronic empyema, open window thoracostomy and myoplasty are indicated. Careless patient management and poor treatment lead to iatrogenic complications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procedimientos quirúrgicos en 156 casos de derrame pleural. Resultados inmediatos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Surgical procedures in 156 cases of pleural effusion. Immediate results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
