<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17295595</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Otero, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cearra, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Astorquiza, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Cristóbal, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Alonso, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE An intestinal reperfusion study with two aims: a) to assess the usefulness of intestinal capillary blood flow measurement by laser-Doppler for intestinal reperfusion studies; and b) to compare the effects of racemic and levo forms of folinic acid in treating the syndrome. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN A murine model of intestinal ischemia by completely clamping the superior mesenteric artery for 90 minutes. A comparison was made of three treatment groups: saline, folinic acid, and levo-folinic acid. The following factors were analyzed: changes in biochemical parameters (levels of creatine kinase, lactic dehydrogenase, and alkaline phosphatase at 60 minutes, and at two and seven days after restoring blood flow), capillary flow in the jejunum and ileum by laser-Doppler (during ischemia and after the first hour of reperfusion), intestinal mucosa injury, and survival curve. RESULTS Laser-Doppler provided reliable data on how the different treatments affected capillary flow during intestinal reperfusion. Levo-folinic acid improved capillary flow in the ileum after 25 minutes of reperfusion, and also reduced mucosal injury in the same stretch of intestine by the seventh day post-reperfusion (p&lt;0.05). On the other hand, it produced an initial increase in serum enzymes during reperfusion, and did not modify survival. CONCLUSIONS The changes observed in intestinal capillary blood flow measurement by laser-Doppler have similarities with the effects of drugs on pathological mucosal changes. We could not prove that the levo form of folinic acid has a stronger protective effect versus racemic folinic acid in intestinal ischemia-reperfusion syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El flujo como indicador del efecto terapéutico del ácido folínico en la isquemia-reperfusión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Capillary blood flow as an index of the therapeutic effect of folinic acid in ischemia-reperfusion syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
