<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17319429</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Baptista Macaroff, W M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castroman Espasandín, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was to assess the cumulative sum (cusum) method for evaluating the performance of our hospital's acute postoperative pain service. MATERIAL AND METHODS The period of analysis was 7 months. Analgesic failure was defined as a score of 3 points or more on a simple numerical scale. Acceptable failure (p0) was set at 20% of patients upon admission to the postanesthetic recovery unit and at 7% 24 hours after surgery. Unacceptable failure was set at double the p0 rate at each time (40% and 14%, respectively). The unit's patient records were used to generate a cusum graph for each evaluation. RESULTS Nine hundred four records were included. The rate of failure was 31.6% upon admission to the unit and 12.1% at the 24-hour postoperative assessment. The curve rose rapidly to the value set for p0 at both evaluation times (n = 14 and n = 17, respectively), later leveled off, and began to fall after 721 and 521 cases, respectively. CONCLUSIONS Our study shows the efficacy of the cusum method for monitoring a proposed quality standard. The graph also showed periods of suboptimal performance that would not have been evident from analyzing the data en block. Thus the cusum method would facilitate rapid detection of periods in which quality declines.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización del método de la suma acumulada (cusum) para la evaluación continua de la calidad de la analgesia en una Unidad de Dolor Agudo postoperatorio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analgesic quality in a postoperative pain service: continuous assessment with the cumulative sum (cusum) method].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
