<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17347938</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bustillo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Servera, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The most common method used to diagnose attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is based on the Diagnostic and statistic manual of mental disorders, 4th edition (DSM-IV) criteria. Nevertheless, it is more likely that the categorical system postulated by DSM-IV is not the most appropriate method as it does not consider the possible differences between the diagnostic capacity of the 18 proposed criteria. AIM. To analyze the predictive power of each DSM-IV diagnostic symptoms/criteria for ADHD using DuPaul's ADHD Parent and Teacher Rating Scales. PATIENTS AND METHODS In a prospective, poblational study to evaluate the prevalence of ADHD the positive predictive power of each item was analyzed for each subtype and informant. A kappa index was applied for positive predictive power to correct the number of accurate predictions based on chance factors, and a ranking of items was established to determinate which ones offered the highest predictive power, comparing parent and teacher ratings. RESULTS The results suggest that not all DSM-IV criteria are equal with regard to their ability to predict ADHD. The predictive power varies as a function of the informant. Parent and teachers agreed more on hyperactivity and impulsivity items, and showed more significant differences with regard to the American sample. CONCLUSIONS The approach that aggregates any combination of items will not be the more effective strategy for ruling in a diagnosis of ADHD. To improve the clinical value of these scales making item combinations is recommended, the ones that will have attached a higher clinical weight for ruling in a diagnosis of ADHD.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Mar 02 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor predictivo de los criterios del DSM-IV en el diagnóstico del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad y sus diferencias culturales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The predictive value of DSM-IV criteria in the diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and its cultural differences].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
