<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17340788</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Balcells Ramírez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez Sampedro, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cañadas Palazón, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Lucas García, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Ibáñez, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Accidents are a frequent cause of death in children older than 1 year. The most frequent causes of death by accident are traffic accidents, drowning, intentional injuries, burns, and falls. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation is one component of the set of actions needed to obtain initial stabilization of a child with serious trauma. In the first few minutes after the accident, cardiorespiratory arrest can occur due to airway obstruction or inadequate ventilation, massive blood loss or severe brain damage; cardiorespiratory arrest in this setting has a dismal outcome. When arrest occurs hours after trauma, it is usually caused by hypoxia, hypovolemia, hypothermia, intracranial hypertension, or electrolyte disturbances. The first response to trauma should include three objectives: to protect (scenario assessment and implementation of safety measures), to alert (activation of the emergency medical system) and to help (initial trauma care). Initial trauma care includes primary and secondary surveys. The primary survey involves several consecutive steps: A. airway and cervical spine stabilization, B. breathing, C. circulation and hemorrhage control, D. neurological dysfunction, and E. exposure. The secondary survey consists of assessment of the victim by means of anamnesis, sequential physical examination (from head to limbs) and complementary investigations. During emergency trauma care, specific procedures such as extrication and mobilization maneuvers, cervical spine control by means of bimanual immobilization, and cervical collar placement or helmet removal. If a cardiorespiratory arrest occurs during initial trauma care, resuscitation maneuvers must be immediately started with the specific adaptations indicated in children with trauma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asistencia inicial al traumatismo pediátrico y reanimación cardiopulmonar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Initial pediatric trauma care and cardiopulmonary resuscitation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
