<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17356716</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peris Diaz, Lola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Szerman Bolotner, Néstor</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Different alcoholism subtypes from Jellinek's modified typology reviewed by Babor of gamma and delta alcoholics and former one group (compulsive alcoholics) relationships with serotonergic function are the main purpose of this work, presenting in that sense our study with sertraline at obsessive compulsive disorder treatment doses. METHOD Open label multicenter six month study with 91 alcohol dependent patients (53% gamma, 20% delta, 27% mixed) treated with sertraline 200 mg to evaluate its effectiveness and tolerance in both subgroups, focusing specially on compulsive alcoholics. Obsessive Compulsive Drinking Scale (OCDS), Barratt Impulsivity Scale (BIS), Craving Evaluation and Clinical Global Impression of Severity (CGI S). CONCLUSIONS Gamma patients showed a slight tendency to recovery than delta, without statistical significance. These results could reflect a statistical bias, as few delta patients were included. According to neurobiological hypotheses, future studies should try to evaluate these types of alcoholism. Improvement (CGI-I) were the measures employed. RESULTS CGI S and CGI I showed a statistically significant improvement. Seventy six per cent of patients were responders. No statistically significant differences were observed between gamma and delta groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alcohólicos compulsivos y función serotoninérgica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Compulsive alcoholics and serotoninergic function].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
