<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17352107</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Del Cañizo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina Hernando, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cerdá Berrocal, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Ruiz, R M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Calvarro, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parente Hernando, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Paris, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez Estévez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Angulo Madero, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cloacal exstrophy is a complex multisistemic anomaly that involves gastrointestinal and genitourinary issues. The aim of our paper is to report our experience in dealing with genital reconstruction and faecal and urinary continence in patients with female cloacal anomalies. We reviewed the clinical records from the three patients we have achieved a final reconstruction. We recorded the surgical management and both functional and anatomic results. The three of them required a bladder neck closure associated with a continent stoma, they are dry with intermittent catheterization and free of upper urinary complications. Genital reconstruction required a unique plan for each one, according to their anatomy and their cosmetic desires. One of the patients reported satisfactory sexual intercourse. Management of patients with cloacal exstrophy has major concerns about urinary and fecal continence and about genital reconstruction and function. Knowing the long-term results may help to develop management strategies and improve counselling for patients who have under-gone reconstruction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia terapéutica en la extrofia de cloaca femenina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Therapeutic strategy in cloacal exstrophy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
