<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17388643</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Fontgivell, Joan Francesc</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mayayo Artal, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infectious diseases caused by fungal pathogens have increased in the past 10 years. More than 300 pathogenic fungal species have been incriminated as the etiologic agents. We carried out a retrospective study (1994-2004) to evaluate the prevalence of mycoses at the University Hospital Joan XXIII (330 beds). This report found 0.24% of the studied cases (78,310 biopsies and 753 autopsies) were diagnosed as fungal infections (0.21% of the total studied biopsy and 4.25% of the whole autopsies). Skin and mucose were involved in 66% of cases, followed by other less affected anatomical areas. 61% of studied cases were caused by Candida spp (the most frequent in our environment), followed by Aspergillus spp (10%) and the Zygomycetes (5%). The most important underlying illness was obstructive chronic pulmonary disease followed by diabetes and AIDS. The incidence of mycoses increased with the patient's age, especially those patients in their 80s. Antifungal management improved the clinical outcome of the patient but predisposing factors are crucial for diagnosis. Systemic mycoses have poor prognosis with 91% of fatal outcome. Thus, it is important to perform a rapid diagnosis of the fungal infections a diagnostic area in which pathology could play a major role.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la patología fúngica en biopsias y autopsias realizadas en el Hospital Universitario Joan XXIII de Tarragona.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of fungal infections detected from biopsies and autopsies in the past 11 years at the University Hospital Joan XXIII in Tarragona, Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
