<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17425885</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Páez, Darío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salgado, Jesús F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes Hirsch's h index as a measure of researchers' scientific productivity and quality, examining its convergent validity with other productivity and quality measures (total citations, maximum citation, sexennials, years since earning Ph.D., and years as a full professor). It shows the distribution of the index among Spanish Social Psychology professors, and a comparison is made among the ten professors with highest h index of the six knowledge areas into which academic Psychology is divided in Spain. The results show that the index largely correlates with the citations but only very modestly with the number of sexennial investigations. The distributions by areas show that Psychobiology and Basic Psychology, as a whole, have a higher h index than the other areas, with Social Psychology in fourth place. Lastly, we discuss the implications of these results and we offer some recommendations for using the index in academic and research decision making.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La productividad científica y el índice h de Hirchs de la psicología social española: convergencia entre indicadores de productividad y comparación con otras áreas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Scientific productivity and Hirsch's h index of Spanish social psychology: convergence between productivity indexes and comparison with other areas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Psicothema</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
