<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17439693</identifier>
<setSpec>1020-4989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>San Martín, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brathwaite-Dick, Olivia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the last 22 years, the Region of the Americas has seen an upward trend in dengue incidence, with epidemics peaking ever higher and recurring every 3-5 years, almost regularly. A major factor in the spread of the disease has been the diminished capacity of national programs to respond with dengue prevention and control. This paper evaluates the Integrated Strategy for Dengue Prevention and Control-approved by the 44th Directing Council of the Pan American Health Organization in September 2003- and its preliminary results. The Integrated Strategy for Dengue is a management model designed to strengthen national programs, with a focus on reducing morbidity, mortality, and the societal and economic burdens produced by outbreaks and epidemics. Currently, 11 of the countries in the Region have developed a plan for or implemented a national strategy. In addition, a sub-Regional plan has been developed for Central America and the Dominican Republic. The Integrated Strategy for Dengue is expected to produce a qualitative leap forward in prevention and control through stronger partnerships among the State, its various ministries, and governing bodies, at all levels; private companies; and the range of community and civil groups. Once implemented, this strategy will reduce risk factors for dengue transmission, establish an integrated epidemiological surveillance system, decrease Aedes aegypti mosquito populations, prepare laboratories to better detect and identify the virus, optimize diagnosis and treatment, and, as a result, decrease the frequency, magnitude, and severity of dengue outbreaks and epidemics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Estrategia de Gestión Integrada para la Prevención y el Control del Dengue en la Región de las Américas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Integrated strategy for dengue prevention and control in the Region of the Americas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
