<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17439313</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sberna, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rousseau, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calle, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Travaglianti, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the use of linezolid in vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus infections in a paediatric hospital. METHOD Retrospective, observational study of hospitalised patients at the "Juan P. Garrahan" paediatric hospital receiving linezolid for the treatment of vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus, during the period between January 2002 and July 2004. RESULTS During 18 months, linezolid was prescribed 17 times for a total of 15 seriously ill patients. The median age was 7 years old (range: 1 month-15 years) and the median length of the treatment was 15 days, with an average hospital stay of 74 days. Infection with vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus was microbiologically documented in 11 (73.3%) patients; they all responded to treatment with linezolid with the exception of two, who died while receiving treatment. The most frequently reported adverse reactions were of a haematological nature (55.5%). CONCLUSIONS Linezolid was effective and moderately well tolerated for the treatment of vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus in children with life-threatening infections.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de infecciones por Enterococcus resistente a vancomicina con linezolid en un hospital pediátrico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus with linezolid in paediatric hospitals].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
