<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17453070</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Iribarren B, Osvaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez C, Cristian</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández V, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez C, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dorn H, Lilian</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrada M, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case-control study for evaluation of cost and outcome of nosocomial surgical site infection in primary hip arthroplasty during a period of 5 years. Mean hospitalization time in the orthopedic service was 54 days for cases, and 13 days for control (p&lt;0.05). Mean hospitalization time in Intensive Care Unit (ICU) was 1.1 days for cases. There were 0.83 post primary surgery interventions in cases, and a mean of 2.08 bacteriological cultures in each case. Controls didn't have hospitalizations in the ICU surgical reinterventions nor cultures necessary. The mean cost of infected patients was US $: 6,174.8. Mean cost in controls was US $: 2,354.7. The excess of cost due to infections was US $: 2,354.7 on the average. Outcomes in cases were: normal function 30.8%; moderate or serious sequelae 46.2%; death rate 15, 4%. The measured parameters contributed to raise case costs, and they caused an unsatisfactory outcome for two third of the patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costo y desenlace de la infección de artroplastía de cadera. Estudio de caso y control.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cost and outcome of hip's arthroplasty nosocomial infection. Case and control study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
