<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17470320</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-7411</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pedroza-Meléndez, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Justo-Janeiro, Jaime M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prado, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-de Lara, Luis G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Theurel-Vincent, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Simulators are effective devices for the development of certain skills needed in laparoscopic surgery. Bench models with laparoscopy equipment, virtual reality and mirror boxes have been used; however, they have limitations such as the need for laparoscopy equipment, high cost or a considerable mismatch with reality. METHODS We undertook this study to test a simulator as a training device that allows the acquisition of eye-hand coordination and two-dimensional spatial orientation without the need of laparoscopic equipment. The simulator consists of a box with an internal light and a color video CCD connected to a television set. Quality of vision, illumination and adequacy as training equipment was assessed by experienced laparoscopic surgeons. Thereafter, 12 general surgeons without experience in laparoscopic surgery and 18 surgery trainees performed seven different drills after a short course on basic skills and knot-tying laparoscopic techniques. The time to completion of each task was recorded at the beginning and after 10 practices of 30-min each. RESULTS Ten experienced surgeons qualified with the simulator with a mean of 42 points (40-44 from a 44 total). There were significant reductions in the final times of all participants. Paired t-test was significant in all the measurements. The mean time decreased 31.8% (from 1108 +/- 96 to 755 +/- 107 sec) with a 95% confidence interval of 15.1-48.5%. CONCLUSIONS The simulator tested in this study helps to develop laparoscopic surgical skills economically and without the need for laparoscopic equipment. This laparoscopy training equipment is novel and original in its design.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un nuevo simulador de laparoscopia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A new laparoscopic simulator].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
