<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17489496</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Royo, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Vernet, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Broto, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabañas, M J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Esophageal stenosis, due to its important implications on the patients' quality of life, poses a serious problem, often difficult to resolve, that requires therapeutical solutions that could irreversibly affect vital conditions and quality of life of those affected. For this reason our group has tried over the last thirty years to employ conservative solutions in the damaged aesophagus, showing that a complete cure is possible in most cases although the way to achieve this can be dramatically long. MATERIAL AND METHODS We present our experience employing topical Mitomicyn C over the last year and a half in eight patients, six of them affected with caustic stenosis and two with secuelae of esophageal atresia, highlighting the three cases that received at least five applications of the product. We describe the method employed that consists in the spraying of the correct dose using a flexible fibroscope on the dilated area, loading the dose in the container of the cleaning water of the fibroscope, employing a system that permits only to apply the exact quantity necessary of the product. The application time is five minutes and the dose is 0.4 mg/ml applying 5ml or 10 ml according to the patient's weight ( under 12 kg = 2.5 ml and over 25 kg=5 ml). Upon completion of the application, a washing of the product is performed using the same fibroscope. RESULTS From the eight cases in which it was applied, we analysed the three that received at least five doses. These were two boys of seven and eight years and a 25 year-old woman. In the children the dilatations interval has passed from 4-5 weeks to 8-11 respectively. The woman has passed from 12 to15 weeks. The children have been in the dilatation program more than 3 years and the woman more than 18. CONCLUSIONS Although the time period that we have been applying Mitomicyn C is still short, the symptom-free interval after dilatations is proving to be highly promising. This fact is highlighted in those patients included in the dilatation program recently. We have not seen any adverse side effect from the application of the product.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empleo de la mitomicina C en las estenosis esofágicas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of mitomycin C in esophageal stenosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
