<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17491612</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Brugos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Astrain, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Nievas, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arbeloa, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monreal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otero, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In January 2005 the Government of Navarre approved the "Care Program for Persons with Severe Mental Disorder" (PA-TMG). This article is intended to ascertain the opinion of experts regarding the PA-TMG. To identify the elements of agreement in the evaluation of positive aspects and aspects that can be improved. To make recommendations on the basis of their opinions. METHODS A Delphi study was designed with 34 experts in health or social care of mentally ill persons. By means of repeated questionnaires, ideas that achieved a consensus of (3)90% were identified and a level of priority was assigned. The percentages of agreement and descriptive statistics of priority were presented, and the recommendations of analysis of the areas of consensus were drawn up. RESULTS Out of the 34 participating experts, 25 (71.4%) completed the study: 1 sociologist, 5 social workers, 3 psychiatrists, 5 psychologists, one representative of the families, 3 occupational therapists, 1 technician in social integration and 6 family doctors. Sixty-four percent evaluated the Plan positively, and 72% were of the opinion that it was drawn up without sufficient professional participation. All thought that it could be improved by widening the participation of experts. CONCLUSIONS The principal ideas on which there was consensus were: socio-health care must be guaranteed by the public administration; good systems of information and evaluation must be established; the Plan must have its own budget; professional follow-up of the patient by the different mechanisms must be guaranteed; a lot of the decision making must be decentralised; access to social benefits for these patients must be universalised.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jan-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del programa social de atención a personas con trastorno mental grave: un estudio Delphi.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the social care program for persons with severe mental disorders: a Delphi study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
