<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17546221</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mayorga-Fayad, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barón, Alexandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Diana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lafaurie, Gloria I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aya, María del Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Periodontitis-associated microbiotas differ in regions around the world and vary with a variety of factors. This suggests that each country must establish its own dental microbiobiotic profile in order to formulate adequate prevention measures and more specific treatments. OBJECTIVE The prevalence and proportions of the following microorganisms were investigated: Porphyromonas gingivalis, Tannerella forsythia, Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans, Prevotella intermedia/Prevotella nigrescens, Eikenella corrodens, Campylobacter rectus, Micromonas micros, Fusobacterium spp, Dialister pneumosintes and enteric rods. The patients selected had been diagnosed with chronic periodontitis and aggressive periodontitis from clinical populations in Bogotá, Colombia. The variables of age, gender and socioeconomic level were included in the comparisons. MATERIALS AND METHODS 183 patients were classified in two groups, chronic periodontitis (n=84) and aggressive periodontitis (n=59); 40 healthy subjects were selected for comparison. A pooled subgingival plaque sample was obtained from the 6 deepest periodontal pockets in every patient and processed by culture for the isolation and identification of bacteria. RESULTS In chronic periodontitis and aggressive periodontitis, P. gingivalis, T. forsythia, P. intermedia/P. nigrescens, C. rectus, Fusobacterium spp and E. corrodens showed high and similar prevalence, whereas M. micros, A. actinomycetemcomitans, D. pneumosintes and enteric rods (commonly from the tribe Klebsielleae) showed less and similar prevalence. In the healthy group, P. intermedia/P. nigrescens, C. rectus and Fusobacterium spp showed high frequency whereas M. micros and E. corrodens showed moderate frequency. CONCLUSIONS Porphyromonas gingivalis, T. forsythia, P. intermedia/P. nigrescens, C. rectus, Fusobacterium spp. and E. corrodens are important constituents of the microbiologic profile of the periodontitis in Colombian populations. Porphyromonas gingivalis was found more frequently than A. actinomycetemcomitans in aggressive periodontitis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microflora subgingival en periodontitis crónica y agresiva en Bogotá, Colombia: un acercamiento epidemiológico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Subgingival microbiota in chronic and aggressive periodontitis in Bogotá, Colombia: an epidemiological approach].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
