<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17643135</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sarasola, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Taragano, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dillon, Carol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iturry, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano, Cecilia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Allegri, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Raczkowski, Amalia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Several studies refer to the relationship between schizophrenia and cognitive dysfunctions. The most frequent disturbances accepted are the deficits in the executive, memory and verbal tests. However, there are few comparative data about the cognitive functioning of the different subtypes of schizophrenia. OBJECTIVE Analyze and compare the neuropsychological disturbances present in patients with paranoid and residual schizophrenia. MATERIALS AND METHOD Eleven patients with paranoid schizophrenia, eleven patients with residual schizophrenia (DSM-IV criteria), and thirty one normal subjects matched by age, educational level, and general cognitive level (Mini Mental State Examination (Folstein, 1975), were assessed with a semistructured psychiatric examination and an extensive neuropsychological battery. RESULTS Significant differences were found in memory, language, and executive functions when schizophrenics were compared with normal subjects. Differences in similarities were found between paranoid and residual schizophrenics. Residual schizophrenics had more disturbances in neuropsychological tests in comparison with paranoid schizophrenics. CONCLUSION Schizophrenics demonstrated disturbances in memory, language, executive functions and attention. Residual schizophrenics had more impairment in neuropsychological tests than paranoid schizophrenics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de los rendimientos cognitivos en pacientes esquizofrénicos (forma paranoide vs residual).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cognitive performance in schizophrenia (paranoid vs residual subtype)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
