<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17642048</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lezaun, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Posada-De la Paz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quinones, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramalle-Gomara, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gonzalez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perucha, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Huntington's disease (HD) is an autosomic dominant neurodegenerative disease characterized by neuromuscular, cognitive and psychiatric symptoms. AIM To analyze the mortality trend for HD from 1981-2004 in Spain. PATIENTS AND METHODS Both crude and specific rates adjusted to the European population were used to show the evolution of mortality. Rates are showed by age and gender per million of inhabitants. Joinpoint regression model was used to analyze mortality trends. RESULTS 866 deaths under HD codes were recorded in Spain during the study period (452 males and 414 females). Adjusted rates ranged from 0.64 in 1981 to 1.65 in 2004 in males and from 0.40 in 1981 to 1.16 in 2004 in females. The trend of the mortality rates in both genders followed a slight and steady increase during the whole period and dramatic changes were not detected. The average yearly percentage of this increase was 3.76% in males and 3.67% in females. CONCLUSIONS The study has showed a yearly age adjusted mortality rates increase close to 4%. No differences have been seen between males and females. The follow up of this trend should be monitored to test if it stabilizes or it rises.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jul 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad por la enfermedad de Huntington en Espana en el periodo 1981-2004.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Huntington's disease mortality in Spain in the period 1981-2004].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
