<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1764195</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Híjar-Medina, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tapia-Yáñez, J R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study on damages to a child's good health caused by injuries (accidents and violence), has been mainly directed towards the analysis of mortality. In reference to morbidity, very few studies have been carried out in our country. One of the primordial objectives of these studies was to explore morbidity through the demand of hospital emergency services. The study was designed using a questionnaire applied to patients during the months of September-October of 1988 while admitted in 12 pediatric hospital emergency wards. The analysis was done using a representative sample per hospital, applying the finite population formula, with a Zc = 90% and a interval of 0.05. The total number of cases studied was 3,294. The most important variables studied were: type of demand, traumatic lesion, place of occurrence, external cause, age groups, sex, day and shift of the demand, hospitalization and number of days in the ward. The results give an overall view of this health problem concerning morbidity, besides offering a basis for future investigations dealing with the identification of risk factors or the application of concrete interventions for their prevention.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la demanda por lesiones traumáticas a servicios de urgencia de 12 hospitales pediátricos de la ciudad de México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[An analysis in traumatic lesions of the demand for emergency services at 12 pediatric hospitals of the city of Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
