<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17655401</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lerís, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boncompte, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Algueró, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Noguera, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this article is to review the phase II and phase III clinical trials with the new pharmaceutical gel form of flutrimazole. The aim of the phase II study was to determine the efficacy and tolerance of flutrimazole 1%, 2% and 4% gel when compared to placebo in the treatment of 80 patients with dandruff or seborrheic dermatitis at a dose of three applications per week during one month. Flutrimazole 1% gel had a similar efficacy compared to the other studied concentrations and a superior efficacy when compared to placebo (p &lt; 0.05). All treatments studied had an excellent tolerance. In the phase III study, the efficacy and tolerance of flutrimazole 1% gel was compared to ketoconazole 2% gel in 192 patients with dandruff or seborrheic dermatitis. Flutrimazole gel had a similar efficacy to ketoconazole gel at a dose of three applications per week for 28 days. Both products were well tolerated and no adverse effects were recorded.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de la eficacia clínica del flutrimazol gel en el tratamiento de la pitiriasis capitis y/o dermatitis seborreica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Review of the clinical efficacy of flutrimazole gel in the treatment of dandruff and/or seborrheic dermatitis.].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
