<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17657327</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rojas, Graciela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Araya, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pilowsky, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fritsch, Rosemarie</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montt, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solís, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Depression is a public health problem, due to its high prevalence and its associated disability. AIM To compare a pharmacological intervention for depression controlled by phone from a central level (TM) and the usual treatment (TH) in a randomized clinical trial. MATERIAL AND METHODS Three hundred and forty five women, aged 22 to 59 years were studied. They were randomly assigned to receive the usual therapy or a pharmacological intervention with periodical telephone contacts with medical collaboration personnel, to reinforce compliance with treatment and educate about the disease. Women were blindly evaluated at 3 and 6 months with the Hamilton depression rating score (HDRS) and the SF-36 to assess depressive symptoms and quality of life, respectively. RESULTS In both evaluations, improvement was significantly greater in the TM group than the TH group. At 3 months, improvement was higher in the TM group in the subscales of physical function, pain, general health, energy, emotional role, mental health and standardized physical and psychic scales of SF-36. At 6 months, this significant difference in favour of TM was maintained for energy, mental health and the standardized psychic scale. CONCLUSIONS A telephone reinforcement improves the outcomes of treatments for depression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un ensayo clínico aleatorizado de farmacoterapia con monitorización telefónica para mejorar el tratamiento de la depresión en la atención primaria en Santiago, Chile.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A randomized trial of pharmacotherapy with telephone monitoring to improve treatment of depression in primary care in Santiago, Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
