<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17661269</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carvajal-Díaz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cánovas-Vergé, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND AIMS Until now treatment of acute cerebral infarction with tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) has been applied to a limited extent in large medical centres with acute stroke units. The aim of this study is to determine the safety and effectiveness of this treatment in a centre with no previous experience following a multidisciplinary model. PATIENTS AND METHODS We conducted a prospective, observation-based study involving patients who were treated with intravenous rt-PA within 3 hours of suffering an acute ischaemic stroke between January 2004 and December 2006. Basal variables, haemorrhagic complications, response to treatment and functional progress were evaluated using the modified Rankin Scale (mRS) at 3 months. Treatment and control were applied following a multidisciplinary protocol implemented by the Intensive Medicine and Neurology services. RESULTS In all, 46 patients were treated, their mean age being 67 +/- 12 years (63% males). NIH pre-treatment: 13.6 +/- 4.7; median: 13.5; range: 5-22. Time elapsed between the onset of symptoms and arrival at the hospital was 53 +/- 27 min, and door-to-needle time was 69 +/- 27 min. At 24 hours, 48% of patients had improved their scores on the NIH scale &gt; 4 points. A total of 10 haemorrhagic transformations (21.7%) were observed, none of which were symptomatic. At three months, 54.3% of patients were functionally independent (mRS: 0-2). Mortality rate at 90 days was 13.1%. CONCLUSIONS Administration of rt-PA to patients with acute ischaemic stroke in health care practice following a multidisciplinary protocol is safe and has a neurological progression that is comparable to clinical trials and studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Aug 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento fibrinolítico con activador del plasminógeno tisular. Resultados en la práctica clínica con un modelo de actuación multidisciplinario.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fibrinolytic treatment with tissue plasminogen activator. Outcomes in clinical practice with a multidisciplinary model of intervention].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
