<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17662188</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Antón Hernández, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uña Gorospe, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos Font, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Fernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albalá González, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Sequera Rahola, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Gimeno, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas Negro, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Allende Riera, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After a 2-year-old male with left impairment underwent surgery for a left vesicoureteral stenosis, his renal function was followed up by means of dynamic renal scintigraphy with 99mTc-DTPA. Incidental radiotracer accumulation was observed in left hemiabdomen tracing the descending and sigmoid colon. A vesico-colonic fistula was suspected. However, ultrasonography and cystography studies showed no presence of a vesico-enteric fistula. Because the patient persisted without symptoms, an expectant approach was adopted. One year later, he began to suffer watery diarrhoea episodes. 99mTc-DTPA renography was again performed to re-evaluated renal function and explore presence of urinary-enteric fistula. Diuretic renography demonstrated the presence of a vesical leak to sigmoid gut, which was confirmed by recovery of fecal matter from the patient. Both isotopic renograms evidenced the presence of uretero-sigmoid fistula, an uncommon postsurgical that was not detected by cystography, ultrasonography or RMN. The patient subsequently underwent surgery for fistula repair.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del renograma diurético en la detección de una fístula enteroureteral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Utility of diuretic renography in the detection of an enteroureteral fistula].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
