<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17694637</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domínguez Romero, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sillero Quintana, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Soidán, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordente Martínez, Carlos Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND It is throughout childhood and adolescence that many behavior patterns which are going to have a powerful influence on health during adult life are established. This study is aimed at analysing the influence physical activity has on the health of adolescents and at determining the relationship thereof with blood pressure (BP) and body composition. METHODS The research was conducted from November 2002 to February 2003, using the Modifiable Physical Activity Questionnaire for Adolescents, which measures the degree of physical activity. The anthropometric variables and blood pressure were also measured for the sample comprised of 554 adolescents within the 12-18 age range from 35 schools in Madrid. RESULTS A total of 13.2% of the males and 36.4% of the females were found to be inactive. The averages for the systolic/diastolic BP were 125.6/71.3 mmHg in the males and 118/69.4 mmHg in the females, but physical activity was found to have an influence solely on the diastolic BP for the males. A total of 48.27% of the females showed a tendency toward being overweight, as compared to 13.53% of the males. In the case of the females, a relationship was found to exist between body fat and degree of physical activity. CONCLUSIONS The degree of physical activity shows itself to be a factor related to the health of adolescents, although taking on a different focus in each gender. Among the males, it has a significant bearing on the diastolic BP, whilst among the females, its influence is seen in the degree of body fat.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación del nivel de actividad física, presión arterial y adiposidad corporal en adolescentes Madrileños.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Relationship of the degree of physical activity, blood pressure and body fat among teenagers in Madrid].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
