<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17692228</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Clèries Costa, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Vicente, Pau</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarrado Soldevila, Joan Josep</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To identify professionals' view of the problem-solving capacity of primary care in the health system. DESIGN Interpretative study, based on the Grounded Theory method and the focus-group technique. SETTING Eight primary care centres. PARTICIPANTS In all, 198 professionals: 86 physicians, 69 nurse and 43 who were not health professionals. INTERVENTIONS Data were obtained by: open questions in the focus groups, recording and transcription of the contributions; division of the text into autonomous sense units; sense units grouped by their common characteristics; inductive definition of each category; relationship between categories and triangulation of inter-team data. RESULTS The problem-solving capacity of professionals should be characterized by: care for the bio-psycho-social demands and needs of the population; the integration of the following dimensions of professional competence: communication and teamwork; the promotion of prevention and public education. However, health-care daily practice prioritised quantitative parameters linked to reactive actions that were distant from the singularity of patients' pathologies. CONCLUSIONS The desired problem-solving capacity of primary health care is threatened by excessive quantitative measurement, by shortcomings in human resources and facilities, and by the well-known lack of time in health-care delivery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La atención primaria y el poder resolutivo del sistema de salud: un estudio desde los profesionales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Primary care and the power of the health system to solve problems: a study from the professionals' view-point].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
