<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1772047</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rioja Sanz, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urruchi Fernández, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cavero Rebollo, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Vela, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Enguita, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tello Royloa, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Report of our experience of complications arisen from treatment of urinary lithiasis with extracorporeal shock-wave lithotripsy, using a Dornier HM3 lithotripter in 218 elderly patients (over 65 years). No complications arose during lithotripsy in 160 patients (73.39%). Most frequent complications (when they happened) were skin disorders, which occurred in 33 patients (15.13%). One hundred and thirty-six (62.38%) patients had no post-lithotripsy non-obstructive urological complications, but when these occurred, renal colic, evident in 52 patients (23.85%), was the most frequent one. During the post-lithotripsy period, 88.53% patients (193) had no obstructive urological complications. When they emerged, they usually developed asymptomatically (13 patients, 5.95%). With regard to the approach used to treat the obstructive cases, the most common one was medical, representing 56%. Surgery was used only in 2 occasions. A total of 175 patients (80.27%) presented no post-lithotripsy complication, fever of up to + 38 degrees C being the most prevalent condition (9.65%).</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones per y post-litotricia extracorpórea en los pacientes de edad avanzada.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Complications during and after extracorporeal lithotripsy in elderly patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
