<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17728921</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zepeda F, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jofré M, Leonor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz A, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luchsinger F, Vivian</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas C, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human metapneumovirus (hMPV), a recently described pathogen of lower respiratory tract infections (LRTI), has been detected in 5,4% of Chilean infants hospitalized for LRTI whom are negative for adenovirus, respiratory syncytial virus, influenza and parainfluenza viruses. hMPV may cause bronchiolitis or pneumonia in hospitalized patients, and ocassionally require admission to intensive care units and mechanical ventilation. The infection has been associated with apnea, especially in preterm infants. Nosocomial dissemination has also been described. We present the case of a one-month-of age premature infant with apnea, and infection caused by hMPV of probable nosocomial aquisition. Clinical features of hMPV infection are reviewed and its association with apnea and nosocomial transmission is discussed. hMPV should be included in the routine diagnosis of respiratory viruses in infants with apnea and should be considered among the respiratory pathogens associated with nosocomial transmission.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apnea como forma de presentación de una infección por metapneumovirus humano.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Apnea as a presenting symptom in human metapneumovirus infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
