<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17896557</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez, L J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meattini, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Detti, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Biti, G P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Livi, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To report toxicity and local control in patients with localized prostate cancer, treated with high dose radiotherapy. MATERIALS AND METHODS The records of 100 consecutive patients with clinically localized prostate cancer treated between june 2003 and may 2006 were reviewed. They received 80 Gy to the target volume with a biphasic technique (3DCRT + IMRT). The median pretreatment PSA was 9. The median follow-up time was 12 months. RESULTS Eighteen (18%) developed acute Grade 2 rectal toxicity, and no patient experienced acute grade 3 or higher rectal symptoms. Forty-four (44%) developed acute Grade 2 urinary symptoms while 34% of the patients experienced no GU symptoms (Grade 0) during treatment. Three patients (3%) developed late rectal toxicity grade 2 and eight patients (8%) experienced late urinary toxicity grade 2; any patients experienced more severe symptoms. We recorded biochemical relapse in two patients, both had poor prognostic factors at initial diagnosis of prostate cancer. CONCLUSIONS The data demonstrate the feasibility and safety of high dose radiotherapy for patients with localized prostate cancer and provide a proof that this method allow safe dose escalation with low severe toxicities to the normal tissues.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cancer de próstata órgano-confinado: tratamiento con altas dosis de radioterapia (radioterapia de intensidad modulada).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Organ-confined prostate cancer: treatment with high doses of radioterapy (intensity modulated radiotherapy)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
