<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17919414</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Repetto, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Orlando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borzone, Gisella</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lisboa, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leiva, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pinochet, Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The role of dynamic hyperinflation in triggering dyspnea and limiting exercise capacity in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease has been recognized in recent years. The degree of dynamic hyperinflation can be assessed by measuring reduction in inspiratory capacity (IC). The aim of this study was to establish reference values for IC in healthy individuals of both sexes between the ages of 50 and 87 years, as such data are scarce in the literature. SUBJECTS AND METHODS We studied 155 healthy volunteers (93 women) with normal spirometry. None had a prior history of respiratory, cardiovascular, or systemic diseases that might alter lung function. All were never-smokers. IC was measured during a normal, unforced inspiration to total lung capacity starting from functional residual capacity. The highest value of 6 satisfactory maneuvers was recorded. Sex, height, age, and weight were included in the regression equations. One thousand bootstrap samples for each sex were also analyzed. RESULTS For each sex, we found that a model including age, height, and weight produced IC prediction equations with a coefficient of determination (r2) of 0.414 for women and 0.447 for men. The mean (SD) intrasubject coefficient of variation was 4.3% (2%) for IC measured during a single session and 5.1% (0.4%) for measurements from 5 weekly sessions. CONCLUSIONS Our results provide reference equations for IC that are valid for a healthy population over 50 years of age. Predicted values were similar to those recently obtained in an Italian population aged between 65 and 85 years.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia de la capacidad inspiratoria en sujetos sanos no fumadores mayores de 50 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reference values for inspiratory capacity in healthy nonsmokers over age 50 years].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
