<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17915151</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero-Vecchione, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Strauss, Miriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Antequera, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosa, Francisco J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vásquez, José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES To investigate the hemodynamic sympathetic response evoked by NaCI microinjection into the third ventricle anteroventral brain area (AV3V) in rats long-term fed with high fructose diet. METHODS Twelve male rats received 60% fructose enriched diet for 6 months. Control rats (n=12) received regular diet. RESULTS Fructose diet increased (P&lt; .01) body weight; plasma glucose, triglycerides; cholesterol, insulin; systolic (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP). Basal heart rate (HR) did not change. AV3V microinjection of 2 microL of hypertonic 1.5 M NaCI in fructose fed rats increased SBP 44.64(3.6) mm Hg, DBP 19.9(2.4) mm Hg and HR 66.2(8.4) beats/min over basal values (P&lt; .01). In control rats, smaller responses were observed, SBP increased 28.33(3.10) mm Hg, DBP 13.0(1.9) mm Hg and HR 23.0(5.0) beats/min over basal values (P&lt; .01). CONCLUSIONS Long-term fructose diet in rats induces cardiovascular hyperactivity of AV3V neurons to sodium chloride, and is associated to hypertension and insulin-resistance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuestas cardiovasculares al NaCI hipertónico inyectado en la región anteroventral del tercer ventrículo de ratas con hipertensión e insulinorresistencia inducidas por fructosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiovascular responses to hypertonic NaCI injection into the anteroventral third ventricle region in rats with fructose-induced hypertension and insulin resistance].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
