<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17939908</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gayoso, Manuel J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Heras, Félix</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matilla, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Yuste, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez Prada, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Crespo, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Local cytokine production is a pathogenic factor in ischemia-reperfusion injury in early graft dysfunction. This study analyzed interleukin 8 (IL-8) messenger RNA (mRNA) expression in lung tissue and the association between IL-8 mRNA levels and interstitial lung changes in an experimental model of warm lung ischemia-reperfusion. MATERIAL AND METHODS We studied 16 New Zealand rabbits divided into 3 groups: control, ischemia (tissue taken from right lower lobe after 1, 2, or 3 hours of ischemia), and reperfusion (tissue taken from right upper and middle lobes after 1 hour of ischemia and 1, 2, or 3 hours of reperfusion). Expression of IL-8 mRNA was determined by reverse transcription and polymerase chain reaction. Interstitial infiltration by polymorphonuclear neutrophils was determined. The Mann-Whitney U-test was used for statistical comparisons, with P&lt; .05 considered to indicate a significant result. RESULTS During ischemia, IL-8 mRNA levels were elevated at the end of hour 1 (P=.009) with respect to the control group, but not thereafter. Interstitial changes were minimal. IL-8 mRNA levels during reperfusion were similar to those observed during ischemia, with a slight increase at the end of hour 2. There were no significant differences between hours 1, 2, and 3. Polymorphonuclear neutrophil recruitment occurred at the beginning of reperfusion (P=.014), but no significant differences were observed at hours 2 or 3. Progressive thickening of alveolar septa and edema was documented. CONCLUSIONS Changes in IL-8 mRNA expression during ischemia precede interstitial infiltration by polymorphonuclear neutrophils during reperfusion, suggesting that the 2 processes are related. Quantification of IL-8 mRNA expression could facilitate early diagnosis of graft dysfunction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la expresión de interleucina-8 en el tejido pulmonar durante la isquemia-reperfusión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Interleukin-8 expression in lung tissue during ischemia-reperfusion].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
