<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17934543</identifier>
<setSpec>1022-5129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Frisancho Velarde, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado Palache, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva Balarezo, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Provide the initial endoscopic experience in the placing of the Montgomery salivary bypass tube (MSBT). PATIENTS AND METHODS Descriptive, retrospective study in 7 patients in the Digestive System Unit of EsSALUD Hospital Edgardo Rebagliati Martins in Lima-Peru from November 2003 to January 2006. RESULTS The average age of the patients was 34.68 years (2 years, 8 months - 76 years); 85.1% were male, 71.4% required hospitalization in the Intensive Care Unit. In 5 patients, the MSBT indications were some kind of fistula in the esophagus, and stenosis in 2 patients, one crichopharyngeal and the other gastric transposition with anastomosis in the cervical esophagus. The endoscopic help for the placing of the MSBT was required in 81.8% and for withdrawal in 77.7%. In the six (6) adult patients, sedation, the endoscopic procedure and the placing of the MSBT were well-tolerated. The average time that the MSBT was in place was 70.5 days. In two (2) patients (28.6%), there were complications associated with the MSBT: one had odinophagia which required withdrawal on the seventh day and another patient had anterograde migration of the MSBT with fatal perforation of the small intestine. In 57.1% of the cases, the fistula or stenosis was cured; in 28.6%, there was partial improvement. CONCLUSIONS The endoscopic technique for the insertion of the MSBT serves as an alternative, allows the diagnosis, confirmation, comparison of fistulas or stenosis in the cervical esophagus and is well-tolerated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colocaci칩n endosc칩pica del tubo de derivaci칩n salival de Montgomery en fistulas y estenosis esof치gicas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endoscopic experience with the Montgomery salivary bypass tube in esophageal stenosis and fistulae].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
