<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17952244</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Avila-Funes, José Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amieva, Hélène</dc:author>
<dc:author>Payette, Hélène</dc:author>
<dc:author>Melano-Carranza, Efrén</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the relationship between depressive symptoms and dependence in activities of daily living. MATERIAL AND METHODS Participants, aged 70 to 104 (n= 1 880), were evaluated twice (2001 and 2003). Depressive symptoms were established by a modified version of Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression scale, whereas functional dependence was assessed with Lawton &amp; Brody and Katz scales. Dependence implies the attendance and assistance of another person to accomplish the activity. Multivariate regression analyses were used to determine the effect of depressive symptoms on incident dependence. RESULTS At baseline, 37.9% had depressive symptoms. After two years, 6.1 and 12.7% developed functional dependence for one or more ADL and IADL, respectively. Multivariate analyses showed that depressive symptoms were a risk factor to the development of functional dependence only for the instrumental activities for daily living. CONCLUSIONS Depressive symptoms are a risk factor for functional dependence. Systematic screening it seems necessary in the evaluation of geriatric patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas depresivos como factor de riesgo de dependencia en adultos mayores.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Depressive symptoms as a risk factor for dependence in elderly people].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
