<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17969274</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morejón Martín, Pedro Lorenzo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro Ortega, Agustín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz Pineda, Carlos Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero Lago, Grisel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An ecological evaluation of retrospective and descriptive temporary trend was conducted from 1999 to 2000 .in 8 water bodies of Fomento, province of Sancti Spiritus. To evaluate the effectiveness and permanence of the biolarvicide, there were used data of systematic samplings and of control actions of the provincial surveillance and antivectorial fight programs taken from the records of each breeding place in the Municipal Unit of Higiene and Epidemiology of the locality. Doses of 10 ml of active ingredient per square meter were administered. It was attained the reduction and stabilization of the larval and adult indices in human primer of important species which are vectors of malaria, phyliriasis, and Western Nile's fever. The extension of the larval recovery range up to 3 weeks was proved.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Sep-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control de culícidos con el empleo de Bacillus thuringiensis SH-14 var israelensis en criaderos permanentes de la localidad de Fomento, provincia Sancti Spíritus, Cuba.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Control of culicides by using Bacillus thuringiensis SH-14 var. israelensis in permanent breeding places of Fomento, province of Sancti Spiritus, Cuba].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
