<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17966577</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Longa, Aurora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Schael, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vizcaya, Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nieves, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morier, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Enrique Cabrera, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The feces of 397 patients with acute diarrheal disease (ADD) and of other 121 patients without diarrea (control group) were studied in the state of Mérida, Venezuela, from June 1993 to December 1994. The genus Aeromonas was identified in patients with ADD in 11.83% and in 5.78% of the patients from the control group. On studying the virulence factors described for Aeromonas (enterotoxin, cytotoxin, hemaglutinins, cellular hydrofibrosity, and hemolytic activity) in the isolated strains, it was detected that all presented at least one of the factors investigated associated with enteropathogenicity. Of the isolated species, Aeromonas caviae was the most frequently identified. All these results suggest that the Aeromonas species are potential enteric pathogens in this population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de virulencia asociados a la enteropatogenicidad en cepas Aeromonas spp. aisladas de niños con diarrea en Mérida, Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors of virulence associated with enteropathogenicity in strains of Aeromonas spp. isolated from children with diarrhea in Mérida, Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
