<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1796857</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Peña, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Piñeiro, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Piñeiro, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cózar Olmo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cisneros, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárcamo Valor, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Matres, M J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epidermoid carcinoma of the penis, although rare, is a very aggressive tumor type. The presence or absence of inguinal metastasis is an essential prognostic factor. Treatment of these metastases is one of the current controversies in urological practice; i.e., when and to what extent lymphadenectomy should be performed. Of 24 patients with penile carcinoma, 10 had undergone regional lymphadenectomy over the past 8 years at our institution. Following treatment of the primary penile tumor, 6 patients had palpable inguinal nodes that persisted after treatment with antibiotic and antiinflammatory agents for 6 weeks. Of these, 3 had a positive node biopsy. They were submitted to regional lymphadenectomy which revealed node metastasis in 5 cases (2 pN3, 2 pN2 and 1 pN1). The patients with no palpable nodes were closely followed and were submitted to lymphadenectomy when these appeared (3 cases). The fatal outcome of 2 cases (both pN3) prompted us to perform lymphadenectomy prophylactically in the last case, a 40-year-old male with pT2G2 N0 penile cancer. This approach is advocated in patients under 65 with invasive penile carcinoma (pT greater than 1) or a high histological grade of malignancy (G2 and G3).</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Controversias sobre la linfadenectomía regional en el carcinoma de pene.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Controversies over regional lymphadenectomy in carcinoma of the penis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
