<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17970542</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barbosa Murillo, J A P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández H de Valera, Y M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, H A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, N G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study has as objective to describe behavior of the different components of functionality and muscular mass, in institutionalized older people. Because levels of muscular mass have been associated with reduced levels of force, activity, functionality, depression of the immune function and increase of the morbidity and mortality risk. Were evaluated 152 elderly people older than 60 years old, men and women, of 14 geriatric centers of the Gran Caracas. Anthropometrical variable was measured to value the muscular mass and the body mass index. It was evaluated: hand isometric force, walking time 4.88 m and getting up of a seat. Descriptive statistic was carried out for all the variables, t of Student, Anova and Scheffé. It was observed that 80 years older elderly as well as, women present higher levels of disability, performed motor activities (to walk and to get up of a seat and a impair in physical conditions (lean mass and muscular strength) that interfere with functional status.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Masa muscular, fuerza muscular y otros componentes de funcionalidad en adultos mayores institucionalizados de la Gran Caracas-Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Muscle mass, muscle strength, and other functionality components in institutionalized older adults from Gran Caracas-Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
