<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>17983530</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Saura-Vinuesa, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perpiñá-Tordera, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yago, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soler-Cataluña, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-García, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Román-Sánchez, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE To analyze the serum levels of immunoglobulin G (IgG) subclasses in a broad range of elderly patients with bronchiectasis. PATIENTS AND METHOD Data were collected from all patients who had a high-resolution chest computerized axial tomography diagnosis of bronchiectasis in our center. We gathered data related to case history, respiratory symptoms, forced spirometry, general laboratory tests, immunoglobulin concentration (including IgG subclasses), Mantoux test, sputum culture and staining, paranasal sinus X-rays/computerized axial tomography, and a specific etiologic evaluation based on the available clinical evidence. RESULTS A total of 128 patients were included -mean age (standard deviation): 71.6 (5.1) years; range: 65-88; 44.5% males- and 20.3% of them had chronic sputum colonization with Pseudomonas aeruginosa. 28.1% cases had a post-infectious nature and in 40.6% the etiology was unknown. Sixteen patients (12.5%) had decreased levels of at least one of the sIgG compared to normal values. The most frequent deficiency corresponded to IgG2 levels. These subjects showed a characteristic profile of bronchiectasis with an increased lung extension of the disease (p = 0.02); greater presence of cylindrical and diffuse bronchiectasis (p = 0.02 and 0.01, respectively), greater percentage of an unknown etiology (p = 0.004); greater presence of paranasal sinus X-ray abnormalities (p = 0.004) and increased number of past repeated upper airway infections (p = 0.03). CONCLUSIONS Decreased serum levels of IgG subclasses might be associated with a characteristic profile of bronchiectasis in elderly patients in whom other etiologies have been ruled out.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Oct 20 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bronquiectasias en pacientes mayores de 65 años. Estudio de los valores séricos de las subclases de inmunoglobulina G.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bronchiectasis in the elderly. Study of serum levels of immunoglobulin G subclasses].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
