<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18019597</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8376</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Shamah-Levy, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Macias, Hortensia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avila-Curiel, Abelardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chávez-Villasana, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galindo-Gómez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuevas-Nasu, Lucia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the feeding and nutrition conditions and its relation with diabetes mellitus (DM-2) in adult population (&gt; 30 years) a sample belonging to the low socioeconomic stratum of the Mexico City metropolitan area was studied. They were participants in the Second Feeding and Nutrition Survey in the Mexico City metropolitan area. (ENURBAL-2002). MATERIAL AND METHODS Information collected by the ENURBAL 2002 was used in order to evaluate the relationship between some risk factors and diabetes mellitus in adult population of low economical level. Logistical regression analysis was applied. RESULTS A complete set of 1279 individuals with ages over 30 years was studied. The 9.9% (IC 95% 7.9, 12.4) had been previously diagnosed as diabetics and 3.9% (IC 95% 2.9, 5.4) were not been diagnosed but their glycemia reached diabetic levels. Total diabetes prevalence observed in this study was 13.8% (IC 95% 11.7, 16.3). People with good score on its knowledge about nutrition, as well as high total fat intake, are significant and positively associated with DM-2 (RM = 2.41, IC 95% 1.09, 5.35 and RM = 2.14 IC 95% 1.24, 3.69, respectively). CONCLUSIONS Diabetes mellitus was highly prevalent among adult (&gt; 30 years population) mainly on the lower socioeconomic stratum of Mexico City. This result is important to promote changes in life style that allow to prevent its appearance by modifying the obesigenic environment and changes in the feeding patterns.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus en estratos socioeconómicos bajos de la ciudad de México: un problema relevante.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diabetes mellitus within low socioeconomic strata in Mexico City: a relevant problem].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de investigacion clinica; organo del Hospital de Enfermedades de la Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
