<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18051223</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pezzotto, Stella M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Ariel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Masoni, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tomat, María Florencia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morosano, Mario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this observational, case-control study, 376 inpatients were evaluated in order to determine the association of risk factors (RF) and hip fracture; 151 patients had osteoporotic hip fracture (cases); the remaining were controls. Data were obtained from medical charts, and through a standardized questionnaire about RF. Mean age of the sample (+/- SD) was 80.6 +/- 8.1 years, without statistically significant difference between cases and controls; the female:male ratio was 3:1 in both groups. Fractured women were older than men (82.5 +/- 8.1 vs. 79.7 +/- 7.2 years, respectively; p &lt; 0.01). Physical activity, intake of alcohol and tobacco, and sun exposure were low in all patients. Falls among cases happened predominantly at home (p &lt; 0.001). Among female cases, time spent in household duties was a RF (p = 0.007), which was absent in males. In multivariate analysis, the following RF were significantly more frequent: Cognitive impairment (p = 0.001), and previous falls (p &lt; 0.0001); whereas the following protective factors were significantly different from controls: Calcium intake during youth (p &lt; 0.0001), current calcium intake (p &lt; 0.0001), and mechanical aid for walking (p &lt; 0.0001). Evaluation of RF and protective factors may contribute to diminish the probability of hip fracture, through a modification of personal habits, and measures to prevent falls among elderly adults. Present information can help to develop local and national population-based strategies to diminish the burden of hip fractures for the health system.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo para osteoporosis y fracturas de cadera. Análisis multivariado.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Association between hip fractures and risk factors for osteoporosis. Multivariate analysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
