<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1807106</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Burgos, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berenguer, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negrin, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castañeda, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escudero Barrilero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Allona, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tellez, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We analyze our experience in 175 patients with transitional bladder cancer for whom radical cystectomy was indicated. Patients were divided into three groups: one group was managed with radical cystectomy only and the other two with pre-operative radiotherapy: long-term approach and short-term approach. No significant differences have been observed when comparing current survival rate and disease-free intervals of all three groups. It can be deduced from our series that, by the scarce number of local recurrences observed, there is no other measure to be added to surgery directed to improve the tumour's local management. Most metastasis were diagnosed within 18 months after cystectomy. 58.4% patients presented bone dissemination. The risk of distant dissemination increases with the extent of vesical wall invasion, degree of anaplasia and presence of positive glands. The gland stage is not necessary for the metastasis to be present. Death's ratio with distant dissemination is significantly lower in the group managed Without pre-operative radiotherapy than in the others. Of the 11 patients where no tumour was observed in the cystectomy piece, 2 developed metastasis, indicating that this was already present before bladder extraction. Management of patients with infiltrating++ bladder cancer is complex, but no efforts should be spared to advise the most appropriate approach for each particular case. Chemotherapy plays an unquestionable role among the procedures we have to control, since most patients' deaths happen within two years after local-regional treatment of the primitive tumour and nearly all of them as a consequence of metastasis. Cytostatic agents are the only effective therapy for distant dissemination. We believe that every patient with a cancer extended to the perivesical fat or with dissemination to regional glands, whichever the stage, should be treated with chemotherapy after extirpation of the bladder, and starting as early as the patient's general status would allow it.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma transicional infiltrante de vejiga. (1a parte). Comparación de 2 grupos tratados con radioterapia preoperatoria (pauta larga y pauta corta) + cistectomía radical con otro manejado con cistectomía radical solo. Análisis de recidiva local y metástasis.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infiltrating transitional carcinoma of the bladder (I). Comparison of 2 groups treated with preoperative radiotherapy (long-term protocol and short-term protocol) + radical cystectomy versus radical cystectomy only. Analysis of local recurrence and metastasis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
