<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18075984</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fournier-Del Castillo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernabeu-Verdú, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gavilán, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The validity of the Asperger syndrome (AS) diagnose continues to be debated due to the lack of consensus on its definition, specially regarding higher-functioning autism. Previous research has suggested that the neuropsychological profile of the non verbal learning syndrome (NVLS) might be utilized to sustain a differential diagnose of the AS with other diseases associated with development. AIM To analyze the neuropsychological profile of children diagnosed with AS and compare with those obtained from children with NVLS. SUBJECTS AND METHODS All cognitive domains from 15 children have been evaluated with an extensive variety of tests; 5 were diagnosed with AS and 5 with NVLS, all of them submitted to the Nino Jesus Children's University Hospital. As a control group, another 5 children with no pathology were evaluated. RESULTS Obtained data shows significant differences between the two groups under study. Profile from individuals under AS shows deficit in linguistic as well as non verbal skills and, when compared to the control group, executive functions seem to be generally more altered. CONCLUSIONS Further investigation is suggested to determine that the NVLS could be an explanation model for AS. On the other hand, we stress the need to deepen the study of the executive functions and their relationship with the mind's theory, as an hypothesis to explain the AS.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Dec 16-31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias entre los perfiles neuropsicológicos del síndrome de Asperger y del sindrome de dificultades de aprendizaje no verbal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Differences between the neuropsychological profiles of Asperger's syndrome and non-verbal learning disorder].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
