<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18082094</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mauri, Josepa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baz, José A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albarrán, Agustín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pinar, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article summarizes the data reported to the 2006 registry of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Cardiac Catheterization and Interventional Cardiology. Data were obtained from 135 centers. Of these, 125 performed catheterizations mainly in adults, while 10 carried out procedures in pediatric patients only. In 2006, 126,196 diagnostic catheterizations were carried out. Of these, 113,228 were coronary angiograms, 7.6% more than in 2005. The population-adjusted rate was 2560 coronary angiograms per million inhabitants. A total of 57,041 percutaneous coronary interventions were performed, which was 7.8% more than in the previous year and which corresponds to a rate of 1293 per million inhabitants. Stents were used in 96.1% of coronary interventions. Overall, 90,006 stents were implanted, of which 59.3% were drug-eluting stents. Moreover, 10,067 interventions were carried out for acute myocardial infarction, 20.6% more than in 2005 and accounting for 17.6% of all percutaneous coronary interventions. Non-coronary interventions were most frequently performed for adult congenital heart disease, with closure of an atrial septal defect being the most numerous, at 334 procedures. Percutaneous mitral valvuloplasties were performed in 431 cases, a similar figure to that recorded in the previous registry, and the success rate was 93.6%. Each year, radial access continues to be used more frequently for coronary procedures. Finally, it is important to emphasize that a high percentage of laboratories reported results, which ensures that the data presented here can serve as an international reference source for percutaneous cardiac interventions performed in Spain.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Hemodinámica y Cardiología Intervencionista. XVI Informe Oficial de la Sección de Hemodinámica y Cardiología Intervencionista de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (1990-2006).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Spanish Cardiac Catheterization and Coronary Intervention Registry. 16th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Cardiac Catheterization and Interventional Cardiology (1990-2006)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
