<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18094909</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rey-Herranz, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Molina, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez de la Riva, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-López, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gandia-González, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega-Martínez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isla-Guerrero, A J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saceda-Gutiérrez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report 3 patients with fibrous solitary tumor of meningeal location where we described the histological study, as well as evolution after the surgical treatment. The described patients presented ages of 37, 52 and 65 years, after the resection has not appeared an objective sign of recurrence in any case after 4, 6 and 7 years of follow-up respectively. Checking the literature the tumor is indistinguishable clinical and radiolocally of the typical meningioma, doing necessary the use of inmunohistochemistry to do the differential diagnosis, where positiveness for CD34 and the negativeness for EMA define the fibrous solitary tumor. It is about a benign tumor, where total removing is the principal factor in prognosis, nevertheless there are cases of local recurrences and long-distance metastasis. We can find all these characteristics in the showed cases of the present article, having the uncertainty of its local or systemic relapse ability in the future.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor fibroso solitario meníngeo: descripción de tres casos y revisión de la literatura.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Solitary fibrous tumors of the meninges: report of three cases and literature review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
