<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1819543</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López Rosales, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Espinosa, R E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez Vazquez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To study the efficacy of lisuride in fibrocystic mastopathy, we conducted a clinical trial in 23 out patients, aged 19-50 years, randomly recruited from the gynecological service of the ISSSTE, Dr. Darío Fernández Fierro. Hospital. The only exclusion criteria was having received previous treatment. The patients clinical history was recorded. Physical examination, hormone profile (FSH, LH, prolactin, testosterone, estrogen and progesterone) and ultrasound exam of the mammae at baseline were performed in all patients, as well as, mammography in patients older than 40 years or those requiring so. Treatment was started with 1/2 tablet of lisuride (0.1 mg)/8 hours, preferably with meals, for 3 months. At the end of therapy, hormone profile, ultrasound of the mammae and physical examination were repeated for control purposes. We obtained the following results; fibrocystic mastopathy was most frequent in women aged 20-29 years, mean age 31 years symptoms disappeared in 36.9% and were reduced notably in 63.1%, of cases. Grade O ultrasound lesions disappeared in 100% of patients and grade I and II lesions improved. On physical examination all patients showed improvement; estrogen values were reduced and progesterone incremented. The prolactin level were normal at baseline, as well as by the end of treatment. One patient suffered severe side effects which required interruption of treatment; 4 patients experimenting light side effects were able to continue therapy and in the remaining 18 patients, no adverse reactions were observed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la mastopatía fibroquística con lisurida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of fibrocystic breast disease with lisuride].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
