<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18209822</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Eslava-Schmalbach, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobar-Córdoba, Franklin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chica-Urzola, Heydy Luz</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Validating the Epworth sleepiness scale (ESS-VC) for use in Colombia . METHODS Individuals were included who consulted sleep centres in Bogotá, Pereira and Cali ( Colombia ). Study design consisted of eight phases: a pilot study for assessing the Spanish version of the scale, translation and retro-translation of the original ESS, a pilot test for evaluating understanding (n=20), validating appearance (experts, n=18), internal consistency (n=120), validating concurrent and discriminating criteria (n=150) with parallel polysomnography, reproducibility (n=15) and sensitivity to change (n=100). RESULTS ESE-VC presented suitable internal consistency (Cronbach's Alpha=0,85). It identified patients suffering from severe sleepiness, according to pathology (K Wallis Chi2=19,81, p=0.003). It was clinically significant in discriminating patients according to sleep apnoea severity and abnormal sleep latency (Chi2=5,391, p=0.1453) in ways, and also in REM sleep latency (Chi2=9,015, p=0.0291). It is reproducible and sensitive to change. CONCLUSIONS ESS-VC compared well with the original version. It is well adapted to urban life conditions in the Colombian adult population, reliable, valid and sensitive to reported changes. It had clinically and statistically significant correlation with polysomnography.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la Escala de Somnolencia de Epworth.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Validating the Epworth sleepiness scale].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
