<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18209818</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cepeda-Cuervo, Edilberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez, Viviana P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moncada-Sánchez, Evelyn</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Determining levels of intra-family violence associated with students attending schools in Ciudad Bolivar, Bogotá, Colombia. MATERIAL AND METHODS The sample consisted of 3,226 students from the 6th to 11th grades attending state schools located in Ciudad Bolivar in Bogotá. The data was collected from a survey in which the students' perception of violence in their homes was determined; data was statistically analysed by using SPSS 14.0. RESULTS A high percentage of students had difficulty in communicating with their parents and felt rejected and a lack of love from some of the members in their homes. 28.4% of those surveyed (915 students) had been victims of more than 20 of the violent situations; 35% of the students in the sample had a family atmosphere characterised by high levels of violence. The percentage of students who stated that they had been physically mistreated depended on their education level; the highest percentages being presented in the 7th and 8th grades. CONCLUSIONS The middle- and upper-school student community in Ciudad Bolivar in Bogotá, Colombia, is affected by many situations concerning intra-family violence.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Violencia Intrafamiliar que afecta a Estudiantes de Educación Básica y Media en Bogotá</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intra-family violence affecting students attending basic- and middle-schools in Bogotá].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
