<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18215385</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramírez-Camacho, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-García, José Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Tallón, Ana Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibáñez, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trinidad, Almudena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verdaguer, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Román, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Berrocal, José Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVE To describe an environmental scanning electron microscopic method for the study of biofilms in clinical samples. A comparison with standard scanning electron microscopy is performed. PATIENTS AND METHOD Nine patients with a past history of recurrent tonsillitis underwent tonsillectomy. Samples from each patient were obtained for both conventional and environmental scanning electron microscopy. The tonsils removed from 2 patients with sleep apnoea syndrome were used as controls. RESULTS Eight of nine tonsils had biofilms on their surface. Scanning electron microscopy showed accumulations of bacteria covered by fibrillar structures resulting from the sample dehydration process. Environmental scanning electron microscopy provided a view of bacteria embedded in a homogeneous, amorphous substance that was preserved during the examination. CONCLUSIONS Environmental scanning electron microscopy permits the imaging of wet systems at different degrees of dehydration. It therefore allows researchers to observe biofilms in their natural hydrated state.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microscopia electrónica de barrido ambiental para la detección de biopelículas en las amígdalas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Environmental scanning electron microscopy for biofilm detection in tonsils].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
