<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18247183</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cardinal, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Legnani, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salamano, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Marchiafava-Bignami disease (MBD) is a rare complication of chronic alcoholism characterized by demyelination and necrosis of the corpus callosum that usually has a poor prognosis. It has an extensive clinical spectrum presentation and can presently be diagnosed in vivo with the computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). CLINICAL CASES We describe two cases of MBD disease with fatal outcome that presented with acute onset coma. Impairment of consciousness, hypertonia, and frontal release signs were the dominant clinical signs. One of the patients had optic neuropathy and the other had neuropsychiatric symptoms before onset of coma and pellagra-like skin lesion. The CT scan and MRI showed lesions of the white matter that were fundamentally in the corpus callosum. CONCLUSIONS The possibility of the existence of MBD should be investigated in all patients with chronic alcoholism who have prolonged confusional syndrome, stupor or coma. A prodromal stage with neuropsychiatric symptoms should be thoroughly investigated with a neuropsychological exploration including interhemispheric disconnection signs. Careful attention should be given to the corpus callosum in the image for the diagnosis of this probably underdiagnosed disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Marchiafava-Bignami en Uruguay.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Marchiafava-Bignami disease in Uruguay].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
