<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18246264</identifier>
<setSpec>1519-566X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro, Juan C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Liria, Jonathan</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the cibarial morphology in eight Psorophora species Robineau-Desvoidy: Ps. (Grabhamia) cingulata (Fabricius), Ps. (Gra.) confinnis (Lynch Arribálzaga), Ps. (Janthinosoma) ferox (Humboldt), Ps. (Jan.) albipes (Theobald), Ps. (Jan.) cyanescens (Coquillett), Ps. (Psorophora) lineata (Humboldt), Ps. (Pso.) cilipes (Fabricius), y Ps. (Pso.) ciliata (Fabricius). The species belonging to subgenus Grabhamia Theobald are characterized by palatal papillae in central position and the presence of cibarial armature. The teeth in Ps. cingulata are equal meanwhile in Ps. confinnis the internal row is spatulate with apex denticulate. In Janthinosoma Lynch Arribálzaga we observed six palatal papillae (the fore pair with less size to others) and armature absent, instead we observe small spicules toward posterior plate: abundant in Ps. ferox, and few in Ps. albipes and Ps. cyanescens. The subgenus Psorophora presents four equal size palatal papillae, cibarial armature absent, also distinctive number of trichoid sensilla (12-17), in comparison to other two subgenera (5-10). We suggest to include those diagnostic characters in the future taxonomic and systematic studies in the genus Psorophora.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Morfología del cibario en subgéneros de Psorophora Robineau-Desvoidy (Diptera: Culicidae).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cibarial morphology in Psorophora Robineau-Desvoidy subgenera (Diptera: Culicidae)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neotropical entomology</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
