<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18273983</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cortés González, Jeff R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Guerra, Lauro S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz Lara, Gerardo E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arratia Maqueo, Jorge A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To demonstrate that continuos intravesical irrigation with amikacin is an effective adyuvant treatment in Emphisematous Cistitis therapy. METHODS A 3 way transurethral Foley catheter was placed and a continuous intravesical irrigation was initiated with amikacin 500 mg in 1L of normal saline (500 micrograms per ml) within 6 hours 4 times a day and three consecutive days. RESULTS After 3 days of treatment the patient showed significant clinical response. A new CT scan showed the absence of gas in the bladder wall compared to the previews CT and negative urine culture was obtained. CONCLUSIONS We established that treatment using adjuvant continuous intravesical irrigation with amikacin can reduce hospital stay and accelerate the patient's healing process, as well as an earlier negativisation of urine cultures. A comparative prospective study is needed to evaluate if in fact this treatment variant produces a real benefit compared to conventional therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Irrigación intravesical continua con amikacina como tratamiento adyuvante en la cistitis enfisematosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continous bladder irrigation with amikacin as adjuvant treatment for emphysematous cystitis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
