<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18273527</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mediavilla R, Marisol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jahnsen K, Johanne</dc:author>
<dc:author>Täger F, Marlis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burgos L, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The characteristic clinical presentation of cat scratch disease is subacute regional lymphadenopathy; nevertheless, 5-25% of Bartonella henselae infections may present an atypical or systemic form, with potential eye involvement. We describe three clinical cases of ocular bartonellosis in two adolescents and one young adult, who had close contact with cats; all of them presented persistent fever ranging from 15 to 21 days, and two of them developed a sudden unilateral loss of visual acuity associated with optic neuritis. The other patient presented retinal choroiditis and unilateral retinal microgranulomas, with normal visual acuity. Patients received macrolides as sole antimicrobial or in association with rifampin, and one patient was additionally treated with systemic corticoids. The outcome was favorable in two patients; one patient developed a permanent visual deficit. Ocular bartonellosis must be suspected in patients with close contact to cats or with cat scratches whom develop persistent fever and sudden loss of visual acuity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bartonelosis ocular: Reporte de tres casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Ocular bartonellosis: report of three clinical cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
