<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18294438</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chávez-Aguirre, Rocío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Hernández, Antonio Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To evaluate the prevalence of dyslipidemia and comorbidity in adults older than 20 years attending to the family medicine clinic number 20 of Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social and to compare it with the prevalence in Mexico. METHOD the study was conducted in 2005 by using a cross-sectional design; dyslipidemia was ascertained by measuring total cholesterol and triglycerides. Additional variables were: gender, age, health status, and diagnosis of diabetes, hypertension, overweight, and obesity. A standardization procedure and a dry run were carried out before beginning the data collection phase. RESULTS The study included 165 participants, 35.2 % had hypercholesterolemia and 63.6 % had hypertriglyceridemia. According to the variables, 20.0% of people aged 40 to 59 years of age; 57.1% of women; 40.9% of overweight, 40.9% of obese and 49.5% of healthy patients had hypertriglyceridemia; while 68.9% of women; 44.8% of patients with hypertension, and 51.7 % of overweight patients had hypercholesterolemia. CONCLUSION The prevalence of hypertriglyceridemia and hypercholesterolemia were significantly different from previous reports (hypercholesterolemia z&lt; or =2.83; p &lt; 0.001; hypertriglyceridemia z = 7.83; p &lt; 00.1), being higher in women and increasing with aging.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y comorbilidad de dislipidemias en el primer nivel de atención.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of dyslipidemia in a family medicine clinic].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
