<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18311677</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Loygorri, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabo-Vaquera, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Delgado, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Herrero, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Asensio-Sánchez, V M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Helicobacter pylori (HP) gastric infection has been implicated as an important factor in occlusive arterial pathology. Nowadays, it is suspected that central serous chorioretinopathy (CSC) is due to a multifocal vascular occlusive disease of the choriocapillaris. The aim of this study was to determine the relation between gastric HP infection and CSC. MATERIALS AND METHODS We evaluated a group of 16 patients with CSC and 20 controls. HP infection was assessed by the 13C-urea breath test (UBT). Clinical CSC diagnosis was confirmed by fundus biomicroscopy and fluorescein angiography. RESULTS Out of 16 patients with CSC, 11 (68.75%) were males and 5 (31.25%) females, with a mean age of 46.3 years. HP infection was positive in 11 patients (68.75%) and negative in 5 (31.25%). Men were HP-positive (HP+) in 72.7% of cases, compared to women who were HP+ in 60% of cases. The difference in prevalence of HP between the CSC-group (68.75%) and the control-group (30%) was found to be statistically significant (p&lt; 0.05). HP+ patients had more gastric pain than HP negative (HP-) patients (72.73% vs 20%). CONCLUSIONS These results indicate a possible statistical association between Helicobacter pylori gastric infection and CSC. HP should thus be considered a risk factor in CSC patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coriorretinopatía serosa central como manifestación extradigestiva de infección gástrica por helicobacter pylori.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Central serous chorioretinopathy as an extradigestive manifestation of Helicobacter pylori gastric infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
