<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18320120</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Poveda, Elpidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baracaldo, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerra, Martha</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Carlina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Callas, Ney</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Research in laboratories around the world has documented the contribution of the E apolipoprotein alleles to structural variations of lipids and apolipoproteins. OBJECTIVE The gene frequencies of the E apolipoprotein alleles were compared with the lipid and apolipoprotein levels in school age children. MATERIALS AND METHODS Six hundred and ninety one 5 to 15 years old school age children from the Colombian departments of Cundinamarca, Boyacá, Meta, Santander and Norte de Santander, were evaluated. The genotypes of the E apolipoprotein were identified by polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism. Plasma levels for the following 5 lipids and lipoproteins were assayed: total cholesterol, HDL (high density lipoprotein) cholesterol, LDL (low density lipoprotein) cholesterol, triglycerides, VLDL (very low density lipoprotein) cholesterol, A-I apolipoprotein and B-100 apolipoprotein. RESULTS Alleles e2, e3 and e4 were found in frequencies of 0.04, 0.86 and 0.08, respectively. The E4 group (E4/3-E4/4), in contrast with the E2 group (E3/2-E2/2), presented highest plasma concentrations of total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol and B-100 apolipoprotein (p=0.014, 0.001 and 0.000, respectively). When the E3/3 group was compared with E2, the same result was obtained (p=0.015, 0.002 and 0.002, respectively). The influence of the E apolipoprotein polymorphism appeared greater in female children than male. CONCLUSIONS The e4 allele was associated with higher levels of total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol and B-100 apolipoprotein and indicates the necessity of additional research into the interactions between polymorphism E apolipoprotein and other genes, life styles, risk factors and potential contribution to cardiovascular diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismo genético de la apolipoproteína E en un grupo de escolares del centro-oriente colombiano: comparación con las concentraciones plasmáticas de lípidos y apolipoproteínas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Genetic polymorphism of the E apolipoprotein in school age children: comparison with levels of plasma lipids and apolipoproteins].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
