<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18320109</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Orjuela, Dora Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribón, Wellman</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, Luz Mary</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garzón, María Consuelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puerto, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Polo, Claudia Llerena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro, Claudia Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Nontuberculous mycobacteria can be saprophytic, pathogenic or opportunistic. The most common diseases produced by these microorganisms are the post-surgical infections due to anesthetic procedures, infections associated with catheters, disseminated cutaneous diseases and pulmonary and central nervous system diseases that especially affect HIV patients. Identification of the nontuberculous mycobacteria can take several weeks and even then, differentiation of complex members is not possible. OBJECTIVE The PCR-restriction analysis (PRA) technique was evaluated as a method for genotypic identification of nontuberculous mycobacteria isolated of clinical samples located in the culture collection of the Instituto Nacional de Salud (National Institute of Health), Bogotá, Colombia. MATERIALS AND METHODS Seventy clinical isolates of nontuberculous mycobacteria stored in 50% glycerol at -70 degrees C were identified by phenotypic techniques. The genotypic identification was made using the PCR-restriction analysis (PRA) using the restriction enzymes BstEII and HseIII, the restriction products were visualized on gels of agarose to 3%, and the concordance between the methodologies was evaluated. RESULTS A matching of 100% was obtained in the identification of Mycobacterium terrae, M. szulgai, M. avium, M. chelonae and M. scrofulaceum, the matching between M. fortuitum species, M. abscessus, M. gordonae and M. intracellulare varied from 44 to 89%; there was no concurrence in the identification of species M. flavescens and M. malmoense. CONCLUSIONS PRA provided a fast, inexpensive and accurate alternative for the identification of nontuberculous mycobacteria that permited the differentiation among species of a complex and determining the subtype of each species sample.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación molecular de micobacterias no tuberculosas mediante el análisis de los patrones de restricción, Colombia 1995-2005.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Molecular identification of non-tuberculous mycobacteria].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
