<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18341903</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fabregat, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jorba, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lladó, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Julià, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torras, Jaume</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valls, Carles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rafecas, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueras, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective of the study is to review our experience in the surgical treatment of Klatskin tumours, after the systematic application of the current concepts of radicalism. Sixty-one patients resected using these criteria are presented. PATIENTS AND METHOD We have studied 154 patients. Surgery was ruled out in 59 (41%) of them, and a liver transplant was performed on 9; of the 86 patients operated on, 25 were resectable. Resectability was 71% (of the 86 patients operated on) and was 39% of the total patients. The results during two periods are compared, 1989-1998 (pre-99) and 1999-2007 (post-99). RESULTS On comparing the two periods, resectability increased from 26% to 53% (p = 0.01), the percentage of exploratory laparotomies decreasing (pre: 45% vs post: 22%; p = 0.04). Hepatectomy was performed in 53 cases (87%), being most frequent post-99 (pre: 66% vs post: 91%; p = 0.02). Resection of the caudate was performed in 48 cases (90%), being most frequent in the post-99 period (pre: 40% vs pos: 89%; p = 0.005). Post-operative morbidity was 77%, with 28% the patients being re-operated on, and the post-operative mortality was 16.4%, with no significant differences between the periods. Actuarial survival at 5 years increases in the post-99 period (pre: 26% vs post: 51%; p = 0.06). CONCLUSIONS Adequate staging, associated with an aggressive surgical strategy can achieve a greater than 50% resectability rate. The post-operative morbidity and mortality of this strategy is high, but the survival that it achieves justifies this.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resección radical del colangiocarcinoma hiliar. Indicaciones y resultados.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Radical resection of a hilar cholangiocarcinoma. Indications and results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
