<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18373297</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Caballero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morente-Matas, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabezas-León, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate visual acuity and quality of life improvement after cataract surgery. METHODS Visual acuity and quality of life were assessed in patients undergoing phaco-emulsification. They were of both genders, ranged from forty-six to ninety-two years of age, and were able to understand the SF-36 quality of life questionnaire which explores the differences in quality of life before and after surgery. The questionnaire was completed before cataract surgery and again 6 and 18 months later. Visual acuity was measured with Snellen optotype. RESULTS The answers of 150 patients were evaluated in this study. The average age was 74.32 years. After the surgery the body pain results increased, with this shown to be statistically significant. The social function, general health, perception, role limitation due to physical problems and physical function significantly improved between the first and third consultations. There were no significant differences in role limitation due to emotional problems, nor in vitality. The mental health dimension became worse between consultations although there was no statistically significant difference found. The average values for Visual Acuity were 18.39, 66.01 and 69.02 at the three timed assessments made. CONCLUSIONS Cataract surgery performed by phacoemulsification has been proven to be effective in improving quality of life, especially in physical aspects, according to the improvement in role limitation due to physical problems. Visual acuity also improves after surgery. Disease specific instruments, such as the SF-36, should be used as the outcome measure in clinical practice after cataract surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la cirugía de catarata: agudeza visual y calidad de vida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Impact of cataract surgery on visual acuity and quality of life].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
