<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18372975</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8910</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Caballero, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campero, Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kendall, Tamil</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the influence of the relationship between people living with HIV/AIDS and health care providers on treatment adherence and quality of life. METHODS Qualitative study conducted in Mexico, in 2003, with informants recruited from HIV/AIDS support groups, non-governmental organizations, and infectious disease clinics in public hospitals. A total of 40 people living with HIV/AIDS and five support group leaders were interviewed. Data were collected using sociodemographic questionnaires and in-depth interviews exploring the experience of living with HIV/AIDS, including treatment, disease perception, quality of life, physical and emotional health, and relationship with physicians. Responses were recorded, transcribed and organized thematically based on codes using an inductive analysis. RESULTS Most respondents aged between 26 and 45 years. The main obstacles to care were related to lack of risk awareness and information among people living with HIV/AIDS and physicians. Physicians proved not to be well trained on HIV/AIDS care. During the follow-up care, most problems were related to inadequate treatment adherence mainly caused by poor communication with physicians and discrimination in public services. CONCLUSIONS Overall the problems identified were related to information deficiencies, physicians' lack of training and paternalism, and social stigmatization of people living with HIV/AIDS associated with the epidemic.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre médicos y pacientes con VIH: influencia en apego terapéutico y calidad de vida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Relationship between physicians and HIV patients: influence on adherence and quality of life].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
