<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18373925</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Etchegoyen, Graciela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negro, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín, Gustavo Horacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivadulla, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gelemur, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence and causes of anaemia among adults in Buenos Aires, Argentina. DESIGN Community-based, cross-sectional, quantitative study, with descriptive and analytic stages. SETTING Study conducted in La Plata, Buenos Aires, Argentina. PARTICIPANTS Rigorous selection from randomised sampling, with 3-stage stratification: geographical area, health aspects, and social/economic status. Adults &gt;18 years old. RESULTS AND MAIN MEASUREMENTS: Social-economic and nutritional data and blood samples were obtained from each participant. If anaemia was detected, either treatment was given until complete recovery or further studies were conducted until definitive diagnosis was reached. Weight, height, haemoglobin, erythrocytes, haematocrit, transferrin, iron and ferritin levels, daily intake of calories, carbohydrates, lipids, proteins, calcium, iron, and vitamin C were measured. One thousand and thirty-six patients out of 1200 selected were analyzed. The prevalence of anemia in adults was 26.3%. Variables such as low social/economic status, nutritional questions, and frequency of doctor's consultation were associated with risk of anaemia. However, basic unsatisfied needs--a variable consisting of precarious housing and low educational level--, female sex, and living in slums were significant in the multivariate analysis (OR&gt;2.5). CONCLUSIONS One in 4 adults has anaemia, with iron deficiency as the major cause. Anaemia diagnosis is mainly associated with social and gender questions and the area of residence. This information, if used by the State to plan appropriate and focused preventive measures, could benefit not just adults but the entire community that depends on them.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio poblacional de prevalencia de anemia en población adulta de Buenos Aires, Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Population study of the prevalence of anaemia in the adult population of Buenos Aires, Argentina].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
