<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18386532</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Flores, Lucio M Martínez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villanueva, Jorge Morales</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, César Augusto Cerda</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To show the experience in management of eight cases of floating shoulder. MATERIAL AND METHODS Descriptive, ambispective, longitudinal and observational study of eight patients treated during the period of November 2003 to April 2005. We determined age, sex, mechanisms of injury, injuries associated to the extremity and other systems and functional results were evaluated. RESULTS Eight patients treated, 7 men and 1 woman, age from 27 to 54 years, the average of hospital stay was of 13.25 days. The dominant extremity was injuried in the 85.5% of the cases. The most frequent morphologic pattern was a type II Ideberg glenoid fracture and a type I Allman clavicle fracture. Surgical treatment used in five patients were in the modalities of a plate to clavicle, or plate to the glenoid. Patients with acromioclavicle dislocation underwent to techniques of Phemister and Stewart. To patients treated with conservative methods were treated with an immobilizer of the shoulder plus device in 45 degrees and 90 degrees of abduction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del hombro flotante: experiencia de ocho casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of the floating shoulder. Eight cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
