<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18381027</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lillo, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tenías, José M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beneyto, Matilde</dc:author>
<dc:author>Querol-Ribelles, José M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Forés, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The delay in the initiation of antibiotic treatment in patients with community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) could influence their prognostic. The aim of our study was to evaluate the influence of a delay in antibiotic treatment on mortality, occurrence of complications, and length of stay in the hospital, in relation to the prior duration of the fever. PATIENTS AND METHOD This is a cohort study which includes all patients over 18 years of age admitted with CAP over a 4 year period. The response variables analysed were in-hospital mortality, average stay in days and occurrence of complications during evolution. The relationship between the delay in antibiotic treatment and the outcome variables was estimated by logistic regression models, adjusting the estimations by PSI (Pneumonia Severity Index) and APACHE II (Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation). RESULTS Six hundred fifty-nine patients were included (average age of 71 years, 71% males). Seventy-six (11.6%) patients died, 12.1% of those who arrived after 48 hours (55.4% of patients) and 10.9% of those who came early. The delay in antibiotic treatment was associated with a higher mortality (odds ratio [OR] = 3.05; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.86-10.9; threshold of 8 h), prolonged stay (OR = 2.38; CI 95%, 1.11-5.14; threshold of 5 h) and a higher rate of complications (OR = 2.24; CI 95%, 0.90-5.53; threshold of 3 h). CONCLUSIONS Our results suggest the importance of the early administration of antibiotics in patients with CAP. There is also an increased risk for each of these outcomes in those patients with a history of fever of more than 2 days before arriving in hospital.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar 22 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demora del tratamiento antibiótico y evolución de los pacientes con neumonía adquirida en la comunidad que requieren hospitalización.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Antibiotic treatment onset delay and clinical evolution in admitted patients with community-acquired pneumonia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
