<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18398555</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil Costa, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz de Lejarazu, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eiros Bouza, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castrodeza Sanz, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Rubio, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luquero Alcalde, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Chicken pox is a mainly childhood contagious disease caused by the Varicella Zoster Virus which gives rise to major healthcare and social costs. In 2005, Castile and Leon added chicken pox vaccine injections to its childhood vaccination schedule for eleven year-olds subject to coming down with this disease. This strategy does not modify the major mobility generated thereby at younger ages. This study is aimed at evaluating the profitability of systematic vaccination for chicken pox in infants 15 months of age in Castile and Leon. METHODS An economic cost-benefit evaluation has been set out by jeans of a decision-making tree. A fictitious cohort of 100,000 children in Castile and Leon having reached 15 months of age in 2004 is studied, to whom the chicken pox vaccine would be administered in conjunction with the mumps, measles, rubella vaccines. This study is approached from the social standpoint. The time horizon selected was that of up until the study cohort was to reach 15 years of age, applying a 3% discount rate. A sensitivity analysis was made for evaluating the uncertainty of some variables... RESULTS The cost-benefit ratio of adding this vaccine to the childhood vaccination schedule amounts to 1.23. CONCLUSIONS From the social standpoint, administering chicken pox vaccine in conjunction with the mumps, measles, rubella vaccines show itself to be profitable. The profitability is modified both if a second dose of vaccine is added as well as if only the direct healthcare costs are analyzed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto social y económico de la vacunación frente a la varicela a los 15 meses de edad en Castilla y León en 2004.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Social and economic impact of chicken pox vaccine at 15 months of age. Castile and Leon, Spain, 2004].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
