<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18405583</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domínguez Coello, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Díaz, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz González, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gobierno Hernández, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Marrero, María Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Hernández, José Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study to what extent a brief intervention increases the rate of participation in the programme of early diagnosis of breast cancer (EDBC). DESIGN Before-and-after intervention study without a control group on women who had not had a mammography. SETTING Primary care: 3 rural lists and 2 urban ones. PARTICIPANTS All women between 52 and 67 who attended the clinic during a 6-month period. INTERVENTION If they had had no mammography in the previous 2 years, the reasons were explored and a brief structured intervention, depending on the reason, was conducted. After this, the woman was invited to make an appointment with the EDBC Unit. MAIN MEASUREMENTS Effective intervention: checking that the mammography had been done at the EDBC Unit. It was checked whether women who had not attended for consultation attended the unit with their mammography done. RESULTS Out of a target population of 565 women, 403 (71%) attended for consultation. Of these, 315 (78%) were in the programme, 51 (13%) had had a mammography outside the programme, and 37 (9%) had not had a mammography. After the intervention, 21 women had a mammography (56.7% [95% CI, 41-73] success of intervention). Seventy of the 162 women who did not attend for consultation had a mammography in the programme. The rate of participation in the EDBC rose from 68% (385/565) to 72% (406/565). CONCLUSIONS The brief intervention was effective in over half the women. This small increase contributed to reaching the minimum levels of coverage recommended in a programme of this kind.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención oportunista de los médicos de familia en el programa de diagnóstico precoz del cáncer de mama.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Opportune intervention of family doctors in the programme of early detection of breast cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
