<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18447976</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Angulo-Martínez, Esther S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán-Durán, José E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almario-Chaparro, Jorge E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ordóñez-Ordóñez, Leonardo E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lora-Falquez, José G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prieto-Rivera, José A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES To determine the risk factors associated with myringoplasty failure among the study population, a case-control study was carried out in 2 tertiary hospital centers. PATIENTS AND METHOD Patients undergoing tympanic membrane perforation or atelectasis within 3 to 6 months following surgery were considered as cases, otherwise, they were considered to be controls. Patients having undergone any type of ossiculoplasty were excluded. Seventy cases and 210 controls were included, a sample size calculated for the following variables: inflammation at time of surgery, place and size of the tympanic membrane perforation, presence of tympanosclerosis, presence of cholesteatoma, and surgical technique. Odds ratio was calculated as main association measure, a stratified analysis was performed to rule out possible confusion factors. RESULTS No significant differences were found between the 2 groups respect to the variables for which the sample was calculated. Although in total group the addition of a modified radical mastoidectomy showed better operative results (95 % CI OR = 0.13-0.72; P=.002), in isolated tympanic membrane perforation this association it was loosed (95 % CI OR = 0.06-7.44; P=.81). CONCLUSIONS Results in this study suggest that the variables for which the sample size was calculated are not associated with myringoplasty failure in this population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo de fracaso de la miringoplastia: un estudio de casos y controles.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors leading to failure in myringoplasty: a case-control study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
