<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18483644</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aranís J, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oporto C, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Riedel K, Ingrid</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinoza, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez C, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>García C, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The diagnostic difficulties of brucellosis makes the evaluation of new diagnostic tests necessary. OBJECTIVES Evaluation of different commercial tests in the serological diagnosis of brucellosis by ELISA and immunocapture antibodies in a clinical series of patients with brucellosis of the Health Network of the Catholic University of Chile. METHODS All the serums received in the Laboratory of Microbiology for suspicion of brucellosis during five years were studied. Two groups were obtained, one that fulfilled diagnostic criteria for brucellosis [clinical evidence, and/or positive blood culture and/or seroagglutination test (SAT) in titers &gt; 1/160] and the control group. Each serum sample was analyzed using irnmunocapture-agglutination test (Brucellacapt), ELISA IgM and IgG. RESULTS Of 10 patients with brucellosis, the serologic results were: 8/10 positives for ELISA IgG, 7/10 for Brucellacapt and SAT, and 5/10 for ELISA IgM. DISCUSSION ELISA IgG alone was superior than SAT. The combination ELISA IgG/ Brucellacapt reaches the best detection performance (9/10) and can be an alternative to SAT.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la determinación de anticuerpos IgG e IgM por ELISA e inmunocaptura en una serie clínica de brucelosis humana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Usefulness of the determination of IgG and IgM antibodies by ELISA and immunocapture in a clinical series of human brucellosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
