<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18492430</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramírez-Sibaja, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bolde, Carmen Castellanos-Pérez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orozco-Gómez, Luis Porfirio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moguel-Ancheita, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND We undertook this study to demonstrate the visuomotor alterations, intelligence level and depression changes in children with recurrent strabismus. METHODS Children with recurrent strabismus were studied with the Human Figure Test, Lauretta Bender Visuomotor Test, Intelligence Level of Weschler, WISC-R, and WPPSI. Complete exploration of strabismus was made. RESULTS We included nine children aged 6.8 years (SD 2). Overfunction of oblique muscles and dissociated strabismus were related to recurrence of strabismus. Stereovision was present in five cases previous to recurrence (rate: 170 sec of arc), and three lost this with recurrence of strabismus. Psychological test determined difficulties in socialization and signs of aggression, including data on depression and "dullness." Bender Test showed relevant defects in fine hand movement, level: 5.4 (SD 1.7). Santucci evaluation for Bender was 3.83 (SD 2.1). Correlation coefficient between values was significant for Santucci evaluation and stereovision (0.89). Global Intelligence Coefficient was 88.1 (SD 12), which was subnormal and poorer in executive function (84). CONCLUSIONS We have demonstrated relevant alterations in visuomotor abilities in patients with strabismus, especially related to stereovision deficiency, effect on learning, intelligence and depression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las funciones sensoriomotoras y depresión en niños con estrabismo. Primera fase.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of depression and sensorial functions in children with strabismus. First phase].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
