<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18499960</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Poggi, Emmanuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cecchini, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luchetti, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vujacich, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Stamboulian, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Herpes zoster (HZ) is a public health problem worldwide. Although, there is paucity of data of this disease from South American countries. The objective of this study was to evaluate clinical and epidemiological aspects of HZ in a population of patients from South America. We underwent a retrospective analysis of clinical charts of an infectious diseases reference center (period: 2000-2005). Univariate analysis was performed to assess variables related to post herpetic neuralgia (PHN). From a total of 302 cases, 62% were in women. The median age was 57 years: 16.1% of the patients had a predisposing condition for the development of HZ. Most frequent dermatomes involved were: thoracic, ophthalmic and lumbar; 93.5% of the patients received antiviral drugs and 94% complementary medications. The most frequent complication was PHN and was related with age over 50 years. Clinical and epidemiological aspects of HZ and the frequency of complications in our population were similar to data from developed countries.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Herpes zoster. Epidemiología y clínica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical and epidemiological aspects of herpes zoster].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
