<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18620672</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cardesa García, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Tallo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias López, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campo Sanpedro, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION There is no clear consensus as regards the exact incidence of congenital heart disease. The objective of this study was to determine the incidence of congenital heart defects in Badajoz province (Spain). MATERIAL AND METHODS This is a retrospective study based on the clinical histories of 742 patients who were seen for the first time during 1997 in the paediatric cardiology unit of Badajoz Women and Children's Hospital. The incidence of congenital Heart defects is calculated by adding the number of patients assessed in 1997 and those who will be assessed in the future, considering the population born in 1997. The last figure is inferred from the number of patients who were born before 1997 and were assessed in that year, comparing the number of newborns between 1997 and previous years. The number of patients is divided by the total newborns in 1997 and multiplied by 1,000. RESULTS Congenital heart defects were found in 15.6 % of the patients seen during 1997. The incidence ranges from 16.1 to 5.4 new cardiac diseases per 1,000 newborn babies per year if some minor congenital heart defects that are not considered in other publications are excluded, such as interatrial communication of the ostium secundum type, interventricular communication of the small muscle, mild prolapsed mitral valve, bicuspid aortic valve, patent ductus arteriosus in prematures infants, silent ductus arteriosus and congenital arrhythmias. CONCLUSIONS The incidence of congenital heart defects in Badajoz province range from 16.1 to 5.5 new cardiac diseases per 1,000 newborn babies per year. We consider that the incidence in the Badajoz province is reliable and similar to other recent publications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de las cardiopatías congénitas en la provincia de Badajoz.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Incidence and clinical characteristics of congenital heart disease in Badajoz Province, Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
