<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18672751</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García Tizoc, Saúl Orlando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Zepeda, Ernesto Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cadenas Tovar, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Huape Arreola, María Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas Espinosa, Juan Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the Robert Jones bandage with the "U" splint in edema control of ankle fractures. MATERIAL AND METHODS A prospective, longitudinal study, open, comparative and randomized made in 32 male patients (72%) and 16 female patients (28%), the average age was 36.9 years. Patients with an ankle fracture within 12 hours of evolution were registered. Both ankles previous to immobilization were measured, dividing the patients in 2 groups. Group 1 were treated with Robert Jones Bandage, and group 2 with "U" splint. The pain previous to immobilization was registered using an analogous visual scale. Twenty-four hours later the circumference and the pain was measured again. RESULTS Group 1 displayed less edema, mean 17.69 mm, in comparison with group 2, of 8.33 mm (p &lt; or = 0.36). Pain previous to immobilization in group 1 was a mean of 7 and in group 2 of 5.5 (p &lt; or = 0.3); 24 hours later, a mean of 2 in both (p &lt; or = 0.8). CONCLUSIONS There were no significant differences between both immobilization methods.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la utilidad del vendaje tipo Robert Jones y la férula en "U" en las fracturas de tobillo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison between Robert Jones dressing and "U" splint in ankle fractures].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
