<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1867919</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ballesta-Vicente, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colina, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castellano, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blasco, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galvao, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casis, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solís-Herruzo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We reviewed retrospectively 120 patients with histologically diagnosed gallbladder carcinoma and collected during 16-years (1974-1989). Age and sex, annual distribution, predisposing factors, histological findings, clinical manifestations, complementary diagnostic methods, therapeutic measures and follow-up of patients were analyzed. Our results suggest the following conclusions: a) the annual incidence of gallbladder carcinoma remains unchanged; b) there is a close association with gallstones; c) the late diagnosis is due to unspecificity of clinical manifestations and low diagnostic effectivity of complementary methods; d) computed tomography and laparoscopy are the more effective complementary diagnostic methods in advanced gallbladder carcinoma; e) early gallbladder carcinoma is only diagnosed casually in cholecystectomy pieces; f) only the early carcinoma (grade I or II) is curable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de dieciséis años en cáncer de vesícula biliar. Revisión de 120 casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sixteen-year experience with gallbladder cancer. Review of 120 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
