<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18697442</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Varela, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carranza Lira, Sebastián</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Learning can be divided in two types: the unconscious learning and the significant learning. The critical aptitude for reading clinical research articles is a learning experience that reflects the doctor's active participation in article reading. OBJECTIVE To know the degree of aptitude for critical reading of clinical research articles in specialists under training. MATERIAL AND METHODS To all the specialist that were under training in the different services of the Hospital, a previous validated evaluation instrument for critical reading of clinical research studies was applied. Kruskal-Wallis and Mann-Whitney's U test were used for statistical analysis. RESULTS After the application of the evaluation instrument, it was found that the global score had a median of 42.5 (12-89) points. In the results obtained by indicator it was found that there was a greater score for to interpret, than for to judge and for to propose. In the analysis of domain degrees according to the interpret indicator, the greater proportion was in low level. According to the indicators to judge and to propose, most of the results were in the by chance expected level. CONCLUSION The critical reading aptitude it's not developed in specialized physicians that are under training. The development of this aptitude will allow them to have a greater profit in their courses.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aptitud para la lectura crítica de estudios de investigación clínica en médicos especialistas en adiestramiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Critical reading aptitude of clinical research texts in teaching specialist doctors].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
