<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18705187</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Albacete, Mariano Pérez</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES With the occasion of the centenary of the birth of Dr. Enrique Pérez Castro, founder, first director and editor of the journal Archivos Españoles de Urología, at this time when the issue No. 61 comes out, we performed a historic study of the evolution of the journal throughout the 36 years it was ruled by him, between April 1944 and December 1980. METHODS/RESULTS Complete review of the 158 issues, together with three extraordinary issues, included in the 31 volumes edited in the period Dr. Pérez Castro directed it. CONCLUSIONS The journal, senior journal in Spanish Urology, developed its main objective of being the communication and knowledge exchange media, with the exposition of scientific works, among the members of the Spanish urological community who admitted it with interest and complete acceptation. The work and devotion of Dr. Pérez Castro as director conferred the journal a great quality and achieved to join it to the Spanish Association of Urology, which demonstrated its category and reinforced its diffusion, acceptation and continuity. It is by itself an exceptional document and splendid historic synopsis of our urology over the second half of the 20th century.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Biography</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Archivos Españoles de Urología. Dirección de Enrique Pérez Castro (1944-1980).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Archivos Españoles de Urología. Enrique Pérez Castro's direction (1944-1980)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
