<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18717271</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zavala-Jaspe, Reinaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alarcón-Noya, Belkisyolé</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Bello, Zoraida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, Erika</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rangel-Lujano, Marieli</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abdul-Hadi, Salha</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueira, Ivonne</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paragonimiasis is a zoonosis affecting wild and domestic animals and human beings, caused by species of trematodes of the genus Paragonimus. Humans become infected after ingestion of raw or poorly cooked fresh water crustaceans. The aim of the present work is the description of a case of a 3-years old child, coming from Guárico State in Venezuela with a year of residence in the seashore of the Provincia Manabí in Ecuador, where he ate crabs in "ceviche". During hospitalization, he presented respiratory distress, hepatomegaly and nodules in the back. The thorax cat scan showed heavy infiltrate in both pulmonary bases and pleural compromise. Based on clinic, radiological images, an eosinophilia of 47% (Eosinophils absolute count (EAC) 6.682/mm3) and the antecedent of raw crabs ingestion, pulmonary paragonimiasis was diagnosed. Paragonimus eggs were not found in sputum and feces. ELISA with crude Paragonimus antigen was positive and Western blot revealed recognition of specific molecules. After treatment for three days with Praziquantel at a daily dose of 25 mg/kg body weight divided into three intakes, the sintomatology disappeared and radiological images and number of eosinophils diminished considerably.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paragonimiasis pulmonar. Descripción de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary paragonimiasis. Case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
