<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18752362</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Repiso, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Grueso, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrobles, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Vela, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE the objective of our study was to evaluate the usefulness of endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS) for the study of the common bile duct in patients diagnosed with acute biliary pancreatitis, and to establish clinical and laboratory factors related to this technique. MATERIALS AND METHODS seventy-three consecutive patients with acute biliary pancreatitis were included in the study (31 males and 42 females with a mean age of 64 +/- 15) who were admitted to our department for biliopancreatic EUS. In all patients the technique was followed by ERCP with sphincterotomy, and endoscopy to remove stones when endoscopy revealed choledocholithiasis. RESULTS mean time from admission to echoendoscopy was 7 +/- 6 days. In 18 patients (24%) the presence of choledocholithiasis was revealed by EUS, and in 17 a sphincterotomy was performed. Choledocholithiasis was more frequent in patients with common bile duct dilation (55 vs. 14%; p &lt; 0.05). Thirteen patients (18%) showed severe acute pancreatitis. Fourteen (19%) showed complications related to acute pancreatitis, and one patient died. Four patients had a new episode of acute pancreatitis. No significant difference was seen in the percentage of complications between patients treated conservatively and patients with choledocholithiasis treated with endoscopic sphincterotomy (18 vs. 22%; p &gt; 0.05). No difference was also detected for the subgroup of patients with severe acute pancreatitis (45 vs. 55%; p &gt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS EUS is a useful technique for the selection of patients with acute biliary pancreatitis who may benefit from endoscopic sphincterotomy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio por ecoendoscopia de la vía biliar extrahepática en pacientes con pancreatitis aguda biliar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endosonographic examination of the common bile duct in patients with acute biliary pancreatitis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
