<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18755101</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Leiva Fernández, Francisca</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luque Hernández, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palma Rodríguez, Sonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segura Domínguez, Nuria</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Ruiz, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz San Basilio, José María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To evaluate the effectiveness of an intervention program on overweight to achieve a minimum decrease of 5% or a optimum of 10% of initial weight a year, and to identify the factors associated with slimming. DESIGN Randomized controlled trial. SETTING Urban health centre. PARTICIPANTS Overweight subjects over 18 years old (n=169), wanting treatment or referred by their doctor. They were randomly assigned to the intervention (n=95) or control (n=70) group. INTERVENTIONS Intervention group: yearly program with consultations every 15-21 days, using a low calorie diet, prescribing physical exercise, changing of habits and health education. CONTROL GROUP low calorie diet, seen 3 times/year. RESULTS The minimum weight loss was achieved in 6 months by 37.9% of the intervention group and by 21.4% of the control group. At one year, 45.3% of the intervention subjects and 24.3% of the control group reached this objective. The optimum loss of 10% was higher in the intervention group, but was not statistically significant. The minimum objective was associated with the intervention group (OR=4.5 [1.36-14.49]). It was also associated to the number of visits during therapy (OR=1.85 [1.50-2.29]) and diabetes (OR=10 [1.13-90.9]). CONCLUSIONS The intervention group had a loss of 5% of initial weight in the first 6 months, 16.5% more than the control group, and 21% more in one year. Achieving the minimum objective was associated with the intervention group, the number of visits and the diagnosis of diabetes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de una intervención terapéutica sobre el exceso de peso en atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectiveness of a therapeutic practice on overweight in primary care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
