<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18770934</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-6722</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanchez Carpio, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gerónimo, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martinessi, Víctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dibenedetto, Nadia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canavoso, Lucas</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND During years the treatment of the insufficiency of the ostial valve of the Internal Safena (IS) it has consisted of the resection of the vein by means of different techniques. OBJECTIVE To propose and to evaluate the results of the preservative treatment by means of tie and section of the cayado one of IF with preservation of the vein in Situ. DESIGN Prospective, experimental and observacional study. METHOD Between March of 2005 and May of 2007 47 patients were dealed with with varices of Inferior Members due to an insufficiency of the ostial valve IS. In all the cases it was made tie and section of IF at level of the cayado one with preservation of the vein in Situ in completely ambulatory form. RESULTS The 93.75% of the treated patients, refered the disappearance of the subjective symptoms, in the 6.25% rest the improvement was partial. There was no morbidity nor mortality inherent to the made procedure. CONCLUSIONS The ambulatory treatment of the ostial insufficiency of IF with preservation of the vein in Situ it demonstrated, in this initial experience, to be effective and safe.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia ostial de la safena interna. Tratamiento ambulatorio mediante ligadura con preservación de la safena in situ.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Saphenous insufficiency. Ambulatory treatment with ligation and vein preservation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
