<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18785787</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jaramillo-Villegas, Sonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pineda, Rosana Paola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montoya, Mauricio Marín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mesa Salgado, Victoria María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mideros, María Fernanda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lagos Mora, Luz Estela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cotes-Torres, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Late blight caused by Phytophthora infestans is one of the most limiting diseases in solanaceous crops in the world. This pathogen is a main constraint in the highland Andes, where these plants are grown under high humidity conditions and continuous cropping. The aim of this research was to increase the available information on the biology of P. infestans, specifically on its level of genetic variation in south-western Colombia, an area where various solanaceous crops susceptible to this pathogen converge. The study was carried out by using AFLP molecular markers with the restriction enzymes EcoRI and MseI and different primer combinations. Results indicated a low level of genetic variation among the 26 isolates evaluated, with only 18 polymorphic bands out of 135 amplicons obtained (13.43%), a Nei's genetic diversity index of 0.04, and a Shannon's information index of 0.06.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Sep 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad genética de aislamientos de Phytophthora infestans procedentes del suroeste de Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Genetic variability of Phytophthora infestans isolates from south-western Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
