<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18783705</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez-Peiró, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez-Peiró, J F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To establish the level of satisfaction and dissatisfaction with the service received by patients attending the Outpatient Pharmacy regarding the care received. METHOD Two-month long cross-sectional study. The study included all patients who had attended the Outpatient Pharmacy (OP) and had given their consent. Satisfaction was measured using a previously validated survey (Likert-type scale), with 5 possible closed answers (1: Disagree and 5: Strongly agree) and the Satisfaction Index established by the Regional Ministry of Health for the Autonomous Community of Valencia. Dissatisfaction was assessed via the complaints received by the Patient Service Department over the last 10 years. RESULTS Patient satisfaction survey (nfinal=138). Overall Satisfaction Index (SI): 76% (95% CI: 72-80%). Greatest satisfaction: Pharmacists Skills (SI: 88%; 95% CI: 87-88%). Lowest satisfaction: dispensing area (SI: 63%; 95% CI: 60-66%) and dispensing process (SI: 68%; 95% CI: 67-70%). Complaints (n=22). Reasons for dissatisfaction: dispensing process (72%) and dispensing area (10%). CONCLUSIONS Although the Satisfaction Index is a useful indicator for identifying improvements, the reasons for dissatisfaction are also required as a complement to this information. Those aspects in need of improvement are the dispensing area and process and increased structural and human resources are required.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la satisfacción y de la insatisfacción de pacientes atendidos en la unidad de atención farmacéutica a pacientes externos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of patient satisfaction in outpatient pharmacy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
