<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18783709</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Darriba, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peláez-de-Loño, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castellá-Rosales, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sicras-Mainar, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the comparison of the consumption of inadequate psichodrugs (PI) in institutionalized population. METHOD Before-after study, that includes ambulatory prescriptions (CatSalut) made in the nursing homes centers of a Sanitary Region during year 2001 (reference: 107 centers) and 2006 (comparison: 152 centers) respectively. PI was considered (Beers Criteria), 15/72 active principles pertaining to the subgroup-therapeutic ones: antidepressants, neuroleptics, sedatives-hypnotics and tranquilizers. The measurement of the consumption was made by means of the establishment of quantitative indicators in defined daily dose (DDD), packages and cost. Statistical meaning, p&lt;0.05. RESULTS Studied patients: 4,795 and 6,350 (years: 2001-2006, respectively), the global use of psichodrugs in DDD was of 1.508,061 and 2.286,347. The PI use was of 19.0% (confidence intervals of 95% [CI]: 17.9-20.1%) as opposed to 12.5% (CI: 11.5-13.5%). Increases of DDD / resident in some PI are observed: perfenazine (22.6%), halazepam (28.6%), amitriptyline (15.9%), clobazam (16.6%) and diazepam (6.6%), p&lt;0.001. CONCLUSIONS A tendency in diminishing the consumption of PI in institutionalized patients is observed, although its use continues being elevated. An excessive drug use exists with ant cholinergic and sedative properties, reason why specific interventions would be due to make, with the purpose of improving the rational use of the drugs in this sensible group of patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de psicofármacos inapropiados en residencias geriátricas: estudio comparativo entre los años 2001 y 2006.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Consumption of inappropriate psychotropic drugs in residential homes for the elderly: comparative study between 2001 and 2006].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
