<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1878158</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peñuela-Olaya, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinoza de los Monteros, A E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Ruiz, M E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is not sufficient information about the follow up of children belonging to mothers with some degree of glucose metabolism disorder. At The National Institute of Perinatology were studied 151 newborn. The babies were divided into four groups. The group 1 consisting of babies born from mothers with diabetes mellitus type I; group 2 of babies born from mothers with diabetes mellitus type II; group 3 including babies from mother with gestational diabetes and group 4 babies from mothers who presented alteration in glucose metabolism during pregnancy. After the evaluation of the somatic indicator we found an harmonic behavior in group 3 in weight, height and head circumference again. The most important finding was the low correlation in anthropometry at birth and one year of age. Finally we conclude that a strict control on the follow-up of the somatic growth of children, must be achieved because the hypertrophy during the first year of age depends on sociocultural and economic patterns.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil antropométrico evolutivo del hijo de madre con alteración en el metabolismo de la glucosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The evolutionary anthropometric profile of the child of a mother with a change in glucose metabolism].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
