<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18798451</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Apaza, Diana Huanco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rendón, Manuel Ticona</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Fetal grow evaluation is decisive to predict some grow problems and to consider high-risk pregnancies attention outcomes. OBJECTIVE To obtain fetal grow curves of a selected group of Peruvian newborns. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective and transversal study with successive enrolment of living newborns. Weighing and measurement techniques standardization in newborns was made by Centro Latinoamericano de Perinatologia's guidelines, as gestational age determination alike, based in date of last menstruation. Patients with some maternal-fetal condition that changes fetal grow were excluded, and smokers and undernourished too. Mean, standard deviation, 10, 50 and 90-weight percentile, height, and cephalic perimeter were used. Curves were traced and smoothed by third grade polynomial adjustment in Excel software. RESULTS During 2005 there were born 99,439 Peruvians, in 29 hospitals of Ministerio de Salud de Perú. Dates from 50,568 (50.8%) newborns were used to trace curves of fetal grow from 24 to 43 weeks of gestation. Weeks 39 and 40 of gestation were the most representative (55.8%), with a weigh average of 3,295 g +/- 407 g, and 3,400 +/- 421 g, respectively (10, 50, and 90-percentile were: 2,750; 3,275; 3,810, and 2,875; 3,385, and 3,930 g, respectively). Average birth size was: 49.7 cm +/- 2.3, and 50.1 +/- 2.3, respectively. Cephalic perimeter was: 342 +/- 16, and 345 +/- 13 mm, respectively. CONCLUSIONS Fetal grow curves according to weight, size, and cephalic perimeter from a selected group of Peruvian newborns were reported.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Curvas de crecimiento fetal de niños peruanos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Peruvian newborn fetal growing curves].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
