<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18842234</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cantón, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Vázquez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oteo, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campos, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro, Ferran</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coque, Teresa M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Curiao, Tânia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nicolau, Carlos Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moyá, Bartolomé</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diestra, Karol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miró, Elisenda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliver, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The epidemiological distribution of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL) types in Escherichia coli and Klebsiella pneumoniae was evaluated in various hospitals in Spain and compared with previous studies. METHODS A total of 11 Spanish hospitals participated in this study. Each center collected the first 15 isolates of E. coli and the first 5 of K. pneumoniae suspected of being ESBL-producers and isolated during the first quarter of 2004. Clonal study was done by PFGE after total DNA digestion with XbaI and by ERIC-PCR (Enterobacterial Repetitive Intergenic Consensus Sequences-Polymerase Chain Reaction), typing. ESBL-producers were characterized by isoelectric focusing (IEF), PCR and sequencing. RESULTS A total of 124 strains were collected. PFGE restriction patterns showed considerable diversity among E. coli strains; 4 clusters of 2 strains each were detected. ESBL characterization of 92 E. coli strains showed a predominance of CTX-M-14 (45.7%), CTX-M-9 (20.6%) and SHV-12 (21.7%). Clonal diversity among the 32 K. pneumoniae strains was less pronounced than in E. coli; 3 clusters included 53.1% of strains. The ESBL detected in these strains included a CTX-M type in 20 cases (62.5%) (CTX-M-1, CTX-M-9, CTX-M-14 and CTX-M-15); a SHV type in 11 (34.4%) (SHV-12 and SHV-5) and TEM-4 (3.1%) in 1 case. CONCLUSION The E. coli and K. pneumoniae strains analyzed in this period displayed a greater diversity of ESBL than has been observed in previous epidemiological studies. Analysis of clonal relationships revealed a greater diversity in E. coli than in K. pneumoniae.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización y epidemiología molecular de betalactamasas de espectro extendido en Escherichia coli y Klebsiella pneumoniae en once hospitales españoles (2004).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characterization and molecular epidemiology of ESBL in Escherichia coli and Klebsiella pneumoniae in 11 Spanish hospitals (2004)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
