<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1893018</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Apellaniz Sainz-Trapaga, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Alberola, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soria Arcos, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Gómez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdes Chavarri, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Luengo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Costa, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">23 rabbits with Staphylococcus aureus methicillin-sensitive, SAMS, experimentally induced endocarditis (EIE) were studied to compare the efficacy of cloxacillin vs the association cloxacillin-gentamicin. Twelve animals made the control group and 11 the treated ones, 5 with cloxacillin-gentamicin and 6 with cloxacillin. The animals were treated 3 days, then, mortality, blood cultures at 48 and 72 hours and the title of the unit-forming colonies per gram of vegetation (UFC/g) were evaluated. The control group had a mortality of 100% in the first 72 hours, its blood cultures were positive at 48 and 72 hours and the UFC/g was 10,48 o 0.20. There was statistical significance between the control group and both treatment, in mortality, blood culture's positivity and the UFC/g of vegetation. This results confirm the similar efficacy of cloxacillin either alone or in combination in the treatment of SAMSIE and the effectiveness of the experimental model to evaluate antimicrobial treatments.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la eficacia de la cloxacilina y cloxacilina-gentamicina en un modelo experimental de Staphylococcus aureus meticilín-sensible.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Efficacy evaluation of cloxacillin and cloxacillin-gentamicin in an experimental model of methicillin-sensitive Staphylococcus aureus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
