<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18938686</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mendoza-González, Celso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Méndez, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Sánchez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Férez-Santander, Sergio Mario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estrada, Catalina Lomelí</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Reding, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastelín, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosas, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Attie, Fause</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzo, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association between arterial systemic hypertension arterial coronary disease has been demonstrated by cumulated evidence of several epidemiological studies. Hypertension is an important independent risk factor for the development of coronary artery disease, vascular cerebral disease and nephropathy. Important advances exist in the knowledge of neurohumoral and hemodynamic factors that come together in the pathophysiology of the hypertension and in the development of coronary disease that allow to establish better strategies not only of treatment, but also of prevention, with the purpose of diminishing the cardiovascular mortality. The spectrum of the coronary artery disease secondary to atherosclerosis is wide and the strategies of treatment of hypertension must be adapted to each particular case. The treatment of both conditions needs of specific limits of agreement to the conditions of the patient and the form of presentation of each one of these disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial sistémica en el paciente con enfermedad arterial coronaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevention and treatment of hypertension and coronary heart disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
