<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>18985598</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lozano, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, C V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT Depression is the most prevalent of all psychiatric disorders. The majority of patients respond to drug therapy and psychotherapy and electroconvulsive therapy are effective in a significant group of medically-resistant patients. Despite these approaches, there are still patients who remain severely disabled. For these patients other therapeutic options must be considered. The advent of deep brain stimulation has revolutionized the treatment of movement disorders. Because of its efficacy, reversibility and safety, the use of deep brain stimulation is becoming more widespread. As a result of our increasing understanding of the mood and affective circuits and their dysfunction in pathologic states, we have been able to identify potential targets for deep brain stimulation for treatment resistant depression. CONCLUSION Despite the limited studies on the role of deep brain stimulation for treatment resistant depression, their results have been positive and they have provided the base for future trials to investigate deep brain stimulation as a treatment for resistant depression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov 1-15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación cerebral profunda para el tratamiento de la depresión resistente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Deep brain stimulation in the treatment of therapy-refractory depression].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
