<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19030637</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez, Patricia F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cometto, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo, Bernardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bonetto, Germán</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salvatico, Estela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varela, Natalia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Every newborn infant is screened for hypothyroidism and phenylketonuria by blood sampling, during the first week of life, but there is not a simple and efficient method to reduce pain during the procedure. OBJECTIVES Prospective randomised trial, to assess if the administration of oral glucose, paracetamol or EMLA, given individually, can reduce the pain caused in newborns by heel prick, in an outpatient setting. METHODS Double-blind study in which seventy six healthy newborns at term were randomly assigned to receive placebo, oral glucose, EMLA in the heel, or oral paracetamol. Heel prick was performed to get a blood sample, and pain was measured by two independent observers, using two scales (NIPS and PIPP). RESULTS NIPS &lt;4: placebo (9/19= 47%), glucose (16/19= 84%), paracetamol (8/19= 42%) and EMLA (12/19= 63%); PIPP &lt;8: placebo (9/19= 47%), oral glucose (12/19= 63%), paracetamol (5/19= 26%) and EMLA (8/19= 42%). With the use of oral glucose we found RAR: 0.37 (IC 95% 0.09-0.64), RRR: 44% (IC 95% 6-67%), NNT: 2.7 (IC 95% 1.5-11). CONCLUSIONS The best results were obtained with the use of oral glucose, being statistically significant with only one of the scales. The administration of paracetamol or EMLA did not reduce pain. Other complementary and/or combined methods, added to oral glucose, should be considered daily to diminish this painful experience in thousands of children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención del dolor en recién nacidos de término: estudio aleatorizado sobre tres métodos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pain prevention in term neonates: randomized trial for three methods].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
