<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19031678</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Allen, Betania</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacio-Mejía, Lina Sofia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Avila, Mauricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lazcano-Ponce, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mortality due to cervical cancer (CC) has decreased in developed countries given extensive screening and effective coverage. In developing countries mortality rates due to CC remain high. Since the mid-nineties there has been a decrease in mortality due to CC in Mexico, which can be attributed to the increase in coverage of the Papanicolaou (PAP) (beta -.195, IC95% -.274, -.117) and the decrease in the birth rate (beta -.407, IC95% -.632, -.182). The use of the PAP in conjunction with an HPV test within the early CC detection program would have a synergistic effect; HPV testing should be combined with the Pap test. Primary prevention of CC is possible with the HPV vaccine. This vaccine will be an additional tool for reducing CC-related morbidity and mortality, but will not replace screening and treatment. To adopt a prevention policy that includes an HPV vaccine we will need to: determine the burden of HPV-related disease; have sufficient epidemiological evidence and data about technical aspects of the vaccine; take into account the psyschosocial and ethical aspects of the vaccine and guarantee good organization of vaccine implementation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2006 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retos en la implementación de estrategias de prevención primaria y secundaria del cáncer cervical en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Challenges to implement strategies for the primary and secondary prevention of cervical cancer in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
