<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19040163</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lanzas Prieto, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Terrazas Hontañon, Jesús María</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Diego Rodríguez, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rado Velázquez, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Castrillo, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galindo Palazuelos, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To report one case of postoperative lateral femoral neuropathy presenting after a retropubic radical prostatectomy. We review the topic. METHODS We describe the case of a 72-year-old patient undergoing radical prostatectomy. Combined anesthesia, general and spinal, was given. A self-retaining automatic retractor (Omnitract) was employed. In the immediate postoperative period the patient presented bilateral femoral neuropathy, with difficulties for knees extension and hips flexion, diminished patellar reflex, and absence of sensitivity in the anterior area of the thighs. MRI was performed to rule out spinal pathology. RESULTS The symptoms improved a lot within a week, completely recovering after two months. CONCLUSIONS Femoral neuropathy is a rare complication after pelvic surgery. In our case we believe it was secondary to nerve compression by the retractor.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía femoral bilateral tras prostatectomía. Presentación de un caso y revisión del tema.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bilateral femoral neuropathy after prostatectomy. Case report and bibliographic review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
