<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19071886</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salavert, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pemán, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zaragoza, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnostic and therapeutic approaches to IFI have changed significantly in recent years, fostered by the introduction of new diagnostic methods and new antifungal products. The diagnosis of invasive candidiasis (IC) involves both clinical and laboratory parameters, but neither of these are specific and the majority of the yeast isolated showed only colonization but not true infection. This situation occurs in critical care setting especially when surgical drainages are used. A substantial number of patients become colonized with Candida spp. after abdominal surgery, but only a minority subsequently develops invasive candidiasis. The clinical and microbiological diagnosis of Candida peritonitis remains problematic. It is still unclear which patients with may benefit from antifungal treatment. Antifungal therapy can be suggested in critically ill patients with peritonitis where Candida is diagnosed based on perioperatively sampled peritoneal fluid. Since fungal infection is also a relatively common complication of severe pancreatitis it seems reasonable that fungal prophylaxis may be an important component of management although actually there is no evidence to support this approach. However, the high mortality associated with IC is partly correlated to the difficulties of making an early diagnosis, thus, to improve earlier diagnosis and survival of IC, new nonculture-based microbiological tools such as Candida albicans germ tube antibodies (CAGTA) and/or polymerase chain reaction (PCR) techniques for the detection of fungal-specific DNA should be used in conjunction with recent published "Candida score" prediction rule. An algorithm based on this approach has been provided to assess early treatment in surgical patients with yeasts isolated from intra-abdominal samples.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Dec 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Implica el aislamiento de Candida spp. en muestras intraabdominales de pacientes críticos la necesidad de tratamiento antifúngico?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Is the use of antifungal management advisable in critical patients with positive isolation of Candida spp. from intraabdominal clinical samples?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
