<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19080950</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Espaulella, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bajo, Lorena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dalmau, Núria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arnau, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barneto, Matilde</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To detect the percentage of patients with dementia admitted to a psychogeriatric department, who have a high risk of falls, and to evaluate acceptance and compliance with hip protectors during their stay in hospital and 2 weeks and 3 months after discharge. MATERIAL AND METHODS We performed a hospital-based prospective cohort study. Risk of falling was evaluated on the basis of immediate bipedal standing instability or abnormal semi-tandem posture, a get-up-and-go test time of more than 20 seconds, or clinical judgement. Compliance during hospital stay was evaluated through nursing records and compliance outside hospital by telephone interviews at 15 days and 3 months after discharge. RESULTS A total of 115 patients consecutively admitted to the psychogeriatric department of the Santa Creu Hospital in Vic were assessed. Sixty patients (52.2%) were excluded from the study, the main reason being dependence on another person for walking. Of the 55 patients included, 44 (80.0%) had a high risk of falls and were candidates for hip protectors. In-hospital compliance was 80.5% (95% CI: 65.1-91.2). The most common cause of non-compliance was removal of the hip protector by the patient. Compliance after discharge was 64.5% (95% CI: 45.4-80.8) at 2 weeks and 57.1% (95% CI: 28.9-82.4) at 3 months. CONCLUSIONS A high risk of falling was found in a large percentage of patients with dementia who were not dependent on others for walking. Compliance was not a problem in the use of hip protectors in a high-risk population in the hospital-admission setting but was weaker in the community setting.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceptabilidad y cumplimiento en el uso de los protectores de cadera en ancianos con demencia ingresados en una unidad de psicogeriatría.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acceptability and compliance with the use of hip protectors in elderly patients with dementia admitted to a psychogeriatric unit].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de geriatria y gerontologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
