<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19087826</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rivas-Ruiz, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perea-Milla, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Las Mulas Béjar, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-López, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-García, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-González, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE We intended to ascertain the effectiveness and safety of oral solutions of magnesium and vitamin B(6) in alleviating the symptoms emerged during clinical exacerbations in children aged 7-14 years suffering from Tourette syndrome (TS). We also aimed to determine the mean and the standard deviation of such an improvement in order to estimate sample sizes in future assays with a control group. PATIENTS AND METHOD The treatment under investigation was administered to children diagnosed with TS, in accordance with Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, fourth edition -IV, under conditions of clinical exacerbation. The effects were scored on the Yale Global Tics Severity Scale (YGTSS) at 0, 15, 30, 60 and 90 days. RESULTS The total tics score decreased from 26.7 (t0) to 12.9 (t4) and the total effect on the YGTSS was a reduction from 58.1 to 18.8. Both results were statistically significant. With respect to the application of conventional treatment or otherwise, no significant differences were observed. No side effects were seen. CONCLUSIONS The treatment assayed is safe and effective in reducing the harmful effects of TS in children. Further studies are needed, with a control group, and evaluation of different doses of the drugs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov 22 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio piloto sin grupo control del tratamiento con magnesio y vitamina B(6) del síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette en niños.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[An open study evaluating the efficacy and security of magnesium and vitamin B(6) as a treatment of Tourette syndrome in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
