<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19087791</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navas Lobato, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Reyes, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peinado Peinado, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lurueña Lobo, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roldán Rabadán, Inmaculada</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Sendón, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE It has been estimated that up to 12% of patients with acute myocardial infarction do not present coronary atherosclerotic disease demonstrable with angiographic studies. We assessed the clinical characteristics and prognosis of acute coronary syndrome without ST-segment elevation with angiographically normal coronary arteries. PATIENTS AND METHOD Comparative retrospective analysis of 58 consecutive patients with this diagnosis and a sample (n = 59) with lesions in angiographic studies, analyzing demographic characteristics, analytical parameters, electrocardiogram, ventricular function and prognosis. RESULTS The group represented 19% of the totality of acute coronary syndromes, showing a lower prevalence rates of hypercholesterolemia, diabetes mellitus and no record of ischemic heart disease (p = 0.043 to p = 0.005). The presence of regional wall motion abnormalities was significantly higher in the group with angiographic lesions (76.3% vs 41.4%; p &lt; 0.01). In-hospital mortality rate showed a non significant trend toward to be lower in the group with normal angiogram (1.7% vs 8.4%). CONCLUSIONS The absence of significant coronary artery disease in acute coronary syndrome without ST-segment elevation is not infrequent and was related to a lower cardiovascular risk profile and the absence of regional wall motion abnormalities showing a trend toward better in-hospital prognosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características clínicas, epidemiología y pronóstico del síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST con coronarias sanas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical characteristics, epidemiology and prognosis of acute coronary syndrome without ST-segment elevation and angiographically normal coronary arteries].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
