<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19080885</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Miró Bonet, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alorda Terrassa, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallego Caminero, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miró Bonet, Margalida</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article is a continuation of two previously published articles in Enfermería Clínica that describe the clinical course of María, a 26-year-old woman with Down syndrome. The first article described the patient's admission to the intensive care unit (ICU) with a diagnosis of atypical pneumonia. During admission, the patient was completely dependent. The second article described the weaning process when the patient showed anxiety, which was favorably resolved. Maria was discharged to a conventional ward with a nursing discharge report that contained the nursing care performed during her stay in the ICU. The present article describes the patient's follow-up by the hospital-at-home team. The specialized team suggested to María that she continue admission with the possibility of being at home until she could be discharged and followed-up by primary care. The evaluations were performed in 2 phases: a first evaluation before the patient's return to home, in which the suitability of domiciliary care was evaluated, and a second evaluation in which care was planned with María and her family. A hygiene deficit and ineffective management of the family therapeutic regimen were identified. Both problems were approached by the specialized healthcare team within the context of domiciliary care, in which work with the family is essential.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de un caso clínico en hospitalización a domicilio: una nueva alternativa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Follow-up of a case by the hospital-at-home service: a new alternative].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
