<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19107305</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil, Leonardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cancilliere, María del Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Lucía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herbón, Fabiana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Little, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In the beginning of 2002 there were an unusually high number of sudden unexpected infant deaths. A prospective study was started to determine the cause of unexpected deaths in infants younger than 1 year. AIMS Investigate the possible causes of sudden and unexpected death in infants of Bariloche and surrounding areas, using a protocol created for that purpose. METHODS All infants under 1 year of age who died unexpectedly between May 2002 and April 2007 were studied. A complete physical examination, a thorough interrogation to the parents and an autopsy were performed. According to the findings a definitive diagnosis was made on each case. RESULTS During the study period 10 infants younger than 1 year died. One case was excluded because the autopsy could not be done. The mean age was 74 days, 6 were males. All died while sleeping and no sign of disease were noticed in any case. In 6 cases, the autopsy findings explained the death. In the 3 others no cause for the death was found. CONCLUSIONS The implementation of this protocol allowed to find out the cause of death in 6 cases, that could not have been achieved without the autopsy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación de las causas de muerte súbita e inexplicable en niños menores de un año en la ciudad de Bariloche y aledaños.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Investigation of the causes of infant sudden unexpected death in children younger than one year in Bariloche city and surrounding areas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
