<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19107313</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferraris, Jorge R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wainberg, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Briones, Liliana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zalba, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Rilo, Laila</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sojo, Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Turconi, Amalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grimoldi, Irene A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sepliarsky, Adrián</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The multicentric study of chronic renal failure, dialysis and transplant started in 1996 by the Nephrology Committee of the Argentine Pediatrics Society with the aim of knowing the development characteristics of children with this pathology. POPULATION, MATERIAL AND METHODS The study included children and adolescents on conservative treatment, dialysis or transplant who have registered any of the three modalities before being 19 year-old, since january 1996 to december 2003. The statistical analysis was made with the statistical software SAS; in order to calculate the survival curve, the method employed was Kaplan-Meier and the standardized height and weight z-scores were calculated. RESULTS In this report, there is data related to 710 patients with chronic renal failure, under conservative treatment 34.2%, dialysis 57.6% and transplant 29.5%. The end-stage renal disease incidence was of 6.5/million inhabitants. The main etiologies were obstructive uropathy 18.3%, reflux nephropathy 15.1%, hemolytic uremic syndrome 14.4%, aplasia/dysplasia/hypoplasia 13.8%, and focal segmental glomerulosclerosis 8.9%. From the patients on dialysis treatment, 62.3% were under hemodialysis, and only 37.7% on peritoneal dialysis. Live-donor sources accounted for 46.2 % of the transplants, with a 1-year patient's survival of 98.7% and a 1-year graft survival of 96.4 %, similar with both donors. CONCLUSION The results obtained, even though they do not correspond to the total population affected and the monitoring is still insufficient, allowed us to have a profile of the chronic renal failure in our country.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad renal crónica, diálisis y trasplante: Estudio multicéntrico: 1996-2003.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic renal failure, dialysis and transplant: multicentric study: 1996-2003].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
