<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1912152</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Suárez Rodríguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Piñeiro Amigo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros Tizón, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz Pedreira, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barreiro Barreiro, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzo Masid, M I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bandrés Gimeno, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A prospective study of the therapeutic use of oxygen in a general hospital was carried out. 120 patients who received oxygen during the first 24 hours of their admission were included. Oxygen was prescribed continually for 113 patients (94%). This was administered with a Venturi mask in 116 patients (97%). Medium FiO2 prescribed initially was of 0.29 (SD = 0.04). Basal arterial blood gas measurement was performed on 101 patients (84%). PaO2 was equal to or lower than 60 mmHg in 69 (68%). Arterial blood gas measurement control was carried out in 51 patients (42.5%). Of the patients with basal PaO2 lower or equal to 60 mmHg, 44 (64%) were submitted to posterior control measurement. 32 of the latter group showed PaO2 higher than 60 mmHg. We observed important deficiencies: increased prescription in patients with PaO2 greater than 60 mmHg; the frequent noncontrol of arterial blood gas measurement; the lack of correction of FiO2 when the initial application of O2 did not increase the PaO2 higher than 60 mmHg.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización del oxígeno como terapéutica en un hospital general.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The use of oxygen as therapy in a general hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
