<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19150019</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Márquez-Celedonio, Félix G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chávez-Negrete, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-López, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berlín-Lascurain, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Téxon-Fernández, Obdulia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín-Rendón, Sadoc</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective was to determine the effect of lifestyle modification on cardiovascular risk in individuals with prehypertension, which is defined as a systolic blood pressure between 120 mmHg and 139 mmHg and a diastolic pressure between 80 mmHg and 89 mmHg. A randomized clinical trial was carried out in prehypertensives to compare those who took part in a program involving dietary modification, physical activity and educational sessions with those who followed normal recommendations. Cardiovascular risk was evaluated using the Framingham risk score and the chi-squared test, the Mann-Whitney U-test and the Friedman test. The mean Framingham score in the intervention group decreased from 5 (rank, -10 to 12) to 3.5 (rank, -11 to 10; P&lt; .05) and the probability of a cardiovascular event at 10 years decreased from 5.29+/-3.88 to 4.24+/-2.86 (P&lt; .05). This improvement was associated with a relative risk of 0.30 (95% confidence interval, 0.11 to 0.83) and a relative risk reduction of -69.8% (95% confidence interval -89% to -16.9%). There was no change in control subjects. Lifestyle modification decreased cardiovascular risk in individuals with prehypertension.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia clínica de la modificación del estilo de vida en el riesgo cardiovascular en prehipertensos: estudio PREHIPER I.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical effect of lifestyle modification on cardiovascular risk in prehypertensives: PREHIPER I study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
