<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19174068</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Del Val Romero, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso-Tarrés, Carles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Ferrín, Pau</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Baranera, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fontecha Gómez, Benito J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) asymptomatic colonization is common in long-term care facilities, but the burden of symptomatic infection appears to be low. It is not usually known whether a patient is colonized at the time of admission to the geriatric facility. Our purpose was to determine the prevalence, characteristics and factors associated with MRSA colonization on admission, and the cumulative incidence of colonization over the following 6 months. PATIENTS AND METHOD Longitudinal and prospective study conducted over a 6-month period. All patients were screened at admission using nasal and ulcers swabs within the first 24h. Patients were screened also at the end of the study to assess carrier status. RESULTS The prevalence of MRSA colonization was 7.6% at the entry (25 patients). In the multivariate analysis, advanced age, recent use of antibiotics, prior colonization by MRSA, and peripheral vascular disease were independent risk factors for colonization at admission. With standard precautions, the 6-month cumulative incidence of MRSA colonization was 4.2%. CONCLUSIONS In our long-term care facility, MRSA colonization at the time of admission was frequent. Few patients were colonized during the study and no episodes of infection were reported. Probably, standard precautions, including hand washing and appropriate barrier procedures during the care of wounds, are the most useful control measures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan 24 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la colonización por Staphylococcus aureus resistente a meticilina en un hospital de media y larga estancia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evolution of patient colonization with methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus in a skilled nursing facility].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
