<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19174049</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Medrano López, Constancio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda Núñez, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moruno Tirado, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guía Torrent, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fields of pediatric cardiology and congenital heart disease have experienced considerable progress in the last few years, with advances in new diagnostic and therapeutic techniques that can be applied at all stages of life from the fetus to the adult. This article reviews scientific publications in a number of areas that appeared between August 2007 and September 2008. In developed countries, congenital heart disease is becoming increasingly prevalent in nonpediatric patients, including pregnant women. Actions aimed at preventing coronary heart disease must be started early in infancy and should involve the promotion of a healthy diet and lifestyle. Recent developments in echocardiography include the introduction of three-dimensional echocardiography and of new techniques such as two-dimensional speckle tracking imaging, which can be used for both anatomical and functional investigations in patients with complex heart disease, including a univentricular heart. Progress has also occurred in fetal cardiology, with new data on prognosis and prognostic factors and developments in intrauterine interventions, though indications for these interventions have still to be established. Heart transplantation has become a routine procedure, supplemented in some cases by circulatory support devices. In catheter interventions, new devices have become available for the closure of atrial or ventricular septal defects and patent ductus arteriosus as well as for percutaneous pulmonary valve implantation. Surgery is also advancing, in some cases with hybrid techniques, particularly for the treatment of hypoplastic left heart syndrome. The article ends with a review of publications on cardiomyopathy, myocarditis and the treatment of bacterial endocarditis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en cardiología pediátrica y cardiopatías congénitas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Update on pediatric cardiology and congenital heart disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
