<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19195436</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tuma, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barreiro, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soriano, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vispo, Eugenia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is common in HIV-infected individuals, especially if the route of infection is intravenous (e.g. intravenous drug use or blood transfusion). Prognosis is poorer in patients with HCV and HIV coinfection than in those with HCV monoinfection, mainly due to the immunodepression caused by HIV infection and probably also to a direct effect of HIV on the liver. Moreover, although antiretroviral therapy can cause liver damage, there is little doubt about the net benefits obtained with triple therapy in coinfected individuals, since suppression of HIV replication and immune recovery help to halt liver damage. However, not all antiretroviral agents are equal and those with the lowest hepatotoxicity and best metabolic profile should be used in coinfected patients, since hepatic steatosis accelerates progression of hepatic fibrosis and insulin resistance hampers the success of treatment with interferon and ribavirin. Tenofovir is currently one of the safest nucleos(t)ide analogues, due to its low hepatotoxicity and its lack of negative interference on treatment of HCV infection.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de tenofovir en la coinfección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana y el virus de la hepatitis C.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Role of tenofovir in HIV and hepatitis C virus coinfection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
