<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19205545</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Flores Molina, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastelín Hernández, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Valle Mondragón, Leonardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Sánchez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tenorio López, Fermín Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nagay Hernández, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ilarraza Lomelí, Hermes</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE The endothelial function is the cornerstone of several cardiovascular disease. In this trial we compared how the Nitric Oxide (NO) and Oxidative Stress (OS) serum levels, as surrogate markers of endothelial function, change in patients who received (or not) rosuvastatin during the first seven days of an acute coronary syndrome (ACS). METHODS Twenty-two patients with ACS (age:66 +/- 9 years, gender: ten female and 12 male) were randomized in two groups. Patients in the first group (G1) received the conventional treatment for an ACS, plus placebo. The other group (G2) additionally received a daily oral dose of 40 mg of rosuvastatin. We measured the blood levels of nitrates and OS in both groups twice: at baseline (admission to Intensive care unit) and seven days after. The statistical analysis was performed using the paired t-test or the Chi2 test depending of the variables. Statistical significance was considered with a p &lt; 0.05. RESULTS Groups (G1 and G2) differed statistically on age (G1=71 years +/- 10 vs. G2 63 +/- 9 years, p=0.04). After 7 days of the ACS onset, ON levels diminished on 21% (p=0.17) in G1, but raised on 24% in the group who re- ceived rosuvastatin (p=0.005), with statistically difference between groups (p=0.005). On the other hand, the OS, augmented statistically on both groups: G1 (17%, p&lt;0.001) and G2 (13%, p&lt;0.001), without any difference between groups (p=0.77). CONCLUSION The endothelial dysfunction in the first days of an ACS is accentuated, but with the use of rosuvastatina, the endothelial function improves. In contrast, the OS increase in both groups, without differences between groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del uso de rosuvastatina en los primeros días de un síndrome coronario agudo en la fiunción endotelial y el poder oxidativo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of rosuvastatin in endothelial function and oxidative stress, in patients with acute coronary syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
