<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19203121</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arilla Iturri, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artázcoz Artázcoz, Ma Angeles</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An external non-invasive pacemaker serves to stimulate the heart by means of an external connection, either transcutaneous or percutaneous. An external pacemaker is composed of a stimulus generator connected to some electrodes in a patch which is applied directly on the thorax wall and these have the function of transmitting electric current. To implant an external non-invasive pacemaker is an emergency treatment which is employed as a transitory measure. The correct use of this technique is based upon adequately placing its patch and on being knowledgeable about the pacemaker generator which can provide satisfactory results. This article hopes to provide nursing professionals with knowledge about this kind of pacemaker its placement and management. The authors describe all the steps involved use of this pacemaker; starting with prior steps, the correct placement of the pacemaker electrode patch, how to use the generator and finally a description of the necessary care after this pacemaker has been implanted. The authors emphasize the specific aspects in the use of an external non-invasive pacemaker by nursing personnel so that these are capable of solving the most frequent problems, thereby contributing to an improvement in the integral care a patient receives.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcapasos temporal externo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[External temporary pacemakers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
