<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19219258</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tarbine, Sergio Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliveira, Maria do Rocio Peixoto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costantini, Costantino Ortiz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guarita-Souza, Luiz Cesar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivetti, Luiz Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Marcelo de Freitas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bubna, Marcos Henrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Braga, Chiu Yun Yu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Stella, Francisco de Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costantini, Costantino Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The efficacy of pharmacological stents in decreasing the incidence of cardiac events is not homogeneous for all lesions or patient subgroups. OBJECTIVE 1) To evaluate the late clinical evolution of patients submitted to pharmacological stent implantation in atherosclerotic lesions of the left anterior descending artery; 2) to identify, among the clinical, angiographic and intravascular ultrasonographic characteristics, the ones predictive of cardiac event risk. METHODS From May 2002 to August 2005, 205 patients were treated with 236 pharmacological stent implants, guided by the intravascular US (IVUS). RESULTS After a mean follow-up period of 711 days, the rate of stent thrombosis was 0.48%, the same observed for acute myocardial infarction or revascularization surgery. The revascularization rate of the treated lesion was 7.31% and the general event rate was 10.24%. The event indicators, according to the multivariate analysis were the implant of more than one stent in the same artery, concentric lesions and the minimal intra-stent area measured by IVUS &lt; 3.88 mm(2). CONCLUSION Based on the data obtained, we conclude that the revascularization of the left anterior descending artery with pharmacological stent implant, chosen and optimized by IVUS, presents a low incidence of late events. The implant of two pharmacological stents for the treatment of long lesions was the main independent factor for the occurrence of late events. The final luminal area &gt; 3.88 mm(2) obtained in the small reference-diameter segments is an independent indicator of event-free evolution.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological stent deployment in the left anterior descending artery: late event indicators.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Arquivos brasileiros de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
