<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19213214</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Angélica-Barrera, Yaneth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basavilvazo Rodríguez, María Antonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Valencia, Marcelino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Montes, Alfredo Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mesenteric cysts are rare, it had been reported a frequency of 1 in 250,000 hospital admissions. We present a case of a 17-year-old female, attended at gynecology service with 8 weeks amenorrhea and diffuse pain in all abdominal regions. Without preceding pathological history of importance, menarche at 14 year, menstrual cycles of 30-45 x 5, nuligesta. She had negative immunology pregnancy tests, and sonography showed left ovary with anecoique ovoid area of approximately 15 x 8.8 x 7 cm. Physical examination showed a soft abdomen, depressible, with pain on the left side, where presence of a tumor of approximately 8 cm was perceived. Vaginal examination showed cervix of 3 x 2 cm, not painful to mobilization, uterus in a head position of 6 x 5 x 4 cm, a tumor of 18 x 10 cm was delimited in left salpinge, not painful to the compressedness. It was carried out a laparotomy with diagnostic of cyst in left ovary, but it was a tumor of 18 x 14 x 10 cm of cyst aspect that was dependented of mesenterious at sigmoid colon level, which could be eradicated without difficulty. Mesenteric tumors are difficult for diagnosis, and can be asymptomatic or to be suspect as cause of recurrent abdominal pain, abdominal tumor or acute abdomen. Unfortunately, it is difficult to establish the diagnosis with precision before surgery, still employing diagnostic resources of high technology, as sonography and tomography.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste mesentérico. Informe de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Mesenteric cyst. A case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
