<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19231725</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castrodeza Sanz, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernán García, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luquero, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Simón Soria, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eiros Bouza, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Padilla, Elisabeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz de Lejarazu Leonardo, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The aim of this study was to determine the weeks of high rotavirus circulation in Valladolid (Spain) and to compare the characteristics of hospitalizations and emergencies in epidemic and nonepidemic periods. METHODS The information sources consisted of the weekly notifications to the Microbiological Information System, the Minimum Data Set, and the Emergency Registry. Expected cases for 2006 were calculated using a previously developed model. Weeks with observed cases over the upper limit of the 95% confidence interval for expected cases were considered epidemic periods. Hospitalization and emergencies in epidemic and nonepidemic periods were compared. RESULTS The number of cases in 2006 was 42% less than the expected number. The mean number of daily admissions was higher in epidemic periods (d=1.49; p=0.01) and the length of admissions was longer. CONCLUSION The activity of the paediatric service increased during the epidemic period. Consequently, implementation of surveillance activities and prevention and control programs for rotavirus in hospitals would seem advisable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de ingresos y urgencias pediátricas en período epidémico de rotavirus en Valladolid. Utilidad de un modelo predictivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Profile of paediatric admissions and emergencies during an epidemic period of rotavirus in Valladolid [Spain]. Utility of a predictive model].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
