<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19272621</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calbo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puerta, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galant Herrero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martí-Bonmatí, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Picazo, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roca, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the usefulness of detecting at MRI an ovarian vascular pedicle or prominent vessels between the uterus and large tumors for determining whether masses originate in the ovary or uterus. MATERIAL AND METHODS We reviewed MRI studies from 80 patients with histologically confirmed pelvic masses greater than 7cm in diameter. We evaluated the presence of gonadal veins draining the tumors and the presence of vessels between the surface of the lesion and the uterus. RESULTS We detected gonadal veins draining the pelvic masses in 36 of the 43 tumors originating in the ovaries (84%); we detected vessels between the uterus and the pelvic mass in 30 of the 37 tumors that originated in the uterus (81%). The sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values for the presence of gonadal veins draining the lesion were 84%, 95%, 95%, and 83%, respectively, for ovarian masses, and 81%, 91%, 88%, and 85%, respectively, for vessels between the uterus and the mass in subserous myomas. CONCLUSION Evaluating the venous drainage of pelvic tumors is very useful in cases in which it is not easy to establish the origin of the tumor.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visualización por resonancia magnética del drenaje venoso en las masas pélvicas: una ayuda para filiar su origen.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[MRI visualization of venous drainage helps determine the origin of pelvic masses.].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
