<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1927644</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zudaire, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berián, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosell, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez de la Muela, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Castro, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguera, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robles, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isa, W</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ninety-nine consecutive patients with renal cell carcinoma in stages pT1-4/N0-3/V0-2/M0 were analyzed. Overall 5 year survival was 61%. Factors with greater impact on survival were: 1) degree of anaplasia (DI 73%, DII 47%, DIII 27%; p = 0.0005), 2) pathological stage (pT1-2 87%, pT3 39%; p = 0.0000), 3) perirenal fat invasion (pT1-2 87%, pT3a 60%; p = 0.007), 4) node status (N0 72%, N1-3 17%; p = 0.0000) and 5) veins invasion (V0 74%, V1-2 35%; p = 0.005). No difference in survival between V1 and V2 (40% vs 33%; p0.05) tumours was found. A multivariable study showed that the degree of anaplasia and veins invasion have a significant and separate influence on survival (p = 0.0000). Among patients with vascular invasion, those with no perirenal fat invasion or node damage show better survival rates than patients with capsular infiltration (62% vs 40%; p) and perform significantly better than patients with capsular invasion and nodal implication (62% vs 30%; p). No survival differences were observed between pT3b stages with venous invasion only and pT1-2 stages (p0.05). Venous invasion is not in itself of prognostic relevance; the prognostic significance of vascular invasion is directly related to the presence of perirenal fat invasion and/or nodal implication.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la supervivencia en el carcioma de células renales con invasión de la vena cava.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Survival analysis in renal cell carcinoma with invasion of the vena cava].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
