<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19278691</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Leta, Rubén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blázquez, Marco A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alomar, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pons-Lladó, Guillem</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros, Antonio J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pujadas, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE We aimed to establish the diagnostic and prognostic usefulness of noninvasive coronary angiography using multidetector computer tomography (MDCT) in patients with clinical suspicion of coronary artery disease (CAD) and a non-diagnostic exercise treadmill test result. PATIENTS AND METHOD Retrospective analysis in 33 patients evaluating the incidence of revascularization and hospitalization due to myocardial infarction or angina, and death. RESULTS There were obstructive lesions in 7 (21%), non-obstructive lesions in 18 (55%), absence of lesions in 6 (18%), and, finally, 2 patients (6%) had an MDCT deemed as non-evaluable. The follow-up was extended up to 21 (10) months. Events appeared in 5 (15%) patients: 4 myocardial revascularizations in the group with obstructive coronary stenosis, and 1 cardiovascular death in the group with non-obstructive coronary lesions. No events were recorded among those 6 patients without coronary lesions nor in those 2 with non-evaluable MDCT studies. CONCLUSIONS Patients with suspected CAD and a non-diagnostic exercise test present with a high prevalence of CAD when studied by MDCT and have a high incidence of cardiovascular events. The severity of stenosis as assessed by MDCT relates to cardiovascular events during the follow-up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 May 09 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coronariografía no invasiva mediante tomografía computarizada con multidetectores en pacientes con sospecha de enfermedad coronaria y ergometría no diagnóstica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Noninvasive coronary angiography using multidetector computed tomography in patients with suspected coronary artery disease and a non-diagnostic exercise treadmill test result].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
