<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19288693</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alonso Arias, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iglesias Rodal, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estévez, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morán Pí, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérula de Torres, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-rabadan, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bauzà Nicolai, K</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Carrillo, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To find out the opinion of Primary Health Care (PHC) professionals on the impact of the Preventive Activities and Health Promotion Program (PAPPS). DESIGN Descriptive qualitative-quantitative study. In a first phase the SWOT technique was used. In a second phase a 47 item questionnaire was designed using an ordinal scale. PARTICIPANTS Professionals of PAPPS health centre, PAPPS managers and PHC management, using the Autonomous Community, and the time of ascribing or knowledge of PAPPS as segmentation criteria. In the qualitative study 62 participants were selected by theoretical sampling. In the quantitative study, 198 professionals took part in the survey. PRINCIPAL MEASUREMENTS The assessment of the results has taken into account the responses to the questions formulated and by performing a crossed analysis between strengths/threats and weaknesses/opportunities. A descriptive statistical analysis of the questions in the questionnaire. RESULTS There is agreement in that PAPPS has greatly influenced the development of PHC, contributing to improving the quality of care, but it is also fundamental to try revitalise the programme, as the limited involvement by the professionals in the postulated preventive recommendations is its main weakness, due to lack of motivation and professional burn-out.. CONCLUSIONS According to the participants PAPPS has contributed significantly to the development of PHC in our country and has had an influence on professional practice by instilling a prevention culture that hardly existed before.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opiniones de los profesionales sanitarios sobre la influencia del Programa de Actividades Preventivas y de Promoción de la Salud (PAPPS) en atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Opinions of health professionals on the impact of the Preventive Activities and Health Promotion Program (PAPPS)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
