<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19280563</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barkley, R A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND AIMS A number of problems have been identified through research and clinical practice with the current DSM-IV criteria for the diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). This paper reviews some of these issues along with possible solutions for consideration in the construction of the criteria for DSM-V. DEVELOPMENT Issues related to the length of symptom lists and how best to conceptualize the neuropsychological constructs they represent, differing developmental thresholds for diagnosis for adults vs. children and teens, the criterion for age of onset, problems related to the current approach to subtyping, and the development of new items for the adult stage of the disorder are discussed along with other issues pertinent to the continuing effort to test and revise the DSM criteria for ADHD as a function of ongoing empirical research. CONCLUSIONS The present paper has briefly raised a number of issues that require some attention by the various workgroups charged with creating the DSM-V diagnostic criteria for ADHD.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Feb 27 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en el diagnóstico y la subclasificación del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad: qué puede pasar en el futuro respecto al DSM-V.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Advances in the diagnosis and subtyping of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: what may lie ahead for DSM-V].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
