<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19308747</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barberán, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Rey, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giménez, M J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the clinical experience with tigecycline in the treatment of infections caused by microorganisms with prevalent resistance mechanisms among nosocomial microbiota, as methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus, vancomycin-resistant enterococci, multidrug- resistant Acinetobacter baumannii and enterobacteria producing extended spectrum beta-lactamases. Most of articles found in the literature describe the use of tigecycline in the treatment of severe infections (sepsis and septic shock, nosocomial pneumonia and ventilator-associated pneumonia...) produced by multidrug-resistant microorganisms, in patients with multiple comorbidities (admitted in ICU, with malignancies, transplants and/or immunodepressed...) and in many occasions after failures of previous antibiotic treatments. Favourable outcomes with tigecycline are reported in most articles. However, an accurate global assessment is difficult since, in addition to the described confounding factors, there are concomitant or sequential antibiotic treatments in several communications, and lack of relevant clinical (as comorbidities), microbiological (as susceptibility) and outcome (different criteria by different authors) data in others. More even, the described series are retrospective and lack of control groups. Nevertheless the usefulness of this revision is based on the fact that in daily clinical practice the use of tigecycline will increase, since epidemiology of specific hospital medical units shows multidrug resistance among nosocomial isolates and tigecycline can be one of the scarce available compounds active against multidrug-resistant strains/clones.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia clínica con tigeciclina en el tratamiento de infecciones nosocomiales producidas por aislados con mecanismos de resistencia prevalentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical experience with tigecycline in the treatment of nosocomial infections caused by isolates exhibiting prevalent resistance mechanisms].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
