<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19386321</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gilabert, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conget, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giménez, Marga</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Carotid intima-media thickness (cIMT) and presence of atherosclerotic plaques were evaluated in a cross-sectional study performed in a group of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1D) subjects from a Mediterranean area without additional cardiovascular risk factors. These results were compared to those obtained from a reference population. PATIENTS AND METHODS Twenty-two patients with T1D (age 34.6 (7.9) years) and a disease duration of 15.3 (5.9) years) were included. B-mode IMT measurements were used to evaluate cIMT and the presence of plaques. RESULTS A significantly higher cIMT and max-cIMT were found in patients with T1D in comparison with the age-reference population (0.52 (0.08) vs. 0.46 (0.09)mm; p&lt;0.001 and 0.63 (0.13) vs. 0.55 (0.12); p&lt;0.007 for cIMT and max-cIMT, respectively). The proportion of subjects affected by plaques within the group of T1D subjects was equivalent to the value observed in the 46-55 year-old reference group. CONCLUSION Even in the absence of major cardiovascular risk factors, subjects with T1D from a low prevalence CVD risk area display signs of an increased and accelerated preclinical atherosclerotic process.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 May 23 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aterosclerosis preclínica en un grupo de pacientes jóvenes con diabetes de tipo 1 de un área mediterránea.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Preclinical atherosclerosis in a group of young subjects with type 1 diabetes from a Mediterranean area].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
