<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>1943305</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mora Maciá, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocón Pujadas, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Blood pressure (BP) and heart rate (HR) show multiple oscillations. The aim of the present study was to evaluate their variability by means of a noninvasive device for the continuous recording of ambulatory BP. METHODS A 24 hour recording was programmed (minimal interval 30 minutes) in 190 individuals: 35 normotensive individuals aged 46 +/- 20 years and 155 patients with essential hypertension aged 49 +/- 12 years. RESULTS In the whole population a significant positive correlation was found between systolic BP (SBP) and its variability (r = 0.360; p less than 0.001). This correlation was found for both normotensive (r = 0.506; p less than 0.01) and hypertensive (r = 0.384; p less than 0.001) groups. There also was significant positive correlation between HR and its variability in the overall population (r = 0.374; p less than 0.001) and in the normotensive (r = 0.594; p less than 0.001) and hypertensive (r = 0.356; p less than 0.001) groups. There was a significant positive correlation between SBP and age in the whole population (r = 0.269; p less than 0.001) and in the normotensive (r = 0.448; p less than 0.001) and hypertensive (r = 0.193; p less than 0.05) groups. When the individuals were divided in those older than 65 years and those younger than 60 years, with same levels of SBP and DBP, it was found that the variability (given as standard deviation) of both SBP and DBP were higher in the older group (similar SBP: 19 +/- 7/13 +/- 4 mmHg vs 15 +/- 4/11 +/- 3 mmHg, p less than 0.01/p less than 0.01; similar DBP: 19 +/- 7/13 +/- 4 mmHg vs 15 +/- 5/11 +/- 3 mmHg, p less than 0.001/p less than 0.01). Multiple regression analysis showed that the most important determinant of this variability was the baseline SBP value, followed by age. CONCLUSIONS SBP and HR show a greater variability with higher baseline values. The variability of both SBP and DBP are greater in elderly patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Sep 14 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad de la presión arterial y de la frecuencia cardíaca en la hipertensión arterial esencial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Variability of arterial pressure and of heart rate in essential arterial hypertension].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
