<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19432360</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Esteban-Ledezma, Rubén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Treviño-Garza, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín-Peña, Oliver</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vilarubias-Guillament, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivas-Fernández, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Surgical treatment of femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) is becoming a worldwide current practice. In this work we describe our developed minimal-invasive anterior technique as well as the results obtained in our first 117 patients. MATERIAL AND METHODS We evaluated our first 117 operated hips in 115 patients, who underwent to femoroacetabular osteoplasty through minimally invasive anterior approach with a minimal follow up of 2 years. Hips were divided into 3 groups according to radiological Tönnis classification: 32 cases were included in group A (stage 0), 61 cases in group B (stage 1), 24 cases in group C (stage 2). A combined score method (Dexeus Combined Score) was used to compare these groups at 3 months, 6 months and 1 year and each subsequent year. RESULTS In 30 cases (93.7%) group A, 56 (91.8%) group B and 14 (58.3%) group C satisfactory result was obtained at 6 months, without significant changes over the year (96.8%, 91.8%, 54.1% respectively). After 2 years same behaviour was observed in groups A and B, exception made with group C (96.8%, 93.4%, 45.8% respectively). Differences between groups A and B when compared to group C were statistically significant (p &lt; 0.01). No statistical difference was observed between groups A and B (p &gt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS Patients improve in their clinical and functional scores. However these results differed in patients with Tönnis stage 0 and 1 when compared to Tönnis 2. Thus, it seems reasonable to recommend to symptomatic patients surgical treatment of FAI as early as it appears.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del pinzamiento femoro-acetabular mediante abordaje mínimo invasivo. Resultados con 2 años de seguimiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of femoro-acetabular impingement by a minimally invasive approach. Results at 2 years follow-up].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
