<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19448916</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8787</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Allen-Leigh, Betania</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Rivera, Leonor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Cerón, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Angeles-Llerenas, Angélica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ponce, Eduardo Lazcano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chavez Ayala, Ruben</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To estimate the prevalence and factors associated with sexual abuse in childhood and adolescence. METHODS Study conducted in a sample of students in the state of Morelos, Mexico, in 2004-2005. Participants (n=1730) were drawn from a cohort of 13,293 students aged 12 to 24 years. Data were collected by means of a questionnaire comprising parts of validated scales. The variables studied were: sociodemographic (gender, living area, socioeconomic status), family (parental education, parental addictions, violence between parents), individual psychological factors (self-esteem assessed using the Coopersmith Self-Esteem Inventory, depression, alcohol consumption), intrafamily violence (assessed through Strauss Scale) and sexual abuse. Multiple logistic regression assessed the risk factors associated. Odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals were estimated. RESULTS Of all students studied, 4.7% (n=80) reported attempted sexual abuse and 2.9% (n=50) were victims of consummated sexual abuse. Women had higher prevalence of attempted (6.1%) abuse; 3.6% of females and 1.9% of men were sexually abused. Main perpetrators were boyfriends in women and a stranger in men. Mean age was 12.02 years old among females and 11.71 years old among men. Factors found to be associated with abuse: high parental alcohol consumption (OR = 3.37, 95% CI 1.40;8.07), violence toward the mother (OR = 4.49, 95% CI 1.54;13.10), female gender (OR = 2.47, 95% CI 1.17;5.24), being a victim of great domestic violence (OR = 3.58, 95% CI 1.32;9.67). High self-esteem was a protective factor (OR = 0.27, 95% CI 0.09;0.75). CONCLUSIONS Overall sexual abuse occurs at the age of 12 in both males and females, and it is more frequent among females. Most victims do not report abuse.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores del abuso sexual en la niñez y la adolescencia en estudiantes de Morelos, México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors for sexual abuse during childhood and adolescence in students of Morelos, Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
