<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19462765</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Valdés Martínez, Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Roldán, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estrada Malacón, Ciro Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We performed a prospective study in 10 patients treated for chronic lateral ankle instability. Subjective evaluation was made with AOFAS functional scale. We included patients with subjective lateral ankle instability and clinical and radiographic instability tests, who persisted with symptoms after 3 months of conservative treatment. Preoperative and postoperative evaluation at the 12 and 52 weeks were performed in patients treated with a minimally invasive technique and arthroscopic for lateral instability. Mean follow-up was of 15 months. Six patients returned to previous activity level with no pain, three improved symptoms, and one did not improve after the procedure. Subjective evaluation with AOFAS functional scale reported excellent results in 73%, good results in 13% and regular results in 13%. We recommend this technique due to it is easily reproducible, minimally invasive, effective and helps the patient through a rapid rehabilitation process.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica en el tratamiento de la inestabilidad lateral crónica de tobillo con injerto autólogo de peroneo lateral corto por mínima invasión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of chronic lateral ankle instability with a minimally invasive technique with autologous peroneus brevis tendon graft].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
