<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19480766</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Everss, Estrella</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Muñoz, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojo Alvarez, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Requena Carrión, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Sánchez, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Alberola, Arcadi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdés Chávarri, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mechanisms responsible for the maintenance and termination of ventricular fibrillation (VF) are poorly understood. The aim of this study was to compare the spectral characteristics of the electrical signal during sustained and non-sustained VF in patients with an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator. The study included 51 patients who had had at least one episode of sustained VF (i.e., duration &gt;5 s and requiring shock administration) and non-sustained VF (i.e., duration &gt;3 s and spontaneously terminated) that were recorded by the device set in a unipolar configuration. Spectral analysis of the first 3 s of each episode was performed. The dominant frequency was higher in sustained VF (4.6+/-0.7 Hz) than in non-sustained VF (4.3+/-0.6 Hz; P=.01), while the other parameters were similar. Although the spectral characteristics of sustained and non-sustained VF were similar, differences were observed during the first 3 s that could be used in algorithms for the early detection of non-sustained VF.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spectral analysis of sustained and non-sustained ventricular fibrillation in patients with an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
