<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19496527</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González de Posada, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It thinks that Mutis chose for the doctor's profession, which he exercised as qualified professional of the Medicine in his time, though in an atypical way he was acquiring in the Spanish America the vocation of spreading the 'fundamental science' of the Nature (the physicist-mathematics newtonian philosophy) as foundation of all higher preparation, and he was dragging from his stay in Madrid a special botanical interest, mode that shared some of the intellectually more endowed doctors of his epoch; serve Linneo of example of the previous generation. The different medical activities of Mutis are catalogued: student of surgery in Cadiz and of medicine in Seville, graduate in Medicine for Seville and Madrid, professional with medical exercise in Cadiz, Madrid and especially in the Viceroyalty of New Granada, professor of Anatomy in Madrid, botanical pharmacological researcher, medical therapeutic author, reformer of studies of medicine, general consultant of Health of the Viceroyalty and academician of Medicine, all this, certainly, with the counterpoint of his dissatisfaction for the state of the medical science of his time.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Biography</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">José Celestino Mutis (1732-1808): su condición de médico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[José Celestino Mutis (1732-1808): his career in medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de la Real Academia Nacional de Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
