<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19505005</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Clavero Núñez, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We expose the regulations for the assistance to the normal childbirth that, recently, publish so much the Ministry of Health and Consumption (MSC) in a draft, as those of the Spanish Society of Gynaecology and Obstetrics (SEGO). Both coincide almost totally, though those of the SEGO deal with more aspects, advising a Clinical Route in order that it should be continued by the qualified personnel (Doctors and Matrons). With it one tries to simplify the obstetric assistance, to humanize it, in terms of the MSC. It is a question of relieving a process that, in general, is long and painful, eluding some troublesome practices that, in occasions can turn out to be unnecessary, as they are, among others, the evacuating enema, the electronic continuous monitoring, the shave one of the perineum or the episiotomy. All this carries in turn an economic very important saving, especially, if the epidural is avoided. We think that these measures can be accepted in very well selected cases, but that if they show themselves will constitute a setback in the statistical and humanitarian results of the obstetric assistance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2008 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas normas para la asistencia al parto. Un avance científico?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[New procedure for the assistance to the childbirth. A scientific advance?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de la Real Academia Nacional de Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
