<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19518016</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz-Torres, Yaneth</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Sámano, Virgilio Augusto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Félix-Espinoza, Faustino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyva-González, Félix Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valencia-Sánchez, Jesús Salvador</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To estimate the impact of an educational strategy aimed at developing critical reading of research reports among medical residents enrolled in a nuclear medicine course. METHODS We carried out an intervention study to measure the degree to which students developed critical reading skills in a one month period (May-June, 2007). We developed an instrument that included five summaries of research articles in nuclear medicine and 96 sentences that measured four indicators (interpret, judge, propose, and assessment of technical and technological aspects). The instrument's internal validity was measured using the Kuder-Richardson test (KR 20 = 0.89) stratified in five scores: very low (17-32), low (33-48), medium (49-64), high (65-80) and very high (81-96). Non-paramentric statistics was employed to determine significant differences. RESULTS At the beginning of the intervention, 0.80 of participating residents scored in the "very low" domain of critical reading even after controlling for a random effect. At the end of the study, 0.90 scored in the "medium" category. Results were statistically significant (p = 0.02). CONCLUSIONS The educational strategy tested, fostered the development of critical reading skills among a sample of nuclear medicine residents.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alcances de una estrategia educativa desde una perspectiva participativa de la educación en el desarrollo de lectura crítica de informes de investigación en médicos residentes de medicina nuclear.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Developing critical skills to analyze research reports in nuclear medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
