<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19526951</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rosado, Alexis Labrada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, Irene Enríquez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morejón, Maytee Mateo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canosa, José S Rodríguez</dc:author>
<dc:author>León, Mayda González</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almarales, Raúl L Castro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castelló, Mirta Alvarez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, Iris García</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viltre, Bárbara I Navarro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Yunia Oliva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Mercedes Ronquillo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Sensitization to three allergic mite species (Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus, Dermatophagoides siboney and Blomia tropicalis) from house dust in Cuba has been reported in different studies. OBJECTIVE To assess allergic sensitization to these mites in a north coast area of Havana city. PATIENTS AND METHODS A total of 210 allergic patients were selected, classified in two groups: from 1 to 14 years, and from 15 to 55 years. Skin Prick Test (SPT) was performed on all patients using standardized allergenic extracts VALERGEN-BT (B. tropicalis), VALERGEN-DS (D. siboney) and VALERGEN-DP (D. pteronyssinus) manufactured by BIOCEN, Cuba. The test was considered positive when the average wheal diameter was greater or equal to 3 mm. RESULTS Both groups showed higher sensitization to D. pteronyssinus (&gt;78%), while for the remaining mites it was below 60%. In patients older than 14 years, the sensitization was apparently higher, although not statistically significant (p &gt; 0.05). Nevertheless, the skin reactivity in this group was significantly greater (p &lt; 0.05) for the three allergens. Unusually, mean wheal size in both groups was significantly superior toward B. tropicalis (p &lt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS In spite of being D. pteronyssinus the mite showing the highest sensitization, Blomia tropicalis showed to be also an important aeroallergen with more than 50% sensitization and greater skin reactivity. Therefore, in our population it would be advisable to perform SPT with the three mites extracts, simultaneously and to combine it in allergen-specific immunotherapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilización a tres especies de acaros en pacientes alérgicos de la zona costera de la ciudad de la Habana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sensitization to three species of mites in allergic patients from the coastal area of Havana city].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
