<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19526955</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sisul, Juan C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Sandra N González</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cagnani, Carlos E Baena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borges, Mario Sánchez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zernotti, Mario E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Khaltaev, Nikolai</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán, María Antonieta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ivancevich, Juan C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Croce, Victor H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Noel Rodríguez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cepeda, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solé, Dirceu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bousquet, Jean</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gereda, José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rhinitis is the most frequent respiratory disease in most countries of the world. It is estimated that 600 million people suffer this condition. Allergic rhinitis is a public health problem at global level. Patients who suffer allergic rhinitis have from mild to annoying nasal symptoms which affect quality of life, cause sleep disorders, scholar and workplace absenteeism, and health expenditure. Rhinitis is frequently associated to co-morbidities such as sinusitis, otitis media, and especially asthma. Rhinitis is under-diagnosed and under-treated worldwide and also in Latin American countries. ARIA is the very first evidence-based guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of rhinitis with focus in its co-morbidities (2001), especially asthma published in 2001. In 2008 an update was published. ARIA recommends an integrative approach for management; including anti-histamines (second generation), intra-nasal corticosteroids, anti-leukotrienes and immunotherapy. It also provides a questionnaire to evaluate asthma and its severity in those patients suffering rhinitis. The prevalence of allergic rhinitis is quite high in Latin American countries and in recent years a great insight on the burden of this condition has been gained.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de rinitis alérgica y su impacto en el asma (ARIA 2008). La perspectiva latinoamericana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Allergic rhinitis update and its impact on asthma (ARIA 2008). Latin American perspective].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
