<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19579892</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gonz치lez-Segura Alsina, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rebollo, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ara침칩, Pere</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Health-related quality of life (HRQoL) assessment on female with urinary incontinence (UI) may be a useful indicator in the management of early treatment depending on the sort of UI which is dominant: Stress UI or Urge UI. The objective of the present study was to evaluate the HRQoL of female with mixed UI, comparing the impact of symptoms of Urge UI and Stress UI. PATIENTS AND METHODS This is an epidemiologic, cross-sectional and multicenter study. HRQoL of 1,100 women with mixed UI was evaluated using the Spanish version of "King's Health Questionnaire" (KHQ). Personal data of patients were also collected along with medical records and clinical data related to diagnostic and treatment of UI. RESULTS Urinary infection was the most frequent medical record found. Mean time since start of UI symptoms was 4 years and 44% of patients had been received some treatment for UI. It was observed a higher use of sanitary napkins (63.9%) than pantyliners (36%) and diapers (11.2%). Mean global score of the KHQ was 42.2 (S.D.= 18.7); higher impact on HRQoL was shown in dimensions: UI impact, Urinary problems and Physical Limitations. Urge UI symptoms cause higher impact on HRQoL than Stress UI symptoms (p&lt; 0.0001). The logistic regression model performed for global KHQ score showed that variables strongly associated were Urge UI, genital prolapse and coital UI symptom. CONCLUSIONS Women with mixed UI showed and important impact on HRQoL. This impact is strongly associated with presence of symptoms of Urge UI.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afectaci칩n de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en mujeres con incontinencia urinaria mixta.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of the health-related quality of life impact in female with mixed urinary incontinence].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
