<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19621174</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pino, María Inés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zarate, Aldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maiz, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ravest, Gonzalo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdivia, Gonzalo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarroel, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crestto, Marco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The health associated costs of obesity can represent between 2% and 9% of the total health costs of a given country. AIM To assess the impact of obesity on health care costs and absenteeism in a cohort of mine workers. PATIENTS AND METHODS Prospective study of 4.673 men, employees of a mining company, aged 49 +/- 7 years that were followed for 24 +/- 11 months. Total health care cost and days of sick leave were recordedfor each individual. The association between obesity and these variables was analyzed by logistic regression adjusting for co-morbidities, age and other variables. RESULTS Mean annual health care costs for obese workers were 17% higher (p &lt;0.001) compared to workers with normal weight and 58% higher (p &lt;0.001) for workers with severe and morbid obesity. Mean annual days of sick leave increased by 25%o in the obese (p =0.002) and by 57%o in subjects with severe and morbid obesity (p &lt;0.001). For health care costs the most significant predictors were: presence of diabetes mellitus (Odds ratio (OR) 6.21, 95%o confidence intervals (95% CI) 4.9 to 7.9), hypertension (OR 3-99; 95% CI3-4 to 4.6) and severe and morbid obesity (OR 2.55, 95%o CI 1.9 to 3-4). For absenteeism the most significant predictors were: presence of diabetes mellitus (OR 1.58, 95%&gt; CI 1.2 to 2.0), hypertension (OR 1,34, 95%&gt; CI 1.2 to 1.6) and severe and morbid obesity (OR 1.50, 95%o CI 1.1 to 2.1). CONCLUSIONS Obesity increases significantly health care costs and absenteeism.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la obesidad en los costos en salud y en el ausentismo laboral de causa médica en una cohorte de trabajadores.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of obesity on health care costs and absenteeism among employees of a mining company].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
