<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19627759</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Quesada Charneco, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary hyperparathyroidism (PHP) is a known endocrine disorder. Many years ago, the most frequent forms of clinical presentation were symptomatic renal or skeletal disease with moderate or severe hypercalcemia; however, currently, most patients have few symptoms and mild hypercalcemia. The last NIH Workshop on Asymptomatic PHP developed criteria for the management of this disease. Multiple endocrine neoplasia (MEN) types 1 and 2 are two genetic syndromes caused by different types of molecular abnormalities. PHP is the most common manifestation of MEN-1 and is the last feature to appear in MEN 2A. Parathyroid carcinoma (PC) is a rare neoplasm and an uncommon cause of parathyroid hormone (PTH)-dependent hypercalcemia. In this report, the treatment of PHP in MEN syndrome and PC are reviewed. Special attention is paid to a new class of drugs called "calcimimetics", which are powerful compounds that may be highly useful in the treatment of both conditions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperparatiroidismo primario en situaciones especiales: síndromes de neoplasia endocrina múltiple y cáncer de paratiroides.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Primary hyperparathyroidism in special situations: multiple endocrine neoplasia syndromes and parathyroid cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
