<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19622318</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gutiérrez Domínguez, María Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bohórquez Zayas, Cristóbal</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Fernández, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez García, María Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>García García, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An experiment was carried out with humans as subjects, aged between 7 and 53, in which a conditional discrimination procedure with compound samples made up by exteroceptive (colored geometric shapes) and proprioceptive stimuli (different ways of pointing at them) was used. Thus, subjects were trained to perform differently in the presence of each sample, and later to choose the correct comparison. They were then evaluated in a conditional discrimination with unitary samples for each one of the components of the previous compound stimulus (only behavior and only colored shapes). For this, a competition procedure was designed. Results showed that the exteroceptive stimuli exerted more influence over the chosen behavior than the proprioceptive stimuli. Results are discussed in relation to the importance that one's own behavior discrimination may have in the origins of bi-directional discriminative control.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencia entre estímulos condicionales propioceptivos y exteroceptivos en una tarea de discriminación condicional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Competence between propioceptive and exteroceptive conditional stimuli in a conditional discrimination task].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Psicothema</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
