<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19660840</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Clusa Gironella, Thais</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lacasta Tintorer, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casabella Abril, Bartomeu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrea Tárrega, Salomé</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Ortega, M A Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albiach Pla, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perelló Bratescu, Aina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To prepare and validate a tool to measure Basic Life Support (BLS) and semi-automatic defibrillator (SAD) skills adapted for use by health professionals in Primary Care Teams (PCT). To propose an updated version and demonstrate self-sufficiency of the team to use it in a training evaluation. DESIGN Validation of measurement tools. Study of reliability with repeated measurements after a training course. SETTING Drassanes Primary Care Centre. Raval Sud Basic Health Area. Barcelona. Spain. PARTICIPANTS A total of 37 voluntary resuscitators (all doctors/nurses), professional camera, medical controller, computerised mannequin, 6 evaluators. INTERVENTIONS Test preparation methodology. Cardiff Model 3.1. IMPLEMENTATION 2 filmed series (professional+domestic), of 26-25 "station type" simulations, separated by 1 month. A training workshop between series. Retrospective evaluation of DVD recordings (5 evaluators). 2nd series scored again at 3 weeks with a blind and random order filmed version. VARIABLES performances classified from worse to best execution. Psychometric analysis: Validity (content/apparent). Test-retest reliability, between-observer and sensitivity to change. RESULTS Compared to the Cardiff test (46 items) our 83 item test contained 38(46%) new, 34(41%) modified and 11(13%) similar. Between-evaluator reliability, excellent/good in 51/62 items analysed; Within-evaluator and between-filming reliability, excellent/good in all except 1 item; the test score doubled after the training course. A version of the test according to BLS-SAD recommendations is proposed. CONCLUSIONS On there not being useful tools available for Primary Care doctors and nurses, one has been prepared with adequate psychometric guarantees and proven self-sufficient evaluation. We propose the immediate application of the updated version for training evaluation purposes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Test Raval Sud para medir habilidades de soporte vital básico y desfibrilación en médicos y enfermeras de atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Test to measure basic life support and defibrillation skills in primary care doctors and nurses].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
