<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19722381</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Estrada-Flores, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-Ramírez, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra-Bravo, J Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lazo-Cárdenas, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toxqui-Terán, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juan-Martínez, Enriqueta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chávez-Fernández, Alejandro A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beirana-Palencia, Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Percutaneous closure of patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) is a well established technique. Our objective was to determine the safety and efficacy of the Amplatzer occluder for the treatment of PDA in children. METHODS From November 2005 to June 2007 we reviewed the clinical records of 39 patients (23 girls and 16 boys), with a mean age of 19.8 +/- 13.7 months and weight 9.2 +/- 3.2 Kg, who underwent percutaneous closure of a PDA with an Amplatzer device. The forty one percent of the patients (16/39) were &lt; or = 1 year of age, and 71.8 % (28/39) weighed &lt; or = 10 Kg. The age of children with body weight &lt; or = 10 Kg was 13.1 +/- 6.1 months (range 5-33 months). The morphology of the PDA was determined by a lateral aortogram and classified according to Krichenko. All the patients were followed-up with radiologic and echocardiographic control at 24 hours, 1, 3, 6 and 12 months postinsertion (median 20 months). RESULTS The PDA diameter ranged between 2.0 mm to 12 mm (3.6 mm +/- 2.0 mm) in the 39 patients included. PDA types according to Krichenko were: type A = 25 (64.1%), type B = 1 (2.6%), type C = 5 (12.8%), type D = 2 (5.1%) and type E = 3 (7.7%). Three patients had a residual PDA post-surgical closure attempt. Qp/Qs ratio was 2.4 +/- 1.5 (range 1.0-6.7) and the relation PSP/PSS was 0.49 +/- 0.18 (range: 0.21-0.87). Pulmonary hypertension was present in 16 patients (41%). The Amplatzer occluder was implanted successfully in 36/39 patients (92.3%). The procedure failed in three cases: 1) difficulty to place the device due to wrong assessment of the ductus size; 2) difficulty to advance the device due to angulation (kinking) of the releasing system; 3) migration of the device to descending aorta. The mean time of fluoroscopy and for the entire procedure was 13.2 +/- 6.3 minutes and 65.3 +/- 21.9 minutes, respectively. There were no deaths with the procedure. Minor and mayor complications occurred in eight patients, all of them but one, in children with body weight &lt; or = 10 Kg. In the 36 successful insertions an aortogram showed complete occlusion in 26 (66.7%), trivial leak through the occluder in 6 (15.45), mild leak in 4 (10.3%), and moderate leak in 2 (5.1%). A control echocardiogram 24 h after the insertion showed a successful rate of 82.1% (32/36). Complete occlusion of the PDA was obtained in 35/36 patients (97.2%) at 3 months follow-up study. In 4 patients the percutaneous occlusion technique did not result in PDA closure, and 3 of them underwent a surgical closure. On follow-up, 3 patients developed mild stenosis of the left pulmonary artery and two a mild pressure gradient in the descending aorta. CONCLUSIONS Percutaneous closure of PDA with an Amplatzer is a safe and effective technique. In children with ductus arteriosus diameter &gt; or = 2 mm the Amplatzer device should be recommended over surgical closure. The incidence of complications after the procedure is higher in patients under 10 kg of body weight.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cierre percutáneo del conducto arterioso persistente con dispositivo Amplatzer en niños: resultados inmediatos y a un año.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Transcatheter closure of patent ductus arteriosus using the Amplatzer duct occluder in children: initial and one-year results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
