<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19781724</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dueñas Sadornil, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina Infante, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Bermejo, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Gallardo, Belén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Alonso, Moisés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateos Rodríguez, José María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Octreotide LAR has shown preliminary promising results in the treatment of recurrent obscure gastrointestinal haemorrhage. PATIENTS AND METHODS Eleven patients with severe comorbidities were treated with continuous octreotide LAR 20mg once a month. No changes were performed in concomitant drugs. Haemoglobin levels, blood transfusions, hospital admissions and adverse effects were recorded every three months. RESULTS Median age and follow-up were 74 yr (65-86) and 15 months (5-48). Five patients were on acenocoumarol therapy and other five on antiplatelet drugs. Eight patients (72%) had diffuse small bowel angiodysplasia and 4 patients died during follow-up. Only two patients (18%) remained free of transfusions but it resulted for the first year in an outstanding decrease in the need of red cell packets (14 (9-49) vs 4 (0-9), p=0,002) and in admission days related to gastrointestinal bleeding (27 (10-99) vs 7(0-23), p=0,001). No side effects were reported. CONCLUSION Octreotide LAR is an effective, safe and comfortable palliative therapy for severe obscure gastrointestinal bleeding. Medical resources saving and improved quality of life may warrant its use irrespective of comorbidities or life expectancy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Nov 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Octreótido long acting release para la hemorragia digestiva en pacientes de edad avanzada con comorbilidad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Octreotide long acting release for severe obscure gastrointestinal haemorrhage in elderly patients with serious comorbidities].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
