<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19833412</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cañas, B Suberviola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Miret, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro, A González</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llorca, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miñambres, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze the prevalence and frequency spectrum of the most relevant diseases found in the autopsies of patients who underwent a lung transplant and died in the first month after transplantation. To evaluate the consistency of the pre-and post-mortem diagnoses, comparing them with the Goldman et al. scale modified by Battle et al. MATERIAL AND METHODS Retrospective and longitudinal analysis, comparison of the medical records and records of autopsies of patients who received a lung transplant in our center (University Hospital Marques de Valdecilla) from 1997 to 2007, who died in the early postoperative period (first month post-transplant). The discordance between clinical and pathological diagnosis was classified according to the classification of Goldman et al. and Battle et al. The Student t test for quantitative variables and chi-square for qualitative variables were used for the comparison of the groups. RESULTS The five class I errors are limited to respiratory diseases: 2 undiagnosed acute rejection, 1 bilateral pulmonary thromboembolism, 1 fat embolism and 1 hemorrhagic infarction of the lung graft. We found a significant difference (p=0.05) between days of survival of patients with group Class I errors (6+/-4.52 days) and patients from the group with no discrepancy (15.42+/-8.99). CONCLUSION The short time between transplant and death of the patient reduces the possibility of reaching a correct diagnosis. Because of this information, diagnostic possibilities must be maximized in life-threatening diseases during this period. Therefore, the rate of autopsy studies in this period should be 100%.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discrepancias entre el diagnóstico clínico y el diagnóstico anatomopatológico en la mortalidad temprana del trasplante pulmonar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Discrepancies between the clinical and pathological diagnosis in lung transplant early mortality].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
