<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19851649</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Reis, Amália Faria dos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abdalah, Rosemery Nunes Cardoso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saud, Claudia Guerra Murad</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dias, Arlisa Monteiro de Castro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leite, Rafaela Ferreira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Faria, Carlos Augusto Cardozo de</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribeiro, Georgina Severo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fiqueiredo, Mariana Ferreira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chilinque, Maria das Graças Leitão</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND There is evidence of the association between the apolipoprotein E (APOE) and coronary disease; however, there are controversies. OBJECTIVE To evaluate the association between the number of coronary vessels with significant obstruction defined by angiography, the APOE polymorphism and clinical variables. METHODS This was a cross-sectional, multicenter study with 207 patients (138 men), with acute coronary syndrome (ACS), in the city of Niteroi, state of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, who underwent coronary angiography and genotype determination for the APOE *2*3*4 polymorphism by the Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism (RFLP) method. RESULTS The frequency of the alleles was APOE *2 - 6.8%, *3 - 82.5%, *4 - 10.7%. Regarding the number of affected vessels, 27% of patients presented monoarterial obstruction, 33.8% biarterial and 39.1% triarterial and/or left coronary trunk. The degree of multivascular lesion did not correlate with the presence of the *4 allele (p= 0.78), but with age &gt; 55 years (p=0.025), being an ex-smoker (p=0.004) and dyslipidemia (p=0.05) at the multivariate analysis and also with previous coronary artery disease (CAD) (p=0.05), diabetes (p=0.038) and metabolic syndrome (p=0.021) at the univariate analysis. The prevalence of dyslipidemia, diabetes and systemic arterial hypertension (SAH) was elevated regarding similar studies, with progressive increases in the prevalence of SAH (p=0.59) and diabetes (p=0.06), according to the number of affected vessels. CONCLUSION The APOE polymorphism was not associated with the number of coronary vessels with significant obstruction at any age range. On the other hand, age &gt; 55 years, being an ex-smoker and dyslipidemia associated with the multivascular lesion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severity of angiographic coronary obstruction and the apolipoprotein E polymorphism in acute coronary syndromes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Arquivos brasileiros de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
