<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19889479</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cotta, Judit</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andrade, Raúl J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toscano, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robles, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lucena, M A Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Immunosuppressants are among the pharmacological agents with the greatest potential to cause adverse reactions, although induction of hepatotoxicity is paradoxical from the pathogenic point of view, since the response of the innate and acquired immune system is a key element in the chain of events leading to chemical liver damage. Hepatotoxicity induced by immunosuppressants is difficult to evaluate since these drugs are sometimes used to treat liver diseases, or in combination with other drugs that can also cause hepatotoxicity, or in the context of liver transplantation, in which rejection or biliary complications can act as confounding factors. In addition, immunosuppressant therapy can favor the development of infections, which by themselves can cause liver damage, or reactivate latent chronic viral hepatitis. Corticosteroids and calcineurin inhibitors only exceptionally cause hepatotoxicity. Methotrexate at high doses and in patients with risk factors can induce advanced fibrosis and cirrhosis. Thiopurine agents can cause a spectrum of hepatic lesions, including hepatocellular of cholestatic lesions, and hepatic vascular alterations. Leflunomide has high hepatotoxic potential, especially when combined with methotrexate. Anti-tumor necrosis factor-alpha agents have rarely been associated with hepatotoxicity, often with detectable autoantibodies, and most of the reactions - some severe - have been linked to infliximab, especially when used in patients with rheumatological diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxicidad hepática inducida por los nuevos fármacos inmunosupresores.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hepatotoxicity induced by new immunosuppressants].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
