<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19893140</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Holguín Prieto, Víctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pila Pérez, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Vargas, Etelivar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosales Torres, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pila Peláez, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To present a new case of adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis, the first report in our hospital since 1962. METHODS We report a clinical case with a brief bibliographic review about adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis. The diagnostic and therapeutic implications are discussed focusing on the role of ultrasound and immunohistochemical studies. RESULTS A 30-year-old man presented pain and inflammation in the left epididymis. Physical examination and ultrasound study demonstrated a tumor of 5x5x2 cm. It was removed and the histopathological study was compatible with adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis. CONCLUSION The adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis is a neoplasm located in the paratesticular region, however it can be found infrequently in other sites. Mesothelial origin has been mentioned and inflammation has played some role in the development of these tumors. Physical examination and testicular ultrasound constituted important tools in the diagnosis. It can minimally invade adjacent structures, though it is benign without metastatic potential. Some reports have mentioned malignant behavior, but it is very rare. Surgical treatment is the procedure of choice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor adenomatoide del epidídimo: una infrecuente observación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis: an infrequent case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
