<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19893867</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montes Berriatúa, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas Sánchez, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montaña González, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales Millán, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jáuregui Lobera, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bolaños Ríos, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Justo Villalobos, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Candau, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>León Lozano, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz Jaramillo, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE This study examined the presence of disordered eating behaviours and the influence that on them could have the degree of body dissatisfaction among adolescents. METHOD By the Eating Attitudes Test-40 (EAT-40), the Sick Control On Fat Food (SCOFF) and the subscale of body dissatisfaction (BD) of the Eating Disorders Inventory-2 (EDI-2) a total of 841 students, aged 12-19, were studied. Eating behaviours, sex and age differences, and eating attitudes and behaviours related to the degree of body dissatisfaction were analized. RESULTS We found that 21,29% had significant punctuations in the SCOFF and 7,13% in the EAT-40. There were significant sex-differences (13,93% and 3,23% in SCOFF and EAT-40 for males, 29,38% and 10,70% for women). With regard to previous studies, a decrease of the risk is observed in women and an increase in males. Major body dissatisfaction was observed among the 12 to 17-year-old girls, though sex-differences in eating alterations, can be mostly found between the ages of 14 and 16. Body dissatisfaction correlated positively and significantly to Body Mass Index, EAT-40 and SCOFF. CONCLUSION In order to implement primary programs in the adolescent population it is necessary to explore the eating behaviours of risky and the degree of body dissatisfaction to be able to raise specifically the interventions to be carried out, involving teachers as primary agents for the work in the school context.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta alimentaria e imagen corporal en una muestra de adolescentes de Sevilla.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Eating behaviour and body image in a sample of adolescents from Sevilla].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
