<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19897437</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Urinovsky, Fernando M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bagur, Rodrigo H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras, Alejandro E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estrada, Carlos D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non-ST elevation acute coronary syndromes (NSTE-ACS) are frequent cause of hospitalization, being responsible for 10-15% of infarcts or deaths per year. The study was designed to analyze 6 months follow-up of cardiovascular events as well as to validate the Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) risk score for patients hospitalized for NSTE-ACS. We retrospectively analyzed patients admitted with NSTE-ACS. Telephone follow-up were performed at 6 month. Combination of death, re-admission for acute coronary syndrome and revascularization were considered as end point. Two hundred and four patients were included for the analysis. There were 70.2% males, with a mean age of 64.5 +/- 11.8 years. After the initial evaluation, we diagnosed unstable angina in 34.6% of cases, MI in 38.9% of cases, and 26.4% of patients were categorized as "non coronary chest pain". Applying the TIMI risk score, 52 (25.5%) patients had low risk, 106 (52%) intermediated risk, and 46 (22.5%) high risk. The global mortality was 12.3%. We found a progressively and significant increase in the rate of combined events as the TIMI score increase (p &lt; 0.001). We conclude that in our population, the intermediated and high TIMI risk score was well related to newer cardiovascular events at 6 month follow-up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del score de riesgo TIMI para pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[TIMI risk score validation for patients with acute coronary syndrome without ST elevation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
