<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19900385</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González Segura, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rebollo, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arlandis Guzmán, Salvador</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Matres, María Justa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The control of overactive bladder (OAB) symptoms, without worsening voiding symptoms, has become an important therapeutic goal in the management of lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) associated with benign prostatic hyperplasia. The objective of the present study was to assess the prevalence of other associated LUTS in patients with OAB. MATERIAL AND METHODS Epidemiological, observational, cross-sectional and multi-centre study, carried out at urology clinics/divisions throughout Spain. The sample included male patients older than 40 who came in for a urology consultation with filling symptoms compatible with OAB. Patient data were collected from the clinical history (demographic data, prostatic disease, other urological and concomitant diseases, OAB and other LUTS symptom data, diagnostic method and treatment data) and from the interview with the patient (I-PSS questionnaire). RESULTS 1,754 patients were included in the study. Mean age (SD) of patients was 65.4 (9.7) years. 74.2% of patients presented a prostatic disease, mainly benign prostatic hyperplasia (90.6%); 8.4% had other urologic diseases and 67.4% had at least one concomitant disease relevant to OAB. 99% of all patients had had at least one urological diagnostic test, 78.4% had received some kind of drug to treat symptoms and 61.3% had taken hygiene or dietetic measures. Filling symptoms were more frequent (93.3%) than voiding symptoms (83.9%). Mean score in the I-PSS was 16.3 (5.6) points, symptoms scored as moderate in 1,153 patients (67.9%) and as severe in 463 patients (27.3%). CONCLUSIONS Most male patients aged over 40 years with OAB symptoms showed other LUTS which worsened their quality of life. Taking this high revalence into account, it seems necessary to manage these patients' diagnosis and treatment according to their symptoms.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de síntomas del tracto urinario inferior en pacientes con síndrome de vejiga hiperactiva. Manejo del paciente en la práctica clínica habitual.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of lower urinary tract symptoms in patients with overactive bladder. Patient management in clinical practice].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
