<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19915770</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galindo A, Héctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jara A, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez J, Elvira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez Z, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocqueteau T, Mauricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nervi N, Bruno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Besa de C, Pelayo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Betancur B, Maritsa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido S, Marcelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez V, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García V, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bertín C-M, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Melgoza P, Geraldine</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burotto P, Mauricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera L, Mirtza</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hematopoietic precursors transplantation is a therapeutic alternative for leukemia, some metabolic diseases and some immune deficiency syndromes. In its allogeneic variety leukemia eradication is based in the conditioning prior to transplantation and the allograñ effect against leukemia. Umbilical cord blood is an alternative source of hematopoietic precursors when there are no HLA compatible relatives available. Between 2003 and 2007 we have performed five umbilical cord blood transplant in adult patients in a University hospital. All patients had malignant diseases. Conditioning protocols were ablative in all except in one patient and in all, more than one unit of umbilical cord blood was used. Hematopoietic engraftment was confirmed in all patients and the main complications registered were infectious and associated to immunosuppression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante con precursores hematopoyéticos de cordón umbilical en adultos con neoplasias hematológicas en Chile: serie clínica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Umbilical cord hematopoietic precursors transplantation. Report of five patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
