<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19913951</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Letona, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Fortea, María Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aibar, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Escalante, Begoña</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vitoria, María Asunción</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olivera, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echezarreta, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Peritoneal tuberculosis (PT) is a form of abdominal tuberculosis that accounts for 1%-3% of all cases of tuberculous disease and often manifests with non-specific symptoms. METHODS Cases of PT diagnosed over a period of 16 years are reviewed and the epidemiological, clinical, diagnostic, and outcome data are analyzed. RESULTS Among 462 patients with extrapulmonary tuberculosis, PT was documented in 13 patients (2.8%), only one whom was infected by human immunodeficiency virus. In most patients, the diagnosis was established on histological findings. In 5 cases, ascitic fluid culture was positive, and the diagnosis was established by this method alone in 3 of them. A multidrug-resistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis Beijing strain was isolated in one patient. The remaining strains isolated were sensitive to classic antituberculosis drugs. Ten patients were treated with 3 antituberculosis agents and 2 were treated with 4 drugs. Eight patients progressed favorably and 5 died due to complications of their underlying medical conditions. CONCLUSION Peritoneal tuberculosis can develop without evidence of concomitant tuberculous disease. Histology is usually needed to confirm the diagnosis, and the prognosis is good with prompt treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Peritonitis tuberculosa: revisión de 16 años en un hospital general.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Peritoneal tuberculosis: a 16-year review in a general hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
