<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>19922832</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Del Val Gómez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallardo, F G</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Terol, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peraira, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION This study has aimed to establish quantitative normality parameters in the thallium-201 GATED SPECT and to assess the changes related to age, gender, risk factors and stress testing. METHODS A total of 427 patients with low pre-test likelihood of coronary artery disease were selected (45.5% men). The examinations were performed, by obtaining 32 25-second images on a 180% arc. The isotope used was thallium-201 and the SU SEGAMI software was using for the examination procedure. RESULTS Myocardial tracer uptake in each one of the vascular territories was: left descending artery 77%+/-4; circumflex artery 76%+/-5 and right coronary artery 70%+/-4 (P=.000). Uptake in the right coronary artery territory was lower in men (68.7% vs 70.5% in women, P=.000) and in the left descending artery territory in the obese. There were no gender-related differences in the post-stress ejection fraction for both genders (65.7% in men vs 66.8% in women). However, ventricular volumes were higher in men (end-diastolic volume 80ml+/-27 vs 61ml+/-22; P=0.000 and end-systolic volume 27.2ml+/-25 vs 19ml+/-8; P=0.000). There is an inverse relationship between age and end-diastolic volume. Smokers have higher end-diastolic volumes than non-smokers. CONCLUSIONS Quantification of T1201 uptake in patients having low pre-test probability of coronary artery disease and normal thallium GATED-SPECT in the RCA territory is lower in men. The ventricular function study shows that there are no differences in post-stress EF based on gender but that the end-diastolic and end-systolic volumes are higher in men.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuantificación del estudio de perfusión miocárdica en pacientes con baja probabilidad de cardiopatía isquémica. Valores normales de gated-SPECT con (201)Tl.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quantification of myocardial scintigraphy in patients with low probability of coronary artery disease. Normal values of thallium-201 gated SPECT].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
