<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20018539</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín-Ruiz, A C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arnau-Santos, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villanueva-Ruiz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Shimizu, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-García, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Torga, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION To evaluate satisfaction among patients attending the outpatient clinics of a Preventive Medicine Department and to identify any problems with the care they receive. MATERIAL AND METHODS We performed a cross-sectional study in outpatient clinics of the Preventive Medicine Department, at Hospital General Universitario in Alicante, during January 2009. A questionnaire was given to all patients after their visit. Patients were satisfied if the final score was &gt; or = 8. Socio-demographic variables were: age, sex, educational level, marital status and type of user (external or internal). chi(2) were used to study the association between these variables and satisfaction. RESULTS The response rate was 84.4% (119/141), 94.1% were correctly completed (112/119), and 82.1% had a final score of &gt; or = 8. The worst aspects were: comfort of waiting room, signs and wait time (percentage dissatisfied: 54.5%, 46.4% and 30.4%, respectively). The rest of the items obtained the following satisfaction percentages: medical treatment (97.3%), privacy of care (95.5%), information received (93.7%), easy next appointment (93.7%), visit length (92.9%), clarity of information (92.9%), to arrange the first appointment (90.2%), nursing treatment (87.5%), time to date of appointment (81.2%). Educational level was the only variable significantly associated with satisfaction. CONCLUSIONS General satisfaction was good, although aspects like waiting time and signs could be better, if changes were made to management of appointments and the signs in the Hospital Department were increased.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Satisfacción de los pacientes atendidos en una consulta externa de medicina preventiva.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Satisfaction among patients attending outpatient preventive medicine clinic].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
