<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20038972</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luque, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido Cantanero, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aparicio López, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Escribano, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo García, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Chronic renal disease (CRD) affects physical, emotional and social wellbeing of children. Renal adult and adolescent patients have a poorer quality of life (QL) than healthy population but few studies have been performed in children with CRD and appropriate QL measurement tools. OBJECTIVES To assess QL in children with CRD comparing it with healthy children. MATERIAL AND METHODS Cross-sectional study in 71 children with CRD and 57 healthy children with the generic health status tool MOSF-SF-20 answered by children older than 9 and their parents and only by parents when children were younger than 9. RESULTS Children with CRD have a poorer QL than healthy children with significant differences in general self-esteem, physical performance and physical activity and no significant difference in socialization. On the contrary they refer less pain and emotional discomfort than healthy population. Perceived QL of children by parents is also worse in CRD population affecting all but pain dominions. 9-12 years old children and their parents agree in all QL dominions while parents underestimate social function and emotional well-being when their children were older than 12. CONCLUSIONS QL in children with CRD is worse than in healthy children mainly in physical function and general self-esteem and agree with parents perceptions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida percibida por niños con enfermedad renal crónica y por sus padres.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Perceived quality of life in children with chronic renal disease and in their parents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
