<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20097454</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez-Ballestero, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Picón-Roig, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Juan-Gadea, Mari Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznar-Oroval, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Yepes, Marina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorente-Alegre, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maíquez-Richart, Joaquín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz-Muñoz, Blanca</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Bacteremia is one of the most important causes of morbidity and mortality in cancer patients. The aim of this study was to evaluate the diagnostic usefulness of procalcitonin (PCT), interleukin 8 (IL-8), interleukin 6 (IL-6), and C-reactive protein (CRP) in the detection of bacteremia in cancer patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS PCT, IL-8, IL-6, and CPR levels were measured in 2 groups of cancer patients who had fever: one group with true bacteremia and another without bacteremia. RESULTS Seventy-nine febrile episodes were analyzed in 79 patients, 43 men and 36 women. Forty-four patients were in the true bacteremia group. Significant differences in PCT (P&lt;0.001), IL-8 (P&lt;0.001), and IL-6 (P=0.002) values were found between patients with and without true bacteremia. CPR results were not significantly different between the groups (P=0.23). The cut-off point for PCT was 0.5 ng/mL and this parameter yielded the best specificity at 91.4%, with a sensitivity of 59.1%. CONCLUSIONS Among the infection markers studied, PCT provided the most information for diagnosing bacteremia in cancer patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor diagnóstico de la procalcitonina, la interleucina 8, la interleucina 6 y la proteína C reactiva en la detección de bacteriemia y fungemia en pacientes con cáncer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diagnostic value of procalcitonin, interleukin 8, interleukin 6, and C-reactive protein for detecting bacteremia and fungemia in cancer patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
