<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20096181</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rouprêt, Morgan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chartier-Kastler, Emmanuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Misraï, Vincent</dc:author>
<dc:author>Renard-Penna, Raphaele</dc:author>
<dc:author>Richard, François</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vaessen, Christophe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferhi, Karim</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The management of ureteropelvic junction (UPJ) obstruction has evolved over the past 20 years in response to the development of new technology. Open surgery is still the reference standard against which all other surgical interventions must be measured. The surgical approach has, however, gone through rapid changes, and the open procedure initially described has evolved considerably. Endoscopic and laparoscopic approaches have largely supplanted open pyeloplasty for the majority of primary ureteropelvic junction obstruction cases. Laparoscopic approaches provide a balance between a highly successful technique in all patients and improved postoperative recovery. It has been shown to improve postoperative outcomes with shorter recovery times and hospital stays, and to provide equivalent functional results with a success rate of 95%. Nevertheless, laparoscopic pyeloplasty is not a simple procedure. There are a certain number of disadvantages, such as the limited range of laparoscopic instrument movement, the two dimensional image, the unfamiliar hand-eye coordination and the relatively inefficient ergonomic position. Since 2000, however, robots have provided a magnified three-dimensional view giving a greater degree of freedom. This system has simplified suturing and has improved precision of the operating technique. However, the system is very expensive and, providing it is available in their institution, it seems easier for beginners to learn the robotic technique. Additionally, it has similar success rates (both radiological and clinical) to those obtained with open techniques.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional outcomes after pure laparoscopic or robot-assisted pyeloplasty.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
