<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20098799</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cayazzo A, Tatiana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez M, Magdalena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarroel D, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pedrals G, Nuria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez D, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Airola G, Gregorio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The work environment of an organization has to do with a set of permanent qualities that are experienced by its members. AIM To assess the work environment perception of faculty members of a Medical School in two different periods (2005 and 2007). MATERIAL AND METHODS A standardized survey was applied to faculty members and Department chairs of the academic units of our Medical School. The survey used the Likert scale from 1 to 5 and included 59 items, distributed in 8 factors. Additionally, there were two groups of statements, indicating the priorities for the School and for the academic departments. RESULTS In the study performed in year 2005, the survey was answered by a total of 399 faculty members (68%) and in year 2007, it was answered by 408 members (68%). The global climate perceptions were 66% and 68% in 2005 and 2007, respectively (ns). Among the dimensions evaluated, communications (p =0,62) and physical conditions (p =0,008) improved in the two years period. CONCLUSIONS The applied instrument was stable and useful to knowing the requirements of the faculty members and for improving the organizational climate.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clima laboral en una escuela de medicina. Estudio de seguimiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Work environment assessment at a medical school].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
