<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20128349</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez, Miryan Margot</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lavalett, Lelia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Múñoz, Nélida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardona-Castro, Nora</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The scheme Kauffman-White (KW) for serotyping of Salmonella recognizes 46 O antigens, and 119 H antigens, thereby permitting the characterization of 2541 serotypes. The serotyping is a useful epidemiological tool in identifying circulating serotypes and to characterize outbreaks. However, the method presents technical limitations, difficulty in interpretation of results and high costs. OBJECTIVE A multiplex polymerase chain reaction test (M-PCR) was developed as an alternative method for the identification of serogroups B, C2, D, and E of Salmonella enterica. MATERIALS AND METHODS The M-PCR detected Salmonella genes rfbJ of serogroups B and C2 and wzx of serogroups D and E. To standardize the M-PCR, reference strains of Salmonella serogroups were compared. Amplification of invA gender-specific gene of Salmonella was included as internal control of amplification. To validate the test, a blind study was conducted to identify by M-PCR 400 isolates that had been previously characterized by serology. RESULTS The M-PCR detected Salmonella serogroups with reproducible results (Kappa index = 0.95). The sensitivity of the test was between 98% to 100% and specificity between 96% to 100%. CONCLUSIONS The polymorphisms in the Salmonella genes rfbJ and wzx permitted the development of a method for molecular typing of Salmonella serogroups that was sensitive, specific and reproducible.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y validación de una reacción en cadena de la polimerasa multiple para la identificación de los serogrupos B, C2, D y E de Salmonella enterica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Development and validation of a multiplex polymerase chain reaction for molecular identification of Salmonella enterica serogroups B, C2, D and E].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
