<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20133176</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-de Paz, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fortes-Bordas, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Pedro-Elvira, Belén</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes two cases of wounds with different aetiology and dissimilar size which were treated with Larval Debridement Therapy. Two different techniques of Larval Debridement were used for each case: Free Range and BioFoam larvae. Observations and treatment were carried out in a Primary Health Centre in Barcelona, Spain. The application and observations were performed by two nurses with the collaboration of two family physicians. The Larval Therapy efficacy outcome was checked with an Ulcer Reverse Stage Scale (PUSH v2), by taking photographs and a Visual Analogue Pain Scale (VAPS) was completed by both subjects before and after the treatment. It was observed in both cases that the larval therapy caused debridement of all fibrin and collagen tissue, and the slough dropped to a normal level. As a consequence of this change the PUSH scale punctuations were improved. On the negative side, the therapy was associated with an increase in pain. The beneficial effect of applying Larval Therapy enables following a basic wound healing care plan. The larval debridement therapy did not pose any threat for the patients; they could go about their Activities of the Daily Life (ADL) without any change. These wound cases treated with larval debridement therapy are the first ones reported in the Primary Health Care field in Spain.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de dos casos de herida, con diferente etiología, tratadas mediante terapia larval desbridante.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Wounds with different aetiology treated using larval debridement therapy: presentation of two cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
