<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20133020</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Balsa Bretón, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mariana Monguía, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Alonso, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pey Illera, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paniagua Correa, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Penín González, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To perform a descriptive analysis of the clinical and diagnostic implications of (123)I-IBZM SPECT in the patients studied in our center for movement disorders suggestive of Parkinson-Plus Disease (PP). SUBJECTS AND METHODS (123)I-IBZM SPECT was performed in 46 patients referred from the movement disorders consultation due to suspicion of PP. According to their symptoms, they were distributed into 3 groups: 35 patients had atypical symptoms (AS) for Parkinson's Disease, 2 showed no response to standard therapy (NR) and 9 presented both factors (AS, NR). The results of SPECT were only assessed qualitatively. RESULTS The (123)I-IBZM supported the diagnosis of PP in 15(42.9%) out of the 35 patients with AS. The (123)I-IBZM was pathological in one of the two NR patients. Regarding the third group of patients (AS+NR), the (123)I-IBZM was pathological in 6 cases (66.7%). In 95.7% of our sample (44 patients), AS with or without NR was the main factor leading to suspicion of PP and the (123)I-IBZM was altered in only 47.7% (22 patients). Of these 22 cases, the final diagnosis was PP (with high positive predictive value) in 20(91%). CONCLUSION The study with (123)I-IBZM is useful in the clinical practice because it provides objective diagnostic information with implications for the treatment and prognosis of patients with suspicion of PP.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con 123I-Iodobenzamida en el diagnóstico diferencial de enfermedad de Parkinson frente a Parkinson plus.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Experience with 123I-Iodobenzamide in the differential diagnosis of Parkinson's disease and Parkinson-plus disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
