<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20143737</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Quintana, Ma Violante</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montesó Curto, Ma Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Up to present times, more studies in medicine have been made on the effects an organic disease can cause in the brain as manifested by depression but, among different health disciplines, researchers are carrying out studies on how the brain can affect the body and cause diseases. By reviewing various epidemiological studies, relationships among some chronic diseases and depression have been noted. The depression-disease order of appearance can de bi-directional. It seems that stress, depression and inflammation have the capacity to affect the balance of cykotines produced by the immunological system. Modulation of the immunological system by the central nervous system is controIled/mediada by a complex bi-directional network composed of signals among the central nervous system, the endocrine system and the immunological system. The most frequent diseases related to depression are chronic but some are acute: of the central nervous system, endocrines, infections. Chronic pain also seems related to this problem. Pain, fatigue or tiredness are considered symptoms of a hidden depression and others, physical as well as psychiatric, could be algias, parestesias, headaches, vertigo, or gastrointestinal, cardio-respiratory neurodegenerative disorders.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad en depresión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Co-morbility during depression].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
