<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20169218</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-Martínez, Farith</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Pedraza, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carmona-Arango, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Describing the occurrence of dental caries in preschool children from the Boquilla neighbourhood in Cartagena and relating it to risk factors reported in the medical literature. METHODS The sample consisted of 238 preschool children aged 3 to 5. Average age was 4.1. Regarding gender, there were 116 boys and 122 girls. The children were individually selected in a probabilistic way, bearing in mind the size of the population from the chosen educational institution; a questionnaire and clinical instrument were used. The data was analysed according to outcome using Odd ratios for bivariate analysis and logistical regression for multivariable analysis. RESULTS Caries prevalence was 60 %, mainly occurring amongst 5 year old children. The major risk factors observed were parents having not progressed to more than secondary level studies and a background of caries. A 26.6 OR was obtained at the moment of adjusting the logistical regression estimators for having a background of caries, 3.37 OR for daily candy consumption and 2.17 OR for non-exposure to fluorides. CONCLUSIONS The presence of caries in this population could be explained by means of the three associated risk factors mentioned above. This evidence may become changed when other circumstances, moments and places are involved in children having the same characteristics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores de Riesgo para la Caries Dental en Niños Preescolares de La Boquilla, Cartagena.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk indicators for dental caries in preschool children from La Boquilla, Cartagena].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
