<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20191983</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz-Hernández, Adela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar-Schettino, Paz Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Angeles, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bialostozky, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera-Bravo, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Irma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez, Clara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nivardo Sobrino, Ayax</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bucio-Torres, Martha</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the left ventricular function and the ventricular synchrony in patients with Chagas disease in latency stage respect to a control group. METHODS We analyze a prospective, comparative, transversal and non randomized study of the left ventricular function (LVF) and the ventricular contraction synchronicity (VCS) in 36 subjects with positive serology for Chagas disease (18 males and 18 females), with mean of 15 +/- 5-years-old. The findings were compared with respect to 23 control volunteers (11 males and 12 females) with mean of 28 +/- 5-years-old. LVF and VCS were evaluated using equilibrium radionuclide angiography images (ERNA). The comparison of both Chagas and control populations was carried out by t Student test for independent samples, considering a statistically significant value of p &lt; 0.05. RESULTS The parameters of the ventricular function and the ventricular synchronicity in subjects with positive serology for Chagas disease were not statistically different with respect to the parameters of the control group. However, although they have a homogeneous contraction, the mean time of contraction for the right and the left ventricle is statistically smaller with respect to the control group. CONCLUSIONS In clinically incipient stages of Chagas disease we do not found abnormalities in the ventricular function and the ventricular synchronicity. It's necessary to consider the follow up of the studied populations using indices for the identification of abnormalities of the autonomic nervous system.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la función y sincronía de la contracción ventricular en pacientes con enfermedad de Chagas en estadio de latencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the function and ventricular synchrony in patients with latency stage of Chagas' disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
