<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20204234</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Krochik, Andrea G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chaler, Eduardo A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maceiras, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aspres, Norma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mazza, Carmen S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Studies on people with low birth weight found metabolic syndrome associated with intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR). OBJECTIVE To study the presence of early risk markers of metabolic syndrome in a prepubertal population with IUGR. DESIGN We studied 45 prepubertal children with a history of IUGR, without apparent disease, and 47 children in a control group. BMI, weight, height, and BMI Z score, and body fat mass were calculated. Basal glycemia, insulin, proinsulin, cortisol, serum lipids and uric acid levels were analyzed. Insulin sensitivity was calculated by QUICKI and insulin resistance by HOMA-IR. RESULTS Basal insulin levels were higher in the IUGR group compared with the controls (6.6 microU/ml vs. 4.4 microU/ml; p= 0.008). Similar results were found for the basal cortisol levels (18.8 ug/dl vs. 13.1 ug/dl; p= 0.006) and uric acid (4.2 mg/dl vs. 2.7 mg/dl; p= 0.0008). QUICKI index was lower in the IUGR group (2.06 vs. 2.86, p= 0.001). The IUGR children who developed obesity presented higher levels of proinsulin (26.04 ug/dl vs. 13.3 ug/dl; p= 0.05), insulin (11 microU/ml vs. 5.5 microU/ml, p= 0.005), and HOMA-IR (2.06 vs. 0.9, p= 0.004), and lower QUICKI (1.71 vs. 2.16, p= 0.01) than in the case of the IUGR children with appropriate weight; these differences weren't observed among the control group. CONCLUSIONS Children with IUGR, without apparent disease, showed metabolic changes that were expressed through risk markers of metabolic syndrome in childhood.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores tempranos de riesgo de síndrome metabólico en niños prepúberes con y sin antecedente de restricción de crecimiento intrauterino.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Presence of early risk markers of metabolic syndrome in prepubertal children with a history of intrauterine growth restriction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
