<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20227733</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vázquez, José Manuel Valle</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barcala, Francisco Javier González</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dobaño, José Manuel Alvarez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuadrado, Luis Valdés</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is a chronic progressive disease. Its natural history may have episodes of acute exacerbation (AE-IPF), whose best accepted definition would be a clinically significant acute worsening, without identified cause, in patients with an underlying IPF. The incidence of AE-IPF ranges from 5%-19% of patients per year. It is estimated that acute deterioration of the respiratory status occurred in 47% of these patients before death. A rapidly progressive dyspnoea is the most prominent symptom, with associated cough, fever and flu-like symptoms. The diagnosis is strengthened by the presence of leukocytosis on the blood count, neutrophilia on the bronchoalveolar lavage, and development of new diffuse bilateral ground-glass opacities superimposed on the pre-existing radiographic findings. The major histological finding is diffuse alveolar damage. Methylprednisolone seems to be the best therapeutic option, although the treatment response is usually poor.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Apr 09 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exacerbaciones agudas de la fibrosis pulmonar idiopática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acute exacerbation of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
