<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20361150</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Herlramp F, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lavados, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uauy, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verdugo, Renato</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lera, Lydia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albala, Cecilia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND There is a correlation between aging and the decrease of plasma levels of vitamin B-12. AIM To determine the prevalence of vitamin B-12 and folate deficiency and its hematological impact among older adults (AM). MATERIAL AND METHODS Cross-sectional study, in 1028 subjects aged 65 to 87years, living in community and evaluated between 2005 and 2008. Percentile distribution of vitamin B-12, folate, hemoglobin, packed red cell volume and mean cell volume by gender and age were analyzed. Deficiency was defined as vitamin B-12 levels &lt; 148 pmol/L, marginal deficiency as vitamin B-12 levels &lt; 221 pmol/L, anemia was defined as a hemoglobin &lt; 13 and 12 g/dL among men and women, respectively. RESULTS The prevalence of vitamin B-12 deficiency was 12% and the figure for marginal deficiency was 25.4%. Males were more affected than females (p &lt; 0.001). The frequency of anemia was 8.6%o, and was higher among women (p = 0.004). CONCLUSIONS There is a high prevalence of full blown and marginal deficit of vitamin B-12 among the elderly. This deficiency should be considered for correction through public nutrition policies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit de vitamina B-12 en adultos mayores: ¿Un problema de salud pública en Chile?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of vitamin B-12 deficiency in older adults].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
