<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20393618</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aparicio López, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Escribano, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luque de Pablos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido Cantanero, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo García, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Chronic kidney disease (CKD) affects the daily life of the child especially during the stage where their personal development takes place. Adult renal patients have a demonstrated worse health related quality of life (HRQL) mainly under hemodialysis (HD), however there are few published data about HRQL in children with CKD, most of them obtained after patient s childhood or with generic tests that do not discriminate changes in a specific disease. OBJECTIVE To assess how our patients perceive their health by measuring the HRQL and its most affected domains. To determine how the different therapies affect the child with CKD and the agreement on the opinion between children and their parents. MATERIAL AND METHODS We included 71 CKD children and their parents in a cross-sectional study (33 transplanted, 11 peritoneal dialysis [PD], 5 HD, 22 conservative treatment). We used a specific quality of life test for CKD children that we had previously developed (TECAVNER). If the child was younger than 9 years, only their parents completed the survey. RESULTS children on HD refer a worse HRQL followed by those who underwent PD and those transplanted. The best HRQL was obtained in children with conservative treatment. Both parents and children agree that the domains more frequently affected are physical activity and school attendance especially those on HD. The way the adolescents 15 years and older perceived their health was similar to that of their parents. This was not the case in the younger group, 9 through 15 ears.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medida mediante un test específico de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en niños con enfermedad renal crónica. Influencia del tratamiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Measurement of health-related quality of life in children with chronic kidney disease using a specific test. Influence of treatment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
