<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20429204</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lázaro-Martínez, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Alvarez, Yolanda</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Morales, Esther A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aragón-Sánchez, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Allas-Aguado, Silva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Año-Vidales, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION highly exudate and maceration is one of the causes of delay in diabetic foot ulcers healing. The purpose of our study was to demonstrate the effectiveness in the periwound skin maceration reduction with the use of no-sting barrier film (NSBF) (3M Cavilon). MATERIAL AND METHODS observational study which includes 40 patients with diabetes (29, 72.5% males) who suffer diabetic foot ulcers with maceration and exudate. It was evaluated the application of NSBF during 30 days and its correlation with maceration control and clinical wounds progress. RESULTS 70% of the ulcers were showed healthy edge or lower exudates after 30 days of treatment (Day 0 n=8 vs Day 30 n=28 p&lt;0.05). Good evolutions of clinical variables were recorded through the study. Fibrin tissues upper 60% of the ulcer area were recorded in 17 cases at day 0 versus 2 cases in day 30 (p&lt;0.001). Granulation tissue presence turned of 13 cases with upper 50% in wound bed at day 0 versus 25 cases at the end of the study (p&lt;0.001). DISCUSSION the use of NSBF for the maceration management of highly exudates diabetic foot ulcers was demonstrated effective.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducir la maceración de úlceras exudativas del pie diabético.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reducing skin maceration in exudative diabetic foot ulcers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
