<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20428608</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tufik, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Paula Ferreira Dos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toffoletto, Odaly</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lucio, Luiz Antonio Galvão</dc:author>
<dc:author>Massud Filho, João</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Adauto Carvalho</dc:author>
<dc:author>Afiune, Jorge Barros</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Millions of men around the world suffer from erectile dysfunction, for which phosphodiesterase 5 inhibitors (PDE-5 inhibitors) are currently the first treatment option. Sexual activity and alcohol consumption are closely related, and the simultaneous use of alcohol and PDE-5 inhibitors can happen. Lodenafil carbonate is a new PDE-5 inhibitor, developed by a Brazilian pharmaceutical company. OBJECTIVE This work aimed at evaluating the cardiovascular safety of lodenafil carbonate, with and without simultaneous alcohol consumption. METHODS Fifteen male volunteers received 160 mg lodenafil carbonate (LC), in three different moments. Participants were assigned to three groups, treated with LC in fasting condition, with alcohol or receiving only placebo. The volunteers were continuously monitored during 24 hours for physical impairment, blood pressure, heart rate, QT interval and lodenafil's pharmacokinetic parameters. RESULTS Lodenafil carbonate alone or with alcohol did not induce clinically relevant modifications in arterial blood pressure or heart rate. A statistically significant decrease in blood pressure was seen four hours after LC and alcohol intake, and an increase in heart rate six hours after intake of lodenafil carbonate alone. The QTc interval was not significantly modified. Lodenafil carbonate bioavailability was increased in 74% when drug intake was associated with alcohol. CONCLUSION These results show that the use of lodenafil carbonate did not have clinically relevant effects on blood pressure or heart rate, and was not associated with QT interval prolongation. The association of lodenafil carbonate and alcohol affected its pharmacokinetic properties, increasing the bioavailability of the drug.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Controlled Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiovascular repercussion of lodenafil carbonate, a new PDE5 inhibitor, with and without alcohol consumption].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Arquivos brasileiros de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
