<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20444527</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Segura Benito, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escribano Sotos, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moya Martínez, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the factors related to pharmaceutical expenditure per primary care physician in the province of Cuenca, which could allow public health authorities to take decisions to curb expenditure. Determining these factors could also be of interest to primary care physicians, specialists, health authorities, health economists, and health management researchers. METHODS We performed a multiple linear regression analysis with three dependent variables to determine which factors explain variability in generic drug prescription, the referral rate, and pharmaceutical expenditure among primary care physicians. RESULTS Not being a resident physician, practicing in a town with more than 10,000 people and having a large patient list had a negative impact on the percentage of generic drugs prescribed. Physicians using electronic medical records and with a high referral rate to specialized care prescribed fewer generic drugs. The two most important factors explaining pharmaceutical expenditure were having a large patient list and a high percentage of patients aged more than 65 years old. Expenditure was reduced by greater prescription of generic drugs and was increased by a larger proportion of elderly patients on the patient list. CONCLUSIONS After controlling for the size of the patient list, the proportion of elderly patients and other factors, the percentage of generic drugs prescribed was one of the most important factors explaining pharmaceutical expenditure in primary care physicians.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gasto farmacéutico de médicos de atención primaria del área de salud de Cuenca.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pharmaceutical expenditure among primary care physicians in the province of Cuenca (Spain)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
