<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20445724</identifier>
<setSpec>1022-5129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cuadra Urteaga, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo Nañez, Leonidas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pintado Caballero, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil Fuentes, Magdalena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canelo-Aybar, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED The liver abscess (LA) continues to cause a high morbidity and mortality worldwide. OBJECTIVES To determine demographic characteristics, clinical presentation, imaging and management at the Arzobispo Loayza Hospital in 5 years. METHODS A descriptive retrospective study, based on medical records of patients diagnosed with LA between January 2003 to December 2007. RESULTS Of 106 medical records reviewed, 46 entered the study. The mean age was 47.8 years (95% CI 41.9-53.8 years), 21 patients were over 50 years (45.6%) and 52.2% were male. The main symptoms were fever (95.6%) and right upper quadrant pain (73.5%). The average time of disease was 2.5 weeks. We found high frequency of hypoalbuminemia, elevated alkaline phosphatase, leukocytosis and anemia. The diagnosis was mostly based on ecography (97.8%), AH were mainly a single abscess (73%) located in the right lobe (77%), with an average diameter of 70 mm (p25-75: 44-90 mm), and 69.6% had more than 5 cm in diameter. Antibiotics were administered for 18.6 days (range: 3-30), being the combination administered more frequently metronidazole and ciprofloxacin. Seventeen patients (36.9%) underwent surgery, 7 patients (15.2%) received external drainage by percutaneous catheter and 10.9% (5 patients) was aspirated directly. CONCLUSION LA is an acute or subacute disease of middle age without gender bias, whose main symptoms are fever and right upper quadrant pain. It is necessary to protocolize the management of this condition.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso Hepático: Caracteristicas Clínicas, Imagenologicas y manejo en el Hospital Loayza en 5 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Liver abscess: clinical, imaging and management features in a 5 year study in the Arzobispo Loayza National Hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
