<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2047934</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Karam Bechara, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sosa, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Posada Maldonado, E E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Naime Libien, J E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Of all the forms of tuberculous infection in children, the most frequent is the pulmonary, but the tuberculous meningitis is the most severe and mortal, it occurs mainly in children under five years old, and the highest mortality is in children under two. The results of a retrospective study carried out at the Children Hospital of Mexico "Dr. Federico Gómez" about all the patients hospitalized with tuberculous meningitis diagnose during the January 1975 to December 1985 period were presented. One hundred and eighteen cases were studied: the majority (80%) corresponded to children under four years old, a percentage of 79 presented some degree of malnutrition, and 86 per cent showed clinical data of neurological affection. The confirmation of the diagnose was made in the majority of cases through laboratory and cabinet studies. Forty per cent showed no alteration in the chest X-rays, and the isolation of the bacillus was in a very low percentage (15%). All the patients were treated with the antituberculous drugs mentioned, with a better development in the ones associated with steroids. The hospital stay was over 30 days in 15 per cent of the cases. The mortality of the series reviewed was 44.5 per cent.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1991 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis tuberculosa: análisis de diez años en el Hospital Infantil de México "Dr. Federico Gómez".</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tuberculous meningitis: a 10-year analysis at the "Dr. Federico Gómez" Children's Hospital of Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
