<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20494821</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramirez-Velez, Robinson</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobar Hurtado, Celia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lucero Gutiérrez, Vanessa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vélez León, Vanessa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study the relationship between disability and health-related quality of life in women with vertigo of peripheral origin. METHODS Cross-sectional study in 26 women diagnosed with vertigo, classified by type of peripheral vestibular disturbance: benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV), vestibular neuritis, Ménière's disease, post-trauma and others. In a self-report interview, a 12-item short-form (SF-12) health survey on quality of life was applied; disability was assessed with the questionnaire "Dizziness Handicap Inventory" (DHI). Measures of central tendency, dispersion for the domains and types of vestibular disturbance were used and internal DHI consistency and inter-scale correlation were calculated. RESULTS Patients in the vestibular neuritis and Ménière groups displayed a higher level of disability according to the DHI functional (29.5+/-5.5 vs. 27.0+/-8.8) and physical domains (23.0+/-4.1 vs. 21.5+/-6.6). Based on the SF-12 domains, greater deterioration in quality of life was perceived in physical (22.9+/-3.9 vs. 22.6+/-4.6) and emotional performance (15.4+/-5.0 vs. 11.3+/-6.0), respectively. Acceptable and significant inverse correlations were found between the physical component summary (PCS-12) of the SF-12 and the physical, emotional and functional aspects of the DHI questionnaire (r=-0.51 to -0.78, p&lt;0.01). Internal consistency (Cronbach's alpha index) of the DHI questionnaire was appropriate for the sample. CONCLUSIONS The DHI and the SF-12 are useful, practical and valid instruments for assessing the impact of dizziness on the quality of life of patients with this symptom.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud y la discapacidad en mujeres con vértigo de origen periférico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Relationship between health-related quality of life and disability in women with peripheral vertigo].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
