<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20529773</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pazo, Valeria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figar, Silvana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Elizondo, Cristina M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes, Nora A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Bernaldo de Quirós, Fernán</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giunta, Diego H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Argentina, education in clinical investigation is based on courses with theoric content. In developed countries programs with ongoing and practical content exist, generating the proper context to learn. In 2006, the Hospital Italiano de Buenos Aires (HIBA) created an area to train physicians, Research Area in Internal Medicine, and enable them to participate in every step of the clinical investigation process. The objective of this study is to describe this teaching area and its impact on the investigation in Internal Medicine in the HIBA, in the period 2006-2008. This area counts with fellow positions and provides training in Clinical Investigation for rotating residents. It has different activities including lectures, project counseling and 3 ongoing Institutional Registers for prevalent medical problems, 33% (6/18) of Intern staff are currently participating, with 3 fellows and 7 monitors for the Registers; 25 residents rotated in the area and generated their own research projects. 59 posters were presented in local and international congresses. Currently 6 original articles are in process of publication and 2 in peer review evaluation. A survey was carried out to evaluate the area where 76% (35/46) of the participants believed that they have acquired new skills; with 93% (44/47) using these knowledges in their every day practice. A 100% thought that they were adequately oriented in their projects, their ideas being fully respected (97%) (45/46). The inclusion of the Research Area in Internal Medicine improved the knowledge of the process of clinical Investigation and increased independent scientific production.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto institucional para la educación médica continua en investigación clínica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continuing medical education: a clinical research institutional project].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
