<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20537666</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castillo Palma, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Hernández, Francisco José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Román, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocaña Medina, Celia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chinchilla Palomares, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Pulido, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE We report our experience with rituximab plus cyclophosphamide in the treatment of patients with resistant idiopathic inflammatory myopathies. PATIENTS AND METHOD Open-label uncontrolled prospective study on 17 patients. RESULTS Evaluation was completed after 1, 6 and 12 months in 95'2, 85'7 y 52'4% of cycles, respectively. Total or partial remission was achieved after 1, 6 and 12 months in 65, 100 y 63'6% of evaluated cycles, respectively. Absolute depletion of B lymphocites from peripheral blood was found in the 18 cases with available data. There were 5 relapses; median of time to relapse: 11 months; treatment was repeated in 4. Four patients (6 cycles) had impaired pulmonary function; one (with a multifactorial etiology) did not improve but the other 3, with interstitial pneumonia associated or not with respiratory muscle weakness, did. Five patients with positive anti-Jo-1 antibodies (6 cycles) displayed similar results. The only adverse event observed was a case of meningitis caused by Corynebacterium, with good results. CONCLUSION Rituximab seems a valid alternative for the treatment of patients with resistant polymyositis or dermatomyosytis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jul 17 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la eficacia del tratamiento con rituximab asociado a ciclofosfamida en pacientes con miopatía inflamatoria idiopática refractaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the effectiveness of treatment with rituximab associated to cyclophosphamide in patients with resistant idiopathic inflammatory myopathy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
