<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20553650</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carranza-Lira, Sebastián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyva-Salas, Rosalba Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arce-Herrera, Rosa María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyva-González, Félix Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the development of critical reading (CR) of clinical research texts (CRT) in medical students. METHODS In 65 students an instrument for the evaluation of CR of CRT was applied. Four groups from three universities were studied: an academic excellence group (n = 21), B1 (n = 19) and B2 (n = 12), C (n = 13). The instrument had eight CRT with 150 items; 50 items to any of the following indicators: interpretation, judgment and proposition. The items were balanced in 50 % false and 50 % true. It was analyzed the global management degrade and by indicator. STATISTICAL ANALYSIS Kruskal-Wallis and Mann-Whitney U test was used. RESULTS Age 22 (median) 20-28 (range) years, gender 56.9 % women, without differences between the three universities. The global score was 50.5 (8 to 112). Group A had statistically significant higher results in global score and by indicator (p &lt; 0.001) in relation with the other universities. According to the interpretation, judgment and proposition indicators, group A had the higher score. CONCLUSIONS The results are similar to those observed in medical residents, because the development degrade for CR reading was low.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2009 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lectura crítica de informes de investigación clínica en estudiantes de pregrado.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Critical reading of clinical investigation reports in pregraduate students].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
