<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20561806</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montoya-Martínez, Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casas-Oñate, Maria Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the influence of the treatment with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion on the quality of life of type 1 diabetics. METHOD An analytical study of cohorts was conducted on 80 patients diagnosed with type 1 diabetes mellitus, with more than five years of evolution and without evidence of micro-macro vascular complications, on treatment with CSII or multiple daily insulin injections (MDII). The quality of life of both groups was evaluated by means of a validated modification of the survey "Diabetes Quality of Life Measure" (DQLM). The SPSS 11.0 software was used to determine Chi(2) and establish statistically significant values for a P&lt;0.05. RESULTS In 86% (31/36) of the questions, the patients on treatment with insulin infusion systems showed higher satisfaction with their quality of life than the patients with multiple daily insulin injections, although only in 16% (6/36) of the questions, were the scores significantly better in the first group. CONCLUSIONS There were no significant differences in the dimensions studied between both groups, but the patients with CSII obtain better results in many variables of the fe DQLM, and they were more satisfied with the flexibility that their treatment offers them in daily life activities.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del tratamiento con bombas de infusión continua de insulina en la calidad de vida de pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Influence of the treatment with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) in the improvement of the quality of life of patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
