<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20673888</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1860</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galicia, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nogué, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miró, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanjurjo, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To describe clinical and epidemiologic characteristics of emergency department visits related with ecstasy usage, determine the rate of re-visits of the patients and their related factors. MATERIAL AND METHODS The clinical histories of the patients coming to the Emergency Department for ecstasy-related problems were reviewed during 89 consecutive months in order to define the epidemiological and clinical profile. The computerized system of admission was used to study re-visits to the emergency department, reviewing the clinical history of the re-visits to see if they were related with drug consumption. RESULTS The study included 498 cases (71% male, mean age 26.5 years). The majority of the patients were attended on the weekend (66.6%) and at night (57%). Main complaints were anxiety or altered thoughts (32.8%), agitation (17.2%), impaired awareness level (7.2%) and convulsions or abnormal movements (5.6%). A total of 81% of the patients had consumed other substances besides ecstasy, mainly ethanol (53%), cocaine (36%) and gammahydroxibutirate (liquid ecstasy, 25%). Twenty six patients (5%) required admission to hospital (6 in the intensive care unit) and 4 died (0.8%). Fifteen percent of the patients were re-attended in the same ED for drug-related problems after a mean follow-up of 3 years, the new visit being more frequent during the first months. The need for an urgent psychiatric visit (OR: 6.3; 95% CI: 2.9-12.8) and hospital admission (OR: 3.5; 95% CI: 1.5-8.4) during their first ED attendance were independently associated with a greater risk of re-attendance. CONCLUSIONS Ecstasy consumption frequently leads to an ED visit, sometimes due to severe medical complications, and at least 15% of patients will need urgent care again for drug-related problems within the next 3 years. This likelihood increases along with increased severity of the index episode (need of psychiatric consultation or hospital admission).</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consultas urgentes derivadas del consumo de éxtasis (3,4-metilenodioximetanfetamina) y derivados anfetamínicos: perfil epidemiológico, clínico y evolutivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Visits to the emergency department due to ecstasy (MDMA) and amphetamine derivative consumption: Epidemiological, clinical and evolutional profile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
