<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20672189</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Linetzky, Bruno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kaplan, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morello, Paola</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Passive smoking is a main public health problem in Argentina. It is estimated that about 55% of children live with a smoker at home. Several reports show that when parents and providers refrain from smoking at home and in the car, environmental tobacco exposure (ETS) and its health consequences decrease. OBJECTIVE To assess pediatricians' knowledge, beliefs and practices regarding passive smoking and its prevention. METHODOLOGY We surveyed a national sample of pediatricians, who participated in the National Pediatric Continuous Education Program (PRONAP) of the Argentine Pediatric Society, via e-mail. RESULTS Overall, 74% of the pediatricians that answered the questionnaire said that they always asked about ETS exposure during the pediatric visit, 50% writes that on the children's chart, 93% advises parents not to smoke at home, 64% motivates parents to quit smoking and 49% provides information materials about the topic. Overall, their knowledge about the diseases most associated with ETS is appropriate. Almost all pediatricians believe the topic is of public health importance and important for children's health. CONCLUSIONS The results of this survey show it is important to improve the training provided to pediatricians and to standardize the discussion and the treatment of ETS during the pediatric visit.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento, actitudes y prácticas de los pediatras argentinos respecto de la exposición infantil al humo de tabaco ajeno.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Knowledge, attitudes, and practices of Argentine pediatricians regarding second hand smoke exposure in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
