<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20694309</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Muñoz, P L</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Luis, D A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Armentia, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>De la Fuente, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dueñas-Laita, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izaola, O</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Marihuana use has effects on appetite; studies in the literature on this topic area are limited. The aim of our work was to evaluate the dietary intake of marihuana smoking patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS A total of 32 male subjects were enrolled (average age 37.25 +/- 8.8 years). In all patients were determined weight, height and body mass index and a three days nutritional questionnaire. RESULTS Total calories intakes were higher (3,350.1 +/- 979 kcal/day). Distribution of calories was 44.3% of carbohydrates, 14% of proteins and 41.7% of lipids (50.6% mono-unsaturate fats, 36.3% saturate fats and 13.1% poluunsaturated fats). Total protein intake was 109.6 +/- 38.5 g/day and corrected by weight was 1.62 +/- 0.73 g/kg. Low intake of vitamin D, E, folic, magnesium and iodine were detected. High intake of vitamin A, C, K, thiamine, riboflavine, B6, niacin, B12, calcium, iron and zinc were observed. No statistical differences in dietary intake or weight were detected between groups of marihuana users by median of consumption time of this drug. CONCLUSIONS Marihuana smoking patients realized a hipercloric and hiperproteic diet, with high amounts of fats and with an intake of micronutrients above international recommendations. This dietary intake has not related with weight.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta dietética en un grupo de pacientes fumadores de marihuana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dietary intakes in a group of marihuana smoking patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
