<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20692862</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Pastor, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio Gil, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abellán Alemán, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales Ortiz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martinez Navarro, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leal Hernández, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Picazo Ferrer, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES 1) To determine the level of registration and control of cardiovascular risk factors in stroke patients treated in primary care in Murcia through electronic medical records. 2) To describe the registered drug treatment in patients with stroke. MATERIAL AND METHODS Observational descriptive, retrospective, evaluated through the records in OMI (electronic medical records) in all areas of Murcia Health Service. A sample of 407 patients with stroke was analyzed. The analyzed variables were type of stroke, time of evolution, registered cardiovascular risk factors, registered cardiovascular disease, medication and degree of control of modifiable risk factors. RESULTS Cardiovascular risk factors recorded were hypertension (81.1%), dyslipemia (72.5%), diabetes (41.3%), abdominal obesity (22.9%) and tobacco (8.8%). Registered cardiovascular diseases were ischemic heart disease (22.1%), atrial fibrillation (13.8%), nephropathy (11.8%), myocardial infarction (5.7%) and left ventricular hypertrophy (3.4%). 2.5% (10) of patients met all criteria for good control. The LDL cholesterol was controlled (&lt;100mg/dl) and recorded in 24.8% of patients and blood pressure in 41.3%. 78.1% of patients were being treated with antihypertensive drugs, 47.4% with lipid-lowering drugs, and 79.1% with antiplatelet or anticoagulant. CONCLUSIONS According to data recorded at OMI-AP the patients who have suffered a stroke have poor control of cardiovascular risk factors.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad del registro en OMI-AP de los pacientes con ictus seguidos en atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quality of records in OMI-AP of the patients with stroke followed in primary care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
