<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20857624</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González Díaz, Sandra N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Weinmann, Alejandra Macías</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sedó Mejía, Giovanni Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vidaurri Ojeda, Alma Catalina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Allergic rhinitis can be caused by allergens such as house dust mites, pollen, fungi, and animals. A less common cause is allergy to Ficus benjamina. OBJECTIVES To determine the prevalence of sensitization to Ficus benjamina on patients with moderate-severe allergic rhinitis, and to describe the epidemiologic factors associated to Ficus benjamina sensitization. PATIENTS AND METHOD It is an observational, transversal, prospective study; patients with persistent moderate-severe allergic rhinitis diagnosis were included; skin tests to the most frequent aeroallergens and to Ficus benjamina were applied to these patients, as well as a questionnaire in order to investigate the degree of exposure to Ficus benjamina. RESULTS 89 patients with persistent moderate-severe allergic rhinitis were included. 59% had a Ficus benjamina plant at home or at work, 97% were located outdoors. Nine patients (10.1%) were sensitized to Ficus benjamina. A statistically significant association was found between sensitization to Ficus benjamina and to Felix domesticus, Canis familiaris, and Periplaneta. CONCLUSIONS Prevalence of sensitization to Ficus benjamina was similar to that reported in the literature, and it is associated to three or more indoor allergens. Patients with allergic rhinitis should avoid contact with Ficus benjamina because of the risk of acquiring sensitization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sensibilización a Ficus benjamina en pacientes adultos con rinitis alérgica moderada-severa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sensitization to Ficus benjamina prevalence in adult patients with moderate-severe allergic rhinitis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
