<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20870337</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vellisco, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barrot, Emilia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Campos, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>de los Ángeles Sánchez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cejudo, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION We analysed the effectiveness of a high intensity behavioural-cognitive intervention compared to minimal intervention started during a hospital stay, to see if the combination of nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) can increase the quitting rate at 12 months of follow up. METHOD A total of 2560 active smokers were studied during their hospital stay. Of these, 717 smokers refused to enter the study and after a minimal intervention they were asked if we could telephone them after one year to ask if they still smoked. The remaining 1843 smokers who received high intensity cognitive therapy were randomised to receive or not receive NRT. The follow up after discharge was carried out by outpatient visits or with telephone sessions. RESULTS At one year of follow up, 7% of those who declined to enter the study had stopped smoking compared to 27% of those who entered the study (p&lt;0.001). There were significant differences between the group that only had behavioural therapy (21% stopped) compared to the group that also had NRT (33% stopped; p=0.002). In this latter group there were significant differences (p=0.03) between those who had follow up in clinics (39% stopped) compared to those who were followed up telephone sessions (30%). In the multivariate analysis, the predictors of quitting at 12 months were: to have used NRT (OR 12.2; 95% CI, 5.2-32; p=0.002) and a higher score in the Richmond Test (OR 10.1; 95% CI, 3.9-24.2; p=0.01). CONCLUSIONS A cognitive type intervention started on smokers when admitted to hospital increases quitting rates at 12 months, compared to a minimal intervention, and these rates increase even more significantly if NRT is added.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a cognitive orientation program with and without nicotine replacement therapy in stopping smoking in hospitalised patients.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
