<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20882093</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Palomares, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Gómez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Perpen, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocaña, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corchete, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bajo, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portolés, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Sánchez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Peso, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In 2007 the Scientific Quality-technical and Improvement of Quality in Peritoneal Dialysis was edited. It includes several quality indicators. As far as we know, only some groups of work had evaluated these indicators, with inconclusive results. AIM To study the evolution and impact of guidelines in Peritoneal Dialysis. METHODS Prospective cohort study of each incident of patients in Peritoneal Dialysis, in a regional public health care system (2003-2006). We prospectively collected baseline clinical and analytical data, technical efficacy, cardiovascular risk, events and deaths, hospital admissions and also prescription data was collected every 6 months. RESULTS Over a period of 3 years, 490 patients (53.58 years of age; 61.6% males.) Causes of ERC: glomerular 25.5%, diabetes 16%, vascular 12.4%, and interstitial 13.3%. 26.48% were on the list for transplant. Dialysis efficacy: Of the first available results, the residual renal function was 6.37 ml/min, achieving 67.6% of all the objectives K/DOQI. 38.6% remained within the range during the entire first year. Anaemia: 79.3% received erythropoietic stimulating agents and maintained an average Hb of 12.1 g/dl. The percentage of patients in the range (Hb: 11-13 g/dl) improved after a year (58.4% vs 56.3% keeping in the range during this time of 25.6%). Evolution: it has been estimated that per patient-year the risk of: 1) mortality is 0.06 IC 95% [0.04-0.08]; 2) admissions 0.65 [0.58-0.72]; 3) peritoneal infections 0.5 [0.44-0.56]. CONCLUSION Diabetes Mellitus patients had a higher cardiovascular risk and prevalence of events. The degrees of control during the follow-up in many topics of peritoneal dialysis improve each year; however they are far from the recommended guidelines, especially if they are evaluated throughout the whole study.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de objetivos de calidad y evolución de los pacientes incidentes en diálisis peritoneal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Approach to quality objectives in incidents of patients in peritoneal dialysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
