<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20880559</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torres-Fuentes, Estrella</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Ríos, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-González, Fayna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Quintana, Efrén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nieto-Lago, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The consumption of fish has been associated with a minor risk of cardiovascular mortality. PATIENTS AND METHODS Thirty-one patients with clinical and angiographic evidence of coronary illness and no data of heart failure were followed up. One gram per day of omega-3-acid ethyl esters was added to their usual cardiologic treatment. Demographic, clinical and analytical data (lipid, ESR, CRP, lipoprotein[a], fibrinogen, and BNP levels) were evaluated at the beginning and at 9 months. RESULTS Six patients had cardiologic events in the follow up although none presented acute coronary syndrome. Significant differences were seen in HDL cholesterol (mg/dL) (38,5[9,6] vs. 42,1 (11,0), p=0,000), hemoglobin (g/dL) (13,2 [1,7] vs. 13,9 (1,7), p=0,009) and pro-BNP (pg/dL) (745,5 [1,035,7] vs. 235,8 [194,0], p=0,008) levels. No significant differences existed either in the inflammatory parameters or in total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol and triglycerides. CONCLUSION One gram day of omega-3-acid ethyl esters added to the usual cardiologic treatment in patients with coronary heart disease improves pro BNP levels of patients with preserved left ventricular function without modifying serum inflammatory parameters.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 May 14 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de los ácidos grasos omega-3 en la evolución clínica, biomarcadores inflamatorios y el péptido natriurético cerebral de pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of omega-3 acids on clinical evolution, plasma inflammatory biomarkers and B-type natriuretic peptide levels in patients with coronary heart disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
