<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2089631</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez-Guadarrama, M de L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Rosales, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brust-Carmona, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez-Mendoza, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Sánchez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Mexican Health Office (SSA) promotes the use and progeny of the appropriate technology for the bacteriological quality evaluation and disinfect the water by means of the in situ progeny of the clorus and ozonus gases when needed, for the human consumption in suburban and rural communities. The clorus water disinfecting conventional methods by many reasons are useless, even in urbanized cities. CEDAT has built and design a group of apparatus, called: "Water treatment whole equipment for small communities", and it's build up by: Membrane Filter, Double Chamber Incubator, ultraviolet Light Sterilizer and a clorus and ozonus progenic gas electrolytic cell with CA and CD power box and a Venturi Tube. The electrolytic cell raw material is the sodium chlorine (salt) water mixed. The evaluation of these equipment was made at the Manuel Gea González Medical Doctor General Hospital. During 38 days there was a daily measure of chlorine sewage in six different parts of the hospital. It was used the cellulose membrane filter technic with a 0.45 mm porus and a sowing in M-Endo and M-FC Broth cultivation was in a 37 and 44 centigrade incubation. The first 10 days chlorine sewage was found, the last 28 weren't measurable. Total coliforms in 23 of 42, 7 days samples and excrement coliforms in 5 of 18, 3 days samples, were developed during the 38 days period. The electrolytic cell was settled for the water gas measure up in its way to the reservoir. Afterwards chlorine sewage was measured from 0.2 mg/l to 1 mg/l in all the sample parts. No germ kind was discovered during the 10 days sampling.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del sistema integral para tratamiento del agua en un hospital general de la Ciudad de México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The evaluation of the integral water treatment system of a general hospital in Mexico City].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
