<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20925030</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de la Peña-González, Ana Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peñasco-Martín, Benito</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Aguilar, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernal-Sahún, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Agudo, Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>de los Reyes-Guzmán, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Virtual reality allows the user to interact with elements within a simulated scene. In recent times we have been witness to the introduction of virtual reality-based devices as one of the most significant novelties in neurorehabilitation. AIM To review the clinical applications of the developments based on virtual reality for the neurorehabilitation treatment of the motor aspects of the most frequent disabling processes with a neurological origin. DEVELOPMENT A review was carried out of the Medline, Physiotherapy Evidence Database, Ovid and Cochrane Library databases up until April 2009. This was completed with a web search using Google. No clinical trial conducted on its effectiveness has been found to date. The information that was collected is based on the description of the various prototypes produced by the different groups involved in their development. In most cases they are clinical trials conducted with a small number of patients, which have focused more on testing the validity of the device and checking whether it works correctly than on attempting to prove its clinical effectiveness. Although most of the clinical applications refer to patients with stroke, there were also several applications for patients with spinal cord injuries, multiple sclerosis, Parkinson's disease or balance disorders. CONCLUSIONS Virtual reality is a novel tool with a promising future in neurorehabilitation. Further studies are needed to demonstrate its clinical effectiveness as compared to the traditional techniques.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Oct 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la realidad virtual en los aspectos motores de la neurorrehabilitación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Application of virtual reality in the motor aspects of neurorehabilitation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
