<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>20929616</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galván-Cervantes, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales-Rojas, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Novelo-Garza, Bárbara Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Benítez, América</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benítez-Arvizu, Gamaliel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The American trypanosomiasis is the second parasitic disease in importance after paludism and one of the main mechanism of transmission is a blood transfusion. Our objective was to measure the effect the Tripanosoma Cruzi screening test in blood banks in the Mexican Institute of Social Security. METHODS Information was obtained from each unit of blood collected. The Tripanosoma cruzi prevalence was calculated only in samples with double reactivity in the blood banks. RESULTS Of 71 blood banks, only 26 had been doing T. Cruzi screen; after implementation of integrated services 55 are doing the screening. There were 935 donors with double reactivity to the T. Cruzi test from 230,074 samples. The national prevalence was 0.406%. The seroprevalence was 0.013% to 3.118%. CONCLUSIONS The screening of the T. cruzi improved the detection and increased the safety and the prevention of its transmission by blood transfusion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de Tripanosoma cruzi en donadores de sangre.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Detection of Trypanosoma cruzi in blood donors].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
