<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2103207</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil de la Peña, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pose Reino, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amaro Cendon, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otero Raviña, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Juanatey, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segade, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A comparative study of the total cholesterol (TC) and its fractions was carried out in 3 groups of males. The first group consisted of (C) 53 healthy males (18 between 30-39 years old, 17 between 40-49 and 18 between 50-65); the second group (M) was of 57 male doctors (19 between 30-39 years old, 21 between 40-49, and 17 between 50-65); third group (E) was of 94 males with myocardial infarction (22 between 30-39 years old, 32 between 40-49, and 40 between 50-65). TC was significantly lower (p less than 0.02 and p less than 0.001) in both the lower ages ranges in Group E compared to Groups C and M in all age ranges. Group M showed significantly lower (p less than 0.001) in Group E compared to Groups C and M in all age ranges. Group M showed significantly lower HDL-C (p less than 0.01) and to group M in the lowest age range (p less than 0.005). LDL-C was significantly higher (p less than 0.001) in Group M compared to C in the higher age range. VLDL-C was higher (p less than 0.05) in Group E compared to C in both the higher age ranges (p less than 0.05) as well as to the middle age range of Group M (p less than 0.05). The indexes TC/HDL-C and LDL-C/HDL-C were significantly higher in Group E compared to Groups C and M in all age ranges. These indexes were significantly higher (p less than 0.01 and p less than 0.05) in Group M compared to group C in all age ranges.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dislipemia en médicos. Necesidad de un plan de prevención primaria de ateroesclerosis en nuestro medio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dyslipemia in physicians. The need for a plan of primary prevention of atherosclerosis in our country].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
