<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2104095</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fdez de Aranguiz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ereño, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>de las Heras, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarria, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campelo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Malave, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cisterna, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We study retrospectively the viral replication state (HBV) of 50 patients with chronic hepatic alterations. The seric DNA-HBV and/or intrahepatic (molecular hybridization), the intrahepatic distribution of HBV antigens (specific monoclonal antibodies labelled with immunoperoxidase), conventional seric HBV markers (commercial enzymoimmunoessay) and the different histopathologic features. We found a correlation between DNA-HBV "in situ" and HBcAg intrahepatic and the seric DNA-HBV production. 81% of the patients with HBsAg (+) had intrahepatic HBcAg and 85% (11/13) of them showed the antigen in their cytoplasms. Patients with HBcAg also had seric and liver DNA-HBV (+). The lack of seric HBsAg did not mean that non-active replication of HBV did not exist because 20% of the patients with HBsAg (-) showed seric and "in situ" DNA-HBV and cytoplasmic HBcAg. The detection of DNA-HBV in endothelial cells and vascular elements in hepatic tissue show that the rate of the HBV host cells is greater.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la replicación del virus de la hepatitis B (VHB) en pacientes con distintas formas de hepatopatía crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hepatitis B virus (HBV) replication in patients with various types of chronic hepatopathy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
