<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21074904</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Adiego Sancho, María Begoña</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Díaz, Rogelio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Misiego Peral, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roc Alfaro, María Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodrigo Val, María Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To quantify and identify the rubella-susceptible population in Aragon according to sociodemographic variables, with the aim of assessing compliance with the 5% limit set by the World Health Organization (WHO). METHODS Rubella serology tests performed in women of childbearing age in the Miguel Servet Hospital from 2003 to 2007 were studied. A descriptive analysis of seronegativity was performed by age, years of study, and WHO region (for 2007). A logistic regression was performed with the independent variables of age and geographical origin. RESULTS We studied 13,136 women. The mean age was 31.2 years. During the study period, 5% were susceptible to rubella (95%CI: 4.63-5.37). In 2003, 8.8% were seronegative and the highest percentage (12.3%) was found in women aged 15 to 19 years. The percentage of seronegativity was higher in foreign-born women (7.7%), especially those from Asia, than in Spanish women (3.3%; p&lt;0.05). CONCLUSIONS Postpartum preventive strategies should be established to prevent possible rubella outbreaks and cases of congenital rubella syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de seroprevalencia de la rubéola en las mujeres en edad fértil de Aragón (2003-2007).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Seroepidemiologic study of rubella in childbearing women in Aragon, Spain (2003-2007)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
