<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21072468</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gianella, Camila</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lopez, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosales-Mayor, Edmundo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paca-Palao, Ada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda, J Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Huicho, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was to ascertain, from patients' perspective, the degree of knowledge and the actual coverage of the Emergency Health Care Law and the Compulsory Insurance against Road Traffic Crashes (SOAT). MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional, active surveillance of emergency wards of selected health facilities in three Peruvian cities (Lima, Pucallpa y Ayacucho) was conducted. RESULTS Out of 644 surveyed victims, 77% did not know about the law about provision of emergency health care (81% in Lima, 64% in Pucallpa y 93% in Ayacucho; p&lt;0.001). Following the explanation of what this law entails, 46% reported to have received care according to the law specifications. As for SOAT, the health care related costs of 237 persons (37.2%) were not covered by any insurance scheme (74% in Pucallpa, 34% in Ayacucho and 26% in Lima: p&lt;0.001). CONCLUSIONS In this study, the lack of knowledge about the provision of emergency health care law was important, and the coverage of care was deficient as nearly half of participants reported not to be treated by one or more of the entitlements stated in such law. Road traffic injuriesrelated health care costs were not covered by any insurance scheme in one of three victims. Improvements on citizens&#146; information about their rights and of effective law enforcement are badly needed to reach a universal and more equitable coverage in the health care of road traffic-related victims.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cobertura real de la ley de atención de emergencia y del Seguro Obligatorio contra Accidentes de Tránsito (SOAT).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Coverage of the Emergency Health Care Law and the Compulsory Insurance against Road Traffic Crashes (SOAT)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
