<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21072449</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Santivañez-Pimentel, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyton-Valencia, Imelda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pomasunco, Denis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quispe, Antonio M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze the trend of the monthly "caesarean section rate" (CSR) at the DISA V Lima-Ciudad Hospitals during the period 2001 - 2008. MATERIAL AND METHODS Ecological study that aim to analyze the monthly reports of all DISA V Lima-Ciudad Hospitals that attends childbirths, and by analyzing the trend of theirs monthly caesarean section ratio or monthly CSR (TCM = total caesarean births in a month * 100/total number of newborns in the same month ) to determine their characteristic patterns. RESULTS Of the 7 hospitals studied, it was found that between 2001 and 2008, TCM average was 36.9% ± 9.1% (range: 16.5%-71.4%). From 2001 (33.5% ± 6.9%) to 2008 (39.7% ± 8.3%) years TCM increased 6.9% ± 7.0% on average, having registered a increase of 7.7% ± 6.4% at the year 2007 (43.5% ± 9.8%). Analyzing the TCM trend was found that most hospitals have a significant increase between 2004 and 2005 years. Analyzing the TCM trend was found that it tends to increase in April (37,9% ± 9,7%) and September (40.2% ± 8.9%), cycle that characterize most DISA V Lima-Ciudad Hospitals. CONCLUSIONS TCM of the DISA V Lima-Ciudad Hospitals length exceeds the limit recommended by WHO and, during the period 2001-2008, has had a significant trend to increase.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cesáreas en siete hospitales públicos de Lima: análisis de tendencia en el periodo 2001-2008.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Caesarean section among seven public hospitals at Lima: trend analysis during 2001-2008 period].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
