<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21140056</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez G, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Franco S, Mireya</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarreal R, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas D, Emma R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galicia R, Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Social representations are value systems. Social stereotypes are a social consensus of traits associated with a specific group. Stereotypes about older subjects, generally have negative connotations. AIM To assess the prevalence of negative stereotypes towards older subjects among health care personnel. MATERIAL AND METHODS A questionnaire about stereotypes towards old age, with Likert type questions that included health, social motivations and personality-character domains, was applied to 52 doctors, 12 residents, 80 general nurses, 36 auxiliary nurses, four social workers and 10 medical assistants, working at a general hospital. RESULTS The mean age of the professionals who answered the questionnaire was 38 years (95% confidence intervals (CI) 37-39 years) and 78% were women. The prevalence of a Global negative stereotype was 65.0%(95% CI: 59.5-70.5). The figure for the health domain was 64.5% (IC95%; 59.0-70.0), for the social motivation domain was 60%(5%CI: 54.3-65.7) and for the character personality domain was 64% (95%CI: 58.4-69.6). CONCLUSIONS There is a high prevalence of a negative stereotype towards old age among health care personnel.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estereotipos negativos de la vejez en personal de salud de un Hospital de la Ciudad de Querétaro, México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of negative stereotypes towards old age among personnel of a general hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
