<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21196018</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil, Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, Ruth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteban-Hernández, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Román Montero, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Anegón, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES Previous studies showed a plausible association between herpetic burden and ischemic heart disease. Our aim is to test this hypothesis in an spanish seroepidemiological context. PATIENTS AND METHODS Sex and age matched case-control study (1:1) including patients with chronic ischemic heart disease and healthy controls. Herpetic burden was defined as the aggregate number of antibody seropositivities (IgG) for Epstein Barr Virus, cytomegalovirus, varicella zoster virus, Herpes simplex type 1 and type 2. RESULTS We found that 90.7% of cases and 70,7% of controles (P=.002), were seropositive to 4 or more herpesvirus (high herpetic burden). Within control group, hypercholesterolemic subjects had a higher proportion of high burden (88,5% vs. 61,2%, P=.02). High herpetic burden was associated with ischemic heart disease, even after adjusting for diabetes, smoking, hypertension and literacy level, (OR: 4,5 [1,23-16,53]), but not when hypercholesterolemia was included in the model (OR 2,2 [0,45-10,62]). CONCLUSION The hypothesized relationship is independent from most but not all classical cardiovascular risk factors.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul 09 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre la carga herpética y la enfermedad isquémica crónica del corazón: estudio de casos y controles.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Association between herpetic burden and chronic ischemic heart disease: matched case-control study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
