<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21214994</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallegos-Hernández, José Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The upper third of the larynx shares a wall with the pharynx, the laryngopharyngeal wall. This anatomic structure is common to both organs and is often the source of epidermoid carcinomas. These carcinomas are more frequent in subjects who ingest large amounts of alcohol. The purpose of this study is to describe the indications, contraindications, technical errors and surgical technique of the supracricoid hemilaryngopharyngectomy and horizontal supraglottic laryngectomy. DISCUSSION These tumors are usually bulky, respect laryngeal function and are limited to this anatomic structure. Laryngeal mobility is respected through advanced stages of the disease. Because tumors originating in this region are highly lymphophilic (presenting occult nodal metastasis in up to 45%), both techniques should be accompanied by cervical lymph node dissection, generally bilateral, and including at least levels II to IV. The presence of lymph node metastases is not an absolute contraindication for these procedures. CONCLUSIONS We describe two surgical techniques designed to obtain adequate cancer control, preserving the natural functions of swallowing, speech and ventilation in patients with tumors arising in the supraglottic region and the region between the larynx and hypopharynx.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Partial laryngectomy in supraglottic pharyngeal tumors.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
