<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21218199</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Teitelbaum, Julia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Levy, Melina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Scévola, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvet, Estefanía</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non-convulsive status epilepticus (NCSE) is a clinical condition characterized by continuous or intermittent state of epileptic activity without restitution, prolonged for more than thirty minutes. The main difference with convulsive status epilepticus (CSE) , is the absence of predominant motor activity. By reviewing the most recent literature, we intend to describe different aspects of NCSE: clinical presentation, classification, diagnostic criteria, differential diagnosis, imaging studies, and treatment. We emphasized the aspects most related to Psychiatry, without living aside characteristics encompassing its neurological aspects. The broad spectrum of clinical presentations, the rare knowledge about this entity , and the lack of clear diagnostic criteria are some of the difficulties to make the proper diagnosis. Because of its high morbidity and mortality, the aim of the present review is to highlight critical characteristics of NCSE, in order to take them into account during daily medical practice enabling an early and adequate treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones psiquiátricas del status epiléptico no convulsivo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Psychiatric manifestations of non-convulsive status epilepticus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
