<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21233032</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Antón, J Gil</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jordan García, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vicente, J C de Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arriourtúa, A Bustinza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torre, J A Concha</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, C Téllez</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Nosocomial infection (NI) is a common complication in paediatric critical care units (PICU), with an associated mortality up to 11%. OBJECTIVE To describe NI epidemiology in the national PICU. To initiate an standard NI control measures to obtain paediatric incidence rates. PATIENTS AND METHOD Multicentre prospective study from 1 to 31 march 2007. Centre Disease Control diagnosis and methodological criteria were used. It was specially analyzed NI related to invasive devices: central venous catheter (CVC), mechanical ventilation (MV), urinary catheter (UC). RESULTS There were recruited 300 patients from 6 PICU, with 17 NI episodes in 16 patients (5,3% from admitted). NI rates resulted in 13,8 infections/1000 patients-day. Middle age from infected patients was 2,31 years (± 3,43), 9 males. Risk factors were found in 7 cases. NI location was: catheter-related bloodstream infection in 7 patients (6,7/1000 days CVC), ventilator associated pneumonia in 4 (9,4/1000 MV days), urinary-tract infection associated with UC in 4 (5,5/1000 UC days), one case of primary bloodstream infection and one surgical site infection. Isolated microorganisms were: 9 gram negatives bacillus, 4 Candida, 2 plasmocoagulase negative staphylococcus, 1 Haemophilus and 1 Staphylococcus aureus. Seven isolations were resistant microorganisms. There weren't any died related to NI. CONCLUSIONS NI epidemiology was similar to published data in our near countries. NI surveillance, with a standardized method of analysis is essential to the NI correct manage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Nosocomial infection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rates</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Multicéntrico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tasas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Multicentre</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección nosocomial</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio multicéntrico nacional sobre la infección nosocomial en la UCIP.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A national multicentre study on nosocomial infections in PICU].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
