<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21233861</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fortes, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espada, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barón, Ma Carmen Espada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, Claudia Grau</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fortes del Valle, Ma Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grau, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper studies the usefulness of a short film in teaching strategies for parents of children with cancer to cope with the situation. The short film is based on an analysis of the transcripts from eight sessions of a self-help group. The short film has been evaluated by psychologists working for each of the parent groups belonging to the Federation of parents of children with cancer. Furthermore, the film has been exhibited in group sessions that took place in the Valencia and Alicante branches of ASPANION (Association of Parents with Oncologic Children in the Valencia Region). About 70% of the experts have declared that the film is a valuable resource for teaching useful strategies to parents. The film also improves the group sessions since it addresses a number of issues that had not been addressed before, and it stimulates the participation of, and communication between, parents during the session.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enseñar estrategias de afrontamiento a padres de niños con cáncer a través de un cortometraje.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Teaching coping strategies to parents of children suffering from cancer using a short film].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
