<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21256786</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rubio Rico, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Anguera Saperas, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roca Biosca, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Grau, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velasco Guillén, M C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Oral hygiene (OH) forms a part of the patient's safety in the prevention of mechanical ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP). The dental plaque index (DP) is considered as a quality marker for OH. HYPOTHESIS The association of electric toothbrush and conventional OH in intubated patients decreases the DP and incidence of VAP. OBJECTIVE To verify the reduction of DP in patients receiving OH and electric toothbrush and its association with to the decrease of VAP incidence. MATERIALS AND METHODS A 3-year long randomized, single blind and prospective study conducted in a 14-bed polyvalent intensive care unit. Patients were included when there was more than 48hours of mechanical ventilation and no expected respiratory infection. Patients were randomized into two groups: Standard (OH with chlorhexidine) (GS) and Raspall (Standard OH with electric dental brush) (GR). The VAP was identified following clinical, medical and microbiological criteria. The DP and halitosis were observed daily. Oral and pharyngeal swabs were collected during the first 5 days. RESULTS 147 patients were included. Mean age was 53.9±17.5. No significant differences were found in the VAP incidence between the two groups (OR=0.78; 95% IC, 0.36-1.68; p=0.56). The relation between halitosis and DP was p=0.7. The dental plaque index on the 5th day was 1.98 (n=60) in GR and 2.04 (n=57) in GS (p=0.3). The dental plaque index on the 10th day was 1.68 (n=29) in GR and 1.91 (n=32) in GS (p=0.7). CONCLUSIONS There is a tendency towards a decrease in the DP which is clearing in the GR group and no relation between VAP and greater DP or halitosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de la neumonía asociada a la ventilación mecánica: estudio comparativo de dos métodos de higiene oral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevention of mechanical ventilator-associated pneumonia: a comparison of two different oral hygiene methods].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
