<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21255768</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Camps, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Feliu, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Clavería, Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Besora, Pere</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viñas, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abad, Josep M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Heller myotomy using the laparoscopic approach is the best treatment that we can offer to patients with achalasia. On not acting on the cause of the disease, we can only alleviate the persistence of the symptoms, but not make them disappear. OBJECTIVE To analyse the results of our group in the treatment of achalasia by laparoscopy. MATERIAL AND METHODS The pre- and post-operative results are analysed of a series of 20 patients intervened prospectively by laparoscopy of achalasia during a period from May 2003 to April 2010. For this we used a modification of the grading scale of pre- and post-operative symptoms described by Velanovich for GER (a scale from 0-5). Data on the complications and the hospital stay were also collected. RESULTS A wide Heller myotomy was performed using a Dor type antireflux mechanism. There were no oesophageal perforations or complications during the surgery. Two (10%) patients had postoperative complications. The mean hospital stay was 3.11 ± 2.13 days. After a mean follow up of 55.8 ± 14.1 months, the symptoms studied had significantly decreased after the surgery. Only 3 (15%) patients had clinical symptoms of GER after surgery. Nineteen patients (95%) said they were satisfied with the operation. CONCLUSIONS The laparoscopic treatment of achalasia is a safe technique, reproducible and effective technique, which achieves very satisfactory control of the achalasia symptoms with a minimum of morbidity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento laparoscópico de la acalasia. Análisis de resultados y reflexiones sobre la técnica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Laparoscopic treatment of achalasia: analysis of results and reflections on the technique].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
