<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21269736</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cozar, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brenes, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Huerta, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Antoñanzas, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palencia, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molero, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Pro, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES to evaluate the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) of the combination therapy with dutasteride and tamsulosin (DUT+TAM) as initiation treatment versus the most used drug in Spain, tamsulosin (TAM), in the treatment of moderate to severe benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) with risk of progression. METHODS a semi-Markov model was developed using 4-year and 35-year time horizons and from the Spanish National Healthcare Service perspective. Data were obtained from the CombAT trial. Effectiveness was measured in terms of quality adjusted life years (QALYs). Health care resources were defined by an experts' panel, and unitary costs were obtained from published Spanish sources. Pharmacologic cost is expressed in PTP(WAT); in the case of TAM, the generic price is used, in the case of DUT+TAM the price of a fixed dose combination is used. Costs are expressed in 2010 Euros. RESULTS combination therapy with DUT+TAM produces an incremental effectiveness of 0.06QALY at year 4 and 0.4QALY at year 35. DUT+TAM represents an incremental cost of € 810.53 at 4 years and € 3,443.62 at 35 years. Therefore, the ICER for DUT+TAM versus TAM is € 14,023.32/QALY at year 4 and € 8,750.15/QALY at year 35. CONCLUSIONS initiation treatment with DUT+TAM represents a cost-effective treatment versus TAM, the most used treatment in Spain, due to the fact the ICER is below the threshold that usually allows a technology to be considered as cost-effective.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-efectividad de la combinación dutasterida y tamsulosina en el tratamiento de la hiperplasia benigna de próstata en España.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cost-effectiveness of the combination therapy of dutasteride and tamsulosin in the treatment of benign prostatic hyperlasia in Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
