<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21279250</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marín, Arnaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pino, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arnaiz, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aglony, Marlene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acevedo, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barja, Salesa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Waist to height ratio and ultrasensitive C-reactive protein are predictors of the presence of the metabolic syndrome in children. AIM To determine the proportional risk of metabolic syndrome component clustering in children, using waist to height ratio and ultrasensitive C-reactive protein. MATERIAL AND METHODS Anthropometric measures, blood pressure, fasting serum lipid profile, blood glucose and ultrasensitive C-reactive protein were determined in 209 children aged 11.5 ± 2 years (50% females). The presence of the metabolic syndrome as a function of waist to height ratio and C-reactive protein was modeled using logistic regression equations. The risk of clustering one, two or more components of the metabolic syndrome was calculated. RESULTS Metabolic syndrome was present in 5% of all children and 18% of those that were obese. The cut off points for waist to hip ratio and ultrasensitive C-reactive protein were 0.55 and 0.61 mg/L, respectively. For each 0.01 increment in waist to height ratio, the odds ratio of increasing one component of the metabolic syndrome was 1.2 (1.15-1.25) or 15 to 25%. The odds ratio for log-transformed ultrasensitive C-reactive protein was 1.62 (1.26-2.09). Excluding waist circumference, the odds ratio of adding one or more components of the metabolic syndrome was 1.05 (1.01-1.09) per 0.01 increment in waist to height ratio, but the odds ratio for C-reactive protein was no longer significant. CONCLUSIONS Waist to height ratio and ultrasensitive C-reactive protein predict the risk of clustering components of the metabolic syndrome in these children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Índice cintura estatura y agregación de componentes cardiometabólicos en niños y adolescentes de Santiago.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Waist height ratio, ultrasensitive c reactive protein and metabolic syndrome in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
