<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2129715</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Crehuet Navajas, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez de la Iglesia, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero Pérez, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To more precisely define the epidemiological characteristics of meningococcal disease (MD) and to try to determine its possible risk factors, 224 cases diagnosed during the 1983-1987 period in all the hospitals of the Cordova province were evaluated. There was an incidence density (ID) of 6 cases/100,000/year. The younger ages were the most commonly involved (81.7% of cases were less than 14 years old), and males had the highest overall incidence. The greatest number of cases accumulated during the coldest months of the year (december, january, february). The highest rate of incidence was in the Guadalquivir Valley area, which has the highest population density. The poorest and socioeconomically lowest districts of the capital had the greatest morbidity (p less than 0.001). The mortality rate was 6.2%. It was higher in patients over 5 years of age and the male/female mortality rate was 0.75. It was concluded that wider and deeper epidemiological studies are required to evaluate the influence of habitat and other possible factors in the development of MD.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio epidemiológico de la enfermedad meningocócica en la provincia de Córdoba (1983-1987).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[An epidemiological study of meningococcal disease in the province of Cordova (1983-1987)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
