<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21305773</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Menolascino, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña, Alix</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amemiya, Hideki</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The product of the proto-oncogene C-MET (the c-Met receptor) and its ligand, hepatocyte growth factor (HGF), have been implicated in the progression of gastric cancer. The aim of this study was to analyze the expression of c-Met receptor, HGF and proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) by the immunohistochemistry method of labeled streptavidin-biotin, as well as survival, and they were correlated with anatomopathological factors in stomach specimens of 40 patients, who underwent gastrectomy for gastric cancer in the Department of General Surgery, Hospital Central Universitario "Antonio María Pineda" in Barquisimeto, Venezuela, in 2001-2004. High expression of c-Met receptor and PCNA was observed in patients with advanced stages of gastric cancer (III and IV) compared with early stages (I and II) (p&lt;0.01). There was also overexpression of the c-Met receptor in histologic variables with low degree of differentiation, deeper tumor invasion into the submucosa, liver metastases and it is reported a lower survival rate in patients with increased receptor expression (+++ and ++++) when compared with patients with the lowest expression (+ and ++) (p&lt;0.01). The expression of HGF was constant in both, advanced and early groups. The c-Met receptor is associated with proliferation and cell migration in Venezuelan patients with gastric cancer and could be used as a prognostic factor in this pathology.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la expresión del receptor c-Met en la progresión del cancer gástrico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Role of the expression of c-Met receptor in the progression of gastric cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
