<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21308196</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cantoral, Valentina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Huarcaya, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segovia, Gualberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero, Avelino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To estimate the taeniosis prevalence and human cysticercosis seroprevalence in a rural town from the Peruvian central Andes (Pampa Cangallo, Ayacucho), we performed a cross sectional study in 2008, included 368 people between 5 and 70 years. Fast sedimentation technique and direct examination of stool samples were used to taeniosis diagnosis, and ELISA are used as screening test to cysticercosis, positives cases were confirmed with immunoblot. We found five positives cases to Taenia sp. eggs, which represents a 1.4% (95%CI: 0.2 - 2.5%) of a taeniosis prevalence, being individuals between the 20 to 49 years those which presented high proportion. We found 3.3% (95%CI: 1.5 - 5.1%) of cysticercosis prevalence for 12 positives cases, being most frequent in women. No association with evaluated factors was found. Though the prevalence is low, the existence of the taeniosis and cysticercosis is confirmed in this population, by what there is suggested the establishment of prevention and control strategies, emphatically in the community education.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de teniosis y seroprevalencia de cisticercosis humana en Pampa Cangallo, Ayacucho, Perú 2008.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Taeniosis prevalence and human cysticercosis seroprevalence in Pampa Cangallo, Ayacucho, Peru 2008].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
