<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21305762</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Quinzaños Fresnedo, Jimena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Vázquez, Juan Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romo Rodríguez, Ranulfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tarazona Velutini, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camacho Galindo, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The proximal interphalangeal (PIP) joint is the most commonly dislocated joint in the body and the hand. We did a review of the literature and report herein our experience treating this condition at the ABC Medical Center from 1991 to 2007. MATERIAL AND METHODS Systematic review of the literature. Retrospective and descriptive study. RESULTS A total of 13 patients were included between 1991 and 2007. Three of them were managed with ORIF with Kirschner nails, 3 with OR and Kirschner nails blocking extension, 2 with plasty with volar plate interposition, and one with CRIF with a Kirschner nail. Mean follow-up was 4.8 months in 8 patients, the ranges of motion were recorded. The following factors were negatively correlated with the range of motion: age, time elapsed between the injury and the treatment, the combined approaches, and the pins blocking extension. Those treated with interposition arthroplasty had a better range of motion. CONCLUSION The fracture dislocation of the PIP joint is a rare pathology with multiple treatments and variable outcomes that usually result in the limitation of flexion and extension.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura-luxación de la articulación interfaláingica proximal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fracture dislocation of the proximal interphalangeal joint].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
