<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21316318</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García Jiménez, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateo Ferrando, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Ruiz, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Mata, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monge Galindo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Delgado, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Pisón, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznar, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The preparation and review of child neurology guidelines can reduce the variability of our medical practice, thus improving health care. We present the continuous monitoring of our Bell's palsy guideline. MATERIAL AND METHODS Emergency and medical reports of the children seen in Child Neurology surgery from July 2006 to August 2009 (group 2) are reviewed for the purpose of finding out the present level of compliance with guideline quality criteria and compare it with the previously reviewed period (group 1, from March 2003 to June 2006). Scientific evidence on this topic is also updated. RESULTS Comparing the compliance rate in group 1 with group 2 shows a rise in group 2 from 85.1% to 100% in facial expression description, from 11.1% to 31.6% on whether or not there is evidence of Herpes Zoster vesicles, from 77.7% to 84.2% whether or not there is evidence fundoscopic examination, and from 77.7% to 86.8% as regards cranial nerve function remaining normal. The rate of fact sheet issue, recorded for the first time in group 2, is 21.1%. DISCUSSION Medical auditing allows us to evaluate our medical practice and set up ways for improvement according to the deficiencies found. We insist on striving to improve the written record of the most relevant data and never overlook the importance of issuing the fact sheets to parents and paediatricians, to ensure continuity of medical care.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización continua de un protocolo: parálisis facial a frigore.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continuous monitoring of a guideline: Bell's palsy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
