<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21327311</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Brugos-Llamazares, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vada-Sánchez, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Terán-Lantarón, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>González de Aledo Linos, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The colorectal cancer (CCR) is a Public Health problem because of its high incidence and mortality. Screening programs are important for early detection of CCR. An early detection of this illness could decrease its mortality. The objectives of our study are to present the colorectal cancer screening program in Cantabria and its main results. METHODS Descriptive study of a two-year screening program for population in the 55 - 69 years age range, according to the Cantabria Health Service data base (92,605 people). The screening test used a qualitative immunochemical method in search of faecal occulted blood (FOB), complemented by optical colonoscopy confirmation. Eligible people were invited to participate in the screening program by means of personal letter and, in case of acceptance, they were dated in their primary Health Center. After application of exclusion criteria, selected people with a positive result test were submitted to optical colonoscopy. Those in which an invasive cancer was detected were directly addressed to the Digestive Service. RESULTS The program was offered to 35,005 (37.8 %) of the eligible population of Cantabria at the end of study period. 2,384 persons participated (32.1%). The main colonoscopy findings were 1 «in situ» cancer, 2 invasive cancer and 43 high-risk adenomas. CONCLUSION Due to its integration into primary care, lack of apparatus, ease use and fast implementation, qualitative immunochemical test FOBT facilitates the extension of screening, with similar results to those of quantitative immunochemical test.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del programa de detección precoz de cáncer colorrectal en Cantabria durante el periodo noviembre de 2008 a marzo de 2010.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Results of the screening program for colorectal cancer screening in Cantabria, Spain, during the period November 2008-March 2010].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
