<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21339014</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castillo, O A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marchetti, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION the management of anterior urethral stricture is controversial. A review article was written, which updates the current situation of the surgical treatment of anterior urethral stricture. MATERIALS AND METHODS the experience of the Hospital del Trabajador in Santiago de Chile regarding its different surgical approaches, as well as scientific literature on the topic, were reviewed. RESULTS traditionally, anterior urethral stricture has been treated using minimally invasive techniques (dilatation and internal urethrotomy), which are unable to cure more than 30-35% of patients. On the other hand, urethral reconstruction surgery (urethroplasty) is more complex and requires training, however it can cure a wide majority of patients in a single surgical procedure. Due to a lack of experience and training in reconstructive surgery, non-invasive methods are overused and abused, to the detriment of the patients' quality of life. There is substantial evidence that internal urethrotomy is an excellent method for treating stricture of up to 1cm in length, however its efficacy decreases drastically above 1.5cm. Notwithstanding, urethroplasty is directly indicated for larger strictures, especially if prior urethrotomy failed. CONCLUSION this procedure must be managed selectively, applying the appropriate treatment aimed at curing and not only palliating the disease. Urologists must be better trained in urethroplasty and/or centres of excellence must be established to be able to offer the best treatment in each case.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo racional y selectivo de los pacientes con estenosis de uretra anterior.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rational and selective management of patients with anterior urethral stricture disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
