<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21334273</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calleja Gero, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sevilla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Madero, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To analyse the characteristics of children with chronic ITP (chronic immune thrombocytopenia) in the Hospital Infantil Universitario Niño Jesús (HIUNJ) between 2003 and 2008. To also evaluate whether clinical variables as age, gender, initial platelet count, and treatment have any prognostic significance on the outcome of ITP. PATIENTS AND METHODS Data were retrospectively collected from 288 patients diagnosed with "Purpura and other haemorrhagic illnesses". Forty-two out of these 288 satisfied the criteria for "chronic ITP". RESULTS Ten patients out of 42 (23.8%) achieved remission with splenectomy, and 25 (almost 60%) achieved it without splenectomy (14 were complete remissions and 11 were partial remissions). Eight patients (almost 20% of patients with chronic ITP) had spontaneous remissions between 6 and 12 months from initial diagnosis. None of the clinical variables analysed were related to the outcome of the disease and the prognosis of the disease. CONCLUSIONS Almost 60% of children with chronic ITP achieve remission without treatment regardless of age, gender, initial treatment or platelet count. Splenectomy is one of the treatments with best results; however the high spontaneous recovery rate in children with cITP, the low percentage of bleeding, and the generally benign outcome should encourage delaying this as long as possible. As it is possible to have a remission between 6 and 12 months from the initial diagnosis, the term "chronic" should be reserved for patients with ITP lasting more than 1 year.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuál es el pronóstico de la trombopenia inmunitaria crónica?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[What is the prognosis of chronic immune thrombocytopenia?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
