<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2135560</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-5504</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Onorato, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soltero, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zambrano, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pietri, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Echocardiographically determined left ventricular mass, diastolic septal and posterior wall thickness and end-systolic wall stress, as well as electrocardiographic indexes of left ventricular enlargement (Sokolow-Lyon index and Romhilt-Estes score) and of left atrial enlargement (P terminal index) were correlated with resting and exercise systolic and diastolic blood pressures, and with several parameters of body size (weight, height, body surface area, Quetelet index), in 130 school children (61 boys, 69 girls) 6 to 15 years of age. Parameters of body size had a positive correlation both with systolic and diastolic blood pressures and with parameters of left ventricular size. Thus, the latter were adjusted for body surface area, for correlation with blood pressure. Left ventricular mass and diastolic septal and posterior wall thickness had a very poor correlation with resting and exercise diastolic blood pressures. Left ventricular mass and diastolic posterior wall thickness had a significantly higher correlation with peak exercise systolic blood pressure than with resting systolic blood pressure. End-systolic wall stress had a positive correlation with resting diastolic and systolic blood pressures. Electrocardiographic parameters of left ventricular and left atrial enlargement had a very poor correlation with resting and exercise blood pressure. Our findings suggest that early in life left ventricular mass and wall thickness are more closely related to maximal systolic blood pressure during physical exercise than to blood pressure in basal conditions. The electrocardiogram is an insensitive method to detect early modifications of left ventricular size in relation to different levels of blood pressure. The echocardiogram is the method of choice for this purpose.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parametros morfológicos y funcionales del ventrículo izquierdo (masa, grosor parietal y stress parietal telesistólico) en escolares con diferentes niveles de presión arterial, en reposo y durante el ejercicio máximo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Morphological and functional parameters of the left ventricle (mass, wall thickness and end-systolic stress) in school children with different levels of blood pressure, at rest and during maximal exercise].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta cientifica venezolana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
