<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21416918</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8376</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruvalcaba-Limón, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Romero, Consuelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escudero-de los Ríos, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cantú-de-León, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cepeda-López, Friedman Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas-Sánchez, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gerson-Cwilich, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cantón-Romero, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Castro, Juan Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Matus, Rolando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Rubí, Lesbia María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santillán-Gómez, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Trejo, Amelia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores-Alvarez, Efrén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega-Rojo, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guevara-Torres, Alfonso Genaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Cervantes, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tirado-Gómez, Laura Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montalvo-Esquivel, Gonzalo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morán-Mendoza, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villavicencio-Valencia, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Garza-Salazar, Jaime G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacios-Martínez, Alma Georgina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isla-Ortiz, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herbert-Núñez, Guillermo Sidney</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dueñas-González, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomeque-López, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kuri-Exsome, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salas-Gonzáles, Efraín</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Enciso, Aarón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Botello-Hernández, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brom-Valladares, Rocío</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alfaro-Ramírez, Paulino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Souto-del-Bosque, Rosalía</dc:author>
<dc:author>León-Rodríguez, Eucario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés-Esteban, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Hernández, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mora-Aguilar, Víctor Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Montiel, María Delia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Capdeville-García, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mota-García, Aída</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robles-Flores, Juan Ubaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales-Vásquez, Flavia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cetina-Pérez, Lucely de Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallardo-Rincón, Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-de-León, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales-Palomares, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coronel-Martínez, Jaime Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Obispo, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Lobatón, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez-Avitia, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castorena-Roji, Gerardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jesús-Sandoval, Ramiro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barragán-Curiel, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crismatt-Zapata, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solorza-Luna, Gilberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oñate-Ocaña, Luis Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sosa-Sánchez, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Novoa-Vargas, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Hernández, Dulce María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Rivera, Samuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torrescano-González, Salvador</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar-Jiménez, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera-Galeana, Paula Anel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ochoa-Carrillo, Francisco J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alanís-López, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cervantes-Sánchez, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quijano-Castro, Félix</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murillo-Cruz, Dino Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trejo-Durán, Elizabeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Juan Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Barrera, Luis Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano-Olvera, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-López, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morgan-Villela, Gilberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aranda-Flores, Carlos Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés-Cárdenas, Seir Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poveda-Velasco, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arrieta-Rodríguez, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maffuz-Aziz, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias-Ceballos, José Héctor Reynaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valle-Solís, Aura Erazo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz-González, David Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Endometrial cancer (EC) is the second most common gynecologic malignancy worldwide in the peri and postmenopausal period. Most often for the endometrioid variety. In early clinical stages long-term survival is greater than 80%, while in advanced stages it is less than 50%. In our country there is not a standard management between institutions. GICOM collaborative group under the auspice of different institutions have made the following consensus in order to make recommendations for the management of patients with this type of neoplasm. MATERIAL AND METHODS The following recommendations were made by independent professionals in the field of Gynecologic Oncology, questions and statements were based on a comprehensive and systematic review of literature. It took place in the context of a meeting of four days in which a debate was held. These statements are the conclusions reached by agreement of the participant members. RESULTS Screening should be performed women at high risk (diabetics, family history of inherited colon cancer, Lynch S. type II). Endometrial thickness in postmenopausal patients is best evaluated by transvaginal US, a thickness greater than or equal to 5 mm must be evaluated. Women taking tamoxifen should be monitored using this method. Abnormal bleeding in the usual main symptom, all post menopausal women with vaginal bleeding should be evaluated. Diagnosis is made by histerescopy-guided biopsy. Magnetic resonance is the best image method as preoperative evaluation. Frozen section evaluates histologic grade, myometrial invasion, cervical and adnexal involvement. Total abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo oophorectomy, pelvic and para-aortic lymphadenectomy should be performed except in endometrial histology grades 1 and 2, less than 50% invasion of the myometrium without evidence of disease out of the uterus. Omentectomy should be done in histologies other than endometriod. Surgery should be always performed by a Gynecologic Oncologist or Surgical Oncologist, laparoscopy is an alternative, especially in patients with hypertension and diabetes for being less morbid. Adjuvant treatment after surgery includes radiation therapy to the pelvis, brachytherapy, and chemotherapy. Patients with Stages III and IV should have surgery with intention to achieve optimal cytoreduction because of the impact on survival (51 m vs. 14 m), the treatment of recurrence can be with surgery depending on the pattern of relapse, systemic chemotherapy or hormonal therapy. Follow-up of patients is basically clinical in a regular basis. CONCLUSIONS Screening programme is only for high risk patients. Multidisciplinary treatment impacts on survival and local control of the disease, including surgery, radiation therapy and chemotherapy, hormonal treatment is reserved to selected cases of recurrence. This is the first attempt of a Mexican Collaborative Group in Gynecology to give recommendations is a special type of neoplasm.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Consensus Development Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primer consenso Mexicano de cancer de endometrio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The first Mexican consensus of endometrial cancer. Grupo de Investigación en Cáncer de Ovario y Tumores Ginecológicos de México].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de investigacion clinica; organo del Hospital de Enfermedades de la Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
