<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21412392</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fierro-Arias, Leonel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-González, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peniche-Castellanos, Amelia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ponce-Olivera, Rosa María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Skin cancer is the most common malignant neoplasm reported worldwide. Over the last 20 years, skin cancer has been recognized in a high proportion among young people not associated with genetic disorders or other diseases. In Mexico there is no epidemiological information about this topic, so we made a retrospective study from 2006 to 2009 in the Dermatology service of the General Hospital of Mexico. We included 730 patients with diagnosis of primary skin cancer; 51 cases occurred in people younger than 40 years with an average age of 38 years, and with an estimated accumulated incidence of 6.8% for the elapsed time. In this study, skin cancer in young people showed a predominance of women (67% of patients); basal cell carcinoma was the most common type. Most of the lesions were found in sun-exposed areas. Skin cancer in people younger than 40 years is increasing dramatically, so we recommend avoiding ultraviolet radiation exposure in childhood and adolescence, and implementing sun-protection campaigns in order to educate this sector of the population and make them more aware of the potential dangers.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de piel en pacientes menores de 40 años. Experiencia de cuatro años en el Hospital General de México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Skin cancer in adults younger than 40 years at the General Hospital of Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
