<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21450504</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil-Prieto, Ruth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Veloso-Carrasco, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vernich-Oliver, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ahijado-Porres, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-de Miguel, Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study the non-delivery pregnancy associated hospitalizations in Spain during the period 1997-2007. METHODS A descriptive epidemiological study was performed using data from the National Epidemiological Surveillance System for hospital data (Minimum Basic Data Set [MBDS]). Records of all pregnant women admitted to hospital with a pregnancy associated complication (excluding delivery) as a principal admitting diagnosis were studied. RESULTS There were a total of 4,506,449 deliveries reported in Spain during the study period (1997-2007), with a hospitalization rate of 11.86% deliveries (95% CI, 11.83%-11.89%). The principal admitting diagnoses were abortions (10%), abnormal products of conception and non-viable pregnancies (1.5%). The mortality rate was 2.35 per 100,000 deliveries (95% CI, 1.9%-2.8%) and the case-fatality rate was 0.02% (95% CI, 0.016%-0.024%). Adolescents and women over 45 years had higher hospitalization and mortality rates. CONCLUSIONS The main causes for hospitalization in pregnant women in Spain were abortions, abnormal products of conception and non-viable pregnancies. Hospitalization and mortality rates were higher in adolescents and women over 45 years, and did not vary during the study period.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hospitalizaciones de mujeres embarazadas en España entre 1997 y 2007.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hospitalizations during pregnancy in Spain in 1997-2007].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
