<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21458702</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez-Vázquez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campos, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oteo, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">International agencies such as the World Health Organization (WHO), the European Union (EU), the European Centre for Disease Control and Prevention, and the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention have carried out various strategies to fight the emergency and spread of antimicrobial resistance. These strategies include surveillance of resistance and use, reduction of the disease burden through vaccination, and measures to control infection and to educate citizens and health professionals. Understanding of antibiotics among the general population is usually poor, so educational activities directed at the public and at health professionals are parts of the majority of campaigns to reduce inappropriate use of antibiotics. From 1990 to 2007, 22 large campaigns have been executed; in Spain, 2 national campaigns were launched in the autumn of 2006 and 2007 with the slogan, "Responsible use of antibiotics. Using them well today will protect us tomorrow". The EU and the WHO recommend the creation of interdisciplinary work groups, supported by the authorities, to promote the development of action plans and national strategies to combat antimicrobial resistance. To be effective, the national campaigns for prudent use of antibiotics should be continuous and carried out within a national strategy for improving the use of antimicrobials.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las estrategias internacionales y las campañas para promover el uso prudente de los antibióticos en los profesionales y los usuarios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[International strategies and campaigns to promote the prudent use of antibiotics by health professionals and patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
