<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21478062</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Oyarzabal Irigoyen, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Casado, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Lacruz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Rigual, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Gila, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hermoso López, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rica Etxebarria, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Cuartero, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luzuriaga Tomás, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barrio Castellanos, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Glucose monitoring methods have made great advances in the last decade with the appearance of the continuous glucose monitoring systems (CGMS) that measure the glucose levels in the interstitial liquid, providing information about glucose patterns and trends, but do not replace the self-monitoring of capillary glucose. Improvement in diabetes control using the CGMS depends on the motivation and training received by the patient and family and on the continuity in its use. Due to the development and widespread use of these systems in clinical practice, the diabetes group of the Sociedad Española de Endocrinología Pediátrica has drafted a document of consensus for their indication and use in children and adolescents. Only a limited number of trials have been performed in children and adolescent populations. More data are needed on the use of this technology in order to define the impact on metabolic control.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual y recomendaciones sobre la utilización de los sistemas de monitorización continua de glucosa en niños y adolescentes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Current status and recommendations on the use of continuous blood glucose monitoring systems in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
