<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21484722</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bardwell, Wayne A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guglielmi, Ottavia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jurado-Gámez, Bernabé</dc:author>
<dc:author>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Ana I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) is a chronic illness characterized by episodes of upper airway obstruction during sleep. Mood disturbance has been frequently related to OSAS, but there is no a consensus among results of different studies. AIMS. To assess depression and anxiety of patients with SAHS, and to determine which of polysomnographic variables that best predicts the mood of the patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS The sample consisted of 100 subjects: 50 patients with OSAS diagnosed with traditional poly-somnography, and 50 without OSAS symptoms. Both groups answered the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory and the State and Trait Depression Questionnaire. RESULTS The results demonstrate that the patients with OSAS show higher scores in depression and anxiety than the control group. The variables that better predict the OSAS patient's mood symptoms were body mass index and total sleep time. CONCLUSIONS This study shows the effect of the OSAS in the mood of the patients and confirms the complex relation between obesity, quality of sleep and mood disorder in OSAS patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 May 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad y calidad de sueño: predictores de la depresión y la ansiedad en pacientes con síndrome de apnea-hipopnea del sueño.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Obesity and sleep quality: the predictors of depression and anxiety in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
