<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21519765</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cantó, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes, Maria D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wanden-Berghe, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Moya, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domenech, Maria D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz Valero, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The PEG is shown as a technique rather aggressive and with few complications. These characteristics have become the route of choice for enteral nutrition in patients who require nutritional support for prolonged periods. OBJECTIVES To know the evolution and quality of life of patients and caregivers with nutrition through PEG. METHODS Retrospective study of patients with PEG in a district hospital from July 1998 to July 2009. We reviewed hospital records and telephone contact with patients. RESULTS There were 299 patients with PEG during the study period. There was a gradual increase in its use for nutritional therapy. Males were 152 (50.8%). There were 152 (50,8%) males. The age was 73.62 ± 13,05 years, males being the youngest (t = 5.07, P &lt; 0.001). The most frequent indication was "neurological disease" 222 (85.7%). The duration of nutrition therapy was 390 days (range 1-2,913) showing independent from the rest of the variables. The completion of treatment was on death 134 (93.1%) or recovering the mouth 10 (6.9%). The QL was significantly improved in both patients (Z = -6.59, p &lt; 0.001) and caregivers (Z = -6.83, P &lt; 0.001) after PEG. CONCLUSIONS There is a progressive increase in the use of PEG. with the mean time of treatment greater than one year, and being complete in most patients with the death. The quality of life experienced an improvement after PEG in both patients and caregivers in this series.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gastrostomía Endoscópica Percutánea (PEG): diez años de experiencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Percutaneous Endoscopic Gastrostomy (PEG): ten years of experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
