<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21537805</identifier>
<setSpec>1606-7916</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Che-Mendoza, Azael</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Fernández, Mariana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dzul-Manzanilla, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manrique-Saide, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guillermo-May, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Bejarano, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villegas-Trejo, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Danis-Lozano, Rogelio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ulloa-García, Armando</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the relative importance of Aedes aegyti breeding sites for potential targeted dengue control interventions in Morelos. MATERIAL AND METHODS Cross-sectional entomological surveys were conducted and collection of Ae. aegypti pupae was taken from all water-holding containers in Cuautla, Jojutla and Tlaquiltenango during dry (1,713 households) and rainy (1,677) seasons in 2008. Relative importance of different types of breeding sites was determined by the contribution (%) to total pupae production within each locality. RESULTS In Cuautla most pupae during the dry season were found in wash basins (48.5%), tanks and buckets/pots (15% each); during the rainy season, diverse small items (21.3%), buckets/pots (19.3%) and plant pots (12.9%) were more productive. In Jojutla and Tlaquiltenango, 97% of all pupae was found in plant pots during the dry season; during the rainy season diverse small items (26.3%), washing/cooking utensils (13.9%), buckets/pots (12.9%) and plant pots (12.7%) were significant. CONCLUSION Prevention and control of the dengue vector should be based on this kind of evidence to target the most productive breeding-sites.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control enfocado de Aedes aegypti en localidades de alto riesgo de transmisión de dengue en Morelos, México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Targeted treatment of Aedes aegypti at localities with high risk for dengue transmission, Morelos, Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
