<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21548254</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fuentes-Nucamendi, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bonfil-Ojeda, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Bonilla, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camarena-Hernández, H P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective of this study is to show that the Ludloff-Ferguson approach is feasible in patients aged 2-4 years and as an outpatient procedure. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective, longitudinal, clinical-trial type of study, conducted from January 2008 to December 2009. Patients aged 2-4 years with a diagnosis of congenital hip dislocation were included. All of them underwent open reduction using the Ludloff-Ferguson approach as an outpatient procedure and they wore a Callot type of cast for 6 weeks. Bilateral hips were treated in a single stage. The study variables included the age, sex, operative time, bleeding, anesthetic time, infections and avascular necrosis of the femoral head. A nonrandomized, non-probabilistic sampling was performed; the statistical analysis included the central trend and scatter measurements, the relative risk, the Spearman correlation and chi2. RESULTS Fifteen patients were included, 8 females and 7 males, for a total of 21 hips. The latter included 4 left and 3 right hips, and 7 cases were bilateral. Median age was 3 years (range 2-4 years). The mean bleeding was 20 cc with a SD of 5 cc (range: 15-30 cc). The mean operative time was 25 minutes, SD = 7 minutes (range: 17-30 minutes). The chi2 test rejected the Ho for sex and necrosis, and age and avascular necrosis, with a P = 0.005. The results of the Spearman test for sex and necrosis were r = 0.23, P = 0.002, for age and necrosis r = 0.25, and a P = 0.003, for the operative time and avascular hip necrosis r = 0.28, P = 001. There were no infections. DISCUSSION The open reduction technique with the Ludloff-Ferguson approach is feasible in patients aged 2-4 years as an outpatient procedure, and the risk of avascular necrosis was minimum.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vía de Ludloff-Ferguson para luxación congénita de caderas en niños de 2 a 4 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The Ludloff-Ferguson approach for congenital hip dislocation in children ages 2-4 years].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
