<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21565439</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Natanek, Samantha Amanda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Polkey, Michael Iain</dc:author>
<dc:author>Riddoch-Contreras, Joanna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kemp, Paul Robert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hopkinson, Nicholas Stephen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moxham, John</dc:author>
<dc:author>Man, William D-C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marsh, Gemma Sarah</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Yin Yang 1 (YY1) is a transcriptional repressor that inhibits muscle gene expression and myogenesis. YY1 has not previously been investigated in the skeletal muscle of patients with COPD. The aims of this study were to investigate YY1 expression and localisation in the quadriceps muscle of COPD patients compared to healthy age-matched controls, and examine the relationship between YY1 expression and localisation and quadriceps muscle fibre cross-sectional area (CSA) in COPD patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS 15 COPD patients and 8 age-matched controls underwent lung and quadriceps function assessments and a percutaneous quadriceps biopsy. Quadriceps muscle fibre CSA and fibre proportions and YY1 localisation were determined by immunofluorescence. YY1 was immunoprecipitated from muscle and YY1 levels assessed by western blotting. RESULTS YY1 levels were inversely correlated with type IIx and type I fibre CSA in patients and controls, though YY1 levels were not significantly different between the groups. Nuclear localisation of YY1 was demonstrated in the patients but not in controls. CONCLUSION YY1 expression is associated with smaller quadriceps fibre CSA in COPD and nuclear localisation of YY1 was found in muscle of patients but not controls. Regulation of YY1 appears altered in COPD and may be implicated in COPD-related muscle atrophy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Yin Yang 1 expression and localisation in quadriceps muscle in COPD.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
