<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21623394</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Monzón-Jiménez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quori, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lago-Alonso, M M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Checa-de-Andrés, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Díaz, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Cantón, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baamonde-Laborda, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toledo-González, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Cabrillana, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Bacterial infections pose a major challenge to risk management activities in the area of chronic haemodialysis, as vascular access-related infections are the main cause of mortality among these patients. METHODS Prospective surveillance study lasting 7 months (March-September, 2008) at two haemodialysis units in a district health area Gran Canaria, Spain. We used the methodology proposed by CDC´s Dialysis Surveillance Network. RESULTS 1545 patients/month were recorded, 60.5% with an arteriovenous fistula (AVF), 35.5% with a permanent catheter (PC), 3.0% with grafts and 1.0% with temporary catheters. The rate of adverse events was 8.6 cases per 100 patients/month, 9.1 for AVF patients, and 2.9 for PC. Nevertheless, the other types of infections (respiratory, urinary tract, skin and chronic ulcers) showed similar rates. Microbiological cultures were taken in 82.2%, but this rate increased to 91.0% when a vascular access-related infection was suspected. Empirical treatment was adjusted to antibiogram results in 90.0% of occasions. A low incidence of multi-resistant microbes was observed. Gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria appeared in similar proportions. CONCLUSIONS Vascular access is the main risk factor for infectious events. Epidemiological surveillance has allowed us to detect areas of improvement in different settings, acting as a key element in risk management and patient safety.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surveillance for infections and other adverse events in dialysis patients in southern Gran Canaria.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
