<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21638890</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Molina, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Farrero, Sara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carulla, Josefina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albero, Inma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tosquella, Roser</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cerdà, Carme</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llinas, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aceituno, Angeles</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION children's Hospital Vail d'Hebron in 2007 children admitted 7086, requiring isolation 440 (6.2%). The purpose of this study was to raise the overall level of adherence to the basic precautions of isolation. The nursing management by objectives allowed us to raise as a management strategy in pediatric inpatient units, improved compliance with isolation measures, multidisciplinary goal framed the need for pediatric patient safety OBJECTIVES to achieve compliance with the protocol of isolation described in 80-90% of patients. METHODOLOGY it provides all pediatric units a dossier of consultation on the types of insulation and measures to follow, informative posters in the areas of work and training sessions. It develops and implements a standardized checklist for the proper performance of isolation measures in two of the six child health. RESULT working in an MBO has focus and unify the resources for the improvement in the performance of isolates. In the units where they have implemented the checklist has found a fulfillment of isolation measures in 96% of cases. CONCLUSIONS this experience has allowed us to confirm that the strategies carried out by monitoring compliance contribute to a more effective isolation measures hospital and export the model of implementation of the checklist to other pediatric units.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Precauciones de aislamiento en un hospital pediátrico estrategias de gestión para mejorar su cumplimiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Design and implementation of management strategies for the improvement in the implementation of the warnings of isolation in a pediatric hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
