<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21640986</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Biondo, Sebastiano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millán, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frago, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trenti, Loris</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fraccalvieri, Domenico</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kreisler, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alba, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Golda, Thomas</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The high morbidity and mortality of emergency surgery, has led to the use of endoluminal self-expanding metal implants (stents) in the management of intestinal occlusion. The purpose of this study was to review the results of the management of intestinal occlusion treatment in a Colorectal Surgery Unit in those patients who had a stent implant, and the relationship between chemotherapy and complications. MATERIAL AND METHODS A retrospective study was carried out on patients treated with a stent in a university hospital between 2004 and 2010. RESULTS A total of 93 patients were treated, of which 77 were considered palliative for a stage IV neoplasm of the colon with non-resectable metastases or due to a performance status &gt; 2. Other indications were 7 ASA IV patients with acute renal failure, 6 with benign disease, and 3 due to other causes. The technical and clinical success of the procedure was 93.5% and 78.5%, respectively. Delayed occlusion was 19.3% and perforation 6.4%. There was migration (2.1%) and intestinal bleeding (2.1%) and 1.1% with tenesmus. No significant differences were seen between complications and chemotherapy. The overall mortality was 17.2%. CONCLUSIONS Stents, as a definitive treatment option in palliative patients with and without chemotherapy, is an alternative treatment that is not exempt from complications. We believe that in patients with mortality risk factors and patients with tumours with non-resectable metastases it could be the initial treatment of choice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones del tratamiento de la oclusión del colon distal con prótesis endoluminales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Complications of distal intestinal occlusion treatment with endoluminal implants].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
