<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21666984</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Altermir Trallero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrejas Gómez, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocón Bretón, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Biliopancreatic diversion (BPD) is a malabsorptivebariatric procedure can lead to the development of several nutritional complications, including fat-soluble vitamins deficiencies. Routine supplementation with vitamins and trace elements and a close follow-up long-term can prevent these nutritional risks. Vitamin A participates in ocular metabolism, epithelial differentiation, growth, and embryogenesis. Have been described several cases of ophthalmological and fetal complications associated with vitamin A deficiency in patients who have undergone BPD. Few information exists in literature about dermatologic manifestations that may occur in these patients. Phrynoderma is a type of follicular hyperkeratosis located on the extensor surfaces of the extremities whose main cause is vitamin A deficiency. We report an exceptional case of severe cutaneous and ocular complications in a patient who had undergone BPD with poor adherence to treatment and postoperative follow-up. Our patient presented simultaneously the characteristic skin lesions of phrynoderma with nytalopia and xerophthalmia in a setting of low serum levels of vitamin A. Treatment with high doses vitamin A obtained the resolution of both processes. We review and discuss the relationship between phrynoderma, malnutrition and vitamin A deficiency.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frinoderma secundario a déficit de vitamina A en un paciente con derivación biliopancreática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Phrynoderma secondary to vitamin A deficiency in a patient with biliopancreatic diversion].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
