<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21665331</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Clemente Jiménez, María Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Cantera, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bartolomé Moreno, Cruz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sobradiel Sierra, Natalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puente, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio Aranda, Encarnación</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the number of passive smokers, the environments where exposure to second-hand smoke (SHS) is higher, the opinion of smokers and non-smokers with regard to these spaces and their influence on smoking. DESIGN Descriptive and cross-sectional observational study of a convenience sample. LOCATION Multi-centre, Spanish Health-care Centres. PARTICIPANTS A total of 9733 people older than 16 years who were seen or were working in Spanish Health-care Centres in April 2008. MAIN MEASUREMENTS Smoker condition, gender, profession and their opinion with regard to second-hand smoke (SHS) exposure. RESULTS A total of 42.4% of participants considered themselves second-hand (passive) smokers in public places and 96.8% in indoor areas. Almost all of them (91.8%) considered SHS exposure harmful for non-smokers, Smoke-free environments were considered to be good for discouraging people from starting to smoke (70.3%), and for quitting smoking (71.8%). Smoke-free environments were preferred by 81.1%. They felt more exposed SHS inside a car (79.8%) and in cafes (34.7%). Non-smokers, both men and women, shared these opinions significantly (P&lt;.05). CONCLUSIONS Altogether, those surveyed considered themselves as second-hand smokers and think that smoke-free environments reduce the impact of smoking and help in quitting smoking. Besides, they prefer living in those environments. Considering the preferences of most of the population, this stresses the need to urge governments to establish legislative measures promoting smoke-free environments.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitudes de los españoles frente a los espacios libres de humo de tabaco.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Spanish opinions on tobacco smoke-free areas].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
