<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21713361</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vargas, Sergio Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, Diego Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cornejo, José William</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Endovascular therapy is a technique accepted throughout the world for the treatment of ruptured and non-ruptured intracranial aneurysms. In Colombia, however, no summary data have been published that validate the method in terms of occlusion grade and morbimortality. OBJECTIVE The clinical and angiographic outcomes were evaluated for endovascular embolization of 473 intracranial aneurysms treated during a 12 year time interval. MATERIALS AND METHODS Between 1996-2008, 473 intracranial aneurysms treated by an endovascular approach were included in the current retrospective study. Pre and postprocedural angiographic images were analyzed, and clinical outcome was recorded according to the Glasgow coma scale. Immediate angiographic results and morbimortality were evaluated. RESULTS The technical feasibility of the procedure was 96.8%. According to Hunt and Hess scale, 8.7% patients were classified as grade I, 35.7% grade II, 19.2% grade III and 7.8% grades IV/V. Non-ruptured aneurysms had occurred in 28.5% of patients. Immediate procedural angiography demonstrated total occlusion in 69.6%, neck remnant in 17.5% and partial or failed occlusion in 16.1%. Global mortality was 10.4% and procedural mortality was 1.5%. Technique-associated complications presented in 7.6% of treated aneurysms. CONCLUSION Endovascular treatment of intracranial aneurysms was associated with low morbimortality and high technical feasibility. The results are comparable with other published data summaries and supporting the use of the method in Colombia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular de 473 aneurismas intracraneanos: resultados angiográficos y clínicos Experiencia colombiana, 1996-2008.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endovascular coil occlusion of 473 intracranial aneurysms: angiographic and clinical results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
