<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21757284</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ginès, Angels</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sendino, Oriol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Esparrach, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main purpose of staging in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is to assess mediastinal lymph node involvement, with thoracic CT being the main non-invasive test for this. However, given that up to 15% of patients who show no mediastinal lymph node involvement in the CT have lymph node metastasis during surgery, other examinations are required. Endoscopic ultrasonography guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has shown to be able to detect advanced disease (metastatic mediastinal lymph nodes, adrenal metastasis, mediastinal invasion by the tumour) in approximately 25% of patients with a CT that suggested a non-advanced disease. Another situation in which CT has a very limited value is in the evaluation of the response to induction therapy, with its most limiting factor being its intrinsic inability to distinguish between a tumour and necrosis. In this context, EUS-FNA has shown to have a good performance, with a sensitivity, negative predictive value and precision of 75%, 67% and 83%, respectively. In conclusion, EUS-FNA may be considered a good alternative in the pre-operative staging of patients with NSCLC, with and without diseased mediastinal lymph nodes in CT, and could play an important role in the mediastinal re-staging of these patients by identifying a patient sub-group who might benefit from additional surgical treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas aplicaciones de la ultrasonografía endoscópica (USE) en el cáncer de pulmón: evaluación de pacientes con mediastino negativo por TC y reestadificación después de tratamiento neoadyuvante.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[New endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) applications in lung cancer: evaluation of patients with negative mediastinal CT and re-staging after neoadjuvant treatment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
