<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21794689</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de la Puente, M A Del Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Rodríguez, Norberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibáñez Ruán, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Pérez, Marisol</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the main causes of neuropathic osteoarthropathy of the shoulder is cervical syringomyelia. Chronic pain and swelling of the shoulder are the most frequent manifestations, but it occasionally can develop rapid osteoarticular destructive lesions (in less than six weeks), which raise the diagnostic possibility of septic arthritis and some tumours We present the report of two men with septic arthritis of the shoulder associated with neuropathic arthropathy secondary to syringomyelia. Both patients presented with sudden shoulder pain exacerbated by either passive or active joint movements, malaise and fever. The first patient, a 39-year-old man, suffered left shoulder arthritis due to Staphylococcus aureus. The second patient, a 59-year-old man presented with right shoulder arthritis caused by to Staphylococcus epidermidis. The last microorganism also was isolated in three blood cultures. Infection should certainly be considered as a possible complication of the natural history of the neuropathic shoulder.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis séptica como complicación de la artropatía neuropática del hombro asociada a siringomielia cervical.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Septic arthritis complicating neuropathic shoulder due to cervical syringomyelia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
