<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21794724</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez-Salazar, José Rosas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo Catalá, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Román Ivorra, José A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate and characterize the current status of the Rheumatology Day Hospital Care units in the Autonomous Community of Valencia. MATERIAL AND METHOD A structured brainstorming meeting was organized with 12 rheumatologists and a nurse and, after that, a questionnaire was sent to 20 rheumatologists to know more about the centers. RESULTS Variability was found in the services that the day care units have for their own operation and for patient care. Rheumatologists place more importance on having some services that are not present in all centers at the moment: specialized nursing, quick drug delivery from the pharmacy and administration supervision by a rheumatologist. The following deficiencies were identified: sharing the workspaces with other specialties, drug delivery delays from the pharmacy, few resources (few spaces, few locations and little time for drug administration), lack of specialized nursing, lack of some services for patients (i.e. hot-line telephone service or patient education), few clinical sessions and lack of some procedures. CONCLUSIONS It is necessary to establish measures that lead to the resolution of deficiencies and improve the services offered to patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual de los hospitales de día donde se administran los tratamientos de reumatología en la Comunidad Valenciana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Current status of day care units where rheumatology treatments are administered in the autonomous community of Valencia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
