<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21794758</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín, José-Ezequiel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda, Blanca</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bossini-Castillo, Lara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Gallo, Lina Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Systemic sclerosis or scleroderma (SSc) is an autoimmune pathology with a variable clinical expression grouped within genetically complex diseases, in which environmental and genetical factors combine. Genes of the HLA regions were those first associated with susceptibility to present SSc, mainly the HLA-DRB1⁎11/⁎06/⁎16 allelles. However, through association studies, different candidate genes that belong to the triad of autoimmunity, endothelial disfunction and fibrosis have been proposed as genes implicated in the predisposition to disease. In spite of these initial advances, up until recently most studies have had little statistical power, due to the small number of patients included and the lack of reproduction in independent populations. Recently, the development of genotyping platforms and data analysis has allowed for the application of a new type of strategy known as «genome wide association studies» the analysis of the genetics to complex diseases, which are potent tools in the study of these multifactorial diseases. This paper pretends to perform a review of the recent advances in the study of the genetics of scleroderma, presenting results obtained in the analysis of the main candidate genes outside the HLA regions and the contribution of GWAS to the understanding of the molecular mechanisms of this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genética de la esclerodermia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Genetics in scleroderma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
