<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21794674</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez López, Juan Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Valverde, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tornero Molina, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvaro-Gracia, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andreu, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Batlle Gualda, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz Fernández, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Reino Carnota, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marenco de la Fuente, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carreño Pérez, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanmartí Sala, Raimon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balsa Criado, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Mola, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Loza Santamaría, Estíbaliz</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Álvaro, Isidoro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To provide a reference to rheumatologists and to those involved in the treatment of RA who are using, or about to use biologic therapy. METHODS Recommendations were developed following a nominal group methodology and based on systematic reviews. The level of evidence and grade of recommendation were classified according to the model proposed by the Center for Evidence Based Medicine at Oxford. The level of agreement was established through Delphi technique. RESULTS We have produced recommendations on the use of the seven biologic agents available for RA in our country. The objective of treatment is to achieve the remission of the disease as quickly as possible. Indications and nuances regarding the use of biologic therapy were reviewed as well as the evaluation that should be performed prior to administration and the follow up of patients undergoing this therapy. CONCLUSIONS We present an update on the SER recommendations for the use of biologic therapy in patients with RA.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización del Documento de Consenso de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología sobre el uso de terapias biológicas en la artritis reumatoide.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Update of the Consensus Statement of the Spanish Society of Rheumatology on the management of biologic therapies in rheumatoid arthritis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
