<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21807282</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanz, Ginés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuster, Valentín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Worldwide, the leading causes of death are ischemic heart disease and stroke. Moreover, patients with several risk factors or a history of ischemic heart disease are at a high risk of coronary event recurrence. There is evidence that primary cardiovascular disease prevention programs are effective when applied to the general population. However, therapeutic strategies designed to control several risk factors simultaneously in patients without evidence of cardiovascular disease are expensive and difficult to implement. In contrast, combination drug therapy is commonly used for secondary cardiovascular prevention and its beneficial effects on morbidity and mortality have been clearly demonstrated. Nevertheless, the actual impact of this approach is less than might be expected, partly because of poor adherence to drug regimens and the high cost of treatment in low- and middle-income countries. In patients who have had an acute myocardial infarction, the complexity of the regimen is inversely correlated ith compliance and is, in most cases, the reason for treatment discontinuation. Moreover, globally the ast majority of cardiovascular events take place in developing countries with limited health resources here access to treatment is poor. The development of fixed-dose combinations of drugs (i.e. polypills) designed for the treatment of myocardial infarction patients could help overcome these limitations, improve compliance and facilitate the distribution of and access to treatment in developing countries. We have begun a large clinical trial in five countries to investigate the beneficial effects of treatment using a polypill (i.e. aspirin, an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor and a statin) on ischemic heart disease recurrence. The results of this study could provide the basis for a new therapeutic approach to the management of not only cardiovascular disease but also diabetes and stroke.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Compuestos de dosis fija en la prevención secundaria de la cardiopatía isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fixed-dose compounds and the secondary prevention of ischemic heart disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
