<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21816692</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferrer-García, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albalat-Galera, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pablos-Monzó, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Juan, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pablos-Abella, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Elvira-Macagno, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez López, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze the effects of a home-based physical exercise program on quality of life, metabolic control, and anthropometric and biochemical parameters in people over 60 years of age with type 2 diabetes mellitus. METHODS Eighty-four Spanish patients aged over 60 years were finally randomized to participate in a home-based, combined physical exercise program (aerobic and anaerobic exercises) or to receive conventional treatment for diabetes. At 6 months, effects on quality of life (EuroQoL questionnaire). HbA1c, fasting glucose, hypoglycemic events, weight, BMI, waist circumference, blood pressure, and biochemical parameters were assessed. RESULTS Mean age of study participants was 66.7 (8.0) years. Patients in the exercise group showed an improved quality of life at six months based on EuroQol: 0.48 (0.38) vs 0.66 (0.35) and analogic scale 67.97 (18.92) vs 76.26 (20.14). An improved glycemic control was also seen: HbA1c 6.35 vs 6.0% and fasting glucose 151.2 (36.7) vs 137.6 (23.5) mg/dL, as well as a weight reduction by 1.7 kg. Hypoglycemic events did not increase. No benefits were seen in the control group. Ten subjects withdrew from the study before 6 months. CONCLUSIONS A home-based physical exercise program improves quality of life, glycemic control, and weight in type 2 diabetic patients older than 60 years.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de un programa ambulatorio de ejercicio físico en sujetos mayores con diabetes mellitus tipo 2.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Benefits of a home-based physical exercise program in elderly subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
