<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21866685</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Oliveira, Luciana Abrão</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro, Anderson Marliere</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Meirelles, Clarissa Janson Costa Souza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costa, Telma Maria Braga</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the present study was to evaluate the urinary excretion of iodine and relate it to the amount present in salt for human consumption. The study involved 145 children from two schools: a rural one and an urban one. We performed anthropometric measurements and collected a urine sample and a kitchen salt sample from each child. In the rural school, 3.38% of children had iodine deficiency. However, most of the values of urinary iodine were above 300 microg/L (62.03%) and 59.49% of the kitchen salt samples contained 20 to 60 mg iodine per kilo of salt. In the urban school, 3.03% of the children had urinary iodine excretion of less than 100 microg/L and 90.91% of the children had urinary iodine values exceeding 300 microg/L. Ofthis total, 84.85% of the kitchen salt samples contained 20 to 60 mg iodine per kilo of salt. Iodine deficiency is controlled in this population, with the current reality showing a high prevalence of excess urinary iodine.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lodação do sal e ingestão excessiva de iodo em crianças.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Salt iodination and excessive iodine intake among schoolchildren].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
