<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21866681</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Míguez Bernardez, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garcia De la Montaña, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>De la Montaña Miguélez, Julia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prevalence of obesity and level of activity physical in school adolescents. The objective of the work was to quantify the prevalence of overweight and obesity in a group of students of Ourense and its relation with the physical activity levels during school. 111 schoolares in the 5th and 6th year of primary school, with an average age of 11.3 years participated. 42.3% were women and 57.7% men. Weight, height and body mass (BMI) index were determined. Overweight and obesity were defined using as criteria the value of BMI-specific percentiles for age and sex. Physical activity (PA) level was assessed using an interview-questionnaire designed to be used with Spanish child population. 38.7% of the population presented overweight or obesity, and although the prevalence was higher in girls, no significant differences for the BMI between sexes were found. Results revealed the 61.2% of the adolescents to be inactive or very inactive, this percentage was higher for the girls than for the boys; for which the average energy expenditure (metabolic equivalent METS expressed in Kcal.kg-1 hour) is significantly smaller than the average for boys.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de obesidad y nivel de actividad física en escolares adolescentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of obesity and level of activity physical in school adolescents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
