<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21879159</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marín, Arnaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pino, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Godoy, Iván</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arnaíz, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berríos, Ximena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acevedo, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kramer, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tagle, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Carotid intima media thickness (CIMT) is a marker of cardiovascular damage that can be modified by traditional risk factors. AIM To determine attributable risk factors for a high CIMT among healthy adults. MATERIAL AND METHODS A sample of 1270 individuals (636 males and 634 females) aged 44 ± 11 years, was studied. Blood pressure, weight, height, lipid profile and blood glucose were measured in all. CIMT and the presence of atherosclerotic plaques were determined by carotid ultrasound. Standard criteria were used to define hypertension, dyslipidemia and diabetes. RESULTS Mean CIMT in the sample studied was 0.62 ± 0.01 mm and percentile 75 was 0.67. The most important risk factor for a CIMT over percentile 75 and the presence of atherosclerotic plaques was hypertension with attributable risks of 54 and 57%, respectively. CONCLUSIONS In this sample, the main risk factor for a high CIMT was hypertension.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertensión arterial: el factor de riesgo más importante para grosor íntima-media carotídeo elevado y placa carotídea en adultos de Santiago.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors for a high carotid intima media thickness among healthy adults].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
