<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21876938</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galvão, Marli Teresinha Gimenez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reis, Renata Karina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Haas, Vanderley José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gir, Elucir</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Claudia Benedita dos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Teles, Sheila Araujo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This is a cross-sectional study conducted with 228 people living with HIV/AIDS in a municipality in the State of São Paulo during 2007 and 2008. The aims of this study were to investigate the intensity of the depressive symptoms in individuals with HIV/AIDS treated at two referral units in Ribeirão Preto, Brazil, and to compare the quality of life with the different degrees of intensity of the depressive symptoms in these individuals, according to gender. Data were collected through individual interviews, using the Beck Depression Inventory and HIV/AIDS Targeted Quality of Life (HATQoL). A total of 63 (27.6%) patients with symptoms of depression (mild, moderate and severe) were detected. The women presented more severe symptoms of intensity of depression than men. Individuals with depressive symptoms presented lower scores of quality of life than individuals without these symptoms, with statistically significant differences between the means/medians in most domains of the HATQoL. Healthcare professionals should offer integral care for people with HIV/AIDS, emphasizing the depressive symptoms.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Symptoms of depression and quality of life of people living with HIV/AIDS.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
