<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21879144</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López Del P, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>López G, J Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abarca V, Katia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña D, Anamaría</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To characterize pet ownership and pet health status in families of immunocompromised (IS) children, with emphasis in zoonotic diseases. POPULATION AND METHODS Families of IS children from two hospitals in Santiago, Chile, were interviewed and their pets were evaluated by veterinary examination, coproparasitologic and skin dermatophytes test. In specific cases, other laboratory tests were performed in IS children or their relatives. RESULTS 47 out of 70 contacted families had pets, 42 participated in the study. Several risk factors for IS children were observed, as having a turtle as a pet and to clean cat or turtle faeces. Lack of adequate veterinary control, immunizations and deparasitation of pets were observed. Some animals showed zoonotic diseases or agents, as Brucella canis, Cryptosporidium sp, Giardia intestinalis, Toxocara canis and scabies. 44% of dogs had ticks and 37% had fleas, both potential vectors of infections. CONCLUSIONS Our results suggest that policies to provide safer pet contact in IS children are needed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tenencia y estado de salud de mascotas de niños inmunocomprometidos, con énfasis en enfermedades zoonóticas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pet ownership and health status of pets from immunocompromised children, with emphasis in zoonotic diseases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
