<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21889823</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carrillo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Collado-Vázquez, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Medicine and literature have been linked from ancient times; proof of this shown by the many doctors who have made contributions to literature and the many writers who have described medical activities and illnesses in their works. An example is The Egyptian, the book by Mika Waltari that provides a masterly narration of the protagonist's medical activity and describes the trepanation technique. DEVELOPMENT The present work begins with the analysis of trepanations since prehistory and illustrates the practice of the trepanation in The Egyptian. The book mentions trepanation frequently and illustrates how to practice it and which instruments are required to perform it. Trepanation is one of the oldest surgical interventions carried out as treatment for cranial trauma and neurological diseases, but it also had the magical and religious purpose of expelling the evil spirits which caused the mental illness, epilepsy, or migraine symptoms. CONCLUSIONS Trepanation is a surgical practice that has been carried out since prehistory to treat post-traumatic epilepsy, migraine, and psychiatric illness. The Egyptian is a book that illustrates the trepan, the trepanation technique, and the required set of instruments in full detail.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Historical Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Medicina egipcia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicine and literature</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antiguo Egipto</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ancient Egypt</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trepanación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>History of neurology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Egyptian medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicina y literatura</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Historia de la neurología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trepanation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cranial trepanation in The Egyptian.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
