<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21892553</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9110</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín Ivorra, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lluch Rodrigo, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor Villalba, Eliseo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portero Alonso, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz Palacio, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alguacil Ramos, Ana María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In the context of the policies of rational use of medicine, and in order to achieve an efficient management of the vaccinations programs, we expect to know the number of packings and cost of prescribed vaccines not included in the vaccination programs of Valencian Community and its departments during 2009 and to analyze its evolution since 2004, focusing on an analysis of Heptavalent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in children under two years old. METHODS Retrospective descriptive study to analyze the prescriptions of vaccines in Valencian Community during 2009 and its evolution since 2004. VARIABLES vaccine availability, number of packings, group of beneficiary (actives/pensioners), department, and cost of prescriptions. DATA SOURCES Gestor de Prestación Farmacéutica (GAIA) and Sistema Información Poblacional (SIP). RESULTS In 2009 prescribed vaccines on official national health system prescription forms that are not included in vaccination programs, supposed a cost of 683.445,71 € corresponding to 17.353 packings (87% of the total prescribed vaccines). Heptavalent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine generated 72% of the total cost of vaccines not included in the vaccination programs. The trend from 2004 to 2009 shows an increase in expenditure of 735.334 € (24,66%) in 2005 from which there takes place a marked and gradual decrease that reaches 1.562.650,67 € (-228.64%). The cost by departments of prescriptions per 1000 children under two years old of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine ranges between 17.377 and 324 €. CONCLUSIONS The declining trend of prescriptions, mainly of pneumococcal conjugate vaccines, continues during 2009. A great interdepartmental variability is observed, nevertheless, in rates of prescription that should be corrected.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción de vacunas no incluidas en el calendario vacunal en la Comunitat Valenciana durante el período 2004-2009.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Public health service prescriptions of vaccines not included in systematic vaccination programs in Valencian community, Spain, during the period 2004-2009].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
