<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21908223</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Estébanez-Carvajal, Francisca María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casals-Sánchez, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-Sánchez, María Ángeles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casals-Vázquez, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Heras-Pérez, María Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar-Trujillo, María Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the influence of dysfunctional thoughts and their relationship on the burden of caregivers. METHOD Descriptive study conducted in the San Andrés Torcal Health Centre, Malaga, Spain, in 2010. SUBJECTS A random sample was selected from dependent person caregivers of the centre. Those patients who were receiving palliative care and those cases where the care was less than 6 weeks were excluded.We used the Dysfunctional Thoughts Questionnaire (DTQ) and the short Zarit questionnaire was used on the caregivers. Sociodemographic variables of the caregiver and variables related to care (presence of support, duration of care, and if applicable, the type of help received by them), were collected. Sociodemographic variables of the patients, as well as the Barthel index and presence or absence of dementia were recorded. ANALYSIS USED: descriptive analysis, Pearson correlation coefficient to assess the association between quantitative variables and Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. RESULTS The mean DTQ score was 49.94 (95% CI; 42.0 - 49.8). The burden measured by Zarit test and dysfunctional thoughts were positively associated (Pearson correlation coefficient 0.57, P&lt;.001). CONCLUSIONS Dysfunctional thoughts have a high impact on our population of caregivers and may be a contributing factor to the onset of fatigue in the caregiver role.There is a positive association between stress of caregivers and dysfunctional thoughts, and is more intensive in caregivers of patients without dementia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los pensamientos disfuncionales en la sobrecarga de los cuidadores de personas dependientes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The influence of dysfunctional thoughts on the burden of the dependent person caregiver].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
