<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21948013</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Jiménez, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Gras, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, Gabriel</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Sánchez, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Prepulse inhibition (PPI) of startle is an operational measure of the pre-attentive filtering process known as sensorimotor gating. PPI occurs when a relatively weak sensory event (the prepulse) is presented 30-500 ms before a strong startle inducing stimulus, and reduces the magnitude of the startle response. This experimental paradigm has been studied in laboratory animal as well as in patients with schizophrenia. Recently, PPI deficits have been observed in other psychiatric disorders that shared some deficit in cognitive and sensorimotor gating. DEVELOPMENT We have reviewed studies examining prepulse inhibition in humans across some neuropsychiatric disorders for asses the clinical and neurobiological implications of this paradigm. CONCLUSIONS PPI deficits have been observed in multiple psychiatric disorders many of which present a common correlate anatomic-functional and a dysfunction in several neurotransmission systems, mainly dopamine system. These dysfunctions are independent of categorical diagnostic and they have proposed as a biological marker of vulnerability for some psychiatric disorders.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inhibición prepulso del reflejo de la respuesta de sobresalto en los trastornos neuropsiquiátricos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prepulse inhibition of the startle response/reflex in neuropsychiatric disorders].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
