<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21947097</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-9518</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Génova-Maleras, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Altés, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez-Martín, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morant-Ginestar, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catalá-López, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND There exists the need to evaluate interventions addressed to prevent, control and reduce the burden of the infectious diseases; being economic evaluation an instrument can help to allocate healthcare resources efficiently. In this context, we assessed the evolution of economic evaluation of interventions for infectious diseases published in Spain, as well as we compared their main methodological characteristics with those of the studies directed to other diseases. METHODS Systematic review and comparative analysis calculating odds ratios (OR). Electronic searches for literature beetwen 1983 and 2008 were conducted in PubMed/MEDLINE, SCOPUS, ISI Web of Knowledge, CRD, IME e IBECS, and manually in specialized journals and technical reports. The following variables were identified to analyze the characteristics of the reports: journal and year of publication, intervention, type of study, design, perspective, type of costs, financing source, and decision-making recommendations. RESULTS One-hundred and one studies were included in the review. The main characteristics of the reports were: cost-effectiveness analysis (n=56; 55.4%), treatments evaluations (n=60; 59.4%) and the use of decision analysis and mathematical simulation models (n=63; 62.4%). Economic evaluation studies of infectious diseases showed the following associations (compared to a cohort of studies of other disease conditions [n=376]): cost-benefit analysis (OR, 3.55; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.63 to 7.74), prevention (OR, 4.14; 95% CI, 2.49 to 6.90), and societal perspective (OR, 2.55; 95% CI, 1.43 to 4.56). CONCLUSION Although there is an increase in the number of economic evaluations of infectious diseases published during last decades, the studies showed heterogeneity in the quality of the information regarding methods of analysis and data sources.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica de intervenciones en enfermedades infecciosas en España: revisión sistemática y análisis comparativo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Economic evaluation of interventions for infectious diseases in Spain: systematic review and comparative analysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
