<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21959722</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sacrist치n Enciso, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mic칩, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Sande Medel, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias Meneses, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>L칩pez G칩mez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alejo, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The aim of this study was to assess serum cystatin C and urinary albumin in the early detection of impairment in cardiovascular and renal function. MATERIAL ANS METHODS: Cystatin C was quantified in sera from healthy people, moreover, cystatin C was quantified in a group of patients diagnosed with chronic kidney disease for predicting a measured glomerular filtration rate &lt;60 ml/min/1.73 m2. Finally serum cystatin C and microalbuminuria were measured in patients with increasing of risk of impairment in cardiovascular and renal function (hypertension, diabetes and hyperlipidemia). RESULTS When the serum cystatin C was quantified in a group of risk, we observe as when being increased the cystatin C, the values of the glomerular filtration rate decreased (p &lt;0.05), the cystatin values C were increased when increasing the age of the patients (p &lt;0.05) and cystatin C values higher than 0.95 mg/l were not observed in patient smaller than 50 years old. In the group of risk, serum cystatin C was high regarding to the values obtained in healthy people in 27.6%, microalbuminuria in the 20.3% and both parameters were high in the 14.4% of patients with a glomerular filtration rate &gt;90 ml/min/1.73 m2, while in patients with a glomerular filtration rate 60-90 ml/min/1.73 m2, cystatin C was high in the 51.7% and the microalbuminuria only in the 6.4%. CONCLUSIONS Determinations of serum cystatin C associated to the quantification of urinary albumin in patients with cardiovascular risk can optimize the early detection of vascular and renal damage. Cystatin C can show vascular and renal damage in patients without urinary albumin.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serum cystatin C and microalbuminuria in the detection of vascular and renal damage in early stages.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
