<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21966794</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Escartín, Minerva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manjarrez, Corinne</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vega, Genaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, Oswaldo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The teenage pregnancy is considered high risk. Often, teenagers have more episodes of eclampsia, preterm delivery, premature rupture of membranes, low birth weight, prematurity, postpartum complications, and surgical wound infections. OBJECTIVE To evaluate nutritional condition of adolescent and adult mother's sons as well as its association with sociodemographic factors in rural communities in Queretaro, Mexico. MATERIAL AND METHOD A comparative and transversal study with mothers under 20 years old and others from 20 to 35 years old whose children's range in age from 1 to 5 years old was made in Rural Health Centers. An aleatory sample with 275 children of each group was made. The association of nutritional condition with maternal age and sociodemographic variables was investigated. RESULTS The height of adolescent mothers' sons was lower [(12.4%)T/E] than adult mothers' sons [(11.6%) P/T] with an excessive weight in 22.2 vs 19.6 % respectively. There was a statistical association between premature birth and adolescent mothers of law socioeconomic means. There was a connection between underweight children (chi2, p &lt; 0.05) and mothers who had completed only elementary-level studies. However, no statistical relationship was found between the mother's age and child malnourishment, low birth weight, or the mother's level of schooling. CONCLUSIONS Chronic malnourishment was similar to the national average. Excessive weight was encountered in both groups. There was a connection between adolescent mothers of low socioeconomic means and premature birth. Low levels of schooling on the pair of the mothers were associated with underweight children. But there was no relationship between the age of the mother and low birth weight, malnourishment, or the mother's level of schooling.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de los hijos de madres adolescentes y adultas de comunidades rurales del estado de Querétaro.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study of teenase and adults in rural communities of the state of Queretaro].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
