<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21966810</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Flores-Santos, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Herrera, Ricardo Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos-González, René</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ochoa-Torres, Mauro</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Quintanilla, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Brain tumors are present in 2.9 per 100,000 newborn. Craniopharyngioma is a benign and slow growing brain tumor, frequently localized in the sellar and suprasellar region. There are few reports of pituitary tumor detected prenatally. CASE REPORT We report a neonate with a craniopharyngioma detected prenatally as a pituitary tumor. In a 23 year old mother, second gestation, with no important history, was detected a sellar tumor at 31 gestation weeks, the obstetric ultrasound reported a suprasellar tumor of 2 per 3 cm diameter. Pregnancy ended in a vaginal delivery at 39 weeks, and obtained a 3.9 kg female, with cephalic diameter of 37.5 cm, the Apgar score was 8-9 at 1st and 5th minutes. In early neonatal period was scanned and confirmed a 3.2/2.3/2.9 cm suprasellar tumor with calcium deposits. The Paediatric Oncology department suggested a surgery and was realized a craniotomy at 3rd week of age. The surgery allowed to obtain 30% of the tumor and confirmed by histology craniopharyngioma. Patient had favourable evolution and was discharged at 3 months of age. CONCLUSIONS We report a neonate in who was detected by prenatal ultrasound the presence of a suprasellar solid tumor, scan and magnetic resonance images in neonatal period defined its size and location and a craniopharyngioma was confirmed by histology. Patient had a satisfactory postsurgical evolution and was discharged at 3 months of age.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor hipofisiario detectado prenatalmente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pituitary tumor detected prenatally].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
