<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21961350</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salazar Esquivel, Edith Lucía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calzada Sánchez, Leobardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND -Na(+)-K+ ATPase is a useful marker which determines the origin of breast cancer cells. OBJECTIVE -Na(+)-K+ ATPase activity, as well as viability of plasma membrane vesicles isolated from breast carcinoma tissues were demonstrated by histochemical detection. PATIENTS AND METHOD Breast carcinoma tissue samples of patients who attended consultation in the oncology service at Hospital de Ginecoobstetricia Núm. 4 Dr. Luis Castelazo Ayala, IMSS were examined. Tissue samples from adenocarcinoma were homogenized in 4 volumes of TED solution at 4 degrees C (Tris-HCI 0.01 M, EDTA 0.0015 M, dithiothreitol 0.001 M, pH 7.4) and subsequently centrifuged. The collected sample was homogenized and stratified in a discontinuous sucrose gradient (20 to 50%) and then centrifuged for 60 min at 30,000 xg. In order to determine -Na(+)-K+ ATPase activity in plasma membrane vesicles, suspension was incubated at Tris-maleate 0.04 M, adenosine triphosphate (ATP) 0.004 M, Mgcl 20.004 M, NaCI 0.1 M y Pb (NO3) 20.005 M, pH 7.0. Reactions were carried out for 15 min at 37 degrees C in prefixed vesicles in 3% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M, cacodylate buffer stock, pH7.4 for 60 min. RESULTS Histochemical detection demonstrated membrane vesicles from breast carcinoma tissues and proved their viability after tumoral progression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2005 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad de la ATPasa-Na(+)-K+ en las vesículas de la membrana plasmática del carcinoma mamario.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[-Na(+)-K+ ATPase activity in vesicles of plasmatic membrane of breast cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
