<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21966855</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Morgan Ortiz, Fred</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Zepeda, Marco Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Total laparoscopic hysterectomy is a procedure that requires proper training so that implementation is safe and effective. OBJECTIVE To describe the clinical outcomes of the teaching of total laparoscopic hysterectomy in a university program. PATIENTS AND METHODS for a period of two years (2009-2010), 18 doctors enrolled in the diploma program in gynecological laparoscopy conducted at the Hospital Civil de Culiacán, Sinaloa, made 82 total laparoscopic hysterectomy. Were analyzed: age and gender of the participating physicians, exercise time of gynecology, general characteristics of the patients, indications, route of access to the pneumoperitoneum, duration of procedure, intraoperative and postoperative complications, size and weight of the uterus, closing time of the dome by laparoscopy and laparotomy conversion rate. RESULTS The median age of physicians was 34 years (range 28 to 50 years), 69.2% were male, seven years on average for the exercise of gynecology (range 1 to 20 years). The mean procedure time was 121.5 minutes (95% CI 110.5-132.4), the mean uterine size was 12.1 cm (95% CI 11.3-12.8) and uterine weight of 229.6 g (95%: 182.5-276.7). The average intraoperative bleeding was 133.9 mL (95% CI 112.9-154.8), hospital stay was 24.8 hours (95% CI 23.1-26.4). Major complications occurred in 1.2% of patients (95% CI 0.6-5.8). Minor complications were demonstrated in 7.3% of procedures (95% CI 3.01-14.5). The frequency of conversion to abdominal hysterectomy was 1.2% (95% CI 0.6-5.8). CONCLUSION Total laparoscopic hysterectomy was performed safely and efficiently by training students in university teaching program in gynecologic laparoscopy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enseñianza de la histerectomía total laparoscópica en un diplomado universitario de laparoscopia ginecólogica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Teaching of total laparoscopic hysterectomy in a gynecological laparoscopy university diploma course].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
