<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>21975230</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Suarez, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lenz, Ana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Landry, Luis M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barretta, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Magliola, Ricardo H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, Analía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Althabe, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salgado, Gladys</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Delucis, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Charroqui, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Laura, Juan P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pilán, María L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Krynski, Mariela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cornelis, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balestrini, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the results of congenital heart surgery at the Hospital de Pediatría J. P.Garrahan. METHODS Between 2004 and 2009, 2942 patients, median age 2.5 years (1 d to 22.5 y), median weight 11.5 kg (1.6 kg to 96 kg), and 84% with cardiopulmonary bypass, were analyzed. Adjusted mortality risk analysis using RACHS and Aristotle score was performed. Newborn surgery and one stage repair in Fallot and ventricular septal defect with coarctation were analyzed as subgroupes. RESULTS Mortality was 5.5%. Required mechanical ventilation 45%, 5% peritoneal dialysis, 12% delayed sternal closure and 8.4% reoperation. Twenty five percent with previous surgery, and 10% in poor clinical conditions. RACHS-1 categories morality distribution were 0.4% in one, 2.4% in two, 7.1% in three, 14% in four y 34 % in 5 and 6. One stage repair was performed in 84% of Fallots and 90% of ventricular septal defects with coarctation, with 3.2% and 10% mortality rate respectively. Two hundred and five newborns were operated with cardiopulmonary bypass with a mortality rate of 15% in the last year. CONCLUSIONS Almost every congenital heart disease can be repaired without previous palliation, with satisfactory results in our institution. Poor clinical conditions significantly increased morbidity and mortality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiopatías congénitas: resultados quirúrgicos en un hospital público en Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Congenital heart disease: surgical results in a public hospital in Argentina].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
