<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2202876</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pascual, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bolumar, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bruno, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez-Dardet, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To analyze the present status of rheumatological research in Spain, three indicators have been evaluated: use of the different study designs, use of statistical techniques and relevance of the studies. This last point was determined by the comparison of the research areas that had been reported during one year and the lines of rheumatological research established as priorities by 10 investigators from the 10 units of clinical care with a higher scientific output during the period 1985-1987. A revision has been made of the 67 articles from Spain out of the 1106 reported in seven of the journals with a better national and international impact index: Scandinavian Journal of Rheumatology, Arthritis and Rheumatism, Journal of Rheumatology, Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases, British Journal of Rheumatology, Clinical Experimental Rheumatology and Revue du Rhumatisme, in addition to Revista Española de Reumatología. It was found that few studies with analytical design are being published and that complex statistical analysis techniques are not being used; therefore, most articles do not have a possible statistical inference and lack value as predictors. The reports of cases and clinical series in the Letters to the Editor section are most common, particularly in the Spanish journal. Most studies are related with clinical research, although the consulted investigators consider that basic and epidemiological research have a higher priority. It is concluded that the Spanish contribution to the international rheumatological literature is still small and has a mainly descriptive character; thus, it is necessary to emphasize the use of analytical designs to improve the competitiveness. The type of studies to be carried out in the future, according to the priorities established by the investigators themselves, should change if their wishes are to be fulfilled.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 May 26 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación en Reumatología. Un análisis de la situación española.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rheumatology research. An analysis of the situation in Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
