<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22051760</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Solís, Loretto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martin, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otth, Carola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Concha, Margarita I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) is ubiquitous, neurotropic, and the most common pathogenic cause of sporadic acute encephalitis in humans. Herpes simplex encephalitis is associated with a high mortality rate and significant neurological, neuropsychological, and neurobehavioral sequels. HSV-1 infects limbic system structures in the central nervous system (CNS), and has been suggested as an environmental risk factor for Alzheimer's disease. The possibility that HSV-1 reactivates in CNS neurons causing chronic progressive damage at cellular level and altering the neuronal functionality has not been thoroughly investigated. Currently it is ignored if recurrent reactivation of HSV-1 in asymptomatic patients involves some risk of progressive deterioration of the CNS functions caused, in example, by a neuroinflammatory response against the virus or by direct toxicity of the pathogen on neurons. Therefore, studies regarding the routes of dissemination of HSV-1 from the peripheral ganglions to the CNS, as well as the possible cellular and molecular mechanisms implied in generating neuronal damage during latent and productive infection, are of much relevance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Herpes simplex virus tipo 1 como factor de riesgo asociado con la enfermedad de Alzheimer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Herpes simplex virus type 1 as risk factor associated to Alzheimer disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
