<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22056227</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez Perruca, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Suárez, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miquel Gómez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez Carramiñana, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bartolomé Benito, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Romero, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To identify and define a minimum and standard set of safety objectives in the Centre Agreement Program (CAP) of the Community of Madrid, the introduction of which has led to improved follow-up and an improvement in quality of care and patient safety in Primary Care. MATERIAL AND METHODS The key element is the Centre Agreement Program developed with the EFQM model as a reference. Methodologically, this project has followed the steps set out in the PDCA cycle., Standardised safety objectives were included in the CAP during the planning phase. Indicators have been monitored by the e-SOAP application. RESULTS We have identified 12 safety goals and 21 indicators. All the criteria of the model included some safety objectives. We highlight the following results: in the criteria relating to processes, the program cover of patients who were on several medications was 59.22%, a bio-alcohol solution was used in 93% of health facilities, 89% of Health Centres had performed a control and maintenance of vital emergency equipment. As regards communication, 1096 medication errors were notified throughout the Community of Madrid. There were 239 adverse reactions to medication and 1945 safety incidents were reported. In criterion 6, 66.22% of INR determinations were within range. There were 19.46 defined daily doses (DDD) for women of 45-65 years, and 16.9 DDD of neuroleptics in the elderly population. The indicator related to minimising drugs considered inappropriate in the elderly (Beers) was 11.9%. An average of 1.19 safety measures were adopted per Centre. For Criterion 7, 14.44% of professionals had been trained in quality and patient safety. By implementing e-SOAP, Health Centres can know their results in order to implement improvements. In addition, improvements have been set up in the 2010 CAP. CONCLUSIONS With the development of the CAP using the EFQM model as a benchmark, safety indicators have been implemented and monitored systematically in the Health Centres of the Community of Madrid. Best practices that ensure patient safety have been extended and we have begun to evaluate the impact of the health care provided in Primary Care with the measurement of indicators that the scientific evidence reveals affect patient safety.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impulso de la seguridad del paciente a partir del contrato programa de centro.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Boost for patient safety with the centre agreement program].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
