<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22056524</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barreiro, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanchez, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fermoselle, Clara</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Among the extrapulmonary manifestations of COPD, dysfunction and loss of muscle mass/weight are those that have the greatest impact on the quality of life of patients. Our objective was to evaluate the molecular mechanisms that are potentially implicated in the limited development of muscle mass in the diaphragm and gastrocnemius of mice with experimentally-induced emphysema. METHODS An experimental model in mice, in which emphysema was induced by means of the local instillation of elastase (n=6), while saline was administered to the controls (n=7). We determined the levels of oxidative stress, proteolytic systems, signaling pathways, growth factors and cell differentiation (western-blot) in the diaphragm and gastrocnemius of all the mice after 34 weeks. RESULTS Upon comparing the mice with emphysema with the controls, the following findings were observed: (1) lower total body weight and lower weight of the diaphragm and gastrocnemius; (2) in the diaphragm, the levels of protein oxidation were increased, the mitochondrial antioxidant systems reduced, the levels of myostatin and of the ERK1/2 and FoxO1 signaling pathways were higher, and the myosin content was lower (67%); and (3) in the gastrocnemius of the emphysematous mice, the cytosolic antioxidants were decreased and the levels of myostatin and of the JNK and NF-kB signaling pathways were increased. CONCLUSIONS The reduction of the myosin content observed in the diaphragm of mice with emphysema could explain their smaller size. Oxidative stress, myostatin and FoxO could be implicated in the loss of this structural protein.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción de la masa muscular mediada por miostatina en un modelo experimental de enfisema pulmonar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reduction of muscle mass mediated by myostatin in an experimental model of pulmonary emphysema].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
