<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22056421</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Palomares-Ortega, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Fernández, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Manzanares, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benito-López, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Alcántara, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The current training program for resident physicians in endocrinology and nutrition (EN) organizes their medical learning. Program evaluation by physicians was assessed using a survey. MATERIAL AND METHOD The survey asked about demographic variables, EN training methods, working time and center, and opinion on training program contents. RESULTS Fifty-one members of Sociedad Castellano-Manchega de Endocrinología, Nutrición y Diabetes, and Sociedad Andaluza de Endocrinología y Nutrición completed the survey. Forty-percent of them disagreed with the compulsory nature of internal medicine, cardiology, nephrology and, especially, neurology rotations (60%); a majority (&gt;50%) were against several recommended rotations included in the program. The fourth year of residence was considered by 37.8% of respondents as the optimum time for outpatient and inpatient control and monitoring without direct supervision. The recommended monthly number of on-call duties was 3.8±1.2. We detected a positive opinion about extension of residence duration to 4.4±0.5 years. Doctoral thesis development during the residence period was not considered convenient by 66.7% of physicians. Finally, 97.8% of resident physicians would recommend residency in EN to other colleagues. CONCLUSIONS Endocrinologists surveyed disagreed with different training program aspects such as the rotation system, skill acquisition timing, and on-call duties. Therefore, an adaptation of the current training program in EN would be required.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del programa de formación de médicos residentes en Endocrinología y Nutrición por facultativos: resultados de una encuesta.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of a residency training program in endocrinology and nutrition by physicians: results of a survey].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
