<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22078696</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barber-Vallés, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Riestra-Juán, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llahí-Vidal, Núria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Senabre-Gallego, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos-Soler, Gregorio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosas-Gómez de Salazar, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos-Ramírez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cano-Pérez, Catalina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salas-Heredia, Esteban</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Barrioluengo, Mabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the duration of etanercept (ETN) treatment and motives for discontinuation in our local cohort of patients with rheumatic pathology and compare them to the group with other biological treatments. PATIENTS AND METHODS Prospective observational cohort study. Disease diagnosis, start and end date and motive for discontinuation were recorded. Survival estimation was explored using Kaplan-Meier analysis with remaining patients censored at 1-year, 2-years and 5-years follow-up. RESULTS Ninety-two (45%) out of 205 patients started ETN treatment. Disease diagnoses recorded were: 48% rheumatoid arthritis, 33% ankylosing spondylitis, 11% psoriatic arthritis, 8% others (juvenile idiopathic arthritis, inflammatory bowel disease related spondylitis, SAPHO syndrome). 52% of patients are still on the drug. The motives for discontinuation were: inefficacy (65%), adverse events (33%) and lack of compliance (2%). Two patients discontinued ETN due to prolonged disease control. Adverse events were: infection (4 patients), post-injection skin reaction (3), uveitis (3), neoplasia (2) and others (3). Using a Kaplan-Meier analysis, at 1-year 64% (CI(95%) 54-74) of patients with ETN treatment had not experienced treatment failure, at 2-years, 59% (48-69) and at 5-years, 43% (30-52). With the rest of biologicals estimated survival was 61% (51-68), 47,5% (40-55) and 23% (10,5-32) respectively. Statistical analysis revealed significant differences (log-rank: P=.024; Breslow: P=.068; Tarone-Ware: P=.040). CONCLUSIONS In our cohort of patients treated with ETN the estimated survival was better than patients treated with other biological drugs at 1-year, 2-years and 5-years.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Duración del tratamiento con etanercept y razones de discontinuación en una cohorte de pacientes con patología reumática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Duration of treatment with etanercept and motives for discontinuation in a cohort of patients with rheumatic disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
