<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22119167</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sáez-López, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tapia-Galán, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Sáez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paniagua-Tejo, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To estimate the prevalence of using potentially inadequate drugs in the elderly population admitted to the Nuestra Señora de Sonsoles Hospital in Ávila according to Beers criteria, and to describe the impacts on these prescriptions following an educational seminar for prescribers. METHOD Before and after observational study, with two periods of 28 days each (P1 in 2008, P2 in 2009), with educational seminars on Beers criteria provided between them. All patients &gt;65 years that were admitted during both time periods in health centres with a single dose drug system were included, taking data on those with inadequate prescriptions. RESULTS The total number of hospitalised patients was 1276. Of these, 18.5% had at least one inadequate medication at P1 and 20.5% at P2, with no significant differences (χ2=0.56, P=.45). We identified a total of 295 inadequate medications (163 in P1 and 132 in P2) in 249 patients. Iron sulfate, digoxin, meperidine, and doxazosine were present in 70% of inadequate prescriptions. The prevalence of inadequate medication prescriptions did not vary between the two periods. CONCLUSION The prevalence of using potentially inadequate medications observed in this study was 23%, with no changes produced by the intervention provided.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción inadecuada de medicamentos en ancianos hospitalizados según criterios de Beers.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inadequate prescription of medications in hospitalised elderly patients according to Beers criteria].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
