<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22118761</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallardo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Irles, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almeida González, C V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the use of parenteral, enteral, and mixed nutrition in one acute and one chronic hospital. DESIGN Retrospective, non-randomised, observational study. STUDY SITES: South Seville Health Area: Acute Hospital (H1) and Chronic Hospital (H2) with 447 and 84 beds, respectively. We analysed all episodes of artificial nutrition administered in a 6-month period. Exclusion criteria included: age &lt;18 years, oral supplements, and peripheral nutrition. RESULTS Artificial nutrition was used in a total of 568 episodes: 406 were enteral nutrition, 162 were parenteral nutrition, constituting 4.95%, 3.54% and 1,41% of all hospitalisations, respectively. Enteral nutrition was more common at H2 hospital (n=219, 15.5/100 hospitalisations) and parenteral nutrition was more commonly used at H1 (n=155, 6.96/100 hospitalisations), with the ICU providing the majority of treatments (43.8%). Mixed nutritional support was used in 68 patients (0.59% of all cases), and was most commonly used in the surgery department (n=32, P&lt;.001). The most commonly used enteral formula was the special diabetes diet; 41.2% at H1 and 46.6% at H2. Patient mortality with enteral nutrition was 37% at H1, 63% at H2, and was correlated with age (OR=1.025, 95% CI: 1.006-1.046, P&lt;.05), male sex (OR=1.612, 95% CI: 1.023-2.540, P&lt;.05), and time in ICU (OR=49.379, 95% CI: 11.971-203.675, P&lt;.01). CONCLUSIONS Enteral nutrition was more frequently used in both the acute and chronic hospitals. Parenteral nutrition and mixed nutritional support were used almost exclusively at the acute hospital.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de uso de los diferentes tipos de nutrición artificial en un hospital de agudos y de crónicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Usage profile of different parenteral support options in acute and chronic care facilities].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
