<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22124686</identifier>
<setSpec>1680-5348</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>De la Hoz Restrepo, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvis, Nelson</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lemos, Elkin V</dc:author>
<dc:author>León, Yazmin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quevedo, Elkin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cañon, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Compare mortality in multidrug-susceptible Acinetobacter baumannii infected patients and multidrug-resistant A. baumannii-infected patients hospitalized in intensive care units (ICUs) in Colombia. METHODS A prospective, observational, and multicenter study. A total of 165 patients admitted to the participating ICUs from April 2006 to April 2010 were included. On day 14 and day 30 of hospitalization, mortality in multidrug-resistant patients with clinical isolates of A. baumannii was compared with that in multidrug-susceptible patients. RESULTS Of the 165 adult patients who had health care-associated infections (HAI) caused by A. baumannii, multidrug-susceptible bacteria were found in 62 patients and multidrug-resistant bacteria in 103. Statistically significant differences in mortality on day 14 of hospitalization in the ICU were not found. On the other hand, significant differences (P &lt; 0.05) in mortality on day 30 of hospitalization were observed between patients with multidrug-resistant isolates and those with multidrug-susceptible isolates. This difference was maintained when the patients' risk factors were evaluated by multivariate analysis. CONCLUSIONS The presence of multidrug resistance is the primary risk factor for mortality in patients with HAI caused by A. baumannii in Colombian ICUs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad por Acinetobacter baumannii en unidades de cuidados intensivos en Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acinetobacter baumannii - related mortality in intensive care units in Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
