<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22138281</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández de Larrea-Baz, Nerea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morant-Ginestar, Consuelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gènova-Maleras, Ricard</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez-Martín, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catalá-López, Ferrán</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE We analyzed the burden of disease in the elderly population in Spain in 2008. METHODS A population-based cross-sectional study was performed to calculate the disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) of the Spanish population aged ≥ 60 years old. DALYs are the sum of the number of years of life lost (YLLs) and the number of years lived with disability (YLDs). Data sources included the national mortality register for YLLs, and inference of Euro-A subregion (including Spain) estimates for YLDs. RESULTS In the elderly population, DALYs lost due to all diseases were estimated at 2.1 million. The main causes of DALYs were malignancies (21.3%), neuropsychiatric disorders (21.1%) and cardiovascular diseases (20.4%). The main specific subcategories were dementias, ischemic heart disease, cerebrovascular disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, lung cancer, hearing loss and osteoarthritis. CONCLUSIONS Burden of disease analysis allows distinct health problems to be reassessed in relation to classical mortality analysis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación a la carga de enfermedad de las personas mayores en España.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Burden of disease in the elderly population in Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
