<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22137198</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calleja Hernández, M Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perez Vicente, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznarte Padial, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zarzuelo Zurita, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Cardiovascular disease is the primary cause of death in the world. Various drugs have shown their efficiency in the management of patients with acute coronary syndrome, along with the recommendations established by different Scientific Societies. The objective of this survey is to assess the monitoring of the quality standards established in Andalusia for the management of patients with myocardial infarction with evaluation of the ST segment and to analyse the source of variability of the prescription provided by the physician. METHOD An observational descriptive survey, of indication-prescription, which analysed all the prescriptions included in the hospital discharge reports in patients treated in a tertiary hospital after having suffered acute myocardial infarction with ST segment elevation, between August 2005 and July 2007. RESULTS A total of 287 patients were included. Antiplatelets were prescribed in 99.3% of the patients, and acetylsalicylic acid in 95.8%. The percentage of beta-blockers received was 89.5%, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) in 74.2%, with ARA-II indicated in 2.85%. The use of statins was 84.6%. The indication of conditional sublingual nitroglycerin was 60.3%. The use of ACEI and sublingual nitroglycerin showed statistically significant differences according to the prescribing physician. CONCLUSIONS The fitness of the prescriptions to the recommendations established in Andalusia is high. The prescription of conditional sublingual nitroglycerin is the indicator which varies most in the quality standards established. Its use in conjunction with the indication of ACEI, are the recommendations which show a higher deviation depending on the prescribing physician.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de indicadores de calidad de la prescripción tras infarto agudo de miocardio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Monitoring of quality indicators of prescriptions after acute myocardial infarction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
