<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22176823</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Flores, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Polycystic ovary syndrome (POS) is a hyperandrogenic state which causes the majority of the fertility and menstrual disorders in premenopausal women. Treatment has focused on gynecologic and endocrine interventions to modify these disorders and the excess androgenic hormone phenotype, which motivates the seeking of treatment for most women. However, there is progressive support for the role of different factors within the disease, such as obesity and insulin resistance. These factors interact with the androgenic hormones and with the ovulatory alterations; but it is yet not known with certainty the fundamental mechanism upon which the disease depends for the manifestation of its symptoms and signs. This association of phenomena has important reflections on the development of cardiovascular diseases. The POS being such a frequent condition, it is often not diagnosed and treated in a multidisciplinary manner. It is important that, apart from looking for improvement in fertility and a decrease of the hyperandrogenic expression, risk factors resulting from this condition are recognized and its treatment include early management of chronic diseases with evidence-based interventions to improve eating and physical activity habits in who, most of the time, are seen to treat other health problems or to improve their reproductive health exclusively.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de ovario poliquístico, el enfoque del internista.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The polycystic ovary syndrome. The point of view of the internist].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
