<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22188754</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castellano, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carles, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Climent, M Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcaraz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maroto, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">CONTEXT Hormonal therapy allows effective control of cancer-related symptoms in advanced stages. However, the disease will progress in almost all these metastatic prostate cancer patient until becoming resistant to androgen suppression. The emergence of new drugs will most probably have open up new expectations regarding the treatment of this cancer. OBJECTIVE The aim of the present review has been to provide an overview of the current status of castration-resistant prostate cancer and to share the high expectations created with the new treatments. EVIDENCE ACQUISITION Evidence was obtained from multidisciplinary meetings with the participation of urologists and oncologists, where they pooled the analysis of original articles in the literature and defined the content of the article. EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS Chemotherapy with docetaxel was a turning point in castration-resistant prostate cancer after the failure of hormonal therapy failure. For the first time, it achieved increased survival time in comparison with mitoxantrone and prednisone. Combination therapy with docetaxel and prednisone is the first-line choice treatment. Once the cancer has progressed, there is no clear alternative, although some novel agents have created expectations for the treatment of this type of cancer. CONCLUSIONS The range of therapeutic options for castration-resistant prostate cancer has increased dramatically with the arrival of new drugs. At present, cabazitaxel, and in the near future, abiraterone, have been found to be effective drugs in second-line treatment after progression to docetaxel, increasing survival by 2-4 months and reducing risk of death by 30-35%.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de próstata resistente a castración: ¿hacia dónde vamos?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Castration-resistant prostate cancer: where are we going?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
