<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22233859</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galarraga, L Moreno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguirre, M Herranz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iturbe, E Bernaola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varas, A Herrero</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero, J C García</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, I San Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of 9 year old male referred to the A and E service with right ocular proptosis and progressive migraine in the context of a sinusitis diagnosed two days earlier by compatible clinical and radiological tests, and receiving treatment with amoxicillin-clavulanic acid. Physcial exploration revealed right ocular proptosis with a slight limitation for conjugate gaze. Facing the suspicion of a possible neurological complication of the sinusitis, cranial computer aided tomography (CAT) was carried out, with right frontal subdural empyema observed. He was admitted for intravenous antibiotic treatment with cefotaxime, vancomicin and metronidazole. He was evaluated by child Neurosurgery, Maxillofacial Surgery and Otorhinolaryngology (ORL) services; the decision was taken to only drain the primary focus, while an expectant neurosurgical attitude was maintained. The patient evolved favourably with a progressive disappearance of the symptoms. Periodical magnetic resonances were carried out, which showed a clear improvement up until the complete resolution of the empyema. Following four weeks of antibiotherapy iv., and after clinical and radiological normalization, the patient was discharged.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Sep-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empiema subdural secundario a sinusitis. Descripción de un caso pediátrico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Subdural empyema secondary to sinusitis. A pediatric case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
