<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22257452</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández, Norma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lasala, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Stecher, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tiraboschi, Iris</dc:author>
<dc:author>Melero, Marcelo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mucormycosis is an opportunistic infection caused by fungi of the order Mucorales. It is characterized by rapid progression and high morbidity and mortality in the absence of early diagnosis and prompt treatment. It was an infrequent disease, but in recent years, its incidence appears to have increased. The aim of this paper is to report the cases of mucormycosis diagnosed from 1982 to 2010 at the Hospital de Clinicas José de San Martín, University of Buenos Aires. We diagnosed 10 cases of mucormycosis; the first three between 1982 and 2004 and the last 7 between 2005 and 2010. The incidence from 1980 to 2004 was 0.13 patient-years and the frequency 0.1/10 000 discharges (95% CI 0.00- 0.3). In the period 2005 to 2010, the incidence was 0.86 patients per year with 1.1/10 000 discharges (95% CI 0.5-2.4). There was a pulmonary mucormycosis case (in a patient treated with corticosteroids) and nine rhinocerebral cases, two in neutropenic and seven in diabetic patients. The diagnosis was made by observation of cenocytic hyphae in 10/10 patients. Mucorales were recovered in 8/9 cultures (5 Rhizopus spp and 3 Mucor spp.). In one case diagnosis of pulmonary mucormycosis was made post-mortem. Nine patients were treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate (in 3 patients supplemented with liposomal amphotericin B) and surgery. Three patients underwent hyperbaric chamber. Seven patients had favorable outcome. In conclusion, mucormycosis is a rare disease, but its incidence has increased over the past five years. A good evolution of the patients is linked to early diagnosis and treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mucormicosis. Una micosis emergente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Mucormycosis. An emergent mycosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
