<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22286827</identifier>
<setSpec>1606-7916</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Palma-Coca, Oswaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Téllez-Rojo Solís, Martha María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trejo-Valdivia, Belem</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Ávila, Mauricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendoza-Alvarado, Laura R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Determine Vaccination Coverage (VC) among adults 60 years of age and older (EP), for influenza, pneumococcal and tetanus vaccines, association with socio-demographic characteristics and heterogeneity at state level. MATERIAL AND METHODS Cross-sectional analysis based on information from 18 015 households visited in a national survey. General and vaccine information (self-report) for a randomly selected elder in each household is available. RESULTS The national VC level was found to be 56.5% (±0.97) for influenza, 44.3% (±0.98) for pneumococcus and 61.8% (±0.96) for tetanus. The VC was significantly lower for EP without health social services and higher for women. Almost 20.0% of EP recognized not having vaccines at all, due mainly that they didn't know it was a duty. CONCLUSIONS Important improvements are shown in vaccination coverage among elderly in Mexico. Differentials suggest the need to intensify information campaigns and actions that could improve the accessibility to vaccines for this population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta Nacional de Cobertura de Vacunación (influenza, neumococo y tétanos) en adultos mayores de 60 años en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[National Survey of Vaccination Coverage (Influenza, pneumococcus and tetanus) in Mexican population of 60 years of age and older].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
