<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22308940</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guerrero, Omaira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moya, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bosch, Virgilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isabel Giacopini, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We compared the effect of the consumption of seje oil (Oenocarpus bataua), with that of olive oil, on plasma lipids and susceptibility in vitro to oxidation of high density lipoprotein (HDL) in the rat. Two groups often male Sprague Dawley rats were fed ad libitum, for a lapse of eight week, with a purified diets with 10g de seje oil or olive oil/100 g of diet (GS y GO respectively). The animals were exsanguinated at the end of the experimental after a 14 hour fast. Plasma was isolated by centrifugation, and the fractions of lipoproteins were separated from the plasma by sequential ultracentrifugation. Rats of GO had a statistically significant lower in concentration of TG (p &lt; 0.05) compared with GS group. HDL fractions in both groups were oxidatively modified by incubation with copper ions. Differences in the fractions susceptibilities to peroxidation were studied by measuring the formation of thiobarbituric acid reactive substance (TBARS) for 3 hours. HDL in GS had a statistically significant decrease in TBARS formation (p &lt; 0.05) relative to HDL of GO. This may be explained by the lower concentration of polyunsaturated fatty acids of HDL in GS compared with HDL in GO.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo del consumo de aceite de oliva virgen o seje sobre el perfil lipídico y la resistencia a la oxidación de las lipoproteinas de alta densidad (HDL) del plasma de rata.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study of the consumption of virgin olive oil or seje on lipid profile and oxidation resistance of high density lipoprotein (HDL) of rat plasma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
