<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22318180</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Solsona, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Radical prostatectomy is an excellent salvage method for patients with prostatic cancer when radical radiotherapy or brachytherapy fail. To define local failure is not always reliable; nevertheless, performing a prostatic biopsy two years after treatment could reach an early diagnosis. Another accepted attitude is to perform the biopsy after biochemical recurrence, but sometimes the pathological stage is already locally advanced tumor. It is also difficult to determine which patients are suitable for this rescue treatment, probably those with locally confined tumors and with favorable PSA kinetics, PSA velocity below 2.0 or a PSA doubling time over 12 months, and in whom detectable PSA is reached 2 years after treatment. These patients are suitable for radical prostatectomy if they have a live expectancy of more than 10 years. Although rescue radical prostatectomy has a higher rate of complications and worse functional results, cancer-specific survival rates are high, and remain high after 15 years of follow-up. Currently, new surgical improvements and new radiotherapy technology are diminishing surgical complications and improving functional results. In summary radical prostatectomy is a feasible rescue procedure after radiotherapy failure although the complications rate remains higher than prostatectomy as initial therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La prostatectomía radical tras radioterapia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Radical prostatectomy after radiotherapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
