<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22321561</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Díaz-Guerra, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Martín, Antonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luque Fernández, Inés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varsavsky, Mariela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jimenez Moleón, José J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández García, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz Torres, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes García, Rebeca</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jódar Gimeno, Esteban</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ballesteros Pomar, María Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Muñoz, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rozas Moreno, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vidal Casariego, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés Berdonces, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palma Moya, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cano Rodriguez, Isidoro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calleja Canelas, Amparo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guadalix Iglesias, Sonsoles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Sáez, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To provide practical recommendations for evaluation and treatment of osteoporosis associated to endocrine diseases and nutritional conditions. PARTICIPANTS Members of the Bone Metabolism Working Group of the Spanish Society of Endocrinology, a methodologist, and a documentalist. METHODS Recommendations were formulated according to the GRADE system (Grading of Recommendations, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation) to describe both the strength of recommendations and the quality of evidence. A systematic search was made in MEDLINE (Pubmed), using the following terms associated to the name of each condition: AND "osteoporosis", "fractures", "bone mineral density", and "treatment". Papers in English with publication date before 18 October 2011 were included. Current evidence for each disease was reviewed by two group members, and doubts related to the review process or development of recommendations were resolved by the methodologist. Finally, recommendations were discussed in a meeting of the Working Group. CONCLUSIONS The document provides evidence-based practical recommendations for evaluation and management of endocrine and nutritional diseases associated to low bone mass or an increased risk of fracture. For each disease, the associated risk of low bone mass and fragility fractures is given, recommendations for bone mass assessment are provided, and treatment options that have shown to be effective for increasing bone mass and/or to decreasing fragility fractures are listed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Consensus Development Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías de práctica clínica para la evaluación y tratamiento de la osteoporosis asociada a enfermedades endocrinas y nutricionales. Grupo de Metabolismo Mineral de la Sociedad Espa˜nola deEndocrinología y Nutrición.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical practice guidelines for evaluation and treatment of osteoporosis associated to endocrine and nutritional conditions. Bone Metabolism Working Group of the Spanish Society of Endocrinology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
