<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22321447</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Pérez, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costa, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Duarte, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the image quality and radiation dose in a group of patients undergoing coronary CT angiography using a 128-slice dual source helical CT scanner with high pitch alto and prospective acquisition with those in a group of patients with similar clinical characteristics undergoing coronary CT angiography using a 128-slice single-source CT scanner with prospective sequential acquisition. MATERIAL AND METHODS We included 80 patients with heart rates ≤65 beats/min: 40 underwent sequential 128-slice single source CT with prospective synchronization and the other 40 underwent 128-slice dual source helical CT with high pitch and prospective synchronization. Two radiologists independently assessed the quality of the images of the coronary arteries on the 80 coronary CT angiograms: image quality was classified on a four-point scale in which 1 represented excellent and 4 deficient. The effective dose of radiation was also calculated. RESULTS The clinical characteristics of the patients in the two groups were similar. The image quality obtained with dual source CT was significantly better than that obtained with single source CT (P=0.006). The mean effective dose of radiation in the group undergoing dual source CT was 36% lower than in the group undergoing single source CT (1.4±0.6 mSv vs. 2.2±0.9 mSv; P&lt;0.01). CONCLUSION Although both sequential 128-slice single source CT with prospective acquisition and 128-slice dual source helical CT with high pitch and prospective acquisition provide good image quality and low effective doses of radiation, 128-slice dual source helical CT with prospective acquisition provides better image quality and results in a lower effective dose of radiation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coronariografía mediante tomografía computarizada con sincronización prospectiva. Comparación de la calidad de imagen y dosis de radiación con equipos de 128 detectores de fuente única y doble fuente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Coronary CT angiography using a prospective protocol. Comparison of image quality and radiation dose between dual source CT and single source CT].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
