<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22358412</identifier>
<setSpec>1680-5348</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Echemendia, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lemus, Dihadenys</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montoro, Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martinez, Maria Rosarys</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llanes, Maria Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llop, Alina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diaz, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mederos, Lilian</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Determine the prevalence of resistance to antitubercular drugs in Cuba in the 2000-2009 decade. METHODS A prospective longitudinal study was conducted. The sample group consisted of 2,285 Mycobacterium tuberculosis isolates obtained from throughout the country in the period from 1 January 2000 to 31 December 2009. The proportion method was used in Löwenstein-Jensen media with the first-line drugs: isoniazid, streptomycin, ethambutol, and rifampicin. RESULTS In the new cases and patients with a history of previous treatment, resistance was 8.5% and 37.0%, respectively. In these case categories, multidrug resistance was 0.4% and 8.8%, respectively. CONCLUSIONS This study shows low prevalence of multidrug-resistant strains in Cuba. The results reflect the progress made by the national control program, which is currently working on the elimination of tuberculosis as a public health problem in the country.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigilancia de la resistencia a los fármacos antituberculosos en Cuba, 2000-2009.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Surveillance of resistance to antitubercular drugs in Cuba, 2000-2009].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
