<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22411368</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz Ramírez, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Souto-Gallardo, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Cruz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bacardí Gascón, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was to perform a systematic review of papers that assess the effect of television food advertisings (TFA) in the food preferences and consumption in different age groups. METHODS Randomized clinical trials published up to November 2010 were searched in Pubmed, Ebsco, Cochrane and Scielo. Studies were included if they assessed the effect of direct exposition to TFA over the food preferences, demand, and consumption. RESULTS Ten studies fulfilled the inclusion criteria. In the three studies conducted on preschooler children an increase in selection and demand of advertized foods was reported. All the fives studies conducted on scholar children reported negative outcomes in those children exposed to unhealthy food. An increase on food consumption was observed in two of the three studies conducted on adults. CONCLUSION The assess studies show that in pre-school and school children the effect of advertising on food consumption was consistent, while in adults there is a trend toward an strong association of exposure food advertising and preference, consumption and demand of the food advertised.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la publicidad de alimentos anunciados en la televisión sobre la preferencia y el consumo de alimentos: revisión sistemática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of food television advertising on the preference and food consumption: systematic review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
