<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22421952</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Comas-Sugrañes, Dolors</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jódar-Masanés, Ramon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pineda-Yuste, M del Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Padullés-Zamora, Núria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Castelao, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Methoxy polyethylene glycol-epoetin beta (PEG-EPO) is indicated for the treatment of anaemia due to chronic kidney disease. Its long half-life allows it to be administered once per month in maintenance therapy. OBJECTIVE To evaluate the use, effectiveness and cost of PEG-EPO in a group of pre-dialysis chronic renal failure patients. METHOD Retrospective observational study in pre-dialysis patients who began treatment with PEG-EPO between May 2008 and February 2009. The following data were gathered: age, sex, haemoglobin levels (Hb) and erythropoiesis-stimulating agent (ESA) dose and frequency. The follow-up period was 12 months. RESULTS We included 198 patients. Mean Hb upon starting PEG-EPO in patients who had received no prior treatment was 10.8g/l, and 11.6g/l at 90 days (P&lt;.0001). In patients previously treated with ESA, mean Hb before starting PEG-EPO treatment was 11.2g/l, and 11.4g/l at 12 months (P=.846). Hb values were higher than 12g/l (P&lt;.0001) after 12 months of treatment in 25% of patients; of these, 45% had values above 13g/l. We observed doses 39% lower than those indicated on the drug leaflet, resulting in a reduction in the originally expected theoretical costs. CONCLUSIONS The doses of PEG-EPO administered to patients with a prior history of ESA treatment were lower than those indicated by the drug leaflet, and Hb remained stable after 12 months of treatment. A large portion of the patients had levels above the 13g/l threshold.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of methoxy polyethylene glycol-epoetin beta in stage 3, 4 or 5 non-dialysis chronic kidney disease.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
