<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22459608</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ulloa Santamaría, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Azpilicueta Idarreta, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gilbert Pérez, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frías Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Borrego, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The 22q11 deletion syndrome is a frequent contiguous-gene deletion syndrome. This disorder has a broad spectrum of phenotypic manifestations. It includes various syndromes such as DiGeorge syndrome. The most frequent clinical manifestations are congenital cardiac defects, characteristic facies, palate malformations, hypoparathyroidism, immunodeficiency due to thymic hypoplasia, growth retardation, and behavioural and psychiatric problems. Among the symptoms observed, many patients suffer from respiratory insufficiency or failure. The origin is often multifactorial. Structural airway abnormalities are frequently found in this syndrome. In many of these patients the malformation is mild or non-existent, and remains asymptomatic. However, in some cases it can cause a severe respiratory insufficiency, being diagnosed when other disorders are ruled out. These cases illustrate the importance of early visualisation of the airway by fibrobronchoscopy in the management of the patient with 22q11 deletion syndrome who has recurrent respiratory difficulties.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de microdeleción 22q11: manifestaciones cardiorrespiratorias y utilidad de la fibrobroncoscopia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[22Q11 microdeletion syndrome: cardiorespiratory symptoms and fibrobronchoscopy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
