<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22459573</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Delgado, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camós, Mireia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estella, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Couselo, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tasso, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Miguel, Purificación</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navajas, Aurora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Badell, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rives, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verdeguer, Amparo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is the most frequent cancer in childhood, with cure rates of 80-85%. In T-cell ALL (15% of ALL), prognostic factors are ill defined. We aimed to describe the event-free survival (EFS) and analyze clinical prognostic factors in a series of pediatric T-ALL of 4 consecutive clinical trials. PATIENTS AND METHODS Children with T-ALL aged 1-18 years treated in 37 institutions in Spain were enrolled in 4 consecutive trials from February-1989 to November-2009. RESULTS A total of 218 T-ALL patients out of 1,652 pediatric ALL were evaluable during the study period (SHOP/ALL-89: 35, ALL-94: 63, ALL-99: 62, ALL-2005: 58). There were 164 boys (75%). Median age (years) was 7.8 range (1.3-18.6). Median leukocytes (10(9)/L) was 78.2, range 0.8-930. Fifteen (6.8%) children had central nervous system (CNS) involvement at diagnosis. Regarding response to induction treatment, 150 (75%) patients had less than 5% blasts on day-14 bone marrow and 199 achieved complete remission at the end of induction. Overall survival (OS) at 60 months for SHOP/ALL-89, ALL-94, ALL-99 was 48 (8), 49 (6), 70 (6) %, respectively, and at 48 months for SHOP/ALL-2005 (ongoing protocol) was 74 (8) %. Median follow-up (months) was 206, 152, 74 and 17 respectively. Analysis of prognostic factors revealed no statistical differences regarding sex or age. Leukocyte count over 200×10(9)/l (P=.024), CNS infiltration at diagnosis (P&lt;.006) and treatment response had prognostic significance (end-induction complete remission) (P=.0000), day 14-bone marrow (P=.005). CONCLUSIONS Results for the SHOP/ALL-89 and ALL-94 protocols were inferior to other contemporary protocols but there has been an improvement in survival in the 2 last trials. In line with other T-ALL series, response to treatment had the strongest prognostic impact.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leucemia linfoblástica aguda T pediátrica: análisis de supervivencia y factores pronósticos en 4 protocolos consecutivos del grupo cooperativo multicéntrico SHOP.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[T-cell pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia: analysis of survival and prognostic factors in 4 consecutive protocols of the Spanish cooperative study group SHOP].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
