<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22470010</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Méndez-Sánchez, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Lara, K</dc:author>
<dc:author>Green-Renner, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sosa-Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Approximately two thirds of cancer patients at advanced stages of the disease suffer from anorexia. Defined as the loss of the desire to eat, anorexia lower the energy intake which further exacerbates a progressive deterioration of the patient nutritional status. Malnutrition has a large impact on morbidity and mortality affecting the quality of life. Cancer anorexia etiology is multifactorial including complex interactions among the tumor, host metabolism and antineoplastic treatment. New related theories include peripheral and brain mechanisms affecting hypothalamic pathways; inducing behavioral and metabolic failure of responses to energy balance. The aim of this review is to describe actual concepts involved in the pathogenesis of cancer anorexia with special interest in brain mechanisms. CONCLUSIONS Anorexia and reduced food intake are important issues in the management of cancer patients, more knowledge about pathogenic mechanism is needed to improve therapeutic options, prognosis and quality of life in cancer patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Observaciones sobre la patogénesis de la anorexia asociada a cáncer y su regulación por el sistema nervioso central.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neural pathophysiology of cancer anorexia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
