<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22512100</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carranco-Toledo, G A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-López, O F</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Palacios, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-Mena, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dufoo-Olvera, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aburto-Trejo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Knowledge of the morphometric anatomy of cervical pedicles is essential for the safe and accurate placement of pedicle screws during instrumentation of the cervical spine. Screw placement in the lumbar and thoracic vertebrae is considered as a safe practice, unlike the cervical vertebrae due to the risks involved. There are few reports on this technique. The little available information comes from populations different from the Mexican population. Knowing the measurements of each cervical vertebra will provide proper screw orientation and selection at the time of screw placement. METHODS Prospective, cross-sectional, descriptive study in subjects who presented at the outpatient and emergency services. Patient's in whom a CAT scan of the cervical spine was ordered as part of the work-up protocol, from April 1st 2010 to October 31st 2010, were included. A morphometric anatomic study was undertaken using the CAT software. In a saggital view: a) Saggital angle, b) Saggital diameter. In an axial view: a) Work distance, b) Cross-sectional angle and c) Cross-sectional diameter. RESULTS The following measurements were obtained for each segment from C2 to C7: mean, standard deviation, range and minimal and maximal values. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL RELEVANCE Appropriate preoperative planning prior to cervical transpedicular instrumentation is essential to achieve greater accuracy during screw placement. The information obtained allows performing the procedure. As a result of this, a report based on out center's experience may be disseminated thus sharing our technique with the medical community.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis morfométrico de los pedículos cervicales en una población mexicana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Morphometric analysis of cervical pedicles in a Mexican population].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
