<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2252850</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Vaquero, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Regás, J S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tresserra, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boix-Ochoa, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ezzedine, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cobos, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Liñan, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors believe that the greater part of chronic cervicofacial adenitis actually observed in our hospitals, are not caused by M. tuberculosis or M. bovis but by scrofulaceum mycobacterium, M. avium, M. fortuitum and M. Kansasii, and above all, by the first two of these. They present their experience with 16 cases of cervico-facial adenitis due to atypical mycobacterium (CAAM) treated in our centre during the last years, in which period no case of cervical tuberculosis (CT) was observed. It is important to establish an early differential diagnosis between both etiologies, seeing as treatment is different. Whilst tuberculostatics can solve the phymic infection, surgical extirpation is the only solution for CAAM. The diagnosis of these types of infection is achieved by means of a very characteristic clinical procedure and by cutaneous tests specific for each bacteria. Faced with the clinical suspicion, the total extirpation should be effected of the adenopathic block affected. The exact diagnosis can only be made by the culture of the operatory mass.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de las adenitis cervicofaciales por micobacterias no tuberculosas (micobacterias atípicas).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Our experience in the treatment of cervico-facial adenitis caused by non-tuberculous mycobacteria (atypical mycobacteria)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
