<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22532221</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Collado-Vázquez, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo, Jesús M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Many diseases have been dealt with in literature, cinema or television, including epilepsy, cancer, mental disorders, movement disorders or infectious diseases. Among the many pathologies that have been considered, locked-in syndrome is one that has been of particular interest to writers and film-makers. AIM To review how locked-in syndrome has been portrayed in literature, cinema and television. DEVELOPMENT Locked-in syndrome is a state that is generally secondary to a brainstem lesion with involvement of the corticobulbar and corticospinal tracts, thereby impeding the patient from producing any kind of motor response. Patients remain conscious, maintain their higher functions and can both see and hear. Yet, they are quadriplegic with paralysis of the lower cranial nerves and cannot move or speak. They only conserve the capacity to move their eyes vertically and their eyelids, which they can use as a way to communicate. This pathology has come to the attention of writers and film and television directors, who have described characters with this syndrome. Likewise, there are also stories told in the first person by patients who have experienced this condition and who have written their story using eye movements as a means to communicate. CONCLUSIONS Literature, cinema and television have shown an interest in locked-in syndrome and have placed special attention on the problems these patients have to communicate with others.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El síndrome de cautiverio en la literatura, el cine y la televisión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Locked-in syndrome in literature, cinema and television].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
