<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22566329</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Álvarez, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano Morago, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Alcón, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarino Marín, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marrodán Serrano, Ma D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION It is well known that to improve the feeding of the students it would improve its health and wellbeing, contributing to the reduction of the risk of chronic diseases in adults. In Spain, this is especially important considering the data of prevalence of infantile obesity. OBJECTIVES To know the number of users of school cafeterias in Spain as well as different considerations on its management, nutritional supervision and the number of special diets served to students with specific requirements due to pathologies or other causes. RESULTS The II national Survey has been realized on school cafeterias: 7,710 used daily by 678,587 users. They provide near the 2.8% of special diets (allergies 38.9%, other pathologies 23.2%, religious causes 26.7% causes and celiac disease 11.1%). CONCLUSIONS The numbers of prevalence of obesity and infantile overweight indicate that it is necessary to improve the diet of the students.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta nacional sobre comedores escolares y demanda de dietas especiales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[National survey on school lunches and demand of special diets].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
