<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22576529</identifier>
<setSpec>0080-6234</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Secco, Iara Aparecida de Oliveira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribeiro, Luiz Cláudio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robazzi, Maria Lúcia do Carmo Cruz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silveira, Renata Cristina da Penha</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to identify the socioeconomic and demographic characteristics of children and adolescents who study and work outside their home. This non-experimental, correlational, cross-sectional study was performed using questionnaires applied to primary education students, enrolled in public schools in Ribeirão Preto (Brazil). Two schools were selected through a draw. Data analysis was performed using Statistical Package for Social Sciences, version 14.0. Of the 133 students who answered the questionnaire, 36 (27.7%) reported working outside their home, 20.6% were between 11 and 13 years of age, and 66.7% were male (p=0.000) and had started working early to help with the family income (p=0.003). The salary they received helped comprise the family income, and it was found that as the family income increased, the need for the youngsters to work was reduced. It was found that many factors contribute to these subjects' early start at work, including family size, structure and poverty.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización socioeconómica y demográfica de niños y adolescentes que estudian y trabajan simultáneamente fuera de casa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The socioeconomic and demographic characterization of children and adolescents who study and work outside their home].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista da Escola de Enfermagem da U S P</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
