<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22575556</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Porta Martínez, Nuria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaén Manzanera, Angels</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mur Martí, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villaró Gabarrós, Mercè</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was: to estimate the prevalence of chronic renal insufficiency (CRI) in diabetic type 2 (DM2) patients treated in Primary Care based on the estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFe); to determine associated factors with CRI, and to evaluate the relationship of GF rate and risk of cardiovascular disease. PATIENTS AND METHODS This was a descriptive cross-sectional study. We included 500 medical histories randomly selected in a total of 2,950 DM2 patients. We registered sociodemographic data, comorbidities, cardiovascular risk factors and laboratory data. CRI definition was based on GFe rate and classified according to the K/DOQI Clinical Practice Guidelines for Chronic Kidney Disease. RESULTS The prevalence of CRI was 23.2%. There were 51.6% females and the mean age was 66.2 years; 70,4% had hypertension and 67% dyslipidemia. The presence of CRI was related with older age, females, smoking habit, plasma creatinine value, microalbuminuria, and history of hypertension, dyslipidemia and cardiovascular disease. After analysing the data according to the category of GF rate, only the significant relationship with smoking habit disappeared. Multivariate statistic analysis supports a relation with older age, female gender, dyslipidemia and heart disease. CONCLUSIONS We confirm a high prevalence of CRI in DM2 patients and their relationship with the presence of cardiovascular disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May 04 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de enfermedad renal crónica en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 mediante determinación del filtrado glomerular y su relación con el riesgo cardiovascular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of chronic renal insufficiency in diabetic type 2 diabetes patients based on the estimated glomerular filtration rate and relation with cardiovascular risk].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
