<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22619142</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fariña-Perez, Luis Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pesqueira-Santiago, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE A retained postoperative drain tube, trapped by one or more of the sutures of the abdominal wall closure, is a rare complication of frustrating consequences and potential legal repercussions. There are few reports of techniques for minimally invasive removal of an anchored postoperative drain tube, which not infrequently has been treated by reopening the wound. METHOD/RESULT A 75 years-old man with a left T2-T3N0M0 renal carcinoma was treated with transperitoneal laparoscopic nephrectomy and a Jackson-Pratt drain was left in place. Drain removal the day after revealed impossible, as if being caught with fascial suture. With the patient under sedation, we introduced a Sachse urethrotome parallel to the drain, and the abdominal fascia was identified, then the polyglycolic stitch anchoring it to the wall could be severed, freeing the drain. CONCLUSIONS Percutaneous extraction with the Sachse urethrotome of an anchored postoperative drain, should be the first option, before trying a forced traction or using more complex options. This technique is for the first time published in the Spanish bibliography, and we think this possibility should be disclosed to abdominal surgeons.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimally invasive retrieval of a retained Jackson--Pratt drainage tube using the Sachse urethrotome.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
