<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22674358</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Páez, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobar, Humberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey-Benito, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapata, John Jairo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, Constanza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Méndez, Jairo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The province of Valle del Cauca has been free of dog rabies for more than 20 years. However, sylvatic rabies foci remain which are threats to the health of the populace and its pets. Rabies vaccination campaigns are carried out annually in all 42 counties of the province. OBJECTIVES The impact of dog vaccination was evaluated on the basis of humoral immunoresponse, population parameters and correlation with variables inherent to the vaccination process and logistics. MATERIALS AND METHODS Sera and associated data were obtained from each of the 42 counties for a total sample of 569 rabies-vaccinated dogs. Rabies neutralizing antibodies were measured by quantitative ELISA. The data were analyzed with the statistical programs in Epi-Info 6.0. RESULTS Nearly 10% of dogs were seronegative (9.1%) and an additional 25.1% did not elicit an adequate humoral immune response to vaccination. Concentration of rabies neutralizing antibodies diminished gradually with the time after vaccination and was correlated with dog age and vaccine quality. No associations were noted between dog gender or breed. CONCLUSIONS These data permit the following recommendations: (1) only viable, non expired rabies vaccines must be used to immunize animals, (2) two doses of rabies vaccine must be applied during the first six months of dog life, (3) booster immunizations must be administered every year, (4) practices and processes related to rabies vaccination in private institutions must inspected regularly by health authorities.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2011 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la seroconversión como respuesta a la vacunación antirrábica en perros en el departamento del Valle del Cauca, Colombia, 2009.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the seroconversion as a response to rabies vaccination in dogs, Valle del Cauca, Colombia, 2009].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
