<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22710091</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castellan, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yanes, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gosalbez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labbie, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lasso-Betancor, C E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE In spite of advances in minimally invasive endoscopic surgery, open dismembered pyeloplasty continues to be used in many pediatric centers, especially in small children. The purpose of this work is to present our experience in the performance of this technique using a minimally invasive open pyeloplasty without intrarenal stents. MATERIAL AND METHODS A retrospective review was made of patients between July 1992 and July 2009. During this time, 348 patients underwent open dismembered pyeloplasty. A total of 310 patients (89%), 223 boys and 87 girls, underwent open pyeloplasty without intrarenal stent. The incision was from 2 to 2.5 cm in the flank. An extrarenal drain (3-5 days) and a bladder catheter (&lt; 24 hs) were placed in all patients. RESULTS A total of 319 pyeloplasties were performed without intrarenal catheter in our Service. Of these, 174 (54.5%) were on the left side, 127 (39.8%) on the right side and 9 (5.6%) were bilateral. Age interval was 14 days to 18 years, 58% of the children being younger than 12 months at the time of surgery. With a mean follow-up of 6.7 years (17 years to 11 months), 312 pyeloplasties (97.8%) were successful, with persistence of the obstructive patient in 7 patients who required a new open pyeloplasty (2.2%). Other complications were: prolonged drainage (6), wound infection (1), and urinary infection (2). Mean stay was 22 hours. CONCLUSIONS Open dismembered pyeloplasty is a safe and effective treatment choice for pyeloureteral stenosis in children and can be done without intrarenal stents with no detriment to its success.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pieloplastia sin drenaje intrarrenal en pacientes pediátricos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pyeloplasty without intrarenal stent in pediatric patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
