<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22819345</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gunlusoy, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arslan, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ceylan, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vardar, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kara, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kozacıoğlu, Z</dc:author>
<dc:author>Degirmenci, T</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Many new agents have been introduced as an alternative to standard MVAC therapy with improved efficacy and lower toxicity profile in advanced bladder carcinoma. The aim of this study is to evaluate the response rate and toxic side effects of gemcitabine-cisplatin (GC) in patients with advanced/metastatic bladder carcinoma. METHODS Between January 2001 and April 2006, 58 patients with histologically confirmed advanced/metastatic transitional cell carcinoma (TCC) were enrolled in the study. All patients received 1,000 mg/m(2) gemcitabine administered via intravenous infusion of 30-60 minutes on days 1, 8 and 15, and 70 mg/m(2) cisplatin as an infusion of 60-min on day 2. All toxicities were graded using the WHO scale and the National Cancer Institute scale. RESULTS The average number of cycles was 4.1. Neutropenia and thrombocytopenia were clinically significant treatment-related side-effects. Hematologic toxicity included mainly grade 3-4 neutropenia in 56%, grade 3-4 thrombocytopenia in 59%, and grade 3- 4 anemia in 33% of patients. There was only one death from neutropenic sepsis. Complete response and partial response were obtained in 13 (22.4%) and 17 (29.3%) of patients, respectively, 17 (29.3%) of patients were found to have stable disease, and progression was observed in 11 patients (18.9%). Median survival for the whole group was 14.7 months (2-67). CONCLUSIONS GC therapy is an effective regimen owing to its high tumor response and long survival with a low incidence of toxicity in advanced or metastatic patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La eficacia y toxicidad de la quimioterapia con gemcitabina y cisplatino en el carcinoma urotelial de vejiga avanzado/metastásico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The efficacy and toxicity of gemcitabine and cisplatin chemotherapy in advanced/metastatic bladder urothelial carcinoma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
