<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22841463</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Casadevall, Carme</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barreiro, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gea, Joaquim</dc:author>
<dc:author>Árbol, Francisca</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pascual-Guardia, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Merlo, Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Oxidative stress and inflammation contribute to the diaphragm contractile dysfunction observed in animal models of sepsis and endotoxemia. In septic patients, molecular events have never been explored in their respiratory muscles. Levels of oxidative stress and inflammation were evaluated in a respiratory muscle, the external intercostal, and a limb muscle, the vastus lateralis, of patients with sepsis. PATIENTS AND METHODS Levels of oxidized and nitrated proteins, protein adducts of malondialdehyde and hydroxinonenal, antioxidant enzymes catalase and Mn-superoxide dismutase, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, TNF-α receptors i and ii, interleukin (IL)-1 and IL-6, the panleukocyte marker CD18, and fiber type composition were explored using immunoblotting, real time-polymerase chain reaction, and immunohistochemistry in the external intercostal and vastus lateralis of patients with severe sepsis and/or septic shock. RESULTS Compared to the controls, in septic patients, levels of oxidized and nitrated proteins were increased in the vastus lateralis, but not in the external intercostal, while those of the antioxidant enzymes did not differ, and the proportions and sizes of the muscle fibers were not significantly different in any muscle between patients and controls. CONCLUSIONS Differences in activity between the respiratory and limb muscles may account for the differential pattern of oxidative stress and inflammation observed among patients with severe sepsis. These findings may have relevant implications for the clinical and therapeutic management of these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Quadriceps</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inflamación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuádriceps</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oxidants</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>External intercostal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oxidantes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sepsis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inflammation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intercostal externo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patients</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pacientes</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Sep 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inflamación y estrés oxidativo en los músculos respiratorios y periféricos de pacientes con sepsis grave.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inflammation and oxidative stress in respiratory and limb muscles of patients with severe sepsis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
