<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22840434</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Plaza Del Pino, Fernando Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Veiga Del Pino, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES -To find out the views of nurses on Muslim patients and to determine whether these views are related to the existence of, or lack of conflicts. - To determine what the Muslim patients think of the nurses who look after them, and to see whether this is related to the existence of, or lack of conflicts. - To look for similarities or differences in the "vision of the other" in the nurse-Muslim patient relationship. METHOD Grounded Theory, using in-depth interviews. INFORMANTS Nurses (N=32), men and women of Muslim tradition who have been hospitalized in one of the public hospitals in the province of Almería (N=37) RESULTS: The nurses. In the discourses there were numerous stereotypes and prejudices towards patients of Muslim tradition. This negative view was in contrast with the lack of conflicts with this type of patient. The patients. These patients gave a positive opinion of the nurses, stressing in particular, their professional attitude and the confidence they install in them. They tended to play down any negative experience with the nursing professionals. CONCLUSIONS In spite of this stereotyped and prejudiced "vision of the other" on the part of the nurses, the relationship is not affected from the point of view of the Muslim patients. It is necessary to be aware of this negative vision that the nursing professionals have, and of the need to work actively to modify it, promoting cultural knowledge and respect through specific training in this field.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La visión del otro y la conflictividad en la relación enfermera-paciente musulmán.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The vision of the other and conflicts in the relationship between nurses and muslim patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
