<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22858767</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Butron, Joece</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lévano, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vicuña, Yuliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aranda, Renzo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miní, Elsy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varas, Rocio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutierrez, Ericson L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We aim to determine the prevalence of self prescribing behaviour during pregnancy and its characteristics. For this purpose, we designed a cross sectional study and interviewed 400 pregnant women who had their prenatal care at Instituto Nacional Materno Perinatal, Lima. We found that 10.5% of the patients (42 patients) had a self prescribing behavior during pregnancy, 64.5% think that self prescribing behavior can produce congenital malformations. The medications used were classified as type A and B according to the Food and Drug Administration (FDA). Paracetamol was used more frequently (47.6%) followed by amoxicillin (16.7%). All the women who self-prescribed have had this behavior before pregnancy. According to these results, we conclude there is a low prevalence of self-prescribing behavior during pregnancy compared to the international literature.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Automedicación en gestantes que acuden al Instituto Nacional Materno Perinatal, Perú 2011.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Self-medication behavior among pregnant women user of the Instituto Nacional Materno Perinatal, Peru 2011].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
