<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22916639</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Levario-Carrillo, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras-Solís, Rosa Emma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán-Juárez, Wendy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avila-Esparza, Marina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Hypertensive complications in pregnancy are a cause of morbidity and mortality. Previous studies have identified similarities and differences in risk factors of hypertensive complications during pregnancy. OBJECTIVE Determine factors associated with gestational hypertension (HTG) and those related to preeclampsia (PEE). PATIENTS AND METHODS Case-control study. We included women who completed pregnancy without complications (n=260) and were diagnosed with HTG (n=65) and PEE (n=65). We excluded patients with gestational or pre-pregnancy diabetes, thyroid disease (hypo and hyperthyroidism), autoimmune diseases (lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis) or diagnosed with heart disease or neuropathy before pregnancy. RESULTS There were similarities in the risk factors such as: age over 35 years (OR 8.8, 95% CI 2.91-22.40), previous HTG (OR 64.16 95% CI 13.04-315.57) in case of patients with PEE. But we found a difference in the magnitude of these associations as odds ratios (OR) estimates were higher than in patients with HTG, age over 35 years (OR 3.33, 95% CI 1.03-10.72), and previous HTG (OR 27.27 95% CI 5.60-132.87). First-time pregnant women showed similar associations (OR 3.11 95% CI 1.52-6.38) in case of PEE or HTG (OR 3.14 95% CI 1.65-5.97). CONCLUSION There are similarities in risk factors: maternal age--35 years, previous gestational hypertension and first-time pregnancy, for the development of gestational hypertension and preeclampsia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con hipertensión gestacional y preeclampsia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors associated with gestational hypertension and preeclampsia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
