<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2292914</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Digioia, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Toblli, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Budani, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chirife, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Collado, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marcuzzi, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association of HBV infection and glomerular damage was first reported by Combes et al in 1971, in a patient with nephrotic syndrome due to membranous glomerulopathy and chronic hepatitis B. Since, then, other glomerular diseases have been reported such as a) minimal changes nephropathy, b) IgA nephropathy, c) membranous-proliferative glomerulonephritis (MPGN), d) membranous, e) mesangial proliferative and f) lupus nephritis. All of them are associated with chronic hepatic disease and some of the following antigens: 1) HBsAg; 2) HBeAg; 3) HBcAg. These disorders are very frequent in Southeast Asia. Vertical transmission from mothers to fetuses may be important in maintaining the high carrier rate, and possibly plays a role in the development of glomerular damage. On the other hand, MPGN associated with HBsAg has rarely been reported and always with a favorable benign course. The present report describes interesting findings in a renal biopsy from a HBsAg and HBeAg carrier, who developed renal failure requiring hemodialysis. A 21 year old Korean man was admitted to the Hospital for nephrotic syndrome, microhematuria hypertension and renal failure. He had no previous history of blood transfusion, intravenous drug addiction, jaundice or liver disease. His father was HBsAg carrier with hepatic cirrhosis. An ultrasound examination showed normal renal size. Renal biopsy was performed and the patient received hemodialysis treatment. The specimen was processed for light microscopy, immunofluorescent studies and peroxidase-antiperoxidase technique. Frozen sections were studied by direct immunofluorescence for the identification of IgG, IgA, C1q, C3, fibrinogen and albumin. Paraffin sections stained by immunoperoxidase technique for HBsAg, using polyclonal monospecific rabbit anti-Human antisera (Dakopatts, Copenhagen).(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glomerulonefritis membranoproliferativa con semilunas y depósitos masivos de IgA asociada a HBsAg.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis with semilunar forms and massive deposits of IgA associated with HBsAg].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
