<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22921101</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rosales-Solís, A A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Huezo, M S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda-Cordero, R M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas-Sánchez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía-García, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-González, E G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hinojosa-Ruiz, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In Mexico, the prevalence of Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) infection is high. The bacterial eradication rate with the administration of antibiotic regimens recommended by international guidelines is not yet clear. AIMS To determine the eradication frequency of H. pylori infection in the adult Mexican population that underwent treatment with the conventional triple regimen. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study was carried out that evaluated the effectiveness of the triple regimen in individuals with confirmed infection that received consensual treatment and then underwent tests to corroborate eradication. RESULTS From a total of 249 potential case records, 26 did not meet the inclusion criteria. Two hundred and twenty-three patients were enrolled for analysis, 64,00% women and 36,00% men, with a mean age of 49,4 years (range 17-86). Comorbidities presented in 55,60% of the patients and 28,60% referred to chronic use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). Bacterial eradication with the triple regimen was 65,50% (146/223); of the 77 patients with no eradication, 11 received a quadruple regimen as second-line treatment resulting in bacterial eradication in 5/11 (45,45%) patients, for an overall eradication of 67,70%. CONCLUSIONS The eradication rate in our study population was suboptimal due to the probability of multiple factors that are difficult to identify, given the retrospective design of the study. A prospective and controlled evaluation of the recommended regimens needs to be carried out in order to determine their true effectiveness.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de erradicación del Helicobacter pylori con triple esquema convencional en pacientes adultos del Centro Médico Issemym.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Helicobacter pylori eradication frequency with the conventional triple therapy in adult patients at the Centro Médico Issemym].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
