<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22981282</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torijano-Casalengua, María Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maderuelo-Fernández, José Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silvestre-Busto, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Astier-Peña, María Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olivera-Cañadas, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE [corrected] To validate a tool to measure patient safety culture in Spanish primary care professionals. METHODS Medical Office Survey on Patient Safety Culture (MOSPSC), from the Agency for Healthcare and Research in Quality (AHRQ). The process has been performed in five steps: original version traslation, conceptual equivalence evaluation, acceptability and viability assessment, content validity and questionnaire test and response analysis and psichometric properties assessment. SETTING Primary care. SUBJECTS 185 Primary care professionals from different Spanish regions represented the sample test. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES Frecuency, response pattern and discrimination power of each item. Cronbach's alpha coefficient and dimensions obtained through factor analysis. RESULTS 17, 8% of respondents answered all the items and 28, 7% of them did not answer, or answered the option "Don't know/Does not apply", to one to four items. All the sentences, with only one exception, present discrimination capacity. Cronbach's alpha coefficient results 0,96 and information is sumarized in 15 factors obtaining the same items in 7 of the total 12 factors in the original questionnaire. CONCLUSIONS Traslated, adapted, extended and validated AHRQ questionnaire is, in this setting, a reliable and useful instrument and it must be used for international comparisons.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un cuestionario para evaluar la cultura de seguridad del paciente de los profesionales de atención primaria en España.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Validation of a questionnaire to assess patient safety culture in Spanish Primary Health Care professionals].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
