<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22991029</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9110</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garrido Estepa, Macarena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Marcos, Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Pezzi, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarrubia Enseñat, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Valín, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND European recent data about paediatric tuberculosis point out the importance of evaluate the trends of the disease to study the recent transmission, as well as the necessity of improving the microbiological diagnosis in paediatric cases. The aim of this paper is to study the epidemiology and trend evolution of paediatric tuberculosis in Spain during the period 2005-2009 and to establish the epidemiological differences between adult and paediatric tuberculosis. METHODS Data reported to the National Surveillance Net (Red Nacional de Vigilancia Epidemiológica) in Spain was checked. Lineal regression was developed to establish the trend of the disease in all, adult and paediatric cases. Bivariate and multivariate logistic regression was used to compare paediatric and adult cases reported in 2009 and estimate the influence of different factors in the development of the disease. RESULTS A total 39775, 2690 paediatrics (6.76%) cases of tuberculosis were reported during 2005-2009 period. Paediatric tuberculosis rates showed a slight increasing tendency (y=0.15x+7.8), while adult rates decrease during the period (y=-0.28x+20.2). In 2009, rates were 8.1 and 18.3 cases/100,000 inhab. for children and adults respectively. Paediatric cases presented higher proportion of pulmonary locations (84% vs. 76% in adults) and lower percentages of cases confirmed by culture (51% vs. 82% in adults) and of cases in non-Spanish population (25% vs. 34%). CONCLUSIONS Paediatric tuberculosis rates showed a slight increasing tendency, while global and adult rates decrease slightly during the period. Tuberculosis disease shows different epidemiology in children and adults, what it is important to take into account to design public heh interventions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la tuberculosis pediátrica en España, 2005-2009.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Epidemiology of childhood tuberculosis in Spain: 2005-2009].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
