<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>22997766</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Erbín, Mariana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cogut, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jordá Vargas, Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Errecalde, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Posse, Tamara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kaufman, Sara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cattani, Eugenia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hermes, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tutzer, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eighty one rectal swabs (RS) were cultured on CHROMagar KPC and the CDC method. Of the 81 samples, 9 were positive for KPC-producing Klebsiella pneumoniae on CHROMagar KPC, and 6 for the CDC method. CHROMagar KPC had two false positive (FP) results: 1 K. pneumoniae and 1 Acinetobacter sp. FP results on the CDC method were: 25 Acinetobacter spp., 2 Escherichia coli and 4 K. pneumoniae: CHROMagar KPC yielded a better recovery of KPC-producing bacteria and less FP results than CDC method. In order to evaluate FP results on CHROMagar KPC, 1247 RS were cultured and yielded 1021 negatives, 171 KPC-producing K. pneumoniae and 55 FP (4.4 %). Because of the FP results growing on CHROMagar KPC, KPC must be phenotypically confirmed in the bacteria isolated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">CHROMagar Kpc. Comparación con el método propuesto por los Centros para el Control y Prevención de Enfermedades (CDC, EE.UU.) para el estudio de portación rectal y evaluación de falsos positivos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[CHROMagar KPC. Comparison with the method proposed by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC, USA) for rectal screening and evaluation of false positive results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
