<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23020978</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanchis, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morillas, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fácila, Lorenzo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Alonso, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Redón, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pallarés, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llisterri, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Age and arterial hypertension are two of the main factors associated with atrial fibrillation and an increased risk of embolism. The objective of this study was to determine the prevalence of atrial fibrillation and the extent of antithrombotic use in hypertensive patients aged ≥65 years in the Spanish region of Valencia. METHODS Each study investigator enrolled the first three hypertensive patients aged ≥65 years who came for a consultation on the first day of each week for 5 weeks. Each patient's risk factors, history of cardiovascular disease, CHADS(2) score and medical treatment were noted and an ECG was recorded. Data were analyzed centrally. A patient was regarded as having atrial fibrillation if it was observable on the ECG or reported in medical records. RESULTS The study included 1,028 hypertensive patients with a mean age of 72.8 years. Overall, 10.3% had atrial fibrillation: in 6.7%, it was observable on the ECG while 3.6% were in sinus rhythm but had a history of the condition. Factors associated with atrial fibrillation were age, alcohol intake, structural heart disease and glomerular filtration rate. In total, 76.2% of patients with ECG evidence of atrial fibrillation and a CHADS(2) score &gt;1 were taking anticoagulants compared with 41.7% of those who had a history of the condition but were currently in sinus rhythm. CONCLUSIONS The prevalence of atrial fibrillation in our group of hypertensives was 10.3%; in 1.7%, it was previously undiagnosed. Antithrombotic use was high in patients with current atrial fibrillation, but lower in those who had experienced an episode previously.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalencia de fibrilación auricular y uso de fármacos antitrombóticos en el paciente hipertenso ≥ 65 años. El registro FAPRES.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
