<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23021574</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez Martín, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez Delgado, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pombo Allés, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo Martínez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avellaneda Fernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Identify the elements that lead to the perception that primary health care physicians (PHCP) have as regards rare diseases (RD) as a whole, and to analyse the characteristics of these patients with rare diseases. METHODS Descriptive cross-sectional study. Surveys completed by PHCP during the years 2008-2010 were used to explore socio-demographic data, health care facilities, manpower, and services, knowledge level, expectations, means of obtaining available information, and training-support preferences of RD. RESULTS A total of 260 questionnaires were analysed. The average level of knowledge was 3.68 (SD 1.93), of interest 7.34 (SD 2.02), and of importance 7.51 (SD 1.69). Less than one quarter (20.4%) of responders had done some training activity. Care at home (6.38, SD 2.07) is the most valued long term care option, emphasising the need of primary prevention (7.63 SD 1.5). Over one-third (35%) applied for some aid, mainly economic (37.4%). Internet is their main source of information (71.2%), and an average of 7.85 (SD 2.38) perceived the need for specific continuing training. By registered lists, each professional attends a mean of 2.45 (SD 3.69) patients with RD, 1.604% having temporary work disability, 1.479% having some disability and 1.62% with a dependence situation. The follow up of RD patients was: at Hospital level 55.72%, by special reference units 44.34%, by specialists 39.75%, and exclusively at PHCP level 14.46%. CONCLUSIONS PHCP have a low level of knowledge of RD, although a high interest, with emphasis on primary prevention, the importance of the family environment, genetic counselling and health education. They rarely request medical resources for RD. Internet is their main source of information, and prefer specific continuing education courses.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de las enfermedades raras por el médico de atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Perception of rare diseases by the primary care physicians].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
