<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23021228</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7286</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Harto-Castaño, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Desco-Esteban, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borghol-Kassar, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Menezo-Rozalén, J L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the effectiveness of various surgical procedures in the management of posterior capsule and anterior vitreous on the prevention of visual axis opacification. SUBJECTS, MATERIAL AND METHODS We retrospectively reviewed 120 eyes operated for unilateral congenital cataracts, with a median age at the time of cataract surgery of 21 months (interquartile range, 6-52 months). The eyes were divided into 3 groups: group 1 (eyes with intact posterior capsule, n=39), group 2 (eyes with posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis, n=38), group 3 (eyes with posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis and anterior vitrectomy, n=43). RESULTS To determine the effect of posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis on visual axis opacification we compared group 2 with group 1 (chi-square Pearson test, P=.281), therefore in this study the implementation of the posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis did not show any decreases in the incidence of visual axis opacification. To study the effect of posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis associated anterior vitrectomy, we compared group 3 with group 1 (chi-square Pearson test, P=.014), demonstrating that the combination of both techniques (posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis and anterior vitrectomy) decreases the incidence of visual axis opacification. CONCLUSION Posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis as a single technique did not show any decrease in the incidence of visual axis opacification. Posterior continuous curvilinear capsulorhexis together with anterior vitrectomy are required to prevent visual axis opacification and to decrease reoperation rate.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de técnicas intraoperatorias para la prevención de la opacificación del eje visual en la cirugía de cataratas congénitas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of intra-operative techniques to prevent visual axis opacification in congenital cataract surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
