<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23040654</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Freire Vila, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juncal Díaz, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Iglesia López, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rett syndrome is a severe and incapacitating neurological disease caused by a structural defect in the short arm of the X chromosome (Xq28). It affects females and consists of multiple and progressive neurological impairments that start from a young age, leading to lifelong disability and dependency. Scoliosis appears in more than 50% of patients and requires surgical correction in cases where the curvature is severe. Pre-anaesthetic assessment is essential in order to identify the risk factors and thus reduce the morbidity and mortality associated with the surgical procedure. We present the case of a patient affected by this syndrome and scoliosis, who was scheduled to have an instrumented thoracolumbar spine arthrodesis with general anaesthesia, which passed without incident. We evaluate the specific details of this syndrome, its potential complications, and its management from an anaesthetic point of view, emphasising the control of postoperative pain using a double epidural catheter with an infusion of local anaesthetics and fentanyl.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Rett: doble catéter epidural para control del dolor postoperatorio tras cirugía de escoliosis. Revisión de la bibliografía.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rett syndrome: double epidural catheter for the control of postoperative pain after scoliosis surgery. A literature review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
