<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23159107</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-8070</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero-Farina, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pizzi, M N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguadé-Bruix, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Dorado, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castell-Conesa, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>De León, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Candell-Riera, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuberas-Borrós, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the evolutive changes in diastolic function after percutaneous coronary revascularization (PCR) in acute myocardial infarction (AMI), using myocardial perfusion gated SPECT. METHODS Thirty-two patients (mean 61.9±9.7 years, 7 women) were studied by two at rest gated SPECT: the first gated-SPECT-1 was performed with an injection of a dose of (99m)Tc-tetrofosmin prior to PCR and the second gated-SPECT-2 between the fourth and fifth weeks after AMI. Changes of peak filling rate (PFR) and the time to peak filling rate (TTPF) were assessed between both studies, and were related to the extent of salvaged myocardium (SM), end-diastolic (EDV) and end-systolic (ESV) volumes, and left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) changes. RESULTS An improvement was observed in diastolic function parameters Gated-SPECT-2: PFR increased significantly (P=0.011) while the TTPF decreased without reaching statistical significance (P=0.288). In multivariate analysis, adjusted by clinical and coronary variables, improvement of PFR was significantly associated with percentage of SM (P=0.030), increase in LVEF (P=0.004) and with ESV volume reduction (P=0.005). Improvement of TTPF was only related significantly to the percentage of SM (P=0.046). PFR increased 0.01 EDV/sec. and TTPF decreased 1.14ms for each cm(2) increase of the area of SM. CONCLUSIONS After PCR in AMI, the myocardial perfusion gated SPECT makes it possible to assess the significant improvement in diastolic function mainly related to the amount of MS.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la función diastólica mediante gated-SPECT de perfusión miocárdica tras revascularización coronaria en el infarto agudo de miocardio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of the diastolic function by myocardial perfusion gated SPECT after coronary revascularization in acute myocardial infarction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear e imagen molecular</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
