<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23169363</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Górriz, J Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Celaya, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcázar, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Egocheaga, M Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lobos, José M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Castelao, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In 2007, the Spanish Society of Family and Community Medicine (semFYC) and the Spanish Society of Nephrology (S.E.N.) created a consensus document in order to reduce the variability in clinical practices for the detection, treatment, and referral of cases of chronic kidney disease (CKD). OBJECTIVES To evaluate the level of awareness, dissemination, agreement, and application of the S.E.N.-semFYC consensus document on chronic kidney disease. METHOD Ours was a cross-sectional, descriptive, and observational study carried out among 476 primary health care doctors and nephrologists using a survey. RESULTS Of the 326 primary care doctors and 150 nephrologists surveyed, 51.1% and 89.6% respectively knew of the consensus document. A total of 70.8% of nephrologists considered the document to be highly necessary, and were very much in agreement with the content. Primary care doctors placed more value on the practical usefulness of the document (63.2% AP vs. 52.1% nephrologists).The sections that reported the greatest level of unfamiliarity among primary care doctors (&gt;20% of those surveyed) included recommendations regarding the suitability of ultrasound examinations in male patients with CKD older than 60 years of age and in regards to the criteria for patient referral to the nephrology department. The level of application of the recommendations set forth in the document varied widely between the two specialties, with greater compliance among nephrologists. Age, sex, field of medicine, professional experience, the population treated, and health care workload were not significantly associated with differences in awareness, perceived need, or application of the consensus document. CONCLUSIONS This survey demonstrates that the level of implementation of the S.E.N.-sem- FYC consensus document for CKD has much room for improvement, above all among primary care physicians. The application of this consensus document can improve clinical practice. Several critical aspects have been identified in the evaluation and referral of patients with CKD that must be addressed through the establishment of strategies for disseminating information and continued training for the scientific societies involved in treating these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Awareness and implementation in daily practice of the S.E.N.-semFYC consensus document on chronic kidney disease.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
