<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23165557</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García Caballero, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vivas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete Aulestia, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete L L, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pulgar, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyba, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The incidence of obesity and its most feared comorbidity, diabetes mellitus type 2, is increasing and there would not seem to be any medical treatment to help control these pandemics. However, there is a bariatric surgery technique, the Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass (RYGB), which is safe and not only helps control excess weight, but produces encouraging results in the control and remission of diabetes. METHODS We present 15 selected patients with a BMI between 30 and 35 kg/mt² and diabetes type 2 who underwent a laparoscopic RYGB with of one-year follow-up. RESULTS A total of 14 women and one man were operated with the following average values: age: 37 years, weight: 88.3 kg, BMI: 32.8 kg/mt², blood glucose: 120 ± 38.8 mg%, HbA1c: 7.6 ± 0.73. Forty percent (40%) suffered from high blood pressure and 33.3% were dyslipidemic. Average surgical time was 75 minutes, hospital length of stay was two days, and there was a low rate of complications and no mortality. Diabetes remission was achieved in 93% of cases with significant drops in blood glucose and HbA1c (p ≤ 0.05 and p ≤ 0.001 respectively), dyslipidemia was 100% controlled and hypertension was 83.3% controlled. CONCLUSIONS RYGB in selected patients with obesity type 1 and diabetes mellitus type 2 is a safe and effective technique for metabolic control and obesity control.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bypass gástrico en Y de Roux para el tratamiento de pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo II con IMC de 30 a 35 kg/m²</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Roux-en-Y gastric bypass for treatment of patients with DM type 2 and BMI of 30 to 35 Kg/m²].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
