<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23174826</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Schmidt, André</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dessotte, Carina Aparecida Marosti</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dantas, Rosana Aparecida Spadoti</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rossi, Lídia Aparecida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, Gislaine Pinn</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM to assess the clinical evolution of patients hospitalized due to the first episode of Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS) according to its clinical manifestation. METHODS data were collected from 234 patients, hospitalized between May 2006 and July 2009 due to the first episode of an ACS, by consulting their medical records. RESULTS 234 patients were hospitalized, 140 (59.8%) due to Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI). In the group with AMI, 19.3% presented complications, against 12.8% in the group with Unstable Angina (UA) (p=0.19). Angioplasty levels were higher among patients with AMI than with UA (p=0.02) and coronary artery bypass graft surgery was more frequent among UA patients (p=0.03). The majority (227; 97%) survived after the coronary event. Among the seven patients who died during the hospitalization, four had AMI (2.9%) and three UA (3.2%). CONCLUSIONS A larger number of complications were found among infarction victims and the accomplishment of coronary artery bypass graft surgery differed between the groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical evolution of patients hospitalized due to the first episode of acute coronary syndrome.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
