<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23177340</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-8070</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Talavera Rubio, M P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poblete García, V M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomar Muñoz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peiró Valgañón, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bellón Guardia, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soriano Castrejón, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cañuelo Merino, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Vicente, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pilkington Woll, J P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero García, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González García, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez García, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the process of implementing a quality management system according to UNE-EN-ISO 9001:2008 standard in a Nuclear Medicine Department. MATERIAL AND METHOD In February 2008, the committee on internal quality of the Department was established, naming a responsible physician. The general operating plan was drawn up, following the requirements established by the ISO 9001:2008 standard. It defined the scope of the standard, defining, preparing and transcribing the various activities of our Department. Four training sessions were carried out. RESULTS A total of nine general and two specific procedures were documented in which all the activities performed in our Department were included. Personnel records of each worker were created, including their profiles and training plan. A record of the equipment and service providers was created, as well as issues with the latter. Satisfaction surveys were obtained from external (patients) and internal customers (faculty applicants). Targets for improvement and activity markers were established. Two audits were performed to complete the process, one internal and one external. The Department was accredited in April 2010. CONCLUSION The quality accreditation process is a tool that requires reflection on how we do things and how they can be improved. It makes it possible to measure what we do, to analyze and introduce improvement measures, and therefore, to achieve a higher level of quality in the service we provide our customers. The involvement of the Department workers with a commitment to team performance was essential.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de un sistema de gestión de calidad según norma UNE-UN-ISO 9001:2008 en un servicio de medicina nuclear.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Implementation of a quality management system according to the UNE-UN-ISO 9001:2008 standard in a nuclear medicine department].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear e imagen molecular</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
