<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23177941</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-8856</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arrazola, M P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz-Gallardo, M I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Resines, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Juanes, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García de Codes, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaén, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the incidence of surgical site infection in knee prosthesis surgical procedure for a follow-up period of one year in twelve hospitals in Madrid region. MATERIAL AND METHOD A prospective study was carried out from January to December 2009 using a national surveillance system called Indicadores Clínicos de Mejora Continua de Calidad. Primary and revision knee joint replacements in patients operated on in the previous year were included. Criteria used to define surgical site infection and patient risk index categories were those established by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and National Nosocomial Infections Surveillance. The incidence rates were worked out crude and adjusted by hazard ratio. RESULTS 2,088 knee prosthesis procedures were analyzed. The overall incidence of surgical site infection was 2.1%. Sixty-five percent of the infections were organ/space. Sixty percent of the infections were identified in the early postoperative period. Of all surgical site infections, 41.9% were microbiologically confirmed. Antibiotic prophylaxis was implemented correctly in 63.3% of the cases. The most important cause of inappropriate prophylaxis was an unsuitable duration in 85.7% of the cases. The presurgical preparation was carried out correctly in 50.3% of surgical operations. The incidence of knee arthroplasty infection was twice as high as in the National Healthcare Safety Network and similar to national rates. DISCUSSION In this study, the incidence of infection was within the range of infection rates in other published European studies. Surveillance and control strategies of health care for associated infections allow us to assess trends and the impact of preventive measures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio multicéntrico sobre la incidencia de infección en prótesis de rodilla.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Multicentre study of infection incidence in knee prosthesis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cirugia ortopedica y traumatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
