<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23182266</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Miranda-Medrano, Luis Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Nava, Silvia Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Jesús Flores, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Rojas, José Emidgio Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Pilar Torres-Arreola, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-García, Blanca Elsa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Stroke is considered a big public health problem in adults and older adults. Increased life expectancy is one of the greatest achievements of development; however it is also a great challenge because of the implications with regard to increasing chronic disease that it will lead complications such as stroke. Stroke is the leading cause of disability worldwide in adulthood and the second leading cause of dementia. In developing countries, it is estimated that the costs of care for stroke are from 6000 to 8000 euros, as well as the social costs of informal care and changes in family dynamics around patients. So the purpose of this clinical practice guideline is to define recommendations based on the best available evidence for the standardization of health care of patients with stroke.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de práctica clínica. Enfermedad vascular cerebral isquémica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical guideline for the prevention, diagnosis and treatment of ischemic cerebral disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
