<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23182251</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cruz-Olivo, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes-Allen, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Bonilla, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Padilla-Reyes, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Rey-Pineda, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Elorriaga, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to determine the relation between IL6, IL10 and TNFa serum levels in a cohort of patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D) and severe soft tissue infections (STI), with severity and mortality factors. METHODS A. comparative and transversal, study with 15 adult patients, any gender, with T2D and STI were done. A T2D control group of 20 patients without STI was included. Apache II Score, glycemia and by ELISA, IL6, IL10 and TNFa, were determined. RESULTS in all patients, it was a correlation at beginning between glycemia and IL6 (r = 0.67, IC 95 % 0.24-0.88), as soon as glycemia and Apache II, (r = 0.59, IC 95 % 0.11-0.83). CONCLUSIONS although IL6 was very usefulness, it is not a routine test in clinical laboratory and it is expensive, but in medical practice, it could be possible to evaluate these patients with Apache II Score and glycemia. However, in STI, the values of IL6 and IL10 were highly significant. It is likely that IL6 is a marker of poor outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Citocinas, diabetes e infección de tejidos blandos. Su relación con la severidad y mortalidad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pro-inflammatory cytokines related to severity and mortality in type 2 diabetes patients with soft tissue infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
