<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23200694</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Foguet Boreu, Quintí</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bullón Chia, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gordo Serra, Núria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roura Poch, Pere</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mauri Martin, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cecília Costa, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To determine the cardiovascular risk factors (CVRF), level of cardiovascular risk (CVR) and to analyse the relationship between CVR and quality of life in patients with severe mental illness (SMI). DESIGN OF STUDY Cross sectional study. SETTING Mental Health Service, Consorci Hospitalari de Vic (Barcelona). SUBJECTS Patients over 18 years diagnosed with SMI. MAIN MEASUREMENTS Data was collected on, socio-demographic variables, toxic habits, previous pathologies, family history of premature cardiovascular disease, psychiatric diagnoses, physical parameters and laboratory findings. The CVR was determined by the SCORE and REGICOR scales. Quality of life was measured by Euro-QoL and Seville Questionnaires. RESULTS A total of 137 patients with SMI were included; 64.9% female, and a mean age 51.1 years (SD 12.9). Major CVRF distribution: 40.1% smoking, 37.9% hypertension, 56.2% dyslipidemia, and 11.1% diabetes. The criteria for obesity and metabolic syndrome were met by 37.9% and 48.4% of the patients, respectively. The average major CVRF was 1.5 factors. The CVR was high in 4.6% of the sample by SCORE and in 5.4% by REGICOR. Neither the patients who accumulated more CVRF or those with high CVR scores showed a worse quality of life. CONCLUSIONS The most prevalent CVRF in patients with SMI are smoking and dyslipidemia, with a prevalence that exceeded population-based studies. The subgroup of depressive disorders showed a higher CVR and worse quality of life. No relationships were found between the CVR and the quality of life.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo cardiovascular, riesgo cardiovascular y calidad de vida en pacientes con trastorno mental severo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiovascular risk factors, cardiovascular risk and quality of life in patients with a severe mental disorder].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
