<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23258723</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mansano-Schlosser, Thalyta Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ceolim, Maria Filomena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to evaluate the characteristics of sleep and the factors associated with the quality of sleep in elderly patients receiving outpatient chemotherapy treatment. METHOD cross-sectional study with 140 elderly patients (51.2% female, average age 69.8 years) with stage III or stage IV cancer (67.9%), undertaken in a university hospital in the state of São Paulo in 2010. The following instruments were used: sociodemographic and clinical characterization questionnaire, validated by specialists; Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; Piper Fatigue Scale-reviewed; and a scale for the subjective measurement of pain. RESULTS the majority of the elderly (62.9%) had a score compatible with poor sleep quality. On average, the duration of sleep was 388.0 minutes, latency was 44.6 minutes and efficiency of 83.8%. Through multiple logistic regression analysis, an increase of 21% in the probability of having poor sleep quality was observed for each single-point increase in the intensity of the pain. CONCLUSION nursing interventions aiming to promote better sleep quality for elderly patients with cancer must include measures for pain control.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with sleep quality in the elderly receiving chemotherapy.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
