<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23282493</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ovalle, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, María A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gianini, Romina</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Fuente, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Feliú, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentealba, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Falcon, Nicolás</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The epidemiologic rates of gonorrhea have declined steadily in Chile, while the incidence of infections with Trichomonas vaginalis and Chlamydia trachomatis is not well known. AIM Since these sexually transmitted infections (STIs) are associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes and perinatal infections, this study aimed to update their prevalence in a public hospital in the Metropolitan Region of Chile. PATIENTS AND METHODS Between April and October 2010 and April and October 2011, pregnant women attending the antenatal Service, Hospital San Borja Arriarán, were randomly selected for detection of T. vaginalis, N. gonorrhoeae and C. trachomatis by culture in modified Diamond's broth, Thayer-Martin agar, and by omp1 gene amplification by nested PCR, respectively. We excluded pregnant women who received antibiotics within the past 30 days. RESULTS Two hundred and fifty five cervicovaginal samples were analyzed. C. trachomatis was detected in 15 (5.9%) and T. vaginalis in 6 (2.4%). N. gonorrhoeae was not found. CONCLUSION The results show low prevalence of C. trachomatis and T. vaginalis and absence of N. gonorrhoeae. These rates have remained stable at this medical center since the 1990s, with a slight increase in C. trachomatis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de infecciones de transmisión sexual en mujeres embarazadas atendidas en un hospital público de Chile.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of sexually transmitted infections in pregnant women attending a public hospital in Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
