<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23282501</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferreira, Noelia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sorgentini, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yantorno, M Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esposto, Amadeo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mileo, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vibrio cholerae is a Gram-negative bacilli with curved, comma shape that belongs to the family Vibrionaceae. The antigenic structure consists of a flagellar H antigen and a somatic O antigen (used to classify V cholerae in various serogroups). Serogroups 01 and 0139 have caused epidemics of cholera. Vibrio cholerae non-01 non-139 has been isolated from patients with bacteremia, acute secretory diarrhea, dysentery, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, fever and cellulitis. Invasive forms such as meningitis, spontaneous bacterial peritonitis (SBP) and encephalitis are uncommon. Immunosuppression and cirrhosis are risk factors for developing invasive disease. This case report describes a cirrhotic patient from Salta, Argentina, consulting for abdominal pain and fever. He was diagnosed with SBP and Vibrio cholerae non-01 non-139 bacteremia. He received antibiotic treatment with third generation cephalosporins for fourteen days with favorable clinical outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Peritonitis bacteriana espontánea asociada a bacteriemia por Vibrio cholerae no O1, no O139.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Spontaneous bacterial peritonitis associated with Vibrio cholerae non-O1, non-O139 bacteremia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
