<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23282554</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alba, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez, Ana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zubleta, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catalán, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Respiratory viruses have been identified as a cause of morbidity and mortality in patients undergoing SOT and HSCT, specially in children. The most frequent are respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), influenza (FLU), parainfluenza (PI) and adenovirus (ADV). These infections are associated with progression to severe lower respiratory tract infections in up to 60% of the cases. It is advised to apply universal protection recommendations for respiratory viruses (A2) and some specific measures for FLU and AD. FLU: Annual anti-influenza vaccination (from 4-6 months post-transplantation in SOT, 6 months in HSCT (A2)); post- exposure prophylaxis in FLU (oseltamivir for 10 days (B2)). In lung transplantion, the prophylaxis should last as long as the risk period (B2). ADV: There is no vaccine nor valid chemoprophylaxis strategy to prevent ADV disease. In some specific HSCT recipients, weekly PCR monitoring is recommended until day+100 (A3).</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profilaxis de infection por virus respiratorios en niños y adultos sometidos a trasplante de órganos sólidos y precursores hematopoyéticos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prophylaxis against respiratory viral disease in pediatric and adult patients undergoing solid organ and hematopoietic stem cells transplantation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
