<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23318163</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9188</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villa López, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saavedra, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera-Carranza, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Doblas Claros, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The significant increase in systemic fungal infections is mainly due to the increase in immunocompromised patients. The high morbimortality of these infections, along with the high hospitalization costs they generate, makes them a problem of great importance in our hospital practice. Saprochaete capitata is a rare fungus that causes invasive infections, usually in immunocompromised patients, and for which there is still no consensus on the treatment regimen to be used. CASE REPORT We present a case of disseminated infection by this fungus in a heavily immunosuppressed patient, who died as a result of multiple organ failure despite the life support measures taken and the wide spectrum antibiotics. CONCLUSIONS It is vital to begin the antibiotic treatment as soon as possible, as well as the monitoring and follow-up cultures to test for fungi in neutropenic patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Neutropenic patients</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Blastoschizomyces capitatus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Invasive fungal infection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pacientes neutropénicos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Saprochaete capitata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección fúngica invasiva</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fallo multiorgánico en paciente con fungemia por Saprochaete capitata.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Multi-organ failure in a patient with fungaemia due to Saprochaete capitata].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
