<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23325137</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9110</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rabanaque Hernández, M José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Feja Solana, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bjerrum, Lars</dc:author>
<dc:author>Malo Fumanal, Sara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abad Diez, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lallana Alvarez, M Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Resistance to antibacterial drugs can be contained by judicious utilization, so we must know about its use. The objective is to describe the prevalence of antibiotic consumption and the variability in the use of antibiotics among outpatients in the different health areas of Aragon. METHODS Study of the prescription of antibiotics in the health areas of Aragon in 2008. Data were extracted from the Aragon Pharmaceutical Consumption Database, a complete register of all dispensed prescriptions. Prescription rates per 1000 individuals adjusted by sex and age were calculated using a direct and indirect standardization method. The subgroups utilization were calculated in Defined Daily Dose per 1000 inhabitants per day (DID). In the variation analysis were used: extremal quotient (EQ), coefficient of variation (CV), weighted coefficient of variation (CVw). RESULTS The adjusted rate of antibiotic varied between 279,8 and 382 per 1000 inhabitants, showing a CVw=0,12. The utilization rate in women was 364.9 per 1,000 and in men 300.0 per 1,000. Cephalosporins have a EQ=2,42 and CVw=0,37; and quinolones have EQ=1,84 and CVw=0,22. CONCLUSIONS The utilization rate was higher in women than men. The higher variability in the prescription of antibiotics among health areas in Aragon was in cephalosporins and quinolones.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad de la prescripción de antibióticos en atención primaria de los sectores sanitarios de Aragón.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Variations in the prescription of antibiotics among primary care areas in the autonomous region of Aragon, Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
