<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23331747</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Sánchez, Eva Aurora</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Herrera, Javier Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zacate-Palacios, Yazmín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva-Sánchez, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ascencio-Montiel, Iván de Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ángeles-Garay, Ulises</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Burkholderia cepacia (B. cepacia) has been the causal agent of infectious hospital outbreaks. METHODS a case-controls study was conducted to describe an outbreak of urinary tract infection associated to lubricant-gel contaminated with B. cepacia. Patients who developed UTIsc were included in this study. Their clinical data, urine cultures, antiobiograms and the molecular bacterial analysis were analyzed. RESULTS the urine culture was positive in 101 (55.8 %); the bacterial strains isolated were: B. cepacia 30.7 %, Escherichia coli 22.7 %, Enterococcus faecalis 9.9 %, Enterococcus spp. 8.9 %. They were 31 patients with B. cepacia isolation that was taken as the cases group and 63 with UTIsc due to another organism as control group. The Charlson comorbidity index was 5.3 ± 1.8 for cases and 4.5 ± 1.2 for controls. The factors associated with death were: heart disease, diabetes, pneumonia, bacteremia and UTIsc B. cepacia. CONCLUSIONS the lubricant gel used for urinary catheter placement originated the outbreak. Heart disease, pneumonia, bacteremia and UTIsc B. cepacia were related to patients' death.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones urinarias nosocomiales. Contaminación de gel con Burkholderia cepacia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hospital outbreak of urinary tract infections by lubricant gel contaminated with Burkholderia cepacia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
