<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23351442</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco-Hernández, Dulce Milagros Razo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colas-Calvere, María Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lima-Gómez, Virgilio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Risk of retinal damage in open globe eye injuries increases as the zone (location of the wound vertex) is more rearward. The value of clinical exploration to assess this variable is unknown. OBJECTIVE To establish the efficacy of clinical exploration as a diagnostic test to identify the injury zone in open globe ocular trauma. METHODS Assessment of patients with open globe ocular trauma, preoperative clinical assessment of injury zone and surgical description of the wound were carried out. The proportion and 95% confidence intervals (CI) of eyes whose zone changed during surgical repair were established, and the efficacy of clinical evaluation to diagnose zone was estimated. Features of eyes with and without zone change were compared using χ(2) test. RESULTS 89 eyes, mean age 27.1 years. Clinically, the identified zone was I in 36 eyes (40.4%), II in 38 (31.5%) and III in 25 (28.1%); the identified zone during surgery was I in 36 eyes (40.4%), II in 43 (48.3%) and III in 10 (11.2%). Zone changed in 30 eyes (34%, 95% C.I. 24 to 44). Specificity (96%), positive predictive value (93%) and positive likelihood ratio (13.9) were high only for zone II. No feature was associated with zone change. CONCLUSIONS Clinical exploration was not efficient enough to identify injury zone in open globe trauma and has low prognostic value. It is not necessary to define the injury zone at first contact; it is enough identifying properly the agent, visual function and pupil reflexes for an efficient assessment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la evaluación clínica como prueba diagnóstica para identificar la zona de lesiónen un traumatismo ocular abierto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Efficacy of clinical evaluation in diagnosing injury zone in open globe ocular trauma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
