<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23398812</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Tello, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Angulo, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cáceres, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gascón, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Segui, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Segmental ureterectomy with preservation of the kidney is a treatment option for the low grade urothelial carcinoma (LG-UC) in distal ureter that is not a candidate for endoscopic resection. Laparoscopic distal ureterectomy (LDU) with ureteral reimplantation is common in benign conditions (stenosis, iatrogenic lesion, endometriosis). However, it has been hardly described in malignant ureteral condition. The literature is reviewed in this regards and the surgical technique described. MATERIAL AND METHODS The experience regarding two cases of LDU due to low grade urothelial carcinoma in distal ureter is presented. In both, previous bladder transurethral resection (RTU) was performed. The urinary cytology was negative and the imaging studies identified urinary obstruction and distal ureter filling defect. One of the patients had a background of T1G3 bladder cancer and suffered renal failure. In both, the ureter was ligated early. Segmental ureterectomy was performed using a combined endoscopic and laparoscopic procedure with ureteral desinsertion in one case. In the other, it was exclusively laparoscopic. Both were done with 4 trocars. Ureteral reimplantation was conducted with continuous hermetic suture and without tension. In one case with background of high grade bladder tumor, pelvic lymphadenectomy was also performed. RESULTS Operating time was 180 and 240 min, respectively, with estimated bleeding of 100 and 250 ml. Hospitalization time was 6 and 4 days. The only post-operatory complication was paralytic ileum (Clavien I) in the first case. With a 20 and 12 month follow-up, there is no evidence of recurrence or dilatation. In the patient with renal failure, creatinine clearance improved. CONCLUSIONS The LDU with ureteral reimplantation is a complex technique. However, it represents a feasible and effective alternative for the treatment of LG-UC in distal ureter, as long as the oncological and reconstructive principles are respected.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ureterectomía distal laparoscópica en el tratamiento del carcinoma urotelial del uréter distal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Ureterectomy in the treatment of urothelial carcinoma of the distal ureter].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
