<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23414603</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Burgos, Felip</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roger, Nuria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosas, Alba</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escarrabill, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tresserras, Ricard</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giner, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Underdiagnosis is one of the problems with the greatest impact on respiratory disease management and requires specific interventions. Access to quality spirometry is especially important and is an objective of the Master Plan for Respiratory Diseases of the Department of Health of the Generalitat de Catalunya. OBJECTIVE To determine the current use of spirometry at public hospitals in Catalonia, possible deficiencies and options for improvement. METHODS A cross-sectional survey of 65 public hospitals in Catalonia in 2009. Descriptive analyses were developed for each public health-care region. RESULTS A lack of uniformity was observed in the use of spirometry at the regional level (between 0,98 and 1.50 spirometries per 100 inhabitants). We identified two factors associated with a higher rate of spirometry: i) the existence of a Respiratory Medicine Department at the hospital, and ii) the existence of a set location to carry out spirometries. Several areas for improvement also were identified: quality control of the test itself, the inclusion of spirometry in electronic health-care records and continuing education programs. CONCLUSIONS The results of this study have identified areas for improvement in spirometry programs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Infradiagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spirometry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Control de calidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Underdiagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Espirometría forzada</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality control</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Standards</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estándares</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey about the use of lung function testing in public hospitals in Catalonia in 2009.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
