<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23411164</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bolíbar, Bonaventura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zabaleta-Del-Olmo, Edurne</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saltó, Esteve</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pueyo, M Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marsal, Josep Ramon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puente, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was to analyze those factors associated with cigarette smoking in adolescent school children, in order to plan future school interventions for promoting good health strategies developed by the schools and Primary Health Care professionals. DESIGN Cross-sectional study with a two-stage cluster sampling. SETTING The study included 97 schools, and was carried out in 2005-06 in Catalonia (Spain). PARTICIPANTS 14-16 year-old secondary school children. MAIN MEASURES The survey was based on a self-administered paper-based questionnaire that collected sociodemographic variables, academic level, health status, family variables, sexual relations, addictive substances, mood state, and variables related to opinions on cigarette smoking The association between these variables and smoker/non-smoker variable was analyzed, as well as factors that could increase the probability of becoming a smoker using multilevel models. RESULTS A total of 9340 completed questionnaires, including 4653 from males, were received from the pupils, with a mean age of 15.2 years. The results showed that 71.1% of pupils were non-smokers, 75% of whom were males and 67.3% of females. The following factors increased the probability of becoming a smoker (OR and 95%CI): being a female 0.60 (0.53-0.68), being in the 4(th) year 1.27 (1.12-1.43), low academic performance 3.38 (2.74-4.17), self-reported regular/poor health status 2.81 (2.21-3.58), smoking parents 1.68 (1.45-1.95), alcohol consumption 5.05 (4.35-5.86), having 3 or more problems of mood state 1.22 (1.05-1.41), living without parents 1.59 (1.07-2.38), agreeing with tobacco industry advertising 1.64 (1.45-1.85) and believing that tobacco acts as a relaxant 3.57 (3.23-4.17). CONCLUSIONS Although the majority of pupils were non-smokers, smoking was more prevalent among females. The factors associated with cigarette smoking in the adolescents included sociodemographic, sociocultural, and personal environmental factors, as well as their opinions on the habit.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y factores asociados al consumo de tabaco en alumnos de enseñanza secundaria de Cataluña.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cigarette smoking prevalence and associated factors in secondary school children in Catalunya].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
