<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23427446</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez Valdez, Lizet</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isela Lantero, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oropesa González, Lisset</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berdasquera Corcho, Denis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Avila, Jorge Lorenzo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gala González, Angela</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sixty three patients were studied using sociodemographic, behavioral, clinical-immunological and risk factor variables. The objective was to estimate the size of clinical start of AIDS in Cuba and characterize these patients in terms of potentially associated factors. Clinical start represented 4.2% of the total number of AIDS patients in Cuba. The risk of suffering the disease turned to be 17 times more frequent in over 50 years-old persons. Males represented 95.2%. The risk of dying was 3 times higher in those with clinical start of AIDS. The presentation form in 25% of patients was weakening caused by AIDS. Of the total number of patients, 34.9% stated that they had suffered some sexually transmitted infection prior to HIV diagnosis and almost half had had unprotected sexual intercourse with HIV-seropositive persons. Most of them (85.2%) were occasional. It was concluded that lack of knowledge on serological situation of patient constituted a barrier to treatment and survival. It was proved that we must insist on prevention and promotion campaigns in vulnerable groups and on active screening in the health area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2007 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Debut clínico de SIDA en Cuba.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical start of AIDS in Cuba].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
