<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23431632</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramos Pérez, Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quesada Martínez, Maritza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez Perera, Antonio A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hevia Jiménez, Yosvania</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wong Sarmiento, Lin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Noda, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes Leyva, Joaquín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION ecological studies were carried out on mollusk populations of medical and veterinary importance with emphasis on Fasciola hepatica intermediary hosts species. OBJECTIVES to determine the relative abundance of populations and the possible use of some species as biological control agents against F. hepatica intermediary hosts. METHODS a total of 13 freshwater bodies were sampled during March and November, 2008 using Capture by effort unit method to capture the mollusks RESULTS thirteen mollusk species (12 gastropods and 1 bivalve) were found after sampling. The relative abundance of species varied in different types of habitat. The intermediary host species of fascioliasis were dominant in two sites. Fossaria cubensis was dominant in Canal de la Entrada despite the presence of Melanoides tuberculata. The specie Pseudosuccinea columella was more abundant in Los Mangos. In La Presa del Matadero y Las Palmas despite the presence of these species, the prevailing ones were Physa acuta and some planorbids. CONCLUSIONS the sites where intermediary hosts of Fasciola hepatica predominated were identified through data on the distribution and relative abundance. In some sites Melanoides tuberculata was present and acted as a biological control agent but it did not in others. Therefore, an evaluation on using a different thiarid would be useful to control these species.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2010 Jan-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudios ecológicos en moluscos de importancia médico-veterinaria en la granja de desarrollo La Coca.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Ecological studies on mollusk populations of medical and veterinary relevance existing in La Coca farm].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
