<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23447830</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fimia Duarte, Rigoberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vásquez Capote, Raisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mentor Sarría, Vivian Engracia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz Martínez, Ireté</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diéguez Fernández, Lorenzo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Malaria is a serious public health problem at present; it affects almost half of the population from over 100 countries and poses a high risk of reintroduction in Cuba. OBJECTIVE To identify the Culicidae species present in natural breeding sites located in three areas of Camagüey municipality, particularly anopheles. METHODS Larval inspections were carried out in 66 natural breeding sites of Anopheles almimanus located in three areas of Camagüey municipality from May to June 2010, according the World Health Organization methodology. The preferential breeding sites of Anopheles albimanus and the association of this species with other Culicidae were ascertained. RESULTS Presence of Culicidae in 28.78% of inspected breeding sites, being Anopheles albimanus the prevailing one with 63.51%. This species was captured together with Culex quinquefasciatus, Culex nigripalpus, Culex erraticus, Culex corniger, Psorophora confinnis, Psorophora howardii and Ochlerottatus scapularis, in low polluted water bodies such as lagoons (58.34%) and streams (25%), and in others more polluted such as ditches (8.33%) and narrow trails (8.33%). CONCLUSIONS The existence of species of medical and veterinary importance, particularly Anopheles albimanus, in the studied areas calls for constant monitoring of these species in order to draw up integrated strategies focused on the biological fight, and the involvement of the community in this process to help in preventing the emergence of cases or epidemic outbreaks of imported malaria.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 May-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Culícidos de relevancia médico-veterinaria presentes en criaderos naturales de tres areas de Camagüey, Cuba.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Culicidae of medical-veterinary importance in natural breeding sites located in three areas of Camagüey province in Cuba].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
