<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23446728</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Miranda-Casas, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Siegenthaler-Hierro, Rebeca</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colomer-Diago, Carla</dc:author>
<dc:author>Presentación-Herrero, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Although the diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in preschoolers is increasingly common, relatively little is known about the treatment in this developmental period. Some side effects of pharmacological intervention discourage its use as first-line intervention at this age. AIM. To analyze the effectiveness of psychosocial interventions designed to respond to the needs presented by these children, especially those based on cognitive-behavioral and socio-constructivist models. DEVELOPMENT. The review highlights the effectiveness of parent training programs, alone or combined with interventions at school and with the children. Communication between parents and teachers has been shown to be a determinant of their success. Another aspect that seems to favor the efficacy of treatment in this stage of education is the inclusion in the school curriculum of mediated activities aimed at developing self-regulation. CONCLUSIONS. In preschoolers with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, preventive action based on these models, increasing the intensity of the intervention depending on the student's response, can help to avoid future problems.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Feb 22 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analisis de factores moduladores de la intervencion psicosocial en preescolares con trastorno por deficit de atencion/hiperactividad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Moderators of psychosocial intervention in preschoolers with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
