<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2344229</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Parcero Valdez, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Necoechea Alva, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aceves Miramontes, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villalpando Gutiérrez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro Robles, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Twenty seven patients, 43 to 69 years of age, all with disabling stable angina and positive Bruce stress test, no amendable for revascularization procedures mainly because of poor distal coronary run-off by angiography, were studied with two calcium-channel blockers, the recently developed gallopamil hydrochloride and nifedipine hydrochloride. According to a double blind, cross-over protocol of 12 week duration and after a 2-week washout period, the patients randomly received during 4 weeks 50 mg gallopamil capsules t i d, or 10 mg nifedipine capsules t i d. After a second 2-week wash-out, the alternative drug was administered for another 4 weeks. The number of anginal episodes decreased significantly (p less than 0.01) with both treatments (from 6.4 to 1.8 crisis with gallopamil and from 6.2 to 2.1 with nifedipine). Heart rate (HR) was progressively reduced with gallopamil (-7.9%, p less than 0.05) but increased with nifedipine (+5.7%) in relation to basal figures. Both medications reduced the level of ST depression during the stress test (52.4% with gallopamil and 41.8% with nifedipine, N.S.). The time for angina at the stress test increased 92.5% with gallopamil and 40.7% with nifedipine (p less than 0.05). HR systolic product at peak exercise was 23,101 with gallopamil and 24,906 with nifedipine (p less than 0.001). Both calcium-channel blockers are drugs with significant anti-anginal effects in patients with stable, disabling angina.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico comparativo de los bloqueadores del calcio, galopamil y nifedipina, en el tratamiento de la angina de pecho estable.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A comparative clinical study of calcium blockers, gallopamil and nifedipine, in the treatment of stable chest angina].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
