<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23472927</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil-Ascencio, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacios-Saucedo, Gerardo Del Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valle-de la O, Adrián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo-Gómez, Carlos Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Postoperative pain is the main symptom and the most incapacitating one in tonsillectomy, and prescribing oral antibiotics to reduce postoperative pain is common. The objective of this study was to evaluate the efficacy of 2 different prophylactic antibiotic schemes to reduce postoperative morbidity in paediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy. One scheme consisted of a single-dose preoperative cephalothin, while the second was an oral antibiotic. METHODS This was an open randomized trial on patients aged 4-15 years undergoing tonsillectomy. The experimental group received single-dose intravenous cephalothin, while the control group received single-dose intravenous cephalothin plus oral suspension of amoxicillin/clavulanate for 7 days. We compared the presence and intensity of pain, limitations to normal diet, habitual activities, halitosis, otalgia and nausea within 7 days after surgery using the Wong-Baker FACES Pain Scale and a questionnaire for the parents. RESULTS For the 102 patients that underwent tonsillectomy (51 per group), there was no difference in the presence and severity of postoperative pain between the 2 groups (P&gt;.05). Neither was there any difference in the days needed to return to normal activities, normal diet, and duration of days with halitosis, otalgia or nausea. Just 1 patient from the control group had postoperative bleeding. There were no infectious complications. CONCLUSIONS The use of single-dose preoperative intravenous cephalothin has the same efficacy as the use of oral amoxicillin/clavulanate for 7 days in reducing morbidity in paediatric patients undergoing tonsillectomy and offers safe antimicrobial prophylaxis. Consequently, the routine use of oral antibiotics should be avoided.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Amigdalectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibiotics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tonsillectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dolor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Morbilidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Morbidity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibióticos</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibiotic prophylaxis in tonsillectomy and its relationship with postoperative morbidity.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
