<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23513405</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zamora Escudero, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Benítez, Carlos Quesnel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acosta Martínez, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vieyra Cortés, Edmundo Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ectopic location of endometrial glands and stroma may cause the formation of a tumor known as endometrioma. It almost always occurs in the ovary, and due to its characteristic appearance has been called "chocolate cyst". Cervical localization of this disease is extremely rare, and when it occurs, tends to be an exocervical and/or endocervical injury, as a result of cervical procedures. We communicate the case of a patient with cystic endometriosis in the cervix after a subtotal abdominal hysterectomy, performed by obstetric hemorrhage. Even though there have been reports about cases of cervical endometriosis, most of them have been reported as superficial cervical endometriosis and as a discovery after a total hysterectomy or cervical biopsy, in some cases even with original diagnosis ofAGUS (atypical glandular cells of undetermined significance). We concluded that in this case, instrumented uterine curettage and subtotal hysterectomy by obstetric indication are a possible origin of cervical endometriosis, due to "seeding" endometrial tissue during the curettage in a friable cervix.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor pélvico crónico y endometriosis cervical después de histerectomía subtotal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic pelvic pain and cervical endometriosis after a subtotal hysterectomy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
