<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23566559</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hermida Pérez, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bermejo Hernandez, Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sobenes Gutierrez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Toxoplasmosis is an infection of worldwide distribution caused by Toxoplasma gondii, and infects a large proportion of the world population. Only under certain circumstances of severe immunosuppression can the parasite reactivate and cause disease. The most common form of presentation of this pathology in patients with positive HIV is the brain abscess. One of the extra-cerebral forms is toxoplasmic chorioretinitis, which could lead to a chronic active form of a slowly progressive retinitis. Diagnosis is made by observing the eye fundus and confirmed by the scarring obtained after specific treatment. We report a case of a patient with diabetes and positive HIV, in whom a toxoplasmic scar injury was detected in the annual retinography follow-up. A conservative therapeutic approach was decided, with regular check-ups for possible detection of disease activation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Coriorretinitis toxoplásmica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oftalmología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Toxoplasmic chorioretinitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Human immunodeficiency virus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ophthalmology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virus inmunodeficiencia humana</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones oftalmológicas de la infección por toxoplasma en paciente portador del virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana. Descripción de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Ophthalmic manifestations of toxoplasmosis in a human immunodeficiency virus-positive patient. Description of a case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
