<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23583184</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fleitas, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tamborero, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leiva, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fonseca, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benejam, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To analyze the lifestyles of family physicians, their influence on cardiovascular prevention activities carried out on their patients and the difficulties in carrying them out. MATERIAL AND METHODS Design cross-sectional study, using as an anonymous ad hoc questionnaire, implemented in 2010. LOCATION Primary care of Mallorca. PARTICIPANTS Representative sample of 185 primary care medical professionals of Mallorca. RESULTS There was a response rate of 78.9% (146/185). Characteristics of physicians surveyed: the mean age was 43.6 years, 24.6% following a healthy diet, 18.6% were smokers, 32.7% did not consume alcohol, and 80.8% performed physical exercise. The most frequent prevention activity on their patients was anti-smoking advice (52.3%), followed by those related to cardiovascular risk factors, hypertension, diabetes, dyslipidemia (22.7%), dietary advice (14.4%), advice about exercise (5.3%), and alcohol consumption (0.8%). Doctors who smoked and drank more alcohol offered less preventive activities to their patients (P&lt;.05). Lack of time was the main limiting factor to properly perform prevention activities. CONCLUSIONS There is a relationship between lifestyle habits of primary care physicians and preventive activities carried out with their patients. Family physicians have relatively healthy lifestyles and promote preventive activities among their patients. The limited investigation into alcohol consumption should be noted.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Prevention</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevención</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estilos de vida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Factores de riesgo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lifestyles</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Risk factors</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de vida de los médicos de atención primaria: percepción e implicaciones sobre la prevención cardiovascular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Lifestyles of primary care physicians: perception and implications on cardiovascular prevention].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
