<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23588454</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramos-Jiménez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Torres, R P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wall-Medrano, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Studies on the state of health and nutrition of Mexicans with intellectual disability (ID) including those with Down syndrome (DS), are scarce. OBJECTIVE To analyze some physiological and social factors associated with the body mass of young people with ID from northern México. METHODS Body weight, height and other anthropometric values were measured in fifty seven young (17 ± 5 years) participants with ID (DS,16%) and at least one guardian. BMI (kg/m²), somatotype and nutritional status were established by three international standards and total blood glucose, cholesterol &amp; triacylglycerides, were also analyzed. Guardian's socio-economic, household food insecurity and nutrition literacy status were estimated with validated questionnaires by direct interview. RESULTS Participants with SD were 12 cm smaller but subscapular skinfold (SECPS) was 6 mm thicker than that from other ID participants (p &lt; 0.05). Prevalence of overweight/obesity was 70 and 44%, respectively. Blood biochemicals were similar between groups, but 25% had dyslipidemias. Participant's BMI correlated (p &lt; 0,01) with several anthropometric &amp; adiposity indicators (r = 0,40 a 0,88 ), blood triglycerides (r = 0,48 ) and cholesterol (r = 0,44) and guardians &amp; participants' age (r = 0,35). The spending in food correlated (p &lt; 0.05) with participant's SECPS (r = -0.33). The circumference of the waist, hip, calf and PSECP, 89% of the variance of the BMI explained. CONCLUSION The body mass of young people with DI from northern Mexico, is strongly related to the degree of body adiposity, dyslipidemias, and some socio-economic factors of their family environment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores fisiológicos y sociales asociados a la masa corporal de jóvenes Mexicanos con discapacidad intelectual.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Physiological and social factors associated with increments of body mass of Mexican young people with intellectual disabilities].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
