<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23680749</identifier>
<setSpec>1851-8265</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gianuzzi, Leda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monteverde, Malena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cipponeri, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Angelaccio, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to analyze the origin and quality of water used for consumption in a sample of households in Matanza-Riachuelo river basin area in Greater Buenos Aires, Argentina. The results of drinking water by source indicated that 9% of water samples from the public water system, 45% of bottled water samples and 80% of well water samples were not safe for drinking due to excess content of coliforms, Escherichia coli or nitrates. Individuals living in households where well water is the main source of drinking water have a 55% higher chance of suffering a water-borne disease; in the cases of diarrheas, the probability is 87% higher and in the case of dermatitis, 160% higher. The water for human consumption in this region should be provided by centralized sources that assure control over the quality of the water.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Origen y calidad del agua para consumo humano: salud de la población residente en el área de la cuenca Matanza-Riachuelo del Gran Buenos Aires.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The origin and quality of water for human consumption: the health of the population residing in the Matanza-Riachuelo river basin area in Greater Buenos Aires].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud colectiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
