<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23693109</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez-González, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarreal-Ríos, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santibáñez-Beltrán, Shaid</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galicia-Rodríguez, Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-Daza, Emma Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos-López, José Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to quantify the economic cost of polypharmacy in the elderly. METHODS cost study design, made in two first-level medical units. The study was conducted in 131 older adult patients with polypharmacy, chronic degenerative disease and at least one medical visit per year. The sample was calculated using the formula of finite population averages. The cost of polypharmacy was assessed in medical consultation, medicine and pharmacy services. The evaluation of the medical cost included the number of visits per year for the same unit cost, the cost of medicine considered the amount of drug per year for the same unit cost, and the cost of the service pharmacy took into account the number of times the pharmacy occupies the unit cost of the same. The statistical analysis included means, percentages and confidence intervals. RESULTS in family practice the average annual cost is $1,263.26. In pharmacy the average annual cost is $229.91. The average time drug use is 4.37 months per year (95 % CI = 0.9-7.9), the annual average cost drugs is $708.00. Considering the three dimensions the annual cost of polypharmacy in the elderly is $2,201.17. CONCLUSIONS the cost of polypharmacy is high and represents a significant economic impact.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>cost-benefit analysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>aged</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>polypharmacy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costo económico de la polifarmacia en el adulto mayor en el primer nivel de atención.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: determinar el costo económico de la polifarmacia en el adulto mayor. Métodos: estudio de costos en dos unidades de medicina familiar. Se estudió una muestra de 131 adultos mayores con polifarmacia, enfermedades crónicas degenerativas y con al menos una consulta al año. La muestra se calculó con la fórmula de población finita para promedios. El costo de polifarmacia fue evaluado en tres dimensiones: consulta médica, medicamentos y servicio de farmacia. La evaluación de la consulta médica incluyó el número de atenciones al año por el costo unitario de la misma; el costo de medicamentos, la cantidad anual de este por el costo unitario del mismo y el costo del servicio de farmacia, el número de ocasiones que se ocupa la farmacia por el costo unitario de las mismas. Resultados: el costo anual de la consulta médica fue de $1263.26 y el de farmacia, de $229.91. El tiempo de uso de medicamentos fue de 4.37 meses al año y el costo anual en fármacos, de $708.00. El costo anual de la polifarmacia en el adulto mayor fue de $2201.17. Conclusiones: la polifarmacia representa un importante costo e impacto económico. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Economic cost of polypharmacy in the elderly in primary health care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
