<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23711815</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9188</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González Martínez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baldominos Utrilla, Gema</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mariño Martínez, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Martínez, María Nélida</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The increase in immunosuppressed patients and in the use of cytotoxic and immunosuppressive agents in the last few years has led to a rise in the incidence of invasive fungal infections. AIMS The objective of this study is to evaluate the use of liposomal amphotericin B according to its indication, dosage, effectiveness and nephrotoxicity. METHODS This is a retrospective study over a 8 year-period. Indications and dosage described in the Summary of Product Characteristics were taken as reference. Effectiveness was measured in terms of resolution of infection, no recurrence or emergence, survival at 7th day, no discontinuation and no addition of another antifungal. Effectiveness was also analysed in relation to indication, dosage, treatment duration, cumulative dose and comorbidity. Nephrotoxicity was defined as a doubled serum creatinine when compared with basal values. RESULTS A total of 47 episodes were analysed, with 91.5% of treatments being adequate for the indications. Effectiveness was achieved in 44.7% of cases: 33% in neutropenic patients, 50% of aspergillosis, 60% of candidiasis, and 100% of the leishmaniasis. Response rates in patients treated for 15 days or less and those for more than 15 days were 25 and 56.5% (P=.039), respectively. The main causes of failure were death (23%) and lack of effectiveness (17%), with 9% of patients suffering from nephrotoxicity. CONCLUSIONS The effectiveness and nephrotoxicity data agree with those obtained in other studies. Liposomal amphotericin B is a safe drug with a moderate effectiveness that is associated with the duration of the treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anfotericina B liposomal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Toxicidad farmacológica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Liposomal amphotericin B</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treatment effectiveness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Drug toxicity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estudio de utilización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Efectividad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Evaluation study</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la utilización de anfotericina B liposomal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of the use of liposomal amphotericin B].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
