<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23764558</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9188</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Queiroz Telles, Flavio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tiraboschi, Iris Nora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarado Matute, Tito</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nucci, Marcio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colombo, Arnaldo Lopes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortes, Jorge Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sifuentes, Jose</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santolaya, María E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zurita, Jeannete</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echevarría, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Thompson-Moya, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzman-Blanco, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Candidemia is one of the most frequent opportunistic mycoses worldwide. Limited epidemiological studies in Latin America indicate that incidence rates are higher in this region than in the Northern Hemisphere. Diagnosis is often made late in the infection, affecting the initiation of antifungal therapy. A more scientific approach, based on specific parameters, for diagnosis and management of candidemia in Latin America is warranted. 'Recommendations for the diagnosis and management of candidemia' are a series of manuscripts that have been developed by members of the Latin America Invasive Mycosis Network. They aim to provide a set of best-evidence recommendations for the diagnosis and management of candidemia. This publication, 'Recommendations for the management of candidemia in children in Latin America', was written to provide guidance to healthcare professionals on the management of children who have, or who are at risk of, candidemia. Computerized searches of existing literature were performed by PubMed. The data were extensively reviewed and analyzed by members of the group. The group also met on two occasions to pose questions, discuss conflicting views, and deliberate on a series of management recommendations. 'Recommendations for the management of candidemia in children in Latin America' includes prophylaxis, empirical therapy, therapy for proven candidemia, patient work-up following diagnosis of candidemia, duration of candidemia treatment, and central venous catheter management in children with candidemia. This manuscript is the third of this series that deals with diagnosis and treatment of invasive candidiasis. Other publications in this series include: 'Recommendations for the diagnosis of candidemia in Latin America', 'Recommendations for the management of candidemia in adults in Latin America', and 'Recommendations for the management of candidemia in neonates in Latin America'.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Consensus Development Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Recommendations</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niños</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>América Latina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Candidemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recomendaciones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latin America</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Manejo</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para el manejo de la candidemia en niños en América Latina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Recommendations for the management of candidemia in children in Latin America. Grupo Proyecto Épico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
