<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23793766</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mengual, Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribal, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Musquera, Mireia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bladder cancer represents a very important entity in the field of urologic oncology. At the time of diagnosis 70% of them are non muscle-invasive tumors with a very variable risk of recurrence and progression. These patients will require a periodic follow up, at least for 5 years, performing multiple cystoscopies and urine cytologies throughout their lifes. These diagnostic tests are either invasive or have a low sensitivity, a fact that has stimulated the search of non-invasive markers with high sensitivity for the diagnosis of bladder cancer. The great advantage in this neoplasia is the availability of a biologic sample such as urine, which being in close contact with the urothelium collects exfoliated cells, representing a valuable non invasive tool for the diagnosis and follow up of this neoplasias. In this article we try to perform a review of those markers for bladder cancer already marketed and under development, as well as future diagnostic perspectives.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico no invasivo en cáncer de vejiga: nuevos marcadores moleculares y futuras perspectivas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Non-invasive diagnosis bladder cancer: new molecular markers and future perspectives].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
