<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23797629</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López López, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Girao Popolizio, Italo Nicolás</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES In recent years, occupational injury rates are declining significantly. This study analyzes temporal trends of nonfatal occupational injuries among employees affiliated with MC Mutual in the period 2005-2009, by sex, age, activity of the company and duration of sick leave. METHODS Time series. We calculated the annual incidence rate adjusted by sex, age and activity of the company through direct standardization, as well as changes in annual and overall rates, together with stratified analysis by duration of sick leave. RESULTS The standardized incidence of occupational injuries decreased from 74.8 per 1000 workers-year in 2005 to 48.3 in 2009 (a 35.4% reduction). The highest standardized incidence and rate of reduction was observed among sick leave processes lasting between 4 and 15 days, which decreased from 41.1 in 2005 to 25.2 in 2009 (a 38.6% reduction). Changes in trends were not consistent when considering the duration of the sick leave. CONCLUSIONS There was a significant reduction in nonfatal occupational injuries resulting in sick leave during the study period, after considering age and sex of workers and the economic activity of affiliated companies, mainly at the expense of sick leave processes of short duration.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2012 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución temporal de lesiones por accidentes de trabajo en población afiliada a MC Mutual, 2005-2009.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             En los últimos años los indicadores de lesiones por accidentes de trabajo están disminuyendo considerablemente. Este estudio pretende analizar la evolución temporal de las lesiones por accidentes de trabajo en trabajadores afiliados a MC Mutual en el período 2005-2009, considerando el papel de las variables sexo, edad, actividad de la empresa y duración de los procesos de incapacidad temporal. MÉTODOS: Estudio de series temporales. Se calcularon el índice de incidencia anual ajustando por edad, sexo y actividad de la empresa mediante estandarización directa, además de las tasas de cambio interanual y total. Se realizó también análisis estratificado según la duración de la incapacidad temporal. 
             La incidencia ajustada de lesiones por accidentes de trabajo disminuyó de 74,8 por 1.000 trabajadores-año en 2005 a 48,3 en 2009 (reducción del 35,4%). La mayor incidencia ajustada y tasa de reducción se observó en las bajas de 4 a 15 días, disminuyendo de 41,1 en 2005 a 25,2 en 2009 (reducción del 38,6%). La tasa de cambio no fue homogénea al considerar la duración de la baja, registrándose un patrón temporal diverso. 
             Se ha producido un importante descenso en las lesiones por accidentes de trabajo no mortales con baja laboral en el periodo de estudio, considerando el sexo y edad de los trabajadores y la actividad económica de las empresas mutualistas, principalmente a costa de procesos de incapacidad temporal de baja duración. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Trends in occupational injuries in employees affiliated with MC Mutual in Spain, 2005-2009].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de prevencion de riesgos laborales</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
