<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23848120</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sáez Martín, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Menor Rodríguez, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar Cordero, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hervás Pérez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Expósito Ruiz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Mendoza, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mur Villar, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The satisfaction's analysis is being used as an instrument to create different sanitary reforms to improve the quality and numerous studies aim to the increase the mother's satisfaction directly related to the maternity care. OBJECTIVES [corrected] Identify the woman satisfaction's degree about birth attention, accompaniment during nativity and the breastfeeding's term. MATERIAL AND METHOD [corrected] Descriptive transversal study in the university hospital San Cecilio in Granada (España), during the time of August 2011 to 2012, it performed with a second prospective tracing phase to a N = 60 mothers. It used a protocol (Annex 1) after 24 hours in hospital and at 14 days by telephone. After 3 months, it performed a tracing pertaining to the baby food. RESULTS The global satisfaction's level about birth is high in study population. It has been shown that breastfeeding (P = 0,514) and vaginal birth without epidural (P = 0,320) creates higher satisfaction for mother. On the other hand, birth satisfaction related with duration of breastfeeding. CONCLUSION Satisfactory mothers' opinion related with birth care and accompaniment during nativity increases in women whose birth happened in a uncomplicated way without epidural and they started early breastfeeding.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del nivel de satisfacción en un grupo de mujeres de Granada sobre atención al parto, acompañamiento y duración de la lactancia.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: El análisis de la satisfacción se está utilizando como instrumento para crear diferentes reformas sanitarias para la mejora de la calidad y numerosos estudios apuntan al incremento de la satisfacción de la madre en relación directa con el cuidado en la maternidad. Objetivos: Identificar el grado de satisfacción de la mujer sobre la atención al parto, el acompañamiento durante el nacimiento y la duración de la lactancia materna. Material y método: Estudio descriptivo transversal en el Hospital Universitario San Cecilio de Granada (España), durante el periodo de tiempo Agosto del 2011 al 2012, se realizo con una segunda fase de seguimiento prospectivo a una N = 60 madres. Se utilizó un protocolo (Anexo 1) a las 24 horas en el hospital y a los 14 días por teléfono. A los 3 meses, se realizó un seguimiento relacionado con la alimentación del bebe. Resultados: El nivel de satisfacción global sobre el parto es alto en la población estudiada. Se ha demostrado que la lactancia materna (P = 0,514) y el parto vía vaginal sin epidural (P = 0,320) crea una mayor satisfacción en la madre. Por otro lado, la satisfacción sobre el parto guarda relación con la duración de la lactancia materna. Conclusión: La opinión satisfactoria de las madres relacionadas con la atención al parto y el acompañamiento durante el nacimiento se incrementa en aquellas mujeres cuyo parto ocurrió de forma eutócica sin epidural e iniciaron la lactancia materna precoz. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Satisfaction rating in a group of women from Granada on birthing care, support and breastfeeding length].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
