<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23884614</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Berlanga, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fres치n, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The inability to experience pleasure, anhedonia, is recognized as al hallmark symptom of depression. A 14-item, self-report scale developed for the assessment of hedonic capacity: the Snaith-Hamilton Pleasure Scale (SHAPS) has proved to be a reliable and valid psychometric instrument. OBJECTIVE Because there are no versions of the scale in other languages, our objective in this study was to translate the instrument into spanish and to determine if the new version maintained the validity and reliability of its original english version. METHODOLOGY The scale was translated into spanish and after reaching final consensus applied to a group of depressed patients participating in a pharmacological trial. The Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS) was also applied for comparative purposes. RESULTS Our results demonstrate that the SHAPS in its spanish version maintains the validity and reliability level of the original english version. A moderate internal consistency was determined by Cronbach alpha value of 0.77. CONCLUSION our results demonstrate the the spanish version of the SHAPS has validity and reliability similar to its original version, and thus it represents a good alternative to evaluate anhedonia in spanish-speaking populations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traducci칩n al espa침ol y validaci칩n de la Escala de Placer Snaith-Hamilton para Anhedonia (SHAPS).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Translation into Spanish and validation of the Snaith-Hamilton Pleasure Scale (SHAPS) for anhedonia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas espanolas de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
