<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23889647</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz García, H J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tapia-Vicente, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Veramendi-Espinoza, L E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quispe-Calderón, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zafra-Tanaka, J H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quispe-Moore, L M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Surichaqui B, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Asato N, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millones-Sánchez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Whittembury, Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar-Saavedra, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basilio-Flores, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chia-Gil, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Casquino, G A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey-Rodríguez, D E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ticona-Rebagliati, D I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Hospital malnutrition is a prevalent problem that cause higher morbidity and mortality, poorer response to treatment and higher hospital stay and cost. OBJECTIVES To determine the prevalence and factors associated with hospital malnutrition in a peruvian General Hospital. METHODS Cross-sectional study including 211 hospitalized patients in Medicine and Surgery wards. Demographic, clinical and anthropometrical indicators' data was collected. Multivariate analysis was binary logistic regression. All tests had a significance level of 5% (p &lt; 0.05). RESULTS Prevalence of hospital malnutrition was 46.9%. Prevalences of caloric and protein malnutrition were 21.3% and 37.5%, respectively. Bivariate analysis found that hospitalization in Surgery wards was associated with a major risk of caloric (OR = 4.41, IC 95% [1.65-11.78]) and protein malnutrition (OR = 2.52, IC 95% [1.297-4.89]). During the analysis of quantitative variables, significant associations between number of comorbidities and caloric malnutrition (p = 0.031) was found, and also between the beginning of food intake changes and the presence of protein malnutrition (p = 0.031). Multivariate analysis showed significant association between diagnosis of neoplasm and presence of caloric malnutrition (OR = 5.22, IC [1.43-19.13]). CONCLUSIONS Prevalence of hospital malnutrition was near 50%, as in similar studies. Protein-caloric malnutrition prevalences obtained, differ from the ones in a previous study in this hospital, which is explained by the different diagnostic criteria and particular characteristics of groups of patients, such as procedence ward and comorbidities. An association between protein-caloric and hospitalization in a Surgery ward was found; the reasons should be investigated in further studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y factores asociados a desnutrición hospitalaria en un hospital general; Perú, 2012.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: La desnutrición hospitalaria es un problema prevalente que genera mayor morbi-mortalidad, peor respuesta al tratamiento, mayor estancia y costo hospitalario. Objetivos: Determinar la prevalencia y factores asociados a desnutrición hospitalaria en un hospital general peruano. Métodos: Estudio analítico transversal de 211 pacientes en servicios de Medicina y Cirugía. Se analizó variables demográficas, clínicas e indicadores antropométricos. El análisis multivariado fue de regresión logística binaria. El nivel de significancia fue 5% (p &lt; 0,05). Resultados: La prevalencia de desnutrición hospitalaria fue 46.9% y las de desnutrición calórica y proteica fueron 21,3% y 37,5% respectivamente. En el análisis bivariado, estar hospitalizado en el servicio de Cirugía se asoció a un mayor riesgo de desnutrición calórica (OR = 4,41, IC 95% [1,65-11,78]) y proteica (OR = 2,52, IC 95% [1,30-4,90]). Hubo asociación significativa entre el número de comorbilidades del paciente y desnutrición calórica (p = 0,031), y el tiempo de cambio de ingesta alimentaria y presencia de desnutrición proteica (p = 0,031). El análisis multivariado mostró asociación significativa entre el diagnóstico de neoplasia y la presencia de desnutrición calórica (OR = 5,22, IC 95% [1,43-19,13]). Conclusiones: La prevalencia de desnutrición hospitalaria fue cerca del 50%, coincidiendo con estudios similares. Las prevalencias de desnutrición calórica/proteica halladas difieren de las de un estudio anterior en este hospital, explicándose por parámetros de diagnóstico diferentes y características particulares de las poblaciones, como el servicio de procedencia y comorbilidades. Se encontró asociación entre desnutrición proteica/calórica y estar hospitalizado en el servicio de Cirugía; las razones deben investigarse en estudios posteriores. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence and associated factors of hospital malnutrition in a general hospital; Perú, 2012].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
