<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23885651</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-8856</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villalón, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueroa, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdés, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vaisman, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tuca, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To identify those clinical characteristic and arthroscopic findings in patients with knee arthrosis that are associated with worsening of the disease and subsequent total knee arthroplasty (TKA). METHOD A retrospective, descriptive study was conducted on 78 consecutive patients (88 knees) who underwent knee arthroscopy for arthrosis. The study included 44 women and 34 men, with a mean age of 58.9 years (range: 37-78 years). After a mean follow-up of 50.4 months (range: 12-96 months), those patients who progressed towards TKA were identified. A logistic regression model was applied to recognise the factors associated with deterioration of the arthrosis, with consequent progression towards a TKA. RESULTS Twenty-four out of the 88 knees progressed towards a TKA (27.3%) within a mean time of 13.5 months after arthroscopy (range: 13-29 months). The clinical characteristics that showed a significant association with poor progression of the arthrosis were: female gender (0.02) and Ahlbäck 2 (P=.04). Arthroscopic finding that proved significant correlation with worsening of the arthrosis towards TKA were: meniscal tears of the posterior horn (P=.02), meniscectomies above 60% (P=.03), and 2nd degree chondral lesions in loading areas of the medial femoral condyle (P=.02). CONCLUSION The variables associated with a greater chance of progressing towards a TKA after a knee arthroscopy due to arthrosis in this study were, female gender, grade 2 radiographic arthrosis, posterior horn meniscal lesions, meniscectomies over 60%, and chondral lesions in loading area of the medial femoral condyle.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Knee</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artrosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arthroscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prognosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pronóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rodilla</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artroplastia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arthroplasty</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artroscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores clínicos y hallazgos en la artroscopia de pacientes con artrosis de rodilla que favorecen la conversión a artroplastia total.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical factors and findings in knee arthroscopy of patients with knee arthrosis candidates for conversion to total replacement].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cirugia ortopedica y traumatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
