<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2388503</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guanyabens, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pons, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortuño, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prat, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bordes, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murcia, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soler, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the histopathology, immunophenotype and immunogenotype of 10 cases of peripheral T-cell lymphoma. The majority of patients showed disseminated disease at the time of diagnosis. From a histopathological view point the cases were classified into 5 types: T zone lymphoma (4 cases); Lennert lymphoma (2 cases); pleomorphic lymphoma, small all type (2 cases); pleomorphic lymphoma of medium-sized cell type (1 case); pleomorphic lymphoma of large cell type (1 case). In most of them the neoplastic cells demonstrated a mature T-cell phenotype: CD3+, CD4+, CD8-, CD43+, CD45RO+, CD45RA-, CD20- and surface immunoglobulins. All cases studied displayed gene rearrangements for the T-cell receptor beta chain while the immunoglobulins genes remained in germinal configuration. Antibodies against the human T-cell lymphotropic virus type I were not found in the 9 samples studied.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 May 19 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma T periférico. Estudios morfológicos, inmunofenotípicos e inmunogenotípicos de diez casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Peripheral T-cell lymphoma. Morphologic, immunophenotypic and immunogenotypic studies of 10 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
