<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23911215</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Benedicto, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miralles, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nuño de la Rosa, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pastor, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palmero, J L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare the results obtained in percutaneous nephrolithotomy after introduction of flexible ureteroscopy/nephroscopy (endoscopic combined intrarenal surgery - ECIRS) with nephrolitomies with only rigid nephroscopy (standard percutaneous nephrolithotomy; sPCNL). MATERIAL AND METHOD A retrospective study of 171 sPCNL in Galdakao position performed between January 2005 and December 2011 was conducted. We compared the results obtained in those procedures in which endoscopic combined intrarenal surgery (ECIRS) was performed with those in which only the rigid nephroscopy (sPCNL) was used. Specific and global success, percentage of lithiasic load eliminated, days of hospital stay and complications derived were calculated. We defined success by complete absence of lithiasis or residual presence of&lt;5mm. We differentiated specific success, that only achieved with percutaneous surgery, from global success, or that achieved after a second line of treatment. RESULTS In 73 procedures (42.4%) ECIRS was performed with flexible endoscopy while in 98 (57.6%) it was done with sPCNL. Both groups were comparable in regards to demographic parameters and characteristics of the lithiasis. The success rates in the first procedure and global success were superior for the ECIRS group (75.3% vs 40.8% and 93.1% vs 74.5%), the differences being statistically significant (P&lt;.05). No statistically significant differences were found in regards to the complications (28.8% vs 28.3% P=.86) or days of hospital stay (4.5 vs 5.0 P=.18). CONCLUSIONS Use of the flexible ureteroscopy/nephroscopy in sPCNL (ECIRS) improves the success rates and elimination of lithiasic load, making it possible to perform the surgery with a single access in most of the cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cirugía intrarrenal endoscópica combinada</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopic combined intrarenal surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Renal lithiasis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Percutaneous nephrolitotomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Litiasis renal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nefrolitotomía percutánea</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A comparative study of percutaneous nephrolithotomy in supine position and endoscopic combined intrarenal surgery with flexible instrument.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
