<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23916983</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bosch, F Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roura, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peris, Mercè</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coma E, Ermengol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silvia de Sanjosé</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Salés, Vanesa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibáñez, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To estimate cervical cytology coverage for the period 2008-2011 by age groups and health regions from data recorded in the medical records of women attending centers within the Catalan national health system. METHODS The data used to estimate coverage were obtained from the primary care information system. This information was anonymous and included age, center, date, and the results of cytological smears for a total of 2,292,564 women aged 15 years or more. RESULTS A total of 758,690 smears were performed in 595,868 women. Among women aged 25-65 years, the estimated coverage was 32.4% of the assigned population and was 40.8% in the population attended. Geographical variation was observed, with higher coverage among health regions closer to Barcelona. Abnormal Pap smears increased slightly from 2008 to 2011 (from 3% to 3.5%, respectively, p &lt;0.001). In women with a negative first smear, the mean interval until the second smear was 2.4 years, but only 50% of women with a negative first smear in 2008 attended a second round during the study period. CONCLUSIONS Cervical screening coverage in the National Health Service of Catalonia includes one in three women. Second round participation was poor. Existing computer systems in primary care centers can ensure monitoring of population-based screening programs for cervical cancer. These systems could be used to plan an organized screening program to ensure wider coverage and better follow-up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Screening</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de cuello uterino</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Salud pública y tecnologías de la información en salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cobertura</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coverage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cribado</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public health and health information technology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cervical cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cobertura del cribado de cáncer de cuello uterino en Cataluña (2008-2011).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Coverage of cervical cancer screening in Catalonia, Spain (2008-2011)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
