<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23918011</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernandes, Josicélia Dumêt</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosa, Darci de Oliveira Santa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Mary Gomes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Rosana Maria de Oliveira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Teixeira, Giselle Alves da Silva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Florêncio, Raíssa Millena Silva</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE This study analyzed the increase in the number of undergraduate nursing courses during the last two decades due to the expansion of higher education in Brazil. METHOD A records-based research concerning the legal frameworks that have driven this movement and a quantitative research that described the increase in the number of professional nursing courses. Data were analyzed using thematic content analysis (qualitative) and descriptive statistics (quantitative). RESULTS the political-ideological argument present in the regulatory documents, which points out higher education as a possibility to change the current social scenario, has not been reflected in the professional nursing field. The expansion of nursing courses has been unfolding in a disorderly manner and is concentrated in the private sector, with geographical inequality in the distribution of these courses. CONCLUSION There does not seem to be a concern with the local needs and with a connection among education, research and extension, which compromises the quality of the education provided to future nurses.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expansion of higher education in Brazil: increase in the number of Undergraduate Nursing courses.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
