<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23918015</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mamede, Marli Villela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mamede, Fabiana Villela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dantas, Rosana Aparecida Spadoti</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Souza, Luiz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prudêncio, Patrícia Santos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to adapt and validate the Patient Expectations and Satisfaction with Prenatal Care instrument for use in Brazil. It contains 41 items divided into two dimensions: expectations and satisfaction. The adapted version was submitted to analysis for stability, convergent construct validity, and internal consistency (Cronbach's alpha) for distinct groups and dimensions. METHOD 119 pregnant women receiving prenatal care were interviewed and 26 of these women answered the instrument twice (retest). Internal consistency was appropriate (Cronbach's alpha ≥ 0.70); test-retest presented strong correlation (r=0.82; p&lt;0.001) for the domain expectations and moderate correlation (r=0.66; p&lt;0.001) for the satisfaction domain. The analysis confirmed that the instrument's adapted version is valid in the studied group. RESULTS there is strong evidence for the validity and reliability of the instrument's adaptation. CONCLUSION the instrument needs to be tested in groups of pregnant women with different social characteristics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation and validation of the Patient Expectations and Satisfaction with Prenatal Care instrument among Brazilian pregnant women.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
