<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2392609</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanjuán Máñez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Curt, S M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morell Cabedo, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Insa Pérez, L D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Querchfeld, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Civera, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz Granell, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanchis Fores, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Merino, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ventricular arrhythmias detected in the late-hospital phase of myocardial infarction have been identified as a risk factor for sudden death, being their prognostic value independent of ventricular function. However, relations between both factors are not clarified. In order to study hypothetic associations between ventricular arrhythmias and some clinical, hemodynamic and angiographic variables, 60 patients (52 males, 8 females) underwent 24-hour Holter recordings and cardiac catheterization with left ventricular and coronary angiographies, 3-5 weeks after hospital admission. Past history data, acute phase complications and hemodynamic and angiographic results were compared between patients with and without significant ventricular arrhythmias during Holter monitoring (10 or more PVC's/hour and/or repetitive forms). No significant differences were found between both groups neither in mean age nor in the incidence of previous angina or infarction, cerebral ischemia, diabetes, lipid disorders or subjective feeling of being under psychological stress. Prior history of arterial hypertension was, however, significantly more frequent in patients with ventricular arrhythmias (53.3% vs 17.8%; p = 0.0183). No differences were observed in the localization of the infarct or in the complications during the acute phase (CPK peak, Killip's score, angina after 24 hours of evolution, intraventricular or A-V conduction disorders and supraventricular and ventricular arrhythmias). Among hemodynamic data, only left ventricular and aortic systolic pressures were different in both groups, being significantly higher in patients with ventricular arrhythmias. There were not differences in left ventricular segmentary contraction and in number of coronary vessels involved. To conclude, significant ventricular arrhythmias were recorded in 25% of patients.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1990 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sustrato anatomofuncional de las arritmias de alto riesgo tras el infarto de miocardio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Anatomo-functional substrate of high risk arrhythmia after myocardial infarct].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
