<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23949518</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fiestas, Fabián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meenan, Richard T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muench, John</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hoffman, Kim</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ponce, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calderón, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to a complex payment system, the health system of the United States is fragmented, expensive, and achieves the goal of improving the health of the entire population. Excessive health costs increase the budget deficit in the US. This situation makes to the government to have greater willingness to try new approaches in the delivery of health services. Is well know that the states that have a solid system of primary health care (PC), spent less money in diseases and have lower utilization of health services (reflected in fewer days of hospitalization). This is why the AP is spreading in the US making doctors, nurses and other providers to collaborate on new proposals for team-based care, coordinated and patient-oriented generating real benefits while controlling costs. The US experience with AP support evidence-based approach to propose, from a foreign perspective, strengthening the AP in Peru.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La atención primaria en los Estados Unidos y la experiencia peruana en perspectiva.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Primary care in the USA and the Peruvian experience in perspective].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
