<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23971385</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez-Adán, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco-Pérez, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-García, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pato-Mosquera, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-Rodríguez, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Diagnostic hysteroscopy is an endoscopic technique that allows the evaluation of the endocervical canal and uterine cavity. OBJECTIVE To evaluate indications, complications and referral to operative hysteroscopy. To analyze the correlation between sonographic display, hysteroscopy findings and histological diagnosis. MATERIALS AND METHODS Retrospective and descriptive study of 904 patients who underwent diagnostic hysteroscopy between January 1, 2008 and June 30, 2012. RESULTS The most frequent indication was sonographic detection of endometrial polyps (75% were premenopausal and 71.2% postmenopausal). The complication rate associated with the test was 11.4%. The reduction experimented in operative hysteroscopies was from 31.2% in 2008 to 12.2% between January and June 2012. When a polyp or a myoma was detected by sonography, diagnostic hysteroscopy showed them in 64.4% y 62.5% of the cases, respectively. The correlation between hysteroscopic findings and histopathologic diagnosis was 77.7% for normal endometrium, 77.9% for polyps, 17.8% for hyperplasic appearance and 100% for carcinoma suspicion. CONCLUSIONS Diagnostic hysteroscopy is a safe technique that allows small interventions avoiding operative hysteroscopies. There is a good relation between hysteroscopic visual inspection and anatomopathologic diagnosis, but biopsy should be taken except if normal endometrium is visualized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicaciones y resultados de la histeroscopia diagnóstica ambulatoria en el Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Ourense.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Diagnostic hysteroscopy indications and results in Complexo Hospitalario Universitario De Ourense].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
