<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23975526</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Nascimento, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vigo, Meritxell</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina, Julita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Natalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Febrer, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colomer, Jaume</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To determine the frequency of fractures in patients with spinal muscular atrophy, their mechanism of production, age at appearance and functional repercussions. PATIENTS AND METHODS Sixty-five patients with spinal muscular atrophy were studied. Cases of fractures diagnosed by means of X-rays were collected and the following parameters were analysed: type of spinal muscular atrophy, gait, age at the time the fracture occurred, mechanism of production, location, treatment applied and functional repercussion. RESULTS Thirteen patients (20%) presented a total of 20 fractures (four of them presented two or more fractures). The mean age was 6.35 years. The fractures were mostly located in the femur and the mechanism of production was falls in 12 cases and minor traumatic injury in eight. No vertebral fractures were detected. All of them were treated conservatively. The only patient with a fracture who was able to walk stopped walking after immobilisation. CONCLUSIONS The existence of fractures in these patients interferes with their quality of life and their level of functioning. It is important to prevent them from occurring during management of the patient and by ensuring a correct posture in the wheelchair with the use of restraint systems. Further studies are needed on the loss of bone mineral density in these patients and their possible relationship with fractures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Sep 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas en la atrofia muscular espinal.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Fracturas en la atrofia muscular espinal. 
             Objetivo. Determinar la frecuencia de fracturas en pacientes con atrofia muscular espinal, mecanismo de produccion, edad de aparicion y repercusion funcional. Pacientes y metodos. Se estudian 65 pacientes con atrofia muscular espinal. Se recogen las fracturas diagnosticadas mediante radiografia y se analizan los siguientes parametros: tipo de atrofia muscular espinal, marcha, edad en el momento de la fractura, mecanismo de produccion, localizacion, tratamiento aplicado y repercusion funcional. Resultados. Presentaron fracturas 13 pacientes (20%), con un total de 20 (cuatro presentaron dos o mas fracturas). La edad media fue de 6,35 años. La localizacion fue en su mayoria en el femur y el mecanismo de produccion, en 12 casos por caidas y en 8 por traumatismo menor. No detectamos ninguna fractura vertebral. Todas se trataron de manera conservadora. El unico paciente ambulante que presento una fractura dejo de caminar despues de la inmovilizacion. Conclusiones. La existencia de fracturas en estos pacientes interfiere en su calidad de vida y en el nivel funcional. Es importante la prevencion de las mismas en el manejo del paciente y vigilando la correcta postura en la silla de ruedas con sistemas de sujecion Deberian emprenderse mas estudios sobre la perdida de densidad mineral osea en estos pacientes y su posible relacion con las fracturas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fractures in spinal muscular atrophy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
