<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>23985459</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sinues Ojas, Bryan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coloma Del Peso, Almudena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido Abad, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Arjona, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To report the preliminary results of one of the first series of patients treated with a new simple surgical technique for the treatment of lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) due to benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) and to evaluate its safety and feasibility. METHODS We have performed a novel surgical treatment of BPH, the UroLift® System (Neotract, Inc). It opens the urethra directly by retracting the obstructing prostatic lobes without applying incisions, surgical resection or thermal injury to the prostate. RESULTS The procedure was carried out in 20 patients with a mean age of 74.3 (43 hyphen;-90) years, with mean prostate volume of 42.6 mL (19 hyphen;109) using the same operative protocol in all case subjects. Mean operative time was 19.1 min (range: 12-45). International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) ) at 4 weeks reduced from 26.7 to 16.7 and peak urinary flow rate (Qmax) increased from 8.6 mL/s to 13.2 mL/s. No major complications were encountered, neither sexual dysfunction. Mean follow-up: 12.3 (2-22) months. CONCLUSIONS The UroLift® System procedure appears to be safe and efficient at short term. This technique minimizes the bleeding of the urethra and, therefore, makes bladder catheter not always necessary, and can preserve sexual function with low morbidity. Further studies are warranted to determine long-term outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urolift®, un nuevo tratamiento mínimamente invasivo para los síntomas de tracto urinario inferior secundarios a HBP. Resultados preliminares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Urolift®, a new minimally invasive treatment for patients with low urinary tract symptoms secondary to BPH. Preliminary results].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
