<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24008524</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sáez-Bueno, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lima-Rodríguez, J S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cáceres-Rodríguez, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lima-Serrano, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To validate scales to measure adolescent attitudes toward sexuality (EAS), toward addictive substances (EASA) and toward vial security (EASV), and to examine their correlations with behaviour on these areas. METHODS We designed the scales by literature review; we validated their content using a Delphi-on-line panel with 18 experts, and a pre-test with a sample of 21 fourth-grade high-school students (similar to 10th in US) in Seville, Spain. The scales were administered to 188 fourth-grade high-school students in order to test their construct validity (exploratory factor analysis), their reliability (Alpha Cronbach test), and to determinate their correlations with age, gender, experience of sexual intercourse, substance use and road behaviour. RESULTS EAS-10 obtained α=0.73, EASA-12 obtained α=0.80, EASV-12 obtained α=0.79. They showed evidence of one-dimensional interpretation after factor analysis, a) all items achieved weights r&gt;0.30 in the first factor, which explained a significant proportion of variance before rotations, and b) total variance explained by the main factors extracted was greater than 50%. We found correlations between EASA-12 and tobacco use (r=-0.43, p&lt;0.001), alcohol use (r=-0.30, p&lt;0.001), age of alcohol initiation (r=0.32, p=0.003), and substance use (r=-0.55, p&lt;0.001), and between EASV-12 and safe road behaviour (r=0.41, p&lt;0.001), tobacco use (r=-0.23, p=0.003), alcohol use (r=-0,22, p=0,003), age of first experience of drunkenness (r=0.22, p=0.003), and substance use (r=-0.27, p=0.013). CONCLUSIONS The scales showed their reliability and validity. They could be employed for assessing adolescent attitudes to these priority intervention areas, for carrying out studies on their mediating role on adopting behaviour, and for designing and evaluating health programs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Sep 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de escalas para medir la actitud adolescente hacia: sexualidad, sustancias adictivas y seguridad vial ¿se relacionan con los comportamientos?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Design and validation of scales to measure adolescent attitudes toward sexuality, addictive substances and road safety. Are they related to behaviour?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales del sistema sanitario de Navarra</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
