<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24021077</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alvear-Galindo, M Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yamamoto-Kimura, Liria T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez-Oropeza, Marco Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acuña-Sánchez, M Eugenia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferreira-Hermosillo, Aldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Durán, Patricia Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solís-Días, M Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morán-Álvarez, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND elementary school students usually stay in school 4.5 hours a day in Mexico. The main food consumption is outside school. The objective was to explore behaviors on food consumption beyond the school environment. METHODS descriptive trial that included 173 children, both sexes, from public elementary school in Mexico City. Eating habits were obtained through questionnaire and anthropometric characteristics from physical measurement. RESULTS participants reported to consume soft drinks and canned juices at high frequency and quantity (80 %) and low consumption of animal foods. They also eat industrialized dairy products with high caloric content and low in protein. Moreover, 30 % of children eat 4 or 5 times a day, whereas 10 % eat one or two times a day. These results were associated with the somatometric characteristics of the children, 37.6 % of whom presented as overweight or obese while 12 % were underweight. CONCLUSIONS it is necessary that health education involves teachers, parents and children in programs for obesity prevention with the objective of increasing healthy behaviors.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>hábitos alimenticios</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sobrepeso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>niño</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>food habits</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>overweight</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>child</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo alimentario dentro y fuera de la escuela.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: en México, los niños de primaria permanecen aproximadamente 4.5 horas en la escuela, por lo que fuera de ese espacio es donde consumen la mayor parte de sus alimentos. El objetivo de esta investigación fue explorar las conductas alimentarias más allá del entorno escolar que pudieran favorecer la obesidad. Métodos: estudio descriptivo de niños de una escuela primaria oficial en el Distrito Federal. Los hábitos alimentarios se conocieron por un cuestionario y las características antropométricas, por medición física. Resultados: los participantes indicaron consumir refrescos y jugos enlatados con alta frecuencia y en cantidades importantes (80 %), así como productos lácteos industrializados con alto valor calórico y bajo contenido de proteínas; ingerían pocos alimentos de origen animal; 30 % comía cuatro o cinco veces al día y 10 %, una o dos veces. Los resultados se asociaron con las características omatométricas de los niños, 37.6 % de los cuales presentó sobrepeso u obesidad y 12 %, bajo peso. Conclusiones: para la prevención de la obesidad son necesarios programas de educación que involucren a profesores, padres de familia y escolares, para obtener conductas saludables y preservar la salud. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Food consumption in and around the school].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
