<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24021073</identifier>
<setSpec>0443-5117</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez-Cruz, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mugártegui-Sánchez, Sharon</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND burnout syndrome is a state of physical and emotional exhaustion that can occur among workers who interact directly with others. This could affect job performance. The objective was to determine the prevalence of this syndrome and its associated factors among family physicians. METHODS a cross-sectional survey applying the Maslach Burnout Inventory was conducted in a selected convenience non-probability sampling of family physicians. Central tendency and dispersion measures were used in determining the prevalence of burnout syndrome; the associated factors were analysed by χ(2) test. RESULTS there were 59 cases of burnout syndrome, 36 had involvement in a single component, 15 in 2 and 8 were affected in 3 components; we observed that 35 % of positive cases reported doing an average of 10 extra shifts a month (p = 0.013). Having a second job was associated with positive cases of burnout syndrome. CONCLUSIONS the results are consistent with similar studies. Working extra shifts or having a second job were the related factors most associated to this syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>burnout, professional</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>agotamiento profesional</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>médicos de familia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>physicians, family</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de agotamiento profesional en los médicos familiares.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: el síndrome de agotamiento profesional es un estado de agotamiento físico y emocional que puede presentarse en trabajadores que interactúan con otras personas. El objetivo de esta investigación fue conocer la prevalencia de este síndrome y los factores relacionados en médicos familiares de Mérida, Yucatán, México. Métodos: se realizó una encuesta transversal en la que se aplicó el Maslach Burnout Inventory a médicos familiares seleccionados mediante muestreo no probabilístico por conveniencia. Se analizaron las medidas de tendencia central y dispersión y se determinó la prevalencia del síndrome de agotamiento profesional. La significación estadística de los factores asociados se determinó mediante χ2. Resultados: se obtuvieron 59 casos de síndrome de agotamiento profesional: 36 con afectación en un componente del Maslach Burnout Inventory, 15 en dos y ocho en los tres. El 35 % de los casos indicó trabajar en promedio 10 turnos extra al mes (p = 0.013); tener un segundo trabajo también se relacionó con el síndrome. Conclusiones: los resultados son consistentes con los obtenidos en estudios similares. Trabajar turnos extra o tener otro trabajo fueron los factores relacionados con el síndrome de agotamiento profesional. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Burnout syndrome among family physicians].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
