<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24034761</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Antoñanzas-Lombarte, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Requeno-Jarabo, M N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amorós-García, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murillo-Díaz de Cerio, I I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 39 year-old patient consulted his family doctor due to migratory polyarthralgia, with C-reactive protein 7.99mg/dl, ESR 89mm and normal anti-streptolysin O (ASO). A sample was taken for analysis in the Rheumatology Clinic: ACE 72 IU, with normal rheumatoid factor, C-reactive protein and ASO; HLA non-specific. Chest X-ray showed an increased pulmonary interstitial pattern, and his chest-CT showed multiple bilateral pulmonary nodules and mediastinal lymph nodes. A differential diagnosis of lymphoproliferative process was considered. A gallium scintigraphy was performed with no relevant findings. The patient was referred to Thoracic Surgery for a lymph node biopsy by mediastinoscopy, which showed a non-necrotizing granulomatous lymphadenitis consistent with a sarcoidosis. Treatment with prednisone and anti-osteoporosis drugs was started and the patient was evaluated at four months with a new chest X-ray. There was a clinical and radiological remission therefore it was decided to gradually reduce the corticosteroid therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Sarcoidosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arthralgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nódulos linfáticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artralgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lymph nodes</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Poliartralgia como primer síntoma de sarcoidosis.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Polyarthralgia as an initial symptom of sarcoidosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
