<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24052443</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arnal-García, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramió-Torrentà, Lluís</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saiz, Albert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, Óscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brieva, Lluís</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matas, Elisabet</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Merino, Juan A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calles-Hernández, M Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villar, Luisa M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Comabella, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oreja-Guevara, Celia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meca-Lallana, José E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arroyo-González, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Téllez, Nieves</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz-García, Delicias</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olascoaga, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tintoré, Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>de las Heras, Virginia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Pérez, Miguel A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendibe-Bilbao, María del Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casanova-Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prieto, José M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most significant data presented at the 28th Congress of the European Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS), held in France in October 2012, have been summarised in the fifth edition of the Post-ECTRIMS Experts Meeting, held in Madrid in October 2012. This led to the drafting of this review, which has been published in three parts. This third part of the Post-ECTRIMS review presents the findings from the latest studies conducted with disease-modifying treatments, more specifically with glatiramer acetate, laquinimod, ponesimod, BG-12, teriflunomide, daclizumab, natalizumab and secukinumab (AIN457). Likewise, we also address the reasons that justify the search for innovative treatments for multiple sclerosis, with antigen-specific therapy, cell therapy and therapy aimed at promoting remyelination being highlighted among other future therapeutic strategies. Access to new pharmacological agents and the complexity of the therapy of multiple sclerosis in the future will require new design strategies and directions in clinical trials, including the use of surrogate markers, new statistical applications, superiority, inferiority or equivalence clinical trials and adaptable designs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Congresses</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Revision de las novedades presentadas en el XXVIII Congreso del Comite Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigacion en Esclerosis Multiple (ECTRIMS) (III). 
             Los datos mas relevantes presentados en la XXVIII edicion del Congreso del Comite Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigacion en Esclerosis Multiple (ECTRIMS), celebrado en octubre de 2012 en Francia, han sido resumidos en la quinta edicion de la Reunion de Expertos Post-ECTRIMS celebrada en Madrid en octubre de 2012, fruto de la cual nace esta revision que se publica en tres partes. Esta tercera parte de la revision Post-ECTRIMS expone los resultados de los ultimos estudios realizados con los tratamientos modificadores de la enfermedad, concretamente con acetato de glatiramero, laquinimod, ponesimod, BG-12, teriflunomida, daclizumab, natalizumab y secukinumab (AIN457). Asimismo, se abordan las razones que justifican la busqueda de tratamientos innovadores para la esclerosis multiple, destacando la terapia antigenoespecifica, la terapia celular y la terapia dirigida a promover la remielinizacion entre las futuras estrategias terapeuticas. La disponibilidad de nuevos farmacos y la complejidad de la futura terapia de la esclerosis multiple necesitan nuevas direcciones y estrategias de diseño en los ensayos clinicos, entre ellas el uso de marcadores subrogados, nuevas aplicaciones estadisticas, ensayos clinicos de superioridad, inferioridad o equivalencia, y diseños adaptables. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties presented at the 28th Congress of the European Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS) (III).</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
