<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24067588</identifier>
<setSpec>1853-0605</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Grandi, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alfaro, Emma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luchtenberg, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moresco, Angélica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dipierri, José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Depending on the geographical altitude the purpose of this work was to analyze in two argentine populations the variation of birth weight (BW) and adverse perinatal outcomes, adjusting for maternal and obstetric factors. MATERIAL AND METHODS Data from 4000 births in the provinces of Jujuy and 4000 in Buenos Aires (Sarda Maternity Hospital) (1996-2000) recruited and randomized from the Perinatal Information System was used. The data were grouped according to an altitudinal gradient composed by Sarda Maternity (20 masl) and the geographic regions of Jujuy province: Ramal (500 masl), Valle (1200 masl), Quebrada (2500 masl) and Puna (3500 masl). Outcome variables were BW &gt; 3000 g, BW &lt;2500 g, ponderal index (PI), prematurity, small for gestational age (SGA) and intrauterine growth restriction (FGR), while potentially confounding variables were: age, type of partner, education, overweight, obesity, smoking, hypertension, preeclampsia, urinary infection, growth restriction and cesarean section. RESULTS An increasing altitudinal gradient for adolescent mothers (&lt;19 years) and decreasing for the rest of the maternal obstetric variables was observed. The BW, BW&gt;3000 g, BW&lt;2500 g and PI were negatively associated with altitude (p &lt;0.001). Prematurity, SGA and FGR showed an opposite trend (p &lt;0.001). Adjusted for confounding variables BW &lt;3000 g, SGA, FGR&lt;0.90 and PI &lt;2.53 showed an increased risk with geographical altitude (p &lt;0.05). CONCLUSIONS Altitude was independently associated with BW restriction and adverse perinatal outcomes. Given the impact of BW reduction in the risk of chronic no communicable diseases this relationship in other populations, regardless of their location altitude, should be assess.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la altitud sobre el peso al nacer y eventos perinatales adversos en dos poblaciones argentinas.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: existe poca información sobre la relación entre tamaño al nacer y altura geográfica ajustada para factores maternos y obstétricos potencialmente confusores. Objetivo: analizar la variación, en función de la altitud geográfica, del Peso al Nacimiento (PN) y resultados perinatales adversos, en dos poblaciones argentinas. Material y Métodos: 4000 registros de recién nacidos (RN) de Jujuy y 4000 de Buenos Aires (Maternidad Sardá) (1996-2000), seleccionados y aleatorizados del Sistema Informático Perinatal. Los datos provenían de la Maternidad Sarda (20 msnm) y las regiones jujeñas: Ramal (500 msnm), Valle (1200 msnm), Quebrada (2500 msnm) y Puna (3500 msnm). Variables resultado: PN &gt;3000 g, PN &lt;2500 g, Índice Ponderal (IP), prematurez, pequeño para edad gestacional (PEG) y restricción del crecimiento intrauterino (FGR). Variables confusoras: edad, tipo de pareja, educación, sobrepeso-obesidad, tabaquismo, hipertensión arterial, preeclampsia, infección urinaria, restricción del crecimiento y terminación cesárea. Resultados: Se observó un gradiente altitudinal creciente para madres adolescentes y decreciente para las variables obstétrico-maternas. El PN, PN &gt;3000 g, PN &lt;2500 g e Índice Ponderal se asociaron negativamente con altitud (p&lt;0.001). La prevalencia de prematurez, PEG y FGR mostraron un comportamiento opuesto (p&lt;0.001). Ajustados para variables confusoras el PN&lt;3000 g, PEG, FGR &lt; 0.90 e IP&lt;2.53 mostraron mayor riesgo con la altitud geográfica (p&lt;0.05). Conclusiones: La altitud se asoció independientemente con restricción del PN y resultados perinatales adversos. Dado el impacto de la reducción del PN en el riesgo de enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles, se debería evaluar esta relación en otras poblaciones, independientemente de su localización altitudinal. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of high altitude on birth weight and adverse perinatal outcomes in two Argentine populations].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
