<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24075584</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Matias-Guiu, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Simal, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Matarrubia, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espejo-Domínguez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matias-Guiu, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serna-Candel, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Demonstrating artery occlusion in ischaemic stroke has gained importance due to the increasing availability of endovascular therapies. This study evaluates the frequency of artery occlusion, its associated factors, and complications following the use of CT-angiography in acute stroke. METHODS We retrospectively analysed a cohort of patients who suffered acute ischaemic stroke between July and-December 2011. RESULTS We included 157 patients (mean age, 74±11; mean NIHSS score, 5 [2-13]). Of that total, 56.7% of the patients were admitted to hospital during the first 8hours. CT-angiography was performed in 71 cases (45.2%); arterial large-vessel occlusion was detected in 37 (52.1%) of these cases, and the most frequent site was M1 (40%). Univariate analysis showed that the NIHSS score (17 vs 7, P&lt;.001) and atrial fibrillation (64% vs 32%, P=.006) were associated with artery occlusion. A logistic regression analysis was performed subsequently, confirming these associations. There were no cases of contrast-induced nephropathy. Door-to-needle time for intravenous thrombolysis was 61.2±24.5minutes in patients who underwent CT-angiography, and 53.5±34.3minutes in those who did not (P=.495). CONCLUSIONS Arterial occlusions are seen in 23.6% of patients, especially in those who are admitted during the first few hours. NIHSS score serves as a useful predictive factor.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Occlusion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>CT-angiography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endovascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrinólisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oclusión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Angio-TC</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ictus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombolysis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Large artery occlusion diagnosed by computed tomography angiography in acute ischaemic stroke: frequency, predictive factors, and safety.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
