<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24099828</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Breda, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villavicencio, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Faba, O</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The indication and timing of nephrectomy in patients with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) remain controversial, especially in patients who are candidates to renal transplantation (RT). The main surgical options such as unilateral vs. bilateral nephrectomy, nephrectomy before vs. after RT, or simultaneous nephrectomy and transplantation, are herein discussed. OBJECTIVE Evidence acquisition of the best surgical management available for ADPKD in the context of kidney transplantation. ACQUISITION OF EVIDENCE Systematic literature review in PubMed from 1978 to 2013 was conducted. Articles selected included:randomized controlled trials and cohort studies. Furthermore, well designed ADPKD reviews were considered for this study. SYNTHESIS OF EVIDENCE Laparoscopic nephrectomy in ADPKD is a safe procedure with an acceptable complication rate. Unilateral nephrectomy has advantages over the bilateral one regarding the perioperative complication rate. Although the timing of nephrectomy is controversial, it seems that simultaneous nephrectomy and renal transplantation does not increase surgical morbidity neither affect graft survival. CONCLUSIONS Simultaneous nephrectomy and RT appears to be an acceptable alternative to conventional two-stage procedure without any increased morbidity, in the context of ADPKD. Furthermore, laparoscopic nephrectomy performed in experienced centres is a safe alternative to conventional approach.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nephrectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trasplante</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nefrectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Transplant</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal transplantation and polycystic: surgical considerations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
