<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24108378</identifier>
<setSpec>1609-722X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ormeño J, Alexis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Asato H, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>García D, Cesar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sumire U, Julia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic fibrosis (CF) is the most frequent recessive genetic disorder in the caucasian population and is produced by the alteration of electrolyte and water transport in the epithelial cell membrane. Liver disease is a frequent complication towards the end of the first decade of life, being weird its onset, except in patients with a history of meconium ileus. The characteristic liver injury in CF is focal biliary cirrhosis, but fatty infiltration can also be found. The diagnosis is made considering the clinical, laboratory and imaging results having in consideration that the normal liver function tests do not rule out the disease. Ultrasound is the most widely used and can detect the presence of steatosis, stones, fibrosis, cirrhosis, portal hypertension or abnormalities of the biliary tree. There is an also available technique such as computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging, which allows a morphological study. Important aspects in the treatment are nutritional management, administration of soluble vitamins and the use of ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA). In cases of advanced cirrhosis, transplantation, isolated or combined with the lung, is an option to consider, with acceptable survival rates. We report the case of an 11 year old patient with a diagnosis of chronic liver disease associated with cystic fibrosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatopatía crónica asociada a fibrosis quística en el Hospital Alberto Sabogal Sologuren, Lima, Perú: reporte de caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic liver disease associated with cystic fibrosis in the Hospital Alberto Sabogal Sologuren, Lima, Peru: report of a case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
