<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24144145</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vargas-Valencia, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-García, Erika Gabriela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galindo-Suárez, Rosa María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salinas-Escudero, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Munciño-Ortega, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to conduct cost-effectiveness analysis of etanercept compared with other biologic therapies in the treatment of moderate or severe rheumatoid arthritis in patients with previous unresponse to immune selective anti-inflammatory derivatives failure. METHODS a pharmacoeconomic model based on decision analysis to assess the clinical outcome after giving etanercept, infliximab, adalimumab or tocilizumab to treat moderate or severe rheumatoid arthritis was employed. Effectiveness of medications was assessed with improvement rates of 20 % or 70 % of the parameters established by the American College of Rheumatology (ACR 20 and ACR 70). RESULTS the model showed that etanercept had the most effective therapeutic response rate: 79.7 % for ACR 20 and 31.4 % for ACR 70, compared with the response to other treatments. Also, etanercept had the lowest cost ($149,629.10 per patient) and had the most cost-effective average ($187,740.40 for clinical success for ACR 20 and $476,525.80 for clinical success for ACR 70) than the other biologic therapies. CONCLUSIONS we demonstrated that treatment with etanercept is more effective and less expensive compared to the other drugs, thus making it more efficient therapeutic option both in terms of means and incremental cost-effectiveness ratios for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>artritis reumatoide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>arthritis, rheumatoid</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>economics, pharmaceutical</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>economía farmacéutica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>and cost analysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>costos y análisis de costo</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etanercept y otras terapias biológicas en artritis reumatoide. Un análisis de costo-efectividad.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: analizar la relación costo-efectividad del etanercept en comparación con otras terapias biológicas para tratar la artritis reumatoide moderada o severa en pacientes con falla previa a fármacos antirreumáticos modificadores de la enfermedad. Métodos: se empleó un modelo farmacoeconómico basado en el análisis de decisiones para valorar la evolución clínica con etanercept, infliximab, adalimumab o tocilizumab para tratar artritis reumatoide moderada o severa. Los parámetros de efectividad fueron las tasas de mejoría igual o superior a 20 % (ACR 20) y de mejoría igual o superior a 70 % (ACR 70). Resultados: etanercept tuvo la mayor efectividad terapéutica: en 79.7 % de los pacientes se observó una ACR 20 y en 31.4 %, una ACR 70. También tuvo el menor costo asociado ($149 629.1 por paciente) y fue más costo-efectiva ($187 740.4 por éxito clínico para obtener ACR 20 y $476 525.8 por éxito clínico para obtener ACR 70) que las demás terapias biológicas. Conclusiones: el etanercept fue el fármaco más efectivo y menos costoso, por lo que resulta la opción terapéutica más eficiente, desde el punto de vista de la relación costo-efectividad media y en términos incrementales para el tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cost-effectiveness analysis of etanercept compared with other biologic therapies in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
