<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24167956</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vio, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fretes, Gabriela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salinas, Judith</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to assess the impact of a nutrition education intervention on fruits, vegetables and fish consumption in pre-school and school age children families, through a three months education intervention with a pre-post evaluation in 27 intervened families and 32 controls from public schools in Santiago, Chile. A food-frequency questionnaire on fruits, vegetables and fish, and a survey on food and nutrition knowledge, attitudes and practices were applied to children and their parents. The intervention consisted in six 90 minutes cooking workshops, including the utilization of videos and photovoice for those who cooked in the families. Results showed a significant more consumption of fruits, vegetables and fish in the intervened than in the control group (test de Kolmogorov-Smirnov, test de Wilcoxon, p &lt; 0.05). Comparing pre-post consumption by group, significance differences were for the intervened group in all cases. (test de Wilcoxon for paired samples, p &lt; 0.05). In parents, fruit consumption increased 135.8 g, vegetables 19.5 g, and fish 10,2 g per day. In children, the increase in fruits was 92.1 g, vegetables 65.9, and fish 5.2 g per day. All the intervened families (n = 22) introduced a significant healthy food improvement at home. Results showed that it is possible to change food habits in families with the implementation of a nutrition education intervention including cooking workshops, videos and photovoice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de una intervención educativa sobre el consumo de frutas, verduras y pescado en familias de niños preescolares y escolares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of a nutrition education intervention on consumption of fruits, vegetables and fish in families of prescholers and scholers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
