<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24176190</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pascual, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pera, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallén, Manel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cáceres, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Courtier, Ricard</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montagut, Clara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, M José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andreu, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grande, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Although the conventional treatment of patients with stage iv colorectal cancer involves resection of the primary tumor followed by chemotherapy, several studies suggest that in patients with few symptoms the first and only treatment should be chemotherapy. The objective of this study is to analyze the complications related to the primary tumor in a series of patients with unresectable metastatic colorectal cancer treated with chemotherapy without surgery. MATERIAL AND METHODS Retrospective descriptive study. The study included all patients with unresectable metastatic colorectal cancer treated with chemotherapy without resection of the primary tumor (January 2007-February 2011). RESULTS The mean age of the 61 patients analyzed was 67±13 years and the performance status was 0-1 in 53 (87%). Twenty (33%) patients developed complications during follow-up. The most common complication was intestinal obstruction in 15 (25%) patients followed by perforation. Complications required surgery in 6 (10%) cases. We did not find differences in patient characteristics between those who had a complication and those without, although the complication rate in patients with a colonic stent (53%) was twice that of other patients (26%). CONCLUSIONS Chemotherapy without surgery is a good option in most patients with unresectable metastatic colorectal cancer. However, although the percentage of patients requiring surgery is low, the total number of complications related to the primary tumor is not negligible. Studies are needed to identify those patients in whom a prophylactic colectomy could be indicated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Chemotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Palliative surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer colorrectal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quimioterapia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Unresectable metastases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colorectal cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía paliativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metástasis irresecables</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del cáncer colorrectal con metástasis irresecables con quimioterapia sin resección del primario: análisis de las complicaciones relacionadas con el tumor.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of colorectal cancer with unresectable metastasis with chemotherapy without primary tumor resection: analysis of tumor-related complications].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
