<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24196768</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mansini, Adrián P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zubizarreta, Pedro A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Felice, María S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallego, Marta S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rossi, Jorge G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina, Adriana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, Cristina N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, Patricia L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with Down's Syndrome have a higher risk of developing acute megakaryoblastic leukemia (AML). Ten per cent of newborn infants with this syndrome have transient abnormal myelopoiesis (TAM), indistinguishable from AML, which generally remits spontaneously. A high incidence of GATA-1 gene mutations was described in both groups of patients. Fourteen bone marrow DNA samples (10 ATM/4 AML) were analyzed by PCR and sequencing; these samples were obtained from 13 patients with Down's Syndrome to describe the rate and mutation characteristics of the GATA-1 gene in the studied population and its consequences at a protein level. Mutations were detected in 10 out of 10 TAM and in 3 out of 4 AML, which at a protein level would result in an early termination codon (n= 5), alterations in the splicing site (n= 6) or sequence change (n= 3). The high rate of GATA-1 gene mutations was confirmed in newborn infants with Down's Syndrome and MAT or AML.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mutation characterization in the GATA-1 gene in patients with Down's Syndrome diagnosed with transient abnormal myelopoiesis or acute megakaryoblastic leukemia.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
