<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2424293</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Elorza, F L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lizaso, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The number of patients clinically suffering from rhinitis and/or asthma is very important in any collective of our society. The usage of drugs with a bronchodilator effect as a symptomatic therapy has been widely studied. However, the appearance of new products which complements the effect of bronchodilator and antianaphylactic union has not been sufficiently studied. The motive of this study is to evaluate the inhibition of histamine as the primary and principal mediator, liberated specifically by the Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus and D. farinae before and four hours after drug administration. Conditions for inclusion were the following: To be affected by rhinitis and/or extrinsic asthma induced by house dust mites. Not to have been previously treated with immunotherapy. Be free of previous prophylactic or symptomatic medication. Prick test positive to house dust mites. Serum IgE concentration higher than 100 U.I./ml. Specific histamine release by antigens with a value lower than 10% of the total histamine. The results obtained were based on 21 patients affected with rhinitis and/or asthma induced by dust mites and show that Procaterol produces a moderate reduction on the liberation of histamine as much as 58.6 and 57.4 for dust mites D. pteronyssinus and farinae respectively, four hours after ingestion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1986 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modificaciones en la liberación de histamina inducida por los ácaros del polvo doméstico tras la administración de procaterol.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Changes in histamine liberation induced by house dust mites after the administration of procaterol].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Allergologia et immunopathologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
