<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24248163</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torres, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera, Nancy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, Priscila</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Infestation by Demodex spp. in the palpebral edge follicles in humans is common. However, these mites are not routinely diagnosed in patients with or without ocular pathologies in Chile and their relevance is unclear. One of the eye diseases most related to infestation by Demodex spp. is blepharitis, a chronic inflammation of the eyelid margin with intermittent exacerbations, which is very common in ophthalmic practice. Its management is prolonged treatment, which is often ineffective, leading to relapses and frustration of patient and treating physician. Blepharitis can be typed by its etiology into various types, one of them is caused by Demodex folliculorum and another species, D. brevis. OBJECTIVE The overall objective was to detect the presence and estimate the rate of infestation of Demodex spp. in healthy subjects and in patients with ocular pathology such as blepharitis, bacterial conjunctivitis, chalazion, and stye. PATIENTS AND METHODS Samples of tabs from both lower eyelids of ophthalmologically healthy patients (23) and patients with ocular pathologies (9) were mounted in immersion oil as described in literature, then visualized with a 10x objective and confirmed with 40x objective. RESULTS Detection rates of eggs, nymphs or adults of Demodex spp. in patients with and without ophthalmological problems were above and below 0.5 mites per tab, respectively. D.folliculorum was the species most frequently found. DISCUSSION The results are consistent with the international literature on both the rate of infestation as the predominant species. CONCLUSION This paper is the first study in Chile on this subject and represents a significant contribution to ophthalmic clinical diagnosis and treatment of patients with this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de índice de infestación por Demodex spp, en pacientes con blefaritis crónica y en pacientes sin otra patología ocular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Measurement of the index of infection by Demodex spp in patients with chronic blepharitis and in patients without other ocular diseases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
