<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24246884</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ten Morón, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vañó Carruana, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arrazola García, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a consensus in the international community regarding both the need for and benefits of systematic registration and planning of the dosage indicators in patients exposed to ionizing radiation. The main interest is in the registration and follow-up of the techniques and procedures that can involve the greatest risk from exposure to radiation. This register should be planned to include the structure and tools necessary to take the radiological safety of the patients into account, enabling the physicians requesting the studies to access the most important information in the register so they can appropriately justify the request for additional studies. Likewise, it should be considered a priority to establish diagnostic reference levels for the different magnitudes that are defined in function of the modality and techniques used; this information is useful for the staff involved in procedures that use ionizing radiation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Historia clínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Historial dosimétrico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Picture Archiving and Communication System</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Protección radiológica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiologic protection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dosimetric history</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Digital Imaging and Communication in Medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clinical history</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistemas de registro automático de pacientes en instalaciones de radiología digital. Historial dosimétrico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Automatic registration of patients in digital radiology facilities: dosimetric record].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
