<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24241363</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez-Vargas, Luis-Octavio</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Rosa-García, Estela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miramontes-Zapata, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mondragón-Padilla, Arnoldo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Oral candidiasis (OC) is a common opportunistic infection in immunocompromised patients. Species identification is sometimes important for treatment. objective: to determine the prevalence of different Candida species colonising or infecting the oral mucosa (OM) of diabetic (DM) and non-diabetic (non-DM) chronic kidney disease patients, comparing both groups and exploring potential risk factors. METHODS 56 DM and 80 non-DM patients on chronic dialysis were examined. OM swabs were cultured on Sabouraud dextrose agar plates. Candida species were identified with API® galleries. OC was confirmed by exfoliative cytology. Statistical associations were analysed using χ2, Fisher's exact test (ET), and multiple logistic regression. RESULTS Candida prevalence was 43.4%: 53.6% DM and 36.3% non-DM, (p=.045). The species identified were C. albicans 74.6%, C. glabrata 22.0%, C. tropicalis 15.2%, C. parapsilosis 3.4 %, C. kefyr 3.4% and C. famata 1.7% without difference between groups. DM patients had a higher xerostomia prevalence (p=.002) and lower salivary flow (p=.008) and lower serum albumin (p=.018). 16.9% of patients had OC, 23.2% DM compared with 12.5% non-DM, (p=.101). The following were associated with the presence of Candida in the OM: the use of dental prostheses (odds ratio [OR] 25.6, 95% confidence interval [CI] 2.5 to 253, P=.001), xerostomia (OR 9.6, 95% CI 2.4 to 38.1, P=.001) and low serum albumin values (OR 0.41, 95% CI 0.22 to 0.98, P=.044). CONCLUSIONS The presence of Candida sp. in the OM was associated with dental prostheses, xerostomia and low serum albumin.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Nov 13 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral colonisation and infection by Candida sp. in diabetic and non-diabetic patients with chronic kidney disease on dialysis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
