<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24256011</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Maiques Llácer, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soler Company, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sangrador Pelluz, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE To study the safety of triple therapy with telaprevir and the time of appearance of the RAM in the treatment of hepatitis C. METHOD A retrospective observational study (January 2012- June 2013) of patients with HCV genotype 1 who had completed 12 weeks of triple therapy with telaprevir. The following variables were needed to characterize patients, and those relating to the treatment received. The classification of ADR was performed according to criteria of the SIDA Division 1.0. RESULTS We included 88 patients (78% male), 75% cirrhotic patients. 40.9% were coinfected with HIV. The main ADR (incidence &gt; 40%) including all grades: haematological toxicity, fatigue, hyperuricemia, hyperbilirubinemia and pruritus. Serious ADR (incidence &gt; 15%): thrombocytopenia, anemia and neutropenia. 3.4% had severe toxicodermia. 51.1% required ribavirin dose adjustment, blood transfusions 13.6%, and 28.4% exogenous erythropoietin. The 8% required hospitalization motivated by treatment toxicity. The treatment was stopped for toxicity in 6.8% of patients: 3 severe toxicodermia, 2 severe haematological toxicity, and 1 severe emesis. Thrombocytopenia and hyperbilirubinemia occurred at an early stage in its higher degree of toxicity, while the other ADR presented progression longer periods. CONCLUSIONS The study shows a superior toxicity profile to that described in clinical trials, mainly with regard to hematologic toxicity, and predicts a time range of highest probability of occurrence of ADR.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad en la pr&amp;aacute;ctica cl&amp;iacute;nica de la triple terapia con telaprevir en la hepatitis C cr&amp;oacute;nica.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivos: Estudiar la seguridad de la triple terapia con telaprevir y el momento de aparici&amp;oacute;n de las RAM en el tratamiento de la hepatitis C. M&amp;eacute;todo: Estudio observacional retrospectivo (Enero 2012- Junio 2013) de los pacientes con VHC genotipo 1 que hubieran finalizado las 12 semanas de triple terapia con telaprevir. Se recogieron las variables necesarias para caracterizar a los pacientes, y aquellas referentes al tratamiento recibido. La clasificaci&amp;oacute;n de las RAM se realiz&amp;oacute; seg&amp;uacute;n criterios de la Divisi&amp;oacute;n del SIDA versi&amp;oacute;n 1.0. Resultados: Se incluyeron 88 pacientes (78% hombres), 75% pacientes cirr&amp;oacute;ticos. El 40,9% estaba coinfectado con VIH. Las principales RAM (incidencia &gt; 40%) incluyendo todos los grados: toxicidad hematol&amp;oacute;gica, cansancio, hiperuricemia, hiperbilirrubinemia y prurito. Las RAM graves (incidencia &gt; 15%): trombocitopenia, anemia y neutropenia. El 3,4% present&amp;oacute; toxicodermia grave. El 51,1% requiri&amp;oacute; ajuste de dosis de ribavirina, 13,6% transfusiones de sangre, y 28,4% eritropoyetina ex&amp;oacute;gena. El 8% requiri&amp;oacute; ingreso hospitalario motivado por la toxicidad del tratamiento. El tratamiento fue suspendido por toxicidad en el 6,8% de los pacientes: 3 por toxicodermia grave, 2 por toxicidad hematol&amp;oacute;gica grave, y 1 por emesis grave. La trombocitopenia y la hiperbilirrubinemia se registraron de manera temprana en su mayor grado de toxicidad, mientras que el resto de RAM presentaron periodos de progresi&amp;oacute;n m&amp;aacute;s prolongados. Conclusiones: El estudio se&amp;ntilde;ala un perfil de toxicidad superior al descrito en los ensayos cl&amp;iacute;nicos, principalmente en cuanto a toxicidad hematol&amp;oacute;gica, y permite predecir un rango de tiempo de mayor probabilidad de aparici&amp;oacute;n de las RAM. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Safety in the clinical practice of the triple therapy with telaprevir in chronic hepatitis C].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
