<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24257257</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7286</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Sánchez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lledó-Riquelme, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Santonja, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campos-Mollo, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuenca-Navarro, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the effects of topical bevacizumab and topical sunitinib on vascular microdensity and morphology of corneal neovascularization (NV). METHODS A total of 33 rabbits were distributed into 3 groups: group 1 (control; n=11): saline; group 2 (n=11): bevacizumab 5mg/ml; and group 3 (n=11): sunitinib 0.5mg/ml. A corneal NV model was used, based on sutures in the right eye of each rabbit. Each treatment was administered topically 3 times daily for 14 days. Corneas were then processed for the study of vascular microdensity (6 eyes) and vascular morphology analysis (5 eyes) using enzymatic staining histological techniques RESULTS The vascular response in group 3 was limited to small-sized tree formations with various vascular axes compared with the extensive, lush and directional corneal NV of group 1 and 2. In the histological sections near the limb, there were no differences in vascular microdensity studies between the three groups. However, the mean sectional area of vessels (MSAV) in group 3 was 41.88% lower than in group 1 and 19.19% lower than in group 2. In distal sections, there were no differences between groups 1 and 2. However, group 3 was characterized by absence of vessels. CONCLUSIONS Bevacizumab produced no changes in the morphology of the vessels or the vascular microdensity. Sunitinib reduced the size of the new vessels and induced changes in the vascular tree.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Angiogenesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cornea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Córnea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sunitinib</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neovascularización corneal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neovascularization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neovascularización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Angiogénesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Corneal neovascularization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bevacizumab</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la morfología y la microdensidad neovascular corneal inducidos tras la administración tópica de bevacizumab y sunitinib en un modelo animal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Vascular morphological and microdensity changes of corneal neovascularization induced by topical bevacizumab and sunitinib in an animal model].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
