<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24255902</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6139</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Stagnaro, Juan C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Teaching theoretical-technical knowledge aimed at training specialists in psychiatry at postgraduate level requires the explicitness of the theoretical model to which the curricula presented to students should be ordered. First, said model should be coherent with the general curricula for the medical training from which candidates to obtain the specialist degree graduate; second, it should serve to transmit theoretical elements, attitudes and skills that allow their work of excellence, which means acquiring the qualities considered relevant and necessary by the consensus among the members of a specialty, discipline or science (in our case, medical specialty in psychiatry) in the present historical moment. Reference points to meet them in the light of the present data concerning medical and psychiatric paradigms are developed. This article refers to those particular aspects with special emphasis on certain epistemological issues, from whose effects the same specialists do not escape, and which also condition their teaching practice, trying to show that an integrative pedagogical model is the one that best fits the contemporary historical conditions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La formación actual de especialistas en psiquiatría: un desafío epistemológico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Present training for specialists in psychiatry: an epistemological challenge].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Vertex (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
