<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24269413</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7286</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rivas, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz-Negrete, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rebolleda, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blázquez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Esteban, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate primary cultures from human conjunctiva supplemented with fetal bovine serum, autologous serum, and platelet-rich autologous serum, over human amniotic membrane and lens anterior capsules. METHODS One-hundred and forty-eight human conjunctiva explants were cultured in CnT50(®) supplemented with 1, 2.5, 5 and 10% fetal bovine serum, autologous serum and platelet-rich autologous serum. Conjunctival samples were incubated at 37°C, 5% CO2 and 95% HR, for 3 weeks. RESULTS The typical phenotype corresponding to conjunctival epithelial cells was present in all primary cultures. Conjunctival cultures had MUC5AC-positive secretory cells, K19-positive conjunctival cells, and MUC4-positive non-secretory conjunctival cells, but were not corneal phenotype (cytokeratin K3-negative) and fibroblasts (CD90-negative). CONCLUSIONS Conjunctiva epithelial progenitor cells were preserved in all cultures; thus, a cell culture in CnT50(®) supplemented with 1 to 5% autologous serum over human amniotic membrane can provide better information of epithelial cell differentiation for the conjunctival surface reconstruction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Suero autólogo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Conjunctival epithelial cells</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diferenciación celular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Membrana amniótica humana</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cultivo primario</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Human amniotic membrane</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary culture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Autologous serum</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Células epiteliales conjuntivales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cell differentiation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización del cultivo primario epitelial de conjuntiva humana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characterization of epithelial primary culture from human conjunctiva].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
