<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24274606</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Amaya-Mejía, Adela Sisy</dc:author>
<dc:author>O'Farrill-Romanillos, Patricia María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galindo-Pacheco, Lucy Vania</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Rivero-Hernández, Leonel Gerardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-Ortega, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segura-Méndez, Nora Hilda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendoza-Zubieta, Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Vitamin D regulates cellular activity, also it has effects on: innate and adaptive immunity, antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory functions. It has been suggested a possible association between vitamin D deficiency and increased risk and length of respiratory infections in patients with common variable immunodeficiency (CVID). METHODS We conducted a descriptive study in patients with CVID. Vitamin D serum levels were measured in all patients. The results were analyzed using descriptive statistics by calculating measures of dispersion and central tendency. RESULTS We studied 20 patients, 13 women and 7 males, with an age average of 37 ± 13.43 years. The mean concentration of vitamin D in patients was 15.43 ng/mL ± 7.23. Thirty percent of all patients had severe Vitamin D deficiency, 45% had mild to moderate deficiency and 25% had insufficiency. Autoimmune diseases were associated in 35% of CVID patients, 42.8% of them had severe vitamin D deficiency. In patients with bronchiectasis, 85% were found with vitamin D deficiency, and it was severe in 35.2%. 41% of patients with bronchiectasis were classified as severe on the Bhalla score of severity, 57% of these patients had severe deficiency and 14.2% mild-moderate deficiency. CONCLUSIONS : We found deficiency of vitamin D in patients with CVID patients. Most of patients with CVID and bronchiectasis were detected with mild to severe vitamin D deficiency. Almost the half of patients with autoimmune diseases associated to CVID showed deficiency of vitamin D. We recommend to investigate the association of vitamin D deficiency on patients with immunodeficiencies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deficiencia de vitamina D en pacientes con inmunodeficiencia común variable, con enfermedades autoinmunes y bronquiectasias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Vitamin D deficiency in patients with common variable immunodeficiency, with autoimmune diseases and bronchiectasis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
