<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24290008</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rojas-Carrasco, Karmina Elena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: when there is a child patient in the family, it is frequent that parents get upset. Anxiety in the mother and father could be different depending on the way each one lives the critical situation of the child patient. The purpose was to measure levels of anxiety in fathers and mothers who had a hospitalized child in an intensive care unit. Methods: the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) was applied to a group of 50 pairs of parents who had a hospitalized child in the intensive care unit in a pediatric hospital. A no probabilistic intentional sample was used. Differences between groups were analyzed by Student's t test. Results: no significant differences were obtained between mothers and fathers for both state-anxiety and trait-anxiety. Significant differences were obtained intra-groups between both kinds of anxiety. Conclusions: having a child who is chronically sick or hospitalized for intensive therapy causes similar levels of anxiety in both parents. Anxiety is significantly increased in both parents when their child is hospitalized in an intensive therapy unit.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>niños hospitalizados</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>state-trait anxiety</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>anxiety</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ansiedad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>hospitalized children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ansiedad rasgo-estado</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 November-December </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de ansiedad en madres y padres con un hijo en terapia intensiva.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: es frecuente que los progenitores de un niño enfermo presenten trastornos en su estado anímico. La ansiedad en las madres y los padres puede ser diferente. El propósito de este trabajo fue conocer las diferencias en los niveles de ansiedad-rasgo y ansiedad-estado en los padres y las madres con un hijo en terapia intensiva. Métodos: se aplicó el Inventario de Ansiedad Rasgo-Estado a 50 parejas de padres que tenían un hijo en terapia intensiva de un hospital de pediatría. El muestreo fue no probabilístico intencional. Las diferencias en los grupos se analizaron con t de Student. Resultados: en la ansiedad-estado ni en la ansiedad-rasgo se obtuvieron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en las madres y los padres, sin embargo, se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas al comparar intragrupos en ambos tipos de ansiedad tanto en los padres como en las madres. Conclusiones: tener un hijo con una enfermedad crónica o internado en terapia intensiva causa niveles de ansiedad similares en ambos progenitores, que se incrementan significativamente al encontrarse el hijo en la unidad de cuidados intensivos. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Levels of state-trait anxiety between mothers and fathers who have children in an intensive care unit.]</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
