<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24300307</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Severa-Ruíz de Velasco, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Miralles Grávalos, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benejam-Gual, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pons-Viver, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz-Granda, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Transurethral resection of the prostate is the gold standard of surgical treatment of lower urinary tract symptoms associated to benign prostate hyperplasia. The new Green Light Photovaporization has been shown to be an alternative that is as effective for this condition as the transurethral resection of the prostate. OBJECTIVES To compare the efficiency of Green Light Photovaporization 120 W versus transurethral resection of the prostate in the treatment of benign prostate hyperplasia (BPH) in a 2-year time horizon from the perspective of the Spanish health service perspective. METHODS A cost utility analysis was performed retrospectively with the data from 98 patients treated sequentially with transurethral resection of the prostate (n: 50) and Green Light Photovaporization 120 W (n: 48). A Markov model was designed to estimate the cost (2012€) and results (quality adjusted life years) in a 2-year time horizon. RESULTS The total cost associated to Green Light Photovaporization 120 W treatment was less (3,377€; 95% CI: 3,228; 3,537) than that of the transurethral resection of the prostate (3,770€; 95% CI: 3,579; 3,945). The determining factor of the cost was the surgical phase (difference: -450€; 95% CI: -625; -158) because admission to hospital after surgery was not necessary with the GreenLight-PhotoVaporization. CONCLUSIONS Surgical treatment of BPH patients with GreenLight-PhotoVaporization 120 W is more efficient than transurethral resection of the prostate in the surgical treatment of benign prostate hyperplasia as it has similar effectiveness and lower cost (-393€; 95% CI: -625; -158).</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Transurethral resection of the prostate</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>GreenLight-PhotoVaporization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hiperplasia benigna de próstata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coste-efectividad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Benign prostate hyperplasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cost-effectiveness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resección transuretral de la próstata</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness analysis at 2 years of surgical treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia by photoselective vaporization of the prostate with GreenLight-Photo vaporization 120 W versus transurethral resection of the prostate.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
