<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24321389</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Peláez Cantero, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Madrid Rodríguez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jurado Ortiz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urda Cardona, A L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVES Parenteral antibiotic treatment has been classically developed in hospitals and is considered as a hospital procedure. The development of Hospital at Home Units (HHU) has led to an increase in outpatient parenteral antibiotic therapy (OPAT) in paediatrics patients. The objective of this study is to describe our experience, as an HHU integrated within a Paediatric Department, in home antimicrobial therapy over a period of 12 years. PATIENTS AND METHODS This prospective and descriptive study included every patient with a disease requiring parenteral antimicrobial therapy who was admitted to our HHU from January 2000 to December 2012. RESULTS During the study there were 163 cases on OPAT. The mean age of the patients was 11.1 years, and the sample group was comprised of 33 males and 22 feamales. The main sources of the treated infections were respiratory tract (76%), catheter-related bloodstream (9.2%), and urinary tract infections (5.5%). Amikacin was the most widely used antibiotic. Almost all treatments (96.6%) were via an intravenous route. Catheter-associated complications were more common than drug-associated complications. Successful at-home treatment was observed in 90.2% of cases. CONCLUSIONS OPAT is a good and safe alternative in many paediatric diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento antimicrobiano domiciliario intravenoso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Home therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intravenoso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento antimicrobiano parenteral ambulatorio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento domiciliario</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pediatric infections</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Outpatient parenteral antimicrobial therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento antimicrobiano parenteral domiciliario: análisis prospectivo de los últimos 12 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Domiciliary parenteral antibiotic therapy: a prospective analysis of the last 12 years].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
