<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24332847</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez López, M I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Among products for the management and control of faeces in patients with fecal incontinence, there are new devices that allow the diversion and collection of fecal matter. This study has aimed to know the complications related to these new devices described in the literature. METHOD A search was made in the main bibliographic databases, obtaining publications on the new devices. The relevant documents were selected, these being those that described complications. After these were described. RESULTS A total of 13 relevant documents were recovered. There were 45 adverse events 36 patients. Those having the greatest incidence were rectal bleeding (10 patients) and abdominal distension (6 patients). CONCLUSION In order to provide the best patient care, it is essential to know the possible complications in order to be able to prevent them. The cares given these patients need to be reevaluated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Fecal incontinence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Catéter de permanencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indwelling catheter</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adverse event</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diarrhea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diarrea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Incontinencia fecal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermería</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Efecto adverso</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos dispositivos de derivación y colección fecal: efectos adversos descritos en la bibliografía.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[New devices of fecal diversion and collection: adverse effects described in the literature].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
