<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24342118</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Borda, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Urién, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borda, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zozaya, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Nowadays, the possible effect of endoscopist fatigue on the results of colonoscopies is under discussion. We aimed to analyze possible differences in cecal intubation and the polyp and adenoma detection rate, depending on whether colonoscopies were performed at the beginning or at the end of the daily endoscopy session and to analyze the influence of the queue position on the detection rate. PATIENTS AND METHODS A retrospective study was performed with 1,000 ambulatory and consecutive colonoscopies, divided into 2 groups: «early» and «late» procedures. A total of 95 colonoscopies were excluded due to poor colon cleansing. After confirming that patient characteristics were homogenous in the two groups, we compared the frequency of complete colonoscopies and the polyp and adenoma detection rate. Possible differences between the 2 groups in the polyp detection rate according to the colonoscopy schedule were analyzed. RESULTS The overall polyp and adenoma detection rates were 44.2 and 30.5%, respectively, with no significant differences among 13 different endoscopists; polyps: p = 0.21; adenomas: p=0.63. No significant differences were found between the «early group» (n= 532) and the «late group» (n = 373) in the rates of complete colonoscopies [97.2 vs 99.4% (p=0.92)], the polyp detection rate [45.9 vs 41.8% (p=0.23)], the adenoma detection rate [30.8 vs 30% (p=0.80)] or the serrated adenoma rate [2.1% vs 1.6% (p=0.62)]. The lesion detection rate did not vary in relation to the «queue position»: polyps [p = 0.60, and adenomas: p = 0.83. CONCLUSIONS In our series, endoscopist fatigue at the end of the day had no influence on the complete colonoscopy rate or on the polyp and adenoma detection rate. There were no differences in the number of polypoid lesions detected according to the timing of the colonoscopy schedule.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Colonoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adenomas/diagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colorectal polyps/diagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colonoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fatigue</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fatiga</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Schedule timing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adenomas/diagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pólipos colorrectales/diagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Carga de trabajo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Horario de trabajo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Workload</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Influye el posible cansancio del endoscopista en la frecuencia de colonoscopias incompletas y de las lesiones polipoideas diagnosticadas?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Does endoscopist fatigue play a role in incomplete colonoscopies and detection of polypoid lesions?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
