<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24354243</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alcocer, Sirley</dc:author>
<dc:author>Durán, Anyelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ochoa, Edixon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maldonado, Mery</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millano, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Olga</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valero, Nereida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dengue is characterized by fever, headache, arthralgia and myalgia. The presence of gastrointestinal signs and symptoms (GISS) is considered a sign of alarm in dengue; however, little information exists regarding the occurrence of these events. The aim of this study was to determine the frequency of gastrointestinal signs and symptoms in a cohort of patients with dengue. A total of 1484 medical records of patients with confirmed dengue were reviewed and classified as: dengue without warning signs (DNWS) (n = 700), dengue with warning signs (DWWS) (n = 700) and severe dengue (SD) (n = 84). Of the studied records, 65.71% of patients with DNWS, 92.59% with DWWS and 100% of patients with SD had GISS. In patients with DNWS, nausea / vomiting were the most common symptoms in 319/700 cases (45.57%), followed by abdominal pain in 142/700 (20.29%) and diarrhea in 125/700 (17.86%). There were no cases with melena, hepatomegaly or hematemesis. While in DWWS nausea/vomiting were present in 529/700 (75.57%), abdominal pain in 439/700 (62.71%) and diarrhea in 198/700 (28.28%),(p &lt;0.0001). Melena, hematemesis and hepatomegaly ranged from 0.57% to 1.86% of cases. In SD, nausea/vomiting were registered in 100% of the cases, abdominal pain in 82/84 (97.62%), diarrhea in 65/84 (77.38%), melena in 32/84 (38.10%), hepatomegaly in 28/84 (33.33%) and hematemesis in 26/84 (30.95%). It was evident the high frequency of GISS in cases of DWWS and SD, in contrast to DNWS, in which the frequency of GISS was significantly lower. This suggests a relationship of GISS with the severity of dengue, and their presence should be considered by the decision-making health team for appropriate patient management.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de signos y síntomas gastrointestinales del dengue. Análisis de una cohorte de 1484 pacientes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Frequency of gastrointestinal signs and symptoms of dengue. Analysis of a cohort of 1484 patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
