<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24365392</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martinez Villar, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín de Lara, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Ferrer, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Bernal, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paya Elorza, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Familial Mediterranean fever (FMF) is a hereditary disease characterized by brief, recurring and self-limited episodes of fever and pain with inflammation, of one or several serous (peritoneum, pleura, pericardium, synovial or vaginal tunic of the testicle). Amyloidosis is its more important complication and the principal reason of death in the cases in which it appears. Diagnosis is based on the clinic and is confirmed by genetic tests. The treatment with Colchicine (0,02-0,03 mg/kg/day) prevents the recurrence of FMF attacks and the development of secondary (AA) amyloidosis. We report a case of a 13-year-old child in which FMF was diagnosed after several coincidental episodes with fever, pericarditis and cardiac tamponade. The genetic confirmation showed an autosomal dominant inheritance that is less frecuent than the recesive form, in this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Autosomal dominant</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mediterranean fever</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fiebre mediterránea familiar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Autosómico dominante</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiac tamponade</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Taponamiento cardiaco</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taponamiento cardiaco como forma de inicio de fiebre mediterránea familiar con herencia autosómica dominante.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cardiac tamponade as first manifestation in Mediterranean fever with autosomal dominant form].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
