<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24365579</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1879</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramírez, Agustín J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urina, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lara, Joffre</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Jaramillo, Patricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cobos, Leonardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peñaherrera, Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Harrap, Stephen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lanas, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sinay, Isaac</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sierra, Iván D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zanchetti, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benderky, Mario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bryce, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lizcano, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Foos, Milton C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Ramiro A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Schmid, Helena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra-Carrillo, José Z</dc:author>
<dc:author>Botero, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present document has been prepared by a group of experts, members of Cardiology, Endocrinology, Internal Medicine, Nephrology and Diabetes societies of Latin American countries, to serve as a guide to physicians taking care of patients with diabetes, hypertension and comorbidities or complications of both conditions. Although the concept of metabolic syndrome is currently disputed, the higher prevalence in Latin America of that cluster of metabolic alterations has suggested that metabolic syndrome is useful nosography entity in the context of Latin American medicine. Therefore, in the present document, particular attention is paid to this syndrome in order to alert physicians on a particular high- risk population, usually underestimated and undertreated. These recommendations results from presentation and debates by discussion panels during a 2-day conference held in Bucaramanga, in October 2012, and all the participants have approved the final conclusions. The authors acknowledge that the publication and diffusion of guidelines do not suffice to achieve the recommended changes in diagnostic or therapeutic strategies, and plan suitable interventions overcoming both physicians and patients from effectively adhering to guideline recommendations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Arterial hypertension</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipertensión arterial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latin American consensus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome metabólico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Consenso latinoamericano</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolic syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso latinoamericano de hipertensión en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 y síndrome metabólico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Latin American consensus on hypertension in patients with diabetes type 2 and metabolic syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Clinica e investigacion en arteriosclerosis : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Arteriosclerosis</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
