<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24483039</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Quijano, Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-López, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arturo-Zárate</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Valencia, Marcelino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-Girón, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) it is a metabolic disorder with insulin resistance associated. Have been recently described contributor factors in the presence of insulin resistance that need to be studied. These factors can be the nutrients in the daily diet, final products of the advanced glycated end-products (AGEs), reactive derivatives of non enzymatic glucose-protein reactions either produced endogenously or ingested from dietary sources. The aim was to modifies the food intake to know the contribution on improve insulin resistance. OBJECTIVE Compare different diets and changes in insulin resistance in patients with polycystic ovary syndrome. MATERIAL AND METHODS As longitudinal, prospective and descriptive study, were included women with age among 18 to 40 years who received a compound with amino acids, extracts and anti-oxidants to dose of 660mg every 8 hours for 6 months. The inclusion approaches included the insulin resistance presence HOMA-IR &gt; 2.6, elevated LH, and presence of ovaries with cysts by ultrasound. Statistical analysis with ANOVA one way to p &lt;0.05. RESULTS Were included a total of 30 patients, of which 28 patients had improvement in the insulin resistance from the 3 months, but until the 6 months they had significant difference (p&lt;0.05), compared with 24 women from control group. CONCLUSION With this result is demonstrated that it is necessary to modify the diet and to offer alimentary support to avoid the oxidative stress that takes impairment the insulin signaling with the subsequent insulin resistance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disminución de la resistencia a la insulina con aminoácidos, extractos y antioxidantes en pacientes con síndrome de ovarios poliquísticos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Decreased insulin resistance with amino acids, extracts and antioxidants in patients with polycystic ovary syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
