<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24528339</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Romero, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Cernadas, Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carballo-Costa, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Clinical characteristics of rheumatoid arthritis (AR) justify its multidisciplinary approach, within which nutritional intervention is included. Certain nutritional components influence the cellular metabolism and interfere in the pathological inflammatory process, so that they may act as coadjutant in the treatment of many inflammatory diseases, among which AR is in - cluded. AIM To analyze the evidence related to the therapeutical effects of the polyunsaturated fatty acids, mediterranean diet, olive oil and certain antioxidant nutrients, on chronic inflammation and AR symptomatology. METHODS Non-Systematic revision in Cochrane, Pubmed, Scopus, Sportdiscus and Amed, from 2003 to March 2013, and subsequent applications of inclusion and exclusion criteria. RESULTS Evidence on polyunsaturated fatty acids suggests that they produce clinical improvement and inhibitory effects over the AR inflammatory response. As regards the mediterranean diet, evidence points out that it decreases both pain and disease activity. In the case of the olive oil, although there are not enough studies, some effects are observed such as inflammatory markers reduction and oxidative stress inhibition. Finally, limited and contradictory evidence is found regarding the effectiveness of antioxidants. CONCLUSION There exist studies which suggest that some dietetic elements (polyunsaturated fatty acids, mediterranean diet and antioxidants) have anti-inflammatory effects and decrease AR disease activity. More studies are required to empower the results on those aspects where evidence is still non conclusive.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Feb 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de los aspectos nutricionales en el proceso inflamatorio de pacientes con artritis reumatoide; una revisión.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: Las características clínicas de la artritis reumatoide (AR) justifican su abordaje multidisciplinar, dentro del cual se incluye la intervención nutricional. Ciertos componentes nutricionales tienen implicaciones en el metabolismo celular e interfieren en el proceso inflamatorio patológico por lo que pueden actuar como coadyuvantes en el tratamiento de numerosas enfermedades inflamatorias, entre las que se incluye la AR. Objetivos: Analizar la evidencia sobre los efectos terapéuticos de los ácidos grasos poliinsaturados, de la dieta mediterránea, del aceite de oliva y de ciertos nutrientes antioxidantes en el estado inflamatorio crónico y en la sintomatología de la AR. Métodos: Revisión no sistemática en Cochrane, Pubmed, Scopus, Sportdiscus y Amed, del 2003 a marzo de 2013, y posterior aplicación de los criterios de inclusión y exclusión. Resultados: La evidencia sobre los ácidos grasos poliinsaturados sugiere que éstos producen mejoría clínica y efectos inhibidores sobre la respuesta inflamatoria en la AR. Sobre la dieta mediterránea, la evidencia apunta a que ésta produce una disminución del dolor y de la actividad de la enfermedad. Para el aceite de oliva, aunque no hay estudios suficientes, se aprecian efectos tales como la reducción de marcadores inflamatorios y la inhibición del estrés oxidativo. Sobre la eficacia de los antioxidantes todavía existe evidencia limitada y contradictoria. Conclusiones: Hay estudios que sugieren que algunos componentes dietéticos (ácidos grasos poliinsaturados, dieta mediterránea y antioxidantes) tienen efectos antiinflamatorios y disminuyen la actividad de la AR. Se requieren más estudios para afianzar los resultados en aquellos aspectos donde la evidencia todavía es inconclusa. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Importance of nutritional treatment in the inflammatory process of rheumatoid arthritis patients; a review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
