<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24522306</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Godoy, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abarca, Katia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sandoval, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Constanza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valenzuela, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montecinos, Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION There is not known if a viraemia post-oral polio vaccine (OPV) is detectable by modern molecular techniques. Such viraemia could affect the performance of the real time-polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for non polio enterovirus (EV) detection, technique of growing clinical use for the study of febrile infants. OBJECTIVE To determine viraemia post-first dose of OPV in healthy infants, by molecular techniques. PATIENTS AND METHODS 50 infants less than three months without previous VPO were randomized in 5 groups: a control group with pre-vaccination blood sample (BS), group 1 BS at day 2, group 2 BS at day 4, group 3, BS at day 6 and group 4, BS at day 8 post-vaccination. Conventional and specific PCR for poliovirus and real time PCR for non polio EV were performed in BS and in OPV samples. RESULTS No genetic material of poliovirus was detected in any infant, while in 9 of them (18%) non polio EV was identified. Real time PCR for EV did not amplify poliovirus from OPV samples. DISCUSSION Results suggest that no post VPO viraemia detectable by molecular methods exists. Considering that real time PCR for EV does not allow to identify polio virus, no false positives of the test are expected as a result of a recent VPO vaccination. We documented presence of non polio EV in blood of healthy asymptomatic infants.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vacuna polio oral en lactantes no interfiere con la detección de enterovirus en sangre.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Oral polio vaccine in infants does not interfere in detection of enterovirus in blood].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
