<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24522310</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez, Paulina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Brucellosis is a zoonosis whose economical impact in endemic countries is significant. Its magnitude for humans has been scarcely measured in Chile, therefore brucellosis was declared a reportable disease since 2004. OBJECTIVE To characterize the epidemiology of human brucellosis in Chile. MATERIAL Data sources were the Obligatory Disease Notification System (ODNS), the National Reference Laboratory for brucellosis, hospital discharges and deaths statistics. RESULTS The average incidence, according to the ODNS was 0.55 cases per 100.000 inhabitants (men 67.8%, median age 44 years). Hospital discharges rate of brucellosis during this period were 0.43 per 100.000 inhabitants. The major diagnosis (84.3%) was A23.9 (Brucellosis unspecified). Two patients died (mortality rate for the period 0.01 deaths per 100 000 inhabitants), their education level was basic. CONCLUSIONS The incidence rates of cases reported, hospital discharges and mortality tend to decrease. The discrepancy between reported cases and clinical/laboratory diagnosis suggests underreporting. It is necessary to improve the notification system and to optimize laboratory confirmation by the National Reference Laboratory.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brucelosis humana: situación epidemiológica en Chile, 2001-2010.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Human brucellosis: epidemiological situation in Chile, 2001-2010].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
