<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24531681</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-8260</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodriguez Fernandez, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernandez Fernandez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Husillos Alonso, Adrian</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escribano Patiño, Gregorio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cancho Gil, Maria Jose</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED To perform a bibliographic review on female urethra stenosis, following the criteria for evidence based medicine. METHODS We performed a PubMed Search with the following keywords; "female urethral stricture ","women urethral stricture","female urethral reconstruction "and " female urethral stricture treatment ",without time limits, both in English and Spanish languages. RESULTS Female urethra stenosis is a rare pathology, in which the working diagnosis is essential, as much as detailed physical examination, urodynamic study and radiological tests. We found in the literature a total of 73 cases treated with dilation with or without maintenance self catheterization, 120 cases treated with meatotomy, 65 cases treated by flap urethroplasty (46 with vaginal flap, 17 with vestibular flap and 12 with labia minora graft and 28 with oral mucosa grafts). There are not comparative studies between the various techniques, making it difficult to set up a therapeutic algorithm. CONCLUSIONS The surgical treatment with flaps/grafts has the highest success rate; whereas less invasive procedures such as urethrotomy/meatotomy/dilations/self-catheterization should be reserved for short female urethra stenosis or women with high comorbidity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estenosis uretral en la mujer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Urethral stricture in women].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
