<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24548475</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Fernández, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llamas-Elvira, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro-Pelayo Láinez, M M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cózar-Olmo, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-Alonso, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Río, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION prostate cancer is the most frequent solid malignant tumor in Western Countries. Positron emission tomography/x-ray computed tomography imaging with radiolabeled choline analogues is a useful tool for restaging prostate cancer in patients with rising prostate-specific antigen after radical treatment (in whom conventional imaging techniques have important limitations) as well as in the initial assessment of a selected group of prostate cancer patients. For this reason a literature review is necessary in order to evaluate the usefulness of this imaging test for the diagnosis and treatment of prostate cancer. EVIDENCE ACQUISITION a MEDLINE (PubMed way) literature search was performed using the search parameters: «Prostate cancer» and «Choline-PET/CT». Other search terms were «Biochemical failure» and/or «Staging» and/or «PSA kinetics». English and Spanish papers were selected; original articles, reviews, systematic reviews and clinical guidelines were included. CONCLUSIONS according to available data, radiolabeled choline analogues plays an important role in the management of prostate cancer, especially in biochemical relapse because technique accuracy is properly correlated with prostate-specific antigen values and kinetics. Although is an emerging diagnostic technique useful in treatment planning of prostate cancer, final recommendations have not been submitted.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de próstata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biochemical relapse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cinética antígeno prostático específico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estadificación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Staging</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Choline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prostate specific antigen kinetics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Positron emission tomography/computed tomography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recurrencia bioquímica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prostate cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tomografía por emisión de positrones/tomografía computarizada</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of positron emission tomography/computed tomography imaging with radiolabeled choline analogues in prostate cancer.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
