<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24584786</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Inda, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kijko, Ivana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Epelbaum, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruvinsky, Silvina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mónaco, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Constanzo, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Taicz, Moira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bologna, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Inadequate antibiotic use is associated with an increased emergence of resistant microorganisms, higher morbidity and mortality rates, and an impact on public health. OBJECTIVE To assess the effectiveness of a program aimed at improving the use of antimicrobials in patients hospitalized at Hospital Garrahan. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective, longitudinal, before and after study with no control group. STUDY PERIOD From November 1st, 2010 to June 30th, 2011. Patients receiving parenteral antibiotics were included. Newborn infants, burned patients and those receiving prophylactic antibiotics were excluded. The periods before and after implementing discussion and monitoring workshops for antibiotic prescription and distributing treatment guidelines were compared. An univariate analysis and a multiple logistic regression study were performed (STATA 8.0). RESULTS In the pre-intervention period,376 patients were included; of them, 35.6% had received inadequate treatment. The multiple regression analysis showed that the endpoints for inadequate antibiotic use were acute lower respiratory tract infection (OR: 3.80; 95% CI: 1.35-3.26; p=0.04), fever without a source in hospitalized patients (OR: 5.55; 95% CI: 2.43-12.6; p &lt; 0.01), and febrile neutropenia (OR: 0.29; 95% CI: 0.10-0.7; p &lt; 0.01). In the post-intervention period, 357 patients were included; 21.5% had received inadequate treatment. A reduction in inadequate antibiotic prescription was observed compared to the pre-intervention period (p &lt; 0.01). The multiple regression analysis showed that endpoints for inadequate use were skin and soft tissue infections (OR: 0.33; 95% CI: 0.13-0.93; p = 0.035), and febrile neutropenia (OR: 0.48; 95% CI: 0.220.94; p= 0.04). CONCLUSION The program was effective and allowed to improve antibiotic prescription practices in hospitalized children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a program to improve antibiotic use in children hospitalized in a children's tertiary care facility in Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
