<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24626693</identifier>
<setSpec>1606-7916</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Escobar-Zaragoza, Leticia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Dommarco, Juan Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Castell, Luz Dinorah</dc:author>
<dc:author>González de Cosío, Teresita</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To present data on infant and young child feeding practices (IYCFP) in Mexico from the 2012 National Health and Nutrition Survey (ENSANUT 2012) to support the development of public policy. POPULATION Women 12-49y and children &lt;2y. Indicators of IYCFP suggested by WHO were analyzed by geographic, socioeconomic, participation in food programs and health insurance variables. RESULTS Median duration of breast-feeding: 10.2mo and 14.4% with exclusive breastfeeding (EBF) &lt;6m. Breastfeeding deteriorated in most vulnerable groups. Decline in EBF&lt;6m 2006-2012 was explained by increases in consumption of formula and other milks (4%) and water (4%). Three-quarters (74%) of 6-11mo infants had minimum food diversity, and it was lower in the most vulnerable. CONCLUSIONS Complementary feeding improved but breastfeeding declined in Mexico. Promotion actions must be integral, coordinated, financed and evaluated, with Federal government leadership and should include the participation of various stakeholders.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas de alimentación infantil y deterioro de la lactancia materna en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infant feeding practices and deterioration of breastfeeding in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
