<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24652135</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fang, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marrugo, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP) has been linked as a susceptibility gene for the development of allergic diseases. It is known that the population of Cartagena is a triethnic mix, in which the component of African ancestry was significantly associated with risk of asthma and high total serum IgE levels. This component comes from African slaves brought into the continent and settled in "palenques", one of them is San Basilio de Palenque, in the Colombian Caribbean Coast. OBJECTIVE To analyze the distribution of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) rs1837253, rs17551370 and rs2289276 located in TSLP gene, in the African-descendent population of San Basilio de Palenque. MATERIALS AND METHODS By real time-PCR and probes TaqMan SNP Genotyping™, we genotyped three polymorphisms in 80 individuals of African-descent aged 5 to 18 years of age. RESULTS The frequency of the rs1837253 allele T was 41.9%, for the allele A, 14.3% for rs17551370, and 22.5% for the allele T of rs2289276. The rs17551370 and rs2289276 distribution remained in Hardy- Weinberg genetic equilibrium. The allele frequency of each SNP did not show statistically significant differences with those reported for other African and African-descendent populations. CONCLUSION The three polymorphisms in the TSLP were present in the sample population of San Basilio de Palenque and its distribution is similar to that reported for African populations and African ancestry in America.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distribución de tres polimorfismos del gen TSLP en población afrodescendiente de San Basilio de Palenque, Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Distribution of three polymorphisms of the TSLP gen in African-descendent population from San Basilio de Palenque, Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
