<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24650654</identifier>
<setSpec>1853-0605</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Parisi, Gustavo R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gilardi, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bürguesser, M V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salomone, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chamale, Roberto A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beacon, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brenna, Eduardo J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Restrictive cardiomyopathy is the least common form of cardiomyopathy, and the disease that most often cause it, is the system amyloidosis. We present a 62-year-old with a history of heart failure, which in its assessment highlights the discrepancy between the low voltage ventricular complexes in the electrocardiogram and the severity of left ventricular wall thickness on echocardiography. This discrepancy was the source of suspicion and subsequent confirmation of systemic amyloidosis with cardiac involvement.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discordancia entre el voltaje del electrocardiograma y el grosor parietal del ventículo izquierdo. clave diagnóstica en amiloidosis cardíaca.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La miocardiopatía restrictiva es la forma menos frecuente de cardiomiopatía, y la enfermedad que con mayor frecuencia la origina, es la amiloidosis sistema. Presentamos un paciente de 62 años, con antecedentes de insuficiencia cardiaca, que en su evaluación, destaca la discordancia entre el escaso voltaje de los complejos ventriculares en el electrocardiograma y la severidad del grosor parietal del ventrículo izquierdo en el ecocardiograma, siendo dicha discordancia, la fuente de sospecha y posterior confirmación de amiloidosis sistémica con compromiso cardiaco. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inconsistency between voltage of the electrocardiogram and the left ventricular wall thickness. diagnostic key in cardiac amyloidosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
