<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24652215</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Valencia, Diana María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caro, María Antonieta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valencia, Ana Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bedoya, Gabriel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Naranjo, Carlos Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra, María Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaramillo, Carlos José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Hypertension is a multifactorial disease influenced by genetic and environmental components, with its prevalence varying across ethnic groups. Manifold studies on blood pressure regulatory system genes have been carried out -such as the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system, the sympathetic nervous system, endothelial factor, and sodium balance-, but the results yielded were inconsistent among populations. OBJECTIVES To evaluate the effect of both variants in genes AGT, AGTR1, ACE, ADRB2, DRD1, ADD1, ADD2, ATP2B1, TBXA2R PTGS2, and the result of the individual ancestry component on hypertension and blood pressure levels among population in Antioquia. METHODS AND MATERIALS 107 cases and 253 controls were genotyped for 12 variants on genes AGT, AGTR1, ACE, ADRB2, DRD1, ADD1, ADD2, ATP2B1, TBXA2R y PTGS2, and for 20 ancestry informative markers. The association of polymorphisms and their interactions, and the association of ancestral genetic composition with hypertension and blood pressure levels were examined. RESULTS Genes ADD2, rs4852706 (OR=3.0; p=0.023); DRD1, rs686 (OR=0.38; p=0.012) and ADRB2, rs1042718 (OR=10.0; p=0.008); as well as genotypic combinations of DRD1 and AGTR1; AGT and ADD1; and ADD1 to ATP2B1 and PTGS2 were associated to hypertension. The Amerindian ancestry component was associated to some decrease in diastolic blood pressure. CONCLUSION Variants on genes ADD2, DRD1, ADRB2, AGTR1, AGT, ADD1, ATP2B1 and PTGS2 individually or interacting, are associated to hypertension. The Amerindian ancestry component has an effect on blood pressure.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación y efectos de interacción en los genes AGT , AGTR1 , ACE , ADRB2 , DRD1 , ADD1, ADD2, ATP2B1, TBXA2R y PTGS2 sobre la hipertensión en la población antioqueña.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Association and interaction of AGT, AGTR1, ACE, ADRB2, DRD1, ADD1, ADD2, ATP2B1, TBXA2R and PTGS2 genes on the risk of hypertension in Antioquian population].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
