<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24661948</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez-Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rebollo Aguirre, A C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano-Falcón, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malignant melanoma accounts for 5% of all malignant skin tumors and its incidence is increasing. In the natural course of melanoma, tumors grow locally and can spread via the lymph system or the blood. Because survival is directly related to the stage of the disease at diagnosis, early detection (secondary prevention) has an impact on prognosis. Positron emission tomography (PET) is a nuclear medicine technique that generates images using molecules labeled with positron-emitting isotopes. The most widely used molecule is fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG). Because of the elevated glycolytic rate in tumor cells, which results in increased FDG uptake, greater quantities of FDG become trapped in tumor cells, enabling external detection. Today, most PET scanners are multimodal PET-computed tomography (CT) scanners, which provide more detailed information by combining morphological information with functional PET findings. The possible utility of PET-CT in patients with malignant melanoma is a subject of debate. Various questions have been raised: when the scan should be performed, whether PET-CT has advantages over conventional diagnostic methods, and whether PET-CT provides a real benefit to patients. In this review of the literature, we will analyze each of these questions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Tomografía por emisión de positrones-tomografía computarizada</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Melanoma cutáneo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Positron emission tomography-computed tomography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cutaneous melanoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>18-Flúor-fluorodeoxiglucosa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fluorodeoxyglucose</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Positron emission tomography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tomografía por emisión de positrones</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic imaging in dermatology: utility of PET-CT in cutaneous melanoma.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
