<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24702977</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Reinoso, Javier Cobo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardenal, Javier Ariza</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteoarticular infections (OAI) include a wide-usually complex-spectrum of clinical scenarios. The approach is usually medical-surgical. In addition to this complexity, there is a low grade of evidence in the medical literature on these infections. Nevertheless, it is possible-and necessary-to integrate microbiological, pharmacological, experimental and clinical information to achieve the best possible clinical results. The most appropriate choice of antibiotic therapy largely depends on the clinical scenario and, obviously, on the microorganisms involved. Given the protagonism of staphylococci in OAI, it is appropriate to elucidate the role that could be played by a new antistaphylococcic agent in these infections. For clinicians who manage OAI, the incorporation of ceftaroline represents the recovery of a beta-lactam to treat methicillin-resistant staphylococci. This perspective can be used to guide the potential role of this new antibiotic for the management of OAI in various scenarios and the clinical research required for its introduction in clinical practice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Osteomyelitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prosthetic joint infection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ceftaroline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ceftarolina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección de prótesis articulares</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Osteomielitis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad potencial de ceftarolina fosamil en las infecciones osteoarticulares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Potential utility of ceftaroline fosamil in osteoarticular infections].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
