<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24718464</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arriagada, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lisbona, María Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roa, Macarena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Donoso, Javiera</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, Sebastián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Godoy, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mimica, Ximena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Trauma is an important cause of death among young adults. AIM To determine the characteristics, treatments and evolution of trauma patients admitted to an intensive care unit (ICU) of a public hospital in Santiago, Chile. MATERIAL AND METHODS All polytrauma (PT) and severely traumatized (ST) patients admitted to ICU were included. We recorded the type of trauma along with demographic and hemodynamic variables, treatments and complications. The evolution and treatments received by PT and ST patients were compared. RESULTS We recorded data from 72 patients aged 43 ± 21 years (93% males). Sixty two percent were PT and 24% had penetrating injuries. TBI (Trauma Brain Injury) was the most common trauma. On admission, acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II (APACHE II) score was 18.7 + 7.3, and Injury Severity Score (ISS) was 32.8 + 20.1. ICU stay was 7.8 + 6 days. Sixty seven per cent of patients required surgery and 58% received blood transfusions. No differences were found between PT and ST. ICU and hospital mortality rates were 15 and 25% respectively. CONCLUSIONS The characteristics and evolution of PT and ST of this series of patients are similar to those described abroad. Mortality was in agreement with ISS and APACHE II scores.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de los pacientes traumatizados que ingresan a la UCI de un hospital general en Chile.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characteristics of trauma patients admitted to the intensive care unit of a general hospital in Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
