<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24725518</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gonzalez-Quintana, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Álvarez, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parés-Pollán, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas-Gallego, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos-Rodríguez, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Docampo-Cordeiro, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diaz Rubio-García, M P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Owing to the decrease in values of biochemical glucose parameter in some samples from external extraction centres, and the risk this implies to patient safety; it was decided to apply an adaptation of the «Health Services Failure Mode and Effects Analysis» (HFMEA) to manage risk during the pre-analytical phase of sample transportation from external centres to clinical laboratories. MATERIALS AND METHODS A retrospective study of glucose parameter was conducted during two consecutive months. The analysis was performed in its different phases: to define the HFMEA topic, assemble the team, graphically describe the process, conduct a hazard analysis, design the intervention and indicators, and identify a person to be responsible for ensuring completion of each action. RESULTS The results of glucose parameter in one of the transport routes, were significantly lower (P=.006). The errors and potential causes of this problem were analysed, and criteria of criticality and detectability were applied (score≥8) in the decision tree. It was decided to: develop a document management system; reorganise extractions and transport routes in some centres; quality control of the sample container ice-packs, and the time and temperature during transportation. CONCLUSIONS This work proposes quality indicators for controlling time and temperature of transported samples in the pre-analytical phase. Periodic review of certain laboratory parameters can help to detect problems in transporting samples. The HFMEA technique is useful for the clinical laboratory.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Seguridad del paciente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acreditación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diagnostic errors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gestión del riesgo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patient safety</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Accreditation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Manipulación de muestras</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Risk management</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Specimen handling</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Errores de diagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del análisis modal de fallos y efectos para la detección de errores en el transporte de muestras al laboratorio clínico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Modal failure analysis and effects in the detection of errors in the transport of samples to the clinical laboratory].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
