<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24736252</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Monti, Fernanda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caberlotto, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Khoury, Marina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boim, Clarisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Storni, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortiñaz, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Participation in a Pulmonary Rehabilitation Program (PRP) improves dyspnea, functional capacity and quality of life in patients with chronic respiratory disease. A retrospective study was carried out to identify variables related to compliance in an out patient PRP at an Argentine center and to evaluate the results in compliant patients. The PRP included an "acquisition" stage consisting of 16 weeks of supervised training twice weekly and lectures on treatment benefits, inhalation devices used, smoking cessation, symptoms recognition and flair up management, among others. Patients were reassessed after this stage. Patients completing the acquisition stage were considered PRP compliant. Of 388 patients evaluated for admission 102 (26.3%) complied with PRP. Multiple logistic regression analysis (Forward Stepwise; p &lt; 0.10 to be eligible for entry into the model) was used to identify factors related to "program compliance". The final model was as follows: having health insurance coverage (OR = 3.99; CI90% = 2.24-7.12), commute time under 60 minutes (OR = 2.07; CI90% = 1.37-3.11) and financial capacity (OR = 2.11; CI90% = 1.03-4.31). All patients complied with the PRP showed significant improvement in the six-minute walking test and quality of life. The results warn about low compliance and their relationship with socioeconomic variables.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>adherence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>compliance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>respiratory rehabilitation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>COPD</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a un programa interdisciplinario de rehabilitación respiratoria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Adherence to interdisciplinary Pulmonary Rehabilitation Program].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
