<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24746311</identifier>
<setSpec>1087-2108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Pugnaire, Ma Antonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porriño-Bustamante, Ma Librada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aneiros-Fernández, Jose</dc:author>
<dc:author>Naranjo-Sintes, Ramon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanchez-Lopez, Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sarcoidosis is a multisystem inflammatory disease characterized by the formation of noncaseating granulomas in various organs and tissues. The majority of patients with systemic sarcoidosis will present with lung and lymph node involvement. In addition, 20% have skin involvement that may be the only manifestation of the disease or may be an important prognostic marker for involvement of other organs. There are multiple forms of presentation of cutaneous sarcoidosis, which may be a true challenge.We report a patient with a one month history of an eruption of skin colored papules. Some were grouped in a symmetrical distribution on the trunk, inner arms, and lumbar region. Pathologic examination revealed an infiltrate in the papillary dermis showing a band of noncaseating granulomas along with disruption of the basal lamina and lichenoid changes. The clinicopathological correlation confirmed the diagnosis of lichenoid sarcoidosis. We consider our case interesting owing to the clinical presentation and the lichenoid distribution of granulomas.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Apr 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de un caso de sarcoidosis liquenoide con hallazgos clínicos e histopatológicos característicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A case of lichenoid sarcoidosis with characteristic clinical and histopathological findings].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Dermatology online journal</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
