<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24747025</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Antón, Ane</dc:author>
<dc:author>Altube, Lander</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salinas, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguirre, Urko</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ballaz, Aitor</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of tuberculosis infection in undocumented immigrant teenagers using a tuberculin skin test (TST) for initial screening and QuantiFERON(®)-TB Gold In-Tube (QFT-GIT) as a confirmatory test. PATIENT AND METHOD From 2007 to 2012, under 19 year-old immigrant teenagers from 2 accommodation centers of the Basque Country (Spain) were included in the study. The TST was done in all of them and the QFT-GIT was done in selected patients with a TST≥5mm. RESULTS Eight hundred and forty-five immigrants were included, most of them from Africa (99.5%). Fifty-one percent of immigrants with TST ≥ 5 mm has a positive QFT-GIT. We found 2 cases of active tuberculosis (2/845: 0.24%). The concordance between TST (≥ 10 mm) and QFT-GIT was 63%, with 57% of positive concordance cases and 96% of negative concordances. There were 246 cases with TST ≥ 10 mm (29%), with significant differences between Magrebis (21.5%) and Subsaharians (67%) (P&lt;.001). Vaccination with Calmette-Guéin bacille was an independent predictor for having a TST ≥ 10 mm (OR: 2.11; P&lt;.001) and for the discordance TST+/QFT-GIT-, both for a TST≥5 and a TST≥10mm (OR 2.16, 95% confidence interval [95% CI] 1.46-3.20, and OR 1.91 95% CI 1.23-2.97, respectively). The positive value of QFT-GIT increased significantly as the TST increased, with a positive association in all the cut-off points analyzed: 10-14 mm (OR 7.95, 95% CI 1.79-35.33), 15-19 mm (OR 35, 95% CI 7.93-154.52) and ≥ 20 mm (OR 91.3, 95% CI 18.20-458.11). CONCLUSION Due to the high prevalence of latent tuberculosis infection in Subsaharian immigrants, we recommend implementing screening programs in this population. Using QFT-GIT, the number of candidates for chemoprophylaxis was reduced to 43% compared with TST alone (≥ 10 mm).</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Inmigrantes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculin skin test</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prueba de la tuberculina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adolescentes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>QuantiFERON(®) Gold In-Tube</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Teenagers</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immigrants</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado de la tuberculosis en inmigrantes adolescentes indocumentados usando el QuantiFERON(®)-TB Gold In-Tube.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tuberculosis screening program for undocumented immigrant teenagers using the QuantiFERON(®)-TB Gold In-Tube test].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
