<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24779268</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Bueno, José Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porias-Cuéllar, Hans L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sandoval-Huerta, Gabriel Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Gamboa, Mireya</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz-Plata, Alma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar-López-Ortiz, Carlos Gerardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vital-Reyes, Victor Saúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tapia-Serrano, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rembao-Bojórquez, J Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Bárcena, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-Castillo, Gumersindo Gaspar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Hyperprolactinemia is a common finding within clinical practice in both endocrinology and general practice fields, amongst other specialties. The general practitioner and other specialists must know the indications and serum prolactin determination parameters in order to, once detected, derive the patient for a correct assessment and begin treatment. OBJECTIVE Formulate a clinical practice guideline evidence-based for the diagnosis and treatment of hyperprolactinemia. METHOD It took the participation of eight gynecologists, two pathologists and a pharmacologist in the elaboration of this guideline due their experience and clinical judgement. These recommendations were based upon diagnostic criteria and levels of evidence from treatment guidelines previously established, controlled clinical trials and standardized guides for adolescent and adult population with hyperprolactinemia. RESULTS During the conformation of this guideline each specialist reviewed and updated a specific topic and established the evidence existent over different topics according their field of best clinical expertise, being enriched by the opinion of other experts. At the end, all the evidence and decisions taken were unified in the document presented here. CONCLUSIONS It is presented the recommendations established by the panel of experts for diagnosis and treatment of patients with high levels of prolactin; also the level of evidence for the diagnosis of hyperprolactinemia, handling drug-induced hyperprolactinemia and prolactinomas in pregnant and non-pregnant patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de práctica clínica para el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la hiperprolactinemia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical practice guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of hyperprolactinemia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
