<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24779275</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ortiz-Villalobos, Roberto Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Gómez, Israel Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna-Covarrubias, Edith Esmeralda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bañuelos-Franco, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano-Enríquez, Raymundo Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acretismo is a condition of abnormal placentation, in which the villi invade the myometrium at the implantation site, Representing a risk of massive obstetric hemorrhage with possible alterations of the coagulation, besides to the damage to other organs. Moving forward even to his death, so it is a challenge for the obstetric services, to make a correct diagnosis and in a timely manner, along with the programming of the interruption of pregnancy, as well as the utilization of proper surgical techniques and the involvement of a multidisciplinary team to the possible complications. The following describes a surgical technique modified for patients with a diagnosis of acretismo placentario, used in the Hospital General de Occidente in Jalisco, Mexico from 1 year ago, presenting two clinical cases of patients who underwent surgery with this technique, considering it necessary to present up to the moment a significant decrease in the amount of bleeding, zero days stay of patients in intensive care, any complications in the mother as well as in the product, and more importantly, it has remained at the hospital with no maternal death by this pathology in the last year, considering the nature of being a referral hospital for the whole entity by the Servicios de Salud Jalisco. It is necessary to consider the risks/benefits in the short, medium and long term for the institution, the mother and the product, allowing present good practices that will impinge on the permanent reduction of the maternal death by this pathology.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modificación de la histerectomía obstétrica en acretismo placentario.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Modification of the obstetric hysterectomy in placental acretism].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
