<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24787686</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Brito-Zerón, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos-Casals, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Retamozo, Soledad</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cryoglobulinemia is a heterogeneous systemic autoimmune disease with a wide variety of causes, symptoms and outcomes, and different etiopathogenic pathways involved in the vasculitic organ damage. The discovery of the hepatitis C virus (HCV) in 1989 changed radically the focus of research of the so-called "essential" cryoglobulinemia. Cryoglobulins can be detected in 25-30% of patients with HCV, overwhelmingly representing mixed cryoglobulins. However, only 10-15% of patients present with cryoglobulinemic vasculitis, with a broad spectrum of symptoms including mild or life-threatening manifestations. Consequently, not all patients can be uniformly treated. The key therapeutic points in HCV+ patients with cryoglobulinemic vasculitis cover different aspects. The first is to treat the underlying cause of cryoglobulinemia whenever possible, hence the use of antiviral therapies must always be considered in these patients. An individualized diagnostic approach to assess the number of organs involved and the severity of organ involvement is also essential in the therapeutic planning. This complex clinical scenario leads to an equally complex therapeutic scenario. There are three main treatment strategies for HCV-associated cryoglobulinemic vasculitis: conventional immunosuppression, antiviral treatment and biological therapies. The most recent studies are suggesting a change from the classical therapeutic approach (monotherapeutic regimens) to combination/sequential regimens, including treatments targeting the virus and those directed against the induced autoimmune disease, with the aim of blocking the various etiopathogenic pathways involved.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Treatment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virus hepatitis C</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatitis C virus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cryoglobulinemic vasculitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vasculitis crioglobulinémica</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 May 08 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la vasculitis crioglobulinémica asociada a infección por el virus de la hepatitis C.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of cryoglobulinemic vasculitis associated with hepatitis C virus infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
