<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24798565</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marín, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcázar, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luño, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quereda, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gorostidi, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Fresnedo, Gema</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Castelao, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santamaría, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goicoechea, Marián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliveras, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aranda, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orte, Luis M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segura, Julián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Pérez, José C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portolés, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Pino, M Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Francisco, Angel L M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Vega, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galcerán, Josep M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Górriz, José L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruilope, Luis M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The new Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) international guidelines on chronic kidney disease (CKD) and the management of blood pressure (BP) in CKD patients are an update of the corresponding 2002 and 2004 KDOQI (Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative) guidelines. The documents aim to provide updated guidelines on the assessment, management and treatment of patients with CKD. The first guidelines retain the 2002 definition of CKD but present an improved prognosis classification. Furthermore, concepts about prognosis of CKD, recommendations for management of patients, and criteria for referral to the nephrologist have been updated. The second guideline retains the &lt;130/80 mm Hg-goal for management of BP in patients with CKD presenting increased albuminuria or proteinuria (albumin-to-creatinine ratio 30-300 mg/g, and &gt;300 mg/g, respectively) but recommends a less-strict goal of &lt;140/90 mm Hg in patients with normoalbuminuria. The development of the guidelines followed a predetermined process in which the evidence available was reviewed and assessed. Recommendations on management and treatment are based on the systematic review of relevant studies. The GRADE system (Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development and Evaluation) was used to assess the quality of evidence and issue the grade of recommendation. Areas of uncertainty are also discussed for the different aspects addressed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 May 21 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Society of Nephrology document on KDIGO guidelines for the assessment and treatment of chronic kidney disease.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
