<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2481374</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Belloni, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mon, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basualdo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castelletto, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jmelnitzky, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rondina, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Data provided by 51 voluntary blood donors identified as asymptomatic HBsAg carriers five to ten years (mean = 7.5 years) before their inclusion in the study are analysed towards their long-term evolution. HBsAg clearance was estimated 2.5% yearly and 83.9% of those remaining positive showed the classical non-replicative serological pattern; another 12.9% were negative for both HBeAg-Anti HBe (seroconversion window?), one of them presenting raised ASAT-ALAT levels and enhanced histological activity (lobular chronic hepatitis). Neither alpha-fetoprotein seric levels (RIA) nor liver ultrasonography demonstrated hepatocellular carcinoma suspicion signs in 35 HBsAg positive cases to this methods; ASAT-ALAT levels raised over two fold the normal superior limit in only 11.4%, and neither aggressive chronic liver disease nor hepatocyte dysplasia was showed in 17 biopsied cases (70.6% normal; 23.6% chronic reactive or chronic persistent hepatitis; 5.8% chronic lobular hepatitis). One out of five patients biopsied with a seven years interval showed histologic worsening.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución alejada en portadores asintomáticos HBsAg (PA-HBsAg) en un area de baja prevalencia de hepatocarcinoma.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Long-term course in asymptomatic carriers of HBsAg in an area of low prevalence of hepatocarcinoma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta gastroenterologica Latinoamericana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
