<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24862804</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>De Cunto, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, Camila</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eymann, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The treatment of chronic diseases usually requires a multidisciplinary professional training.There are comprehensive accommodations that are adapted to the needs of the families that have to stay away from home for long periods. OBJECTIVES To assess the impact of a comprehensive accommodation on the health-related quality of life of children with chronic conditions seen at a hospital of the City of Buenos Aires compared to children lodged at a traditional accommodation and to healthy children. To analyze the agreement between children's and caregivers' opinions. Metfeods.Cross-sectional, observational study. Group 1: children with chronic conditions lodged at a comprehensive accommodation. Group 2: children with chronic conditions lodged at a traditional accommodation. Group 3: healthy children. The Argentine version of the Kidscreen-52 questionnaire was used. A value of p &lt; 0.05, the effect size (ES) &gt; 0.20, and the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) &gt; 0.60 were considered significant. RESULTS Two hundred and fifty children/caregiver dyads (50 in each chronic group and 150 healthy controls). Mean age: 12.6 years old (range: 8-18 years old), 56% were males. The children in Group 1 showed better moods and emotions, a better relationship with parents and peers, and a better school environment than those in Group 2 (p &lt; 0.05, ES &gt; 0.20). Agreement between children's and caregivers' opinion was low, especially in relation to psychosocial dimensions (ICC &lt; 0.29). CONCLUSIONS In spite of their uprooting, children with chronic conditions are capable of maintaining a good relationship with their parents, a good peer bond and social support, and do not need discontinue their education while lodged at a comprehensive accommodation adapted to their needs during their stay in the City of Buenos Aires.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-related quality of life in children with chronic conditions lodged at a comprehensive accommodation in the City of Buenos Aires.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
