<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24866317</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bojórquez-Ramos, María del Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is currently the most common cause of liver disease in children and adolescents in the United States of America (USA) and probably in the entire western hemisphere, due to the increase in the prevalence of overweight and obesity. Steatosis can progress to inflammation, fibrosis and even cirrhosis, which increases the morbidity and mortality associated to liver disease. In every overweight and obese child a thorough analysis should be performed including liver function tests and liver ultrasound, in order to establish a timely diagnosis. The liver biopsy is the most specific study to rule out other potentially treatable entities. It is necessary to count on non-invasive methods to detect children with NAFLD and identify those in risk of progression. Biomarkers related to inflammation, oxidative stress, apoptosis and fibrosis have been reported. The main goal of the treatment is to modify the life style, starting with a healthy diet and an increase of physical activity. Regarding pharmacological treatment, there is evidence of histological improvement with vitamin E use, as opposed to metformin, but more conclusive studies regarding this subject are needed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Childhood obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fatty liver</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad por hígado graso no alcohólico en pediatría.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La enfermedad por hígado graso no alcohólico (EHGNA) es actualmente la primera causa de enfermedad hepática en niños y adolescentes en Estados Unidos de América (EUA) y probablemente en el mundo occidental, dado el incremento en la prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad. La esteatosis hepática puede progresar a inflamación, fibrosis y cirrosis que incrementa la morbilidad y mortalidad asociadas a enfermedad hepática. En todo niño con sobrepeso y obesidad se requiere un escrutinio mediante determinación de transaminasas y ultrasonido hepático para un diagnóstico oportuno. La biopsia hepática es el estudio con mayor discriminación para descartar otras entidades potencialmente tratables. Es necesario contar con métodos no invasivos para detectar niños con EHGNA e identificar a aquellos con riesgo de progresión. Se han reportado biomarcadores de inflamación, estrés oxidativo, apoptosis y fibrosis. El tratamiento tiene como objetivo la modificación del estilo de vida con dieta saludable y mayor actividad física. Respecto a tratamiento farmacológico, hay evidencias de mejoría histológica con vitamina E, y no se presenta ningún beneficio con Metformin, pero se requieren más estudios con resultados más sólidos. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
