<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24878081</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Santibáñez-Velázquez, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvirde-Gutiérrez, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Montoya, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To know the survival rate in patients with RIFLE I and II stages on acute renal failure, treated with supportive care or continuous renal replacement therapy with PRISMA machine, at an intensive care unit. METHODS There were included patients of both sexes, aged 16 to 69 years, with acute renal failure in RIFLE I and II stages and score of scale APACHE II lower than 36 points. The sample studied was divided in two groups: a group was treated with supportive care, and the other group received continuous renal replacement therapy via PRISMA machine. We compared mortality between both groups and the association with the RIFLE stages with Pearson's chi-squared test. RESULTS The average score of the scale APACHE I was 14 points, and the probability of death was 15 %. The patients with acute renal failure RIFLE I were 54.5 % and RIFLE II 45.5 %, with mortality of 30.4 % and 38.8 %, respectively. Patients in RIFLE I stage who received supportive care and continuous replacement therapy had non-statistical differences in mortality (p = 0.356). The mortality in patients with acute renal failure in RIFLE II stage treated with continuous replacement therapy was higher (p = 0.000). CONCLUSIONS Because of its accessibility and lower mortality, supportive care should be the initial procedure in patients with acute renal failure in RIFLE I and II stages.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Acute kidney injury</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Renal replacement therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>APACHE</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia en insuficiencia renal aguda tratada en forma convencional o con reemplazo continuo.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             conocer la supervivencia en pacientes con insuficiencia renal aguda estadios RIFLE I y II que recibieron terapia convencional, en comparación con los que recibieron terapia de reemplazo renal continuo (TRRC) mediante equipo PRISMA, en una unidad de cuidados intensivos. MÉTODOS: se incluyeron pacientes de uno u otro sexo, con edad entre 16 y 69 años, insuficiencia renal aguda en estadios RIFLE I y II y puntuación en la escala APACHE II inferior a 36 puntos. Un grupo recibió terapia convencional y otro, TRRC con equipo PRISMA. Se comparó la frecuencia de la mortalidad en ambos grupos con chi cuadrada de Pearson. La asociación con el estadio RIFLE se obtuvo mediante la razón de momios. 
             la puntuación promedio en la escala APACHE II fue de 14 puntos, que establece una probabilidad pronóstica de mortalidad de 15 %. Los pacientes con insuficiencia renal aguda estadio RIFLE I representaron 54.5 % y aquellos con estadio RIFLE II, 45.5 %; la mortalidad en esos grupos fue de 30.4 y 38.8 %, respectivamente. No se encontró diferencia estadísticamente significativa en el estadio RIFLE I al comparar la mortalidad según el tipo de tratamiento (p = 0.356). La mortalidad fue mayor en los pacientes en estadio RIFLE II que recibieron TRRC (p = 0.000). 
             por su accesibilidad y menor mortalidad, el manejo convencional debe seguir siendo el tratamiento inicial de elección en los pacientes con insuficiencia renal aguda en estadios RIFLE I y II. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Survival in acute renal failure with conventional therapy or continuous replacement therapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
