<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24878092</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romo-Martínez, Jesús Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarreal-Hernández, Liliana del Sagrario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Suffering a non communicable chronic disease in combination with low educational level and low economic income develops a synergy, which contributes to a poor prognostic about the expectancy of life. A better educational level may improve the life expectancy. The objective of this research was to explore this relation. METHODS A retrospective cohort study from January 1, 1999, to December 31, 2011, was performed. We included 2306 patients obtained from the information system in mortality of Family Medicine Unit 3 of the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social in Guadalajara, Jalisco. The main measures were average age-at-death and educational level. We used Student's t, chi-squared test and relative risk (RR) calculations for statistical analysis. RESULTS The average age-at-death for those who had a low educational level (n = 1936) was 73.24 ± 12.18 years, while for those who had a satisfactory level of education (n = 370) was 63.47 ± 14.51 years, estimating a mean difference of 9.77 years with p &lt; 0.001. Having a low educational level and not reaching life expectancy compared to the satisfactory level meant a RR = 0.24 (IC 95 % = 0.19, 0.30). The projected linear regression for each educational grade showed that patients lost 2.5 years of life. CONCLUSIONS Diabetes accompanied by a low educational level showed a double probability of not reaching the expectation of life.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educación y expectativa de vida en pacientes con enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             INTRODUCCIÓN: una enfermedad crónica no transmisible, el nivel educativo bajo y los bajos ingresos económicos pueden hacer sinergia y contribuir a un mal pronóstico en cuanto a la expectativa de vida esperada. Se estima que alcanzar un mejor nivel de educación hace posible que mejore la expectativa de vida. El objetivo de esta investigación fue explorar esta relación. MÉTODOS: estudio de cohorte retrospectivo realizado del 1 de enero de 1999 al 31 de diciembre de 2011, de individuos que fallecieron por enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles. Se incluyeron 2306 pacientes registrados en el Sistema de Información en Mortalidad de la Unidad de Medicina Familiar 3, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, en Guadalajara, Jalisco. Se registró la edad al momento de la muerte y el nivel educativo. Las pruebas estadísticas aplicadas fueron t de Student y 2. Se calculó el riesgo relativo. 
             la edad promedio al morir en quienes tuvieron un bajo nivel educativo fue de 73.24 ± 12.18 años y en quienes tuvieron un nivel educativo satisfactorio fue de 63.47 ±14.51 años; la diferencia de medias fue de 9.77 años (p &lt; 0.001). Tener un bajo nivel educativo y no alcanzar la expectativa de vida mostró un RR = 0.24 (IC 95 % = 0.19, 0.30). Por cada grado escolar alcanzado, los pacientes perdieron 2.5 años de vida. La diabetes mostró un RR = 2.02 (IC 95 % = 1.65, 2.40), ajustado por bajo nivel educativo y sexo. 
             padecer diabetes en combinación con bajo nivel educativo mostró una doble probabilidad de no lograr la expectativa de vida esperada. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Educational status and life expectancy in patients with chronic non-communicable diseases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
