<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24877615</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Kiza, A H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lobete Prieto, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey Galán, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare infant pain knowledge between a group of nurses who work in a pediatric hospital and one that works in a general hospital. MATERIAL AND METHODS Descriptive study based on the use of a validated questionnaire for assessing the knowledge and attitudes of nurses about pediatric pain (Pediatric Nurses' Knowledge and Attitude Survey Regarding Pain [PNKAS]). PNKAS questionnaire was distributed to the nursing staff of a pediatric hospital and a general hospital and the results were compared. RESULTS The average score obtained in the pediatric vs. the general hospital was: mean, 51.7% vs. 47.2%, 95% confidence interval, 47.5 to 56% vs. 43.6 to 50.8% (P=.098). CONCLUSIONS There were no differences between the scores in the PNKAS questionnaire between nurses working exclusively with children and nurses working with general population. Training on pediatric pain needs to be improved in nurses caring for sick children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Analgesia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nursing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dolor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermería</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de los conocimientos sobre dolor infantil en 2 poblaciones de profesionales de enfermería.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison between 2 groups of nursing professionals on the knowledge of pediatric pain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
