<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24878096</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Pérez, Francisco Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Henry, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The incidence of milking phenomenon is between 0.6 and 4 % in angiographic series; however, autopsy studies raise the incidence of myocardial bridges up to 85 %. This malformation goes unnoticed in most cases but can have a big impact on personal and professional level. The objective was to present an example of milking phenomenon with disability and professional consequences. CLINICAL CASE Male, 44 years old, bricklayer and farmhand laborer. He referred tonsillectomy and osteoarthritis and being a smoker of 10 cigarettes per day, drinking 2-3 cups of coffee daily and 2-3 glasses of wine at the weekends. The primary care physician referred him to cardiologist with suspicion of arrhythmia. The cardiology service report mentioned electrocardiogram at sinusal rhythm, 90 beats per minute and incomplete right bundle-branch block. At ergonomics test, in the first stage of Bruce protocol, the patient's development of hypertensive crisis suggested a milking phenomenon. Finally, the diagnosis was established by angiographic studies with left common branch, circumflex coronary artery, right coronary artery and anterior descendent artery, without evidence of pathology but it was seen systolic compression on the medial segment. The case was concluded by the disability assessment team, recognizing a total permanent disability with limitations for activities requiring moderate physical efforts. CONCLUSIONS The milking phenomenon diagnosis that could be related with ischemic heart disease is by angiography. Finally, the patient ended with total permanent disability.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Myocardial bridge</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Disability insurance</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Limitaciones orgánicas y funcionales por el fenómeno de milking. Informe de un caso clinic.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             INTRODUCCIÓN: según series angiográficas, la incidencia del fenómeno de milking oscila entre 0.6 y 4 %, sin embargo, en estudios de autopsias hasta en 85 % se ha identificado puente miocárdico, patognómónico de este trastorno. La malformación del fenómeno de milking no es identificada en la mayoría de las ocasiones, pero puede tener grandes repercusiones. El propósito es ejemplificar un caso de fenómeno de milking con consecuencias de incapacidad permanente y consecuencias laborales. CASO CLÍNICO: hombre de 44 años de edad que laboralmente se ocupaba como peón albañil y peón agrícola. Como antecedentes refirió amigdalectomía y artrosis, tabaquismo de 10 cigarrillos diarios, dos o tres tazas de café diarias y dos o tres copas de vino en fin de semana. Mediante electrocardiograma se identificó ritmo sinusal y bloqueo incompleto de la rama derecha del fascículo atrioventricular. Su frecuencia cardiaca fue de 90 latidos por minuto. Para la prueba de esfuerzo se utilizó el protocolo de Bruce, que se detuvo en el primer estadio debido a crisis hipertensiva y fibrilación auricular paroxística. El cateterismo mostró tronco común izquierdo, arteria coronaria cincunfleja y arteria coronaria derecha sin lesiones, arteria descendente anterior sin lesiones con trayecto intramiocárdico y compresión sistólica en segmento medio, con lo cual se integró el diagnóstico de milking coronario. El paciente requirió incapacidad permanente total con limitación para actividades que necesitaran esfuerzo moderado. 
             el diagnóstico del fenómeno de milking es angiográfico. Este trastorno puede estar relacionado con cardiopatía isquémica aguda. Este caso terminó con incapacidad permanente laboral. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Organic and functional limitations due to milking phenomenon: a clinical case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
