<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24878218</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torres-Olalde, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojano-Rodríguez, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valenzuela-Salazar, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas-Lailson, L E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Loera, L S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Portillo, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Human obesity is associated with a proinflammatory state and an elevated level of mediators, such as C-reactive protein (CRP). OBJECTIVES To establish CRP levels as baseline preoperative values and then at 6 months after bariatric surgery, as well as to determine the changes in weight, body mass index (BMI), leukocytes, and glycemia. MATERIALS AND METHODS An observational, analytical, retrospective, longitudinal, and open study was conducted. Serum CRP values were measured in 36 adults presenting with morbid obesity, and their baseline relation to weight, BMI, leukocytes, and glycemia was determined; the relation to the same parameters was established again, 6 months after bariatric surgery. RESULTS The mean and standard deviation of preoperative and postoperative CRP (mg/L) was 1.15±0.86 and 0.34±0.28, respectively with p&lt;0.0001; weight (kg) 112.10±22.91 and 84.82±17.11, p=0.0443; BMI (kg/m(2)) 42.48±5.97 and 32.2±4.79, p=0.0988; glucose (mg/dL) 100.58±17.82 and 87.11±8.49, p&lt;0.0001, and leukocytes (× 10(3)/mm(3)) 8.62±1.69 and 6.99±1.56, p=0.3192. Baseline CRP only correlated with weight and BMI (p=0.047 and p=0.027 respectively) and there was no correlation between postoperative CRP and the evaluated parameters. CONCLUSIONS Preoperative CRP had a significant lineal relation to weight and body mass index. Patients who underwent bariatric surgery had a significant decrease in CRP, weight, and fasting glucose at 6 months after surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Obesidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>C-reactive protein</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía bariátrica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bariatric surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Proteína C reactiva</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">C-reactive protein level in morbidly obese patients before and after bariatric surgery.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
