<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2491581</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Climent, G I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Medical knowledge that can be used in everyday life is easily learned; therefore, the educational activities about care of pregnancy, puerperium and the newborn are important. In a study about appropriate technologies in obstetrics it was investigated to what extent the surveyed women had followed psychoprophylactic courses and had received information at the time of discharge after admission for delivery. Only 47% had followed a psychoprophylactic course and 54-71% had received information before discharge; the rates were smaller in those women receiving attention at public institutions. This group started the surveillance of pregnancy later (27% after the fourth month); it was also in this group where the least proportion of women always cared for by the same physician during pregnancy (60%) and delivery (26%) was found. It was this group, therefore, that had the least opportunity to create an adequate relation with the physician and to receive educational care. This is a matter for consideration about the modalities of attention and underlying purposes of educational activities, which seem to be directed in a greater proportion to the groups with higher socioeconomic status.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acciones educativas: artículos de consumo o medidas preventivas?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Educational actions: consumer articles or preventive measures?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
