<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24915617</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Del Rivero-Hernández, Leonel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gaspar-López, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Mireles, Karen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Segura-Méndez, Nora</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Rocha, Eunice</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Sensitization to mites and cockroach are a common cause of respiratory allergy, especially in children. There is little information about its cross-reactivity with shrimp, which is common in adult patients. OBJECTIVES To determine the frequency of sensitization to house dust mites (Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus, Dermatophagoides farinae) and cockroach species Periplaneta americana, in adult patients attending to a third level hospital and to determine the frequency of sensitization to shrimp in patients with positive skin test to house dust mite and/or cockroach, in patients with clinical manifestations suggestive of allergy to shrimp. MATERIAL AND METHOD A retrospective study was done in which results were reviewed of 672 patients clinical records, attending to the Allergy and Clinical Immunology department in a third level hospital, those patients with positive skin test results to Dermatophagoides and/or Periplaneta americana were investigated for sensitization to shrimp through Prick-to-Prick test. RESULTS Data from 672 patients were obtained, 69.8% (469) males, with a mean age of 33.5 years. Dermatophagoides positivity was 72.2% (486/672), and its relationship with other invertebrates that also have tropomyosin was 5.6% (4.9% with cockroach and 0.74% with shrimp). CONCLUSIONS In our population, house dust mite sensitization was similar to that reported in the international literature. There was low positivity to cockroach, probably due to geographical conditions. There is very little information about shrimp's cross-reactivity with Dermatophagoides, despite its clinical significance, which requires more specific studies such as measurement of specific IgE to tropomyosin.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cockroach</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Respiratory allergy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mites</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sensitization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Shrimp</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de sensibilización a ácaros, cucaracha y camarón en adultos con alergia respiratoria.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             la sensibilización a ácaros y cucarachas es una causa común de alergia respiratoria, especialmente en los niños. Existe poca información de la reactividad cruzada con camarón, común en pacientes adultos. 
             determinar la frecuencia de sensibilización a ácaros (Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus, Dermatophagoides farinae) y cucarachas especie Periplaneta americana en pacientes adultos atendidos en un hospital de tercer nivel y determinar la frecuencia de sensibilización a camarón en pacientes con pruebas cutáneas positivas a ácaros, cucarachas o ambos en pacientes con manifestaciones clínicas sugerentes de alergia a camarón. MATERIAL Y MÉTODO: estudio retrospectivo en el que se revisaron los resultados de las pruebas cutáneas en 672 expedientes de pacientes atendidos en el servicio de Alergia e Inmunología Clínica de un hospital de tercer nivel; en los pacientes con pruebas cutáneas positivas a Dermatophagoides, Periplaneta americana, o ambos se investigó si tenían sensibilización a camarón por medio de Prick-to-Prick. 
             se obtuvieron los datos de 672 pacientes, 69.8% (469) eran del sexo masculino, la edad media fue de 33.5 años. La positividad para Dermatophagoides fue de 72.2% (486/672) y la relación de positividad con otros invertebrados que también tienen tropomiosina fue de 5.6% (4.9% con cucaracha y 0.74% con camarón). 
             en nuestra población, la sensibilización a ácaros fue similar a lo reportado en la bibliografía internacional. Existe baja positividad a cucaracha, probablemente debido a las condiciones geográficas. Existe poca información de la reactividad cruzada de camarón con Dermatophagoides, a pesar de la importancia clínica, por lo que se requieren estudios más específicos como la medición de IgE específica a tropomiosina. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Frequency of sensitization to mites, cockroach and shrimp in adults with respiratory allergy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
