<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24967863</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gatica, Valeska Fabiola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manterola, Carlos Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán, Eduardo Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Irene Velásquez, Sofía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Méndez, Guillermo Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Physical disability is the most common disability (10.3 %) in the central area of Chile. The cerebral palsy is one of the diseases that generates motor deficits and loss of balance. Balance is crucial for maintaining postural stability. OBJECTIVE To establish the differences in area and average velocity of the center of pressure between typically developing children and cerebral palsy patients, and to determine the degree of use of different sensory systems. MATERIALS AND METHODS This was a cross-sectional study. A convenience sample was divided into two groups: typically developing children (n=7) and cerebral palsy patients (n=7). The parameters measured by a force plate were the area and average velocity of excursion of the center of pressure, as well as the frequency bands ( 0.0625, 0.125, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 Hz) . RESULTS During the eyes open condition, the cerebral palsy subject had an average velocity of the center of pressure significantly higher than the typically developing children group (p=0.043). The frequency bands 0.25 Hz and 0.5 Hz related to the vestibular system showed significant differences between groups (p=0.021 y p=0.036). In the eyes closed phase a significant increase in the area of the center of pressure and a higher use of the otolithic vestibular system were observed in the cerebral palsy group. CONCLUSIONS Cerebral palsy patients showed a lower standing balance in addition to using the vestibular system significantly more both in eyes open and eyes closed phases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en el balance de pie en pacientes con parálisis cerebral y niños con desarrollo típico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Differences in standing balance in patients with cerebral palsy and typically developing children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
