<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>24967928</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cuéllar, Adriana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pavía, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, John M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llano, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flórez, Astrid Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puerta, Concepción</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The diagnosis of Chagas' disease is essential to provide early treatment and improve patients' prognosis . The discriminatory efficiency of the serological tests varies according to the disease prevalence and the test- antigen used . OBJECTIVE To evaluate the discriminatory efficiency of the commercial kit Chagas ( Trypanosoma cruzi ) IgG-ELISA ® (Nova Tec Immunodiagnostica GmbBH) in a group of Colombian individuals, using indirect immunofluorescence antibody testing (IFAT) and enzyme immunoassay (ELISA) tests as references. MATERIALS AND METHODS Seventy-eight samples from chronic chagasic patients (36 asymptomatic and 42 symptomatic) and 21 healthy controls were included. Seventeen samples from non-infected people with Chagas' disease epidemiological risk, seven with leishmaniasis and nine with non-chagasic cardiomyopathy were also analyzed. Real time PCR was performed on four individuals whose results differed among tests. RESULTS Significant differences at 450 nm optical absorbance were found (p&lt;0.0001) when the median absorbance values of healthy controls (0.143), asymptomatic (2.401) and symptomatic (2.776) chagasic patients were compared, as well as when asymptomatic and symptomatic patients (p=0.0408) and seronegative people with epidemiological risk (0.232), cardiomyopathy (0.367) or leishmaniasis (0.337) were compared with chagasic patients (p&lt;0.0001). Finally, there were differences among healthy controls and non-infected people with epidemiological risk (p=0.0264), patients with non-chagasic cardiomyopathy (p=0.0015) and patients with leishmaniasis (p=0.002). Real-time PCR was positive in three out of four analyzed cases. CONCLUSIONS The commercial ELISA test allowed us to discriminate the chagasic patients from the controls. A phase II study of diagnostic tests for determining field reliability of this test is required.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación preliminar de la prueba comercial Chagas ( Trypanosoma cruzi ) IgG-ELISA ® en individuos colombianos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Preliminary evaluation of the commercial kit Chagas ( Trypanosoma cruzi ) IgG-ELISA ® in Colombian individuals].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
