<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25011590</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Santillan, Graciela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calabro, Arnoldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrero, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albarracín, Silvina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Araya, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crowley, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Talmón, Gabriel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uchiumi, Leonardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sepúlveda, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arezo, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Volpe, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salvitti, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Seleiman, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mujica, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labanchi, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grizmado, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrieu, Edmundo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Avila, Agustín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic echinococcosis (CE) is an endemic disease in the province of Río Negro, Argentina. The control program against CE has developed monitoring surveillance systems. Currently, the coproELISA/Western blot (WB) test is used to determine transmission in livestock farms (epidemiological units or EU) from collected dry field-dispersed dog feces. The objective was to evaluate the prevalence of CE on livestock farms and its relationship with CE cases in children aged 0-14 years. Canine fecal samples were obtained from randomly selected livestock farms and processed by the coproELISA/WB test. Furthermore, new cases in children in the same age group mentioned above were identified. In 278 EU, 571 samples of canine feces were obtained. There were 37 positive samples for coproELISA/WB (6.5%) and the presence of transmission was demonstrated in 37 EU (13.3%). There were no significant differences (p=0.9) with the survey conducted in the period 2003-2004 while there were significant differences (p=0.02) with the EU survey of native populations conducted in 2009-2010. With respect to animal density in the work area, the EU yielding negative results had an average of 2 dogs (SD 2.1) per EU while in the EU having positive results the average was 3 dogs (SD 4.2), showing statistically significant differences (p=0.02). In children under 15 years of age, 12 cases were diagnosed. This study has identified, on average, that the cases of hydatid disease are closer in the positive fields than in the negative fields (p=0.00307).The coproELISA/WB test allowed to identify the dispersion of CE on livestock farms and its relationship with the occurrence of cases in children in 2009-2010.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Coproantígenos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Equinococosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Control</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Casos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surveillance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coproantigen</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vigilancia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Echinococcosis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigilancia de la equinococosis quística en perros y niños en la provincia de Río Negro, Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cystic echinococcosis in dogs and children in the province of Río Negro, Argentina].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
