<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25011594</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Soloaga, Rolando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ochiuzzi, María E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guelfand, Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maldonado, Ivana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arechavala, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this investigation was to evaluate the results of antifungal susceptibility for various Candida species using the Vitek 2 semi-automated system (AST-YSO1 cards, bioMérieux), and to compare them with those obtained by the CLSI (Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute) broth microdilution reference method (Document M27-A3,2008). The essential agreement (EA) was &gt; 90%, except for Candida glabrata against voriconazole (VCZ); and for Candida krusei against fluconazole (FCZ). The overall categorical agreement (CA) was &gt; 90% when FCZ was evaluated and 89.5% at 24h and 80.7% at 48 h for VCZ. The average time for obtaining results was 15.5h. Minor errors were 7.8% at 24h and 6.1% at 48 h for FCZ, and 10.5% at 24h and 19.3% at 48 h for VCZ. There was only one very major error for FCZ against Candida parapsilosis and no major errors were observed. For amphotericin B, only three isolates showed MICs ≥ 2 μg/ml. The Vitek 2 system detected the MIC value for various Candida species and showed excellent agreement with the reference method proposed by the CLSI.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Candida spp</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vitek 2 system</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sensibilidad a los antifúngicos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Susceptibility testing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vitek 2</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las tarjetas AST-YSO1 del sistema Vitek 2 para determinar la sensibilidad a antifúngicos de levaduras del género Candida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the VITEK 2 system (AST-YSO1 cards) for antifungal susceptibility testing against different Candida species].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
