<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25066492</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Salas-Cansado, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vivancos Mora, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo Esteban, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres González, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz Otero, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega-Casarrubios, M Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Escalonilla Escobar, C I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Torres, M P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto Álvarez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ximénez-Carrillo Rico, Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barriga Hernández, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Núñez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo Moreno, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casado Gómez, M Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Andrés-Nogales, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Stroke is the main cause of admission to Neurology departments and cardioembolic stroke (CS) is one of the most common subtypes of stroke. METHODS A multicentre prospective observational study was performed in 5 Neurology departments in public hospitals in the Region of Madrid (Spain). The objective was to estimate the use of healthcare resources and costs of acute CS management. Patients with acute CS at&lt;48h from onset were recruited. Patients' socio-demographic, clinical, and healthcare resource use data were collected during hospitalisation and at discharge up to 30 days after admission, including data for rehabilitation treatment after discharge. RESULTS During an 8-month recruitment period, 128 patients were recruited: mean age, 75.3±11.25; 46.9% women; mortality rate, 4.7%. All patients met the CS diagnostic criteria established by GEENCV-SEN, based on medical history or diagnostic tests. Fifty per cent of the patients had a history of atrial fibrillation and 18.8% presented other major cardioembolic sources. Non-valvular atrial fibrillation was the most frequent cause of CS (33.6%). Data for healthcare resource use, given a mean total hospital stay of 10.3±9.3 days, are as follows: rehabilitation therapy during hospital stay (46.9%, mean 4.5 days) and after discharge (56.3%, mean 26.8 days), complications (32%), specific interventions (19.5%), and laboratory and diagnostic tests (100%). Head CT (98.4%), duplex ultrasound of supra-aortic trunks (87.5%), and electrocardiogram (85.9%) were the most frequently performed diagnostic procedures. Average total cost per patient during acute-phase management and rehabilitation was €13,139. Hospital stay (45.0%) and rehabilitation at discharge (29.2%) accounted for the largest part of resources used. CONCLUSIONS Acute CS management in the Region of Madrid resulted consumes large amounts of resources (€13,139), mainly due to hospital stays and rehabilitation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Costs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infarto cerebral cardioembólico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spanish National Health System</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sanidad Pública</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comunidad de Madrid</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Region of Madrid (Spain)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardioembolic stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ictus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Costes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Utilización de recursos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resource use</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of healthcare resources and costs of acute cardioembolic stroke management in the Region of Madrid: The CODICE Study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
