<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25064517</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Padín, Juan M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almau Trenard, Héctor M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gondolesi, Gabriel E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Stringa, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moulin, Luis E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barros Schelotto, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Liver failure might be a cause of death after major hepatectomies. The ALPPS technique appears to be a promising strategy to avoid it, however no experimental studies supporting this procedure have been previously described. The aim was to develop an experimental model of ALPPS in rats. METHOD Experimental. A total of 30 Sprague Dawley rats were used. To develop the ALPPS procedure, ligation of the left portal branch of the middle lobe (LM) was performed. This demarcates the left side (SILM) from the right side (SDLM); parenchyma transection was performed following the demarcated line. The animal's weight, volume and weight of both LM were analyzed. Sacrifice at 3, 7 and 14 days after the procedure (10 per group) was performed. RESULTS No bleeding or ascites were observed during the postoperative period. The LM increased by 24.1, 86.9 and 120.4% at 3, 7 and 14 days. The SDLM increased by 34.4, 78.8 and 102.0% at 3, 7 and 14 days. The SILM decreased 42.6, 64.8, and 79.3% at day 3, 7 and 14 days respectively. CONCLUSION The ALPPS procedure can be performed in rats, achieving the expected results. Comparison studies to 2 staged hepatectomy will be necessary.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hepatectomía en 2 tiempos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ALPPS</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Two-stage hepatectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of an experimental model of portal vein ligation associated with parenchymal transection (ALPPS) in rats.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
