<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25074709</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Botet Mussons, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Astorquiza, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lailla Vicens, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iriondo Sanz, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueras Aloy, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Immersion in water during labor and delivery as an alternative to traditional delivery is a practice that has increased in many countries. This technique is effective in reducing pain and duration of labor. The American Academy of Pediatrics and The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists have published a clinical report which indicates the potential maternal benefits during the first stage of labor but, questions the performance of this technique during delivery and birth of the newborn. In this report, the Spanish Society of Neonatology and the Spanish Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology analyze the current scientific evidence on water immersion delivery, and the impact this practice could have in the mother and especially in the wellbeing of newborn.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Consensus Development Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Inmersión en agua</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Newborn</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Expulsivo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parto</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Delivery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immersion in water</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Labor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recién nacido</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención del parto en el agua. Consenso de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología y de la Sección de Medicina Perinatal de la Sociedad Española de Obstetricia y Ginecología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Underwater delivery. Consensus of the Spanish Neonatology Society and the Perinatal Section of the Spanish Obstetrics and Gynecology Society].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
