<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25109767</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mayor Arenal, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vidaurrázaga Díaz-Arcaya, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Bandera, A I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vorlicka, K</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz Bravo-Burguilllos, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero Vega, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Our aim was to describe the epidemiologic, clinical, and laboratory characteristics of acute parvovirus B19 infection in adults. MATERIAL AND METHODS This study describes all cases of acute parvovirus B19 infection in patients older than 18 years of age who were treated at Hospital Universitario La Paz in Madrid, Spain, in 2012. RESULTS Forty-nine adults were treated for acute parvovirus B19 infection. Most were young women who were infected in the spring or early summer. In over half the cases skin lesions were key diagnostic signs.We saw the full range of types of rash of purplish exanthems that were fairly generalized; vasculitis was relatively common (in &gt;18%). Mild or moderate abnormalities in blood counts and indicators of liver dysfunction resolved spontaneously in all but 2 immunocompromised patients, who developed chronic anemia. CONCLUSIONS This is the largest case series of acute parvovirus B19 infection published to date. This infection should be suspected on observing signs of purplish skin rashes, no matter the location or pattern of distribution, or vasculitis, especially if accompanied by fever and joint pain in young women in the spring. Measures to avoid infection should be recommended to individuals at risk.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Exantema</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adultos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vasculitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Exanthema</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parvovirus B19</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adults</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute parvovirus B19 infection in adults: a retrospective study of 49 cases.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
