<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25125066</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cruz-Castillo, Juan Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pacheco-Pittaluga, Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Enríquez-Vega, María Elizabeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solorio-Rosette, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Linarte-Márquez, Lizbeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iturburu-Enríquez, Alessandra</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Arthroscopy of the knee is a surgical performed world-wide considered extremely safe, rates of complication ranging from 0.56 to 8.2%. Vascular complications are even more rare (0.0032%), and generally related to the popliteal artery injury. CLINICAL CASE We are reporting the cases of two patients who had unsuspected vascular complications after arthroscopy. Both cases presented vascular injuries after elective knee arthroscopy. First case was a patient with thrombosed pseudoaneurysm in the popliteal artery and total section of the popliteal vein, unfortunately the diagnosis was done 72 hrs after knee arthroscopy and finally required amputation, the 2nd case presented popliteal arteriovenous fistula, the diagnosis was done 3 weeks after knee arthroscopy, the patient was successfully treated by resection of the fistula and direct repair of the artery and vein. CONCLUSIONS Although extremely infrequent, the vascular injury after knee arthroscopy should be remembered as a surgical complication, a low index of suspicion may have caused an unfortunate and untimely delay in diagnosis and treatment with potential risk of leg amputation and death.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>vascular injury</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>fístula arteriovenosa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>lesión vascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>amputación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>pseudoaneurysm</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>artroscopia de rodilla</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>arteriovenous fistula</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Knee arthroscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesión vascular, complicación de la cirugía artroscópica de rodilla. Reporte de dos casos y revisión de la bibliografía.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: la artroscopia de rodilla es uno de los procedimientos más seguros, con tasas de complicaciones que van de 0.56 a 8.2%. Las complicaciones vasculares son aún más raras (0.0032%) y generalmente se relacionan con lesiones en la arteria poplítea. Casos clínicos: reportamos los casos de dos pacientes con complicaciones no sospechadas de lesiones vasculares post artroscopia. Ambos casos tenían lesión vascular posterior a cirugía electiva de artroscopia de rodilla. El primer caso es el de un paciente con pseudoaneurisma trombosado de la arteria poplítea y sección completa de la vena poplítea, desafortunadamente el diagnóstico se estableció 72 horas después de la artroscopia de rodilla y requirió amputación. El segundo caso tenía una fistula arteriovenosa a nivel poplíteo y se trató exitosamente con desmantelamiento de la fístula y reparación directa de la arteria y la vena. Conclusiones: aunque es extremadamente infrecuente, la lesión vascular postartroscopia de rodilla debe tenerse en mente como una posible complicación postquirúrgica porque su bajo índice de sospecha puede causar una desafortunada e inoportuna demora en el diagnóstico y tratamiento, con un riesgo potencial de amputación de la extremidad y muerte. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Vascular injury as a complication of knee arthroscopic surgery. Report of two cases and review of the literature].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
