<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25123996</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz-Ruiz, Carlos E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Aristizábal, Liliana Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manrique-Hernández, Rubén D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Ascertaining factors associated with exclusive breastfeeding until the sixth month in teenage mothers included in SISBEN system levels I and II in the city of Medellin. METHODOLOGY This was a case-control study which included 323 teenage mothers, involving 197 cases and 126 controls for the "Buen comienzo había una vez -BCHV" (good start) strategy. Univariate analysis involved using descriptive statistics; a correspondence analysis was also made. Qualitative variables were compared using contingency tables and the Mann-Whitney U test was used for quantitative variables having non-normal distribution. Logistic regressions was used to identify factors associated with exclusive breastfeeding until the sixth month. Kapplan-Meier curves were made for the duration of breastfeeding and for the significant variable in the model. The attributable risk to which the population was exposed was calculated, as were population attributable risks. RESULTS 27.9% of teenage mothers in the sample managed exclusive breastfeeding until the sixth month. Average maternal age was 17.56 years. Logistic regression analysis revealed that the time spent involved in the strategy and education following the birth of a child for those belonging to a nuclear family were associated with a longer duration of breastfeeding. CONCLUSIONS The duration of exclusive breastfeeding in the teenage mother population could be extended, emphasizing continuity and the type of education received by being in the program.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2013 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con lactancia materna exclusiva hasta el sexto mes en madres adolescentes. Medellin, 2010.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors associated with exclusive breastfeeding until the sixth month in teenage mothers. Medellin, 2010].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
