<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25127746</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1879</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Clara, Fernando Mario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meschino, Gustavo Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corral, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Scandurra, Adriana Graciela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco, Gustavo Hector</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION We studied the alteration on the distensibility of the arterial walls caused by dyslipidemia LDLc dependent, along the decades of life, by means of a study of the radial artery pulse wave. METHODS We made an analysis of the radial artery pulse wave records acquired by means a movement displacement sensor, placed on radial palpation area. We recruited 100 dyslipidemic men without other cardiovascular risk factors, between the 3rd and the 6th decade. We identified the reflected wave in the records and we computed the augmentation index in order to quantify its amplitude and position. This index is useful to assess the endothelial dysfunction. Besides, we defined a velocity coefficient as the ratio between the size of the individuals and the delay time between the peak of the systolic wave and the arrival of the reflected wave. Results were compared against those obtained in a group of 161 healthy volunteers. RESULTS We found that dyslipidemic patients presented augmentation index values similar to controls until the fourth decade, increasing thereafter with significant differences only in the 6th decade. No significant differences were found in the velocity index in any of the ages studied. CONCLUSIONS We conclude that alterations produced by dyslipidemia take decades to manifest, and they begin affecting the mechanism of vasodilation of distal arteries with highest proportion of smooth muscle, without altering the proximal conduit arteries with more elastin content.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hiperlipoproteinemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arterial ageing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Envejecimiento arterial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pulse wave</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hyperlipoproteinemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Onda de pulso</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones en la distensibilidad arterial de pacientes dislipidémicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Alterations in arterial compliance of dyslipidemic patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Clinica e investigacion en arteriosclerosis : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Arteriosclerosis</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
