<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25156025</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Pisón, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo-Álvarez, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cemeli-Cano, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Segura, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernando-Martínez, Ruth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monge-Galindo, Lorena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Legius syndrome is an autosomal dominant disorder caused by the mutation in the SPRED1 gene involving a negative regulator of the RAS-MAPK pathway, similar to neurofibromin and therefore shows some clinical similarities to neurofibromatosis type I (NF1) but less severe. These patients have multiple cafe-au-lait spots, sometimes associated with skin fold freckling, dysmorphic features, lipomas, and mild learning disabilities. However, this syndrome is not associated with neurofibromas, optic gliomas, Lisch nodules or tumor predisposition. CASE REPORT We present a 10 months child, without a personal interest history, consulting by hypotonic extremities, cafe-au-lait spots and mild psychomotor difficult. Mother's sister and grandfather have some cafe-au-lait spots. In our patient, NF1 genetic study was negative, but we observe a mutation in the SPRED1 gene, compatible with Legius syndrome. Asymptomatic mother shows the same mutation in SPRED1 gene. CONCLUSION We emphasize the relevance of the differential diagnosis of NF1 with respect to numerous complications to appear, with a better prognosis recently described entity as it is Legius syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Sep 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un nuevo síndrome neurocutáneo: síndrome de Legius. A propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Un nuevo sindrome neurocutaneo: sindrome de Legius. A proposito de un caso. 
             Introduccion. El sindrome de Legius es un trastorno autosomico dominante resultante de la mutacion del gen SPRED1, que implica perdida de funcion de una de las proteinas implicada en la via patogenica RAS-MAPK, similar a la neurofibromina y por ello muestra similitudes clinicas con la neurofibromatosis tipo 1 (NF1), pero con menor gravedad. Estos pacientes presentan multiples manchas cafe con leche y pueden asociar efelides, rasgos dismorficos, lipomas y trastornos del aprendizaje sin relacionarse con la aparicion de neurofibromas, gliomas opticos, nodulos de Lisch o predisposicion tumoral. Caso clinico. Niño de 10 meses, sin antecedentes personales de interes, que consulta por hipotonia de extremidades, manchas cafe con leche y leve retraso psicomotor. En los antecedentes familiares destaca una hermana de la madre y el abuelo materno con manchas cafe con leche. En nuestro paciente, el estudio genetico fue negativo para NF1, pero se hallo una mutacion en el gen SPRED1, compatible con el sindrome de Legius. La madre asintomatica presenta la misma mutacion en el gen SPRED1. Conclusion. Es de destacar la importancia del diagnostico diferencial de NF1, con las numerosas complicaciones que puede conllevar, con una entidad recientemente descrita de mejor pronostico como es el sindrome de Legius. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A novel neurocutaneous syndrome: Legius syndrome. A case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
