<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2518663</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zeni, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Gómez del Río, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Piazza, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Portela, M L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have previously reported that, in the first stages of nutritional recovery, the needs of undernourished infants, in terms of protein-calories percentage (P%) are higher than normal, producing an accelerated catch-up. Consequently, calcium (Ca) and phosphorus (P) balances increase proportionally to weight gain rate (WGR) in order to attain a normal body composition. As for the control of Ca metabolism by vitamin D, the question is whether vitamin D intake must also be increased during this accelerated catch-up growth period. In this report we have analysed retrospectively previous results in order to clarify the interrelationship between Ca absorption, Ca retention and vitamin D intake. A total of 29 undernourished infants, from 2 to 18 months of age, were fed Ad libitum with one of two proprietary milk formulas containing, per 100 g.: Ca, 0.50 and 1.17 g.; P, 0.37 and 0.50 g.; vitamin D, 350 and 400 UI (8.7 and 10 micrograms); proteins, 11.34 and 17.00 kcal/100 kcal of total diet, respectively. Recommended Dietary Allowances (RDA) of Ca and vitamin D, according to FAO/OMS and NRC, were calculated with reference to normal infants body weight and to 1000 kcal of recommended dietary energy intake. Ca intake was higher than the RDA and ranged between 60 and 413 mg/kg/day; intake of vitamin D increased proportionally to food intake; calcium absorption ranged between 40.0 and 92.0% (mean = 69.8 +/- 14.6) and CaB correlated with Ca intake (r = 0.97), being higher than normal.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interrelaciones entre ingesta de vitamina D y absorción y retención de calcio durante la recuperación nutricional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Interrelationship between vitamin D intake and absorption and retention of calcium during nutritional recovery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
