<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25184458</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Patiño-Gómez, Lina M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arango-Pérez, Eduin A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Delgado, Cecilia M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Palacio, Ana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Pabón, María C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Identify the changes in some physiological and microbiological parameters in the saliva from a group of women during and after their pregnancies. METHODS Stimulated whole saliva was collected from a cohort of 35 women during their pregnancy and afterwards to determine each sample's physicochemical (secretion rate, pH and buffer capacity) and microbiological characteristics (acidogenic bacteria count). RESULTS The pH and buffer capacity of saliva during pregnancy were lower than after pregnancy. There were no statistically significant changes regarding S. mutans and Lactobacillus spp. count, but a tendency towards increased values during pregnancy was noted. CONCLUSIONS Changes occurring in the saliva of pregnant women can lead to an increase of risk of suffering disease affecting one's oral health, such as caries, gingivitis and periodontal disease; this could be prevented by appropriate diagnosis and dental follow-up, including education regarding pregnant women's oral health.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características fisicoquímicas y microbiológicas de la saliva durante y después del embarazo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The physicochemical and microbiological characteristics of saliva during and after pregnancy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
