<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2518895</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salas, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Piñeiro, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pacheco, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guinot, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, T</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence and social and health aspects of smoking habits among physicians of the Hospital San Pedro de Alcántara (Cáceres) were evaluated with the questionnaire used in the course on smoking habits delivered by the INSALUD in 1988. The sample consisted of 123 physicians. 47.1% (+8.7%) declared to be smokers. This prevalence is higher than that in the general population. The rate of female nonsmokers was significantly higher than that of male nonsmokers (p less than 0.05). 51.7% of smokers had not made any attempt to give up smoking. 90% thought that the role of the doctors as a model is important, and that the health system should undertake their treatment. 97.2% declared to lack therapeutic resources. The results disclose the need for specific programs directed to exemplary groups of professionals, such as those devoted to health care, so as to achieve a reduction in the smoking habit.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre el hábito tabáquico en el personal médico del Hospital San Pedro de Alcántara (Cáceres).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Survey of smoking habits of the medical personnel at the Hospital San Pedro de Alcántara (Cáceres)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
