<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2520832</identifier>
<setSpec>0074-0276</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gusmao, R D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Comach, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aldao, R R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chiechie, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Hubsch, R M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A survey of human Trypanosoma cruzi infection in four rural communities of two Venezuelan states with different epidemiological Chagas' disease situations was carried out using the Dot-ELISA and conventional serology. In the two hamlets of Zulia state, no seropositives were found in the under-15 age group whereas seropositivity in the over-15 group was 15.6%. In Cojedes state, the two hamlets studied exhibited a seropositivity of 8.9% in the under-15 group and 51.6% in the over-15 group. Upon comparison with conventional methods, Dot-ELISA evidenced high co-positivity, co-negativity and efficiency indexes. In the samples taken from Zulia, the predictive value of the test was 66% and 60% for cytoplasmatic and integral antigens, respectively; with the Cojedes samples, 100% and 95%. The results suggest that Dot-ELISA could be a practical alternative for seroepidemiological Chagas' disease studies in underdeveloped regions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ensayo inmunoenzimático en microgotas sobre nitrocelulosa (Dot-ELISA) en el diagnóstico de la enfermedad de Chagas. II. Estudio seroepidemiológico en cuatro comunidades rurales de Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The Dot immunoenzymatic assay on nitrocellulose (Dot-ELISA) in the diagnosis of Chagas disease. II. Seroepidemiologic study in 4 rural communities of Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Memorias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
