<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25256629</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Masip-Simó, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Polo-Miquel, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arcos-Machancoses, J V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Donat-Aliaga, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribes-Koninckx, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pereda-Pérez, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Diagnostic delay of inflammatory bowel disease in children might be responsible for complications and a poor response to treatment. The study of diagnostic delay and its determining factors may help implement corrective measures and improve the prognosis of the disease. PATIENTS AND METHODS A retrospective study of the information collected from primary care medical records and that from the pediatric gastroenterology service at a tertiary hospital between 2000 and 2012 was carried out on 53 patients: 31 with Crohn's disease, 19 with ulcerative colitis, and 3 with unclassified pediatric inflammatory bowel disease. The main response variable was the interval from the first physician-patient contact to diagnosis. RESULTS The median time to diagnosis was 12 weeks (interquartile range 5-24). However for 26.3% of the ulcerative colitis cases and 25.8% of the Crohn's disease cases, the interval was longer than 1 year. There was a more marked delay trend in Crohn's disease cases, but it was not statistically significant. None of the evaluated risk factors was associated with a relevant diagnostic delay, although it tended to be longer in younger children. CONCLUSIONS Whereas the median delay for pediatric inflammatory bowel disease seems to be acceptable, the diagnostic time spans are considerable for a large proportion of children with heterogeneous clinical characteristics. Further research into lost diagnostic opportunities needs to be carried out.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Inflammatory bowel disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Retraso diagnóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diagnostic delay</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary care</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retraso diagnóstico en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal pediátrica. Descripción y estudio de los factores de riesgo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Description and study of risk factors for the diagnostic delay of pediatric inflammatory bowel disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
