<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2528193</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alfonso, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iñiguez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bañuelos, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodrigo, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Espinosa, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zarco, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Macaya, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To determine if the results of percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty are similar in women and in men or any difference between both sexes exists, we have compared 43 clinical and 61 angiographic or procedural variables of 85 consecutive transluminal coronary angioplasties performed in women with 421 similar consecutive procedures in men. Only cigarette smoking was more frequent in men (84 vs 11%, p less than 0.001), being the remaining coronary risk factors more common in women (hypertension 69% vs 37%, p less than 0.001; hypercholesterolemia 46% vs 33%, p less than 0.05, and diabetes mellitus 42% vs 14%, p less than 0.01). In addition, unstable angina was a more frequent indication of coronary angioplasty in women than in men (74% vs 61%, p less than 0.05), whereas coronary angioplasty after intravenous thrombolysis was more frequent in men (12% vs 1%, p less than 0.001). Coronary angioplasty angiographic success (87% vs 91%), and minor (16% vs 10%) or major (5% vs 3%) complications were not statistically different in the two groups. Nevertheless, success of the procedure in the absence of any complication was achieved in a higher percentage (86% vs 76%, p less than 0.05) of men than in their female counterparts. After coronary angioplasty 88% of women had an angiographic follow-up available which yielded a restenosis rate of 41% (vs 32% in men, NS), despite the absence of symptoms in the 89% of these patients in their last visit. In conclusion, we have found that the feminine population subjected to coronary angioplasty have a higher incidence of coronary risks factors and more frequently unstable angina than the masculine group.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil clínico y resultados de la angioplastia coronaria transluminal en la mujer. Comparación con el varón.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical profile and results of transluminal coronary angioplasty in women. Comparison with men].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
