<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25306870</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Truchuelo, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaén, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mavura, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The high rate of relapse of acne lesions following oral isotretinoin treatment is a common problem which remains unsolved. To avoid or minimize relapses, topical retinoids have been used for many years as maintenance treatment. However, adverse effects frequently occur. AIMS To determine the efficacy and safety of a new retinoid combination (Retinsphere technology) in maintaining post-treatment response to oral isotretinoin. PATIENTS AND METHODS Prospective, randomized, double-blind and vehicle-controlled study of 30 patients with acne previously treated with isotretinoin. Treatment with the retinoid combination was applied to one side of the face and vehicle was applied to the other, once daily, for 3 months. Standardized photographs were taken using RBX technology at baseline, 1.5 months and 3 months. The primary efficacy endpoint was the appearance of relapse on the treated side compared to the vehicle-treated side. Other endpoints included lesion count, investigator-reported improvement, patient-reported improvement, impact on quality-of-life, and side effects. RESULTS Although the majority of patients did not reach the total target dose of oral isotretinoin, the relapse rate was significantly lower on the retinoid-treated side compared to the vehicle-treated side. Likewise, improved lesion count and excellent tolerance were observed. CONCLUSIONS This new retinoid combination (Retinsphere technology) were effective and safe as maintenance therapy after post-treatment response to oral isotretinoin in patients with acne.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Topical retinoids</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acné</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recaídas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Maintenance therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Relapses</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acne</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia de mantenimiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Isotretinoína oral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recurrencias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Retinoides tópicos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oral isotretinoin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recurrences</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the efficacy and safety of a combination of 2 topical retinoids (RetinSphere) in maintaining post-treatment response of acne to oral isotretinoin.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
