<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25327191</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García, Mónica Giseth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echeverri-Toro, Lina María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Zila Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ospina, Sigifredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez, Faiver</dc:author>
<dc:author>Agudelo, Yuli</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ossa-Giraldo, Ana Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION multi-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa (MR) is frequently associated with healthcare infections. Its epidemiology is complex and few studies help to understand it. A study about risk factors associated with this type of bacteria is needed. OBJECTIVE To determine risk factors associated with MR P. aeruginosa infection in hospitalized patients from the Hospital Universitario San Vicente Foundation-Medellin. MATERIALS AND METHODS case-control study to identify risk factors associated with infection by MR P. aeruginosa. RESULTS 140 patients were included, 70 in each group. Bivariate analysis found association with previous use of carbapenems (OR 3.12 - IC 1.21 to 8.03, p = 0.02), aminoglycosides (OR 5.09 - CI: 1.38 to 18, 77, p = 0.01) and days of stay prior to isolation of the organism (OR 1.03 - CI: 1.01-1.05, p = 0.01). In multivariate analysis MR P. aeruginosa infection was associated with hospital stay (OR 1.03 - IC 1.01 to 1.05), use of aminoglycosides (OR 1.30 to 19.28) and treatment with two or more antimicrobials in the last 30 days (OR 3.09 - CI: 1.26 to 7.58). The risk of developing infection was 3% per day of hospital stay prior to isolation of the agent. CONCLUSION Developing MR P. aeruginosa infection was associated with prior use of antimicrobials and prior hospital stay.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo para infección por Pseudomonas aeruginosa multi-resistente en un hospital de alta complejidad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors for multidrug-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection, in a tertiary hospital in Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
