<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25327325</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Braghetto, Italo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Las Heras, Facundo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés, Claudio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Musleh, Maher</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montesinos, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sarcomatoid squamous carcinoma (ESC) is a rare esophageal neoplasm, with a clinical, etiological and pathological behavior that differs from squamous cancer. From the histological point of view it has a dual configuration. The squamous epithelial component is usually limited to small areas, while the major part is constituted by mesenchymatous (sarcomatoid) polypoid tissue. Treatment is esophagectomy or total esophagogastrectomy depending on the tumor location. Early detection is critical in terms of survival. For large lesions, preoperative chemo-radiotherapy can be considered. We report a 78-year-old male presenting with dysphagia. An upper gastrointestinal endoscopy showed a tumor located below the cardia. The patient was subjected to a total esophageal and gastric resection. In a second operation, the digestive transit was reconstituted in 2 steps. The pathology report informed a sarcomatoid squamous carcinoma. After 18 months of follow up, the patient is ambulatory.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma escamoso sarcomatoide de la unión gastroesofágica: caso clínico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Esophageal sarcomatoid squamous carcinoma: report of one case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
