<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25326843</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Delgado, Elías</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 2 diabetes represents one of the most important health problems, provided due to its high prevalence and significant morbi-mortality. At present time, we know that an intensive control of all cardiovascular risk factors from the beginning prevents the appearance and progression of micro and macrovascular complications. Nevertheless, only few patients achieve the degree of metabolic control recommended by diabetes therapeutic guidelines. This is due to different reasons such as lack of patients compliance and therapeutic inertia by doctors. Also, the available therapeutic approaches are limited. We still do not have the ideal antidiabetic drug, which should be able to be used in all phases of the disease, have sustained durability, be well tolerated not inducing hypoglycaemia, and promote weight loss, cardiovascular protection and reducing morbi-mortality at a low cost. The launching of new drugs with attractive mechanisms of action and few side effects may help to achieve these goals, though we still should wait for the results of studies demonstrating their effect on cardiovascular endpoints.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Control glucémico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Therapeutic inertia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inercia terapéutica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treatment priority</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prioridad en el tratamiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oral antidiabetic drugs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antidiabéticos orales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glucose control</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades no cubiertas en el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Unmet needs in the treatment of type 2 diabetes].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
