<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25344133</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rentero, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urbieta, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iniesta, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Madrigal, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, M D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective of this study was to determine the main causes of errors of medication reconciliation at hospital admission in medical and surgical department and establish factors associated with medication reconciliation errors. MATERIAL AND METHOD Cross-sectional study. We included all patients admitted to two services and two surgical for a month. To determine the presence of error reconciliation, the pharmacist compared the medication history interview by the order physician. The factors associated with errors were identified by multivariate logistic regression analysis. RESULTS 221 patients were included, of which 58.4% had at least one error reconciliation. We detected 629 discrepancies, 339 (53.9%) reconciliation errors. The incidence of errors in medical services was 24.3% and in the surgical services 43.0% (p &lt;0.001) in both groups being most prevalent error of omission (46.2% and 50.8%). Regarding factors associated, the equation determines that patients older than 65 years, polymedicated and taking oral antidiabetic are more likely to have an error with a sensibility of 75.2% and a specificity of 68.5%. CONCLUSION There is a high rate of error reconciliation in medical and surgical patients, which confirms the need to implement a strategy to reduce these errors. Given the difficulty of applying the process to all patients, the strategy must be directed to patients who are at increased risk of error.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Sep 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas y factores asociados a los errores de conciliación en servicios médicos y quirúrgicos.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Determinar las principales causas de errores de conciliacion de la medicacion al ingreso hospitalario tanto en los servicios medicos, como en los quirurgicos y que factores se asocian a dichos errores de conciliacion. 
             Estudio observacional transversal. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes que ingresaron en dos servicios medicos y dos quirurgicos durante un mes. Para determinar la presencia de error de conciliacion se cotejo la historia realizada por el farmaceutico con la del medico prescriptor. Los factores asociados a los errores se identificaron mediante un analisis de regresion logistica multivariante. 
             Se incluyeron 221 pacientes, de los cuales el 58.4% presentaron al menos un error de conciliacion. Se detectaron un total de 629 discrepancias, 339 (53.9%) errores de conciliacion. La incidencia de errores en los servicios medicos fue del 24.3% y en los quirurgicos del 43.0% (p. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Causes and factors associated with reconciliation errors in medical and surgical services].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
