<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2535559</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3503</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marzullo, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Piñate, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapata-Sirvent, R L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larocca, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, R C</dc:author>
<dc:author>París, M M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Antequera, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Médico, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olavarría, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We designed a model of intestinal obstruction (IO) to study the histological alterations in the intestinal wall and the mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN). Therefore we used 32 Sprague-Dawley rats and under anesthesia a laparotomy was performed and the distal ileum was ligated with 3-0 silk, producing a complete occlusion. At different interval (24, 48, 72 and 96 hours) the animals were sacrificed by cervical dislocation and were histologically analyzed. At 24 hours post IO, congestion, edema and a inflammatory infiltrate were observed at the level of the lamina propia and the MLN were reactive. At 48 hours the congestion and edema increased and the intestinal mucosa began to fragment, allowing the bacteria to translocate and getting to the lymph nodes in the intestinal wall. The reactivity at the MLN increased. The observation of bacterial translocation in IO widen the scope of the alterations in this pathology, were not only absorption of toxic products and endotoxin occurs in the compromise segment and this phenomenon could explain the incidence of bacteremia and sepsis in the IO patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores involucrados en la translocación bacteriana en un modelo experimental de obstrucción intestinal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors involved in bacterial translocation in an experimental model of intestinal obstruction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>G.E.N</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
