<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25362926</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Spini, Roxana Gabriela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orofino, Guillermina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Debaisi, Gustavo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferraris, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casanovas, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Glasman, María Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Community-acquired Staphylococcus aureus (CA-SA) infections are becoming more frequent. Most cases present an infection of skin and soft tissue, and the most invasive forms observed are osteoarticular and pleuropulmonary infections. Meningitis is a rare manifestation of Staphylococcus aureus infections. We describe an unusual case of CA-MRSA infection. An infant of eight months presented with signs of irritability and 4 days duration fever, with alternating sensory and abdomen pain. Acute abdomen surgery was discarded and hospitalization was decided with diagnosis of sepsis due to probable enteral focus; antibiotics were indicated. Blood cultures and cerebrospinal fluid culture were positive for MRSA. Sepsis with meningitis by MRSA was diagnosed. On the 7th day of hospitalization the infant presented neurological signs and symptoms. On the resolution computed tomography and the magnetic resonance, images compatible with myelitis were observed. The patient complied with the 21 day endovenous treatment, and showed positive results, being discharged from hospital a month after the appearance of the symptoms.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis por Staphylococcus aureus meticilino resistente proveniente de la comunidad: a propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Methicillin resistant Staphylococcus aureus community acquired meningitis: a case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
