<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25365021</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martín Salvador, Adelina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortiz Rubio, Araceli</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Alzueta, Elisabeth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Sánchez, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valenza, Marie Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Torres, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a progressive disease with a prevalence that increases with the aging of the subject. It presents a high prevalence of comorbidities, such as cognitive decline, which is gaining great clinical relevance in recent years. Factors such as pulmonary function, hypoxemia, hypercapnia or exacerbations contribute to the decline of cognitive functions. The nutritional status has been added to these factors as contributing to cognitive function decline when presenting in COPD. OBJECTIVE To evidence the relationship between cognitive decline, nutritional status and the clinical profile of patients admitted because of an acute exacerbation of COPD (AECOPD). METHODS 110 subjects hospitalized because of COPD, divided in two groups according to their nutritional status and assessment of cognitive decline at admittance, nutritional status and clinical profile. RESULTS Significant differences between groups concerning nutritional status in anthropometric variables (sex and IMC), functional ability (Barthel index and Daily Life Activities Scale), quality of life (Euroqol- 5D y SGRQ), sleep quality (Pittsburgh), mood (HAD) and cognitive decline (MoCa attention, MoCa abstraction). (p&lt;0.05). CONCLUSION Cognitive function is affected in COPD patients with an altered nutritional status when compared to those with a normal nutritional status. The nutritional decline is a factor contributing to the impairment of cognitive functions in this kind of patients, particularly a decline in attention and abstraction ability.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Nov 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro cognitivo, estado nutricional y perfil clínico en la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) es una enfermedad progresiva, cuya prevalencia aumenta con la edad. Se caracteriza por su elevado número de comorbilidades, entre ellas el deterioro cognitivo, que ha ido adquiriendo gran relevancia clínica en los últimos años. Factores como la función pulmonar, la hipoxemia, la hipercapnia o las exacerbaciones contribuyen al deterioro de las funciones cognitivas. Se ha incluido el estado nutricional como un factor más que presentándose en la EPOC, contribuya también al deterioro de la funciones cognitivas. 
             Evidenciar la relación entre el deterioro cognitivo, el estado nutricional y el perfil clínico de los pacientes que ingresan por exacerbación aguda de EPOC (EAEPOC). 
             Ciento diez sujetos hospitalizados por EAEPOC, divididos en dos grupos según su estado nutricional y evaluación a su ingreso de deterioro cognitivo, estado nutricional y perfil clínico. 
             Diferencias significativas entre grupos de estado nutricional en las variables antropométricas (sexo e IMC), capacidad funcional (Índice de Barthel y escala de Actividades de la Vida Diaria) calidad de vida (Euroqol- 5D y SGRQ), calidad de sueño (Pittsburgh), estado de ánimo (HAD) y deterioro cognitivo (MoCa atención, MoCa abstracción). (p. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cognitive impairment, nutritional status and clinical profile in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
