<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25365200</identifier>
<setSpec>1853-0605</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gramática, Luis h</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palas, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferreira, Gastón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez, Facundo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The treatment of benign multinodular goiter (BMNB) is a matter of ongoing debate in recent decades despite evidence that total thyroidectomy (TT) is associated with a significant reduction in disease recurrence and minimal morbidity in trained hands. OBJECTIVE Determine BMNB recurrence after 10 years in 100 patients treated with TT and evaluate the technique-related complications. DESIGN Prospective non randomized. MATERIAL AND METHODS From March 1999 to March 2001, one hundred patients, 95 female, with an average age of 42.4 years (range 23-67) underwent TT for having a BMNB, which was confirmed by cervical ultrasound, which also served as a guide to perform fine-needle aspiration (FNA). In all cases, laryngoscopy was performed before and after post-surgical bitstream. RESULTS Mean operative time was 49 minutes (range 35-58). Recurrencial recorded paralysis (1%) and five hypoparathyroidism (5%), both transient and no definitive case. All patients were discharged within 24 hours of surgery. We did not record any recurrence BMNB a follow-up period of more than 10 years. CONCLUSION The TT is the treatment choice of BMNB, being an effective, safe, with low rates of complications and to avoid or significantly reduce the recurrence of this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiroidectomía total en el bocio multinodular benigno.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción. El tratamiento del bocio multinodular beningo (BMNB) es motivo de continuo debate en las últimas décadas pese a la evidencia de que la tiroidectomía total (TT) está relacionada a una reducción significativa en la recurrencia de la enfermedad y a una mínima morbilidad en manos entrenadas. Objetivo. Determinar la recurrencia del BMNB al cabo de 10 años en 100 pacientes tratados con TT y evaluar las complicaciones relacionadas a la técnica.Diseño. Prospectivo no randomizado.Material y métodos. Desde marzo del 1999 a marzo del 2001, cien pacientes, 95 del sexo femenino, con un promedio de edad de 42,4 años (rango: 23-67), fueron sometidos a una TT por padecer un BMNB, el cual fue confirmado por la ecografía cervical, la que además sirvió de guía para realizar la punción aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF). En todos los casos se realizó un laringoscopía inderecta pre y post postquirúrgica. Resultados. El tiempo operatorio promedio fue de 49 minutos (rango: 35-58). Registramos una parálisis recurrencial (1%) y cinco hipoparatiroidismos (5%), ambos transitorios y ningún caso definitivo. Todos los pacientes fueron dados de alta antes de las 24 horas de la cirugía. No objetivamos ninguna recurrencia del BMNB en un período de seguimiento de más de 10 años.Conclusión. La TT es el tratamiento elección del BMNB, por ser un procedimiento eficaz, seguro, con mínimas tasas de complicaciones y por evitar o reducir significativamente la recurrencia de esta enfermedad. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Total thyroidectomy treatment of bening multinodular goiter].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de la Facultad de Ciencias Medicas (Cordoba, Argentina)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
