<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25393869</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navas, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Febrero, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lloret, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ríos, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) were identified only recently. These tumors usually have no symptoms, although they are localized, operable and curable. Although rare, if they are not diagnosed and treated early, they become very aggressive. The most common manifestation is gastrointestinal bleeding from mucosal erosion. Their presentation as severe lower gastrointestinal bleeding is exceptional. CLINICAL CASE We report a patient with severe lower gastrointestinal bleeding stabilized by interventional radiology that subsequently required surgery for definitive care. CONCLUSIONS Therapeutic use of radiological embolization is increasingly widespread in bleeding at various levels, achieving hemodynamic stabilization of patients. However, it must be kept in mind that, in cases of unknown etiology of lower gastrointestinal bleeding, possible causes must be investigated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>cirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>tumor de GIST</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>GIST tumor&gt;</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>embolization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Severe lower gastrointestinal bleeding</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>hemorragia baja severa del tubo digestivo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>embolización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia baja severa del tubo digestivo por tumor de GIST. Embolización radiológica y cirugía.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: los tumores del estroma gastrointestinal (GIST) se identificaron hace muy poco tiempo. Son tumores que no suelen alertar con síntomas mientras permanecen en fase localizada, operable y curable. Aunque son poco frecuentes, cuando no se diagnostican y tratan oportunamente son muy agresivos. Su manifestación clínica más común es la hemorragia gastrointestinal por erosión de la mucosa, pero su presentación como hemorragia baja del tubo digestivo severa es excepcional. Caso clínico: se comunica un caso de hemorragia baja del tubo digestivo severa estabilizada por radiología intervencionista, que posteriormente requirió cirugía para su tratamiento definitivo. Conclusiones: la embolización radiológica está cada vez más difundida como tratamiento de hemorragias en distintos sitios porque permite la estabilización hemodinámica de los pacientes. No hay que olvidar, sin embargo, que en los casos de hemorragia baja del tubo digestivo, de origen desconocido, es necesario investigar las posibles causas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Severe lower gastrointestinal bleeding due to GIST tumor. Radiological embolization and surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
