<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25441420</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Iáñez Velasco, Benjamín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saura Rojas, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jorques Infante, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Corral, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero Tous, Nicolás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Horcajadas Almansa, Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Román Cutillas, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To analyze the usefulness of intracranial pressure (ICP) monitoring in overt long-standing ventriculomegaly patients. MATERIAL AND METHODS There were 22 patients with ventriculomegaly and neurological symptoms. Demographic, clinical and radiological data were collected, as well as ICP monitoring data and complications related to the procedure. Results were evaluated 6 months after surgery. RESULTS Mean age was 44 years (22-70). Mean Evans index was 0.47 (0.35-0.66). Aqueductal stenosis was present in more than half of the patients (55%). Mean ICP was higher than 12 mmHg in only 9% of patients. Morphological analysis of ICP recordings was abnormal in 64% of patients. "Pre-plateau" A waves were seen in 7 patients, with B waves seen in 20 patients (high amplitude B waves in 14). Twelve patients were operated on the basis of ICP recordings (CSF shunt or ventriculostomy). Seventy per cent of treated patients had improved at 6 months. There were no complications related to the monitoring technique. CONCLUSIONS ICP monitoring is a valuable, safe tool, very useful in these cases. Selection of surgical candidates on the basis of ICP monitoring seems to be advisable. Mean ICP may be normal even with pathological recordings. Morphological analysis is essential to establish a correct diagnosis. The presence of A and B waves in the recording is highly related to good shunt response.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Aqueductal stenosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>NeuroPICture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Longstanding Overt Ventriculomegaly in Adults</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neuropicture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estenosis de Silvio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Long-standing overt ventriculomegaly</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ventriculomegalia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ondas B</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monitorización de la presión intracraneal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intracranial pressure monitoring</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>B waves</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la monitorización de la presión intracraneal en pacientes con ventriculomegalia marcada de larga evolución.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Usefulness of continuous intracranial pressure monitoring in long-standing overt ventriculomegaly in adults].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
