<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25444360</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Martos, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Tapia, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerrero, Inmaculada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galán, Fátima</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Agudo, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Iglesias, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Identification of yeasts is based on morphological, biochemical and nutritional characteristics, and using molecular methods. Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight (MALDI-TOF) mass spectrometry, a new method for the identification of microorganisms, has demonstrated to be very useful. The aim of this study is to evaluate this new method in the identification of yeasts. METHODS A total of 600 strains of yeasts isolated from clinical specimens belonging to 9 genera and 43 species were tested. Identification was made by sequencing of the ITS regions of ribosomal DNA, assimilation of carbon compounds (ID 32C), and mass spectrometry on a Microflex spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics GmbH, Germany). RESULTS A total of 569 strains (94.8%) were identified to species level by ID 32C, and 580 (96.7%) by MALDI-TOF. Concordance between both methods was observed for 553 strains (92.2%), with 100% in clinically relevant species: C. albicans, C. glabrata, C. parapsilosis, C. tropicalis, and almost 100% in C. krusei. MALDI-TOF identified species requiring molecular methods: Candida dubliniensis, C. nivariensis, C. metapsilosis and C. orthopsilosis. Some irregularities were observed in the identification of arthroconidia yeast and basidiomycetes. CONCLUSION MALDI-TOF is a rapid, effective and economic method, which enables the identification of most clinically important yeasts and the differentiation of closely related species. It would be desirable to include more species in its database to expand its performance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Medically-important yeasts</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Yeasts</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Espectrometría de masas MALDI-TOF</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Candida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Levaduras</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Levaduras de interés clínico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la espectrometría de masas en la identificación de levaduras de interés clínico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of mass spectrometry for the identification of clinically interesting yeasts].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
