<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25443768</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco-Reina, Encarnación</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ocaña-Riola, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez-Romero, Elisa Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bellido-Estévez, Inmaculada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vega-Jiménez, M Auxiliadora</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to evaluate the prescription profile and to assess the off-label and unlicensed uses of medicines among non-hospitalised pediatric patients. DESIGN cross-sectional study. SETTING pediatric units in two urban health centers and general emergency room (Hospital Materno-Infantil, Málaga). MAIN MEASUREMENTS sociodemographics variables, reasons for consultation and information about therapeutic medications. The classification of prescriptions was established according to information requirements contained in the Summary of Products Characteristics (SPC). RESULTS A total of 388 children were included (a subsample of 105 treated in the emergency room). Four hundred sixty-two prescriptions (involving 74 different active ingredients) were evaluated. Each infant received and average of 1,7 drugs (95% CI: 1,6-1,9). The most prescribed medicines were ibuprofen, paracetamol, amoxicillin-clavulanate and budesonide. The therapeutic group with the greatest variety of drugs was the respiratory group. 27,4% (95% CI: 23,5-31) of prescriptions were off-label and the main cause was different age (60%; 95% CI: 54,1-63), followed by different dose (21,5%; 95% CI: 18-25), different indication (12%; 95% CI: 9,2-15) and different route of administration (7%; 95% CI: 5,4-10). CONCLUSIONS The rate of off-label uses presents intermediate figures. Around one third of the paediatric outpatients in our sample are exposed to at least one off-label or unlicensed prescription. We should, however, point out that such usage is based on scant official, quality information, although it is not necessarily incorrect. Evidence-based medicine should be encouraged to improve drug therapy in children, as well as following the rules on drugs in special situations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Off-label use</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niños</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Unlicensed</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prescripciones fuera de ficha técnica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Off-label</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary care</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las prescripciones farmacológicas en niños a nivel de atención primaria: evaluación de los usos off-label o fuera de ficha técnica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Drug prescriptions study in the outpatient setting: assessment of off-label uses in children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
