<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25459193</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moreno Samos, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pradillo Martín, María Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Pérez, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordón Martínez, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urda Cardona, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amores Torres, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos Fernández, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Pertussis is a re-emerging disease that mostly affects infants. At this age, the severity can be affected by intercurrent infections such as respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). OBJECTIVES To estimate the incidence of RSV infection during an epidemic period in patients hospitalized due to pertussis. The impact on the severity was also observed during hospitalization. PATIENTS AND METHOD A descriptive study of cases diagnosed with pertussis admitted to a tertiary hospital over a 3year period, where the presence of co-infection with RSV was analyzed. The estimate of severity was estimated using the incidence of complications and the level of care required. RESULTS From a total of 73 infants with pertussis, 34 occurred in a bronchiolitis season epidemic. A co-infection due to RSV was detected in 17 patients. The mean age was not significantly different compared to the non co-infected. The mean stay and the need for intensive care was similar in both groups. The need for oxygen therapy care and nutritional support was higher in the coinfected patients. CONCLUSIONS Coinfection with RSV in infants hospitalized with pertussis occurred in ono in 2 patients during a RSV epidemic season, in infants of similar age. Severity in terms of stay, presence of apnea and admission to intensive care was similar, but more need for respiratory care and nutritional support was found.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pertussis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virus respiratorio sincitial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niños</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coinfección respiratoria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tosferina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Respiratory coinfection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Respiratory syncitial virus</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y gravedad de la tosferina en lactantes coinfectados por el virus respiratorio sincitial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Incidence and severity of pertussis in infants with a respiratory syncytial virus infection].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
