<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25475657</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alós, Juan-Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The introduction of antibiotics into clinical practice represented one of the most important interventions for the control of infectious diseases. Antibiotics have saved millions of lives and have also brought a revolution in medicine. However, an increasing threat has deteriorated the effectiveness of these drugs, that of bacterial resistance to antibiotics, which is defined here as the ability of bacteria to survive in antibiotic concentrations that inhibit/kill others of the same species. In this review some recent and important examples of resistance in pathogens of concern for mankind are mentioned. It is explained, according to present knowledge, the process that led to the current situation in a short time, evolutionarily speaking. It begins with the resistance genes, continues with clones and genetic elements involved in the maintenance and dissemination, and ends with other factors that contribute to its spread. Possible responses to the problem are also reviewed, with special reference to the development of new antibiotics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Extensión de la resistencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nuevos antibióticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spread of antibiotic resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Genes de resistencia a antibióticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>New antibiotics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Uso racional de antimicrobianos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibiotic resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resistencia a antibióticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antimicrobial stewardship</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibiotic resistance genes</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resistencia bacteriana a los antibióticos: una crisis global.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Antibiotic resistance: A global crisis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
