<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25510589</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torijano-Casalengua, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>S치nchez-Holgado, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gonzalez-Gonzalez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze the level of knowledge in palliative care that health and non health housing for the elderly workers refer, to study the differences between professional categories and to detect their interest in receiving palliative care training. PATIENTS AND METHODS Cross-sectional study conducted among physicians, nurses, physiotherapists, nursing assistant and occupational therapists applying a questionnaire assisting terminal patients with 22 items grouped into four sections: generalities palliative care, physical care, psycho-emotional and spiritual. Each question is answered using a four point scale in much-regulate-little-nothing. RESULTS 86.8% of respondents know quite what they mean or regular palliative care. 3.8% consider themselves sufficiently trained in palliative care. We found significant differences in non-pharmacological management of dyspnea and insomnia where concerns have less knowledge worker. Medicine and nursing reported having more knowledge in the recognition of a tumor ulcer. CONCLUSIONS There is a very high interest in receiving palliative care training and these are considered very useful. Required impact on the acquisition of knowledge in the medical staff not optional as to non-pharmacological management of major symptoms It also emphasizes the need to approach not to question the patient's pain by physicians. The test to detect cognitive impairment are not well known for nursing assistants. The spiritual realm is the acceptable level of knowledge on the part of all professional categories surveyed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Atenci칩n primaria de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidados paliativos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary health care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Palliative care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Housing for the elderly</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Centros de personas mayores</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepci칩n sobre conocimientos en cuidados paliativos de los trabajadores de los centros sociosanitarios de personas mayores de una zona b치sica de salud.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Perception of knowledge in palliative care housing for the elderly workers in a basic health zone].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
