<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25529172</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Quesada, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cano, L M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lara, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardona, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Cardioembolic stroke is associated with poorer outcomes. Prevention is based on oral anticoagulant (OAC) therapy. Haemorrhage is the main complication of OACs, which are sometimes ineffective. PATIENTS AND METHODS We retrospectively reviewed 1014 consecutive patients who suffered an ischaemic stroke between 2011 and 2013, analysing those who were receiving OAC treatment at stroke onset (107 patients in total) with special attention to aetiology, outcomes, and INR value in the acute phase. RESULTS The mean age (SD) was 71.9 (10) years. Patients had been treated with OACs for 5.9 (5.5) years; 98.1% of them were being treated for heart disease. INR was &lt;2 in 77 patients (72%), and 30 patients (28%) had an INR≥2. Nine patients (8.4%) had INR values within the therapeutic range. According to TOAST classification criteria, 88.8% of strokes were cardioembolic and 1.9% were atherothrombotic. Anticoagulation therapy was discontinued in 48 patients (44.9%) due to haemorrhagic transformation (24 patients), extensive infarction (23), or endarterectomy (1). Therapy was resumed in 24 patients (50%) after a mean lapse of 36 days. This was not possible in the remaining patients because of death or severe sequelae. New OACs (NOACs) were prescribed to 9 patients (18.7% of all potential candidates). At 3 months, patients with INR&gt;1.7 in the acute phase exhibited better outcomes than patients with INR≤1.7 (mRS 0-2 in 62% vs 30.8%; death in 10% vs 38.4%; P=.0004). CONCLUSIONS Some patients taking OACs suffer ischaemic strokes that are usually cardioembolic, especially if INR is below the therapeutic range. OACs can be resumed without complications, and NOACs are still underused. Despite cases in which treatment is ineffective, outcomes are better when INR is above 1.7 at stroke onset.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cociente internacional normalizado</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>International normalized ratio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oral anticoagulants</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardioembolic stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anticoagulantes orales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ictus isquémico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ictus cardioembólico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ischaemic stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ictus isquémico en pacientes en tratamiento anticoagulante por vía oral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ischaemic stroke in patients treated with oral anticoagulants.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
