<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25533320</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carrillo-García, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vivo-Molina, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quiñonero-Méndez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Celdrán-Gil, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Roche, M E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective was to analyze the phenomenon of work satisfaction of doctors of the Mobile Emergency Team and the Emergency Coordinator Office 061 of the Region of Murcia. MATERIAL AND METHOD A observational, analytical and cross-sectional study of development carried out with the medical staff of the Casualty and Emergency Operations Department 061 of the Region of Murcia. Data collection was carried out in December 2013 and January 2014. NTP 394 was used. Work satisfaction: general satisfaction scale. DATA ANALYSIS nonparametric tests for 2 samples or k samples depending on type of comparison. RESULTS A participation rate of 88.2% was obtained, in relation to the general job satisfaction, the average of the participants was 69.55 (SD = 14.4). Of the 15 items that make up the questionnaire, « work colleagues » is the factor with which doctors are more satisfied with, indicating that up to an 87%, show a positive assessment on this point. Being the second aspect most respondents valued their « job stability » with a percentage of positive ratings of 76.7%. CONCLUSIONS The main findings clearly demonstrate the importance of inter-professional relations and human potential as the cornerstone in the exercise of the activity of healthcare professionals.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Medicina de emergencias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad de la atención de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality of health care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Unidades móviles de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Emergency medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Servicios médicos de urgencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Job satisfaction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mobile health units</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Satisfacción en el trabajo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Emergency medical services</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Satisfacción laboral de los médicos de Unidades Móviles de Emergencia y del Centro Coordinador de la Gerencia de Urgencias y Emergencias 061. Región de Murcia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Professional satisfaction for doctors of the Mobile Emergency Team and the Emergency Coordinator Office 061. Region of Murcia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
