<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25542870</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pardo, Otilia Bisbal</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega, Federico Pulido</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sebastián, María de Lagarde</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Interest in simplification arises from the need to dispense with nucleoside analogs due to their long-term toxicity. Since the first trials analyzing the safety and effectiveness of the strategy with lopinavir/ritonavir (LPV/r) emerged more than 10 years ago, simplification continues to arouse scientific, clinical and economic interest. At present, there is no consensus on recommendations; interpretations of results are discordant: while some emphasize the greater risk of loss of virologic control, others indicate that the possible virological rebound with this strategy is unrelated to a loss of therapeutic options or to the emergence of resistance to ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitors. This scenario governs the recommendations that can be made in clinical practice; almost all groups agree that candidates should be selected for a simplification strategy with fewer drugs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Simplification</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>HIV</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lopinavir/ritonavir</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>VIH</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia dual</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dual therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Simplificación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monoterapia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2014 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lopinavir/ritonavir en nuevas estrategias de simplificación del tratamiento antirretroviral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Lopinavir/ritonavir in new simplification strategies in antiretroviral therapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
