<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25558745</identifier>
<setSpec>1592-7830</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Boccuni, Valeria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rondinone, Bruna Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Buresti, Giuliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Petyx, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iavicoli, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boccuni, Fabio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cesana, Giancarlo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Persechinot, Benedetta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The INSuLa project consisted of a national survey on health and safety at work involving all the relevant actors such as workers, employers, occupational physicians (MC), worker safety representatives (RLS), prevention and safety service in the workplace (SPSAL). The survey aimed, on one hand, at investigating workers' risk perceptions at the workplace and, on another hand, at exploring the general level of awareness about the enforcement of the Legislative Decree 81/2008 and subsequent amendments. The survey was conducted on a stratified sample of8000 workers representative of the national situation taking into consideration some of the most important socio-demographic and occupational variables, such as gender, geographic area, age, type of contract and sector of activity. The analysis of the results presented here and the subsequent secondary analyses will contribute to identify the needs and critical issues for implementing preventive interventions at the workplaces, also in consideration of the emerging risks and changes in the world of work.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Progetto INSuLa: I'indagine conoscitiva sui lavoratori.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The INSuLa Project: a knowledge survey among workers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Giornale italiano di medicina del lavoro ed ergonomia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
