<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25596651</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7286</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Harto-Castaño, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Desco-Esteban, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borghol-Kassar, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Menezo-Rozalén, J L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this article is to study the effect of unilateral congenital cataract surgery on ocular growth and corneal flattening. METHODS This is a cross-sectional study of 59 patients operated on due to a unilateral congenital cataract. The median age of the patients at the time of diagnosis was 17 months (interquartile range, 5-39 months). The median age at cataract the time of surgery was 28 months (interquartile range, 8-52 months), and the mean follow-up between cataract surgery and assessments was 149.7±69.9 months (range, 30-319 months). Axial length and corneal curvature were measured in both operated and non-operated eyes, comparing the results between them. RESULTS There were no statistically significant differences for axial length growth or corneal flattening between operated and non-operated eyes: axial length (P=.327, Student t test) and corneal curvature (P=.078, Student t test). A sub-analysis was performed using the visual acuity and the age of the patient at the time of surgery. The only statistically significant data (P=.007, Student t test) was a lower axial length in operated eyes compared to non-operated eyes, in the non-deep-amblyopia group. CONCLUSIONS No significant axial length growth modifications were observed between operated and non-operated eyes. Only the non-deep-amblyopia group presented with a lower axial length in the operated eyes compared to non-operated eyes. No significant differences in corneal flattening were found between groups after unilateral congenital cataract surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Queratometría</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Corneal curvature</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Longitud axial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Congenital cataract</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Axial length</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biometría</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cataratas congénitas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Curvatura corneal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biometry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Keratometry</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of unilateral congenital cataract surgery on ocular axial length growth and corneal flattening.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
