<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25617589</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Planells del Pozo, Elena María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz Alférez, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Aliaga, Inmaculada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallardo-Escudero, Alba</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The university stage involves a series of emotional, physiological and environmental changes that will determine consumer patterns that, in many cases, will be maintained and will affect their health. The aim of this study is to analyze the lifestyle (alcohol and tobacco consumption, and levels of physical activity) of female students at the University of Granada. Several authors have noted that the student population is particularly vulnerable to develop risk customs and habits, since the period of university studies is often the time when students take first responsibility for determining their own styles and customs, which in many cases will be maintained throughout its entire life. METHODOLOGY This is a cross / descriptive and analytical study in which 55 students participated in two age groups (18-24 and 25-31 years). A lifestyle-questionnaire was applied to evaluate the type and frequency of alcohol consumption, number of cigarettes smoked daily and physical activity levels (sedentary, light, moderate and severe). RESULTS Alcohol consumption is higher in the older group, and preferably drinks beer and wine; however the younger group shows a pattern of consumption centered on the weekends being preferably consumed distilled beverages. A third of the population smokes with an increase in the number of cigarettes as age increases. There is a positive correlation between snuff and alcohol. A direct positive correlation between tobacco and alcohol was observed. The 88.9% of lesser age group and 52.7% of higher age group show a sedentary-low physical activity. CONCLUSION The need to sensitize the college female population on the benefits of no-consumption of alcohol and snuff, and regular physical exercise is suggested. It would also be advisable to develop protocols of educational intervention in universities promoting healthy living habits.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Nov 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La etapa universitaria no favorece el estilo de vida saludable en las estudiantes granadinas.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: La etapa universitaria conlleva una serie de cambios emocionales, fisiológicos y ambientales que van a determinar unas costumbres y hábitos de riesgoque en muchos casos serán mantenidos a lo largo de la vida y repercutirán en su estado de salud. El objetivo del presente estudio es analizar el estilo de vida (consumo de alcohol, tabaco y niveles de actividad física) de mujeres estudiantes de la Universidad de Granada. Metodología: Se trata de un estudio transversal/descriptivo y analítico en el que han participado 55 estudiantes de dos grupos de edad (18-24 y 25-31años). Se aplicó un cuestionario de estilo de vida evaluando el tipo de alcohol y frecuencia de consumo, cantidad de cigarrillos consumidos diariamente y niveles de actividad física (sedentaria, ligera, moderada e intensa). Resultados: El consumo de alcohol es mayor en el grupo de mayor edad, y con preferencia beben cerveza/vino, sin embargo el grupo más joven muestra un patrón de consumo centrado en los fines de semana siendo las bebidas destiladas las consumidas preferentemente. Una tercera parte de la población fuma con un incremento en el número de cigarros conforme aumenta la edad. Existe una correlación positiva entre tabaco y alcohol. El 88.9% del grupo de menor edad y el 52.7% del grupo de mayor edad tienen una actividad física sedentaria-ligera. Conclusión: Se sugiere la necesidad de concienciar a la población femenina universitaria sobre los beneficios del abandono del consumo de alcohol y tabaco y la práctica regular de ejercicio físico. Además, sería aconsejable desarrollar protocolos de intervención educativa en el ámbito universitario potenciando los hábitos de vida saludables. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The university stage does not favor the healthy life style in women students from Granada].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
