<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25618779</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-4600</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bagney, Alexandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jimenez-Arriero, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torio, Iosune</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivas, Francisco de Paula Jose</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodriguez-Jimenez, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Continuation/maintenance electroconvulsive therapy has been shown to be effective for prevention of relapse in affective and psychotic disorders. However, there is a limited nubber of studies that investigate clinical management, associated costs, and perceived quality variables. MATERIAL AND METHODS A series of 8 cases included during the first 18 months of the Continuation/Maintenance Electroconvulsive Therapy Program of the Psychiatry Department at 12 de Octubre University Hospital is presented. Clinical variables (Clinical Global Impression-Improvement Scale, length of hospitalization, number of Emergency Department visits, number of urgent admissions) before and after inclusion in the continuation/maintenance electroconvulsive therapy program were compared for each patient, as well as associated costs and perceived quality. RESULTS After inclusion in the program, 50.0% of patients reported feeling « much better » and 37.5% « moderately better » in the Clinical Global Impression-Improvement Scale. In addition, after inclusion in the continuation/maintenance electroconvulsive therapy program, patients were hospitalized for a total of 349 days, visited the Emergency Department on 3 occasions, and had 2 urgent admissions, compared to 690 days of hospitalization (P = .012), 26 Emergency Department visits (P = .011) and 22 urgent admissions (P = .010) during the same period before inclusion in the program. Associated direct costs per day of admission were reduced to 50.6% of the previous costs, and costs associated with Emergency Department visits were reduced to 11.5% of the previous costs. As regards perceived quality, 87.5% of patients assessed the care and treatment received as being « very satisfactory », and 12.5% as « satisfactory ». CONCLUSIONS This continuation/maintenance electroconvulsive therapy program has shown to be clinically useful and to have a favourable economic impact, as well as high perceived quality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Continuation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electroconvulsive therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Continuación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coste-efectividad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia electroconvulsiva</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Maintenance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cost-efectiveness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mantenimiento</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical usefulness and economic implications of continuation/maintenance electroconvulsive therapy in a Spanish National Health System public hospital: A case series.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de psiquiatria y salud mental</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
