<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25617578</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fresno-Flores, Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerra-Sánchez, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Rincón, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Malnutrition increases mortality and hospital stay. Increasingly Sanitary institutions follow nutritional screening in order to detect early malnutrition or the risk of developing. There is not universally accepted method for nutritional assessment or screening. OBJECTIVE Determine a fast and reliable method that doesn't require prior training, for the screening and nutritional assessment of heart failure's patients. METHOD Observational study. The nutritional status have been evaluated by Subjective global assessment (SGA), Mini nutritional assesment (MNA) in his short form (MNA-SF) and in his evaluation form (MNA-LF), the nutritional Risk Screnning (NRS 2002), the controlling nutritional status or method Ulibarri's method(- CONUT), the Cardona's method and the Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool (MUST) the nutritional status of 242 patients joined in a high complexity hospital with decompensation of chronic heart failure. There were analyzed the sensibility, specificity, the predictive values, the reasons of verisimilitude, the odds ratio diagnoses and the kappa correlation index, of the different methods compared with the subjective global valuation, which was considered like gold standard. RESULTS The mean age was 75±9. The 50,8%(n=123) were men. The kappa index was MNA -LF : 0,637; MNASF: 0,556; NRS =0,483; MUST =0,197; Cardona =0,188; CONUT =0,076.75. Discusion: Mini Nutritional assessment (MNA) was the method that best value offered, both in its screening stage of assessment in relation with Subjetive global assesment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jan 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado nutricional en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca: análisis de 5 métodos.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introduccion: La malnutrición aumenta la mortalidad y la estancia hospitalaria. Cada vez más instituciones sanitarias adoptan medidas de cribado nutricional con el fin de detectar precozmente la malnutrición o el riesgo de desarrollarla. No existe un método universalmente aceptado para la valoración nutricional. Objetivo: Determinar un método rápido y fiable, que no precise de entrenamiento previo, para el cribado nutricional de pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca. Métodos: Estudio observacional, transversal, en el que se evaluaron mediante la valoración subjetiva global (VSG), el Mini nutritional assesment (MNA) tanto en su versión abreviada o de cribado (MNA-SF) como en su versión extendida o de valoración (MNA-LF), el nutritional Risk Screnning (NRS 2002), el Conocimiento nutricional o método Ulibarri (CONUT), el método Cardona y el Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool (MUST), el estado nutricional de 242 pacientes ingresados en un hospital terciario de alta complejidad con diagnósticos compatibles con descompensación de insuficiencia cardiaca crónica. Se analizaron la sensibilidad, especificidad, los valores predictivos, las razones de verosimilitud, la odds ratio diagnostica y el índice de correlación kappa, de los distintos métodos comparados con la valoración subjetiva global, que fue considerada como prueba cierta. Resultados: La edad media fue de 75±9. El 50,8% (n=123) fueron hombres. El índice de correlación kappa de los distintos métodos de cribado con respecto a la valoración subjetiva global fueron MNA valoración =0,637; MNA cribado =0,556; NRS =0,483; MUST =0,197; Cardona =0,188; CONUT =0,076. Discusión: El Mini Nutritional Assesment fue el método que mejor relación ofreció, tanto en su etapa de cribado como en la de valoración con la Valoración subjetiva global. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Nutritional screening in heart failure patients: 5 methods review].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
