<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2562331</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Elías, L G</dc:author>
<dc:author>de León, L F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bressani, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Samples of cotyledons and whole black beans (Phaseolus vulgaris), Tamazulapa variety were stored during six weeks at 37 degrees C and 90% relative humidity to establish chemical and physical changes which occur during storage, and to determine the role played by the seed coat in the hard-to-cook phenomenon. After the storage period, samples of whole beans were divided in two subsamples, with and without the seed coat. These two samples and the cotyledons were analyzed for cooking time, water absorption, dietary fiber, tannic acid, soluble pectins and phytic acid. Cooking time of the whole beans increased from 99 to more than 480 minutes in the six-weeks period; for the cotyledons this value increased from 45 to 111 minutes. Cooking time of the dehulled bean, stored as whole bean, increased from 45 to 111 minutes. Cooking time of the dehulled bean, stored as whole bean, increased from 45 to 103 minutes. Water absorption in the whole beans and the cotyledons decreased, although in the cotyledons it was higher, due perhaps to the great absorption capacity to the seed coat. No changes were observed in the dietary fiber content of the cotyledons nor in the beans dehulled after storage. However, in the whole grains neutro-detergent fiber decreased, while acid detergent fiber, cellulose and lignin did not present significant changes. On the other hand, soluble pectates decreased in the whole bean and in the cotyledons; nevertheless the tannin content (as tannic acid) decreased only in the whole beans (from 3.28 to 1.64 mg/g). The data obtained suggest that the seed coat plays a significant role in the hard-to-cook process of hardening of the bean, before and during storage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la cáscara sobre el mecanismo de endurecimiento del frijol común (Phaseolus vulgaris).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of the seed coat on the hardening of common beans (Phaseolus vulgaris)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
