<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25638425</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arias Varela, Cesar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Jové, Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sala Farré, Maria Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Osorio Sánchez, Dimelza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Recasens Recasens, Assumpta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Simó Sanahuja, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE In Catalonia the current surveillance systems do not allow to know the true incidence or the health care utilization of acute gastroenteritis (AGE) caused by Campylobacter and Salmonella infections. The aim of this study is to analyze these characteristics. PATIENTS AND METHODS Descriptive study of Campylobacter and Salmonella infections reported in 2002 and 2012 in Catalonia, Spain. We included cases isolated and reported by the laboratory to a regional Surveillance Unit. RESULTS The estimated incidence of Salmonella and Campylobacter AGE decreased by almost 50% and 20% respectively in 2012. Children between one and 4 years old were the most affected in both years. Significant differences in the clinical characteristics and disease duration were observed between Campylobacter and Salmonella. Visits to the Emergency Department and hospitalization rates were 63.7% and 15%, being more frequent among salmonellosis cases. CONCLUSION The estimated incidence of Campylobacter and Salmonella infections has decreased, however rates are still important, as well as it is the health care utilization in both diseases. Current surveillance systems need appropriateness improvements to reach a better control of these infections.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Epidemiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Salmonella</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adecuación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Foodborne diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health care quality access, and evaluation/utilization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedades transmitidas por los alimentos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Incidence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Utilización de servicios de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Incidencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastroenteritis aguda</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Appropriateness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acute gastroenteritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Campylobacter</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Oct 05 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos epidemiológicos y carga asistencial de gastroenteritis agudas por Campylobacter y Salmonella.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Campylobacter and Salmonella acute gastroenteritis: epidemiology and health care utilization].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
