<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25636681</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yahni, Corinne Zara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puig Soler, Rita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perramon Colet, Meritxell</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garcia Puig, Anna M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Identify the level of knowledge, opinions and attitudes of medicines in general population. METHODS Descriptive transversal study realised in a sample of≥18 years old public health users from primary health centres in the city of Barcelona. Sample has been chosen using a two phases sampling, stratified by district, gender and age. Questionnaire administered face-to-face. SPSSv15 used for the analysis. STUDY PERIOD December 2011. RESULTS 484 surveys has been done (IC 95%, α=5%). 53% were women and 21,3% had university studies. Medicine use: 81% had taken medicines in the last 3 months; average of 2,34. TECHNICAL CONCEPTS 80% of medicated people know what they take and its indication. 55,6% don't know active ingredient concept. Only 35% recognise the active ingredient showed in the box of the medicine (3 cases shown) and 44,5% not one. 22,7% know the meaning of security concepts contraindication, adverse effect and drug interaction. 20% ignore. This fact grows with age and reduces with high study levels. OPINION AND ATTITUDE Global rational use of medicines indicator obtains 5,03 from 10: 3,42 opinion and 6,51 attitude. 70% of people think there is no rational use of medicines in general and 21,3% would promote raising awareness. CONCLUSIONS Low level of knowledge and poor attitude and opinion in rational use of medicines have been shown in this study. It is necessary involve citizens and improve their basic knowledge to promote rational use of medicines.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Actitudes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Questionnaires</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Attitudes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patient medication knowledge</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public opinion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuestionarios</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Conocimiento del medicamento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Opinión pública</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Establecimiento de los conocimientos, actitudes y opiniones de la población sobre el uso racional de medicamentos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Establishment of knowledge, attitudes and opinions of general population about rational use of medicines].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
