<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25649338</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Llavero, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calpena, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zubiaga, Lorea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Tovar, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Endocrine pancreatic segregation is regulated by the autonomic nervous system. The parasympathetic system stimulates insulin production by the beta cells and inhibits the adrenergic discharge by the sympathetic nervous system. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of percutaneous neurostimulation (PENS) of dermatome T7, generating a somato-autonomic reflex, whose efferent pathway are the vagal branches that specifically stimulate the pancreas. The effect of this treatment on glycemia, insulin secretion and insulin resistance was investigated. METHODS A prospective randomized clinical trial was performed. Patients with Body Mass Index&gt;30kg/m(2) and diagnosis of diabetes mellitus treated with Metformin were included. Patients were divided into 2 groups: Patients undergoing PENS of dermatome T7 (12 sessions of 30minutes weekly) associated with a 1,200 Kcal/day diet (Group 1) and patients following only a 1,200Kcal/day diet (Group 2). All the patients underwent a blood sample extraction before the treatment and 7 days after finishing it. RESULTS 60 patients were included: 30 in each group. After finishing the treatment, in Group 1 a significant decrease in glycemia (Mean decrease of 62,1mg/dl; P=.024) and HOMA (Mean decrease 1.37; P=.014) was observed. In Group 2, no significant differences between pre and post-treatment values were observed. CONCLUSION PENS of dermatome T7 associated with a 1,200Kcal/day diet achieves a greater reduction in glycemia and insulin resistance than with diet exclusively after 3 months of treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Dermatoma T7</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Percutaneous neurostimulation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dermatome T7</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neuroestimulación percutánea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Homeostasis Model Assessment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulin</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous electric neurostimulation of dermatome T7 improves glycemic profile in obese and type 2 diabetic patients. A randomized clinical study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
