<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25687944</identifier>
<setSpec>2340-3284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pizarro, N E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Martín, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Timoneda, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Encabo, C M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is a childhood epileptic encephalopathy, and is characterized by frequent and difficult to treat seizures associated with mental retardation. The case is presented of a 21 year-old male with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, with bilateral cervical facet joint dislocation fracture at C6-C7 and spinal canal compression as a result of a fall during a seizure. In this case the management of the difficult airway expected in an awake and uncooperative patient, with cervical spinal cord injury is described. An airway management strategy was proposed, that allowed a rapid and safe airway control with the best possible tolerance and maintaining the neck immobilised, so as not to increase neurological injury. Within this strategy, plan A was defined as inhalation induction with sevoflurane to maintain spontaneous breathing and tracheal intubation with Airtraq®. We believe that the Airtraq® video laryngoscope with inhalational induction with sevoflurane is a valid and effective alternative in the management of expected difficult airway.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Inducción inhalatoria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neck immobilization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Video laryngoscope</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inmovilización cervical</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Difficult airway</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Airtraq(®)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inhalation induction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Videolaringoscopio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vía aérea difícil</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de vía aérea difícil con inducción inhalatoria en paciente con síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut y traumatismo cervical.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Management of difficult airway with inhalation induction in a patient with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome and neck injury].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
