<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25688532</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luján, Marcos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mora, Jose Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Every organization with the intention to be oriented to processes management must know it is a system and what are the factors that characterize it. Health care institutions are open and mixed systems. It is in this system where the chain of value of the productive process occurs, generating a very complex integrated management system, as the productive system main recipients are people with health needs. The process management approach in clinical centers, departments and units means that, once the processes have been identified, they have to be set depending on their mission, establishing a boxes and connections architecture known as process maps. Therefore, a map of processes is the graphical representation of the organizational management system, which may be deployed applying modeling techniques at various levels. In this article we will review the conceptual framework of the health care productive system and management with the focus on processes, incorporating didactic products based on experiences from various centers and health services.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arquitectura y diseño de un mapa de procesos en un Servicio de Urología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Architecture and design of a processes map in a Urology Department].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
