<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25710689</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cimas-Hernando, Icíar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzo-González, José R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Constenla, Iria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pato-Pato, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Sativex® is a drug approved for use in the treatment of spasticity in multiple sclerosis. We sought to study the tolerability and effectiveness of this drug product in pathologies beyond the scope of the indications of the product data sheet, by means of its compassionate use. AIM To evaluate the effectiveness and safety of Sativex in pathologies that are not included on the product data sheet, using a compassionate use protocol. PATIENTS AND METHODS A six-month observational study was conducted to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of Sativex in neuropathic pain and in spasticity from causes other than multiple sclerosis. RESULTS A total of 10 patients were included: six females and four males. Side effects appeared in only two of them and the drug product was withdrawn in one case. After starting treatment with Sativex by means of a compassionate use protocol, the consumption of concomitant drugs was reduced by 34.2% (p=0.004), and administration of botulinum toxin was suspended in seven patients (70%). The improvement on the Ashworth spasticity scale was 65.6% (p=0.004) and the score on the analogical visual scale dropped by 49.2% (p=0.026). CONCLUSIONS Sativex may be an interesting therapeutic alternative in patients with spasticity and pain when the treatments that are usually available have been employed but patients' quality of life continues to be significantly compromised.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Mar 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de eficacia y tolerabilidad de Sativex® en uso compasivo.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Evaluacion de eficacia y tolerabilidad de Sativex ® en uso compasivo. 
             Introduccion. Sativex ® es un farmaco aprobado para el tratamiento de la espasticidad en la esclerosis multiple. Hemos querido estudiar la tolerabilidad y eficacia de este farmaco en patologias fuera de indicacion de ficha tecnica, mediante su uso compasivo. Objetivo. Valorar la eficacia y tolerabilidad de Sativex en patologias no incluidas en la ficha tecnica, mediante un protocolo de uso compasivo. Pacientes y metodos. Se realizo un estudio observacional, de seis meses de duracion, para evaluar la eficacia y tolerabilidad de Sativex en el dolor neuropatico y en la espasticidad de causa diferente a la esclerosis multiple. Resultados. Se incluyo un total de 10 pacientes, seis mujeres y cuatro hombres. Solo hubo efectos adversos en dos de ellos, y el farmaco se suspendio en un caso. Tras el inicio del tratamiento con Sativex mediante protocolo de uso compasivo, el consumo de farmacos concomitantes se redujo un 34,2% (p = 0,004), y se suspendio la administracion de toxina botulinica en siete pacientes (70%). La mejoria de la escala de espasticidad de Ashworth fue del 65,6% (p = 0,004) y la escala visual analogica disminuyo su puntuacion un 49,2% (p = 0,026). Conclusion. Sativex puede ser una alternativa terapeutica interesante en pacientes con espasticidad y dolor cuando se han utilizado los tratamientos habituales disponibles, pero los pacientes continuan con afectacion significativa de su calidad de vida. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of the effectiveness and safety of Sativex® in compassionate use].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
