<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25726207</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-Rodríguez, Liliana Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Sobaler, Ana María</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Piero Belmonte, Alexia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ortega Anta, Rosa María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Rodriguez, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze the vitamin D status and its relationship with metabolic syndrome (MS) risk factors in a group of Spanish schoolchildren. MATERIAL AND METHODS A group of 314 Spanish schoolchildren (8-13 years old) from A Coruna, Barcelona, Madrid, Seville and Valencia were studied. Anthropometric data on weight, height, waist and hip circumferences, and triceps skinfold, as well as blood pressure data were collected. Serum levels of glucose, triglycerides, HDL-c and 25-hydroxycholecalciferol (25 (OH) D) were assessed. Following Cook criterion, the following MS risk factors were defined: glucose ≥100 mg/dL; ≥P90 waist circumference; triglycerides&gt; P90, HDL ≤P10; and sistolic and/or diastolic blood pressure &gt; P90. RESULTS Mean serum 25(OH)D were 23.0&#129;±8.6 ng/mL. Forty seven percent of children had hypovitaminosis (20- 30 ng/mL) and 35% had vitamin deficiency (&lt;20 ng/mL). Compared to the first tertile, children in the second tertile have a lower risk of elevated triglycerides (OR = 0.50 [CI = 0.25 to 0.99]; those in the the third tertile had lower risk of high blood pressure and triglycerides (0.60 [CI = 0.42-0.86] and 0.50 [CI = 0.32 to 0.79], respectively). CONCLUSION The prevalence of vitamin D deficiency is high in this group of Spanish schoolchildren. Low serum levels of vitamin D are associated with an increased risk of elevated triglycerides and blood pressure.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Dec 17 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vitamina D serica y factores de riesgo metabolico en un grupo de escolares espanoles.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: Analizar la situacion nutricional en vitamina D y su relacion con diferentes factores de riesgo asociados al sindrome metabolico (SM) en un grupo de escolares espanoles. Materiales y métodos: Se ha estudiado un colectivo de 314 escolares con edades comprendidas entre 8 y 13 anos, residentes en A Coruna, Barcelona, Madrid, Sevilla y Valencia. Se recogieron datos antropometricos de peso, talla, circunferencias de cintura, cadera y pliegue tricipital, datos de tension arterial y en suero se valoraron los niveles de glucosa, trigliceridos, HDL-c y 25-hidroxicolecalciferol (25(OH)D). Teniendo en cuenta el criterio de Cook se ha establecido la presencia de los siguientes factores de riesgo de SM: glucosa ≥100 mg/dL; perimetro de cintura ≥P90; trigliceridos &gt;P90, HDL ≤P10; y presion arterial sistolica o diastolica &gt;P90. Resultados: Los niveles sericos de 25(OH)D medios fueron de 23.0&#129;}8.6 ng/mL. Un 47,1% tuvo niveles indicadores de hipovitaminosis (20-30 ng/mL) y el 35% tuvo deficiencia de la vitamina ( 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Serum vitamin D and metabolic risk factors in a group of Spanish schoolchildren].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
