<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25728878</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9188</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arenas, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isa-Isa, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arrazola-Guerrero, Jisel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Guerrero, Edoardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Tinea capitis is a common fungal infection in children. Diagnosis is confirmed by mycological study, including direct examination of the samples with potassium hydroxide/chlorazol black and culture. Previous studies have reported the presence of "comma hairs" and "corkscrew hairs", as well as short hairs and black dots. AIMS To describe the dermoscopic patterns in the trichoscopic examination in patients with tinea capitis. METHODS A descriptive, observational and cross-sectional study was conducted on 37 patients with tinea capitis, studied during May, 2012, at Dr. Manuel Gea González General Hospital in Mexico, and the Instituto Dermatológico y Cirugía de Piel Dr. Huberto Bogaert Díaz, in the Dominican Republic. Clinical, mycological and dermoscopic evaluations were performed. RESULTS Of the 37 patients included, 28 were of mixed race from Dominican Republic and 9 mixed race cases from Mexico. Seventy six percent were male and 24% female, and 94% were children. The following dermoscopic patterns were confirmed: "comma hairs" (41%), "corkscrew hairs" (22%), short hairs (49%), and black dots (33%). The presence of scales (89%), peripilar casts (46%), alopecia (65%), pustules (8%), and meliceric crusts (16%), were also observed. CONCLUSIONS Dermoscopy in tinea capitis showed the presence of "comma hairs", and "corkscrew hairs". Scales, peripilar casts and alopecia were also found. It would be desirable to establish this diagnostic tool, particularly when an optical microscope or a mycology reference laboratory are not available.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pelos «en sacacorchos»</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dermatoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dermoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tinea capitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tiña de la cabeza</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>“Corkscrew hairs”</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pelos «en coma»</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>“Comma hairs”</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiña de la cabeza: descripción de los hallazgos dermatoscópicos en 37 pacientes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tinea capitis. Dermoscopic findings in 37 patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista iberoamericana de micologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
