<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25739483</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Field-Cortazares, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barreras-Serrano, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tinoco-Gracia, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Valencia, Gilberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escárcega-Ávila, Angélica María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Rickettsiosis caused by Rickettsia rickettsii is capable of infecting vertebrates, including humans. The symptoms are high fever, headache, myalgia, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, and cough. Mortality can be up to 30% in untreated patients. AIMS To prove the existence of rickettsiosis in Ensenada, Baja California, Mexico, because no human cases have been reported. MATERIAL AND METHODS This observational, cross-sectional, descriptive study included 384 samples of humans in Ensenada, Baja California. Antibodies against R. rickettsii were measured with the kit R. rickettsii ELISA(®) Helica Biosystems, Inc., adapted for use in humans using human IgG conjugate antibodies. To determine the sensitivity and specificity, 32 human samples were submitted to IFA. Specific primers were used for the molecular diagnosis of R. rickettsii in dogs and ticks. RESULTS The seroprevalence adjusted rickettsiosis in humans was 2.9% (95% CI: 0.8-5.3), seropositivity was not associated with sex, age, occupation, household, dogs, pet deworming program against ticks, the type of yard, and mobility of the dog between home and the street. CONCLUSIONS With substantial agreement of k between ELISA and IFA, it follows that the results of seroprevalence of this work are reliable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seroprevalencia y factores de riesgo asociados a riquetsiosis (Rickettsia rickettsii) en humanos de Ensenada, Baja California, México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Seroprevalence of risk factors associated with rickettsiosis (Rickettsia rickettsii) in humans in Baja California, Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
