<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25769195</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Amegló-Parejo, María R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nocua-Rodríguez, Ileana I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Carmen-Peña, Marlen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cordero-Prieto, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gajardo-Barrena, María J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nicola, Carla M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra-Sánchez, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Jiménez, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze whether an exercise program can modify glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c), blood pressure (BP), body mass index (BMI), lipids, cardiovascular risk profile (CVR), self-perceived health status (SHS), and pharmaceutical expenditure (PE). DESIGN A randomized, single blind, controlled trial. INTERVENTION program of supervised aerobic physical exercise. Analysis by intention to treat. LOCATION Primary Care: 2 rural health areas. Health Area of Navalmoral. Cáceres. Extremadura. Spain. PARTICIPANTS 100 type 2 diabetic patients, aged 65 to 80 years, sedentary. Distribution: 50% control group (CG) and 50% intervention group (IG). Abandoned 12%. INTERVENTION monitored aerobic exercise: 40minutes, 2 days/week, 3 months. KEY MEASURES HbA1c, BP, BMI, lipid, CVR, SHS, PE. Complications during exercise. RESULTS There were post-intervention differences between groups in HbA1c, BP, BMI, cholesterol and SHS. In the IG, there was a significant decrease in; HbA1c: 0.2±0.4% (95% CI: 0.1 to 0.3), systolic BP: 11.8±8.5mmHg (95% CI: 5.1 to 11.9), BMI: 0.5±1 (95% CI: 0.2 to 0.8), total cholesterol: 14±28.2mg/dl (95% CI: 5.9 to 22.2), LDL: 18.3±28.2mg/dl 95% CI: 10.2 to 26.3), CVR: 6.7±7.7% (95% CI: 4.5 to 8.9), PE: 3.9±10.2 € (95% CI: 0.9 to 6.8), and an increase in SHS; 4.7±5.7 (95% CI: 3 to 6.3). CONCLUSIONS In diabetics over 65 years, a program of monitored aerobic exercise, of easy implementation, improves HbA1c, BP, cholesterol, CVR, PE, and SHS.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary health care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Exercise therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus type 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ejercicio físico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa de ejercicio físico supervisado en pacientes sedentarios mayores de 65 años con diabetes mellitus tipo 2.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of a supervised physical exercise program in sedentary patients over 65 years with type 2 diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
