<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25789640</identifier>
<setSpec>0080-6234</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rosselló, Maria Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verger, Sebastià</dc:author>
<dc:author>De la Iglesia, Begoña</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paz-Lourido, Berta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To identify the psychopedagogical training needs of the pediatric nurses in the largest public hospital of the Balearic Islands, Spain. METHOD This study was developed with a quantitative and qualitative design, where 78 nurses (97.5% of the service) answered a questionnaire, and 15 participated in interviews that were analyzed via content analysis. RESULTS The quantitative results show gaps in the knowledge and psychopedagogical skills of the staff. These aspects could facilitate the development of tasks tailored to the personality and the psychoevolutional time of children with chronic diseases, as well as to the emotional state of families. The qualitative data was organized into four categories: family support; hospital and education; psychopedagogical training and difficulties in practice. The little communication between nurses and teachers is evident. CONCLUSION The data reinforces the need to implement training strategies and interdisciplinary work among health professionals, educators and families.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades de formación psicopedagógica para la atención de niños con enfermedad crónica: percepciones de enfermería hospitalaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Needs of psychopedagogical training for the care of children with chronic disease: perceptions of hospital nursing].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista da Escola de Enfermagem da U S P</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
