<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25791307</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Niño, Larry</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Characterizing breastfeeding in Puerto Carreño and identifying factors associated with providing breast-milk for the newborn, exclusive breastfeeding and total breastfeeding. METHODS This descriptive, cross-sectional study, using structured individual and non-random surveys, involved 609 mothers. The statistical analysis methods included univariate and bivariate analysis, survival curves, binary logistic regression and Cox proportional hazard models. RESULTS The duration of total and exclusive breastfeeding was higher than reported times at national and regional level in most cases. The main factors associated with breastfeeding were related to occupation, family background, Indigenous status, previous maternal experience and access to healthcare services. CONCLUSIONS Exclusive breastfeeding was influenced more by the mother'&#146;s occupation, while the total duration of breastfeeding was influenced by home-based family support network. The results are significant regarding planning intervention measures addressed towards improving breastfeeding habits in the target municipality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de la lactancia materna y factores asociados en Puerto Carreño, Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characterizing breastfeeding and associated factors in Puerto Carreño, Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
