<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25814171</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1879</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rosa Guillamón, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tarraga Marcos, Loreto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez García, Pedro L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gálvez Casas, Arancha</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Cantó, Eliseo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Soto, Juan J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tarraga Lopez, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aerobic capacity is a powerful physiological indicator of the overall health status. The objective of this study was to analyse the relationship between aerobic capacity and quality of life in a sample of 298 (159 girls) school children aged 8-12 years. Aerobic capacity was tested using the Course-Navette test. Quality of life was assessed using the KIDSCREEN-10 Index scale. Males showed higher performance in the Course-Navette test and highest values of VO2max (P&lt;.001 for both). ANOVA statistical analysis showed that the quality of life was significantly higher in school children with increased level of aerobic capacity compared to those with a low level (P=.001). Children with high aerobic capacity showed higher quality of life scores in relation to their peers with low scores (P&lt;.001). As for the females, significant differences were found among those with high aerobic capacity level and their peers low levels (P&lt;.031). The results of this study suggest that school children with higher level of aerobic capacity show better results in the quality of life index. Long-term intervention studies are needed to verify if an aerobic capacity development programme may upgrade the quality of life of children and adolescents.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Physical exercise</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Physical fitness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niños</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Condición física</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular fitness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Capacidad cardiovascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ejercicio físico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capacidad aeróbica y calidad de vida en escolares de 8 a 12 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Aerobic capacity and quality of life in school children from 8 to 12].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Clinica e investigacion en arteriosclerosis : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Arteriosclerosis</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
