<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25860362</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cordero, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palavecino, Patricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Horta, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Marcelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dotte, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poniachik, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chesta, Caterina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro, Ariel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Multidetector computed tomography (MDCT) of the abdomen, with use of contrast medium, is able to detect and differentiate most focal liver lesions. AIM To determine the prevalence and features of benign focal liver lesions (BFLL) detected by abdominal MDCT. PATIENTS AND METHODS We reviewed the reports of contrast abdominal MDCT performed to outpatients between August 2011 and July 2012. Clinical data of examined patients and imaging findings in terms of description of the hepatic parenchyma and the presence of BFLL, were recorded. RESULTS Data from 1,184 studies were analyzed. Of these, 461 studies (38.4%) reported BFLL. The most prevalent lesions were simple cysts in 290 studies (24%) and hemangiomas in 61 studies (5.1%), granuloma-calcification in 39 (3.2%), focal nodular hyperplasia in 19 (1.6%) and one adenoma. If patients with known causes of liver disease were excluded, the prevalence of BFLL did not change substantially (lesions were found in 396 (37.5%) patients). Compared with livers with signs of damage, normal livers had more cystic lesions (27 and 16.2% respectively, p = 0.014) and hemangiomas (5.3 and 1.1% respectively, p = 0.043). CONCLUSIONS BFLL are very common findings in MDCT studies. Most of these lesions are simple cysts and hemangiomas.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones focales hepáticas benignas: un hallazgo frecuente a la tomografía computada.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Benign focal liver lesions detected by computed tomography: Review of 1,184 examinations].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
