<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2588074</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lozano, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Infante, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Langer, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bobadilla, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frenk Mora, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Five years after the creation of the Center for Public Health Research (SPHR), this essay reviews its origins and evolution and points to the challenges it will face in the future. The seven basic organizational principles underlying the academic development of the Center are described. In the quantitative aspect, the institution's growth is reflected in the rapidly increasing trend in the number of researchers, projects and scientific publications, as well as in the volume of the external financial resources received. In the qualitative aspect, the article highlights the ever growing number of themes approached by the seven lines of research, the elaboration of conceptual models, the creation of data bases and the methodological development. Among the most important challenges of the CPHR in the future are: (1) solving existing organizational problems; (2) building links with the decision makers and (3) establishing an equilibrium between relevance and excellence in public health research.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en la investigación en salud pública. Cinco años de labores del Centro de Investigaciones en Salud Pública, 1984-1989.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Advances in public health investigation. 5 years' work of the Center for Research in Public Health, 1984-1989].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
