<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25919660</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6384</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Fontana, Gastón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Octavio A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Laur, José Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vidal-Mora, Ivar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For six decades, it has been a part of the conventional medical wisdom that higher levels of testosterone increase the risk of prostate cancer. This belief is mostly derived from the well-documented regression of prostate cancer after surgical or pharmacological castration. However, there is an absence of scientific data supporting the concept that higher testosterone levels are associated with an increased risk of prostate cancer. Moreover, men with hypogonadism have substantial rates of prostate cancer in prostatic biopsies, suggesting that low testosterone has no protective effect against the development of prostate cancer. Moreover, prostate cancer rate is higher in elderly patients when hormonal levels are low. These results argue against an increased risk of prostate cancer with testosterone replacement therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>prostate cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>familial; testosterone; hypogonadism; hormone replacement therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Apr 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de reemplazo con testosterona y cáncer de próstata: ¿la caída de un paradigma?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Por casi seis décadas ha sido parte de la cultura médica en general, que los niveles altos de testosterona incrementan el riesgo de padecer o agravar un cáncer de próstata. Esta creencia se ha derivado fundamentalmente de la bien documentada regresión del cáncer de próstata luego de la castración médica o quirúrgica. Sin embargo, no existe evidencia científica que apoye la idea de que niveles altos de testosterona están asociados con un incremento del riesgo de cáncer de próstata. Más aún, los hombres con hipogonadismo tienen una tasa substancialmente alta de cáncer de próstata detectado por biopsia, lo que sugiere que los niveles bajos de testosterona no tienen un efecto protector en el desarrollo de cáncer de próstata y, además, la tasa de cáncer de próstata es más alta en los pacientes de edades avanzadas cuando sus niveles hormonales son más bajos. Estos argumentos tienden a demostrar que no existiría un incremento del riesgo de padecer un cáncer de próstata asociado a la terapia de reemplazo con testosterona. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Testosterone replacement therapy and prostate cancer: the downfall of a paradigm?].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medwave</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
