<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25910550</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sobradillo Ecenarro, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villena Garrido, Maria Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ávila Martínez, Regulo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llopis Pastor, Estefanía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Guzmán, Estibaliz</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The quality of care received by patients is a basic element of modern medicine. Medical residents or interns are essential within the healthcare system, but their lack of experience can raise concerns about the quality of care given. A registrar or specialist has greater knowledge and skills, while a resident has greater motivation and enthusiasm. The aim of training programs is to prepare residents to provide high quality care. This requires close supervision that seems to be lacking, with the consequent impact on both healthcare quality and academic results. The so-called "July effect" refers to the diminished quality of care during the summer months when resident physicians switch over. The results of studies analysing this effect vary widely, but the loss of efficacy during these months does seem to be real. Pulmonology is one of medical specialties that generates the least demand for internships and residencies, but it is impossible to determine if this affects the quality of care. The high prevalence of respiratory diseases and the latest diagnostic and therapeutic advances may mean that this situation will change in coming years.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pulmonology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Training</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medical residents</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neumología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Formación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Médico Interno Residente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>July</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Julio</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Provision of care by medical residents and the impact on quality.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
