<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25921323</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Font, Albert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Areal, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bonet, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caro, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chabrera, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zabalegui, Adelaida</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of this study is to develop a Spanish version of the Satisfaction With Decision scale (SWDs) and analyse the psychometric properties of validity and reliability. DESIGN An observational, descriptive study and validation of a tool to measure satisfaction with the decision. SETTING Urology, Radiation oncology, and Medical oncology Departments of the Hospital Universitari Germans Trias i Pujol, Institut Català d'Oncologia and the Institut Oncològic del Vallès - Hospital General de Catalunya. PARTICIPANTS A total of 170 participants diagnosed with prostate cancer, and who could read and write in Spanish and gave their informed consent. MAIN MEASUREMENTS A translation, back-translation and cross-cultural adaptation to Spanish was performed on the SWDs. The content validity, criterion validity, construct validity and reliability (internal consistency and stability) of the Spanish version were evaluated. RESULTS The SWDs contains 6 items with 5-item Likert scales. A Spanish version (ESD) was obtained that was linguistically and conceptually equivalent to the original version. Criterion validity, the ESD correlated with "satisfaction with the decision" using a linear analogue scale, was significant (r=0.63, P&lt;.01) for all items. The factorial analysis showed a unique dimension to explain 82.08% of the variance. The ESD showed excellent results in terms of internal consistency (Cronbach alpha=0.95) and good test-retest reliability with intraclass correlation coefficient of 0.711. CONCLUSIONS The ESD is a validated Spanish scale to measure the satisfaction with the decisions taken in health, and demonstrates a correct validity and reliability.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Neoplasias de próstata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reproducibilidad de resultados</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prostatic neoplasms</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Decision support Techniques</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Participación del paciente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patient participation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reproducibility of results</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patient satisfaction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Satisfacción del paciente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Técnicas de apoyo para la decisión</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión española de la Satisfaction With Decision scale: adaptación transcultural, validez y fiabilidad.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Spanish version of the Satisfaction With Decision scale: cross-cultural adaptation, validity and reliability].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
