<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25945992</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4464</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dover, Robert V H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Mattar, Ornella</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Herrera, Eliana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to understand the meaning of social capital in relation to type 2 diabetes according to gender, within an urban setting in Colombia, based on a qualitative design for symbolic interactionism. Twenty-four women and 16 men with diabetes, family members, and healthcare personnel participated in six focus groups. A total of 850 codes emerged that comprised a set of 142 codes for ego, alter, and alter ego. Three categories and 20 subcategories were identified for the "coding paradigm design". The meaning differed between men and women. Social ties in social networks, created daily through trust and solidarity for care, were valued differently due to the social experiences and events resulting from self-confidence, self-efficacy for social support, and mainly self-esteem vis-à-vis management and control of the disease. An individual's social resources are reified for the management and care of the disease as a strategy to mitigate health inequalities.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El significado del capital social "individual" en diabéticos receptores de cuidado en un contexto urbano colombiano.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The meaning of "individual" social capital for diabetics receiving care in a Colombian city].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cadernos de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
