<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25953707</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Suárez-Cuartín, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torrejón, Montserrat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torrego, Alfons</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belda, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Plaza, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos-Barbón, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crespo, Astrid</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateus, Eder</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giner, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Recent studies have found variability in asthma inflammatory phenotypes determined by the inflammatory cells in induced sputum (IS). The aim of this study was to determine the frequency and factors affecting inflammatory phenotype variability in IS. METHODS Retrospective observational study that included 61 asthmatic patients who underwent at least two IS tests over a period of 5 years. They were classified according to their baseline inflammatory phenotype and subsequently grouped according to phenotype variability (persistent eosinophilic, persistent non-eosinophilic and intermittent eosinophilic). Demographic, clinical and functional data and factors potentially influencing IS variability were collected in all cases. RESULTS Of the 61 patients, 31 (50.8%) had a change with respect to baseline inflammatory phenotype. Of these, 16 (51.6%) were eosinophilic, 5 (16.1%) neutrophilic, 1 (3.2%) mixed and 9 (29.1%) paucigranulocytic. According to phenotype variability, 18 patients (29.5%) were classified as persistent eosinophilic, 17 (27.9%) non-persistent eosinophilic, and 26 (42.6%) intermittent eosinophilic. Smoking and recent asthma exacerbation were significantly associated with increased risk of variability of the IS inflammatory phenotype (OR=6.44; p=.013; 95% CI=1.49-27.80 and OR=5.84; p=.022; 95% CI=1.29-26.37, respectively). CONCLUSION Half of asthma patients, predominantly those with eosinophilic phenotype, present a change in IS inflammatory phenotype. This variability is associated with smoking and recent asthma exacerbation. Data suggest these factors can modify the classification of IS inflammatory phenotype in clinical practice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Phenotype</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Eosinófilos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neutrófilos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Esputo inducido</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neutrophils</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fenotipo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asthma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Eosinophils</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Induced sputum</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in Asthma Inflammatory Phenotype in Induced Sputum. Frequency and Causes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
