<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25987369</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arnedo Pena, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortés Miró, Pascual</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romeu García, María Angeles</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Sidro, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miravet Sorribes, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bellido Blasco, Juan B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil Fortuño, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To describe an outbreak of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) in two schools METHODS This was a prospective, observational study of an outbreak of MDR-TB in 2 schools located in the towns of Onda and Nules, in the Spanish province of Castellon, from the moment of detection in November 2008 until November 2014, including patient follow-up and contact tracing. RESULTS Five cases of MDR-TB were diagnosed. Overall attack rate was 0.9%, and among the contacts traced, 66 had latent tuberculous infection, with an infection rate of 14.4%. Molecular characterization of the 5M. tuberculosis isolates was performed by restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) analysis of the IS6110 sequence. In all 5 patients, cultures were negative at 4-month follow-up, showing the efficacy of the treatment given. No recurrence has been reported to date. CONCLUSIONS In the context of globalization and the increased prevalence of MDR-TB, outbreaks such as the one presented here are only to be expected. Contact tracing, strict follow-up of confirmed cases, the availability of fast diagnostic techniques to avoid treatment delay, and chemoprophylaxis, together with the molecular characterization of strains, are still essential.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Multidrug-resistant tuberculosi</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Outbreak</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colegio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Brote</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis multirresistente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spoligotyping</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Schools</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outbreak of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in two secondary schools.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
