<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>25986975</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Pérez, Juana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Onieva-González, Francisco Gabriel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matito-Díaz, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco-Fernández, Gerardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Guerra, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galeano-Díaz, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Inflammatory pseudotumour is a rare entity, considered benign, and characterised by inflammatory cell mesenchymal proliferation. CLINICAL CASE The case is presented 70 year-old man with fever of unknown origin syndrome. He was diagnosed with liver abscesses (one segment IV, adjacent to gallbladder fundus and segment VI), who progressed slowly after antibiotic treatment. In the absence of a diagnosis, although fine needle puncture-aspiration and different imaging tests were performed, elective surgery was decided. The intra-operative histopathology reported the existence of an inflammatory pseudotumour. CONCLUSIONS Inflammatory pseudotumours are clinically classified into different types according to their aetiology, varying therapeutic management based on the same. It is very difficult to diagnose because of the absence of symptoms, blood disorders, or specific radiological findings. Definitive diagnosis often requires histopathological confirmation, in most cases by percutaneous liver puncture, but sometimes exploratory laparotomy or even performing a hepatectomy for confirmation is necessary. The natural history of inflammatory pseudotumour is its regression; thus conservative management may be used through regular checks until resolution, or can be treated with antibiotics, anti-inflammatories and even corticosteroids. Surgical resection is indicated for persistent unresolved systemic symptoms despite medical treatment, in those situations where growth is evident, with or without symptoms, when involving the hepatic hilum, and finally, in case where the possibility of malignancy cannot be ruled out.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Fiebre de origen desconocido</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inflammatory Pseudotumour</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoplasias hepáticas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pseudotumor inflamatorio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fever of unknown origin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatic neoplasms</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudotumor inflamatorio hepático. Importancia de la anatomía patológica intraoperatoria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inflammatory pseudotumour of the liver. Importance of intra-operative histopathology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
