<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26021103</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dobarganes-Barlow, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negrete-Corona, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otero-Cámara, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Frías, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Vargas, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGOUND Gonarthrosis is a degenerative condition that importantly limits an individua's performance. Surgical treatment is used in patients with important functional limitation and severe pain. Knee arthroplasty is one of the surgeries with the best functional results in patients with this condition. However, its limitations include the risk of heavy bleeding and the resulting need for blood transfusion. The objective of this study was to assess the need for blood transfusion in patients undergoing knee arthroplasy in whom the cell saver was used postoperatively and find out the cost differences between the cell saver and standard blood transfusion. METHODS Retrospective, cross-sectional, retrolective trial including 300 records of patients who underwent knee arthroplasty at Hospital Angeles Querétaro that included the use of the cell saver and allogeneic blood transfusion from October 2001 to June 2013. RESULTS Only 3 of the 246 operated knees required allogeneic blood transfusion. There were no complications/infections resulting from the use of the cell saver. Mean age of patients was 67.1 +/- 9.78 years; females were predominant, as they were 141 (60.5%), compared to 92 (39.5%) males. The blood collected with the cell saver ranged from 150 to 1,225 ml with a mean of 318 +/- 100.6 ml and was retransfused to each patient. CONCLUSIONS Cell saver use in patients subjected to knee arthroplasty importantly decreases the need for allogeneic blood transfusion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de recuperador de sangre durante la artroplastía de rodilla.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cell saver use during knee arthroplasty].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
