<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26020663</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vera-Lastra, Olga Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Gutiérrez, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coria-Moctezuma, Luis Alonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Pilar Cruz-Domínguez, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Systemic sclerosis (SSc) is a systemic autoimmune disease characterized by fibrosis, immunological and vascular abnormalities. Cerebral hypoperfusion can be caused by cerebral ischemia. Cognitive impairment (CI) are a major cause of morbidity in SSc The aim of this study is to estimate the frequency of alterations in cerebral perfusion (CP) in SSc patients with CI. METHODS We studied 88 patients with SSc. The Montreal Test (MT) was given to all patients to evaluate CI. To 15 patients with CI and without systemic hypertension, diabetes mellitus, cerebrovascular disease, vasculitis, hypothyroidism, depression, and drugs that interfere with the cognitive assessment, the PC was measured by cerebral gammagram (CG). RESULTS Of the 88 patients with ES, 58 had CI by MT. A decrease in CP was observed in following lobes: frontal in 9 of 15 patients, temporal in 7 of 15, and parietal in 3 of 15. Concordance between MT and CG was 60% for the frontal, 46% for the temporal and parietal 13%. CONCLUSIONS The CI is common in SSc. A decrease in CP was more frequent in the frontal lobe, predominating in older patients and with longer duration of SSc.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Gammagram cerebral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cerebral perfusion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Systemic sclerosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cognitive impairment</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones en la perfusión cerebral en pacientes con esclerosis sistémica y deterioro cognitivo.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la esclerosis sistémica (ES) es una enfermedad autoinmune, sistémica, caracterizada por fibrosis, alteraciones inmunológicas y vasculares. La hipoperfusión cerebral puede ser causada por isquemia. Los trastornos cognitivos son causa importante de morbilidad. El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar la frecuencia de alteraciones en la perfusión cerebral (PC) en pacientes con ES y deterioro cognitivo (DC). Métodos: se estudiaron 88 pacientes con ES. A todos se les aplicó el Test de Montreal (TM) para evaluar el DC. A 15 pacientes con DC que cumplieron con los criterios (sin hipertensión arterial sistémica, diabetes mellitus, evento vascular cerebral, vasculitis, hipotiroidismo, depresión, sin ingesta de fármacos que interfieran con la evaluación cognitiva), se les midió la PC mediante Gamagrama Cerebral Perfusorio (GCP).Resultados: de los 88 pacientes con ES, 58 tuvieron DC con el TM. La PC se encontró disminuida en 12/15. La disminución de la PC se observó en los siguientes lóbulos (frontal en 9/15; temporal en 7/15, y parietal en 3/15. La concordancia entre el TM y GC fue 60 % para el lóbulo frontal, 46 % para el lóbulo temporal y 13 % parietal.Conclusiones: el DC es frecuente en la ES, la disminución de la PC fue más común en el lóbulo frontal, predominado en los pacientes de mayor edad y tiempo de evolución de la ES. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Alterations in cerebral perfusion in patients with systemic sclerosis and cognitive impairment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
