<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2602609</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vilacosta, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodrigo, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zarco, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>O'Connor, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pinto, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intraoperative echocardiography with Doppler color flow imaging technique can provide the surgeon with an immediate and direct assessment of cardiac anatomy and function. To determine the utility of this recent technique, we have examined 15 patients pre, per, and postoperatively with Doppler color flow imaging. The intraoperative study was performed before and after cardiopulmonary bypass. A sterile transducer was placed directly on the epicardial surface of the heart, and multiple views were recorded. Intraoperative echocardiography with Doppler color flow imaging technique demonstrated excellent correlation with preoperative and postoperative findings, allowing an immediate evaluation of the surgical results. These preliminary results suggest that intraoperative Doppler color flow imaging technique is a valuable adjunct in heart surgery. It is particularly useful in valve repair, and in surgical repair of congenital heart disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la ecocardiografía intraoperatoria mediante eco-Doppler color en cirugía cardíaca. Estudio preliminar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Role of intraoperative echo-Doppler color echocardiography in cardiac surgery. Preliminary study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
