<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26049666</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1879</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Auguet, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porras, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guiu-Jurado, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berlanga, Alba</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aragonès, Gemma</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) has become the most common liver disease in developed countries, covering a spectrum of pathological conditions ranging from single steatosis to non-alcoholic steatohepatitis, cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma. Its pathogenesis has been often interpreted by the "double-hit" hypothesis, where the lipid accumulation in the liver is followed by proinflammatory mediators inducing inflammation, hepatocellular injury and fibrosis. Nowadays, a more complex model suggests that free fatty acids and their metabolites could be the true lipotoxic agents that contribute to the development of NAFLD and hepatic insulin resistance, suggesting a central role for metabolic lipases in that process.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Lipasas metabólicas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolic lipases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad del hígado graso no alcohólica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lipotoxicidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lipotoxicity, Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de las lipasas metabólicas y la lipotoxicidad en el desarrollo de esteatosis hepática y esteatohepatitis no alcohólica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Role of metabolic lipases and lipotoxicity in the development of non-alcoholic steatosis and non-alcoholic steatohepatitis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Clinica e investigacion en arteriosclerosis : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Arteriosclerosis</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
