<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26070223</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Botros, Raif M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hendawy, Laila M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eid, Yara M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nasr, Merihan S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sabry, Inas M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abdelbaky, Rania S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Vitamin D deficiency is becoming endemic in many parts of the world. AIM To study vitamin D status in Egyptian females of different age groups. SUBJECTS AND METHODS A cross-sectional study was conducted on 404 females, who were categorized into group 1 (51 nursing females); group 2 (50 pregnant females); group 3 (208 females of childbearing age); group 4 (38 elderly females); and group 5 (57 geriatric females). Females completed a questionnaire regarding dietary calcium and vitamin D intake, sun exposure, and clothing habits, and performed laboratory tests including calcium, PO4, alkaline phosphatase, intact PTH, and 25-OH vitamin D levels. RESULTS Median and IQR of vitamin D levels across groups 1, 2, 3 and 5 were in the deficient range, being lowest in groups 3, 5, and 1, respectively. Vitamin D deficiency was found in 72.6% of the nursing group, 54% of the pregnant group, 72% of the childbearing age group, 39.5% of the elderly group, and 77.2% of the geriatric group. Vitamin D was significantly higher in non-veiled females [23ng/dl] as compared to veiled females [16.7ng/dl]. Vitamin D levels with poor, fair, and good sun exposure were 14.1, 14, and 37ng/dl, respectively. CONCLUSION These results show a high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency among healthy Egyptian females.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pregnancy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parathyroid disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sol</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vitamin D deficiency</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad metabólica del calcio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Embarazo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad paratiroidea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calcium metabolic disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sun</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Déficit de vitamina D</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin D deficiency among healthy Egyptian females.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
