<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2609226</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lobato-Mendizábal, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galindo-Rodríguez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marín-López, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarez-Suárez, Y</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We analyzed the clinical and epidemiological characteristics of seven patients with AIDS who were infected through contaminated needles or blood letting equipment; no other risk factor was identified in these patients. In the Dirección de Epidemiología de los Servicios Coordinados de la Salud in the state of Puebla, 37 cases of AIDS were registered up to June 15, 1988. Nineteen percent of these were paid donors between the ages of 26 and 45. There were five males and two females. All of them had weight loss, fever, chronic diarrhea and adenomegaly. Six had respiratory complaints, four candidiasis and two pulmonary tuberculosis. In the state of Puebla, there are 517 paid donors registered as carriers of Human Immune Deficiency Virus (HIV). We do not know the number of blood donations and therefore the number of receptors. In this state, 52 percent of AIDS cases are post-transfusional and we fear an increase. We propose that all paid blood donors should be considered as a high risk group.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Donadores sanguíneos remunerados: un nuevo grupo de riesgo para desarrollar SIDA en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Paid blood donors: a new risk group for the development of AIDS in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
