<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26118003</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gómez García, Carmen Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrillo García, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Léon Navarro, Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION This paper analyzes, by a descriptive study, the closing of the Basic Hospital of the Defence the restructuration of the Santa María del Rosell University Hospital, and the moving of both to a new hospital: the Santa Lucía University Hospital. This process was carried out in coordination with a coincident objective: the creation of an only management staff for the area. The aim is the analysis of the opening of a hospital complex that coincided with the restructuration of the health area. METHODOLOGY This paper analyzes the actions in relation to the scheduling, training and moving, that concerned above 600 hospital beds and 275.000 inhabitants. Analyzes the intervention in infrastructures, logistics and training. The whole process is seen from de nursery point of view, as a professional stratus that knows the roles of the hospital and personnel. The period of the study comprises since October2010, beginning of the activity in the new hospital, to November 2011, moment of the effective culmination of the move. RESULT The result of the works carried out was the transfer of people and roles in a very short time (eleven months). All the patients were moved without any event. CONCLUSION During the whole process healthcare continuity was obtained, whit the less economic impact, as in patients and professionals. From the point of view of future and practical implications, the basis for a modern and qualified provision of services have been established; and best results from means provided have been obtained in relation to health care quality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de enfermería: proceso de creacín de un compleoj hospitaalrio. AÁea II del Servicio Murciano de Salud (Cartagena).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[NURSING MANAGEMENT: CREATION OF A HOSPITAL COMPLEX. AREA II OF THE MURCIA HEALTH CARE SERVICE (CARTAGENA)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
