<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26123157</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cazarez-Aguilar, Marcel Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morgan-Ortiz, Fred</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bolívar-Rodríguez, Martín Adrián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna-Madrid, Eduardo Esaú</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Mesenteric cysts are very rare abdominal growths, generally asymptomatic, and which are usually detected incidentally while performing a physical examination or an imaging test. Complications such as infections, haemorrhage, torsion, rupture, or bowel obstruction, are seldom found in this pathology, but they can be a cause of acute abdomen. The purpose of this report is to describe the characteristics and the clinical outcome of a male patient with an infected mesenteric pseudocyst of the jejunum. CLINICAL CASE A 49 year-old male was admitted to the emergency department with 6-day onset of abdominal pain, bowel obstruction signs, palpable tumour located in the upper hemi-abdomen, systemic inflammatory response syndrome, 36,100/mm(3) white cells, 4.21 ng/ml procalcitonin, abdominal computed tomography scan with evidence of a mesenteric cystic tumour. An exploratory laparotomy was performed, finding the presence of a mesenteric pseudocyst of the jejunum with infection signs, extirpated and sent for histopathological examination. The clinical progress of the patient was satisfactory with the discharge of the patient 7 days after the surgical intervention. CONCLUSION These cysts can debut as an acute abdomen due to haemorrhage, infection, obstruction and/or bowel perforation, complications can be life threatening if not detected and surgically treated at an early stage by performing a resection of the pseudocysts, with or without bowel resection, depending on the location and the size of the cyst.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Infection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Case report</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Jejunum</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mesenteric cyst</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quiste mesentérico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reporte de caso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Yeyuno</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudoquiste mesentérico infectado en yeyuno: reporte de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infected jejunal mesenteric pseudocyst: A case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
