<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26159366</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez-García, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruescas-García, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Santos, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Fernández, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puerto-Puerto, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alberca-Páramo, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Pneumoperitoneum is defined as the existence of extraluminal air in the abdominal cavity. In 80-90% of cases is due to perforation of a hollow organ. However, in 10-15% of cases, it is nonsurgical pneumoperitoneum. OBJECTIVE The case of a patient undergoing mechanical ventilation, developing abdominal compartment syndrome tension pneumoperitoneum is reported. CLINICAL CASE Female, 75 years old asking for advise due to flu of long term duration. Given her respiratory instability, admission to the Intensive Care Unit is decided. It is then intubated and mechanically ventilated. Chest x-ray revealed a large pneumoperitoneum but no pneumothorax neither mediastinum; and due to the suspicion of viscera perforation with clinical instability secondary to intra-abdominal hypertension box, emergency surgery was decided. CONCLUSIONS When discarded medical history as a cause of pneumoperitoneum, it is considered that ventilation is the most common cause. Benign idiopathic or nonsurgical pneumoperitoneum, can be be treated conservatively if the patient agrees. But if intraabdominal hypertension prevails, it can result in severe respiratory and hemodynamic deterioration, sometimes requiring abdominal decompression to immediately get lower abdominal pressure and thus improve hemodynamic function.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Abdominal pressure</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pneumoperitoneum</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ventilación mecánica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mechanical ventilation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Presión abdominal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neumoperitoneo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Barotrauma</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome compartimental abdominal por neumoperitoneo a tensión secundario a barotrauma. Presentación de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Abdominal compartment syndrome by tension pneumoperitoneum secondary to barotrauma. Presentation case].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
