<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26162488</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-García, Héctor Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Elizondo, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores-Villalba, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cavazos-García, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Gallbladder agenesis is a very rare congenital abnormality of the biliary tract. The diagnosis is made during surgery, because all preoperative studies have failed to identify this malformation. The purpose of this article is to present a case of gallbladder agenesis diagnosed during surgery, its management, and a review of the literature. CLINICAL CASE The case involves a sixty-two year- old female, referring to repeated biliary colic symptoms. The abdominal ultrasound diagnosed cholelithiasis. It was impossible to identify the gallbladder during surgery. Diagnosis was confirmed by intra-operative cholangiography. DISCUSSION Preoperative diagnostic workup has failed to recognise patients with gallbladder agenesis. It is currently recommended to abandon the surgery once this diagnosis is suspected and confirm it by a cholangio-magnetic resonance scan in order to avoid a bile duct injury. CONCLUSIONS Agenesis of the gallbladder is a rare congenital abnormality of the biliary tree. Every surgeon must keep this rare entity in mind when a "difficult dissection" or an anatomic variant is identified during surgery, and make use of an intra-operative cholangiography, mainly to prevent a bile duct injury.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anormalidades congénitas de la vesícula biliar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Malformación de la vesícula biliar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Agenesia vesícula biliar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Congenital abnormalities of gallbladder</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gallbladder malformation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Agenesis of gallbladder</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agenesia de la vesícula biliar. Reporte de caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Gallbladder agenesis. Case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
