<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26179967</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-4805</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bauk, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costa, H A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caligiuri, S I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION A low number of patients who are treated with antihypertensive drugs achieve therapeutic goals. Home blood pressure monitoring is an excellent tool for studying this population. OBJECTIVES To determine the prevalence of patients with controlled and uncontrolled hypertension, as well as white-coat-effect and masked hypertension, and to evaluate the relationship with target organ damage in different groups. METHODS Blood pressure readings were performed simultaneously in the clinic and in the home using the same validated oscillometric equipment on 83 hypertensive patients on treatment with 2 or more antihypertensive drugs. They were then classified into 4 groups according to the cut-off values of the clinic and home blood pressure measurements. Left ventricular mass index, carotid intima media thickness, and microalbuminuria as markers of target organ damage, were also evaluated. RESULTS Controlled blood pressure was present in 32.5%, 30.2% had sustained hypertension. The white coat effect was seen in 26.5%, while 10.8% were masked uncontrolled hypertension. Left ventricular mass index was higher in patients with no ambulatory control compared to controlled patients, and carotid IMT was also higher too in uncontrolled and white coat effect groups than controlled patients. CONCLUSIONS More than one third of our patients who were treated with 2 or more drugs were not properly controlled, and they had significantly greater target organ damage than controlled patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hipertensión de bata blanca</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monitorización domiciliaria de presión arterial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Home blood pressure monitoring</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>White coat hypertension</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Target organ damage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lesión de órgano diana</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad clínica de la monitorización domiciliaria de la presión arterial en pacientes bajo tratamiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Clinical utility of home blood pressure monitoring in patients under treatment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Hipertension y riesgo vascular</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
