<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26177436</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Olvera-Acevedo, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera-Lastra, Olga Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-Domínguez, María del Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peralta-Amaro, Ana Lilia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The metabolic syndrome (MS) is a group of cardiovascular risk factors whose prevalence is increased in rheumatic diseases. The aim of this study was to estimate de prevalence of MS and insulin resistance (IR) in systemic sclerosis (SSc). METHODS Fifty five patients with SSc were included. The World Health Organization criteria were used to define MS. Demographic, anthropometric and blood pressure data were recorded. Blood glucose, high density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-c), triglycerides and insulin were measured. Oral glucose tolerance curve was performed to identify impaired glucose tolerance and diabetes mellitus in those patients with normal fasting blood glucose. The HOMA index was calculated as well as a quantified proteinuria in urine of 24 hours. RESULTS The prevalence of MS was 36.4 % (20 of 55 patients). Seventy percent of the patients with MS had limited SSc and 30 % diffuse SSc. An increased IR was observed in the limited SSc in comparison with the diffuse SSc (2.948 vs. 1.817 ± 0.3844 ± 0.2771, p = 0.03). An association between IR and MS was found in the limited SSc (p = 0.0001). Regarding the rest of the MS criteria, hypertriglyceridemia and an abnormal waist/hip ratio were the variables most often encountered, 95 % and 85 % respectively. Fifty percent of MS patients had low levels HDL-c and 40 % of them were hypertensive. None of the patients had proteinuria. CONCLUSION The prevalence of MS in SSc was 36.4 %, similar to the found in other rheumatic diseases, but higher compared to the found in the Mexican population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Systemic scleroderma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulin resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolic syndrome X</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de síndrome metabólico y resistencia a la insulina en esclerosis sistémica.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: el síndrome metabólico (SM) es un conjunto de factores de riesgo cardiovascular cuya prevalencia se encuentra incrementada en enfermedades reumáticas. El objetivo de este estudio fue estimar la prevalencia de SM y resistencia a la insulina (RI) en esclerosis sistémica (ES). Métodos: se incluyeron 55 pacientes con ES. Se evaluó SM utilizando los criterios de la OMS. Se registraron datos demográficos, antropométricos y presión arterial. Se midieron valores de glucosa, colesterol de lipoproteínas de alta densidad (c-HDL), triglicéridos e insulina. Se realizó una curva de tolerancia oral a la glucosa para identificar intolerancia a la glucosa y diabetes mellitus en pacientes con glucosa normal en ayuno. Se calculó el índice HOMA y se cuantificó proteinuria en orina de 24 horas. Resultados: la prevalencia del SM fue del 36.4 %. El 70 % de los pacientes con SM correspondió a ES limitada y 30 % a ES difusa. Se observó mayor resistencia a la insulina (RI) en la ES limitada frente a ES difusa. Se encontró asociación entre RI y el SM en la forma limitada. Del resto de los criterios de SM, la hipertrigliceridemia y el índice cintura/cadera anormal fueron las variables más frecuentes, 95 % y 85 % respectivamente. El 50 % de los pacientes con SM tuvo niveles bajos de c-HDL, e hipertensión arterial sistémica 40 %. En ningún paciente hubo proteinuria. Conclusiones: la prevalencia de SM en ES fue del 36.4 %, similar a la encontrada en otras enfermedades reumáticas, pero mayor en comparación con la población mexicana. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of metabolic syndrome and insulin resistance in system sclerosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
