<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26215894</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bardinet, Thierry</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lomba, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bañares, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olmedo, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Buño, Ismael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Plá, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Health research institutes are a strategic commitment considered the ideal environment to develop excellence in translational research. Achieving quality research requires not only a powerful scientific and research structure but also the quality and integrity of management systems that support it. The essential instruments in our institution were solid strategic planning integrated into and consistent with the system of quality management, systematic evaluation through periodic indicators, measurement of key user satisfaction and internal audits, and implementation of an innovative information management tool. The implemented management tools have provided a strategic thrust to our institute while ensuring a level of quality and efficiency in the development and management of research that allows progress towards excellence in biomedical research.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Quality improvement</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biomedical research</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Evaluación de programas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Investigación biomédica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Programme evaluation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gestión de la calidad total</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mejora continua</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Management information systems</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sistemas de gestión de la información</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Total quality management</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La gestión de un Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria: hacia la investigación de excelencia a través de la mejora continua.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Managing a health research institute: towards research excellence through continuous improvement].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
