<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2623303</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Muñoz, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Gallego, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carratalá, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frutos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gamallo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mesa, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a 52 year old man, who without previous thoracic trauma, cardiac diseases or cardiovascular risk factors presented after mild epigastric discomfort acute pulmonary oedema. He did not present clinical, electrocardiographic and biochemical manifestation of acute myocardial infarction. He was hospitalized and 15 days later he was sent to our hospital intubated and with assisted respiration. Haemodynamic studies showed severe acute mitral regurgitation and absence of significant obstructing lesions in the coronaries arteries. He was operated few hours after admission. The surgeon found a dysplasic mitral valve and rupture of a head of the posteromedial papillary muscle. The anatomopathological studies discovered mitral myxoid degeneration and ischemic lesion of the papillary muscle. We review the literature of the exclusive infarction of the papillary muscles and their possible relationships with the mitral prolapse syndrome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura del músculo papilar posteromedial mitral asociada a válvula mitral mixomatosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rupture of the mitral posteromedial papillary muscle associated with myxomatous mitral valve].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
