<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26239670</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Quereda-Castañeda, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz de Escalona-Rojas, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-García, O</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is considered the most common cause of blindness in the working-age population in industrialised countries, with diabetic macular oedema being the most common reason of decreased visual acuity in diabetics. According to the results of large multicentre studies, blindness prevention for RD involves conducting periodic check-ups, which include examinations of the back of the eye, so they can be treated in time. The use of non-mydriatic cameras and telemedicine have been shown to be useful in this regard (sensitivity&gt;80% and specificity&gt;90%). If this procedure is followed, the first retinography should be performed 5 years from diagnosis in type 1 diabetics and immediately after diagnosis in type 2 diabetics. Therefore the role of the Primary Care physician is crucial to enable early diagnosis of this disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Telemedicina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetic retinopathy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevention and control</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Telemedicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Macular oedema</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Retinopatía diabética</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Edema macular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevención y control</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de la retinopatía diabética para médicos de atención primaria: hacia una mejora de la medicina telemática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Update of diabetic retinopathy for Primary Care physicians: Towards an improvement of telematic medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
