<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2623311</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9437</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ainz, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Arzua, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>De la Puente Bilbao, M A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In view of the lack of studies on the percentage of atypical forms of duodenal ulcer, we made one based on our cases, analyzing separately the location, hours and time periods. We personally studied 3,120 duodenal ulcers, considering as atypical those that diverged form the norm in any of the 3 variables. The epigastrium was considered to be the characteristic location, extending from the infraxiphoid zone to the navel, although there can be simultaneous pain in other abdominal zones, the breast or back. The hour was found to be more than an hour after the feeding. Time intervals of more than 2 months without discomfort were established and the pain intervals lasted from 10 days to 2 months. Complicated ulcers were not considered. Atypical duodenal ulcers represent more than a fourth, 27.37%. Of the three variants, one the most common and three were less frequent. The absence of pain during determined time periods in more than two thirds is emphasized, while those without a pattern of hours and of atypical location are more or less equal. We note that the absence of determined time periods represents 80% of atypical duodenal ulcers and a fifth of all duodenal ulcers.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las formas atípicas de la úlcera duodenal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Atypical forms of duodenal ulcer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de las enfermedades del aparato digestivo</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
