<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26249139</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallardo-Ramírez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojano-Rodríguez, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabral-Oliver, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arce-Liévano, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Loera, L S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Crisanto-Campos, B A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas-Lailson, L E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Portillo, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Invasive management of pancreatic pseudocysts (PP) is currently indicated in those patients with symptoms or complications. Treatment options are classified as surgical (open and laparoscopic) and non-surgical (endoscopic and radiologic). AIM To describe the morbidity, mortality, and efficacy in terms of technical and clinical success of the laparoscopic surgical approach in the treatment of patients with PP in the last 3 years at our hospital center. METHODS We included patients with PP treated with laparoscopic surgery within the time frame of January 2012 and December 2014. The morbidity and mortality associated with the procedure were determined, together with the postoperative results in terms of effectiveness and recurrence. RESULTS A total of 38 patients were diagnosed with PP within the last 3 years, but only 20 of them had invasive treatment. Laparoscopic surgery was performed on 17 of those patients (mean pseudocyst diameter of 15.3, primary drainage success rate of 94.1%, complication rate of 5.9%, and a 40-month follow-up). CONCLUSIONS The results obtained with the laparoscopic technique used at our hospital center showed that this approach is feasible, efficacious, and safe. Thus, performed by skilled surgeons, it should be considered a treatment option for patients with PP.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopic drainage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acute peripancreatic fluid collections</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pancreatic pseudocyst</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Seudoquiste pancreático</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Drenaje laparoscópico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Walled off pancreatic necrosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colecciones peripancreáticas agudas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Necrosis pancreática encapsulada</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic management of pancreatic pseudocysts: experience at a general hospital in Mexico City.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
