<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26259742</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Evaristo-Méndez, Gerardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rocha-Calderón, César Haydn</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The risk of post-operative pneumonia is a latent complication. A study was conducted to determine its risk factors in abdominal surgery. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study was performed that included analysing the variables of age and gender, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and smoking, serum albumin, type of surgery and anaesthesia, emergency or elective surgery, incision site, duration of surgery, length of hospital stay, length of stay in the intensive care unit, and time on mechanical ventilation. The adjusted odds ratio for risk factors was obtained using multivariate logistic regression. RESULTS The study included 91 (9.6%) patients with pneumonia and 851 (90.4%) without pneumonia. Age 60 years or over (OR=2.34), smoking (OR=9.48), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (OR=3.52), emergency surgery (OR=2.48), general anaesthesia (OR=3.18), surgical time 120 minutes or over (OR=5.79), time in intensive care unit 7 days or over (OR=1.23), time on mechanical ventilation greater than or equal to 4 days (OR=5.93) and length of post-operative hospital stay of 15 days or over (OR=1.20), were observed as independent predictors for the development of postoperative pneumonia. CONCLUSIONS Identifying risk factors for post-operative pneumonia may prevent their occurrence. The length in the intensive care unit of greater than or equal to 7 days (OR=1.23; 95% CI 1.07 - 1.42) and a length postoperative hospital stay of 15 days or more (OR=1.20; 95% CI 1.07 - 1.34) were the predictive factors most strongly associated with lung infection in this study.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pneumonia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Factores de riesgo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neumonía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Risk factors</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo para neumonía nosocomial en pacientes con cirugía abdominal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors for nosocomial pneumonia in patients with abdominal surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
