<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26262723</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fonollá-Joya, Juristo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro-Alarcón, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera-Vique, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Martínez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to evaluate the possible hypotensive effect in pre-hypertensive and hypertensive subjects of an olive leaf extract (OLE) standardized to 15% (w/w) in oleoeuropein, and with a 10% (w/w) mean content of triterpenic acids and 1% (w/w) in hydroxytirosol. Moreover, the possible effects on the blood antioxidant status and lipid profile have been also evaluated. MATERIALS AND METHODS this interventional study has been performed in human volunteers, to whom 1 600 mg OLE/days, was administered. The analyzed parameters at the beginning and end of the study were diastolic and systolic pressure, delay in the LDL-cholesterol oxidation "lag time" and blood levels of nitric oxide (NO), malonic dialdehyde (MDA), antioxidant capacity (AOC) lipid profile, glucose, transaminases and creatinine. RESULTS a decrease in the diastolic and systolic pressure, and an increase in the NO values all statistically significant (CHO) for all volunteers, was found. In volunteers with higher systolic pressure their levels were also significantly diminished after the intervention trial (P = 0,002). The LDL lag time increased significantly (P = 0,047). Additionally, in all volunteers CHO levels were significantly decreased, and those of LDL cholesterol, triglycerides (TG) and the CHO/HDL cholesterol ratio were diminished with a tendency to the significance (P = 0,076; P = 0,059; P = 0,056; respectively). CONCLUSIONS this preliminary study reports by the first time the positive influence of the OLE assayed in the regulation of the hypertension, LDL lag time and blood lipid profile. Therefore, further studies are of great interest.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jul 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">EFECTO HIPOTENSOR DE UN EXTRACTO DE COMPONENTES BIOACTIVOS DE HOJAS DE OLIVO: ESTUDIO CLÍNICO PRELIMINAR.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: evaluar el posible efecto hipotensor en sujetos pre-hipertensos e hipertensos, de un extracto de hoja de olivo (EHO) estandarizado al 15% (m/m) en oleoeuropeína y con un contenido medio del 10% (m/m) en ácidos triterpénicos y del 1% (m/m) en hidroxitirosol. Asimismo, se ha valorado su acción sobre el estatus antioxidante y el perfil lipídico sanguíneos. Material y métodos: se ha llevado a cabo un ensayo de intervención en humanos con administración de 1.600 mg de extracto/día. Los parámetros evaluados han sido presión sistólica y diastólica, retardo de la oxidación del colesterol LDL (lag time) y niveles sanguíneos de óxido nítrico (NO), malondialdehído (MDA), capacidad antioxidante (CAO), perfil lipídico, glucosa, transaminasas y creatinina. Resultados: se observó en todos los sujetos una disminución estadísticamente significativa de la presión sistólica y diastólica, y un aumento de los niveles de NO (P &lt; 0,050). En los sujetos con presión sistólica más elevada también se redujo significativamente su valor tras la intervención (P = 0,002). El “lag time” de las LDL aumentó significativamente (P = 0,047), y en todos los sujetos los niveles de colesterol (CHO) se redujeron significativamente. Los niveles de colesterol LDL, triglicéridos (TG) y del índice CHO/colesterol HDL disminuyeron con tendencia a la significancia (P = 0,076; P = 0,059; P = 0,056; respectivamente). Conclusión: este estudio, aunque preliminar, pone de relieve por primera vez la influencia positiva del EHO ensayado en la regulación de la hipertensión así como en la velocidad de oxidación de las LDL y en el perfil lipídico sanguíneo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[HYPOTENSIVE EFFECT OF AN EXTRACT OF BIOACTIVE COMPOUNDS OF OLIVE LEAVES: PRELIMINARY CLINICAL STUDY].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
