<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2627482</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sáenz Lope, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rapún Pac, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Estévez Guerra, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Martín, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to establish the epidemiologic features of infectious meningitis in the adult population in our environment, the experience of the Department of Neurology of the Hospital del Rey during the 3-year period, from 1984 to 1986, has been analyzed. Three-hundred-ninety episodes were handled, of which, 51% were acute bacterial meningitis, 45% were acute lymphocytic meningitis, 26% were tuberculous meningitis, 1% were brucellar meningitis and 0.5% were due to Candida albicans. Acute bacterial meningitis predominated in winter, whereas acute lymphocytic meningitis predominated in summer (p less than 0.001). Forty-seven percent of acute bacterial meningitis were due to Neisseria meningitidis and 14.5% of acute lymphocytic meningitis with virologic study, were due to Herpesviridae. The mortality rate of acute bacterial meningitis was 8.5% and that of tuberculous meningitis was 10%. In order to emphasize the importance of these processes, the main epidemiologic data are compared with that of other studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis infecciosas del adulto: experiencia clínica de tres años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infectious meningitis in the adult: 3-year clinical experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
