<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26298083</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jiménez-Penick, Virginia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallego-Izquierdo, Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil-Martínez, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pardo-Montero, Joaquín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrer-Peña, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>La Touche, Roy</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To adapt the Graded Chronic Pain Scale for use in Primary care patients in Spain, and to assess its psychometric properties. METHODS Clinical measures observational study investigating the severity of chronic pain. The methodology included a process of translation and back-translation following the international guidelines. Study participants were 75 patients who experienced lower back pain for more than six months and were sent to Primary Care physiotherapy units. Internal consistency, construct validity, test-retest reliability, floor and ceiling effects, and answering capacity were analysed. RESULTS The Spanish version of the Graded Chronic Pain Scale had a high internal consistency, with a Cronbach's alpha of 0.87 and intraclass correlation coefficient of 0.81. Regarding construct validity, it was identified that two factors explained 72.37% of the variance. Convergent validity showed a moderate positive correlation with the Visual Analogue Scale, the activity avoidance subscale of the Tampa Scale of Kinesophobia, the Pain Catastrophizing Scale, the Roland-Morris Low Back Pain and Disability Questionnaire, and the FearAvoidance Beliefs Questionnaire. A moderate negative correlation was identified with the Chronic Pain Self-Efficacy Scale. The mean time of questionnaire administration was 2minutes and 28seconds. CONCLUSIONS The Spanish version of the Graded Chronic Pain Scale appears to be a valid, reliable, and useful tool for measuring chronic pain at an early stage in Primary Care settings in Spain.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Dolor crónico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Severity of illness index</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary health care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Low back pain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dolor de la región lumbar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Scales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Traducción</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Índice de severidad de la enfermedad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic pain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estudios de validación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Translations</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Escalas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Validation studies</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación y validación de la Escala de gradación del dolor crónico al español.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation and validation of the Spanish version of the graded chronic pain scale.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
