<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26290022</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barrera de León, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Martel, José Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgadillo-Pérez, Saturnino</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the results of percutaneous closure by means of the Amplatzer Septal Occluder (ASO) device in pediatric patients with intra-auricular communication (IAC). MATERIALS AND METHODS Descriptive transversal study in patients submitted to percutaneous closure of IAC from March 2005 to March 2013. Patients aged &lt;16 years, weight&gt;6 kg, IAC type ostium segundum, and patent foramen ovale, with border separations borders&gt;5 mm, and absence of coexisting pathology were included in the study. We excluded from the study children with severe pulmonary blood pressure/arterial hypertension. Descriptive statistics with the SPSS v. 20.0 statistical software package. RESULTS We included in the study 28 patients, feminine gender (n=19, 68%), median age=8 years (range, 4-14), weight 30.7 kg (range, 15-69). New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional class I (n=21, 75%), II (n=7, 25%). Median IAC size, 15.50 mm (range, 5-25), and a median ASO size of 17.54 mm (range, 8-28). After ASO placement, 100% presented NYHA I at one month, cardiac murmur (n=2, 7.1%), cessation of cardiac murmur at month 6 (n=28, 100%), without evidence of arrhythmias at one month 100%, residual short circuit at 24 hours (n=4, 14%), complete occlusion at month 6 (n=28, 100%), normalization size of VD, and cessation of tricuspid insufficiency 100% at one year. Complications included minimal bleeding during the procedure (n=2, 7%), transitory cephalea (n=5, 18%), and dysautonomia (n=1, 4%). CONCLUSION Percutaneous closure of IAC of children fitted with the ASO device is safe and exhibits good results.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de los resultados del cierre percutáneo mediante el dispositivo Amplatzer en pacientes pediátricos con comunicación interauricular (CIA).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of the results of percutaneous closure by means of the Amplatzer device in pediatric patients with intra-auricular communication (IAC)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
