<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26296626</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de Micheli, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iturralde Torres, Pedro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Nominalists of the XIV century, precursors of modern science, thought that science's object was not the general, vague and indeterminate but the particular, which is real and can be known directly. About the middle of the XVII Century the bases of the modern science became established thanks to a revolution fomented essentially by Galileo, Bacon and Descartes. During the XVIII Century, parallel to the development of the great current of English Empiricism, a movement of scientific renewal also arose in continental Europe following the discipline of the Dutch Physicians and of Boerhaave. In the XIX Century, Claude Bernard dominated the scientific medicine but his rigorous determinism impeded him from taking into account the immense and unforeseeable field of the random. Nowadays, we approach natural science and medicine, from particular groups of facts; that is, from the responses of Nature to specific questions, but not from the general laws. Furthermore, in recent epistemology, the concept that experimental data are not pure facts, but rather, facts interpreted within a hermeneutical context has been established. Finally a general tendency to retrieve philosophical questions concerning the understanding of essence and existence can frequently be seen in scientific inquiry. In the light of the evolution of medical thought, it is possible to establish the position of scientific medicine within the movement of ideas dominating in our time.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Enfoque racional de la medicina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rational approach to medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicina científica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mexico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>México</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfoque racional de la cardiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rational approach to cardiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Scientific medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">En torno a la evolución del pensamiento científico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[On the evolution of scientific thought].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
