<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26319829</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fernández-Vázquez, Rosalía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millán Romero, Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barbancho, Miguel Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvero-Cruz, José Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE central obesity has a higher risk of metabolic syndrome. The present work aimed to study the relationship of trunk fat and the visceral fat index, and other anthropometric indices in relation to the metabolic syndrome in middle aged male Methods: design: transversal descriptive and correlational study. PARTICIPANTS 75 male, volunteers who have access to a medical assessment, with an age range of 21 to 59 years, from different professions. MEASUREMENTS Weight, height, body mass index, waist circumference, gluteal circumference, waist-to-hip ratio, waist-to-height ratio, trunk fat and visceral fat level by bioelectrical abdominal impedance analysis with Tanita AB-140 (ViScan) and biochemical markers: fasting glucose, total cholesterol, and triglycerides. Likewise, the systolic and diastolic blood pressure was measured. RESULTS there are significant correlations of anthropometric measurements with trunk fat and visceral fat level and the same with biochemical variables. Receptor-operator curves (ROC curve) analysis shows that the cutoff points from which arises the metabolic syndrome are 32.7% of trunk fat and a level of visceral fat of 13 with a high sensitivity and specificity, attaining the same cut-off points for the metabolic syndrome and obesity status. CONCLUSIONS trunk fat and visceral fat levels determined by bioelectrical abdominal impedance analysis, values are variables very sensitive and specific for the detection of metabolic syndrome and obesity, though not over the variables and anthropometric indices. In the condition of the overweight, trunk fat and visceral fat level are more predictive than anthropometric measures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Sep 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PREDICCIÓN DEL SÍNDROME METABÓLICO POR BIOIMPEDANCIA ABDOMINAL Y ANTROPOMETRÍA EN HOMBRES DE MEDIANA EDAD.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: la obesidad central tiene una gran relación con el síndrome metabólico. Estudiar la relación de la grasa del tronco, el índice de grasa visceral y las medidas antropométricas con el síndrome metabólico. Métodos: diseño: transversal descriptivo y correlacional. Participaron 75 varones, voluntarios, de distintas profesiones, que accedieron a un reconocimiento médico- laboral, con un rango de edad de 21 a 59 años. Mediciones de peso, talla, índice de masa corporal, perímetro abdominal, perímetro glúteo, índice cintura-cadera y grasa de tronco y nivel de grasa visceral mediante bioimpedanciometría (Tanita AB-140-ViScan) y parámetros bioquímicos: glucosa, colesterol total y triglicéridos. Así mismo, se midió la presión arterial sistólica y diastólica. Se comparan los estados de síndrome metabólico, sobrepeso y obesidad. Resultados: existen correlaciones de las medidas antropométricas con la de grasa de tronco y el nivel de grasa visceral, así como con los parámetros bioquímicos (p &lt; 0,001). Un análisis de curvas ROC muestra que los puntos de corte a partir de los cuales se puede presentar el síndrome metabólico son de 32,7% de grasa de tronco y de 13 para el nivel de grasa visceral, con una alta sensibilidad y especificidad. Se obtienen los mismos puntos de corte para el estado de obesidad y síndrome metabólico. Conclusiones: la grasa de tronco y los niveles de grasa visceral son muy sensibles y específicos para la detección del síndrome metabólico y la obesidad, aunque no superan a las variables e índices antropométricos. En la condición de sobrepeso, la grasa de tronco y visceral son medidas algo más predictivas que las variables antropométricas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[ABDOMINAL BIOELECTRICAL IMPEDANCE ANALYSIS AND ANTHROPOMETRY FOR PREDICTING METABOLIC SYNDROME IN MIDDLE AGED MEN].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
