<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26315650</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zafra Anta, Miguel Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores Martín, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil García, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Durán, Carla</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez López, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ponte Hernando, Fernando Julio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION On the centenary of the foundation of the Paediatrics Society of Madrid, a tribute is presented to rural medical practice of that time, although there are few documents on the history of rural medicine. The main objective is to describe the context of the rural medical practice in the late 19th and beginning 20th century, while presenting a historical biographical review of Manuel Martínez Saldise, who was medical specialist from Cazalegas (Toledo). He was appointed an Honorary Member by the Paediatrics Society of Madrid in 1927. MATERIAL AND METHODS A search was carried out in repositories of digitized media, web portals of history of medicine, PubMed, IME files of local councils and medical colleges. The family archives were reviewed with the collaboration of his descendants. RESULTS The hiring of rural doctors was carried out by the municipalities, and the salary largely depended on private practice as well as "retainers". Specialist physicians took part in epidemics, legal medicine, and in hygiene measures. They also had disputes with mayors, chiefs, with colleagues and with protectionism. A summary of the biography and occupational activity of Manuel Martínez Saldise is presented. COMMENTS Rural doctors were subjected to the society of their time, with the issues that arose, denouncing the shortcomings of the local administrations, dedicated efforts to their family and the most disadvantaged.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Historical Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Médicos titulares</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rural medical practice</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Early decades of the 20th century</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicina rural</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Principios del siglo XX</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Historia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>History</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Titular physicians</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La medicina rural a principios de siglo XX. A propósito de Martínez Saldise (1855-1937), socio de honor de la Sociedad de Pediatría de Madrid en 1927.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Rural medical practice at the beginning of the 20th century. Martínez Saldise (1855-1937), honorary member of Paediatric Society of Madrid in 1927].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
