<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26320340</identifier>
<setSpec>2340-3284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bisbe Vives, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basora Macaya, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patient Blood Management (PBM) is the design of a personalized, multimodal multidisciplinary plan for minimizing transfusion and simultaneously achieving a positive impact on patient outcomes. The first pillar of PBM consists of optimizing the erythrocyte mass. The best chance for this step is offered by preoperative preparation. In most cases, a detailed medical history, physical examination and laboratory tests will identify the cause of anemia. A correct evaluation of parameters that assess the state and function of iron, such as ferritin levels, and the parameters that measure functional iron, such as transferrin saturation and soluble transferrin receptor levels, provide us with essential information for guiding the treatment with iron. The new blood count analyzers that measure hypochromia (% of hypochromic red blood cells and reticulocyte hemoglobin concentrations) provide us useful information for the diagnosis and follow-up of the response to iron treatment. Measuring serum folic acid and vitamin B12 levels is essential for treating deficiencies and thereby achieving better hemoglobin optimization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anestesia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anesthesia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Preoperative care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidados preoperatorios</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primer pilar del "Patient Blood Management". Tipos de anemia y parámetros diagnósticos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The first pillar of patient blood management. Types of anemia and diagnostic parameters].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
