<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26336717</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Adrianza de Baptista, Gertrudis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murillo Melo, Carolain</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since nutrition can influence the process of carcinogenesis, this study's objectives are to review the relationship between nutrition and cancer from the point of view of the role of micronutrients in the treatment of cancer patients, and to get to know the deficit relationship and the excess of micronutrients, with the etiology and cancer treatment. At the same time the patient's weight loss relates, among other things, to the type of cancerous tumor, its location, stage thereof, reason for which it may be associated with the deficiency of macro and micronutrients as from psychogenic, anorectics and mal-absorption effects or with mechanical effects as obstruction, among other toxic effects that are common in the treatment of cancer. Hence, the importance that the nutrition expert must have in making an adequate overall nutritional evaluation that allows the nutritional diagnosis, in studying the dietary patterns, to determine the toxic effects of the antineoplastic treatment in order to handle the treatment's timing excellence, symptoms and signs, and thus act effectively optiimizing the patient's life quality, and therewith his/her survival. There are controversies as to which specific dietary factors are related to cancer etiology and the results of studies on metabolic factors, and therefore, the relationship Cancer-Nutrition is quiet complex.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2014 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer-vitaminas-minerales: Relación compleja.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cancer-vitamins-minerals: Complex relation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
