<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26342414</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pla, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gifre, Mariona</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gil, Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monreal-Bosch, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roig, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To identify factors that people with a traumatic brain injury and their families perceived as helping to improve their quality of life. METHODS Three focus groups and five interviews were conducted with a total of 37 participants: 14 persons with traumatic brain injury and 23 caregivers. A content analysis was conducted. The constant comparative method was applied. RESULTS We detected five factors that improved the quality of life of persons with a traumatic brain and their families: 1) Informal support (family and friends); 2) formal support (counseling, employment, built and bureaucratic environment); 3) type of clinical characteristics; 4) social participation, and 5) social visibility. CONCLUSIONS The needs expressed by our participants primarily focused on social and emotional factors. For persons with severe traumatic brain injury attempting to achieve the best possible community integration, a new semiology is required, not limited to medical care, but also involving social and psychological care tailored to the needs of each individual and family and their environment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Investigación cualitativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Qualitative research</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Relaciones familiares</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Integración a la comunidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Traumatic brain injury</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Community integration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Traumatismo cerebral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>España</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Family</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad de vida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality of life</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spain</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Y después del accidente? Las necesidades psicosociales de las personas con traumatismo craneoencefálico y de sus familiares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[What happens after the accident? Psychosocial needs of people with traumatic brain injury and their families].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
