<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26383062</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Pousa, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olazarán, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Casanova, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conde-Sala, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarejo-Galende, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>del Ser, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliveros-Cid, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cacho, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carnero-Pardo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bermejo-Pareja, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hoyos-Alonso, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido Barral, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Martínez, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Brief cognitive tests (BCT) may help detect cognitive impairment (CI) in the clinical setting. Several BCT have been developed and/or validated in our country, but we lack specific recommendations for use. DEVELOPMENT Review of studies on the diagnostic accuracy of BCT for CI, using studies conducted in Spain with BCT which take less than 20 min. We provide recommendations of use based on expert consensus and established on the basis of BCT characteristics and study results. CONCLUSION The Fototest, the Memory Impairment Screen (MIS) and the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) are the preferred options in primary care; other BCT (Clock Drawing Test [CDT], test of verbal fluency [TVF]) may also be administered in cases of negative results with persistent suspected CI or concern (stepwise approach). In the specialised care setting, a systematic assessment of the different cognitive domains should be conducted using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment, the MMSE, the Rowland Universal Dementia Assessment, the Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination, or by means of a stepwise or combined approach involving more simple tests (CDT, TVF, Fototest, MIS, Memory Alteration Test, Eurotest). Associating an informant questionnaire (IQ) with the BCT is superior to the BCT alone for the detection of CI. The choice of instruments will depend on the patient's characteristics, the clinician's experience, and available time. The BCT and IQ must reinforce - but never substitute - clinical judgment, patient-doctor communication, and inter-professional dialogue.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Detección</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Test cognitivos breves</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Screening</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Deterioro cognitivo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Specialised care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención especializada</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Brief cognitive tests</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cribado</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Detection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cognitive impairment</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical application of brief cognitive tests.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
