<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26394912</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calleja, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Temprano, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vidal, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trigo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, M B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villanueva, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castaño, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amorín, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benavente, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Vega, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vega, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrosa, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casado, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murias, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Intravenous thrombolysis with alteplase is an effective treatment for ischaemic stroke when applied during the first 4.5 hours, but less than 15% of patients have access to this technique. Mechanical thrombectomy is more frequently able to recanalise proximal occlusions in large vessels, but the infrastructure it requires makes it even less available. METHODS We describe the implementation of code stroke in Asturias, as well as the process of adapting various existing resources for urgent stroke care in the region. By considering these resources, and the demographic and geographic circumstances of our region, we examine ways of reorganising the code stroke protocol that would optimise treatment times and provide the most appropriate treatment for each patient. RESULTS We distributed the 8 health districts in Asturias so as to permit referral of candidates for reperfusion therapies to either of the 2 hospitals with 24-hour stroke units and on-call neurologists and providing IV fibrinolysis. Hospitals were assigned according to proximity and stroke severity; the most severe cases were immediately referred to the hospital with on-call interventional neurology care. Patient triage was provided by pre-hospital emergency services according to the NIHSS score. CONCLUSIONS Modifications to code stroke in Asturias have allowed us to apply reperfusion therapies with good results, while emphasising equitable care and managing the severity-time ratio to offer the best and safest treatment for each patient as soon as possible.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Gravedad-tiempo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Código ictus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrinólisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Áreas sanitarias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health district</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Code stroke</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Severity-time</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrinolysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trombectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Code stroke in Asturias.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
