<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2640412</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ignacio, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibrahim, H H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Harding, T W</dc:author>
<dc:author>Climent, C E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wig, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This questionnaire has been designed considering transcultural differences. Its validation includes an approximately 400-patient sample, with their relatives as control sample population. Such populations come from General Health Centers located in Colombia, India, the Philippines, and Sudan. In each area, different cut-off points were used on the calculation of sensitivity and specificity. This instrument is currently used in different parts of the world: It is demonstrating to be valuable and sensitive a tool for identifying mental disorders among individuals seeking treatment at General Health Services. At the same time, it is being used in a training manual for Psychiatry primary care workers. Even though the instrument does not diagnosticate, it nonetheless identifies individuals suffering from psychological disrupting symptoms. Both its simplicity and high sensitivity help in a practical approach to Psychiatry primary care strategies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jul-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cuestionario de síntomas para la detección de problemas en adultos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The symptoms questionnaire for problem detection in adults].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta psiquiatrica y psicologica de America latina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
