<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26418090</identifier>
<setSpec>1851-8265</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Menéndez, Eduardo L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Following Giovanni Berlinguer's proposal that health/disease processes are one of the primary spies into the contradictions of a system, this article describes cases that occurred in central and peripheral capitalist contexts as well as in the so-called "real socialist" States that allow such a role to be seen. Secondly, we observe the processes and above all the interpretations developed in Latin America and especially Mexico regarding the role attributed to traditional medicine in the identity and sense of belonging of indigenous peoples, which emphasize the incompatibility of indigenous worldviews with biomedicine. To do so we analyze projects that were carried out under the notion of intercultural health, which in large part resulted in failure both in health and political terms. The almost entirely ideological content and perspective of these projects is highlighted, as is the scant relationship they hold with the reality of indigenous people. Lastly, the impact and role that the advance of these conceptualizations and health programs might have had in the disengagement experienced over the last nearly ten years in the ethnic movements of Latin America is considered.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades ¿son solo padecimientos?: biomedicina, formas de atención "paralelas" y proyectos de poder.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Is disease merely illness?: Biomedicine, "parallel" forms of care and power].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud colectiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
