<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26436784</identifier>
<setSpec>0716-1018</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luzio, Álvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luzio, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Troncoso, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jara, Alexis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, Ítalo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belmar, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The contamination of public squares and parks with dog feces poses a risk to the population, since it may contain parasitic elements of zoonotic importance. AIM To identify human pathogenic parasites in samples of dog feces collected from parks and public squares. METHODS 452 fecal dog samples collected from 65 squares and public parks were analyzed using the technique of Burrows. RESULTS 60% (39/65) of the samples contained some parasitic forms with a zoonotic potential. Parasitic taxa with zoonotic risk were Toxocara sp., Ancylostoma sp., Dipylidium caninum, Giardia sp., Taenia sp., Toxascaris sp., Strongyloides sp., and Uncinaria sp. CONCLUSION The detected parasites present a risk to human health, so it seems necessary to implement health education activities in the community, develop deworming plans, and control the canine overpopulation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formas parasitarias de importancia zoonótica, encontradas en heces de perros recolectadas desde plazas y parques públicos de la ciudad de Los Ángeles, Región del Bío Bío, Chile.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Parasites of zoonotic importance in dog feces collected in parks and public squares of the city of Los Angeles, Bío-Bío, Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
