<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26437699</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luna-García, Jairo E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rubio-Castro, Natalia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The goal of this study is to analyze the performance of the three questionnaires and the file of general information that comprise the Set of Instruments for the Assessment of Psychosocial Factors in six companies from different economic sectors in Colombia, with regard to: (a) content of the instruments, (b) application methodology, and (c) the response from workers and employers. METHODOLOGY This research was performed through the study of multiple instances. It was based on the processing of: (1) the observation logs with regard to the application of the questionnaires, (2) workers' annotations about their questionnaires and (3) minutes of meetings with representatives of the workers. A reclassification into more specific subcategories was done taking into consideration some particular and common elements found between companies. RESULTS Regarding the "Content" category, there are significant limitations in the questionnaires about both outside and inside-of-work factors. This is because some items cannot be applied under specific working conditions such as outsourcing or field work. In "Methodology" it was observed that some practices could decrease the reliability of the assessments, such as not having adequate schedules or locations. In the "Reception" category, it was found that even though this assessment is deemed desirable by most workers and employers, there are, however, some actions taken by companies that could affect this perception. CONCLUSIONS It is positive to implement the assessment of psychosocial working conditions in companies of this country, even though this assessment, with a universal assessment tool, has difficulties in a changing and increasingly complex working world. It is advisable to complement these assessments with qualitative methods.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del desempeño de la batería de evaluación de factores psicosociales en Colombia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Analysis of the performance of the assessment battery related to psychosocial factors in Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
