<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26452620</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bartel, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domenech Juan, Iván</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moya, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Merán Gil, Jorge L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz Toro, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Callejo Castillo, Ángela</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The middle fossa approach is a surgical technique that is very useful for lateral skull base surgery. However, it is true that it has limited surgical indications and implementation due to its technical complexity. We present our experience in 10 patients in whom the middle fossa approach was the treatment of choice because of the extent of the injury and complexity of the lesion or process. Despite the complexity of the cases, there was no mortality associated with surgery. Postoperative complications were found in 2 patients who presented an epidural hematoma and a cortico-subcortical hematoma. Hearing function was preserved in 5 patients out of the 7 who had adequate hearing at the time of surgery. House/Brackmann I-II facial nerve function was achieved in 8 patients; the remaining 2 had no deterioration of the nerve function. In 9 out of 10 patients, the surgery achieved complete solution of the lesion. The middle fossa approach is a safe and reliable surgical technique. It gives us great control and exposure of different skull base processes. We consider its knowledge of great importance, because it may be the only viable surgical alternative in some specific patients. That is the reason why it is important to learn this approach and know about it in our specialty.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cholesteatoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Facial palsy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Middle fossa approach</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tumor epidermoide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cholesterol granuloma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colesteatoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidermoid tumour</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hearing preservation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parálisis facial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Granuloma de colesterol</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Preservación auditiva</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Abordaje fosa media</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje por fosa media, aplicaciones en lesiones del hueso temporal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Middle fossa approach: Applications in temporal bone lesions.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
