<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26454645</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Noriega-Iglesias, Sabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carro-Fernández, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llorente-Pendás, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guntín-García, Maite</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez-Batalla, Faustino</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Conventional audiometry is the gold standard for quantifying and describing hearing loss. Alternative methods become necessary to assess subjects who are too young to respond reliably. Auditory evoked potentials constitute the most widely used method for determining hearing thresholds objectively; however, this stimulus is not frequency specific. The advent of the auditory steady-state response (ASSR) leads to more specific threshold determination. The current study describes and compares ASSR, auditory brainstem response (ABR) and conventional behavioural tone audiometry thresholds in a group of infants with various degrees of hearing loss. METHODS A comparison was made between ASSR, ABR and behavioural hearing thresholds in 35 infants detected in the neonatal hearing screening program. RESULTS Mean difference scores (±SD) between ABR and high frequency ABR thresholds were 11.2 dB (±13) and 10.2 dB (±11). Pearson correlations between the ASSR and audiometry thresholds were 0.80 and 0.91 (500Hz); 0.84 and 0.82 (1000Hz); 0.85 and 0.84 (2000Hz); and 0.83 and 0.82 (4000Hz). CONCLUSION The ASSR technique is a valuable extension of the clinical test battery for hearing-impaired children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Auditory brainstem response</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Potenciales evocados de tronco cerebral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sensorineural hearing loss</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipoacusia infantil</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Auditory steady-state response</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Childhood hearing loss</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Potenciales evocados de estado estable</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipoacusia neurosensorial</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad de los potenciales evocados auditivos de estado estable en la fase diagnóstica del cribado neonatal universal de la hipoacusia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Auditory-steady-state response reliability in the audiological diagnosis after neonatal hearing screening.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
