<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26462508</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aguilar-Lemarroy, Adriana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Silva, María G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Hernández, Dulce M</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-López, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jave-Suárez, Luis Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The Official Mexican Norm for the prevention, treatment and control of Cervical Cancer (CC) indicates that the Papanicolau (Pap) is the procedure for the detection of this neoplasia; therefore, it is of interest to know the prevalence of suspected cases by this technique in Mexican population. In this study, we show the diagnosed cases in the State of Jalisco, México. METHODS A retrospective study was made to the samples that arrived for their analysis to the Laboratorio Regional de Citología Exfoliativa (LARCE), of the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social (IMSS) in Guadalajara, Jalisco. We considered all cases from January 2010 to December 2012. RESULTS We analyzed 188 095 cases, from which 5.3 % had a diagnosis of low dysplasia, 0.18 % of moderated dysplasia and 0.05 % of high dysplasia. Microinvasive and invasive cancer showed a low frequency (0.03 %). CONCLUSIONS The frequency of abnormal findings identified by vaginal cervical cytology is relatively low. The number of inadequate and limited samples for cytological assessment is high; there is a high proportion of women attending for the first time in life to cytology evaluation in older age groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Screening</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cervical intraepithelial neoplasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cytology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mexico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de lesiones epiteliales cervicales reportadas en el Laboratorio Regional de Citología Exfoliativa de Jalisco.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: La Norma Oficial Mexicana para la prevención, tratamiento y control del Cáncer Cérvico Uterino (CaCU) indica que el Papanicolaou (Pap) es el procedimiento de elección para la detección oportuna de esta neoplasia, por lo que es de interés conocer la prevalencia de casos tamizados mediante esta técnica en la población mexicana. En la presente investigación se muestran los casos que se identificaron como sospecha para CaCU por tamizaje en el estado de Jalisco, México. Métodos: se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de las muestras que llegaron para su análisis al Laboratorio Regional de Citología Exfoliativa (LARCE) del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social (IMSS) en Guadalajara, Jalisco. Se consideraron todos los casos de enero de 2010 a diciembre de 2012. Resultados: se analizaron 188 095 casos, de los cuales el 5.3 % se reportaron con sospecha de displasia leve, el 0.18 % de displasia moderada y el 0.05 % de displasia grave. En cáncer microinvasor e invasor se observó una baja frecuencia (0.03 %). Conclusiones: la frecuencia de hallazgos anormales identificados por citología cervicovaginal es relativamente baja. El número de muestras inadecuadas más limitadas para valoración citológica es alto; existe una elevada proporción de mujeres que asisten por primera vez en la vida a estudio citológico en grupos de edad avanzados. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Frequency of cervical epithelial lesions reported in the Regional Laboratory of Exfoliative Cytology in Jalisco].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
