<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26521154</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Abad, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuesta, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aristizábal, Natalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hincapié-García, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacio, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez, Alex</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aristizábal, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monsalve, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hincapié, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Laiton, Estefany</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, José-Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Botero, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado, Maria-Rocio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapata, Eliana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe baseline characteristics of diabetic patients who were started on insulin pump and real time continuous glucose monitor (CSII-rtCGM) in a specialized center in Medellin, Colombia. MATERIALS AND METHODS All patients with diabetes with complete data who were started on CSII-rtCGM between February 2010 and May 2014 were included. This is a descriptive analysis of the sociodemographic and clinical characteristics. RESULTS 141 of 174 patients attending the clinic were included. 90,1% had type 1diabetes (T1D). The average age of T1D patients at the beginning of therapy was 31,4 years (SD 14,1). 75.8% of patients had normal weight (BMI&lt;25), 21.0% were overweight (BMI 25-30) and 2,3% were obese (BMI&gt;30). The median duration of T1D was 13 years (P25-P75=10.7-22.0). 14,2% of the patients were admitted at least once in the year preceding the start of CSII-rtCGM because of diabetes related complications. Mean A1c was 8.6%±1.46%. The main reasons for starting CSII-rtCGM were: poor glycemic control (50.2%); frequent hypoglycemia, nocturnal hypoglycemia, hypoglycemia related to exercise, asymptomatic hypoglycemia (30.2%); severe hypoglycemia (16.44%) and dawn phenomena (3.1%). CONCLUSION Baseline characteristics of patients included in this study who were started on CSII-rtCGM are similar to those reported in the literature. The Clinic starts CSII-rtCGM mainly in T1D patients with poor glycemic control, frequent or severe hypoglycemia despite being on basal/bolus therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Sistemas de infusión de insulina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Continuous insulin infusion system</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological characterization of diabetic patients on therapy with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion and continuous glucose monitoring in real time.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
