<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26520600</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-Hernández, Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-Rivera, Leonor</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Los Santos, Lilia Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyva-López, Ahidée</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Guerra, Armando</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Castro, Filipa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To estimate the mean age of sexual intercourse debut (SID) and associated family and individual factors in 14-19-year-olds of both sexes in the 32 states of Mexico in 2007. METHODS A cross-sectional study was conducted of a representative sample of 9,893 students aged between 14 and 19 years old. The data were collected through a self-administered, anonymous and voluntary questionnaire. Logistic regression models were used to estimate odds ratios (OR) with 95% confidence intervals (95%CI) by category: no SID, SID at 10-15 years and SID at 16-19 years. RESULTS The national mean age of SID was 16 years, being 15 years for boys (95%CI: 15.88-16.11) and 16 years for girls (95%CI: 15.26-15.42). Factors associated with SID in boys were disadvantaged socioeconomic level (OR=0.66; 95%CI: 0.46-0.94), living with parents (OR=0.65; 95%CI: 0.56-0.75), less offensive communication between parents and boys/girls (OR=0.66; 95%CI: 0.57-0.77), and high social self-esteem (OR=1.68; 95%CI: 1.35-1.77). Factors associated with SID in girls were traditional gender beliefs (OR=0.49; 95%CI: 0.32-0.74), high depressive symptoms (OR=1.88; 95%CI: 1.19-2.99), and high family self-esteem (OR= 0.50; 95%CI: 0.38-0.65). CONCLUSIONS In Mexico, SID occurred early in boys. In addition, the findings of this study show that in Mexico, the age of SID and associated factors differ in boys and girls. The age of SID is strongly influenced by gender and cultural beliefs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Sexual behavior</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Conducta sexual</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adolescentes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>México</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Autoestima</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Self esteem</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adolescents</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inicio de relaciones sexuales con penetración y factores asociados en chicos y chicas de México de 14-19 años de edad con escolarización en centros públicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sexual intercourse debut and associated factors in Mexican students aged 14-19 years in public schools].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
