<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26540904</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Noguera Julian, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guix Comellas, Eva Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rozas Quesada, Librada</dc:author>
<dc:author>Force Sanmartín, Enriqueta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Tuberculosis (TB) remains a major cause of morbidity and mortality in many countries. This involves a serious public health problem. Adherence to TB treatment is a cornerstone for the control of this disease. DEVELOPMENT Globally, there are major differences between countries as to the prevalence, incidence and mortality tuberculosis. Spain has a incidence rate higher than that of other countries in their socio-economic background. Treatment is prolonged, with significant side effects. Adherence to treatment is essential to be effective, prevent drug resistance and disease control. Children are more vulnerable to developing the disease than the rest of the population. Several direct and indirect methods measure the adherence to treatment, but none is ideal. Some socio-demographic risk factors that influence on adherence are described (immigration...). In addition, there are another more specific child factors to have been add. CONCLUSIONS The literature reviewed highlights the importance of proper monitoring of patients to increase adherence to TB treatment. The role of the nurse and their interventions are very important.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La importancia de una adherencia correcta at tratamiento antitubercutoso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[THE IMPORTANCE OF PROPER ADHERENCE TO ANTI-TUBERCULOSIS TREATMENT].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de enfermeria (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
