<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26542773</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sala, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Demestre, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Raspall, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Nadal, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Foetal malnutrition (FM) is the result of a loss or failure of intrauterine acquisition of the correct amount of fat and muscle mass, with short and long term implications. As the diagnosis of FM is essentially clinical, the aim of this study is to detect the incidence of FM using the Clinical Assessment of Nutritional Status (CANS) score, and compare the results with the classic anthropometric parameters. PATIENTS AND METHODS Retrospective population of term infants was studied between 2003 and 2014 (n=14,477). They were classified into adequate weight (AGA), small weight (SGA) and large weight (LGA) for gestational age newborns. The CANS score was performed on all infants enrolled in the study, and the ponderal index (PI) was calculated, considering an FM cut off value of a CANS score &lt;25 and PI &lt;2.2g/cm(3). RESULTS Using the CANS score, 7.6% (n 1,101) of the population showed FM, 50.3% (n=538) of SGA, 76.2% (n=193) subgroup &lt;p3, and 4.67% (n=559) of AGA. The CANS score was &lt;25 in 7.26% (n=1,043) of newborns with PI ≥2.2g/cm(3) (n=14.356), and the CANS score was &gt;24 in 49% with PI &lt;2.2g/cm(3) (n=109) CONCLUSIONS: It is worthwhile identifying all newborns with FM due to the risks they may have in the short and long term. CANS score assessment allows a better identification of nutritional status of infants than only using the curves of weight for gestational age.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Intrauterine growth restriction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anthropometric parameters</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Malnutrición fetal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parámetros antropométricos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Índice ponderal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clinical assesment of nutritional status score</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Foetal malnutrition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ponderal index</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Restricción de crecimiento intrauterino</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración clínica del estado nutricional fetal al nacer mediante el Clinical Assessment of Nutritional Status score.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of foetal nutrition status at birth using the CANS score].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
