<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26547107</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alsius-Serra, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballé-Martín, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Ollé, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barba-Meseguer, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Yeste, M L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Description of the procedures followed in Catlab's pre-analytical area for UNE-EN ISO 15189 accreditation, and implementation of quality indicators to evaluate the standard requirements in the pre-analytical phase processes. MATERIAL AND METHODS Description of Catlab's 2 self-developed computer applications: Catlab Program Incidents (CPI) and Refrigerator Management Program (RMP). Both of them, among other applications, documentation and quality indicators, had enabled us to achieve UNE-EN ISO 15189 accreditation and have traceability in the pre-analytical phase. RESULTS Results of 4 quality indicators are shown. In the customers satisfaction measurement indicator, 97.3% clinicians value positively (quite/lot) different aspects of the laboratory. The indicator of pre-analytical incidents went from 7.2% in 2011 down to 4.4% in 2014. In the prompt transport of late arrival samples, 3 of the routes (33%) did not reach the acceptable target. And finally, the indicator of default opening time of sample coolers, 100% of the routes reached the desired objective in the second quarter of 2014. CONCLUSIONS The use of those applications, allowed us to design quality control indicators of the processes in the pre-analytical phase; from sample extraction to its analytical process in the laboratory, enhancing the collaboration with extraction sites, and allowing improvement actions to be established.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Acreditación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ISO 15189</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Accreditation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Preanalítica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pre-analytical</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acreditación según la norma UNE-EN ISO 15189, de la fase preanalítica del laboratorio de análisis clínicos Catlab.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[UNE-EN ISO 15189 accreditation of the preanalytical phase of a clinical laboratory].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
