<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26545527</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mendoza, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyna, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urdaneta, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artigas, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Rojas, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cámara Martos, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyna, Nadia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND the nutritional content and energy density of foods is related to greater control of appetite, satiety and reducing food intake. METHODS/SUBJECTS the randomized crossover study included 20 healthy women, aged 20 and 30 years with a BMI of 20 to 24.9 kg/m2 and who completed that included 3 day trial comparing 8 hours 130 kcal snacks consumed afternoon: yoghurt with added whey protein (PSL), biscuits and chocolate. Participants consumed a standardized menu; snack was consumed 3 hours after lunch. Perceived hunger and fullness were evaluated during the afternoon until dinner voluntary intake ad libitum. They repeat the same snack 3 times. RESULTS consumption of yogurt with PSL led to a further reduction of appetite in the afternoon in front of the snack of chocolate and biscuits (p &lt; 0.001). No differences of appetite in the afternoon between chocolate vs cookies but significant difference between yogurt with PSL and other treatments (p &lt; 0.001) were detected. At snack, yogurt there was a significant reduction in caloric intake compared to other snacks (p &lt; 0.001) and a later request for dinner with about 45 minutes apart. CONCLUSIONS snacks with less energy density and rich in protein (yogurt with PSL) improve the control of appetite, satiety and reduces food intake in healthy women later.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">LA MERIENDA CON ELEVADA PROTEÍNA DE LACTOSUERO MEJORA EL NIVEL DE SACIEDAD Y DISMINUYE EL APETITO EN MUJERES SANAS.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: el contenido nutricional y la densidad energética de los alimentos están relacionados con un mayor control del apetito, la saciedad y la reducción de la ingesta de alimentos. Material y métodos: el estudio consistió en un diseño cruzado aleatorizado que incluyó 20 mujeres sanas, con edades entre 20 y 30 años y con un IMC de 20 y 24,9 kg/m2 que se sometieron durante tres días a una prueba de ocho horas comparando meriendas de 130 kcal consumidas por la tarde: yogur con adición de proteína de suero de leche (PSL), galletas y chocolate. Consumieron un menú estandarizado; la merienda se consumía tres horas después del almuerzo. El hambre percibida y la plenitud se evaluaron durante la tarde hasta el consumo voluntario de la cena ad libitum. Resultados: el consumo de yogur con PSL ocasionó una mayor reducción del apetito y un aumento de la saciedad tras su ingesta y hasta la cena, respecto a la merienda de chocolate y galletas (p &lt; 0,001), no existiendo diferencias entre estas últimas. La merienda de yogur con PSL ocasionó una reducción significativa de la ingesta calórica en la cena, en comparación con las otras meriendas (p &lt; 0,001) y una solicitud más tardía de alimentos de hasta 45 minutos. Conclusiones: las meriendas con baja densidad energética y ricas en proteína (y concretamente el yogur con PSL), pueden ser una solución eficaz para mejorar el control del apetito y reducir la ingesta de alimentos en mujeres sanas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[SNACK HIGH WHEY PROTEIN IMPROVES THE LEVEL OF SATIETY AND REDUCES APPETITE HEALTHY WOMEN].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
