<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26546937</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Arroyo, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Madero, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Menacho-Miguel, David</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to determine the prescription of drugs with known risk to prolong the QT interval in a Healthcare Area, to provide information to those physicians responsible about the risk factors associated with its development, and to improve patient safety. METHODS a descriptive cross-sectional observational study of prevalence. A total of 4, 964 patients from a Healthcare Area treated in one month with drugs with known risk were included in the study. Risk drugs, interactions and predisposing factors were identified. Physicians were provided with the list of patients with drugs with known risk, recommendations, and a questionnaire to know more risk factors, utility and clinical attitude. A descriptive statistical analysis was conducted. RESULTS of the total number of patients in the Area, 3.2% were treated with drugs with known risk. 64.0% were women, 57.5% were older than 65 years and 39.6% had drug interactions. The mean number of risk factors per patient was 1.78 (CI 95%: 1.74-1.81). Antidepressants (41.2%) and antibiotics (40.4%) were the most commonly prescribed drugs with known risk. 25.4% of the physicians returned the questionnaire and reported the clinical attitude in 1, 073 patients: the drug with known risk was withdrawn in 289, the dose was reduced in 113, and an electrocardiogram was performed in 398. Physicians identified other risk factors: heart disease (17.9%) and hypo/hyperthyroidism (8.8%). CONCLUSIONS the detected prevalence of prescription of drugs that prolong the QT interval is relevant, considering that the patients also had other risk factors. Their identification can improve the quality of care and patient safety.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Sep 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad en el paciente: prescripción de fármacos que prolongan el intervalo QT.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: conocer la prescripcion de farmacos con riesgo conocido de prolongar el intervalo QT en un area de salud, informar a los medicos responsables de los factores de riesgo asociados a su aparicion y mejorar la seguridad del paciente. Métodos: estudio descriptivo transversal y observacional de prevalencia. Se incluyeron 4.964 pacientes de un area de salud en tratamiento con farmacos con riesgo conocido en un mes. Se identificaron farmacos de riesgo, interacciones y factores predisponentes. Se proporciono a cada medico los pacientes con farmacos con riesgo conocido, las recomendaciones y la encuesta para conocer mas factores de riesgo, su utilidad y su actitud clinica. Se realizo un analisis estadistico descriptivo. Resultados: el 3,2% de los pacientes del area estaban tratados con farmacos con riesgo conocido. El 64,0% eran mujeres, 57,5% mayores de 65 anos, y el 39,6% presentaban interacciones. El numero medio de factores de riesgo por paciente fue 1,78. Los farmacos con riesgo conocido mas frecuentes fueron antidepresivos (41,2%) y antibioticos (40,4%). El 25,4% de los medicos devolvio la encuesta informando de la actitud clinica en 1.073 pacientes: se retiro el farmaco con riesgo conocido en 289, se redujo la dosis en 113 y se realizo electrocardiograma en 398. Los medicos identificaron otros factores de riesgo: problema cardiaco (17,9%) e hiper/hipotiroidismo (8,8%). Conclusiones: la prevalencia detectada en la prescripcion de farmacos que prolongan el intervalo QT es relevante teniendo en cuenta que los pacientes tenian ademas otros factores de riesgo. Su identificacion permite mejorar la calidad de la atencion y la seguridad del paciente. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Patient safety: prescription of drugs that prolong the QT interval].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
