<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26578415</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7450</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Uribe-Villa, Esteban</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Briceño, Paola</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Jaramillo, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacio-Ortíz, Juan David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Duque-Ríos, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Quintero, Cristian Esteban</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapata-Henao, Violeta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Offspring of bipolar parents are a high risk population for the develop of mental diseases, their study allow determining the genetic risk, early symptoms, prodromes and psychopathology of bipolar disorder. OBJECTIVE To describe the psychopathological characteristics and neurocognitives profiles of the offspring of bipolar type I parents. And to identify the presence of sub-syndromal symptoms in all the symptom domains. METHODS A descriptive and cross-sectional study was conducted on 110 offspring between 6 and 30 years old. Semi-structured diagnostic interviews were performed. The intelectual coeficient was determined and a neuropsychological assessment was performed on 89 offspring. RESULTS The most prevalent disorder in the offspring was ADHD (27.6%), with major depression (15.5%) and separation anxiety (14.1%) also being prevalent. Seven patients of the sample were diagnosed with bipolar disorder. There was a statistically significant difference between the age groups for ADHD prevalence. The most frequent sub-syndromal symptoms were observed in the disruptive group. Alterations in the cognitive domains: attention, verbal fluency, work memory, and speed of information processing, were observed in the group younger than 18 years. CONCLUSIONS The offspring of bipolar parents have an elevated rate of psychopathology and cognitive alterations. They are a high risk population for the development of mental disease. These subjects also require close longitudinal observation and early and preventive therapeuthic interventions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Bipolar's offspring</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Offspring</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trastorno afectivo bipolar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neurocognitives profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neurocognitivos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bipolar disorder</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hijos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hijos de pacientes con trastorno bipolar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psychopathology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psicopatología</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de perfiles psicopatológicos y neurocognitivos de hijos de pacientes con trastorno bipolar tipo I dentro un programa de intervencion multimodal: PRISMA.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Description of Clinical and Neurocognitive Profiles in Offspring of Bipolar-Type-I Parents From a Multimodal Intervention Program: Prisma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista colombiana de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
