<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26574122</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>De Troya Martín, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Canedo, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Repiso-Jiménez, J B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivas-Ruiz, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blázquez-Sánchez, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Surgical reconstruction of the external nose, a common site for nonmelanoma skin cancer, is difficult. Oncologic surgery often leaves large skin defects, occasionally involving the underlying cartilage and nasal mucosa. We describe our experience with the paramedian forehead flap for reconstruction of nasal defects. METHODOLOGY We performed a retrospective study of consecutive patients in whom a paramedian forehead flap was used to repair surgical defects of the nose between July 2004 and March 2011. We describe the clinical and epidemiologic characteristics, the surgical technique, complications, secondary procedures, and cosmetic results. RESULTS The series comprised 41 patients with a mean (SD) age of 67 (10.36) years. The majority were men (male to female ratio, 2.4:1). Associated risk factors included diabetes in 27% of patients, cardiovascular risk factors in 49%, and smoking or drinking in 19.5%. The tissue defects were distal in 80% of cases and nonpenetrating in 78%. The mean (SD) diameter was 21.6 (6.78) mm. Early postoperative complications occurred in 14.6% of patients and late complications in 31.7% (trap door effect in 22% and hair transposition in 19%), with a need for Readjustment in a second operation was needed in 19.5% of patients. The cosmetic results were considered acceptable or excellent in 90.2% of cases. DISCUSSION The paramedian forehead flap is versatile and provides skin of a similar color and texture to that of the external nose. It has a reliable vascular pedicle that guarantees the viability not only of the flap but also of other tissues that may be used in combination, such as chondromucosal or chondrocutaneous grafts. Revision of the technique in a second operation may sometimes be required to achieve an optimal result.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Nasal reconstruction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de piel no melanoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nonmelanoma skin cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colgajo paramediofrontal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Paramedian forehead flap</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reconstrucción nasal</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of the Paramedian Forehead Flap in Nasal Reconstructive Surgery: A Retrospective Series of 41 Patients.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
