<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26573267</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marcos-Camina, R M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo-Buey, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calvo-Marcos, D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine whether the use of CPRmeter(®) during the resuscitation manoeuvres, is related to a higher quality of external cardiac massage, as recommended by the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (ILCOR). To compare the quality obtained without the use or this, and whether there are differences related to anthropometric, demographic, professional and/or occupational factors. METHOD Experimental, open trial performed with life support simulators in a stratified random sample of 88 health workers randomly distributed between groups A (without indications of the device) and B (with them). The homogeneity of their confounding variables was compared, as well as the compressions depth and compressions rate, the proportion of completed release, and distribution of the quality massage variable (according to criteria ILCOR) between the groups. The qualitative variables were analysed with the chi-square test, and quantitative variables with the Student t-test or Mann-Whitney U-test and the association between the variable quality massage variable, and use of the device with the odds ratio. RESULTS Group A: mean depth 42.1mm (standard deviation 10.1), mean rate 121.3/min (21.6), percentage of complete release 71.2% (36.9). Group B: 51.2mm (5.9) 111.9/min (6.4), 92.9% (10.1) respectively. Odds ratio for quality massage regarding the use of the device was 5.170 (95% CI; 2.060-12.977). CONCLUSIONS The use of CPRmeter(®) device in simulated resuscitations is related to a higher quality of cardiac massage, improving the approach to the ILCOR recommendations, regardless of the characteristics of the participants. They were 83.8% more likely to achieve a quality massage using the device than without it.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Simulation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiopulmonary resuscitation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiac arrest</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dispositivos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Heart massage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Devices</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Paro cardiaco</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Masaje cardiaco</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resucitación cardiopulmonar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Simulación</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio aleatorizado de la relación entre el uso del dispositivo CPRmeter® y la calidad de las compresiones torácicas en una resucitación cardiopulmonar simulada.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Randomised study of the relationship between the use of CPRmeter® device and the quality of chest compressions in a simulated cardiopulmonary resuscitation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
