<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26573115</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7450</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández, José Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espejo, Lina María</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Espriella, Ricardo Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES Determining the presence of cortical release signs associated with white matter damage, is a clinically easy method to perform. The objective of this study is to determine the presence of cortical release signs in patients with mental illnesses and cerebrovascular disease, as well as its clinical usefulness, given that it indicates cortical damage. MATERIAL AND METHODS A review was made of cortical release signs in patients hospitalized in clinical psychiatry and general hospitals with bipolar affective disorder (40), depression (37), schizophrenia (33), cardiovascular disease (33) and dementia (37). RESULTS The signs of cortical release do not have the same importance as cortical damage. For example, the glabellar reflex was found in all the groups, that of paratonia, particularly in the group with schizophrenia, and others signs in the group of patients with dementia. CONCLUSIONS It is suggested that these signs imply subcortical white matter damage. The appearance of these signs shows the need for a follow up of patients diagnosed with bipolar affective disorder, depression and schizophrenia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cortical reflexes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reflejos corticales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vascular dementia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mental Illness</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Demencia vascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad mental</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2013 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Signos de liberación cortical en pacientes con esquizofrenia, trastornos depresivos, trastorno afectivo bipolar, demencia y enfermedad cerebrovascular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cortical Release Signs in Patients with Schizophrenia, Depressive Disorders, and Bipolar Affective Disorder].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista colombiana de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
