<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26572112</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7450</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Acosta, Miguel Barrios</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas, Rafael Vásquez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Amaya, Javier Guillermo Díaz</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Child upbringing of women engaged in prostitution has been little explored. METHODS Child upbringing beliefs, attitudes and practices regarding sexuality in prostitutes' children and adolescents were explored downtown in Bogota. Analytical-interpretive research included in-depth interviews and a focus group. There were ten women between 28 and 56 years of age. Core issues were their subjectivity as mothers, sexual development challenges, upbringing social and cultural conditions. RESULTS Structural, symbolic and economic violence are the main determinants of parenting. Sexual abuse and the possibility of pregnancy in their adolescent daughters are the most important concerns. CONCLUSIONS In general, the participants share the same values and reproduce traditional ideals in gender and sexuality, which are transmitted and modeled from upbringing.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Crianza</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Upbringing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>prostitución</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sexualidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>sexuality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>prostitution</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>violencia estructural</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>structural violence</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2012 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crianza y sexualidad de hijos de mujeres prostitutas marginales del centro de Bogotá.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Upbringing and Sexuality in Children from Marginal Prostitute Women Downtown in Bogotá].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista colombiana de psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
