<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26580926</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chirino-Galindo, Gladys</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trejo-González, Ninna Leslie</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palomar-Morales, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To evaluate the anti-hyperglycemic and anti-teratogenic capacity of resveratrol in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. MATERIAL AND METHODS Experimental study. There were three groups, of five rats each; two groups were treated with a single dose of 50 mg/Kg of streptozotocin (STZ), in citrate buffer, at the 4th day of gestation, and the third group was considered the control, and were administered with citrate buffer only. One of the two STZ induced groups was administered with 100 mg/Kg resveratrol the days 8th to 12th, when neurulation occurs. Fetuses were obtained the 19th gestational day, and were subjected to morphologic analysis; and in fetal liver the activities of scavenging enzymes catalase, superoxide dismutase and gluthathione peroxidase were measured. RESULTS Resveratrol can decrease the teratogenic effect of STZ-induced diabetes, and scavenging activities were beneficed by the administration of this antioxidant. CONCLUSION Resveratrol shown embryoprotective properties mediated by amelioration of oxidative stress produced by maternal hyperglycemia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capacidad antiteratogénica del resveratrol en diabetes inducida por estreptozotocina en ratas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Antiteratogenic capacity of resveratrol in streptozotocin-induced diabetes in rats].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
