<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26593799</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dilmen, Ugur</dc:author>
<dc:author>Celik, Istemi H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uras, Nurdan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oguz, Erife S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Erdeve, Omer</dc:author>
<dc:author>Demirel, Gamze</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In our clinical practice, we observed high interleukin-6 (IL-6) levels in gram-negative sepsis. OBJECTIVE To investigate the relationship between IL-6 and C-reactive protein (CRP) levels and early determination of neonatal sepsis of gram-negative or gram-positive aetiology. POPULATION AND METHODS White blood cell count, IL-6 and CRP levels were compared among different groups. RESULTS Gram-negative, gram-positive and fungal infection groups consisted of 73, 82 and 15 patients, respectively. The optimal cut-off levels of IL-6 between gram-negative and gram-positive fungal infection groups were 202 and 57 pg/ml. The fungal infection group had higher CRP levels than gram-negative and positive infection groups. CONCLUSIONS To our knowledge, this is the largest reported study aiming at determining of IL-6 cut-off levels to differentiate neonatal sepsis aetiology. Gram-negative microorganisms led to 10 fold higher IL-6 production. The evaluation of IL-6 and CRP is useful to diagnose and also differentiate neonatal sepsis aetiology.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Dec 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función de la concentración sérica de interleucina 6 y proteína C-reactiva para diferenciar la etiología de la septicemia neonatal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The role of serum interleukin-6 and C-reactive protein levels for differentiating aetiology of neonatal sepsis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
