<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26602103</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1747</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Puzo, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viñuales, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viñuales, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanclemente, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the level of adherence to the Mediterranean dietary pattern (DMedit) in people over 65 in rural and urban areas of the region of Hoya de Huesca (Spain) and investigate whether there are sociodemographic factors related to that adherence. MATERIAL AND METHODS Exploratory cross-sectional study. Two questionnaires were used: one self-made for sociodemographic factors, and the PREDIMED validated questionnaire to assess the level of adherence to the DMedit. After prior informed consent, a total of 240 questionnaires were collected over a period of 2 consecutive weeks in March 2014. RESULTS The mean age was 74±6.8 years, with an equal proportion of rural and urban areas and both sexes. Both populations showed a similar adherence pattern to Dmedit, with an average overall score of 9 on a scale of 0 to 14. Furthermore, the influence of sociodemographic factors was observed on the level of adherence to the Dmedit, such as purchasing power or presence of chronic diet-related diseases. CONCLUSIONS The urban and rural population of the Hoya de Huesca seems to have a good adherence to the Dmedit, although some economic and health factors could modify it.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Demographic factors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mediterranean diet</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dieta mediterránea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rural and urban population</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ancianos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Elderly</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Factores sociodemográficos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ámbito rural y urbano</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores sociodemográficos asociados con el grado de adherencia al patrón de dieta mediterránea en personas mayores.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sociodemographic factors associated with adherence to the Mediterranean dietary pattern in elderly people].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de geriatria y gerontologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
