<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26618377</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-753X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arrabal Durán, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Haba Peña, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanjurjo Sáez, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Buendía Bravo, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Sánchez, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Fresneda, María Norberta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE to assess the causes of the Emergency Department visits in cancer patients treated with antineoplastics. The secondary objective is to analyse the use of growth stimulating factors in febrile neutropenia. METHODS a retrospective observational study was conducted during six months of 2012. The adult patients diagnosed with solid tumour that visited the Emergency Department and whose physician was an oncologist, were included. RESULTS a total of 83 patients fulfilled the inclusion criteria. The causes of visits were: 63% due to the tumour, 31% due to the chemotherapy toxicity and 6% due to other causes. In patients with chemotherapy toxicity, 65% had fever or infection, 50% pain and 42% febrile neutropenia. The treatment and prophylaxis with filgrastim followed the recommendations. CONCLUSIONS in cancer patients, most of emergencies are due to the tumour. The management of the pain, the fever and the neutropenia is important.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Nov 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis descriptivo de los motivos que originan visitas a urgencias en pacientes oncológicos: toxicidad postquimioterapia.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: cuantificar y analizar las causas por las que los pacientes oncológicos acuden al Servicio de Urgencias y analizar el uso de factores estimulantes de colonias para la profilaxis o el tratamiento de la neutropenia febril. Método: estudio retrospectivo de seis meses del año 2012. Se incluyeron pacientes adultos con tumor sólido y tratamiento activo atendidos por oncólogos en el Servicio de Urgencias. Resultados: se incluyeron 83 pacientes. Respecto al motivo de consulta: en el 63% es causa tumoral, 31% toxicidad postquimioterapia y 6% otras causas. En los que acuden por toxicidad, el 65% presentaron fiebre o síntomas de infección, el 50% dolor y el 42% neutropenia febril. La profilaxis y el tratamiento de la neutropenia febril con filgrastim siguieron las recomendaciones. Conclusiones: la mayor parte de los episodios oncológicos en Urgencias son debidos al propio proceso tumoral. Algunos problemas importantes son el manejo del dolor, la fiebre y la neutropenia. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Causes of the emergency department visits in cancer patients: postchemotherapy toxicity].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Farmacia hospitalaria : organo oficial de expresion cientifica de la Sociedad Espanola de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
