<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26667729</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Jurado, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Porres, Jesús María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nebot, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kapravelou, Garyfallia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Moral, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:author>Talbi, Chouhra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bedmar, Eulogio Jose</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to study the effect of co-inoculation with Ensifer meliloti and Halomonas maura of the leguminous Medicago sativa L., on growth, nutritional and functional value, grown under salinity conditions. METHODS plants of M. sativa were grown in a solution with a mixture of salts (CaSO4, MgCl, NaCl and NaHCO 3) and were co-inoculated with its specific rhizobium and the halophilic moderated bacterium H. maura. Different physiologic parameters were determined, as well as, nitrogen and minerals content. Furthermore, an assay of in vitro digestibility was carried out. RESULTS salinity had a negative effect on the plants; however, co-inoculation increased yield, nitrogen content, total minerals, Ca and Mg. Moreover, physiologic parameters as water potential and leghemoglobin content in fresh nodules were higher compared to those of plants inoculated only with E. meliloti. Both, salinity and bacterial treatment with E. meliloti and H. maura increased the antioxidant capacity of the legume, in dialyzates and retentates collected after an in vitro digestibility assay. CONCLUSION co-inoculation of plants with E. meliloti and H. maura could improve the alfalfa yield under specific salinity conditions, increasing the nutritional and functional value of the plants. M. sativa could be considered in the formulations of nutritional supplements for the human diet.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Dec 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">MEDICAGO SATIVA L: MEJORA Y NUEVOS ASPECTOS DE SU VALOR NUTRITIVO Y FUNCIONAL POR COINOCULACIÓN BACTERIANA.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Objetivo: estudiar el efecto de la inoculación con Ensifer meliloti y Halomonas maura sobre el crecimiento y el valor nutricional y funcional de la leguminosa Medicago sativa L., cultivada bajo condiciones de salinidad. Método: las plantas de M. sativa se cultivaron con una solución de mezcla de sales CaSO4, MgCl, NaCl and Na- HCO3 y se coinocularon con su rizobio específico y la bacteria H. maura. Se determinaron los parámetros fisiológicos de las plantas, así como el contenido en nitrógeno y minerales, y se llevó a cabo un proceso de digestibilidad in vitro. Resultados: la salinidad ejerció un efecto negativo sobre las plantas; sin embargo, la coinoculación de las mismas incrementó su productividad, el contenido en nitrógeno, minerales totales, Ca y Mg. Además, los parámetros fisiológicos de potencial hídrico y concentración de leghemoglobina se incrementaron. Tanto la salinidad como la coinoculación de las plantas aumentaron la capacidad antioxidante de la leguminosa en los dializados y retenidos obtenidos tras someter a la planta a un proceso de digestibilidad in vitro. Conclusión: la coinoculación con E. meliloti y H. maura podría mejorar el cultivo de la alfalfa bajo condiciones específicas de salinidad, aumentando su composición nutricional y funcional, pudiendo considerarse en la formulación de suplementos nutricionales para el consumo humano. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[MEDICAGO SATIVA L: IMPROVEMENT AND NEW APPROACHES OF ITS NUTRITIONAL AND FUNCTIONAL VALUE BY BACTERIAL CO-INOCULATION].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
