<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26662870</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gargallo-Vaamonde, Álvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Seijas-Gomez, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iridoy-Zulet, Marina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna-Lario, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabada-Giadas, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tirapu-Ustarroz, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jerico-Pascual, Ivonne</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lopez-Goni, José Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basterra-Jimenez, Izaskun</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Type 1 myotonic dystrophy (MD-1) or Steinert disease is a multisystemic progressive disorder. Studies have shown cognitive deficits, depressive symptoms and a high incidence of anxiety personality traits that compromise both the functionality and the quality of life of these patients. AIM To describe the cognitive and psychopathological profile of a sample of patients with the adult variant of MD-1. PATIENTS AND METHODS A sample of 27 patients diagnosed with MD-1 was selected from those being followed up in the neurology service of the Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra. Eligibility criteria were age under 50 years and the absence of any other pathology or physical condition that prevented them from performing the psychological evaluation. A neuropsychological evaluation battery specifically designed for this kind of pathology was used, together with psychopathological and functionality measures. RESULTS The neuropsychological evaluation revealed mainly deficits in visual-constructional and visuospatial skills, alternating attention and in other-reported dysexecutive signs and symptoms. The group of patients did not present any clinically significant symptoms of depression or anxiety, but did score high on obsession-compulsion, interpersonal sensitivity, paranoid ideation and psychoticism. The results point towards a deterioration in functionality. CONCLUSIONS In the integral approach to MD-1, the characterisation and developmental monitoring of the cognitive, psychopathological and personality profile, as well as the level of functionality, all contribute to an improvement in the quality of life of these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Dec 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo del perfil neuropsicologico y psicopatologico en pacientes con distrofia miotonica tipo 1.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Estudio descriptivo del perfil neuropsicologico y psicopatologico en pacientes con distrofia miotonica tipo 1. 
             Introduccion. La distrofia miotonica tipo 1 (DM-1) o enfermedad de Steinert es un trastorno multisistemico y progresivo. Se han encontrado deficits cognitivos, clinica depresiva y alta incidencia de rasgos de personalidad ansiosos con afectacion tanto en la funcionalidad como en la calidad de vida de estos pacientes. Objetivo. Describir el perfil cognitivo y psicopatologico de una muestra de pacientes con la variante adulta de DM-1. Pacientes y metodos. Se selecciono una muestra de 27 pacientes con diagnostico de DM-1 en seguimiento en el Servicio de Neurologia del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra. Los criterios de inclusion fueron tener menos de 50 anos y descartar cualquier otra patologia o condicion fisica que impidiese realizar la evaluacion psicologica. Se utilizo una bateria de evaluacion neuropsicologica especificamente disenada para este tipo de patologia, ademas de medidas de psicopatologia y funcionalidad. Resultados. La evaluacion neuropsicologica reflejo, principalmente, deficits en habilidades visuoconstructivas, visuoespaciales, atencion alternante y en sintomatologia disejecutiva heteroinformada. El grupo de pacientes no presento sintomatologia depresiva ni ansiosa clinicamente significativa, pero si puntuaciones elevadas en obsesion-compulsion, sensibilidad interpersonal, ideacion paranoide y psicoticismo. Los resultados orientaron hacia un deterioro en la funcionalidad. Conclusiones. En el abordaje integral de la DM-1, la caracterizacion y el seguimiento evolutivo del perfil cognitivo, psicopatologico y de personalidad, asi como del nivel de funcionalidad, contribuyen a la mejora de la calidad de vida de estos pacientes. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A descriptive study of the neuropsychological and psychopathological profile in patients with type 1 myotonic dystrophy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
