<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26677776</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fittipaldi-Márquez, M Sol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Forn, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belenguer-Benavides, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-Gómez, Álvaro J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Bronchal, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION One of the most prevalent cognitive deficits in multiple sclerosis (MS) patients relates to (both verbal and visual) information encoding, a process related the hippocampus. AIM To assess the relationship between information learning and long-term retention processes and hippocampal volume and functional connectivity (FC) in MS patients. SUBJECTS AND METHODS MS patients and a control group of healthy volunteers were assessed using the brief neuro-psychological battery, which includes tests of verbal and visual memory. Gray matter volume was assessed through the voxel based morphometry technique, and a study of seed-based FC focused on the region of ??interest (hippocampus) was also conducted. RESULTS Results revealed that, as compared to the control group, MS patients display gray matter atrophy at the left hippocampus gray matter and smaller FC between left hippocampus and brainstem, cerebellum, fusiform gyrus and superior temporal gyrus. Association analyses were performed between memory tests performance and both volumetric and FC changes. Results showed a positive correlation between gray matter hippocampal (bilateral) volume and verbal memory performance of the MS group. Further, in MS patients, a positive correlation between visual memory performance and FC between the left hippocampus and several temporal regions was also found. CONCLUSIONS The results of the present study reveal a relationship between structural and functional changes in the hippocampus of MS patients and their performance on verbal and visual memory tests.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jan 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios estructurales y funcionales del hipocampo en pacientes con esclerosis múltiple y su relación con procesos de memoria.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Cambios estructurales y funcionales del hipocampo en pacientes con esclerosis multiple y su relacion con procesos de memoria. 
             Introduccion. Una de las alteraciones cognitivas mas prevalentes en los pacientes con esclerosis multiple son los problemas de codificacion de la informacion (tanto verbal como visual), proceso relacionado con el hipocampo. Objetivo. Estudiar la relacion entre los procesos de aprendizaje y retencion de la informacion a largo plazo con el volumen hipocampal y la conectividad funcional (CF) en pacientes con esclerosis multiple comparados con un grupo control. Sujetos y metodos. Ambos grupos fueron evaluados con la bateria neuropsicologica breve, que incluye pruebas de memoria verbal y visual. Se realizo el estudio de volumetria de la sustancia gris mediante la tecnica de morfometria basada en el voxel y un estudio de CF de voxel de semilla centrado en la zona de interes (hipocampo). Se realizaron analisis de asociacion entre rendimiento en memoria y cambios volumetricos y de CF. Resultados. Los resultados mostraron atrofia en la sustancia gris en el hipocampo izquierdo y una menor CF entre el hipocampo izquierdo y el troncoencefalo, el cerebelo, el giro fusiforme y el giro temporal superior en los pacientes respecto al grupo control. En el grupo de pacientes se observa una correlacion positiva entre la sustancia gris en ambos hipocampos y el rendimiento en memoria verbal, asi como una correlacion positiva entre el rendimiento en memoria visual y la CF entre el hipocampo izquierdo y diversas regiones temporales. Conclusiones. Los resultados muestran una relacion entre el rendimiento de memoria verbal y visual, y cambios estructurales y funcionales en el hipocampo en pacientes con esclerosis multiple. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Structural and functional changes of the hippocampus in patients with multiple sclerosis and their relationship with memory processes].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
