<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26675268</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Real, José Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Hervás, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Civera, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ascaso, Juan Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Basanta-Alario, María Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferri, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is a chronic, highly prevalent disease that increases with age. Because of this, and due to its chronic complications, T2DM causes high human, social, and financial costs. In addition, the elderly population with T2DM has a marked clinical heterogeneity. Therefore, our main objective was to analyze the relationship of age with the clinical and biological manifestations of the disease and the prevalence of chronic complications in patients with T2DM. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study of a large population with T2DM (n=405) randomly selected from a Diabetes Unit and 2 health care centers (60%). The clinical, anthropometric, and biochemical variables of the subjects were collected using standard methods to assess the effect of age on the clinical and biochemical phenotype of patients with T2DM. RESULTS We have noted that patients with T2DM &gt; 70 years old have a clinical and biochemical phenotype different from younger subjects (&lt;60 years) including longer times since diabetes onset, higher diastolic blood pressure levels, and lower body mass index (BMI) values. As regards to biological variables, these patients have lower triglyceride levels, impaired kidney function, and lower HbA1c values. Prevalence of metabolic syndrome is lower in patients with T2DM &gt; 70 years of age. Age was inversely related to parameters associated to metabolic syndrome (BMI, waist circumference, blood pressure, and triglyceride levels). CONCLUSIONS We have defined the clinical and biochemical profile of patients with T2DM &gt; 70 years attending health care centers. In addition, the prevalence of stroke, kidney disease, and distal symmetrical polyneuropathy is higher in patients with T2DM &gt;70 years as compared to younger patients (&lt;60 years).</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anciano</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clinical and biochemical profile</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes tipo 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones crónicas de la diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic diabetic complications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome metabólico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolic syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Elderly</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Perfil clínico biológico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in clinical and biological characteristics and prevalence of chronic complications related to aging in patients with type 2 diabetes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
