<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26681433</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vergara-Mitxeltorena, Itziar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vrotsou, Kalliopi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dorronsoro-Iraeta, Miren</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrañaga-Larrañaga, Nerea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Larrañaga-Padilla, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Machón-Sobrado, Mónica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyse the dimensions studied with respect to living and health conditions of the non-institutionalised elderly in the scientific literature in Spain. METHOD A content analysis based on secondary sources was carried out by literature searches in Pubmed and Embase in Spanish and English. The search strategies combined terms related to older people, health and/or living conditions and with Spain. All studies assessing living and/or health conditions of elderly in Spain were included. Studies analyzing a specific aspect of living or health conditions and those based on institutionalized population were excluded. RESULTS A total of 14 studies were considered in the content analysis. The studies are usually local, cross-sectional and data collection is done by direct interview. Variability was observed in the aspects analysed about living and health conditions. All studies included: sociodemographic characteristics, health status and lifestyle habits. Issues related to the status of the out-of home environment are poorly analysed. CONCLUSIONS This work allows knowing the dimensions prioritised in the studies carried out to date about health and living conditions in Spain. It also provides key elements for the development of future research aiming to integrate both living and health conditions of elderly population, both aspects closely related.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Health status</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aging</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Envejecimiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad de vida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estado de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality of life</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual de la investigación sobre las condiciones de vida y el estado de salud de las personas mayores en España.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Current situation of the research on living conditions and health status of elderly people in Spain].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
