<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26708736</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Marín, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, Olga</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardozo, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soler, María Del Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz, Oscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, Ruth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Avila, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bautista-Molano, Wilson</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Few studies report the epidemiological profile of RA patients attending clinics for comprehensive care. We describe the clinical, socio-demographic characteristics and comorbidities of a cohort of patients with RA. METHODS Cross-sectional study in a cohort of patients according to ACR criteria/EULAR 2010 classification who have entered to the AR clinic since October 2012 until May 2014, referred from primary care. Frequencies for socio-demographic, comorbidity, state of disease activity, functional status, biomarkers and therapeutic modalities variables are described. RESULTS In total, 1652 patients were included with a mean age of 58 years and a duration of 9 years. Rheumatoid factor was positive in 80% and anti-citrullinated peptide antibody in 63% of patients. In total, 43.6% of patients had comorbidities: Hypertension (20.4%), osteoporosis (17.3%) and Sjögren's syndrome (10.4%). Fifty percent of the patients had moderate and high disease activity level measured by DAS-28 score, and the mean HAQ score was 0.64 (DS 1.12). Seventy three percent of patients were treated with oral disease modified anti rheumatic treatment and 63.6% of them were with methotrexate. 42.4% of the patients were treated with glucocorticoids (mean dose 6.3mg). CONCLUSIONS The epidemiological behavior of a group of RA patients is reported. The presence of comorbidities is significant affecting the risk of morbidity and mortality in these patients. The definition of the epidemiological profile of this population will allow the design of research questions to resolve outstanding problems in the clinical context of this pathology.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Artritis reumatoide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiological profile</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cohort</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rheumatoid arthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cohorte</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Perfil epidemiológico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil epidemiológico de pacientes colombianos con artritis reumatoide evaluados en una clínica especializada de atención integral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological profile of colombian patients with rheumatoid arthritis in a specialized care clinic.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
