<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26710539</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alvarado, Primavera</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuestal, De</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mendoza, Mireya</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cermehol, Julman R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herndndez, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Broth microdilution, the reference method recommended by the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI), is not available for use with dimorphic fungi, such as those of the Paracoccidioides genus. In this work, in vitro susceptibility of the Paracoccidioides complex (n=19) to systemic antifungals: amphotericin B, 5-flucytosine, ketoconazole, itraconazole, fluconazole, voriconazole and caspofungin, was evaluated using the microdilution method (Document M27-A3, M27-S3), with some modifications such as: culture time in Sabouraud dextrose agar (7-10 days), RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 2% glucose and the incubation time (7, 8 and 18 days). The sensitivity in vitro was variable; the majority of Paracoccidioides isolates was susceptible to ketoconazol (73.7%), followed by voriconazole (68.4%), itraconazole (63.1%), amphotericin B (52.6%), fluconazole (47.4%), 5-flucytosine (42.1%) and caspofungin (5%). The overall resistance was mainly to caspofungin (94.7%), followed by 5-flucytosine (52.6%) and amphotericin B (47.4%). Fifty-three percent of the isolates were susceptible-dose dependent to fluconazole followed by itraconazole (15.7%) and 5-fluorocytosine (5.3%). Amphotericin B, itraconazole and voriconazole were the most potent antifungal drugs against Paracoccidioides spp (CMI: 0.03-1 microg/mL). Based on these results, we tentatively propose a microdilution assay protocol for susceptibility testing of Paracoccidioides spp to antifungal drugs. This method may be clinically useful to predict resistance, even though further studies are needed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad in vitro de aislados del complejo Paracoccidioides spp a antifúngicos sistémicos utilizando el método de microdilución.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[In vitro susceptibility of isolates of Paracoccidioides spp complex to systemic antifungals using the microdilution method].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
