<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26711504</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2021</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>de la Figuera, Mariano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orera, Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martell-Claros, Nieves</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escalada, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso-Moreno, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the flow of care for patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and hypertension between primary care (PC) and specialized care (SC) in clinical practice, and the criteria used for referral and follow-up within the Spanish National Health System (NHS). DESIGN A descriptive, cross-sectional, multicenter study. PLACEMENT A probability convenience sampling stratified by number of physicians participating in each Spanish autonomous community was performed. Nine hundred and ninety-nine physicians were surveyed, of whom 78.1% (n=780) were primary care physicians (PCPs), while 11.9% (n=119) and 10.0% (n=100) respectively were specialists in hypertension and diabetes. KEY MEASUREMENTS: was conducted using two self administered online surveys. RESULTS A majority of PCPs (63.7% and 55.5%) and specialists (79.8% and 45.0%) reported the lack of a protocol to coordinate the primary and specialized settings for both hypertension and T2DM respectively. The most widely used method for communication between specialists was the referral sheet (94.6% in PC and 92.4% in SC). The main reasons for referral to a specialist were refractory hypertension (80.9%) and suspected secondary hypertension (75.6%) in hypertensive patients, and suspicion of a specific diabetes (71.9%) and pregnancy (71.7%) in T2DM patients. CONCLUSIONS Although results showed some common characteristics between PCPs and specialists in disease management procedures, the main finding was a poor coordination between PC and SC.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hypertension</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health care levels</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipertensión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niveles de atención de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary care</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professionals' perception of circuits of care for hypertensive or diabetic patients between primary and secondary care.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia y nutricion : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Endocrinologia y Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
