<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26726117</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moreno-Ramírez, M Paz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Salvador, Adelina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colodro-Amores, Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Sánchez, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera-Martos, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valenza, Marie Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE Respiratory infections involve not only hospitalization due to pneumonia, but also acute exacerbations of COPD (AECOPD). The objective of the present study was to evaluate the effectiveness of a physical therapy intervention during hospitalization in patients admitted due to community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) and AECOPD. MATERIAL AND METHOD Randomized clinical trial, 44 patients were randomized into 2 groups: a control group which received standard medical therapy (oxygen therapy and pharmacotherapy) and an experimental group that received standard treatment and a physical therapy intervention (breathing exercises, electrostimulation, exercises with elastic bands and relaxation). RESULTS Between-groups analysis showed that after the intervention (experimental vs. control) significant differences were found in perceived dyspnoea (P=.041), and right and left quadriceps muscle strength (P=.008 and P=.010, respectively). In addition, the subscale of "domestic activities" of the functional ability related to respiratory symptoms questionnaire showed significant differences (P=.036). CONCLUSION A physical therapy intervention during hospitalization in patients with AECOPD and CAP can generate skeletal muscle level gains that exceed the deterioration caused by immobilization during hospitalization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pneumonia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Modalidades de fisioterapia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hospitalization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Physical therapy modalities</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hospitalización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neumonía</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención fisioterápica durante la hospitalización en pacientes con exacerbación aguda de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica y neumonía: un ensayo clínico aleatorizado.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Physical therapy intervention during hospitalization in patients with acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and pneumonia: A randomized clinical trial].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
