<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26731420</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6384</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navajas-Galimany, Lucas</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Mario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic spontaneous urticaria is a disorder mediated by mast cells, characterized by the development of wheals, angioedema or both, lasting six weeks or more, with or without a known trigger agent. First and second line treatment are antihistamines, but some refractory cases require other alternatives, such as omalizumab. Searching in Epistemonikos database, which is maintained by screening 30 databases, we identified four systematic reviews including five pertinent randomized controlled trials overall. We combined the evidence using meta-analysis and generated a summary of findings following the GRADE approach. We concluded omalizumab reduces symptoms and improves quality of life in patients with chronic spontaneous urticaria.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Dec 24 </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La urticaria crónica espontánea es una enfermedad mediada por degranulación de mastocitos, caracterizada por la aparición de ronchas y/o angioedema por más de seis semanas, con o sin un gatillante conocido. El manejo de primera y segunda línea son los antihistamínicos, pero existen casos refractarios que requieren otras alternativas terapéuticas, dentro de las cuales destaca el omalizumab. Utilizando la base de datos Epistemonikos, la cual es mantenida mediante búsquedas en 30 bases de datos, identificamos cuatro revisiones sistemáticas que en conjunto incluyen cinco estudios aleatorizados. Realizamos un metanálisis y tablas de resumen de los resultados utilizando el método GRADE. Concluimos que el uso de omalizumab disminuye los síntomas y mejora la calidad de vida en pacientes con urticaria crónica espontánea. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What are the effects of omalizumab in refractory chronic spontaneous urticaria?</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medwave</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
