<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26738642</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Balcázar-Rincón, Luis Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez-Alcántara, Yunis Lourdes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gordillo Gómez, Enrique Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Retained surgical items after a surgical procedure is a real, existing, and preventable problem that affects the safety of the surgical patient. Its incidence is not exactly known due to under-reporting of occurrence, due to the potential risk of lawsuits. CLINICAL CASE A 31 year-old women that had an elective caesarean, apparently without complications. In the immediate post-operative period, clinical features appeared that were compatible with intestinal obstruction, such as inability to channel gas, bloating, abdominal pain and vigorous peristalsis. The diagnosis is made by the recent history of abdominal-pelvic surgery and the finding of a foreign body on a simple x-ray of the abdomen. The patient was operated upon, with a satisfactory outcome, and was discharged 5 days later. CONCLUSION A retained surgical instrument is an under-reported event that represents a medical-legal problem, leading to various complications, including death if it is not diagnosed and treated early. It is important to know the risk factors and adopt a culture of prevention through perioperative monitoring of equipment and instruments used during the surgical act.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Textiloma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Foreign body</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gossypiboma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuerpo extraño</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Oblito</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Retained foreign object</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Oclusión intestinal secundaria a oblito quirúrgico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intestinal occlusion secondary to a retained surgical item].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
