<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26778671</identifier>
<setSpec>2340-3284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arbeláez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliván, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pelavski, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Miguel, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Brugada syndrome is an autosomal dominant genetic disease affecting sodium ion channels. It is characterised by right bundle branch block and ST elevation in the right precordial leads, and with no structural cardiac abnormalities. It is associated with sudden death. This disease may be unmasked by certain drugs and sudden changes in autonomic tone. Local anaesthetics may increase ECG changes due to a blockade of the sodium channels, mainly depending on the dose and the type of anaesthetic. Thus, there have been reported electrocardiographic changes consistent with Brugada syndrome, triggered after epidural or paravertebral infusion of bupivacaine and ropivacaine. The case is described of a 66 years old man, scheduled for inguinal herniorrhaphy as an outpatient. He had no history of syncope or arrhythmias. After spinal anaesthesia with 40mg of prilocaine the ECG showed ST elevation&gt;2mm, and right bundle branch block in V1-V3.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anaesthesia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Muerte súbita</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Brugada syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anestesia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sudden cardiac death</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome de Brugada</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de síndrome de Brugada tras inyección subaracnoidea de prilocaína.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of Brugada's syndrome after subarachnoid injection of prilocaine.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
