<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26780984</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-García, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosas-Vitorino, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carmona-Sánchez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The different forms of lubrication are among the most simple, accessible, and economic techniques that have been implemented for improving the diagnostic performance of colonoscopy. AIM To determine whether the use of oil improved the number of complete colonoscopies, facilitated the procedure, reduced pain, or improved the study's diagnostic performance, compared with the conventional lubrication technique. PATIENTS AND METHODS One hundred and seventy-five patients referred for colonoscopy were alternately allocated to receive treatment with the standard lubrication method with chlorhexidine gel (group 1) or lubrication with corn oil administered through the working channel (group II). The number of complete colonoscopies, the length of time needed to reach the cecum, the degree of difficulty estimated by the endoscopist and the assistant, the level of pain at the end of the study estimated by the patient, and the endoscopic findings were all determined. RESULTS Eighty-eight patients made up group I and 87 made up group II. No statistically significant differences were found between the two groups in relation to general characteristics, the number of complete colonoscopies (93 vs. 97%, respectively), the time needed to reach the cecum (8:00 vs. 8:41min, respectively), the level of pain at the end of the study, or the detection of polyps. The degree of difficulty was slightly lower in group II, but with no statistical significance. CONCLUSIONS Lubrication with oil during colonoscopy did not improve the number of complete colonoscopies, did not facilitate the study, nor did it reduce pain or increase the diagnostic performance of the study, when compared with the conventional technique.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Colonoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Assisted colonoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colonoscopia asistida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colonoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality in colonoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Calidad en colonoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colon</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lubrication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lubricación</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of oil lubrication during colonoscopy: A comparative study with the conventional technique.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
