<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26811023</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Artiles-Hernández, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Armas-Molina, J V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía-Chavarría, D M</dc:author>
<dc:author>León-Medina, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco-Díez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Cabrillana, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Perform a comparative analysis of the outcomes of conventional laparoscopic adrenalectomy (LC) and the newly introduced laparo-endoscopic single-site surgery (LESS) over ten years. MATERIAL AND METHOD We retrospectively reviewed the experience of a single surgeon from our medical centre with laparoscopic adrenalectomy, either through LC or LESS, with 75 patients between August 2005 and June 2015. Here we describe: age, sex, size, lateralization, preoperative diagnosis, total operating time, intraoperative bleeding, conversion to open surgery, mean hospital stay, intra- and postoperative complications and histopathology report. We used Fischer's and the Chi-squared tests to compare categorical data and Student's T-test for a comparison of the means with a normal distribution. Statistical significance was determined when p&lt;0.05. RESULTS LC was performed in 51 patients, and LESS in 24 patients. No statistical significance was found for total operating time (LC: 103.9±13.21min vs. LESS: 101.46±13.65min; p=0.07), estimated bleeding (LC: 258.82±136.92cc vs. LESS: 131,25±36,74cc; p=0.46), intraoperative complications (5 cases in LC, none in LESS; p=0.47), nor for postoperative complications (two in LC vs. one in LESS; p=0.69), as catalogued according to the modified Clavien classification system. We detected a statistical significance difference in the comparisons of the mean hospital stay, which was reduced in LESS (LC: 3.55±0.69 days vs. LESS: 2.21±0.31 days; p=0.01). CONCLUSIONS Adrenalectomy with LC is the approach of choice for surgical treatment of adrenal pathologies. The LESS technique is safe, improves the cosmetic results, and does not increase mortality if performed by experienced teams.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Suprarrenalectomía laparoscópica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Single-site laparoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Suprarrenal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adrenal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Puerto único laparoscópico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparascopic adrenalectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la suprarrenalectomía laparoscópica: técnica convencional vs puerto único laparoscópico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcomes of laparoscopic adrenalectomy Conventional technique versus laparo-endoscopic single-site surgery.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
