<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26820212</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aviña-Fierro, Jorge Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Aviña, Daniel Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuhauser syndrome is an extremely rare genetic disease, most cases are sporadic by spontaneous mutation, but there are cases of autosomal recessive genetic transmission; the specific cause is unknown and has no diagnostic test. The disease is clinically characterized by primary megalocornea, congenital hypotonia, mental retardation of varying degree and delayed psychomotor development. The diagnosis in childhood is usually performed by oculo-neurological criteria. The patients have a peculiar face by specific craniofacial anomalies: round face, wide prominent forehead, hypertelorism, broad nasal bridge, bulbous nose, wide philtrum nasolabial wide, thin elongated mouth, big and protuded ear "cup", jaw undersized (micrognathia) and abnormal posterior positioning of the mandible (retrognathia).The use of facial dysmorphism helps to delineate the phenotype and achieve the punctuation required for the diagnosis, allowing early management and prevention of complications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Phenotype</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Craniofacial abnormalities</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Neuhauser: su fenotipo facial dismórfico.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El síndrome de Neuhauser es una enfermedad genética extremadamente rara. La mayoría de los casos son esporádicos y se deben a una mutación espóntanea, pero también existen casos de transmisión genética autosómica recesiva; se desconoce la causa específica y no tiene actualmente ninguna prueba diagnóstica. La enfermedad se caracteriza clínicamente por megalocórnea primaria, hipotonía congénita, retardo mental de grado variable y retraso en desarrollo psicomotor. El diagnóstico se realiza generalmente en la infancia con base en los criterios clínicos óculo-neurológicos. Los pacientes tienen un rostro peculiar por anomalías craneofaciales especiales: rostro redondo, frente amplia prominente, hipertelorismo, puente nasal amplio, nariz bulbosa, filtrum nasolabial amplio, boca delgada alargada, oreja grande en “taza” y protuyente; mentón en micrognatia y retrognatia. Utilizar este dismorfismo facial delinea el fenotipo del síndrome y ayuda a lograr la puntuación requerida para el diagnóstico de certeza, lo cual permite un manejo temprano para prevenir complicaciones. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neuhauser syndrome: the facial dysmorphic phenotype].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
