<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26820201</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Antillón-Ferreira, Carlos Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espejel-Huerta, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rendón-Macías, Mario Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iglesias-Leboreiro, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernárdez-Zapata, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Ramos Méndez, Angélica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Diabetes is a serious health problem for pediatrics. In pediatric patients control depends on correct insulin administration. The most usual is subcutaneous administration according to the glycemic control. The aim was to analyze the indications for continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) in type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) children and adolescents. METHODS It was carried out a descriptive study in patients from 1 to 16 years with T1DM who underwent CSII therapy. The main cause to use this therapy was analyzed, and also if that cause was different regarding age, sex and disease progression. RESULTS 61 patients underwent CSII therapy. The median age at the beginning of treatment was 9 years old; 43 patients (71.6 %) had more than one year of diagnosis. The main reasons to use CSII were: 42.6 % had to improve their quality of life, 34.4 % had to reduce the high glycemic variability, 13.1 % had to control severe recurrent hypoglycemia, and 9.8 % had to control their HbA1c. For children under 6 years of age (n = 14) the more frequent indication were recurrent hypoglycemia and to improve their quality of life; children from 6 to 12 years of age (n = 27) had to improve their quality of life, and in children over 12 years CSII was indicated for high glycemic variability and severe recurrent hypoglycemia. There was no different indication related between sexes. CONCLUSION Improve their quality of life and reach a better glycemic control were the main reasons to start CSII in our patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glycosylated hemoglobin A</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulin infusion systems</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicaciones para el uso de microinfusora de insulina en pacientes pediátricos con diabetes mellitus tipo 1.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la diabetes es un problema serio de salud para la pediatría. En pacientes de ese grupo etario, el control depende de la adecuada administración de la insulina.Se buscó analizar las indicaciones para el uso de terapia de infusión continua subcutánea de insulina (ICSI) en niños y adolescentes con diabetes mellitus 1 (DM1). Métodos: estudio descriptivo en pacientes de 1 a 16 años con DM1, en quienes se propuso el inicio de la terapia con ICSI. Se analizó el motivo principal para justificar su inicio y si este fue diferente según edad, sexo y tiempo de evolución. Resultados: en 61 pacientes se aceptó el inicio de ICSI. La mediana de edad fue de 9 años al momento de la colocación y 43 pacientes (71.6 %) tuvieron más de un año de diagnóstico. Los motivos principales para su inicio fueron: 42.6 % (26 de 61) ante un deseo de mejorar su calidad de vida; 34.4 % (21 de 61) para reducir una variabilidad glucémica importante; 13.1 % (8 de 61) para controlar hipoglucemias recurrentes, y 9.8 % (6 de 61) para lograr metas de control en su valor de HbA1c. En los menores de 6 años (n = 14) se indicó más por hipoglucemias recurrentes y para mejorar su calidad de vida; para los de 6 a 12 años (n = 27) para mejorar su calidad de vida; y en los mayores de 12 años (n = 20) por variabilidad glucémica importante e hipoglucemias recurrentes. No hubo diferencias por sexos. Conclusión: los principales motivos que influyeron en la indicación de la ICSI en nuestros pacientes pediátricos fueron mejorar su calidad de vida y lograr un mejor control glucémico. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Indications for the use of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion in pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
