<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26837520</identifier>
<setSpec>1680-5348</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vidal Casanovas, Jaume</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fitzgerald, James</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Ana Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Delgado, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Di Fabio, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The objective of this study is to analyze the legal framework for health and intellectual property in Cuba and its impact on people's access to health resources and on the roles of different social actors. METHODS The methods used were those developed by the Pan American Health Organization to implement the project of the Conceptual Map on Public Health and Intellectual Property. RESULTS Information retrieved specifically on the legal framework for the National Health System, the Intellectual Property System and the strengthening of the country's biopharmaceutical industry-and on the framework's development over time-was processed and analyzed to generate Cuba's Conceptual Map on Public Health and Intellectual Property. CONCLUSIONS Analysis of Cuba's adaptation of its legal framework and assessment of the interaction between the social actors involved show how the political will that has prevailed over several decades has had a positive impact on people's access to health resources.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Salud pública y propiedad intelectual en Cuba: mapa conceptual.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Public health and intellectual property in Cuba: a conceptual map].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
