<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26859921</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Veloz-Martínez, María Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras-Morales, María del Rosario Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Vieyra, Carlos Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quintana-Romero, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia (VAIN) represents a variety of changes that initiate as an intraepithelial squamous lesion with the possibility of resulting in cancer. OBJECTIVE To compare the results of the treatment for the different categories of VAIN with electrocoagulation, 5-fluorouracil and combined treatment. MATERIALS AND METHODS Observational an analytical study. We stablished groups according to the category of VAIN evaluating and comparing remission, persistence, recurrence, or progression of the disease ac- cording to the received treatment, with a 1-year follow up. The results were compared by chi2 and Kruskal Wallis. The statistics analysis was done with the SPSS program version 20. RESULTS One hundred thirty seven patients between 20 and 81 years of age (mean age: 52.49 years) were included. Seventy-four percent of the patients had a history of premalignant or malignant cervical lesions. Seventy-four patients had VAIN I, 34 patients had VAIN II, 22 patients had VAIN III and there were seven cases of vaginal carcinoma in situ. Fifty-eight patients were treated with electrocoagulation, 55 patients were treated with 5-FU, 16 patients had combined treatment, and eight patients received expectant management. Sixty three percent of patients had total remission of the lesion, 34% had persistence and 3% showed progression, and there were no cases of recurrence. Results were better in patients with VAIN I treated with 5-FU (bigger percentage of remission P .026), for the remaining categories of VAIN, no treatment showed superior results. CONCLUSIONS The superior response occurs in patients with VAIN I treated with 5-FU. None of the treatments achieves a 100% remission. The VAIN frequency is high, patients with a history of malignant or premalignant cervical pathology should undergo a closer surveillance through cytocolposcopic control with respect to the remaining population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del tratamiento con esferolisis, 5 fluorouracilo y mixto de pacientes con diferentes categorías de neoplasia intraepitelial vaginal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment results for different categories of vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia with electrocoagulation, 5-fluorouracil and combined treatment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
