<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26877195</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferré, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) is characterised by the presence of intractable fatigue and non-restorative sleep, symptoms which are also very prevalent in multiple diseases and appear as side effects of different drugs. Numerous studies have shown a high prevalence of sleep disorders in patients with CFS. However, non-restorative sleep and fatigue are frequently symptoms of the sleep disorders themselves, so primary sleep disorders have to be ruled out in many cases of CFS. DEVELOPMENT This review was performed using a structured search of the MeSH terms ([Sleep]+[Chronic fatigue syndrome]) in the PubMed database. CONCLUSION Identifying primary sleep disorders in patients meeting diagnostic criteria for CFS will allow for a more comprehensive treatment approach involving new diagnostic and therapeutic strategies that may improve quality of life for these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Fibromyalgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fatigue</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sleep apnoea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fatiga</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibromialgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic fatigue syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sleep disorders</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Somnolence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trastornos del sueño</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sueño no reparador</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Non-restorative sleep</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome de fatiga crónica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Apnea del sueño</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Somnolencia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Feb 11 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de fatiga crónica y los trastornos del sueño: relaciones clínicas y dificultades diagnósticas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic fatigue syndrome and sleep disorders: clinical associations and diagnostic difficulties.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
