<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26914072</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Petriz, Natalia A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Busaniche, Julio N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cortines, María C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parisi, Claudio A S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frangi, Fernando A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portillo, Santiago A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Badiola, Francisco I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Latex allergy is one of the main reasons of anaphylaxis in the operating room. The prevalence of this condition is higher among patients with myelomeningocele. Epidemiological data obtained from Argentine patients is scarce. OBJECTIVE To estimate the prevalence of latex sensitivity and latex allergy in a population of patients with myelomeningocele and to describe associated risk factors. POPULATION AND METHODS Descriptive, cross-sectional, observational study. Family and personal history of allergy, number of surgeries, history of symptoms caused by having been in contact with latex or cross-reactive foods, eosinophil count, measurement of total immunoglobulin E and specific immunoglobulin E levels by means of skin and serologic testing for latex, aeroallergens and cross-reactive fruit. RESULTS Eighty-two patients diagnosed with myelomeningocele were assessed: 41 were males and their average age was 15.3 ± 7.66 years old. Out of all patients, two did not complete skin and serologic testing. Among the remaining 80 patients, 16 (19.51%) had latex allergy, 46 (57.5%) were not allergic, and 18 (22%) showed sensitivity but not allergy. Having undergone more than five surgeries was a risk factor associated with latex allergy (p= 0.035). No significant association was observed with the remaining outcome measures. CONCLUSION According to this study, the prevalence of latex allergy in this population of patients is 19.51% and the most important risk factor for this condition is a history of having undergone more than five surgeries.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Allergy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Myelomeningocele</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latex</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Risk factors</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La alergia al látex se encuentra dentro de las primeras causas de anafilaxia en el quirófano. La prevalencia de esta enfermedad es más elevada en pacientes con mielomenigocele. Existen escasos datos epidemiológicos en pacientes argentinos. 
             Estimar la prevalencia de la sensibilidad y de la alergia al látex en una población de pacientes con mielomeningocele y describir los factores de riesgo asociados. 
             Estudio descriptivo, transversal, observacional. Se analizaron los antecedentes familiares y personales de alergia, el número de procedimientos quirúrgicos, la historia de síntomas ante el contacto con látex o alimentos con reactividad cruzada, el recuento de eosinófilos, la inmunoglobulina E total y la inmunoglobulina E específica mediante pruebas serológicas y cutáneas para el látex, los aeroalérgenos y las frutas con reactividad cruzada. 
             Se evaluaron 82 pacientes con diagnóstico de mielomeningocele, 41 del sexo masculino (50%), con edad promedio de 15,3 ± 7,66 años. Del total de los pacientes, 2 no realizaron las pruebas cutáneas y serológicas. De los 80 restantes, 16 (19,51%) presentaban alergia al látex, 46 (57,5%) no eran alérgicos y 18 (22%) fueron sensibles pero no alérgicos. Se observó que haber tenido más de 5 cirugías representaba un factor de riesgo asociado a alergia al látex (p= 0,035). No se encontró una asociación significativa con el resto de las variables evaluadas. 
             El estudio estima que la prevalencia de alergia al látex en esta población de pacientes es de 19,51% y que el factor de riesgo más importante para el desarrollo de esta patología es el antecedente de haber sido sometido a más de 5 intervenciones. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of latex allergy in a population of patients diagnosed with myelomeningocele.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
