<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26928619</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Palma, Sergio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jalil, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Massardo, Loreto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wurgaft, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Foster, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carpio, J Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roessler, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ardiles, Leopoldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goecke, Annelise</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguirre, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvo, Miriam</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Renal involvement affects over one half of patients with Systemic Lupus Erythematosus increasing their mortality and morbidity, including chronic renal disease and the need of renal replacement therapies. Aiming to achieve a consensus in the most relevant topics on diagnosis, therapy and follow-up of patients with lupus renal disease, the Chilean Societies of Nephrology and Rheumatology constituted a workgroup that, based on a critical review of the available literature and their experience, raised and answered by consensus a set of relevant questions. This document includes aspects related to the clinical diagnosis, the importance of a suitable histological classification, therapeutic alternatives to induce and maintain disease remission, strategies for follow-up, additional therapies and gynecological-obstetric issues.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones sobre el manejo del compromiso renal del lupus eritematoso sistémico: Documento de Consenso de las Sociedades Chilenas de Nefrología y Reumatología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A consensus of the Chilean Nephrology and Rheumatology Societies on renal involvement in systemic lupus erythematosus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
