<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26949138</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-8856</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Atoun, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bruguera, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Levy, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Natera, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the surgical parameters and the clinical and radiological outcomes of revisions of resurfacing shoulder arthroplasty to non-cemented short-stem reverse total shoulder arthroplasty. MATERIAL AND METHODS A total of 23 revisions from resurfacing shoulder arthroplasty to reverse total shoulder arthroplasty were performed. The mean age was 70.3±11.95 years. The patients included 82.6% (19/23) revised for cuff failure; 13.04% (3/23) cuff failure and aseptic loosening, and 4.35% (1/23) peri-prosthetic fracture. The need for humeral osteotomy or structural allograft, operation length, blood loss, blood transfusions and intraoperative fractures were recorded. Minimum follow-up 25 months. RESULTS No humeral osteotomy or humeral structural allograft was required, and 2/23 (8.69%) required allograft for glenoid reconstruction. The mean operation time was 113.35±21.30minutes. Intra-operative blood loss was 374±245.09 mls. Blood transfusion was required in one case. Intra-operative fracture occurred in 1 case. The Constant score improved from 17.32 to 59.78 (age/sex adjusted, 84). Overall satisfaction improved from 1.37 to 8.04. The range of motion increased 79.57° in forward elevation; 72.88° in abduction; 38.06° in internal rotation; and 13.57° in external rotation. There was no evidence of radiolucency, subsidence, or bone resorption. CONCLUSION Revisions of resurfacing implants to non-cemented short-stem reverse prosthesis show good clinical and radiological outcomes, with minimal intra-operative complexities. LEVEL OF EVIDENCE IV, case series.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Evaluation Studies</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Prótesis invertida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artroplastia de revisión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Perioperative complications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Revision arthroplasty</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Shoulder resurfacing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prótesis de superficie de hombro</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones perioperatorias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reverse prosthesis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia de revisión de prótesis de superficie de hombro hacia prótesis invertida no cementada con vástago corto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Revision shoulder arthroplasty from resurfacing to non-cemented short-stem reverse prosthesis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cirugia ortopedica y traumatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
