<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26959330</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tai, Winnie Ling Yin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chung, Joanne Wai-Yee</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wong, Thomas Kwok Shing</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yan, Vincent Chun Man</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tung, Fabian Ling Ngai</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chen, Jing Han</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES to explore nurses' knowledge of universal health coverage (UHC) for inclusive and sustainable development of elderly care services. METHOD this was a cross-sectional survey. A convenience sample of 326 currently practicing enrolled nurses (EN) or registered nurses (RN) was recruited. Respondents completed a questionnaire which was based on the implementation strategies advocated by the WHO Global Forum for Governmental Chief Nursing Officers and Midwives (GCNOMs). Questions covered the government initiative, healthcare financing policy, human resources policy, and the respondents' perception of importance and contribution of nurses in achieving UHC in elderly care services. RESULTS the knowledge of nurses about UHC in elderly care services was fairly satisfactory. Nurses in both clinical practice and management perceived themselves as having more contribution and importance than those in education. They were relatively indifferent to healthcare policy and politics. CONCLUSION the survey uncovered a considerable knowledge gap in nurses' knowledge of UHC in elderly care services, and shed light on the need for nurses to be more attuned to healthcare policy. The educational curriculum for nurses should be strengthened to include studies in public policy and advocacy. Nurses can make a difference through their participation in the development and implementation of UHC in healthcare services.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurses' knowledge of universal health coverage for inclusive and sustainable elderly care services.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
