<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26964515</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-9518</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Coira, Amparo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Pérez, Begoña</dc:author>
<dc:author>Treviño, Mercedes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Losada, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Rodríguez, Maria F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hervada, Xurxo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Escherichia coli is the microorganism responsible for most of the community-acquired urinary tract infections (UTI). Our purpose was to determine the susceptibility of E. coli associated with UTI in Galicia and consider the most appropriate antibiotics for empirical treatment. METHODS Retrospective study during the period 2011- 2012 of the isolation of E. coli in urine samples from almost all the Galician population. Demographic variables, minimum inhibitory concentration, and reading data were collected: amoxicillin-clavulanate, cefotaxime, gentamicin, amikacin, ciprofloxacin, cotrimoxazole, nitrofurantoin and fosfomycin. The identification and susceptibility studies were mainly conducted by automated systems. The interpretation of the results was performed according to CLSI criteria. RESULTS During the study period 55,046 E. coli were isolated in UTI. The percentages of resistance were: cotrimoxazole, 30%; ciprofloxacin, 33%; amoxicillin-clavulanate, 23% and 10% for 3rd generation cephalosporins. Fosfomycin and nitrofurantoin showed the highest activity with more than 96% of susceptibility in our study. The linear trend of resistance regarding age was statistically significant (p &lt;0.0001) as it was regarding males (p &lt;0.00001) for all antibiotics. CONCLUSIONS In Galicia, the most active antibiotics against E. coli associated with UTI are fosfomycin and nitrofurantoin so they should be considered as empirical treatment of choice by the community-acquired UTI not complicated by E. coli.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigilancia de la sensibilidad a antimicrobianos de Escherichia coli productor de infecciones del tracto urinario comunitarias en Galicia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Surveillance of antimicrobial susceptibility of Escherichia coli producing urinary tract infections in Galicia (Spain)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
