<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>26999923</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Estrada-G칩mez, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alpizar-Aguirre, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosales-Olivares, L M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes-S치nchez, A A</dc:author>
<dc:author>S치nchez-Bringas, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Z치rate-Kalfopulus, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION A variety of systems have been developed to fix and perform arthrodesis of the cervical spine, with the advantages of reducing the risk of pseudoarthrosis, extrusion and graft collapse and achieving a more precise sagittal alignment. We therefore need to compare the results of the following approaches to patients with cervical stenosis: plate-graft, cage-plate and PEEK cage. MATERIAL AND METHODS Prospective, interventional, comparative trial involving three groups: group I, arthrodesis with plate-graft; group II, cage-plate, and group III, PEEK cage. The pre- and postoperative assessments included the cervical disability scale, the pain visual analog scale (VAS), and cervical spine X-rays. The results were analyzed with non-parametric tests such as the Wilcoxon sign test and the Kruskal-Wallis test for the comparison of more than two groups. Significance level was 0.05. RESULTS The sample included a total of 37 patients: n = 12 in group I, with 22 levels; n = 11 in group II, with 19 levels, and n = 14 in group III, with 25 levels. Patient age ranged between 60 and 80. One year after surgery there was an improvement in cervical disability and the pain VAS score, with a statistically significant difference among the three groups (p = 0.001). However, radiographic measurements at that time showed a significant improvement in segmental lordosis (p = 0.02) only in plate-graft patients. CONCLUSIONS The plate-graft approach provides better clinical and radiographic results compared to the cage-plate and PEEK cage techniques, at the one-year follow- up.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo entre placa-injerto, caja-placa y caja de PEEK en artrodesis de la columna cervical con conducto cervical estrecho.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparative study between plate-graft, cage-plate and peek cage in cervical arthrodesis for cervical stenosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
