<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2699671</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8899</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calderón, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Historically, Epidemiology arose from the need to take steps in forming health care policy, and up until a few decades ago, its interest has centred on illnesses caused by infectious agents. Recent developments in Medicine and Biology have permitted the evaluation of the behaviour of genetic material in vital processes. From these advances arose Genetic Epidemiology which researches the relationship between heredity and illness among human populations defined by their biosocial characteristics. Its primary field of application is in complex aetiology illnesses in which the genotype and the environment interact. Its complexity has inevitably converted it into a multi-disciplinary science. The basic parametres of the population structures, such as parentage and consanguinity, which is what physical anthropologists have been researching in recent years in Spain, form an important data base which must be integrated into future Genetic Epidemiology studies; these studies will result in its natural progression. Significant success is being obtained in this direction in many advanced countries, therefore it is advisable for our health care authorities to do the same and encourage this type of multidisciplinary work which will serve as a basis for a modern and efficient health care policy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una reflexión antropológica sobre epidemiología genética. De la necesidad de un enfoque multidisciplinar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[An anthropologic reflection on genetic epidemiology. On the need of a multidisciplinary approach].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de sanidad e higiene publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
