<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27040303</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Churruca-Grijelmo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Imbernón-Moya, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lobato-Berezo, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Respiratory tract infection due to Mycoplasma pneumoniae can provoke cutaneous and mucosal rashes, which have been classified within the spectrum of erythema multiforme or Stevens-Johnson syndrome. This classification is of therapeutic and prognostic importance and has generated intense debate in the literature. A recent systematic review of 202 cases of mucocutaneous rashes associated with M. pneumoniae infection concluded that these rashes might constitute a distinct entity, for which the term Mycoplasma-induced rash and mucositis was proposed. We describe a patient with acute M pneumoniae respiratory tract infection who presented mucosal and cutaneous lesions that were difficult to classify as erythema multiforme or Stevens-Johnson syndrome; the lesions were compatible with the proposed new disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Stevens-Johnson syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Exantema</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rash</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mucositis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treatment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clinical classification</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Eritema multiforme</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Erythema multiforme</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clasificación clínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome de Stevens-Johnson</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exantema mucocutáneo inducido por Mycoplasma pneumoniae: ¿un nuevo síndrome separado del eritema multiforme? Un nuevo caso y revisión de la literatura.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mycoplasma pneumoniae-Induced Mucocutaneous Rash: A New Syndrome Distinct from Erythema Multiforme? Report of a New Case and Review of the Literature.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
