<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27079395</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Attie, Myriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bacciedoni, Viviana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Donato, Hugo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of thrombosis is higher among newborn infants than in any other stage of pediatric development. This fact is the consequence of labile characteristics of the neonatal hemostatic system, in addition to exposure to multiple risk factors and the wide use of vascular catheters. Venous thromboses, which mainly affect the limbs, the right atrium and renal veins, are more frequently seen than arterial thromboses. A stroke may be caused by the occlusion of the arterial flow entering the brain or by occlusion of its venous drainage system. Purpura fulminans is a very severe condition that should be treated as a medical emergency, and is secondary to severe protein C deficiency or, less frequently, protein S or antithrombin deficiency. Most thrombotic events should be managed with antithrombotic therapy, which is done with unfractionated and/or low molecular weight heparins. Purpura fulminans requires protein C replacement and/or fresh frozen plasma infusion. Thrombolytic therapy is done using tissue plasminogen activator and should only be used for life-, or limb-, or organ-threatening thrombosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anticoagulants</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Newborn infant</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Heparin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombolytic therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La probabilidad de padecer trombosis es mucho mayor en el período neonatal que en cualquier otra etapa pediátrica. La labilidad del particular sistema hemostático del neonato, sumada a los múltiples factores de riesgo a que está expuesto y la presencia casi constante de catéteres, son responsables de este hecho. Las trombosis venosas son más frecuentes que las arteriales y ocurren principalmente en los miembros, la aurícula derecha y las venas renales. El accidente cerebrovascular puede ser causado por la oclusión del flujo arterial que llega al cerebro o del sistema de drenaje venoso de este. La púrpura fulminans es una patología de altísima gravedad, que debe ser considerada una emergencia médica y se debe a la deficiencia grave de proteína C o, menos frecuentemente, de proteína S o antitrombina. La mayoría de los episodios trombóticos tienen indicación de tratamiento anticoagulante, que se puede realizar con heparina no fraccionada y/o con heparina de bajo peso molecular. La púrpura fulminans requiere terapia de sustitución con proteína C y/o plasma fresco. El tratamiento trombolítico se realiza con activador tisular del plasminógeno y debe quedar reservado solo para aquellas trombosis cuya localización implique compromiso de vida o pérdida de un órgano o de un miembro. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thrombosis in newborn infants.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
