<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27079391</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-Jiménez, Emilio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Schmidt-RioValle, Jacqueline</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez-Vélez, Robinson</dc:author>
<dc:author>Correa-Bautista, Jorge E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobar-Cardozo, Germán D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The analysis of body composition is a fundamental part of nutritional status assessment. The objective of this study was to establish body fat percentiles by bioelectrical impedance in children and adolescents from Bogotá (Colombia) who were part of the FUPRECOL study (Asociación de la Fuerza Prensil con Manifestaciones Tempranas de Riesgo Cardiovascular en Niños y Adolescentes Colombianos - Association between prehensile force and early signs of cardiovascular risk in Colombian children and adolescents). METHODS This was a cross-sectional study conducted among 5850 students aged 9-17.9 years old from Bogotá (Colombia). Body fat percentage was measured using foot-to-foot bioelectrical impedance (Tanita®, BF-689), by age and gender. Weight, height, waist circumference, and hip circumference were measured, and sexual maturity was self-staged. Percentiles (P3, P10, P25, P50, P75, P90 and P97) and centile curves were estimated using the LMS method (L [BoxCox curve], M [median curve] and S [variation coefficient curve]), by age and gender. RESULTS Subjects included were 2526 children and 3324 adolescents. Body fat percentages and centile curves by age and gender were established. For most age groups, values resulted higher among girls than boys. Participants with values above P90 were considered to have a high cardiovascular risk due to excess fat (boys &gt; 23.428.3, girls &gt; 31.0-34.1). CONCLUSIONS Body fat percentage percentiles measured using bioelectrical impedance by age and gender are presented here and may be used as reference to assess nutritional status and to predict cardiovascular risk due to excess fat at an early age.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pediatrics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular risk factors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fat</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Body composition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reference values</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El análisis de la composición corporal constituye una parte fundamental en la evaluación del estado nutricional. El objetivo de este estudio fue establecer percentiles de grasa corporal por bioimpedancia eléctrica en niños y adolescentes de Bogotá, Colombi pertenecientes al estudio FUPRECOL (Asociación de la Fuerza Prensil con Manifestaciones Tempranas de Riesgo Cardiovascular en Niños y Adolescentes Colombianos). 
             Estudio transversal, realizado en 5850 escolares de entre 9 y 17,9 años de edad, de Bogotá, Colombia. El porcentaje de grasa corporal fue medido con bioimpedancia eléctrica pie-pie (Tanita®, BF-689), según edad y sexo. Se tomaron medidas de peso, tall circunferencia de cintur circunferencia de cadera y estadio de maduración sexual por autorreporte. Se calcularon percentiles (P3, P10, P25, P50, P75, P90 y P97) y curvas centiles por el método LMS (L [curva Box-Cox], M [curva mediana] y S [curva coeficiente de variación]), por sexo y edad. 
             Se incluyeron 2526 niños y 3324 adolescentes. Se determinaron los porcentajes de grasa corporal y las curvas de centiles por edad y sexo. En la mayoría de los grupos etarios, los valores de las mujeres fueron mayores que los de los varones. Se consideró que los participantes con valores por encima del P90 tenían un elevado riesgo cardiovascular por exceso de grasa (varones &gt; 23,4-28,3 y mujeres &gt; 31,0-34,1). 
             Se presentan percentiles del porcentaje de grasa corporal por bioimpedancia eléctrica según edad y sexo, que podrán ser usados como referencia en la evaluación del estado nutricional y en la predicción del riesgo cardiovascular por exceso de adiposidades en edades tempranas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percentiles of body fat measured by bioelectrical impedance in children and adolescents from Bogotá (Colombia): the FUPRECOL study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
