<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27085511</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez, C Marín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lancharro Zapata, Á M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is essential to minimize exposure to ionizing radiation in children for various reasons. The risk of developing a tumor from exposure to a given dose of radiation is greater in childhood. Various strategies can be used to reduce exposure to ionizing radiation. It is fundamental to avoid unnecessary tests and tests that are not indicated, to choose an alternative test that does not use ionizing radiation, and/or to take a series of measures that minimize the dose of radiation that the patient receives, such as avoiding having to repeat tests, using the appropriate projections, using shields, adjusting the protocol (mAs, Kv, or pitch) to the patient's body volume, etc… When contrast agents are necessary, intracavitary ultrasound agents can be used, although the use of ultrasound agents is also being extended to include intravenous administration. In fluoroscopy, contrast agents with low osmolarity must be used, as in CT where we must adjust the dose and speed of injection to the patient's weight and to the caliber of the peripheral line, respectively. In MRI, only three types of contrast agents have been approved for pediatric use. It is sometimes necessary to use double doses or organ-specific contrast agents in certain clinical situations; the safety of contrast agents for these indications has not been proven, so they must be used off label.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Contrastes en Pediatría</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiación ionizante</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ionizing radiation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radioprotection in pediatrics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radioprotección en Pediatría</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Contrast agents in pediatric imaging</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioprotección y uso de contrastes en pediatría: qué, cómo y cuándo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radioprotection and contrast agent use in pediatrics: what, how, and when.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
