<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2710987</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9437</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Enríquez Navascues, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Capote, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carda, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vicente, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrero, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Devesa, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, V</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study was made of the histologic changes in the mucosa of the ileoanal reservoirs of 10 patients who 2 years earlier had undergone ileoanal anastomosis with a J reservoir for ulcerative colitis (CU). In biopsies of the reservoirs were evaluated: 1) basic morphologic changes; 2) morphometric differences with respect to normal ileal mucosa; 3) the immunohistochemical pattern (IHQ) (IgA, IgG, IgM and CEA) of the reservoir mucosa as compared to normal ileum, active ulcerative colitis. Crohn's disease and celiaca; 4) the possible existence of atypias or dysplasias of the reservoir mucosa; and 5) the number of argentaffin cells per field. The basic morphologic alteration consisted of colonic metaplasia. Reservoir biopsies exhibited partial (8 cases) or subtotal atrophy (2 cases) of the mucosa. With respect to the normal ileum there was a decrease in villi height (p less than 0.05), an increase in crypt depth (p less than 0.05) and a higher index of mucosal regeneration, with a larger number of cells and mitoses per crypt (p less than 0.05). Fifty percent of the reservoirs presented a chronic inflammatory pattern with an acute component in 30% of them. The immunohistochemical pattern of the reservoirs not inflamed was similar to that of normal ileum (IgA much greater than IgM greater than IgG) and that of the inflamed reservoirs was similar to that of intestinal inflammatory disease (marked increase in the IgG. CEA (similar to what?) an alteration of local immune homeostasis could have of the genesis of pictures of "pouchitis". No alarming signs of atypia or dysplasia were found, nor changes in the population of argentaffin cells.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones morfológicas de los reservorios ileoanales a los dos años de su construcción.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Morphologic changes in ileoanal reservoirs 2 years after their construction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de las enfermedades del aparato digestivo</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
