<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27130566</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chalela, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Curull, Víctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pijuan, Lara</dc:author>
<dc:author>Badenes-Bonet, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Font, Albert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez-Álvarez, Marisol</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Mediastinal tuberculosis (TB) is rare and a diagnostic challenge. Transbronchial needle aspiration guided by endoscopic ultrasonography (EBUS-TBNA) is an essential tool for staging and diagnosing patients with lung cancer but to date there are no studies in our environment evaluating its efficacy in mediastinal TB. METHODS Patients with a final diagnosis of isolated intrathoracic tuberculous lymphadenitis over a 6-year period were included. We analyzed the cases on whom EBUS-TBNA was performed. RESULTS Forty-six patients with mediastinal lymphadenopathy without pulmonary involvement were identified and 29 underwent EBUS-TBNA. In 28 of 29 patients (96.6%) EBUS-TBNA was diagnostic and cytological findings confirmed granulomas in 93% of cases. Microbiological investigation revealed positive TB culture in 14 (48.2%) and positive PCR for Mycobacterium tuberculosis in 30% of cases on whom it was carried out. Eighty-four per cent of the patients were immigrants and when compared with the native population we found statistical differences in immune status and culture yield. CONCLUSION EBUS-TBNA is a safe and effective technique in the diagnosis of patients with suspected mediastinal TB.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>EBUS-TBNA</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ecobroncoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis ganglionar mediastínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intrathoracic tuberculous lymphadenitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endobronchial ultrasound</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>PATb-USEB</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jun 17 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la punción aspirativa transbronquial guiada con ultrasonografía endobronquial en el diagnóstico de la tuberculosis mediastínica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Role of endobronchial ultrasound-guided transbronchial needle aspiration in the diagnosis of mediastinal tuberculosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
