<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27149187</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Monroy-Sosa, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera-Gomez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olvera-Manzanilla, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Xolio-Villanueva, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cacho-Diaz, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodriguez-Orozco, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Granados-Garcia, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes-Soto, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzana-Mendoza, N A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Cancer is one of the leading causes of death in our population; neurologic manifestations are frequent and are associated with higher rates of morbidity and mortality. AIM To describe the neurological manifestations in patients with cancer. PATIENTS AND METHODS From January 2010 to December 2014 a database was created from patients with cancer, required a neuro-oncological assessment at a referral cancer center. RESULTS 17,092 reasons for neuro-oncological consultation are described. Neoplasms most frequently associated with neurological manifestations were: breast cancer, hematologic malignancies, primary central nervous system tumors, lung cancer and gynecological malignancies. The most frequent neurological manifestations were: neuromuscular disease (including neuropathy), central nervous system metastasis, primary headaches, seizures, stroke and primary neurological tumors. CONCLUSION It is important that neurologists, physicians and those involved in the management of patients with cancer recognize and get to know the neurological complications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 May 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones neurologicas en pacientes con cancer: mas de 17.000 motivos de consulta.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Manifestaciones neurologicas en pacientes con cancer: mas de 17.000 motivos de consulta. 
             Introduccion. El cancer es una de las primeras causas de muerte en nuestra poblacion. Las complicaciones neurologicas asociadas son frecuentes e incrementan significativamente la morbilidad y la mortalidad de estos pacientes. Objetivo. Describir las manifestaciones neurologicas en pacientes con cancer. Pacientes y metodos. Desde enero de 2010 hasta diciembre de 2014 se creo una base de datos de pacientes con cancer que merecian una valoracion por neurooncologia en un centro de referencia. Resultados. Se describen 17.092 motivos de consulta de neurooncologia. Las neoplasias que mas se relacionaron con manifestaciones neurologicas fueron: cancer de mama, neoplasias hematologicas, tumores primarios del sistema nervioso central, cancer de pulmon y neoplasias ginecologicas. Las manifestaciones neurologicas mas frecuentes fueron: afeccion neuromuscular, actividad tumoral en el sistema nervioso central, cefalea primaria, crisis convulsivas, enfermedad vascular cerebral y tumores neurologicos primarios. Conclusiones. Es importante que los neurologos, medicos de distintas areas de la medicina y personal paramedico, involucrados en el manejo de estos pacientes, reconozcan las complicaciones neurologicas de manera temprana. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neurological manifestations in patients with cancer: more than 17,000 reasons for consultation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
