<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27157001</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1747</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Baeza-Monedero, María Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz-Jentoft, Alfonso J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero-Errasquín, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Corral, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the indications of insertion of a percutaneous gastrostomy (PG) in older patients in a university hospital, as well as patient characteristics, short and long term complications, and mortality. METHODS Retrospective descriptive study of all patients over 75 years who had a PG inserted during a three year period by the Interventional Radiology Department. The indication of the procedure was reviewed, and the incidence of complications and mortality during a 36 months follow-up period were assessed through electronic medical records. RESULTS The study included 74 patients, with a mean age of 84±6.1 years, and 57% were female. Furthermore, 40% lived in nursing homes and 80% had cognitive impairment. The main indications for PG insertion were dysphagia in severe dementia (56.8%), tumours of the oropharyngeal cavity (12.2%), Parkinson's disease (10.8%), and stroke (9.6%). PG was permanent in 90.5% of cases. The most common complication was aspiration pneumonia (32.4%). Overall mortality was 59.5% after a median follow-up of 18 months. CONCLUSIONS Dysphagia in severe dementia was the main indication for PG in patients over 75 years. This intervention did not prevent aspiration pneumonia, which was the most common complication. Mortality in patients who have a PG was high.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Gastrostomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indicaciones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastrostomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Broncoaspiración</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aspiration pneumonia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Demencia avanzada</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mortality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mortalidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Advanced dementia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Mar - Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de sondas de gastrostomía en mayores de 75años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of gastrostomies in patients over 75 years old].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de geriatria y gerontologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
