<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27161091</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vila Santandreu, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blázquez-Gómez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos Cebrian, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Haro, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tarrado, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila-Cots, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martin, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Aparicio, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camacho Diaz, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Some guidelines recommend an early voiding cystourethrography (VCUG) after endoscopic treatment of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR), but there's no consensus if it's necessary a long-term follow-up in these patients. The aim of our study is analyze if it's necessary a delayed VCUG after initial successful treatment with Dx/HA. MATERIAL AND METHOD We have reviewed all medical charts of patients that underwent Dx/HA treatment from 2006 to 2010. We have selected patients with initial successful treatment and more than 3 years of radiological and clinical follow-up. We have analyzed late clinical and radiological outcomes. RESULTS One hundred and sixty children with 228 refluxing ureters underwent Dx/HA endoscopic treatment with a mean follow-up of 52.13 months. Early VCUG was performed in 215 ureters with an initial successful rate of 84.1%. The group of study was 94/215 ureters with more than 3 years of follow-up with a delayed VCUG. VUR was still resolved in 79,8% of the ureters. Clinical success rate was 91.7%. The incidence of febrile urinary tract infection in those patients with cured VUR and those with a relapsed VUR was 8 and 15%, respectively; but there were no significant differences. We have not found any variable related with relapsed VUR except those ureters that initially received 2 injections (P&lt;.05). CONCLUSION If our objective in the treatment of VUR is to reduce the incidence of febrile urinary tract infection it is not necessary to perform a delayed VCUG even though the long-term radiological outcomes is worse than clinical outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cystography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vesicoureteral reflux</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infancia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cistografía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reflujo vesicoureteral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es necesario realizar una cistouretrografía miccional seriada (CUMS) tardía tras el tratamiento endoscópico exitoso inicial con copolímero de dextranómreo/ácido hialurónico (Dx/HA) para el reflujo vesicoureteral (RVU)?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Routine delayed voiding cystourethography after initial successful endoscopic treatment with Dextranomer/Hialuronic Acid Copolimer (Dx/HA) of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR). Is it necessary?</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
