<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27174756</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alcalá-Padilla, Guadalupe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bedolla-Barajas, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdez-López, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kestler-Gramajo, Amanda</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Allergic sensitization is dependent on the geographical and climatic conditions in each region; therefore, identify agents most commonly sensitized children with asthma is important for planning prevention measures. OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence of the sensitization to allergens in children with asthma. MATERIAL AND METHOD This cross-sectional and prolective study includes children from ages 6 to 14, who have asthma, attended for the first time in an allergy service. The patients were recruited consecutively between the months of January 1st 2014 to December 31st 2014. The frequency of the allergen sensitization was estimated. RESULTS This study included 186 children, the median age was 7 years olds, the male group was 104/186 (55.9%) The median of the positive results was 5 and monosensitized were 47/186 (2.2%). The most common category of allergens was the indoor (90.3%), then trees (71.0%), and finally the fungi (9.7%). Individually, the house dust mites were more common in between the interior allergens, followed by the epithelial; in the tree pollen were oaks (31.7%) and ashes (28.0%), in weeds was mugwort (21.5%), in grasses was Zea mays (18.3%) and in the fungi was Cladosporium spp. (6.5%). CONCLUSION The high prevalence of the sensitization to house dust mites and epithelial in children with asthma, stimulates to implement methods of environmental control for contributing a better control of the disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>prevalence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>asthma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>skin prick test</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>allergens</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>child</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sensibilización a alergenos en niños escolares con asma que viven en la zona metropolitana de Guadalajara.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: la prevalencia de rinosinusitis crónica en pacientes adultos con inmunodeficiencia común variable (IDCV) es de 52%. Los pacientes con esta enfermedad tienen mayor frecuencia de rinosinusitis crónica, enfermedad inflamatoria que afecta a la mucosa de uno o más senos paranasales y la cavidad nasal. Objetivo: identificar los microorganismos de secreción del meato medio obtenida por endoscopia asociados con rinosinusitis crónica en pacientes adultos con inmunodeficiencia común variable (IDCV). Material y método: estudio descriptivo, transversal, que incluyó a pacientes adultos con inmunodeficiencia común variable, de quienes se obtuvo una muestra vía endoscópica de secreción del meato medio de ambas fosas nasales, que se envió a cultivo para bacterias aerobias, anaerobias y hongos. Se obtuvo consentimiento informado de todos los pacientes. Resultados: se estudiaron 29 pacientes: 18 mujeres y 11 hombres, con edad promedio de 40±13 años. Los resultados obtenidos fueron: 2 muestras de pacientes no tuvieron desarrollo microbiano, 24 tuvieron desarrollo de bacterias aerobias, en 3 casos hubo crecimiento fúngico sin desarrollo de bacterias anaerobias. Conclusiones: nuestros resultados muestran que los microorganismos asociados con rinosinusitis crónica en pacientes adultos con inmunodeficiencia común variable más comunes son: Moraxella catarrhalis, Staphylococcus, Sphingomonas paucimobilis y Citrobacter koseri; los agentes micóticos asociados fueron: Candida albicans y Aspergillus fumigatus. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of sensitization to allergens in school children with asthma residents from Guadalajara metropolitan area].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
