<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27187002</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Álvarez-López, C A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Lorenzo, Y C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Osteoarthritis of the knee is a common disease and angular deformities are usually associated to this degenerative affection. Secondary causes of angular deformities are well known in the scientific literature, but there are not many articles about the relationship between angular deformities and primary osteoarthritis. OBJECTIVE To deepen in the relationship between angular deformities and primary osteoarthritis of the knee. METHOD We conducted a literature review of a total of 300 articles in PubMed, Medline and Hinari locator information by EndNote, 52 of them were used and selected quotes to do the review, 47 of them in the last five years, including five books. DEVELOPMENT A revision of important biochemical and biomechanics aspects were made in regards to the relationship between angular deformities and primary osteoarthritis of the knee. Causes of deformities according to the sagittal, coronal and rotational axis were taken into account. Factors related to deformities could be osseous or soft tissues of the knee joint. CONCLUSIONS Deformities of the knee in patients suffering from primary osteoarthritis are common and there are osseous and soft tissues causes to justified the presence of these deformities.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Knee</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>angular deformity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>incidence</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2015 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre deformidad angular y gonartrosis primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La gonartrosis es una entidad muy frecuente en la actualidad, las deformidades angulares son un hallazgo usual en pacientes con esta entidad y aunque está bien justificada su presencia como causa secundaria, no existen muchos reportes sobre la relación entre deformidad angular y gonartrosis primaria. 
             Profundizar en la relación existente entre gonartrosis primaria y deformidad angular de la articulación de la rodilla. 
             Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica de un total de 300 artículos publicados en PubMed, Hinari y Medline mediante el localizador de información EndNote, de ellos se utilizaron 52 citas seleccionadas para realizar la revisión, 47 de ellas de los últimos cinco años, donde se incluyeron cinco libros. 
             Se realizó una revisión de los aspectos bioquímicos y biomecánicos más importantes relacionados con las deformidades angulares. Con respecto a la asociación entre deformidad angular y gonartrosis primaria, se plasmaron los elementos relacionados con cada tipo de deformidad tanto en el eje axial, coronal como rotacional. Los factores relacionados con la deformidad pueden ser de tipo óseo y de partes blandas, en especial del aparato capsuloligamentoso de la articulación. 
             Las deformidades angulares en pacientes con gonartrosis primaria son frecuentes y en su presencia influyen factores relacionados con la arquitectura ósea y de partes blandas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Relationship between angular deformity and primary osteoarthritis of the knee. Review article].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
