<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27197098</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Macías-de la Torre, Aída Anahí</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murillo-Zamora, Efrén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Higareda-Almaraz, Martha Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Depression is a common morbidity in end- stage kidney disease (ESKD) patients and impacts negatively on treatment outcomes. This study aimed to assess the prevalence of depression among Mexican ESKD patients in maintenance hemodialysis (MHD) and to evaluate the relationship with elapsed time (&lt; 1 year or ≥ 1 year) since the beginning of therapy. METHODS A cross-sectional study took place in a urban hospital from the Mexican Institute of Social Security and 81 subjects aged 30 - 69 years old were enrolled. Beck depression inventory (BDI) was applied and a stratified analysis was made. RESULTS The overall prevalence of depression (≥ 16 points, BDI) was 42.0 % and 35.6 % and 50.0 % in the group with &lt; 1 and ≥ 1 year on treatment respectively (p = 0.191). CONCLUSIONS Our findings suggest that depression prevalence is high among adult patients undergoing MHD and it seems to be independent from elapsed time since the beginning of therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Chronic kidney failure</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic renal insufficiency</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Depression</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Renal dialysis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de depresión entre pacientes con enfermedad terminal en hemodiálisis de mantenimiento.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la depresión es una morbilidad frecuente en pacientes con enfermedad renal terminal (ERT) e impacta negativamente en los resultados esperados del tratamiento. El objetivo de este estudio fue mediar la prevalencia de depresión entre pacientes mexicanos con ERT en hemodiálisis de mantenimiento (HDM) y evaluar la relación con el tiempo transcurrido (&lt; 1 año o ≥ 1 año) desde el inicio de la terapia. Métodos: se realizó un estudio de tipo transversal en un hospital urbano del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social y 81 individuos de 30 – 69 años de edad fueron incluidos. El inventario de depresión de Beck (IDB) fue aplicado y se realizó un análisis estratificado. Resultados: la prevalencia general de depresión (≥ 16 puntos, IDB) fue 42.0 % y 35.6 % y 50.0 % en el grupo con &lt; 1 año 0 ≥ 1 año en tratamiento respectivamente (p = 0.191). Conclusiones: nuestros hallazgos sugieren que la prevalencia de depresión es alta entre pacientes adultos en HDM y parece ser independiente del tiempo transcurrido desde el inicio de la terapia. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Depression prevalence among end stage renal disease patients in maintenance hemodialysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
