<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27207599</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Redón-Gálvez, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Escudero, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otaola-Arca, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alarcón Parra, R O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez-Ardura, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Páez-Borda, Á</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aim of the study was to analyse the clinical-demographic variables of the series and the predictors of urethral stricture recurrence after endoscopic urethrotomy. MATERIAL AND METHODS We retrospectively analysed 67 patients who underwent Sachse endoscopic urethrotomy between June 2006 and September 2014. Those patients who had previously undergone endoscopic urethrotomy or urethroplasty were excluded. The other patients who presented urethral stricture were included. We analysed age, weight, smoking habit, and cardiovascular risk factors, as well as the number, location, length and aetiology of the strictures, previous urethrotomies, vesical catheter duration and postsurgical dilatations. A univariate and multivariate analysis was conducted using the chi-squared test or Fisher's test and logistic regression to identify the variables related to recurrence. RESULTS Thirty-seven percent of the patients had a relapse. The majority of the patients were older than 60 years (56.7%), obese (74.6%), nonsmokers (88%) and had no cardiovascular factors (56.7%). The majority of the strictures were single (94%), &lt;1cm (82%), bulbar urethral (64.2%), iatrogenic (67.2%) and with no prior urethrotomy (89.6%). The majority of the patients carried a vesical catheter for &lt;15 days (85.1%) and did not undergo postsurgical dilatation (65.7%). Only the length of the stricture was an independent risk factor for recurrence (P=.025; relative risk, 5.7; 95% CI 1.21-26.41). CONCLUSIONS In the treatment of urethral strictures through endoscopic urethrotomy, a stricture length &gt;1cm is the only factor that predicts an increase in the risk of recurrence. We found no clinical or demographic factors that caused an increase in the incidence of recurrence. Similarly, technical factors such as increasing the bladder catheterisation time and urethral dilatations did not change the course of the disease. Their routine use is therefore unnecessary.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Recurrence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recidiva</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estenosis uretral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urethral stricture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopic urethrotomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Uretrotomía endoscópica</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos de recidiva de estenosis uretral tras uretrotomía endoscópica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of urethral stricture recurrence after endoscopic urethrotomy.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
