<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27225053</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilera, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso-Dorrego, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bañuelos, Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cisneros, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Prostate cancer is considered a tumour with a long natural history. However, its high-risk variants exhibit variable behaviour. We analyse the factors that affect BR and CSS (multivariate, Kaplan Meier). METHODS From 1997 to 2013, 657 patients were operated of a high-grade prostate cancer (pT2b 7.2%, pT3a 73%, pT3b 18.3%, pT4 1.5%). Gleason score was ≥8 in 23% of cases. Percentage of PSMs was 46.1%. Mean follow-up was 113 months (24-192). RESULTS BR occurred in 36.5%. Patients with Gleason score &lt;8, 31.7% had BR, Gleason ≥8 had BR in 48% (p&lt;0.05). PSMs recurrence occurred in 48.9%, whereas 26.1% in NSM (p&lt;0.05). If lymphadenectomy, BR occurred in 48.7%, if not 30.9% (p&lt;0,05). In multivariate analysis, stage, Gleason≥8 and PSMs were independent factors for BR. Treatment of BR was 36.5% radiotherapy, 24.1% HT, and 21.2% both simultaneously. Active surveillance was performed in 13.3%. Disease progression (biochemical or radiological) occurred in 23.5%. CSS was 98.93%, pT4 was the stage with the greatest mortality (10%), followed by pT3b (3.4%), p&lt;0.05. Patients with a Gleason score ≥8 accounted for 71% CSM (p&lt;0,05). PSMs and lymphadenectomy didn't have repercussions for survival. In multivariate analysis, Gleason≥8 was independent factor for CSM. CONCLUSIONS Radical prostatectomy plays an important role in multi-modal approach with good oncological control at medium follow up. Gleason score ≥8 was the factor with the greatest effect on CSM. Lymphadenectomy didn't affect CSS.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados oncológicos en el cáncer de próstata de alto riesgo tratado quirúrgicamente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Oncological results in high grade prostate cancer treated surgically].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
