<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27241558</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pont, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mazón, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most cases of acute otitis media resolve with antibiotics and imaging is not required. When treatment fails or a complication is suspected, imaging plays a crucial role. Since the introduction of antibiotic treatment, the complication rate has decreased dramatically. Nevertheless, given the critical clinical relevance of complications, the importance of early diagnosis is vital. Our objective was to review the clinical and radiological features of acute otitis media and its complications. They were classified based on their location, as intratemporal or intracranial. Imaging makes it possible to diagnose the complications of acute otitis media and to institute appropriate treatment. Computed tomography is the initial technique of choice and, in most cases, the ultimate. Magnetic resonance is useful for evaluating the inner ear and when accurate evaluation of disease extent or better characterization of intracranial complications is required.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Intracranial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intratemporal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intratemporales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acute otitis media</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intracraneales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Otitis media aguda</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan - Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicaciones y hallazgos radiológicos de la otitis media aguda y sus complicaciones.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indications and radiological findings of acute otitis media and its complications.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
