<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27262363</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Gavín, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hervella-Garcés, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silvestre-Salvador, J F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Spanish standard patch test series, as recommended by the Spanish Contact Dermatitis and Skin Allergy Research Group (GEIDAC), has been updated for 2016. The new series replaces the 2012 version and contains the minimum set of allergens recommended for routine investigation of contact allergy in Spain from 2016 onwards. Four haptens -clioquinol, thimerosal, mercury, and primin- have been eliminated owing to a low frequency of relevant allergic reactions, while 3 new allergens -methylisothiazolinone, diazolidinyl urea, and imidazolidinyl urea- have been added. GEIDAC has also modified the recommended aqueous solution concentrations for the 2 classic, major haptens methylchloroisothiazolinone and methylisothiazolinone, which are now to be tested at 200ppm in aqueous solution, and formaldehyde, which is now to be tested in a 2% aqueous solution. Updating the Spanish standard series is one of the functions of GEIDAC, which is responsible for ensuring that the standard series is suited to the country's epidemiological profile and pattern of contact sensitization.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Consensus Development Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Epidemiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Allergic contact dermatitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pruebas cutáneas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pruebas del parche</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipersensibilidad tipo IV</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hapten</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hapteno</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patch tests</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Skin tests</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Type IV hypersensitivity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dermatitis de contacto alérgica</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de la serie estándar española de pruebas alérgicas de contacto por el Grupo Español de Investigación en Dermatitis de Contacto y Alergia Cutánea (GEIDAC) para 2016.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Spanish standard patch test series: 2016 update by the Spanish Contact Dermatitis and Skin Allergy Research Group (GEIDAC).</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
