<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27269197</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Granda Membiela, Carla María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sirgo Rodríguez, Paloma</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez Marcos, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Gutiérrez, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mamolar Andrés, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santamarina Rabanal, María Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Parkinson's disease is a type of chronic neurodegenerative pathology with a typical movement pattern, as well as different, less studied symptoms such as dysphagia. Disease-related disorders in efficacy or safety in the process of swallowing usually lead to malnutrition, dehydration or pneumonias. The aim of this study was identifying and analyzing swallowing disorders in Parkinson's disease. SUBJECTS AND METHODS The initial sample consisted of 52 subjects with Parkinson's disease to whom the specific test for dysphagia SDQ was applied. Nineteen participants (36.5%) with some degree of dysphagia in the SDQ test were selected to be evaluated by volume-viscosity clinical exploration method and fiberoptic endoscopic evaluation of swallowing. RESULTS Disorders in swallowing efficiency and safety were detected in 94.7% of the selected sample. With regards to efficiency, disorders were found in food transport (89.5%), insufficient labial closing (68.4%) and oral residues (47.4%), relating to duration of ingestion. Alterations in security were also observed: pharynx residues (52.7%), coughing (47.4%), penetration (31.64%), aspiration and decrease of SaO2 (5.3%), relating to the diagnosis of respiratory pathology in the previous year. CONCLUSION The SDQ test detected swallowing disorders in 36.5% of the subjects with Parkinson's disease. Disorders in swallowing efficiency and safety were demonstrated in 94.7% of this subset. Disorders of efficiency were more frequent than those of safety, establishing a relationship with greater time in ingestion and the appearance of respiratory pathology and pneumonias.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Disfagia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parkinson's disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Método volumen-viscosidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pneumonia aspiration</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dysphagia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neumonía aspirativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Videoendoscopia deglución</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Volume-viscosity examination</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fiberoptic endoscopic swallowing</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan - Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos de la deglución en la enfermedad de Parkinson.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Swallowing disorders in Parkinson's disease.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
