<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27265383</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-1364</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>March-Cerdà, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Danet, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Romera, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the perception and self-assessment on leadership among health care team leaders in Andalusia. MATERIAL AND METHODS Design: Exploratory descriptive study using quantitative and qualitative methodology, developed between 2013 and 2015, using a questionnaire and semi-structured interviews. PLACE Andalusia. PARTICIPANTS All health managers from the Primary Care Management Units and Health Management Areas of the Departments of Paediatrics, Emergency and Internal Medicine, for the quantitative study. A purposive sample of 24 health managers was used for the qualitative study. METHODS Descriptive statistical study and bivariate analysis of comparison of means. Content analysis of the semi-structured interviews: Codification, category tree, and triangulation of results. RESULTS The best self-assessment dimension relates to support, and the worst to considering oneself as a 'good leader'. The definition of a 'good leader' includes: Honesty, trust, and attitudes of good communication, closeness, appreciation, and reinforcement of the health team members. Different leadership styles were perceived. Main difficulties for leadership are related to the economic crisis and the management of personal conflicts. CONCLUSIONS Health managers describe an adaptive leadership style, based on personal and professional support, and using communication as the main cohesive element for the team project. More studies on leaders' perspectives are important, in order to better understand their experiences, needs and expectations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Investigación cualitativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Qualitative research</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Leadership</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quantitative research</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Liderazgo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Investigación cuantitativa</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autopercepción de las personas responsables en los equipos sanitarios de Andalucía. Estudio cuantitativo y cualitativo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Self-perception of health care team leaders in Andalusia. A quantitative and qualitative study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de calidad asistencial : organo de la Sociedad Espanola de Calidad Asistencial</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
