<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27295708</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Piñero, Tamara A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vaccaro, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santino, Juan Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kalfayan, Pablo G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferro, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cajal, Andrea R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verzura, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solano, Angela R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lynch syndrome is the most frequent syndrome in hereditary colorectal cancer, a family-specific deleterious mutations in genes encoding DNA reparation proteins: MLH1 (mutL homolog 1), MSH2, MSH6 (mutS homolog 2 y 6, respectively), PMS2 (PMS1 homolog 2, mismatch repair system component) y MUTYH (mutY DNA glycosylase). The c.2252_2253delAA, p.Lys751Serfs*3 mutation in MLH1 gene segregates with a haplotype reported in the northern region of Italy and whose origin was attributed to a founder effect. This mutation co-segregates with typical characteristics of Lynch syndrome, including early age at onset and multiple primary tumors in the same individual, a high frequency of pancreatic cancer, high microsatellite instability and lack of PMS2 expression. This report describes a mutation in an Argentinian patient with endometrioid adenocarcinoma of uterus. Her first-degree relatives had a history of colon cancer diagnosed before 50 years, fulfilling the Amsterdam Criteria I and Lynch syndrome II. The high pathogenicity associated to this mutation makes necessary the study of all members from families with hereditary cancer, allowing pre-symptomatic genetic diagnosis, early assessment and the instauration of preventive treatments.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>MLH1 gene</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lynch syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>founder mutation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mutación fundadora en síndrome de Lynch tipo II.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Founder mutation in Lynch syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
