<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27299815</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez N, Vania</dc:author>
<dc:author>George L, Myriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>González A, Electra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina G, Temistocles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina C, Ramiro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hidalgo-Rasmussen, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>SepúLveda P, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Health-related quality of life (HRQOL) refers to individuals' perception of their subjective well-being, considering various aspects of their life and the impact on their health. AIM To analyze gender differences in the HRQOL of adolescent students in Chile, by age, type of school attended, and area of residence. MATERIAL AND METHODS Analytical cross-sectional study conducted in a population of 5th and 12th grade students attending municipal, subsidized and private schools in 11 regions of the country. HRQOL was assessed with the KIDSCREEN-52, an instrument that has been previously adapted and validated in Chile. The database obtained from that adaption and validation process was analyzed. RESULTS In total, 7,910 students (median age 14 years, 53% female) completed the questionnaire. Compared to males, females had lower HRQOL scores in most of the KIDSCREEN-52 dimensions. However, males were more likely to have lower scores in the &#147;Peers and Social Support&#148; and &#147;School Environment&#148; dimensions. These differences remained valid when the sample was stratified by age, type of school, and area of residence were analyzed. CONCLUSIONS This study supports the existence of inequalities in the self-perceived HRQOL of Chilean adolescent students. The existing differences are not only related to gender but are also evident when stratifying by type of school attended.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de género en la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en adolescentes escolarizados chilenos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Gender differences in health-related quality of life of Chilean adolescent students].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
