<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27305181</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Borrego, María-Aurora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almonacid, Clara Inés Flórez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos, Alfredo Jurado</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE estimate the prevalence of anxiety in laryngectomy patients in the pre and postoperative periods and its relation with the self-care level. METHOD observational research of 40 patients with stage IV laryngeal cancer. Three observations took place: in the preoperative phase, at seven and at 14 days after the surgery; between June 2010 and December 2012. Two self-care levels were defined: self-sufficient and needing help for activities of daily living and treatment-related activities. To assess the anxiety levels, Zigmond's hospital anxiety scale (1983) was used. RESULTS in the preoperative and postoperative phases, the patients presented high levels of anxiety. Concerning self-care, on average, self-sufficient patients presented lower levels of anxiety than patients who needed help to accomplish activities of daily living and activities deriving from the surgery, without significant differences. CONCLUSION anxiety is present at all times in laryngectomy patients and the reduction of the self-care deficit seems to decrease it, without putting a permanent end to it. OBJETIVO estimar a prevalência de ansiedade do paciente laringectomizado no pré-operatório e pós-operatório e sua relação com o nível de autocuidado. MÉTODO pesquisa observacional de 40 pacientes com câncer da laringe estágio IV. Foram realizadas 3 observações: no pré-operatório, a 7 e 14 dias pós-operatório, no período de junho de 2010 a dezembro de 2012. Dois níveis de autocuidado foram definidos: autossuficientes e precisar ajuda para as atividades da vida diária e relacionadas ao tratamento. Para avaliar a ansiedade, foi utilizada a escala de ansiedade hospitalar de Zigmond (1983). RESULTADOS no pré-operatório e pós-operatório, os pacientes apresentaram níveis elevados de ansiedade. Com relação ao autocuidado, os pacientes autossuficientes apresentaram na média níveis inferiores de ansiedades que os pacientes que precisavam de ajuda para realizar as atividades da vida diária y as derivadas da cirurgia, sem chegar a ser significativas estas diferenças. CONCLUSÃO a ansiedade está presente a todo momento no paciente laringectomizado e a diminuição do déficit de autocuidados parece diminuí-la sem acabar definitivamente com ela. OBJETIVO estimar la prevalencia de ansiedad del paciente laringectomizado, en el preoperatorio y postoperatorio y su relación con el nivel de autocuidados. MÉTODO investigación observacional de 40 pacientes con cáncer de laringe estadio IV. Se realizaron 3 observaciones: en el preoperatorio, a los 7 y 14 días del postoperatorio; en el periodo junio 2010 a diciembre de 2012. Se definieron dos niveles de autocuidados: autosuficientes y necesitar ayuda para las actividades de la vida diaria y derivadas del tratamiento; para evaluar la ansiedad se utilizó la escala de ansiedad hospitalaria de Zigmond (1983). RESULTADOS en el preoperatorio y postoperatorio los pacientes presentaron niveles elevados de ansiedad. En relación a los autocuidados, los pacientes autosuficientes presentaron en media niveles más bajos de ansiedad que los pacientes que necesitaban ayuda para realizar las actividades de la vida diaria y las derivadas de la cirugía, sin llegar a ser significativas estas diferencias. CONCLUSIÓN la ansiedad está presente en todo momento en el paciente con laringectomia y la disminución del déficit de autocuidados parece disminuirla sin terminar definitivamente con ella.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jun 14 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Level of anxiety versus self-care in the preoperative and postoperative periods of total laryngectomy patients.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
