<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27314998</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6341</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sandoval, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo, Giannina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes, Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labraña, Yenis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cofre, Fernanda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delpiano, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a lot of bacterial, viral or parasite infections who are able to be transmitted vertically from the mother to the fetus or newborn which implicates an enormous risk for it. The TORCH acronym is used universally to refer to a fetus or newborn which presents clinical features compatible with a vertically acquired infection and allows a rational diagnostic and therapeutic approach. The traditional "TORCH test" is nowadays considered not appropriate and it has been replaced for specific test for specific pathogens under well defined circumstances. The present document reviews the general characteristics, epidemiology, pathogenesis, diagnostic and therapeutic options for the most frequently involved pathogens in the fetus or newborn with TORCH suspicion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de TORCH: enfoque racional del diagnóstico y tratamiento pre y post natal. Recomendaciones del Comité Consultivo de Infecciones Neonatales Sociedad Chilena de Infectología, 2016.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[TORCH syndrome: Rational approach of pre and post natal diagnosis and treatment. Recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Neonatal Infections Sociedad Chilena de Infectología, 2016].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
