<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27316593</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Uscanga, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velasco-Zamora, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Reyes, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND AIMS The chronic use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) can cause complications in the gastrointestinal tract. The use of proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) is recommended in high-risk patients to prevent them. OBJECTIVE The aim of this article was to evaluate the gastroprotection measures taken in persons with chronic NSAID use. MATERIALS AND METHODS A descriptive cross-sectional study was conducted. The clinical records were reviewed of patients seen as outpatients at the Rheumatology Department over a 4-month period, choosing those with chronic NSAID use, and intentionally looking for gastroprotection measures according to the recommendations published by the American College of Gastroenterology. RESULTS A total of 417 patients (347 women; mean age: 48.12±14.2 years) were included. The most frequent diagnosis was rheumatoid arthritis (65%). Nine patients (2.1%) had a history of peptic ulcer, 48 (11.5%) patients were 65 years of age or older, 26 (6.2%) patients took NSAIDs and aspirin, and 130 (31.2%) took NSAIDs with steroids. Tests for Helicobacter pylori infection were done in just 53 cases, and there were positive results in only 9 (16%). Some risk for gastrointestinal toxicity was established in 211 cases and only 65 (30.8%) received gastroprotection. In contrast, 31 (15%) patients received gastroprotection when there was no indication for it. CONCLUSION Prophylaxis with PPIs in chronic NSAID users was inadequately employed. It was not prescribed in the majority of patients (69.2%) and it was used with no justification in others (15%).</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Riesgo gastrointestinal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastroprotection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antiinflamatorios no esteroideos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastroprotección</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Proton pump inhibitors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adverse effect</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Efecto adverso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastrointestinal risk</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inhibidor de la bomba de protones</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué tanto se siguen las recomendaciones de las guías clínicas sobre gastroprotección? Una revisión en enfermos que consumen antiinflamatorios no esteroideos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are the clinical guideline recommendations on gastroprotection being followed? A review in patients taking nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
