<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27399022</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz-Botero, Felipe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pachajoa, Harry</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Langer-Giedion syndrome, also known as trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type II, is a hereditary multisystemic disease part of the group of contiguous gene deletion syndromes. The cause of this syndrome is a heterozygous deletion that involves the chromosomal region 8q23.3-q24.11 and mainly affects genes TRPS1, RAD21, and EXT1. This syndrome is characterized by the presence of multiple osteochondromas in limbs, hypertrichosis, and facial phenotype that includes sparse scalp hair, large laterally protruding ears, a long nose with a bulbous tip. We report the case of a Colombian patient with finding of an 8q23.1-q24.12 deletion by comparative genomic hybridization array technique and classical clinical findings, being the first case reported in Colombia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type II</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Langer-Giedion syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Multiple exostoses</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Aug 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Langer-Giedion con deleción 8q23.1-q24.12, diagnosticado por hibridación genómica comparativa.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El síndrome de Langer-Giedion, también conocido como síndrome tricorrinofalángico tipo II, es una enfermedad hereditaria multisistémica que pertenece al grupo de síndromes por deleción de genes contiguos. La causa de este síndrome es una deleción heterocigota que compromete, por lo general, la región 8q23.3-q24.11 y afecta, principalmente, los genes TRPS1, RAD21 y EXT1. Este síndrome se caracteriza por osteocondromatosis múltiple en las extremidades, hipertricosis y fenotipo facial, que incluye pelo escaso en el cuero cabelludo, orejas grandes sobresalientes y nariz larga con una punta bulbosa. Se reporta el caso de un paciente colombiano con hallazgo de deleción en la región cromosómica 8q23.1-q24.12 mediante técnicas de hibridación genómica comparativa y hallazgos clínicos clásicos. Este es el primer caso reportado en Colombia. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Langer-Giedion syndrome with 8q23.1-q24.12 deletion diagnosed by comparative genomic hybridization].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
