<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27428341</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cortés-Sanabria, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez-Márquez, José Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Orozco-González, Claudia Nelly</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cueto-Manzano, Alfonso M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viera-Franco, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To determine the prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors (CVRF) in healthcare workers from two tertiary-care hospitals of the Mexican Institute of Social Security, as well as their association with professional activities (PA). METHODS Descriptive study. One-thousand eighty-nine health-care workers ≥ 18 years were included. Clinical history, physical exam, and blood tests were performed. RESULTS Mean age 41 ± 9 years, 76% women. Hypertension prevalence was 19%, diabetes mellitus 9.6%, dyslipidemia 78%, overweight and obesity 73%, metabolic syndrome (MS) 32.5%, and smoking 19%. The following significant associations (p &lt; 0.05) were found: MS with medical asisstants (OR: 2.73, CI 95%: 1.31-5.69) and nutritionist (OR: 2.6, CI 95%: 1.31-5.24); obesity with administrative personnel (OR: 3.64, CI 95%: 1.40-7.46); dyslipidemia with medical asisstants (OR: 2.58, CI 95%: 1.15-6.34). In the whole sample, the probability to have a vascular event in the following 10 years was 10%. CONCLUSION Prevalence of CVRF was high in this sample of health-care workers and did not seem to be different from those in general population. Medical assistants, nutritionist, and administrative personnel displayed a higher risk. It is necessary to create programs to promote healthy lifestyle and to improve the epidemiological profile of health-care workers.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Prevalence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiovascular risk factors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health-care workers</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en trabajadores de la salud.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: el objetivo de este trabajo es determinar la prevalencia de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV) y su asociación con actividad laboral (AL) en trabajadores de dos hospitales de enseñanza de tercer nivel de atención del IMSS. Métodos: estudio descriptivo que incluyó a trabajadores ≥ 18 años. Se realizó historia clínica, examen físico y pruebas de laboratorio para identificar FRCV y asociarlos con AL. Resultados: se estudió un total de 1089 trabajadores, con edad de 41 ± 9 años, el 76% fueron mujeres. La prevalencia de hipertensión fue de 19%, diabetes mellitus 9.6%, dislipidemia 78%, sobrepeso y obesidad 73%; síndrome metabólico (SM) 32.5%, tabaquismo 19%. El SM se asoció con el área de asistentes médicas (OR: 2.73, IC 95%: 1.31-5.69) y nutrición/dietética (OR: 2.6, IC 95%: 1.31-5.24). La obesidad con el área administrativa (OR 3.64 IC 95%: 1.40-7.46). La dislipidemia con el área de asistentes médicas (OR 2.58, IC 95%: 1.15-6.34). La probabilidad de sufrir evento vascular en 10 años fue de 10%. Conclusiones: la prevalencia de FRCV fue alta y no es diferente a la de la población general. Las actividades laborales en riesgo fueron: asistentes médicas, nutricionistas y personal administrativo. Es necesario reorientar programas de promoción de la salud en unidades médicas para mejorar el perfil epidemiológico de los trabajadores. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors in a population of health-care workers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
