<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27428337</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero-Velarde, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vásquez-Garibay, Edgar Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fonseca-Reyes, Salvador</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez-Román, Yussani Arelhi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casillas-Toral, Erika</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguirre-Salas, Liuba Marina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The prevalence of overweight and obesity in children in Mexico are high, as well as the complications associated with their presence. The objective of this work was to estimate the prevalence of metabolic syndrome in obese children and adolescents attending a Hospital Clinic and identify the associated factors. METHODS Cross sectional design with 120 children and adolescents; of either sex, with exogenous obesity and BMI &gt; 2.0 standard deviations. Personal and family history was collected, blood pressure was measured and determination of serum glucose, insulin, lipoprotein HDL cholesterol and triglycerides were performed. The presence of metabolic syndrome with the ATPIII, WHO and International Diabetes Federation criteria was identified. The association of metabolic syndrome with different variables was identified with chi square test and calculation of odds ratio. RESULTS Mean age was 10.6 ± 2.7 years. The prevalence of metabolic syndrome was 37.5% to 54.5% depending on the criteria used. The presence of metabolic syndrome was associated with a history of large birth weight (OR= 2.21 [1.01-4.82]), and insulin resistance (OR= 6.53 [2.40-18.2]). CONCLUSIONS The prevalence of metabolic syndrome is high in this group of children and adolescents with obesity. The history of large birth weight and the presence of insulin resistance should alert us to the presence of the disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulin resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children and adolescents</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metabolic syndrome X</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de síndrome metabólico y factores asociados en niños y adolescentes con obesidad.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad es elevada en niños y adolescentes en nuestro país, así como las alteraciones asociadas a su presencia. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue estimar la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en niños y adolescentes con obesidad que acudieron a una clínica hospitalaria e identificar factores asociados a su presencia. Métodos: diseño transversal con 120 niños y adolescentes, de cualquier sexo, con obesidad exógena e IMC &gt; 2.0 desviaciones estándar. Se recolectaron antecedentes personales y familiares; se midió la presión arterial y se realizaron determinaciones de los niveles séricos de glucosa, insulina, lipoproteínas de colesterol de alta densidad y triglicéridos. Se identificó la presencia de síndrome metabólico con los criterios ATPIII, OMS y de la Federación Internacional de Diabetes. Se identificó la asociación del síndrome metabólico con diferentes variables con la prueba Chi cuadrada y cálculo de razón de momios. Resultados: la edad promedio fue de 10.6 ± 2.7 años. La prevalencia de síndrome metabólico fue de 37.5 a 54.5%, dependiendo del criterio utilizado; se asoció al antecedente de peso grande al nacimiento (RM = 2.21 [1.01-4.82]) y resistencia a la insulina (RM = 6.53 [2.40-18.2]). Conclusiones: la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico es elevada en este grupo de niños y adolescentes con obesidad. El antecedente de peso grande al nacer y la presencia de resistencia a la insulina nos deben alertar sobre la presencia de la enfermedad. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of metabolic syndrome and associated factors in children and adolescents with obesity].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
