<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27420477</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6384</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jadresic, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Until recently, social blushing was rarely discussed in the medical literature. It was usually considered only a normal and occasional physiological reaction associated with emotions such as embarrassment brought on by social situations. This has changed in recent years with attention increasingly being paid to blushing, either in the context of social anxiety disorder or in its own right. Some argue that blushing has adaptive value, so it may not make sense to treat people for blushing, a view we do not agree with since the blushing experience is not the same for everyone and those who seek medical help do so because their blushing impairs their quality of life. Furthermore, the fact that a symptom is adaptive does not place it beyond the scope of medical treatment. Quite the contrary: physicians treat many symptoms that cause discomfort, e.g. pain and vomiting, which may be regarded as adaptive, yet few doubt the value of treating such problems. The same is true for blushing. Recognizing its potential adaptive value does not mean that it should not be treated. The distress of those who blush easily and seek help justifies attempts to find ways to help them. This article underlines the need to distinguish between normal social blushing and pathological social blushing and, at the same time, reviews current available treatments for individuals who seek help for this condition.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>blushing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adaptive behavior</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>social discomfort</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jul 05 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El sonrojo social: ¿un trastorno neuropsiquiátrico?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Hasta hace poco tiempo, rara vez se debatía sobre el sonrojo social en la literatura médica. Se le consideraba solo una reacción fisiológica normal y ocasional, provocada por situaciones sociales. Esto ha cambiado en años recientes pues se le presta cada vez mayor atención, ya sea en el contexto del trastorno de ansiedad social o por derecho propio. Algunos argumentan que sonrojarse tiene valor adaptativo y que por lo tanto no tiene sentido tratar a las personas que se sonrojan, visión que no compartimos porque la experiencia de ruborizarse no es igual en todos los individuos y porque los que consultan lo hacen debido a que las sucesivas experiencias de rubor van minando su calidad de vida. Más aún, el que un síntoma sea adaptativo no lo pone fuera del ámbito de la medicina. Al contrario: hay numerosos síntomas que tratamos los médicos, desagradables para el individuo -el dolor y los vómitos son buenos ejemplos-, los cuales pueden considerarse adaptativos y sin embargo pocos podrían en duda la legitimidad de tratarlos. Lo mismo es válido para el sonrojo. Reconocer su potencial valor adaptativo no hace ilegítimo su tratamiento. El sufrimiento de aquellos que se sonrojan fácilmente y buscan ayuda por ello, justifica los intentos de encontrar modos de ayudarlos. Este texto subraya la necesidad de distinguir entre el sonrojo social normal y el sonrojo social patológico y, a la vez, revisa los tratamientos actualmente disponibles para las personas que consultan por esta condición. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social blushing: a neuropsychiatric disorder?</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medwave</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
