<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27445225</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8865</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Foncillas, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lostalé-Latorre, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zamora-Catevilla, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nabal-Vicuña, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calderero-Aragón, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zamora-Mur, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Sedation, used as a therapeutic measure in the field of Palliative Care, continues to present difficulties for many professionals in its management and indications. Is varied existing literature in this regard, often exclusive cancer patients. Our objective is to analyse the characteristics of patients attended by a Home Care Support Team who required sedation compared to non-sedated patients, for possible determining factors for its use that could help in decision-making. METHOD A prospective analytical study conducted in Barbastro (Huesca) from September 2007 to February 2011. The study population are patients referred to the Home Care Support Team of Barbastro. MAIN VARIABLES Age, sex, medical history, symptoms, previous and current Barthel, Karnofsky, primary caregiver, previous drugs, drugs after intervention, sedation yes/no. RESULTS Required sedation 16.6% (n=106) of the cases (N=638). Sedated patients were younger, with no differences in sex, and the large majority (83%) were oncology patients. The presence of metastases showed no differences in need for sedation. Sedated patients have an increased functional impairment, determined by Barthel index decreased and a worse Karnofsky. Sedated patients showed increased frequency of uncontrolled symptoms, except psychomotor agitation, a fact determined by the medications used pre- and post-intervention. CONCLUSIONS The presence of neoplastic disease, marked with existence of functional decline, and uncontrolled clinical need for certain medications to control symptoms may determine the need for sedation at the end of the process, above other factors such as patient comorbidity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Home care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sedación paliativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención domiciliaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidados paliativos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Palliative care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Palliative sedation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores condicionantes de sedación en pacientes geriátricos y oncológicos atendidos en el domicilio.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Determining factors in the sedation of geriatric and oncology patients treated at home].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Semergen</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
