<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27461232</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Liñán, Milagrosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacios-Eito, Amalia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bueno-Serrano, Carmen M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Barbadillo, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otero-Romero, Ana M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Cabezas, Sonia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Preoperative short-course radiotherapy with immediate surgery improves local control in patients with rectal cancer. Tumor responses are smaller than those described with radiochemotherapy. Preliminary data associate this lower response to the short period until surgery. The aim of this study is to analyze the response to preoperative short-course radiotherapy and its correlation with the interval to surgery especially analyzing patients with mesorectal fascia involvement. METHODS A total of 155 patients with locally advanced rectal cancer treated with preoperative radiotherapy (5×5Gy) were retrospectively analyzed. Tumor response in terms of rates of complete pathological response, downstaging, tumor regression grading and status of the circumferential resection margin were quantified. RESULTS The mean interval from radiotherapy to surgery was 23 days. The rate of complete pathological response was 2.2% and 28% experienced downstaging (stage decreased). No differences between these rates and interval to surgery were detected. Eighty-eight patients had magnetic resonance imaging for staging (in 31 patients the mesorectal fascia was involved).The mean time to surgery in patients with involvement of the fascia and R0 surgery was 27 days and 16 days if R1 (P=.016). The cutoff of 20 days reached the highest probability of achieving a free circumferential resection margin between patients with mesorectal fascia involvement, with no statistically significant differences: RR 3.036 95% CI=(0.691-13.328), P=.06. CONCLUSIONS After preoperative short-course radiotherapy, an interval&gt;20 days enhances the likelihood of achieving a free circumferential resection margin in patients with mesorectal fascia involvement.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Respuesta patológica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pathological response</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Delay surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rectal cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comorbidity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>5×5Gy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comorbilidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía diferida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Short course</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radioterapia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Curso corto</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de recto</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta al tratamiento e intervalo de tiempo hasta la cirugía con radioterapia preoperatoria de curso corto en el cáncer de recto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Response to treatment and interval to surgery after preoperative short-course radiotherapy in rectal cancer.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
