<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27480910</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Toscano, Maximiliano</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carrizo, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ajler, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beltrame, Sofia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goldschmidt, Ezequiel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campero, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garategui, Lucas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yampolsky, Claudio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To present the clinical and radiographic outcomes of 140 patients with pituitary adenomas treated by an endoscopic endonasal approach (EEA) over a period of 4 years. MATERIAL AND METHODS A retrospective analysis was performed between 2011 and 2014. Pre and post operative MRI, ophtalmological assessment, endocrinological laboratory evaluation and surgical morbidity and mortality were assessed. RESULTS 57,9% of the patients had functional tumors (n=81), acromegaly being the most frequent sub-type (29.3%). 78.6% of the lesions were macroadenomas (n=110) of which 56.4% (n=62) involved the cavernous sinus, 61 patients presented with visual field defects (44%) of which 50.8% of patients showed improvement after surgery. Gross total removal was achieved in 60% of the cases. Hormonal remission was achieved in the 75% of the patients with functional tumors. The morbidity rate was 15% and one patient died after surgery (mortality 0.7%). CONCLUSION EEA is a safe and effective tool to treat pituitary adenomas. The main limitation for complete surgical resection is the cavernous sinus invasion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pituitary adenomas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Transnasal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adenomas de hipófisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Mar - Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endoscópico de 140 tumores de hipófisis, resultados y complicaciones.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Endoscopic treatment of 140 pituitary tumors, results and complications].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurocirugia (Asturias, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
