<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27509012</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8787</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramsey, Janine M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monreal, Luz Arenas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rangel, José Antonio Santana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To explore the pillars of community resilience in a region where Chagas disease is endemic, with the aim of promoting participatory processes to deal with this condition from the resilience of the population. METHODS Qualitative study using ethnographic record and six interviews of focus groups with young people, women and men. The research was carried out in a rural area of the state of Morelos, Mexico, between 2006 and 2007. We carried out educational sessions with the population in general, so that residents could identify the relationship between the vector Triatoma pallidipennis, the parasite (Trypanosoma cruzi), symptoms, and preventive actions for Chagas disease. The ethnographic record and groups were analyzed based on Taylor and Bogdan's modification, and the focus was to understand the socio-cultural meanings that guide the speeches and activities of residents in relation to the pillars of community resilience. RESULTS The population felt proud of belonging to that location and three pillars of community resilience were clearly identified: collective self-esteem, cultural identity, and social honesty. Having these pillars as bases, we promoted the participation of the population concerning Chagas disease, and a Community Action Group was formed with young people, adult men and women, and social leaders. This Group initiated actions of epidemiological and entomological surveillance in the community to deal with this problem. CONCLUSIONS It is necessary to create more experiences that deepen the understanding of the pillars of community resilience, and how they contribute to enhance participation in health to deal with Chagas disease. OBJETIVO Explorar los pilares de la resiliencia comunitaria en una región en la que la enfermedad de Chagas es endémica, con la finalidad de partir de la resiliencia de la población para impulsar procesos participativos para enfrentar este padecimiento. MÉTODOS Estudio cualitativo que utilizó registro etnográfico y seis entrevistas de grupos focales con jóvenes, mujeres y hombres adultos. La investigación se efectúo en una localidad rural del Estado de Morelos, México, entre 2006 y 2007. Se efectuaron sesiones educativas con la población en general, para que los habitantes identificaran la relación entre el vector Triatoma pallidipennis, el parásito (Trypanosoma cruzi), la sintomatología y acciones preventivas para la enfermedad de Chagas. El registro etnográfico y los grupos fueron analizados con base en una modificación de Taylor y Bogdan, y el foco fue comprender los significados socioculturales que guían los discursos y actividades de los pobladores en relación a los pilares de la resiliencia comunitaria. RESULTADOS La población se sentía orgullosa de pertenecer a esa localidad y se identificaron con claridad tres pilares de la resiliencia comunitaria: autoestima colectiva, identidad cultural y honestidad social. Tomando como base estos pilares, se impulsó la participación de la población en torno a la enfermedad de Chagas, y se formó un Grupo de Acción Comunitaria con jóvenes, hombres y mujeres adultos, y líderes sociales. Este Grupo inició acciones de vigilancia epidemiológica y entomológica en la comunidad para hacer frente a esta problemática. CONCLUSIONES Es necesario generar más experiencias que profundicen en la comprensión de los pilares de resiliencia comunitaria, y en la manera en que estos contribuyen a potenciar la participación en salud para enfrentar la enfermedad de Chagas.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Aug 04 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Community resilience and Chagas disease in a rural region of Mexico.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
