<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27556875</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sousa, Fátima Aparecida Emm Faleiros</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Talita de Cássia Raminelli da</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saltareli, Simone</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hortense, Priscilla</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gomez, Rodrigo Ramon Falconi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Siqueira, Hilze Benigno de Oliveira Moura</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to describe acute and chronic pain from the perspective of the life cycle. METHODS participants: 861 people in pain. The Multidimensional Pain Evaluation Scale (MPES) was used. RESULTS in the category estimation method the highest descriptors of chronic pain for children/ adolescents were "Annoying" and for adults "Uncomfortable". The highest descriptors of acute pain for children/adolescents was "Complicated"; and for adults was "Unbearable". In magnitude estimation method, the highest descriptors of chronic pain was "Desperate" and for descriptors of acute pain was "Terrible". CONCLUSIONS the MPES is a reliable scale it can be applied during different stages of development. OBJETIVO descrever a dor aguda e a crônica na perspectiva do ciclo vital. Métodos: participaram 861 pessoas com dor. Foi utilizada a Escala Multidimensional de Avaliação da Dor (EMADOR). Resultados: no método da estimação de categoria o descritor da dor crônica de maior atribuição para crianças e adolescentes foi "Chata" e para adultos foi "Desconfortável". Os descritores de maior atribuição para dor aguda em crianças e adolescentes foram "Complicada" e em adultos "Insuportável". No método de estimação de magnitude, o descritor de maior atribuição na dor crônica foi "Atormentadora" e na dor aguda foi "Terrível". CONCLUSÕES a EMADOR é uma escala confiável e pode ser utilizada nas diferentes etapas do desenvolvimento humano. OBJETIVO la descripción del dolor agudo y crónico desde las perspectiva del ciclo de vida. MÉTODOS participaron 861 personas con dolor. Se utilizó la Escala Multidimensional de Evaluación del Dolor (EMEDOR). RESULTADOS en el método de estimación de categoría el descriptor de dolor crónico más alto para niños y adolescentes fue de Molesto y para adultos fue Incómodo. Los descriptores mayores de dolor agudo para niños y adolescentes fueron Complejo y para adultos Insoportable. En el método de estimación de magnitud, el mayor descriptor de dolor crónico fueron Atormentador y el mayor de dolor agudo fue Terrible. CONCLUSIONES la EMEDOR es una escala confiable y puede ser utilizada en diferentes etapas de desarrollo.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Aug 18 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pain from the life cycle perspective: Evaluation and Measurement through psychophysical methods of category estimation and magnitude estimation.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
