<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27552008</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Solís, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto, Gabriela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras, Aixa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dois, Angelina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo, Paulina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mora, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The integral Model of Family and Community Health care is based on three essential principles: patient centered care, comprehensive care and continuity of care. AIM To know the perception of primary care clinic users about the elements that should be considered in a patient centered integrated health care. MATERIAL AND METHODS Ten males and 31 females aged 18 to 78 years, users of two public family primary care centers participated in focus groups, which were recorded. A qualitative descriptive research design based on content analysis according to Krippendorf was done. RESULTS Seven issues emerged from the description of patients&#146; experiences: professional-patient relationship, fragmentation of care, continued care with the same professional, promotion and prevention, availability of services and patient records. CONCLUSIONS There are difficulties to install an integral model of family and community health care. The concerns raised by participants should be considered in order to modify the design of these models.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principios orientadores del Modelo Integral de Salud Familiar y Comunitario desde la perspectiva de los usuarios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Perception of users about an Integral Model of Family and Community Health care in Santiago, Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
