<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27568400</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallegos-Sierra, Cuauhtly</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leonher-Ruezga, Karla Lisseth</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Cruz-Temores, Salvador</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez-Jaimez, Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belmonte-Chico Goerne, Manuel Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Intussusception is defined as a segment of the gastrointestinal tract and mesentery within the lumen of an adjacent segment. It is a rare condition in adults that can occur anywhere in the gastrointestinal tract from the stomach to the rectum. Only 5% of all intussusceptions are presented in adults, and in 1-5% of all cases of intestinal obstruction. Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumour is rare, and is usually found in the lung, and rarely detected in some intestinal portions. It causes a variety of non-specific symptoms, with those that present as an intussusception being uncommon. CLINICAL CASE A female of 69 years with partial bowel obstruction secondary to intestinal intussusception due to an inflammatory myofibroblastic tumour, a rarely diagnosed condition and never published before. DISCUSSION Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumours are rare, and in this case with an atypical presentation that was surgically resolved satisfactorily. These entities are difficult to diagnose, with histopathology giving the definitive diagnosis. A literature review was performed to gather recent information about their diagnosis and treatment. CONCLUSIONS Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumours require a high level of suspicion, as diagnosis prior to surgery is difficult. Surgery is considered the treatment of choice, requiring leaving free surgical edges to prevent recurrences.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Intususcepción</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obstrucción intestinal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intussusception</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intestinal obstruction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tumor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tumour</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoplasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoplasms</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep - Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intususcepción intestinal secundaria a tumor miofibroblástico en un adulto mayor. Reporte de caso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Intestinal intussusception secondary to myofibroblastic tumor in an elderly patient. Case report].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
