<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2757779</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blum-Gordillo, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gordillo-Paniagua, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This presentation comprises: a) the study of psychosocial problems in children with chronic disease (1980-83); b) application and results of a "pluridimensional approach" model, designed to solve these conflicts (1982-88). Thirty-five children with end stage renal disease (ESRD) and 34 families were studied, as well as the members of the professional team. The methods of study were: conducted observations, projective tests, recording and analysis of psychotherapy (individual and familiar) and Balint sessions. The data were analized in the framework of psychoanalysis, theory of the systems and groups, etc. The results showed: depression, anguish and regression, interfering with rehabilitation, in the group of children. The problems worsening with greater length of the dialysis periods and with younger age of the patients. Poverty increases losses and guilty feelings decreasing the defensive and adaptive mechanisms. In the families, ESRD provoked migration, fragmentation, dynamic and structural dysfunctions and several inter and intrapersonal conflicts. In the professional team, tension, anxiety, compulsive and indiscriminate conducts were detected, as well as a great difficulty to communicate with the patients and their families. In an attempt to decrease these conflicts a pluridimensional approach was designed and applied in the patients, families and members of the professional team, with the aim of interrupt the pathologic interaction patterns and change them in therapeutic. This model included the practice of several independent and simultaneous psychological interventions, ergotherapy, recreative and occupational activities with the patients; group sessions for information, diagnostic interviews and psychotherapy with the families and Balint sessions with the professional team.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemática psicosocial del niño con enfermedad crónica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Psychosocial problems of children with chronic disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
