<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27598275</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6341</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Leyton, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete, Maritza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ismail, Kissy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caroca, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saavedra, Farides</dc:author>
<dc:author>Venegas, Nadialett</dc:author>
<dc:author>Otth, Carola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hott, Melissa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Currently in Chile, due to the frequent clinical suspicion of Hantavirus disease and the high public health impact that this causes, it is necessary to strengthen the criteria for clinical and epidemiological suspicion in the health team. OBJECTIVE To analyze the information contained in the reports of suspected Hantavirus infection versus the confirmatory diagnosis with the reference technique, IgM capture ELISA anti-hantavirus. Material andMethods: Correlation between the information provided in notifications versus the result of confirmation was analyzed by calculating diagnostic accuracy. RESULTS 3.4% of 1,566 patients studied (53 cases) was confirmed as SCPH. 58.6% of the analyzed notifications was incomplete. The percentage of positivity of the reference technique associated with fever, myalgia and headache was 80-85%. The presence of immunoblasts (&gt; 10%) showed 25% sensitivity, 98% specificity, 37% PPV, 97% NPV. Thrombocytopenia exhibited 98% sensitivity, 74% specificity, 16% PPV, 100% NPV. CONCLUSION It is necessary to reinforce the importance of comprehensive data reporting at the health system level. The presence of thrombocytopenia and immunoblasts (&gt; 10%) is highly sensitive and specific, respectively, for detecting patients with SCPH. There is a need to develop training programs in order to optimize the suspicion of Hantavirus infection and appropriate use of health resources.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación entre criterios clínicos y de laboratorio de casos notificados por sospecha de hantavirosis y el resultado de la técnica de referencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Correlation between clinical and laboratory criteria of suspected Hantavirus cases and the results of the reference diagnostic technique].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista chilena de infectologia : organo oficial de la Sociedad Chilena de Infectologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
