<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27595514</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-2284</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Perelló, Manel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Obispo, Matilde</dc:author>
<dc:author>Güell, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lara, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Sierra, Sandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torra, Roser</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyes, Pere</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Begué, Nieves</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camacho, Juan Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gámez, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torregrosa, J Vicens</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Villoria, Judit</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pintos-Morell, Guillem</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila-Santandreu, Anna</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ariceta, Gema</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Polo, Aurora</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Improved outcome and longer life-expectancy in patients with cystinosis, and disease complexity itself, justify planning a guided-transition of affected patients from Pediatrics to adult medicine. The aims of the process are to guarantee the continuum of care and patient empowerment, moving from guardian-care to self-care. METHODS review of articles, expert opinion and anonymous surveys of patients, relatives and patient advocacy groups. RESULTS elaboration a new document to support and coordinate the transition of patients with cystinosis providing specific proposals in a variety of medical fields, and adherence promotion. Nephrologists play a key role in transition due the fact that most cystinotic patients suffer severe chronic kidney disease, and need kidney transplantation before adulthood. CONCLUSION we present a document providing recommendations and suggesting a chronogram to help the process of transition of adolescents and young adults with cystinosis in our area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Adherence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cystinosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Kidney transplant</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trasplante renal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adolescent</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Transición</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Transition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cistinosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adherencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adolescente</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transición coordinada del paciente con cistinosis desde la medicina pediátrica a la medicina del adulto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A coordinated transition model for patients with cystinosis: from pediatrics to adult care.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nefrologia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola Nefrologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
