<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27598488</identifier>
<setSpec>0717-6163</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cabrera, Walter E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lamberts, Ludwig</dc:author>
<dc:author>D'Haese, Patrick</dc:author>
<dc:author>Behets, Geert</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED The role of lead (Pb) as an environmental cause of nephropathy is difficult to ascertain due to the difficulty to determine clinically its exposure. AIM To assess lead levels and renal function in a group of males working in mechanical workshops. MATERIAL AND METHODS Blood and urine samples were obtained from 100 mechanical workshop workers aged 38 ± 16 years and 95 non-exposed office clerks aged 37 ± 17 years. Blood lead and creatinine levels were determined. In exposed workers, urinary excretion of intestinal alkaline phosphatases (IAP) and N-acetyl-glucosaminidase (NAG) were measured as early markers of renal failure. RESULTS Blood lead levels were 66.4 ± 43 and 33.6 ± 18 µg/L among mechanical workshop workers and non-exposed controls, respectively, p &lt; 0.01. The figures for serum creatinine were 0.9 ± 0.1 and 0.9 ± 0.1 respectively, p = NS. Among exposed workers urinary excretion of IAP was 0.47 ± 0.6 U/L and of NAG, 0.92 ± 1.1 U/L. There was a positive correlation between blood lead levels and NAG excretion (r = 0.284) and IAP excretion (r = 0.346). CONCLUSIONS Exposed workers had higher blood lead levels and there was a weak positive association between these levels and the urinary excretion of NAG and IAP.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plomo y nefropatía: Biomarcadores urinarios en la detección de daño renal precoz.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Blood lead levels and markers of renal dysfunction among mechanical workshop workers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
