<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27595248</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salinas-Salinas, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rajmet-Hace, Victoria Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez-Rodríguez, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brea-Andrea, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mariño-Rojas, Fabiola</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The multinational EDGE (Effectiveness of Diabetes control with vildaGliptin and vildagliptin/mEtformin) study assessed the effectiveness and tolerability of vildagliptin versus other oral antihyperglycemic drugs (OAD) when added to monotherapy in patients in the real-world setting. METHODS Prospective, real-world observational study. The primary endpoint (PEP) was the proportion of patients achieving a reduction in HbA1c &gt; 0.3% without peripheral edema, hypoglycemia, discontinuation, dueto gastrointestinal event, or weight gain &gt; 5%. The secondary endpoint (SEP) was the proportion of patient achieving HbA1c &lt; 7% (at month 12), without proven hypoglycemia or weight gain (≥ 3%). RESULTS Of the 3,523 patients enrolled in Mexico, 2,847 were in the vildagliptin and 676 in the comparator cohort. The PEP was reached in 61.8 and 53.2% in the vildagliptin and comparator cohorts, respectively. The unadjusted odds ratio was 1.42 (95% CI: 1.19-1.68) in favor of vildagliptin. A similar advantage for vildagliptin-based therapies was seen for the SEP. The percentage was lower in the vildagliptin (n = 145; 5.0%) than in the comparator group (n = 95; 14.0%). CONCLUSION Vildagliptin, added to a first-line OAD monotherapy, allows patients to reach target HbA1c without experiencing significant adverse events.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad y seguridad de vildagliptina como tratamiento adicional para la diabetes mellitus de tipo 2 (DMT2) en condiciones de vida real en México. Sub-análisis del estudio EDGE.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectivity and security of vildagliptin as additional treatment for Type 2 diabetes mellitus in real-life conditions in Mexico. EDGE Study subanalysis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
