<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27600863</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Segura, José V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Pérez, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ariza-Solé, Albert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Elola, Francisco J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernal, José L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cequier, Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iñiguez, Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES To analyze the association between the development of network systems of care for ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) in the autonomous communities (AC) of Spain and the regional rate of percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) and in-hospital mortality. METHODS From 2003 to 2012, data from the minimum basic data set of the Spanish taxpayer-funded health system were analyzed, including admissions from general hospitals. Diagnoses of STEMI and related procedures were codified by the International Diseases Classification. Discharge episodes (n = 302 471) were distributed in 3 groups: PCI (n = 116 621), thrombolysis (n = 46 720), or no reperfusion (n = 139 130). RESULTS Crude mortality throughout the evaluation period was higher for the no-PCI or thrombolysis group (17.3%) than for PCI (4.8%) and thrombolysis (8.6%) (P &lt; .001). For the aggregate of all communities, the PCI rate increased (21.6% in 2003 vs 54.5% in 2012; P &lt; .001) with a decrease in risk-standardized mortality rates (10.2% in 2003; 6.8% in 2012; P &lt; .001). Significant differences were observed in the PCI rate across the AC. The development of network systems was associated with a 50% increase in the PCI rate (P &lt; .001) and a 14% decrease in risk-standardized mortality rates (P &lt; .001). CONCLUSIONS From 2003 to 2012, the PCI rate in STEMI substantially increased in Spain. The development of network systems was associated with an increase in the PCI rate and a decrease in in-hospital mortality.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación de segmento ST</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ST-segment elevation acute myocardial infarction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrinolisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intervención coronaria percutánea primaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>STEMI network</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estrategias de reperfusión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary percutaneous coronary intervention</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Políticas de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Redes de IAMCEST</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombolysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health policies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reperfusion strategies</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact on Mortality of Different Network Systems in the Treatment of ST-segment Elevation Acute Myocardial Infarction. The Spanish Experience.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
