<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27606641</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro, Ximena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gatica, Darwin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Núñez, Iván</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manterola, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Respiratory muscle training is the most commonly used method to revert respiratory muscle weakness; however, the effect of protocols based on non-respiratory maneuvers has not been adequately studied in the pediatric population. The objective of this study was to establish the effect of abdominal muscle training on respiratory muscle strength and forced expiratory flows in healthy adolescents. METHODS This was a quasi-experiment. The sample was made up of healthy adolescents divided into two groups: an experimental group who completed eight weeks of active abdominal muscle training, and an equivalent control group. The following indicators were measured: abdominal muscle strength, maximal inspiratory pressure, maximal expiratory pressure (MEP), peak expiratory flow, and peak cough flow, before and after protocol completion. A value of p &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. RESULTS All studied outcome measures increased significantly in the experimental group but only MEP increased in the control group. In addition, a higher MEP was observed in the experimental group compared to the control group at the end of the protocol, together with a greater increase in MEP and peak expiratory flow. Finally, the increase in MEP was associated with an increase in cough peak flow in the experimental group but not in the control group. CONCLUSION After eight weeks of abdominal muscle training, MEP and peak expiratory flow increased in healthy (sedentary) adolescents. Such effects were associated with intervention-induced increases in cough peak flow.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Respiratory muscle</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Peak expiratory flow</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Abdominal training</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cough</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Respiratory muscle training</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del entrenamiento de músculos abdominales sobre la fuerza muscular respiratoria y flujos espiratorios forzados en adolescentes sanos sedentarios.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El entrenamiento muscular respiratorio es el método más utilizado para revertir la debilidad muscular respiratoria; no obstante, el efecto de protocolos basados en maniobras no respiratorias no ha sido suficientemente estudiado en población pediátrica. El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar el efecto del entrenamiento de la musculatura abdominal sobre la fuerza de los músculos respiratorios y los flujos espiratorios forzados en adolescentes sanos. 
             Estudio cuasiexperimental. La muestra estuvo integrada por adolescentes sanos divididos en dos grupos: un grupo experimental, quienes realizaron 8 semanas de entrenamiento de la musculatura abdominal activo, y un grupo control equivalente. Se midió la fuerza de los músculos abdominales, la presión inspiratoria máxima, la presión espiratoria máxima (PeMax), el flujo espiratorio máximo y el flujo máximo de tos antes y después del protocolo. Se consideró significativo un valor de p &lt; 0,05. 
             Todas las variables estudiadas aumentaron significativamente en el grupo experimental; sin embargo, solo la PeMax se incrementó en el grupo control. Adicionalmente, el grupo experimental presentó una mayor PeMax que el grupo control al final del protocolo, así como también una mayor ganancia en la PeMax y flujo espiratorio máximo. Finalmente, el incremento en la PeMax se asoció con el aumento en el flujo máximo de tos en el grupo experimental, lo que no fue observado en el grupo control. 
             En 8 semanas de entrenamiento de la musculatura abdominal, se logró incrementar la PeMax y el flujo espiratorio máximo en adolescentes sanos (sedentarios). Estos efectos se asociaron a incrementos en el flujo máximo de tos inducidos por la intervención. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of abdominal muscle training on respiratory muscle strength and forced expiratory flows in sedentary, healthy adolescents.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
