<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27627773</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Abdala-Dergal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vázquez-Alonso, M F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The frequent causes of relapsing carpal tunnel syndrome were analyzed. Nine patients were followed-up from January 1st to December 31st, 2011. They underwent a physical exam and imaging tests. Pain was measured in all of them with the VAS, and the Brigham and Womens Hospital questionnaire was used to assess disability. Patients included seven females and two males; mean age was 52 years. Major causes for relapse included postoperative fibrosis with incomplete release in seven patients and incomplete release in two patients in whom minimally invasive approaches were used. Three of the nine patients had retractile scars. The main cause of relapse was postoperative fibrosis associated with the minima-lly invasive approach.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>recurrence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>pain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>mri</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>fibrosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Carpal tunnel</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principales causas de recidivas en el túnel del carpo.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Se analizaron las causas frecuentes del síndrome del túnel del carpo recidivante. Seguimiento de una serie de casos del 1 de Enero al 31 Diciembre 2011; se estudiaron nueve pacientes mediante examen físico y de gabinete. A todos se les evaluó el dolor con escala visual análoga, cuestionario de &lt;i&gt;Brigham and Womens&lt;/i&gt; Hospital para conocer la discapacidad. Siete pacientes correspondieron al género femenino y dos al masculino, con un promedio de edad de 52 años. Entre las principales causas de recidiva se encontró la fibrosis postquirúrgica acompañada de una liberación incompleta en siete pacientes; en dos pacientes se observó una liberación incompleta y se les realizó abordajes mínimos invasivos. Tres pacientes de los nueve presentaron cicatrices retráctiles. La principal causa de recidiva es la fibrosis postquirúrgica asociada al abordaje mínimamente invasivo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Principal causes for recurrent carpal tunnel syndrome].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
