<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27658359</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garreta-Figuera, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>En Representacion Del Grupo de Estudio 5e, En Representacion Del Grupo de Estudio 5e</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torrequebrada-Gimenez, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Although spasticity is a disabling complication of high incidence, there is a lack of either regional or national epidemiological studies in Spain evaluating its management. AIM To evaluate the management of spasticity in Spain. PATIENTS AND METHODS An epidemiological, observational, multicenter, and retrospective study involving 49 rehabilitation services of public and private hospitals was designed. RESULTS Two hundred and thirty-five patients from 49 centers, with evidence of upper (UL) or lower limb (LL) spasticity with one valid baseline visit and at least one follow-up visit, were included. Among the patients included in the study 148 (62.9%) have post stroke spasticity; 79 (33.6%) have LL spasticity, 38 (16.1%) UL, and 118 (50.3%) in both. At baseline, Modified Ashworth Scale, goniometry, Visual Analog Scale for pain and Tardieu Scale had been performed in 164 (69.8%), 99 (42.1%), 85 (36.2%), and 26 (11.1%) patients, respectively. A 93.8% (IC 95%: 81.4-97.6%) of the centers accurately defined the treatment goals and 52% of the objectives were agreed with the patient. Botulinum A toxin was administered in 186 (79.1%) of patients; 49 (20.9%) patients were treated with oral antispastic medications and 93 (39.6%) were under physiotherapy treatment. CONCLUSIONS Most of the patients have post-stroke spasticity. Moreover, botulinum A toxin was the most commonly treatment applied to patients with spasticity. The results demonstrate that the management of spasticity varies significantly across the different centers participating in the study.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluacion del tratamiento de la espasticidad en Espa単a: estudio 5E.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Evaluacion del tratamiento de la espasticidad en Espa単a: estudio 5E. 
             Introduccion. Aunque la espasticidad es una secuela que presenta una incidencia alta, hay una carencia de estudios que evaluen su manejo terapeutico en Espa単a. Objetivo. Evaluar el tratamiento de la espasticidad en Espa単a. Pacientes y metodos. Estudio epidemiologico, observacional, multicentrico y retrospectivo en el que participaron 49 servicios de rehabilitacion de hospitales publicos y privados. Resultados. Se incluyeron 235 pacientes, con espasticidad del miembro superior (MS) o inferior (MI), que realizaron una visita basal valida y al menos una visita de seguimiento. De los pacientes incluidos en el estudio, 148 (62,9%) tenian espasticidad postictus; 79 (33,6%), espasticidad del MI; 38 (16,1%), del MS; y 118 (50,3%), de ambos. En la visita basal, la escala modificada de Ashworth, la goniometria, la escala analogica visual para el dolor y la escala de Tardieu se habian realizado en 164 (69,8%), 99 (42,1%), 85 (36,2%) y 26 (11,1%) pacientes, respectivamente. Un 93,8% (intervalo de confianza al 95%: 81,4-97,6%) de los centros definio los objetivos del tratamiento de forma exacta, y un 52% de los objetivos fueron consensuados con el paciente. La toxina botulinica tipo A se administro a 186 (79,1%) pacientes; 49 (20,9%) se trataron con antiespasticos orales, y 93 (39,6%), con fisioterapia. Conclusiones. La mayoria de los pacientes incluidos presentaban espasticidad postictus. Ademas, la toxina botulinica tipo A era el tratamiento mas comunmente aplicado a los pacientes con espasticidad. Los resultados demuestran que el tratamiento de la espasticidad varia considerablemente entre los diferentes centros participantes en el estudio. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[An assessment of the management of spasticity in Spain: the 5E Study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
