<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27656928</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guillén-Pinto, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Turín, Christie Gloria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zegarra, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Alva, Pilar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivas, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ochoa, Theresa J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cam, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tori, Aldredo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda, María Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zea-Vera, Alonso</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castañeda, Anne</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to analyze the use of lumbar punctures (LP) in the evaluation of late-onset neonatal sepsis. It is recommended to perform an LP as part of the evaluation of late-onset sepsis. We used a cohort of 414 newborns with a birth weight &lt;2000g in three hospitals in Lima. A LP was performed in 45/214 (21.0%) of sepsis evaluations and in 13/48 (27.1%) of culture-proven sepsis. Meningitis was diagnosed in 8/214 (3.7%) of the episodes and 8/45 (17.5%) of the evaluations that included an LP. The duration of treatment of the sepsis episodes without a LP and the episodes with a negative LP was similar, and shorter than the episodes with a positive LP. The use of LP in the evaluation of late-onset sepsis is low and can result in undiagnosed and undertreated meningitis. The use of LP in the evaluation of neonatal sepsis must be encouraged in the neonatal units.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de la punción lumbar en la evaluación de sepsis neonatal tardía en recién nacidos de bajo peso.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of lumbar puncture in the evaluation of late-onset sepsis in low birth weight neonates].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
