<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27692603</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fontenla, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Fernández, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pedrote, Alonso</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES This report presents the findings of the 2015 Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry. METHODS For data collection, each center was allowed to choose freely between 2 systems: retrospective, requiring the completion of a standardized questionnaire, and prospective, involving reporting to a central database. RESULTS Data were collected from 82 centers. A total of 12 863 ablation procedures were performed, for a mean of 157±119 and a median of 138 procedures per center. The ablation target most frequently treated was cavotricuspid isthmus (n=2992 [23.2%]), followed by atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (n=2966 [23%]) and atrial fibrillation (n=2640 [20.5%]). There were fewer ablation procedures for atrial tachycardia, idiopathic ventricular tachycardia and accessory pathways, while those for ventricular tachycardia in ischemic cardiomyopathy remained steady. The overall success rate, excluding atrial fibrillation and ventricular tachycardia in cardiomyopathy, was 87.5%, the rate of major complications was 2%, and the mortality rate was 0.08%. CONCLUSIONS The 2015 registry is the first to show a slight reduction in the number of centers sending in their results and in the total number of ablation procedures performed. The most frequently treated substrate was the cavotricuspid isthmus. There was also a slight decrease in the success rate. The complications and mortality rates remained low.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Arritmia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arrhythmia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Registro</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Catheter ablation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electrofisiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electrophysiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ablación con catéter</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Registry</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry. 15th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Electrophysiology and Arrhythmias (2015).</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
