<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27716756</identifier>
<setSpec>1609-722X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zegarra Chang, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aliaga Ramos, Miluska</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Borda, Jenny</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo Paredes, Eduar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prochazka Zárate, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinoza-Ríos, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miraval Wong, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE We present a descriptive analysis of our cases of sphincterotomy followed by papillary large balloon dilation in a single session (ES-LBD) in the management of difficult to extract calculi, with the objective of assessing rates of therapeutic success and complications in local experience. MATERIAL AND METHODS ERCP procedures with ES-LBD performed for choledocholithiasis between January 2009 and December 2014 in patients older than 18 years and without preexistent sphincterotomy were selected from records of the Gastroenterology Service at Cayetano Heredia National Hospital. A descriptive analysis of therapeutic success and complications was performed. RESULTS 73 procedures in 73 patients were included (65.8% female, 34.2% male). Patient's average age was 59.4±19.8 years. Average diameter of calculi was 14.6±3.3mm. Average diameter of dilations was 14.6±2.27 mm. In 8 cases mechanical lithotripsy was performed. Complete calculi extraction was achieved in 56 procedures (76.7%). Complications occurred in 4 cases (5.5%). There were no deaths. CONCLUSION Our figures of therapeutic success and complications with ES-LBD for difficult to extract calculi are similar to those reported in literature. ES-LBD is an effective and safe technique for management of choledocholithiasis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esfinterotomía seguida de dilatación con balón de gran tamaño en el manejo de coledocolitiasis. Eficacia y seguridad en un hospital de Lima-Perú.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sphincterotomy followed by papillary large balloon in the management of cholecolithiasis. Therapeutic success and safety in a Lima-Peru hospital].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia del Peru : organo oficial de la Sociedad de Gastroenterologia del Peru</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
