<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2773694</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-5062</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pacheco Yáñez, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author reviews the census of outpatients in a Psychiatric Department of a General Hospital between 1969 and 1985, finding 12,241 cases. Following the first selection, 644 patients were found to be diagnosed with alcoholic disorder, at least, typified in the ICD-8 or ICD-9 of the O.M.S. Later, 31 cases were rejected due to insufficient information. A protocol of investigation was elaborated to apply retrospectively and establish a descriptive study. The epidemiological and clinical profile of the patients showed a 5% frequency of alcoholic disorder, a male patient (93.96%), an average age of 40, primary studies (65.74%), unskilled laborer (69.65%), starting to drink between the age of 15-19 (41.59%), wine drinker (65.74%), with an average intake of 244 g, without a diagnosis related to alcoholic psychoses (83%), discontinues the consultation after the first interview (38%), and continues drinking in the last consultation carried out, in 57.91% of the cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribucíon al estudio epidemiológico del alcoholismo en una cátedra y departamento de psiquiatría desde 1969 hasta 1985.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Epidemiologic study of alcoholism by a university section and a department of psychiatry from 1969 to 1985].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas luso-espanolas de neurologia, psiquiatria y ciencias afines</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
