<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27773365</identifier>
<setSpec>2444-054X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chavez-Montoya, Ramiro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Araujo-Ramírez, Osvaldo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Govea-Camacho, Luis Humberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo-López, Irma Yolanda</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Silent sinus or imploding antrum syndrome is a very rare condition, consisting of a usually asymptomatic spontaneous collapse of the sinus walls and floor of the orbit. It is associated with negative pressures, and when this occurs, it presents with manifestations such as enophthalmos, hypoglobus, and tilt flow orbital floor. As its incidence is very low, it is frequently missed as a diagnosis, and in fact there are currently fewer than 150 cases reported in the literature. CLINICAL CASES Three patients have been identified in our practice over a period of two years, with different symptoms that influenced the decision of the treatment modality, which were: watch and wait, endoscopic sinus surgery, or endoscopic sinus surgery plus orbitoplasty. CONCLUSIONS Despite being a rare entity, it stills catches the attention of the ENT, OMF surgery and Ophthalmologist. The diagnosis is mainly radiological, due to the late clinical manifestations and symptomatology. The treatment should be individualised and based on the symptoms and the individual decision of each patient, firstly by Functional Endoscopic sinus surgery, and once sinus permeability is restored, it may require augmentation surgery of the orbital floor, either with autologous bone implant, titanium or other material. It is important to be aware of this pathology, to know and to suspect it, avoiding misdiagnosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Atelectasia crónica maxilar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ostiomeatal complex</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complejo osteomeatal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Silent sinus syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hypoglobus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic maxillary atelectasis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enophthalmos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome de seno silente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enoftalmos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hipoglobus</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de implosión maxilar: tres casos y sus diferentes abordajes de tratamiento.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Imploding antrum syndrome: three cases with different management approaches].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia y cirujanos</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
