<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27795215</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González-Solórzano, Evaristo Víctor Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Ávalos, Miguel Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barnica-Alvarado, Raúl Humberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mancilla-Hernández, Eleazar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Asthma is a chronic disease that has increased over the past 2 decades. OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence of asthma and its symptoms in the city of Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico. METHODS A descriptive study of prevalence in public schools of the city of Cuernavaca, Morelos, at the preschool, elementary, and high school levels using the "Asthma diagnosis for epidemiological studies questionnaire." RESULTS 7947 surveys were obtained from students ages 3 to 15 years, funding a prevalence of asthma of 11.9%, 49% in boys and 51% in girls. As for the symptoms of asthma, the highest prevalence was cough that increases with cold weather (63%), however, in asthma patients this symptom only occurred in 17%; chest tightness had the lowest prevalence of symptoms (10%); however, in asthma patients it was 49%. CONCLUSIONS The asthma diagnosis for epidemiological studies questionnaire found an average asthma prevalence of 11.9% in preschool, elementary, and high school students, slightly below that diagnosed in other cities in central Mexico. The prevalence of asthma symptoms was higher than the diagnosis of asthma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Epidemiological studies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevalence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Symptoms</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asthma</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de asma y sus síntomas en población escolar de Cuernavaca, Morelos, México.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: El asma es una enfermedad crónica que se ha incrementado en las 2 últimas décadas. Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de asma y sus síntomas en la ciudad de Cuernavaca, Morelos, México. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo de prevalencia en escuelas oficiales de la ciudad de Cuernavaca, Morelos, de nivel preescolar, primaria y secundaria, mediante el “Cuestionario diagnóstico de asma para estudios epidemiológicos”. Resultados: Se obtuvieron 7947 encuestas en escolares de 3 a 15 años, encontrándose una prevalencia de asma de 11.9%, 49% en niños y 51 % en niñas. En cuanto a los síntomas de asma, la mayor prevalencia la obtuvo la tos que aumenta con el frío (63%), sin embargo, en los pacientes con asma este síntoma solo se presentó en 17%; la opresión torácica tuvo la prevalencia más baja entre los síntomas (10%), sin embargo, en pacientes con asma fue de 49%. Conclusiones: Con el cuestionario diagnóstico de asma para estudios epidemiológicos se encontró una prevalencia promedio de asma de 11.9% en preescolares, escolares y alumnos de secundaria, discretamente inferior a la diagnosticada en otras ciudades del centro de México. La prevalencia de los síntomas de asma resultó más elevada que la del diagnóstico de asma. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of asthma and its symptoms in schoolchildren from Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
