<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2781180</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8376</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rogelio Pérez-Padilla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Jouanen, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viniegra, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luis Jiménez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Iatrogenesis, understood here as an unfavourable effect to the health of patients provoked by the medical institution, has risen little interest in the researchers of the health area in spite of its growing presence. The present study had the aim of exploring the iatrogenic behavior of 659 recently graduated physicians by a questionnaire composed by clinical cases which described diagnostic and/or therapeutic situations that required the making of decisions. The questionnaire consisted of 600 general medical knowledge questions of which 112 explored commission of iatrogenic behavior. The group showed a iatrogenicity index of 39.5% ranging between 15.2% and 74.1%. When this iatrogenicity index was compared to that of global medical knowledge (600 questions) no correlation was found. It is concluded that the "iatrogenicity" index of this group is high and lacks correlation with the global medical knowledge. This suggests that the individualized and careful use of the diagnostic and therapeutic resources suitable for specific situations in patients does not receive sufficient emphasis during the teaching-learning process nor does it play a prominent role within the priorities of knowledge that are learned in the school of medicine. The need to deepen our understanding of the iatrogenic behavior of the physicians at different levels of their professional training is emphasized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1989 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias iatrogénicas como indicador de competencia clínica en los cursos de especialización en medicina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Iatrogenic trends as indicator of clinical competence in courses of specialization in medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de investigacion clinica; organo del Hospital de Enfermedades de la Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
