<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27819786</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Kershenovich-Gersson, Janisse</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galnares-Olalde, Javier Andrés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meraz-Ávila, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benardete-Harari, Denise N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olaya-Guzmán, Emilio José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of malignant tumors during pregnancy complicates the management of both tumor and pregnancy, since any diagnostic or therapeutic intervention could imply risks that may bring on detrimental effects to fetus or mother. The risks involved in exposing a fetus to cytotoxic therapy are associated to gestational age and the time of in utero exposure to that therapy. Cancer treatment has two different objectives: local control by surgery and radiotherapy, and one that seeks to eradicate systemic disease through chemotherapy, immunotherapy, hormone therapy, or targeted therapies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pregnancy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Teratogenesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chemotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de quimioterapia durante el embarazo.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La presencia de tumores malignos durante la gestación complica tanto el manejo como el propio embarazo, ya que cualquier intervención diagnóstica o terapéutica puede conllevar riesgos que puedan generar efectos nocivos para la madre o para el feto. Los riesgos que tiene un feto sometido a la administración de la terapia citotóxica se correlacionan directamente con la edad gestacional y con el tiempo de la exposición intrauterina a la misma. El tratamiento antineoplásico busca dos objetivos principales; el primero es el control local por medio de cirugía complementada con radioterapia; el segundo busca erradicar la enfermedad sistémica a través de quimioterapia, inmunoterapia, hormonoterapia o terapias blanco. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of chemotherapy during pregnancy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
