<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27819782</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garibay, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Major depression is a public health problem that threatens to become the second leading cause of disability in the world. In this study we show the results obtained once we applied a psychodynamic psychotherapeutic and long-term process in patients with major depressive disorder, attending a public health institution (PHI). METHODS From a list of female volunteers, we randomly selected 30 patients who met the diagnostic criteria of major depression. They were divided into 5 groups, with 6 members each. Due to the high percentage of early desertions, we had to select from the very same list other 28 depressed women. In this framework there was not a full-time psychotherapist organizing and directing the psychotherapeutic process; the patients themselves were the ones who assumed such functions. RESULTS From the group of 58 patients, 26 completed the program scheduled. From this subgroup, 20 were responders and the rest, the other 6, non-responders. After the end of the psychotherapeutic process, the latter kept ingesting psychotropic drugs. CONCLUSION If we correct the mistakes made in this first opportunity and we implement new strategies, the psychotherapeutic process can be transformed into a more institutional tool. Psychotherapy directed only to the cases difficult to solve is significantly effective, safe, cheap, and it may achieve a wide coverage.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Psychodynamic psychotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Depressive disorder</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoterapia dinámica, prolongada, a nivel Institucional, para trastornos depresivos de difícil solución (irreductibles).</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la depresión mayor es un problema de salud pública que amenaza con convertirse en la segunda causa de incapacidad en el mundo. En este estudio se buscó presentar los resultados obtenidos al aplicar un procedimiento psicoterapéutico psicodinámico y prolongado en pacientes con trastorno depresivo mayor, atendidas en una institución pública de salud (IPS). Métodos: de una lista de candidatas voluntarias, en forma aleatoria se seleccionaron 30 pacientes con depresión mayor. Fueron distribuidas en cinco grupos (seis por grupo). Debido al alto porcentaje de deserciones tempranas, de la misma lista se tuvieron que incluir en los cinco grupos otras 28 deprimidas. En este encuadre no hubo un psicoterapeuta fijo que dirigiera el procedimiento psicoterapéutico; fueron las propias pacientes quienes asumieron tales funciones. Resultados: del grupo de 58 pacientes, completaron el ciclo programado 26. De este subgrupo, 20 fueron respondientes y las otras 6 no respondientes. Después de terminado el proceso, estas continuaron ingiriendo psicofármacos. Conclusiones: si se corrigen los errores de esta primera exploración y se implementan nuevas estrategias, el procedimiento psicoterapéutico puede transformarse en una herramienta más institucional. La psicoterapia dirigida exclusivamente a los casos irreductibles tiene una eficacia significativa, además de que es segura, barata y puede alcanzar una amplia cobertura. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dynamic, long-term, and institutional psychotherapy to treat persistent depressive disorders].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
