<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27838353</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moreno Algarra, María Concepción</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Romero, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Tamayo, Tomás</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinosa Fernández, María Gracia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salguero García, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Proper nutrition is one of the primary objectives in the management of preterm infants. However, lack of evidence on the best strategy to achieve this objective has led to a great variability in feeding practices. This variability may be related to the differences in the incidence of complications, such as necrotising enterocolitis (NEC). OBJECTIVE The aim of this study is to assess the variability in clinical practice regarding enteral feeding in SEN-1500 Spanish network. METHOD An observational study was conducted using a questionnaire sent out in 2013 requesting information about feeding very low birth weight (VLBW) neonates (bank milk, start time, trophic feeding, increases, fortifiers and probiotics). RESULTS Responses were received from 60 of the 98 hospitals. The response rate was higher in centres with more than 50VLBW/year (30/31). Just over two-thirds (67%) have feeding protocols, and 52% refer to variability within their unit. A milk bank is available in 25% of the units. First feeding occurs fairly evenly throughout first 48hours, although it is delayed in lower gestational ages, even when there is no haemodynamic failure. In addition to hemodynamic instability there are other situations when the start is delayed (absence of breast milk, CIR, altered umbilical flow, asphyxia), while it is rarely delayed by absence of meconium or maintain an umbilical catheter.Half of those under 25 weeks begin directly with progressive increases instead of trophic feeding. Increases rarely reach 30ml/kg/day. Almost all use fortification and vitamins. There was a significant use of probiotics at the time of the survey. CONCLUSIONS There is great variability in enteral nutrition policies in VLBW in Spain. Although some differences are justified by the lack of evidence, there are other interventions that have proven to be effective, such as evidence-based protocols or access to donor milk. Implementation in all the units could reduce the incidence of NEC and improve the nutritional status.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Premature</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enteral nutrition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enterocolitis necrosante</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevención</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trophic feeding</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recién nacido de muy bajo peso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prevention</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Very low birth weight infant</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nutrición enteral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Variaciones en la práctica clínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nutrición enteral trófica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Necrotising enterocolitis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prematuro</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Variations in clinical practice</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en las prácticas sobre alimentación enteral del prematuro entre hospitales españoles de la red SEN-1500.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Variability in enteral feeding practices of preterm infants among hospitals in the SEN1500 Spanish neonatal network].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
