<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27837795</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domingo-Salvany, Antonia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez-Berjón, M Felicitas</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borrell, Carme</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espelt, Albert</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monge, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Continente, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Cantero, M Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perez, Glòria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Villa, Tania</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Public health surveillance is the systematic and continuous collection, analysis, dissemination and interpretation of health-related data for planning, implementation and evaluation of public health initiatives. Apart from the health system, social determinants of health include the circumstances in which people are born, grow up, live, work and age, and they go a long way to explaining health inequalities. A surveillance system of the social determinants of health requires a comprehensive and social overview of health. This paper analyses the importance of monitoring social determinants of health and health inequalities, and describes some relevant aspects concerning the implementation of surveillance during the data collection, compilation and analysis phases, as well as dissemination of information and evaluation of the surveillance system. It is important to have indicators from sources designed for this purpose, such as continuous records or periodic surveys, explicitly describing its limitations and strengths. The results should be published periodically in a communicative format that both enhances the public's ability to understand the problems that affect them, whilst at the same time empowering the population, with the ultimate goal of guiding health-related initiatives at different levels of intervention.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Social determinants of health</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indicadores del estado de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vigilancia en salud pública</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fuentes de información</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Comunicación en salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public health surveillance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Determinantes sociales de la salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health status indicators</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sistemas de información geográfica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Data sources</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health communication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Geographic information systems</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vigilancia de los determinantes sociales de la salud.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Monitoring social determinants of health].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
