<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27855047</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ojeda-Reyes, Ángel Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Figueroa, María Socorro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vallecillo-Velázquez, Hernán</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barragán-Hervella, Rodolfo Gregorio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alvarado-Ortega, Iván</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montiel-Jarquín, Álvaro José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Functional and radiographic evaluation at midshaft clavicle fractures is better with surgical than conservative management. The aim of this paper is to describe the functional and radiological evaluation of patients with midshaft clavicle fracture surgery at the Hospital de Traumatología y Ortopedia of the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. METHODS Descriptive studies, conducted during the period June 2014 to June 2015, patients undergoing surgical treatment for midshaft clavicle fracture were included. Constant-Murley and Montoya Scales were used to evaluate the functionality and radiological consolidation 6 months after the treatment. RESULTS There were 90 patients, average age was 33.63 years, 78.9% were men, left side affected in 53.3% patients. At 6 months after surgery, functional results were excellent in 87.8% of patients, in 91% there was disappearance of fracture line regardless callus. The group of patients aged 18 and 40 years present better functional and radiographic results compared to the other groups (p &lt;0.05). CONCLUSIONS The management of patients with diaphyseal clavicle fracture should be surgical, ages between 18 to 40 years and between 61 to 76 years have better functional outcomes with greater consolidation of fracture line regardless of the callus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Bony callus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bones of upper extremity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clavicle</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bone fractures</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación funcional y radiológica de pacientes con fractura diafisiaria de clavícula manejados quirúrgicamente.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: el manejo quirúrgico de las fracturas diafisiarias de clavícula da buenos resultados funcionales y una consolidación radiológica adecuada. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la evaluación funcional y radiológica de los pacientes con fractura diafisiaria de clavícula operados en el Hospital de Traumatología y Ortopedia del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. Métodos: estudio descriptivo, realizado durante el período de julio 2014 a junio 2015, en el que se incluyeron pacientes sometidos a tratamiento quirúrgico por fractura diafisiaria de clavícula. Se aplicaron las escalas Constant-Murley y Montoya para evaluar la funcionalidad y la consolidación radiológica a los 6 meses. Resultados: fueron 90 pacientes, con edad promedio de 33.63 años, 78.9% fueron hombres, el lado izquierdo estuvo afectado en el 53.3% de los pacientes. A los 6 meses de operados, los resultados funcionales fueron excelentes en el 87.8% de los pacientes, en el 91% hubo desaparición del trazo fracturarlo, independientemente del callo óseo. El grupo de pacientes de edades entre 18 y 40 años presentan mejores resultados funcionales y radiográficos que los otros grupos de edades (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusiones: el manejo quirúrgico de los pacientes con fractura diafisiaria de clavícula ofrece buenos resultados funcionales y consolidación radiográfica. Las edades entre 18 a 40 años y entre 61 a 76 años tienen mejores resultados funcionales con una mayor consolidación del trazo fracturario independientemente del callo óseo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Functional and radiological evaluation of patients with midshaft clavicle fracture surgically treated].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
