<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27869433</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yagmurlu, Aydin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ates, Ufuk</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kucuk, Gonul</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gollu, Gulnur</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">La rotura traqueal tras una contusión es rara, aunque potencialmente mortal. En general, se recomienda el tratamiento quirúrgico para la rotura traqueal, aunque también se ha informado recientemente el abordaje conservador en los pacientes con signos vitales y parámetros respiratorios estables. El objetivo de este estudio es informar sobre un caso de rotura traqueal tras una contusión en el cuello producto de un accidente de bicicleta que se trató de manera conservadora.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Tracheal disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neck injuries</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Wounds</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nonpenetrating</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Dec 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje conservador de una rotura traqueal en un niño tras una contusión.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Tracheal rupture following blunt trauma is rare but is potentially life threatening. Usually surgical treatment is suggested for tracheal rupture however recently conservative management has also been reported for patients with stable vital signs and stable ventilatory state. The aim of this study is to report a case with tracheal rupture following a blunt trauma to the neck after a bicycle accident that was managed conservatively. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Conservative management of tracheal rupture in a child after blunt trauma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
