<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27869426</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Abay, Elif</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oztan, Mustafa O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ilhan, Ozkan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Koyluoglu, Gokhan</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Umbilical venous catheterization has become a widely accepted intravenous route for premature babies. These catheters allow administration of parenteral nutrition and medication and facilitate blood sampling. Besides these benefits, they also have significant potential complications like portal vein thrombosis, infection, vascular or hepatic injury, arrhythmia and sepsis. One of the rare but important complication is extravasation of the fluids due to misplacement of the catheter. The typical symptoms of this condition are sudden deterioration, hepatic enlargement, hematocrit drop, hypotension and abdominal distension. We herein present a premature newborn with unusual acute abdomen findings suggesting a surgical pathology after the extravasation of total parenteral nutrition into the abdomen.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Newborn</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Catheterization</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Extravasation of parenteral nutrition</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Umbilical veins</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Dec 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicación del catéter venoso umbilical que se presentó como abdomen agudo: a propósito de un caso.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El cateterismo venoso umbilical se ha convertido en una vía intravenosa ampliamente aceptada para los recién nacidos prematuros. Estos tipos de sondas permiten la alimentación parenteral y la administración de medicamentos y facilitan la obtención de muestras de sangre. Además de estos beneficios, también conllevan complicaciones significativas, tales como trombosis de la vena porta, infección, lesión hepática o vascular, arritmia y septicemia. Una complicación rara, aunque importante, es la extravasación de líquido debido a la mala colocación del catéter. Los síntomas típicos de esta afección incluyen deterioro súbito, hepatomegalia, descenso brusco del hematocrito, hipotensión y distensión abdominal. En este artículo presentamos el caso de una recién nacida prematura con signos inusuales de abdomen agudo, indicativos de una patología quirúrgica luego de la extravasación de la nutrición parenteral total hacia el abdomen. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An umbilical venous catheter complication presented as acute abdomen: case report.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
