<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27869391</identifier>
<setSpec>0120-4157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cochero, Suljey</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bejarano, Eduar Elías</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaramillo, María Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Atencia, María Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caldera, Sandy Milena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, María De Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The main strategy for the control of Aedes aegypti, vector of dengue, chikungunya and Zika viruses, is based on the use of insecticides to reduce its populations. However, their use has led to insect resistance to these chemicals. Objective: To determine the presence of the F1534C mutation associated with cross-resistance to DDT and pyrethroids in A. aegypti in Sincelejo, Colombia. Materials and methods: We studied nine specimens of A. aegypti that showed resistance to lambdacyhalothrin in bioassays developed by the Secretaría de Salud de Sucre. We used a semi-nested PCR as previously described by Harris, et al., to amplify exon 31 of the para gene of the voltage-dependent sodium channel of A. aegypti. We sequenced, edited, and analyzed PCR products with the MEGA 5 software. Results: We detected the wild and mutant alleles of exon 31 in all of the nine mosquitoes tested, and observed the substitution of thymine for guanine in the nucleotide sequence of the mutant allele, producing a change to UGC in the UUC codon, which led to the replacement of phenylalanine by cysteine in residue 1534 of the protein. Conclusion: The nine mosquitoes analyzed presented a heterozygote genotype for the F1534C mutation, whose phenotypic effect is knockdown resistance (kdr) to DDT and pyrethroids.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Colombia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>mutation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>mosquito control</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>insecticide resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aedes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>genotype</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Sep 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[First report of the F1534C mutation associated with cross-resistance to DDT and pyrethroids in Aedes aegypti from Colombia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Biomedica : revista del Instituto Nacional de Salud</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
