<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27911069</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Domínguez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Maldonado, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Forner-Cordero, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domènech, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serrano, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Lymphatic disease is a rarely cause of some very unspecific genitourinary manifestations, assuming a diagnostic challenge in most cases. The aim of this paper is to warn about the possible etiology of these urological lymphatic presentations and discuss its management. METHODS Retrospective review of clinical data in pediatric patients with urological pathology of lymphatic origin between 2008-2014. Three patients, two boys and a girl, were included. The complaints were: redundant prepuce, inguinal scrotal tumor and urinary incontinence. Clinical, diagnosis and treatment protocol is described. RESULTS The first case is a male with genital lymphedema presented at birth as a redundant prepuce and the subsequent emergence of lower limb lymphedema, treated with compression bandages. The second case, a groin lymphangioma which debuted as a sudden painless inguinal tumor simulating a cord cyst, it was sclerosed and treated with OK- 432. Finally, a preteen who consulted for involuntary leakage of urine, genital lymphedema likely primary cause (lymphodisplasia) or malformation was diagnosed, which improved with two Lipiodol® embolization. CONCLUSIONS Genitourinary manifestations can be the debut of more complex lymphatic pathology, so it is necessary to consider this cause, uncommon and nonspecific. Its management must be conservative initially by compression bandages, OK-432 or embolization with Lipiodol®.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Lymphodysplasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lymphedema</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lymphangioma</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Jan 25 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología urológica de origen linfático.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La patología linfática es infrecuente como causa de manifestaciones genitourinarias inespecíficas, suponiendo un reto diagnóstico en la mayoría de los casos. El objetivo de este trabajo es advertir sobre la posible etiología linfática de estas presentaciones urológicas y discutir su manejo. 
             Revisión retrospectiva de los datos clínicos de los pacientes pediátricos con patología urológica de origen linfático entre el año 2008-2014. Se incluyeron 3 pacientes, dos niños y una niña. Todos ellos se evaluaron para obtener un diagnóstico fiable. Los motivos de consulta fueron: prepucio redundante, tumoración inguino-escrotal e incontinencia urinaria. Se describe la clínica, el protocolo diagnóstico y el tratamiento de los mismos. 
             El primer caso se trata de un lactante varón con un linfedema genital que presentaba un prepucio redundante congénito y la aparición posterior de linfedema en el miembro inferior que es tratado con vendajes compresivos. El siguiente, un linfangioma inguinal que debutó con una tumoración inguinal indolora de aparición súbita simulando un quiste de cordón y tratado mediante esclerosis con OK-432. Por último, una preadolescente que consultó por escapes involuntarios de orina diagnosticada de linfedema genital de probable causa primaria (linfodisplasia) o malformativa que mejoró con dos embolizaciones de Lipiodol®. 
             Las manifestaciones genitourinarias pueden ser el debut de una patología linfática más compleja, por ello es necesario tener presente esta etiología infrecuente e inespecífica. Su manejo inicialmente debe ser conservador, mediante vendajes compresivos, OK-432 o embolización con Lipiodol®. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Urological pathology of lymphatic origin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
