<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>27916194</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero Simó, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santamaría Olabarrieta, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sancho-Muriel, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escoll Rufino, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Bañeres, Manolo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos Rodriguez, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frasson, Matteo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hervás, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flor-Lorente, Blas</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Granero, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viñas Martinez, José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Lately there has been an increasing interest in identifying quality standards in different pathologies, among them colon cancer due to its great prevalence. The main goal of this study is to define the quality standards of colon cancer surgery based on a large prospective national study dataset. METHODS Data from the prospective national study ANACO were used. This study included a consecutive series of patients operated on for colon cancer in 52 Spanish hospitals (2011-2012). Centers with less than 30 patients were excluded. The present analysis finally included 42 centers (2975 patients). Based on the results obtained in 4main indicators from each hospital (anastomotic leak, lymph-nodes found in the specimen, mortality and length of stay), a nomogram that allows the evaluation of the performance of each center was designed. Standard results for further 5 intraoperative and 5 postoperative quality indicators were also reported. RESULTS Median of anastomotic leak and mortality rate was 8.5% (25th-75th percentiles 6.1%-12.4%) and 2.5% (25th-75th percentiles 0.6%-4.7%), respectively. Median number of nodes found in the surgical specimen was 15,1 (25th-75th percentiles 18-14 nodes). Median length of postoperative stay was 7.7 days (25th-75th percentiles 6.9-9.2 days). Based on these data, a nomogram for hospital audit was created. CONCLUSIONS Standard surgical results after colon cancer surgery were defined, creating a tool for auto-evaluation and allowing each center to identify areas for improvement in the surgical treatment of colon cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Reference standards</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Evaluación de resultados</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colon surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neoplasias de colon</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Quality indicators</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Indicadores de calidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colonic neoplasms</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estándares de referencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía de colon</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Outcome assessment</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados quirúrgicos estándar tras resección oncológica de colon. Creación de un nomograma para la autoevaluación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Standard outcome indicators after colon cancer resection. Creation of a nomogram for autoevaluation.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
