<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28000907</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Leon-Estrada, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garcia-Garcia, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roldan-Tapia, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The cognitive reserve theory may contribute to explain cognitive performance differences among individuals with similar cognitive decline and among healthy ones. However, more psychometric analysis are needed to guarantee the usage of tests for assessing cognitive reserve. AIMS To study validity evidences in relation to the structure of the Cognitive Reserve Scale (CRS) and to create reference norms to interpret the scores. SUBJECTS AND METHODS A total of 172 participants completed the scale and they were classified into two age groups: aged 36-64 years (n = 110) and 65-88 years (n = 62). RESULTS The exploratory factor analysis using ESEM revealed that the data fitted the proposed model. Overall, the discriminative indices were acceptable (between 0.21 and 0.50) and congruence was observed in the periods of young adulthood, adulthood and late adulthood, in both age group. Besides, the index of reliability (Cronbach's alpha: 0.80) and the typical mean error test (mean: 51.40 ± 11.11) showed adequate values for this type of instrument. CONCLUSION The CRS seemed to be set under the hypothetical theoretical model, and the scores might be interpreted by the norms showed. This study provided guarantees for the usage of the CRS in research.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jan 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escala de reserva cognitiva: ajuste del modelo teorico y baremacion.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Escala de reserva cognitiva: ajuste del modelo teorico y baremacion. 
             Introduccion. La teoria de la reserva cognitiva contribuiria a explicar las diferencias en el rendimiento intelectual en sujetos con deterioro cognitivo similar y en sujetos sanos. Sin embargo, son necesarios mas datos psicometricos que garanticen el uso de los instrumentos de medicion de reserva cognitiva. Objetivo. Aportar evidencias de validez respecto a la estructura interna de la escala de reserva cognitiva (ERC) y establecer un baremo de referencia para la interpretacion de sus puntuaciones. Sujetos y metodos. Un total de 172 sujetos completaron la ERC y fueron distribuidos en dos grupos en funcion de la edad: 36-64 años (n = 110) y 65-88 años (n = 62). Resultados. El analisis factorial mediante modelos de ecuaciones estructurales exploratorios indico un moderado ajuste de los datos al modelo propuesto. En general, los indices de discriminacion fueron correctos (entre 0,21 y 0,50), y se registro congruencia entre los items a lo largo de los periodos de juventud, adultez y madurez para ambos grupos de edad. Se observaron valores adecuados del indice de fiabilidad (alfa de Cronbach: 0,80) y de los errores tipicos de medida (media: 51,40 ± 11,11). Conclusiones. La ERC se enmarcaria dentro del modelo teorico hipotetizado y las puntuaciones podrian interpretarse mediante el baremo ofrecido, lo que avalaria su empleo en la investigacion en este campo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cognitive Reserve Scale: testing the theoretical model and norms].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
