<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28001202</identifier>
<setSpec>1680-5348</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Triunfo, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Harris, Jeffrey</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balsa, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 2005, shortly after ratifying the Framework Convention on Tobacco Control (FCTC), Uruguay began an ambitious tobacco control campaign that brought the country to the global forefront in the fight against smoking. The wide range of measures implemented in a relatively short period and the rigorousness with which policies were implemented and enforced have few precedents, even in the most developed countries. This paper presents a synthesis and update of several papers by the authors that evaluate different aspects of the campaign ten years following ratification of the FCTC. In particular, these research studies highlight the campaign's aggregate impact on the drop in prevalence of current tobacco consumption in adult and youth populations, and on decisions by pregnant women to quit smoking (1, 2), as well as the relative impact of tax policies in relation to non-price tobacco control measures. The analyses are based on observational studies (at the population or individual level) that use external (Argentina and Chile) and internal (nonsmokers) control groups. Pending challenges in the design of antismoking policies are also discussed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la campaña antitabaco en Uruguay: balance de diez años y desafíos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of Uruguay's antismoking campaign: progress and challenges at ten years].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista panamericana de salud publica = Pan American journal of public health</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
