<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28041688</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Parvaiz, Amjad</dc:author>
<dc:author>Khan, Jim</dc:author>
<dc:author>O'Leary, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conti, John</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parés, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flashman, Karen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Senapati, Asha</dc:author>
<dc:author>Shamali, Awad</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The aim of our study was to analyse the short-term outcomes of laparoscopic surgery for a no medical responding ileocolic Cohn's disease in a single centre according to the presence of obesity. METHODS A cross-sectional study was performed including all consecutive patients who underwent laparoscopic resection for ileocecal Crohn's disease from November 2006 to November 2015. Patients were divided according to body mass index ≥ 30 kg/m2 in order to study influence of obesity in the short-term outcomes. The following variables were studied: characteristics of patients, surgical technique and postoperative results (complications, reintervention, readmission and mortality) during first 30 postoperative days. RESULTS A total of 100 patients were included (42 males) with a mean age of 39.7±15.2 years (range 18-83). The overall complication rate was 20% and only 3 patients had an anastomotic leak. Seven patients needed reoperation in the first 30 days postop (7%). The median postoperative length of hospitalization was 5.0 days. Operative time was significantly longer in patients with obesity (130 vs. 165minutes, P=.007) but there were no significant differences among the postoperative results in patients with and without obesity. CONCLUSIONS This study confirmed that laparoscopic approach for ileocecal Cohn's disease is a safety and feasible technique in patients with obesity. In this last group of patients we only have to expect a longer operative time.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad de Crohn</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resultados</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Results</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Crohn's disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía laparoscópica en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Crohn del área ileocecal: impacto de la obesidad en los resultados postoperatorios inmediatos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic surgical treatment of ileocecal Crohn's disease: Impact of obesity on short term results.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
