<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28089216</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carrillo-Alduenda, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villareal-Velarde, Héctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Padilla, Rogelio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz-Torrico, Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caminero-Luna, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>D'Ambrosio, Lia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Migliori, Giovanni Battista</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores-Vergara, Héctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Mendoza, Dina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Salazar-Lezama, Miguel Ángel</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Sancho, Cecilia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Centis, Rosella</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Cruz, Alfredo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Diabetes mellitus (DM), a very common disease in Mexico, is a well-known risk factor for tuberculosis (TB). However, it is not known by which extent DM predisposes to adverse events (AE) to anti-TB drugs and/or to worse outcomes in patients with multidrug-resistant (MDR-TB) and extensively drug-resistant TB (XDR-TB). The main objective of this study was to describe the outcomes of TB treatment, the impact of DM and the prevalence of AE in a cohort of patients with MDR-/XDR pulmonary TB treated at the national TB referral centre in Mexico City. RESULTS Ninety patients were enrolled between 2010 and 2015: 73 with MDR-TB (81.1%), 11 with pre-XDR-TB (12.2%) and 6 (6.7%) with XDR-TB, including 49 (54.4%) with DM, and 3 with Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) co-infection (3.3%). In 98% of patients, diagnosis was made by culture and drug susceptibility testing, while in a single case the diagnosis was made by a molecular test. The presence of DM was associated with an increased risk of serious drug-related AEs, such as nephrotoxicity (Odds Ratio [OR]=6.5; 95% Confidence Interval [95% CI]: 1.9-21.8) and hypothyroidism (OR=8.8; 95% CI: 1.8-54.2), but not for a worse outcome. CONCLUSIONS Our data suggest that DM does not impact second-line TB treatment outcomes, but patients with DM have a higher risk of developing serious AEs to drug-resistant TB treatment, such as nephrotoxicity and hypothyroidism.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adverse events</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis multirresistente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mexico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>México</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reacciones adversas</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La diabetes se asocia con reacciones adversas graves en la tuberculosis multirresistente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diabetes is Associated with Severe Adverse Events in Multidrug-Resistant Tuberculosis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
