<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28081896</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1275</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Comín, Eva</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cavero, Myriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aragonès, Enric</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Víctor</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palao, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite its clinical relevance and its importance as a public health problem, there are major gaps in the management of depression. Evidence-based clinical guidelines are useful to improve processes and clinical outcomes. In order to make their implementation easier these guidelines have been transformed into computerised clinical decision support systems. In this article, a description is presented on the basics and characteristics of a new computerised clinical guideline for the management of major depression, developed in the public health system in Catalonia. This tool helps the clinician to establish reliable and accurate diagnoses of depression, to choose the best treatment a priori according to the disease and the patient characteristics. It also emphasises the importance of systematic monitoring to assess the clinical course, and to adjust therapeutic interventions to the patient's needs at all times.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Computer-assisted decision making</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención primaria de salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Toma de decisiones asistida por ordenador</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Historia clínica electrónica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primary health care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Clinical practice guideline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trastorno depresivo mayor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electronic clinical record</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Guía de práctica clínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Major depressive disorder</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jun - Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un sistema informatizado de apoyo a las decisiones clínicas para el manejo de la depresión en atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A computerised clinical decision-support system for the management of depression in Primary Care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
