<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28092243</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Sánchez, Sandra Fabiola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guzmán-Pantoja, Jaime Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Galindo, María Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Cerebral palsy (PCI) is the leading cause of disability in children. Botulinum toxin type A (TBA) is a treatment to improve the function and pattern in the gait, although with a few studies that quantify the improvement. METHODS Quasi-experimental study was conducted from May 2010 to September 2011, in Integrated Rehabilitation Center, in 36 patients with spastic PCI. Was evaluated: functionality of travel by the scale of Koman, speed of the gait with tone scale of Ashworth and arches of passive mobility, were applied TBA and was sent to 10 sessions of physical therapy, with measurements taken before, the 1st and 4th month. RESULTS 30 Patients completed the study, between the ages of 2 and 12 years, the majority had improvement in the functionality of the gear, tone, dorsiflexion and abduction of ankles to the motion, which was maintained at 4 months. CONCLUSIONS Botulinum toxin is an effective treatment to increase the arches of mobility and functionality of the gait of patients with hemiparesis and spastic paraparesis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cerebral palsy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Central nervous system diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Type A botulinum toxins</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neurologic gait disorders</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxina botulínica A y terapia física, en la marcha en parálisis cerebral.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: La parálisis cerebral (PCI) es la principal causa de discapacidad en la infancia. La toxina botulínica tipo A (TBA) es un tratamiento para mejorar la función y patrón en la marcha, aunque con pocos estudios que cuantifiquen la mejoría. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio cuasiexperimental, de mayo de 2010 a septiembre de 2011, en un centro de rehabilitación integral, participaron 36 pacientes con PCI espástica. Se evaluó: funcionalidad de la marcha por la escala de Koman, velocidad de desplazamiento de la marcha, tono con escala de Ashworth y arcos de movilidad pasivas. Se les aplicó TBA y se les envió a 10 sesiones de terapia física, con mediciones antes, al mes 1 y 4. Resultados: 30 pacientes terminaron el estudio, con edades entre 2 y 12 años, la mayoría tuvieron mejoría en la funcionalidad de la marcha, tono, dorsiflexión y abducción de tobillos al mes, que se mantuvo a los 4 meses. Conclusiones: La toxina botulínica es un tratamiento eficaz para aumentar los arcos de movilidad y la funcionalidad de la marcha en los pacientes con hemiparesia y paraparesia espástica. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Botulinum toxin A and physical therapy in gait in cerebral palsy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
