<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28092250</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Robles-San Román, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Borjón, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Roldán, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aldrete-Velasco, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meza-Reyes, Gilberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espinosa-Morales, Rolando</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the modern world, among the different clinical presentations of osteoarthritis, gonarthrosis and coxarthrosis exhibit the highest prevalence. In this paper, the characteristics of osteoarthritis and the different scales of assessment and classification of this pathology are exposed, to provide an exhibition of current evidence generated around diagnostic algorithms and treatment of osteoarthritis, with emphasis set out in the knee and hip, as these are the most frequent; a rational procedure for monitoring patients with osteoarthritis based on characteristic symptoms and the severity of the condition is also set. Finally, reference is made to the therapeutic benefits of the recent introduction of viscosupplementation with Hylan GF-20.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Orthopedic procedures</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hip osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Osteoarthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Viscosupplementation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteoartrosis: implementación de los algoritmos de diagnóstico y terapéutico vigentes.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             En el mundo moderno, de entre las distintas presentaciones clínicas de la osteoartrosis, la gonartrosis y la coxartrosis son las que exhiben las mayores prevalencias. En el presente artículo se enuncian los rasgos característicos de la osteoartrosis y las diferentes escalas de evaluación y clasificación de esta patología, para a continuación ofrecer una exposición de la evidencia actual generada en torno a los algoritmos de diagnóstico y terapéuticos de la osteoartrosis, con énfasis en la de rodilla y la de cadera por ser estas las de mayor frecuencia; también se establece un procedimiento racional para el seguimiento del paciente con osteoartrosis en función de la sintomatología característica y el grado de severidad del padecimiento. Finalmente, se alude a los beneficios terapéuticos de la reciente introducción de la viscosuplementación mediante Hilano GF-20. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Osteoarthrosis: implementation of current diagnostic and therapeutic algorithms].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
