<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28128803</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Casa-Medina, Guillermo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Sancho, Cecilia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olmedo-Torres, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Briseño, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Cruz, Herminia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Plata, Rosario</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Periodontal disease is a chronic inflammatory gingival process that has been associated with the severity of respiratory diseases. In Mexico a prevalence of 78% was found in population with social security and &gt; 60 years old. The aim of this study is to establish the association between periodontal disease and respiratory diseases according to the inpatient days. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study was conducted from January to December 2011. We included hospitalized patients, ≥ 18 years of age, without sedation or intubated. A dentist classified patients into two groups according to the severity of the periodontal disease: mild-to-moderate and severe. We estimated medians of inpatient days by disease and severity. Negative binomial models were adjusted to estimate incidence rate ratios and predicted inpatient days. RESULTS 3,059 patients were enrolled. The median of observed and predicted inpatient days was higher in the group of severe periodontal disease (p &lt; 0.05). Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, tuberculosis, and influenza had the highest incidence rates ratios of periodontal disease (p &lt; 0.05). CONCLUSIONS The severity of periodontal disease is positively -associated with inpatient days of patients with respiratory diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Días de estancia hospitalaria (DEH) en pacientes con enfermedades respiratorias (ER) y enfermedad periodontal (EP).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inpatients days in patients with respiratory diseases and periodontal disease].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
