<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28128807</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Álvarez-Bastidas, Lucía</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sabag-Ruiz, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Soto, Alfonso</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The requirement of the anesthesiologist for patient care outside the surgical area is constantly increasing. It is an activity that encompasses the different degrees of monitoring, sedation, and anesthesia. OBJECTIVE To compare the safety and efficacy of midazolam midazolam-diphenhydramine against magnetic resonance with level of sedation on the Ramsay scale. MATERIALS AND METHODS We performed a study in the Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social Obregon, Sonora, of patients scheduled for cranial magnetic resonance imaging with sedation, during October and December 2013, comparing two groups: midazolam/diphenhydramine against midazolam groups. RESULTS We included 68 patients, 34 in the experimental group (midazolam-diphenhydramine) versus 34 controls (midazolam). The Ramsay scale showed, in the experimental group, an increased sedation effect resulting in one Ramsay 1, at 10 minutes 2.8 2.8 20 minutes and 30 minutes 2.0. In the control group the basal Ramsay was 1, 2.1 to 10 minutes, 20 minutes and 2.1 to 2.0 at 30 minutes (p = 0.0001). The analysis of heart rate, respiratory, and baseline oxygen saturation, at 10, 20 and 30 minutes, was p = 0.0001 for both groups. CONCLUSION The combination of diphenhydramine with intravenous midazolam is safe, with the degree of sedation being better compared with use of midazolam alone, resulting in less failure of sedation during magnetic resonance imaging.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la sedación intravenosa con midazolam- difenhidramina en pacientes a quienes se va a realizar una resonancia magnética (RM).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectiveness of intravenous sedation with midazolam-diphenhydramine in patients who are going to perform an magnetic resonance].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
