<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28126234</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guadix, Juan A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gálvez-Martín, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zugaza, José L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent advances in the field of cell therapy and regenerative medicine describe mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) as potential biological products due to their ability to self-renew and differentiate. MSCs are multipotent adult cells with immunomodulatory and regenerative properties, and, given their therapeutic potential, they are being widely studied in order to evaluate their viability, safety and efficacy. In this review, we describe the main characteristics and cellular sources of MSCs, in addition to providing an overview of their properties and current clinical applications, as well offering updated information on the regulatory aspects that define them as somatic cell therapy products. Cell therapy based on MSCs is offered nowadays as a pharmacological alternative, although there are still challenges to be addressed in this regard.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Células madre mesenquimales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cell therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medicina regenerativa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Regenerative medicine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia celular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mesenchymal stem cells</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características, aplicaciones y perspectivas de las células madre mesenquimales en terapia celular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics, applications and prospects of mesenchymal stem cells in cell therapy.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
