<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28176520</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-9518</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rascado, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trastoy, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Del Molino, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarro, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Manso, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barbeito, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, X</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Pulmonary nocardiosis is an uncommon pulmonary infection caused by aerobic gram-positive bacteria of the genus Nocardia. Nocardia sp. are environmental organisms spread worldwide. Approximately 50 Nocardia species have been described to date, about 30 of which are known to cause human disease. Nocardia cyriacigeorgica was first reported in 2001. CASE REPORT We report a case of infection caused by N. cyriacigeorgica in a patient with B-cells non-Hodgkin lymphoma and diabetes mellitus. The microbiological findings reflect a possible co-infection by N. cyriacigeorgica and Aspergillus fumigatus. CONCLUSIONS Patient's background and information related to risk factors are essential to detect the growth of Nocardia sp. in the laboratory. Furthermore, diagnosis of invasive pulmonary aspergillosis is particularly controversial, especially in intensive care units patients. Taking everything into account, we will discuss a possible co-infection by N. cyriacigeorgica and A. fumigatus in a critically ill patient.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coinfección pulmonar por Nocardia cyriacigeorgica y Aspergillus fumigatuss.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary co-infection due to Nocardia cyriacigeorgica and Aspergillus fumigatus].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de quimioterapia : publicacion oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Quimioterapia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
