<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28212478</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romo-Gamboa, Juan Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-López, Ana Bertha</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sandoval-Pérez, Bertha Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barrera-de León, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-González, Marco Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP) represents the second cause of nosocomial infections and it is associated with greater morbility, duration of mechanical ventilation (MV), and hospital stay. The objective was to determine factors related with VAP in neonates. METHODS Analytical transversal study including newborns admitted already intubated with at least 48 hours of MV or who were intubated in Neonatal Therapy. VAP was defined according to the criteria of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: "those patients submitted to MV during at least 48 hours". We used inferential statistics for statistical analysis (chi squared, Mann-Whitney U test, and Kaplan-Meier estimator). RESULTS 82 neonates were studied, out of which 27 developed VAP (33%). The median time to develop pneumonia was 6 days (range 5-11). The most commonly isolated germ was Escherichia coli (27%). Statistically significant variables were gestational age (p = 0.05), and the use of antacids at admission (p = 0.007). Patients with pneumonia had longer hospital stay (p = 0.001) and time with MV (p = 0.002). Of all the patients, 22 neonates died (27%), of which nine patients had VAP. CONCLUSION Risk factors for VAP in neonates include lower gestational age, the use of antacids, and prolonged MV.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Ventilator-associated pneumonia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nosocomial infections</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a neumonía secundaria a ventilación mecánica en terapia intensiva neonatal.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: la neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica (NAVM) representa la segunda causa de infección nosocomial y se asocia con una mayor morbilidad, duración de ventilación mecánica (VM) y estancia hospitalaria. El objetivo fue determinar los factores asociados a NAVM en neonatos. Métodos: estudio transversal analítico en el que se incluyeron recién nacidos que ingresaron intubados con menos de 48 horas de VM o que se intubaron en terapia neonatal. Se definió la NAVM, según los criterios de los Centros para el Control y la Prevencion de Enfermedades (CDC), como “aquella infección nosocomial diagnosticada en pacientes sometidos a VM durante al menos 48 horas”. Se empleó estadística inferencial para el análisis estadístico. Resultados: se estudiaron 82 neonatos, desarrollaron NAVM 27 (33%). La mediana del desarrollo de neumonía fue de seis días (rango 5-11). El germen aislado más común fue la Escherichia coli (27%). Las variables estadísticamente significativas fueron la edad gestacional (p = 0.05) y el uso de antiácidos al ingreso (p = 0.007). Los pacientes con neumonía tuvieron mayor tiempo de estancia hospitalaria (0.001) y tiempo con VM (p = 0.002). Murieron 22 neonatos en población general (27%), de los cuales nueve eran pacientes con NAVM. Conclusión: los factores de riesgo para NAVM incluyen menor edad gestacional, antiácidos y ventilación mecánica prolongada. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Risk factors related with ventilator-associated pneumonia in a neonatal intensive care therapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
