<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28215909</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alcántara Montero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Carnerero, C I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Eslicarbazepine acetate (ESL), together with carbamazepine and oxcarbazepine, belongs to the dibenzazepine family. According to the latest clinical practice guidelines, tricyclic antidepressants, dual antidepressants (venlafaxine, duloxetine), and some antiepileptics (gabapentin, pregabalin) are first-line drugs for neuropathic pain; tramadol, lidocaine 5% patches, and capsaicin 8% patches are considered second-line drugs; and strong opioids constitute a third line of treatment. Such other antiepileptics as lamotrigine and lacosamide are not authorised as treatments for neuropathic pain by the regulatory agencies, but are nonetheless prescribed off-label in routine clinical practice. Carbamazepine, on the other hand, is indicated for trigeminal and glossopharyngeal neuralgia. DEVELOPMENT We conducted a literature search to gather evidence on the use of ESL for neuropathic pain, headache, and cranial neuralgia. CONCLUSIONS Evidence is insufficient to recommend ESL for neuropathic pain, headache, and cranial neuralgia. Most of the available evidence comes from open and observational studies with small sample sizes and no control group; however, their favourable results call for further studies on the usefulness of ESL for neuropathic pain, headache, and cranial neuralgia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Diabetic polyneuropathy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postherpetic neuralgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antiepilépticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trigeminal neuralgia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Eslicarbazepine acetate</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antiepileptics</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neuralgia postherpética</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acetato de eslicarbazepina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dolor neuropático</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Polineuropatía diabética</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neuralgia del trigémino</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Neuropathic pain</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Feb 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acetato de eslicarbazepina en dolor neuropático, cefaleas y neuralgias craneales: Evidencia y experiencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eslicarbazepine acetate for neuropathic pain, headache, and cranial neuralgia: Evidence and experience.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
