<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28229439</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fagoaga, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Girabent-Farres, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bagur-Calafat, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION The Individualized Neuromuscular Quality of Life (INQoL) is a questionnaire that evaluates the quality of life related to the health of adults with neuromuscular diseases. AIM To validate and analyze the reliability of the Spanish version of the INQoL scale as an instrument for measuring quality of life related to health in individuals with neuromuscular diseases. PATIENTS AND METHODS A translation-back translation of the INQoL in the Spanish population is performed and, subsequently, for the analysis of reliability, two measurements are carried out; test retest, with 50 patients aged between 19 and 67 years. In this way we assess the intraobserver concordance and assess the internal consistency of the scale. RESULTS The study of the reliability of the intraobserver concordance index has a value of excellent in seven of the ten subdimensions as well as in the total score of the quality of life. It has a value of good in two and of moderate in one subdimension. The analysis of Cronbach's alpha for the subdimensions of the INQoL has a value of excellent (&gt; 0.818) in seven of them, as well as in the total score of the quality of life related to health (0.928), a value of good internal consistency in three of the subdimensions, and of moderate in one. CONCLUSIONS The Spanish version of the INQoL is a valid and reliable instrument as a tool for measuring quality of life in adult patients with neuromuscular diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Mar 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traduccion y validacion de la escala Individualized Neuromuscular Quality of Life para la poblacion española: evaluacion de la calidad de vida para personas afectas de enfermedades neuromusculares.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Traduccion y validacion de la escala Individualized Neuromuscular Quality of Life para la poblacion española: evaluacion de la calidad de vida para personas afectas de enfermedades neuromusculares. 
             Introduccion. La escala Individualized Neuromuscular Quality of Life (INQoL) es un cuestionario que valora la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud de personas adultas con enfermedades neuromusculares. Objetivo. Validar y analizar la fiabilidad de la version española de la INQoL, como instrumento de medicion de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en individuos con enfermedades neuromusculares. Pacientes y metodos. Se realiza una traduccion-retrotraduccion de la INQoL en la poblacion española y, posteriormente, para el analisis de fiabilidad se llevan a cabo dos mediciones, test-retest, a 50 pacientes de 19 a 67 años. De este modo se evalua la concordancia intraobservador y se evalua la consistencia interna de la escala. Resultados. El estudio de la fiabilidad del indice de concordancia intraobservador tiene un valor de excelente en siete de las diez subdimensiones y en la puntuacion total de la calidad de vida; de buena, en dos; y de moderada, en una. El analisis del alfa de Cronbach para las subdimensiones de la INQoL tiene un valor de excelente (&gt; 0,818) en siete de ellas, asi como en la puntuacion total de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (0,928), un valor de buena consistencia interna en tres de las subdimensiones y de moderada en una. Conclusiones. La version española de la INQoL es un instrumento valido y fiable como herramienta de medicion de la calidad de vida en individuos adultos con enfermedades neuromusculares. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Translation and validation of the Individualised Neuromuscular Quality of Life scale for the Spanish population: quality of life assessment for persons with neuromuscular diseases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
