<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28225941</identifier>
<setSpec>1606-7916</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Espinosa-de la Peña, Rodrigo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, Juan Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Saisó, Sebastián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balandrán, Dulce Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze inequalities in health care indicators of children 0 to 9 years old in Mexico reporting gap and gradient measures. Materials and methods: Cross-sectional analysis of national health surveys in 2000, 2006 and 2012, measuring absolute and relative gap measures as well as the Slope Index of Inequality for four health care indicators (vaccination, care for acute respiratory infections, care for acute diarrheal diseases, and care for accidents) with socioeconomic stratification, as well as absolute gaps by sex, urbanicity and ethnic background. Results: Between 2000 and 2012, immunological equity was reached in Mexico, as well as elimination in the socioeconomic gap related to care for accidents; nevertheless, there is a persistent socioeconomic gap of care for acute respiratory infections that is also there regarding rural residence and indigenous population. Conclusion: In Mexico, there is a trend to the elimination of socioeconomic differences in the probability of receiving adequate health care among children, although some socioeconomic gaps remain in particular related to provision of services that require more participation of health personnel. There is a need to ensure homogenous access to effective services for all.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualdad en indicadores de resultados y acceso a la salud para niños en México: análisis de tres encuestas de salud.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Health inequality on results and access indicators for children in Mexico: analysis of national health surveys].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
