<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28233713</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barrio, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roldán, Belén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín Frías, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yelmo, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colino, Esmeralda</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez, María Ángeles</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The aims of the study are to evaluate the efficacy and safety of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) treatment in pre-school children with type I diabetes, and to assess whether the criteria of good metabolic control are achieved. METHOD A review was performed on the medical charts of patient's&lt;6 years of age who started CSII treatment between 2003 and 2014. The cohort consisted of 27 patients (mean age 4 (2.9-4.7) years, 56% males). An analysis was made including the age at onset, type I diabetes duration, HbA1c (HPLC, Menarini, normal value 5.1±0.31%), insulin dose (u/kg/day), number of capillary blood glucose measurements, number of baseline processes per day, % baseline/total insulin (B/TI), insulin ratios (I/HC) at different meals, severe hypoglycaemia (HS episodes/100 patients years), DKA events, percentages of normal blood glucose (70-180mg/dl), hyperglycaemia (&gt;180mg/dl), and hypoglycaemia (&lt;70mg/dl), mean blood glucose, standard deviation and coefficient of variation (SD/mean glucose ×100). Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS. RESULTS HbA1c decreased from 6.9% (6.7-7.5) to 6.8% (6.4-7.1) after one year of CSII. Afterwards, it remained under 6.8% during the follow-up (median 5 years [3-6]). Prior to CSII, 74% of children had HbA1c levels &lt; 7.5%. It increased to 96% after one year of CSII. Median blood glucose measurements /day was 10 (9-11). Total insulin dose did not change significantly. During the follow-up, there was one episode of DKA and one episode of HS. I/HC at breakfast were higher than at other meals (0.92 vs. 0.55, 0.6 and 0.5, respectively). CONCLUSIONS CSII is effective and safe in pre-school children. It allows good metabolic control (based on Society for Paediatric and Adolescent Diabetes / American Diabetes Association criteria) to be achieved and maintained for long periods of time without an increase in adverse events.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Preescolares</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pre-school children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infusión continua de insulina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infusión subcutánea continua de insulina en menores de 6 años: evolución a largo plazo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion in children less than 6 years-old: long-term progress].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
