<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28256690</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tudela-Torras, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Abad-Mas, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tudela-Torras, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today, the fact that sensory integration difficulties with a neurological basis exist and that they seriously condition the development of those individuals who suffer from them is widely accepted and acknowledged as being obvious by the vast majority of professionals working in the field of community healthcare. However, less is known and there is more controversy about effective treatments that can be applied to them. This is because many professionals criticise the fact that there is not enough scientific evidence to prove, both quantitatively and empirically, the outcomes of the interventions implemented as alternatives to pharmacological therapy. Consequently, when the symptoms and repercussions on the quality of life deriving from a distorted sensory integration are really disabling for the person, pharmacological treatment is used as the only possible approach, with the side effects that this entails. The reason for this is largely the fact that little is known about other effective therapeutic approaches, such as occupational therapy based on sensory integration.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Conference</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Feb 24 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Integracion sensorial: beneficios y efectividad del abordaje terapeutico en los trastornos del procesamiento sensorial.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Integracion sensorial: beneficios y efectividad del abordaje terapeutico en los trastornos del procesamiento sensorial. 
             En la actualidad, el hecho de que existen dificultades de integracion sensorial de base neurologica y que estas condicionan gravemente el desarrollo de las personas que las sufren, esta aceptado y reconocido como evidente por la gran mayoria de profesionales del campo sociosanitario. No obstante, en cuanto a tratamientos efectivos para abordarlas, hay mas controversia y desconocimiento, ya que existe la critica generalizada de que las intervenciones alternativas a la farmacologica no constan con la suficiente evidencia cientifica que demuestre de forma cuantitativa y empirica los resultados obtenidos a traves de ella. Consecuentemente, cuando los sintomas y repercusion en la calidad de vida derivados de una integracion sensorial distorsionada son realmente limitantes para la persona, se acaba recurriendo al tratamiento farmacologico como unico abordaje posible, con los efectos secundarios que ello conlleva, debido al desconocimiento de enfoques terapeuticos efectivos, como la terapia ocupacional basada en el enfoque de la integracion sensorial. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sensory integration: benefits and effectiveness of therapeutic management in sensory processing disorders].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
