<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28272728</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-6578</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garzon, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diez-Garcia, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Distributed neural networks in the brain sustain generation of wakefulness and two sleep states: non-REM sleep and REM sleep. These three behavioral states are jointly ingrained in a rhythmic sequence that constitutes the sleep-wakefulness cycle. This paper reviews and updates knowledge about the involvement of the histaminergic system in sleep-wakefulness cycle organization. Histaminergic neurons are exclusively located in the hypothalamic tuberomammillary nucleus, but are the source of a widespread projection system to many brain regions. Histamine neurons are active during waking, especially with high attention need, and remain silent in both non-REM and REM sleep. There have been described four metabotropic histamine receptors, of which H1R, H2R and H3R are present in the nervous system. H1R and H2R are mainly postsynaptic heteroreceptors, whereas H3R is thought to be mostly a presynaptic auto- and hetero-receptor. Histaminergic neurons are excited by hypocretinergic neurons and most of the arousing hypocretin effects are thought to depend on histaminergic actions. Interactions among histaminergic axons and cholinergic nuclei within forebrain and brainstem are particularly important for cortical activation. In contrast, histaminergic tuberomammillary neurons, similarly to other aminergic neurons in locus coeruleus or dorsal raphe nucleus, are inhibited by non-REM sleep-promoting neurons of the preoptic region. Further inhibitory actions on histamine neurons come from adenosine release on tuberomammillary region. Finally, histaminergic neurons inhibit REM-on hypothalamic neurons containing melanine-concentrating hormone, thus supporting a permissive role of tuberomammillary nucleus in REM sleep. Actually, knockout mice for histidine decarboxylase, the enzyme synthetizing histamine, show a significant REM sleep increase.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Mar 16 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regulacion de las fases del ciclo vigilia-sueño por la histamina.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Regulacion de las fases del ciclo vigilia-sueño por la histamina. 
             Redes neurales distribuidas en el encefalo sustentan la generacion de la vigilia y dos estados de sueño: sueño no REM y sueño REM. Estos tres estados comportamentales se engranan conjuntamente en una secuencia regular que constituye el ciclo vigilia-sueño. Este trabajo revisa y actualiza el conocimiento sobre la implicacion del sistema histaminergico en la organizacion del ciclo vigilia-sueño. Las neuronas histaminergicas se localizan exclusivamente en el nucleo tuberomamilar hipotalamico, pero son el origen de proyecciones extensas a numerosas regiones encefalicas. Las neuronas histaminergicas estan activas durante la vigilia, especialmente con alta demanda atencional, y permanecen silentes en sueño no REM y sueño REM. Se han descrito cuatro receptores histaminergicos metabotropicos, de los cuales H1R, H2R y H3R estan presentes en el sistema nervioso. H1R y H2R son fundamentalmente heterorreceptores postsinapticos, mientras que se piensa que H3R es mayormente un auto y heterorreceptor presinaptico. Las neuronas histaminergicas son activadas por las neuronas hipocretinergicas y se cree que muchos de los efectos activadores de las hipocretinas se deben a acciones histaminergicas. Las interacciones entre los axones histaminergicos y los nucleos colinergicos en el prosencefalo y el troncoencefalo son particularmente importantes para la activacion cortical. Por el contrario, las neuronas histaminergicas tuberomamilares, al igual que otras neuronas aminergicas del locus coeruleus o del nucleo dorsal del rafe, son inhibidas por las neuronas del area preoptica promotoras de sueño no REM. Acciones inhibidoras adicionales sobre las neuronas histaminergicas proceden de la liberacion de adenosina en la region tuberomamilar. Finalmente, las neuronas histaminergicas inhiben a las neuronas hipotalamicas REM-on que contienen hormona concentradora de melanina, apoyando asi un papel permisivo del nucleo tuberomamilar en el sueño REM. De hecho, ratones deficientes para descarboxilasa de histidina, la enzima de sintesis de la histamina, muestran un aumento significativo de sueño REM. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Regulation of the phases of the sleep-wakefulness cycle with histamine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
