<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28296366</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zevallos-Morales, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Málaga, Marco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Taype-Rondan, Alvaro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The aim of this article is to evaluate the interest in complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) therapies using Google Trends in spanish-speaking countries. METHODS An observational study was conducted using GoogleTrends. The search volume of 34 CAM therapies in spanish were evaluated globally and in 21 spanish-speaking countries. Also, the relationship between the median of the most popular searches and the gross domestic product (GDP) per capita in each of the countries was evaluated using Spearman's test. RESULTS A decreased trend in search volume was observed in homeopathy, herbal medicine, acupunctureand sensory therapies; and an increasing trend in chiropraxy. A direct association was observed between the GDP per capita and the median between the most popular CAM therapies, this relationship was no significant (p = 0.432). CONCLUSIONS The interest in CAM therapies shows temporal and geographic variations that must be studied in depth. These results can be used for the establishment of an international monitoring for the use of CAM therapies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Complementary therapies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Acupuncture</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Phytotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gross domestic product</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Homeopathy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias de las búsquedas en Google sobre terapias de medicina alternativa y complementaria.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Introducción: el objetivo de este artículo es evaluar el interés de la población en terapias de medicina alternativa y complementaria (MAC), a través de la herramienta Google Trends y en países de habla hispana. Métodos: se realizó un estudio observacional mediante la herramienta Google Trends. Se evaluaron las tendencias de búsqueda de 34 terapias de MAC en español, de manera global y en 21 países de habla hispana. Se evaluó la asociación entre la mediana de búsquedas de las terapias más populares y el producto interno bruto (PIB) per cápita en cada país, mediante la prueba de Spearman. Resultados: se observa una tendencia descendente en el volumen de búsquedas de homeopatía, medicina herbaria, acupuntura y terapias sensoriales; así como una tendencia ascendente de la quiropraxia. Además, al analizar los países se observó una asociación directa entre el PIB per cápita y la mediana de la búsqueda de las terapias de MAC más populares, pero esta no fue significativa (p = 0.432). Conclusiones: el interés de terapias de MAC presenta variaciones temporales y geográficas que deben estudiarse a profundidad. Estos resultados pueden ser de utilidad para establecer una vigilancia internacional al respecto. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Trends in Google searches on complementary and alternative medicine].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
