<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28292522</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Acosta, Orlando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bollo, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valenzuela, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Fabrellas, Estrella</dc:author>
<dc:author>Xaubet, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Portal, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ancochea, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Molina, María</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis is defined as chronic fibrosing interstitial pneumonia limited to the lung, with poor prognosis. The incidence has been rising in recent years probably due to improved diagnostic methods and increased life expectancy. In 2013, the SEPAR guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis were published. Since then, clinical trials and meta-analyses have shown strong scientific evidence for the use of pirfenidone and nintedanib in the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. In 2015, the international consensus of 2011 was updated and new therapeutic recommendations were established, prompting us to update our recommendation for the medical treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis accordingly. Diagnostic aspects and non-pharmacological treatment will not be discussed as no relevant developments have emerged since the 2013 guidelines.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Fibrosis pulmonar idiopática</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treatment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nintedanib</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pirfenidona</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pirfenidone</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Normativa sobre el tratamiento farmacológico de la fibrosis pulmonar idiopática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the medical treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
