<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28291534</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Muñoz-Valle, José Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Bello, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palafox-Sánchez, Claudia Azucena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Ureña, Sergio Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Noa, Yeniley</dc:author>
<dc:author>Padilla-Gutiérrez, Jorge Ramón</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valle, Yeminia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra-Rojas, Isela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rangel-Villalobos, Hector</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVES The protein tyrosine phosphatase non-receptor type 22 (PTPN22) gene encodes an important negative regulator of T-cell activation, lymphoid-specific phosphatase -Lyp- and has been associated with different autoimmune disorders. The PTPN22 -1123G&gt;C polymorphism appears to affect the transcriptional control of this gene, but to date, the biological significance of this polymorphisms on rheumatoid arthritis (RA) risk remains unknown. We evaluate the association of PTPN22 -1123G&gt;C polymorphism with anti-cyclic citrullinated protein antibodies (anti-CCP) and risk for RA in population from Western Mexico. MATERIAL AND METHODS A transversal analytic study, which enrolled 300 RA patients classified according to ACR-EULAR criteria and 300 control subjects (CS) was conducted. The -1123 G&gt;C polymorphism was genotyped by PCR-RFLP. The anti-CCP antibodies levels were quantified by ELISA kit. RESULTS We found a higher prevalence of homozygous PTPN22 -1123CC genotype in CS than in RA patients (OR 0.41; 95% confidence interval 0.24-0.71; P=.001), suggesting a potential protective effect against RA. Concerning anti-CCP levels, the CC genotype carriers showed the lowest median levels in RA (P&lt;.05). CONCLUSION The PTPN22 -1123CC genotype is a protector factor to RA in a Mexican-mestizo population and is associated with low anti-CCP antibodies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Artritis reumatoide</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rheumatoid arthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Proteína linfoide tirosina fosfatasa (Lyp)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anti-cyclic citrullinated protein antibodies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>PTPN22</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lymphoid-specific phosphatase (Lyp)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anticuerpos antipéptido citrulinado cíclico</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Aug 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismo −1123G&gt;C en el gen PTPN22 y anticuerpos antipéptido citrulinado cíclico en la artritis reumatoide.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PTPN22 -1123G&gt;C polymorphism and anti-cyclic citrullinated protein antibodies in rheumatoid arthritis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
