<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28301031</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Oliveira, João Lucas Campos de</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gabriel, Carmen Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fertonani, Hosanna Pattrig</dc:author>
<dc:author>Matsuda, Laura Misue</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze managers and professionals' perceptions on the changes in hospital management deriving from accreditation. Method: descriptive study with qualitative approach. The participants were five hospital quality managers and 91 other professionals from a wide range of professional categories, hierarchical levels and activity areas at four hospitals in the South of Brazil certified at different levels in the Brazilian accreditation system. They answered the question "Tell me about the management of this hospital before and after the Accreditation". The data were recorded, fully transcribed and transported to the software ATLAS.ti, version 7.1 for access and management. Then, thematic content analysis was applied within the reference framework of Avedis Donabedian's Evaluation in Health. Results: one large family was apprehended, called "Management Changes Resulting from the Accreditation: perspectives of managers and professionals" and five codes, related to the management changes in the operational, structural, financial and cost; top hospital management and quality management domains. Conclusion: the management changes in the hospital organizations resulting from the Accreditation were broad, multifaceted and in line with the improvements of the service quality. Objetivo: analizar las percepciones de gestores y trabajadores sobre los cambios en la gestión hospitalaria resultantes de la Acreditación. Método: estudio descriptivo con aproximación cualitativa. Participaron cinco gestores de calidad hospitalaria y otros 91 trabajadores de las más diversas categorías profesionales, niveles jerárquicos y áreas de actuación de cuatro hospitales del sur de Brasil certificados por la Acreditación nacional de diferentes niveles, que contestaron la pregunta "Cuéntame sobre la gestión de este hospital, antes y después de la Acreditación". Los datos fueron grabados, transcritos por completo y transportados para acceso y manoseo en el software ATLAS.ti, versión 7.1. A seguir, fue aplicado el análisis de contenido, modalidad temática, a la luz del referencial de la Evaluación en Salud de Avedis Donabedian. Resultados: fue aprendida una gran categoría temática (family), llamada "Cambios Gerenciales Resultantes de la Acreditación: perspectivas de gestores y trabajadores" y cinco subcategorías (codes), relacionadas a los cambios gerenciales en las esferas operacional; estructural; financiera y de costo; en la alta gestión hospitalaria; y en la gestión de calidad. Conclusión: los cambios gerenciales en las organizaciones hospitalarias, resultantes de la Acreditación, fueron amplias, polifacéticas y coherentes con las mejoras en la calidad de los servicios. Objetivos: analisar as percepções de gestores e trabalhadores sobre as mudanças no gerenciamento hospitalar advindas da Acreditação. Método: estudo descritivo com abordagem qualitativa. Participaram cinco gestores da qualidade hospitalar e outros 91 trabalhadores das mais diversas categorias profissionais, níveis hierárquicos e áreas de atuação de quatro hospitais do sul do Brasil certificados pela Acreditação nacional de diferentes níveis, que responderam à questão "Fale-me sobre o gerenciamento deste hospital, antes e depois da Acreditação". Os dados foram gravados, transcritos na íntegra e transportados para acesso e manejo no software ATLAS.ti, versão 7.1. Após isso, procedeu-se a análise de conteúdo, modalidade temática, sustentada à luz do referencial da Avaliação em Saúde de Avedis Donabedian. Resultados: apreendeu-se uma grande categoria temática (family), denominada "Mudanças Gerenciais Advindas da Acreditação: perspectivas de gestores e trabalhadores" e cinco subcategorias (codes), relacionadas às mudanças gerenciais no âmbito operacional; estrutural; financeiro e de custo; na alta gestão hospitalar; e na gestão da qualidade. Conclusão: as mudanças gerenciais nas organizações hospitalares, advindas da Acreditação, se mostraram amplas, multifacetadas e coadunam às melhorais da qualidade nos serviços.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Mar 02 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management changes resulting from hospital accreditation.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
