<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28341228</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-8070</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carrera, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benítez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pujol, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Siurana, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guspí, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jaén, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flor, M de la</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izquierdo, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Casals, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jordà, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Picas, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the efficiency of radioguided occult lesion localising in non-palpable breast lesions (NPBL) compared to the surgical wire technique. METHOD A prospective study was conducted on 161 women with NPBL, of whom 80 marked with the wire (group 1), whereas 81 women were marked with an intratumour injection of 99mTc-nanocoloid (group 2). The NPBL were located by ultrasound or stereotactic guidance. The lumpectomies were performed following the wire direction in group 1, and with the aid of a gamma-probe in group 2. Surgical margins were then checked, determining the need of extension if the margin was less than 5mm in the intra-surgical study, and less than 2mm in the deferred study. Data were collected on the mean number detected by surgery, surgical margins, number of extensions, presence of residual tumour in the extension, second surgeries, lumpectomy volume, as well as total resected volume, volume/tumour ratio, and complications. RESULTS No significant differences were observed between the two groups in the mean number detected, surgical margins, number of extensions, presence of residual tumour in the extension, second surgeries, lumpectomy volume, total resected volume, volume/tumour ratio or complications. The multivariate analysis showed the determining factors of the resected volume were the radiological guidance technique, as well as the surgeon. CONCLUSIONS The radioguided occult lesion localising technique helps in the detection and resection of NPBL with the same efficiency as the surgical wire, and adds the possibility of sentinel node detection in the same surgery. The determining factors of the resected volume were the radiological guidance technique and the surgeon.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Surgical wire</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Arpón</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de mama</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Breast cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ROLL</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep - Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la técnica ROLL en la exéresis de lesiones no palpables de mama.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of the ROLL technique for lumpectomy in non-palpable breast lesions.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear e imagen molecular</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
