<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28366421</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-8070</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mucientes Rasilla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardona Arboniés, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Ballesteros, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carballido Rodriguez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Alfonso, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapata Paz, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prieto Soriano, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mitjavila Casanovas, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the role of the 18F-Choline PET/CT in prostate cancer management when detecting distant disease in planning radiotherapy and staging and to evaluate the therapy changes guided by PET/TC results. MATERIAL AND METHODS A retrospective evaluation was performed on 18F-Choline PET/CT scans of patients with prostate cancer. Staging and planning radiotherapy scans were selected in patients with at least 9 months follow up. There was a total of 56 studies, 33 (58.93%) for staging, and 23 (41.07%) for planning radiotherapy. All scans were obtained using a hybrid PET/CT scanner. The PET/CT acquisition protocol consisted of a dual-phase procedure after the administration of an intravenous injection of 296-370MBq of 18F-Choline. RESULTS There were 43 out of 56 (76.8%) scans considered as positive, and 13 (23.2%) were negative. The TNM staging was changed in 13 (23.2%) scans. The PET/CT findings ruled out distant disease in 4 out of 13 scans, and unknown distant disease was detected in 9 (69.3%) scans. CONCLUSIONS 18F-Choline PET/CT is a useful technique for detecting unknown distant disease in prostate cancer when staging and planning radiotherapy. The inclusion of 18F-choline PET/CT should be considered in prostate cancer management protocols.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Cáncer de próstata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiotherapy planning</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estadificación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Planificación de radioterapia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Staging</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Choline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>PET/CT</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>PET/TC</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recurrencia bioquímica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biochemical recurrence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prostate cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colina</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep - Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La PET/TC con 18F-Colina en la estadificación y recidiva bioquímica de pacientes con cáncer de próstata: cambios en la clasificación y planificación de radioterapia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">18F-Choline PET/CT scan in staging and biochemical recurrence in prostate cancer patients: Changes in classification and radiotherapy planning.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de medicina nuclear e imagen molecular</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
