<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28385467</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Parkman, H P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Midani, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Schey, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alla, S P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Patients with gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) are treated with proton pump inhibitors (PPIs). Those that do not achieve symptom relief, or non-responders, usually undergo esophageal pH monitoring off PPIs in order to confirm the presence of GERD. AIMS To assess the efficacy of the reverse-PPI trial in evaluating the presence of GERD or its recurrence rates, as well as to identify a correlation between the symptom recurrence rates and GERD severity determined by 48-hour Bravo® esophageal pH-monitor testing. METHODS A final total of 205 patients that underwent the 48-hour Bravo® esophageal pH-monitoring study were retrospectively included. Patients discontinued PPI usage for at least 7 days prior to testing, and completed symptom questionnaires during the 2-day test. The Bravo® test was considered positive if the percentage of time with esophageal pH &lt;4 was &gt;4.4%. RESULTS A total of 363 patients underwent 48-hour Bravo® testing and of those patients, 205 were eligible for the study. Ninety-two patients reported symptoms as being «same/better» and 113 as being «worse» after stopping PPIs. Of the 92 patients with improved symptoms, 44 (48%) had documented acid reflux during the Bravo® study, compared with 65 of 113 (58%) patients with worsening symptoms that also complained of acid reflux. Of the 109 patients found to have confirmed GERD upon pH monitoring, 65 (59.6%) reported a worsening of symptoms, compared with 48 of 96 (50.0%) patients without GERD (p=0.043). Main symptoms stated to be worse included heartburn, chest pain, regurgitation, nausea, and belching (p&lt;0.05). Of the 205 patients, 103 were off PPIs for 7 days. Seventy-two of them (68.9%) reported a worsening of symptoms, compared with 40 of the 102 (41.2%) patients that were off PPIs for&gt;7 days (p=0.042) CONCLUSION: Symptom exacerbation following PPI cessation for at least 7 days correlated with acid reflux severity assessed by Bravo® testing. Patients off PPIs for 7 days had a higher likelihood of experiencing worsening symptoms, compared with those off PPIs for more than 7 days. These findings suggest that when PPIs are held for 7 days or less prior to Bravo® testing, acute worsening of upper GI symptoms due to the abrupt discontinuation of therapy may influence the Bravo® results. The etiology of this may be related to rebound acid hypersecretion and needs to be further elucidated in future studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Síntomas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad por reflujo gastroesofágico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Descontinuación de inhibidor de la boma de protones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Gastroesophageal reflux disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Monitorización de pH Bravo(®)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Proton pump inhibitor discontinuation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bravo(®) pH monitoring</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Symptoms</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recurrencia sintomática relacionada con la enfermedad por reflujo gastroesofágico en pacientes que descontinúan los inhibidores de la bomba de protones durante el estudio inalámbrico de monitorización de pH esofágico Bravo®.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastroesophageal reflux disease-related symptom recurrence in patients discontinuing proton pump inhibitors for Bravo® wireless esophageal pH monitoring study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
