<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28421809</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García Gabarra, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castellà Soley, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calleja Fernández, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this document is to refl ect the changes happened in the European Union legislation and the opinions of the European Food Safety Authority in relation to the nutritional labeling on food, the reference values for energy, macronutrients and micronutrients, and the tolerable upper safe levels. The European legislation in force uses the labeling reference values established by the Scientific Committee on Food in 2003. There would be advisable an update of them from the reference values for vitamins and minerals established by the European Food Safety Authority. Equally, there would be good to include reference labeling values for polyunsaturated fatty acids, dietary fiber and choline, and specific reference labeling values for children from 6 to 36 months. For vitamins and minerals there would be desirable the revision of tolerable upper safe levels and the establishment of maximum amounts allowed in fortified food and food supplements in the European Union; its absence might represent a risk in some population groups for an excessive and unsafe intake of certain minerals and vitamins.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 03 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingestas de energía y nutrientes recomendadas en la Unión Europea: 2008-2016</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Esta revisión tiene por objeto reflejar los cambios producidos en la legislación de la Unión Europea y los dictámenes de la Autoridad Europea de Seguridad Alimentaria en relación al etiquetado nutricional de los alimentos, a los valores de referencia de energía, macronutrientes y micronutrientes, y a los niveles máximos de ingesta tolerable. La vigente legislación europea utiliza los valores de referencia para el etiquetado establecidos por el Comité Científico de la Alimentación Humana en 2003. Sería aconsejable una actualización de los mismos a partir de los valores de referencia establecidos por dicha autoridad europea para vitaminas y minerales. Igualmente sería positiva la inclusión de valores de referencia para el etiquetado de ácidos grasos poliinsaturados, fibra alimentaria y colina, y para el etiquetado específicamente referido a niños de 6 a 36 meses. Para vitaminas y minerales sería deseable una revisión de los niveles máximos de ingesta tolerable y el establecimiento de cantidades máximas permitidas en los alimentos enriquecidos y en los complementos alimenticios en la Unión Europea; su ausencia puede representar un peligro de ingesta excesiva e insegura de determinados minerales y vitaminas en algunos grupos de población. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommended energy and nutrients intakes in the European Union: 2008-2016</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
