<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28438378</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salcedo, Mauricio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Esquivel, Miriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ornelas-Corral, Nora</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Morelos, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Taniguchi, Keiko</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bandala, Cindy</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poot-Vélez, Albros</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Romero, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdespino-Zavala, Mariana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marrero-Rodríguez, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uribe-Jiménez, Arizbett</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJETIVE Human papilloma virus (HPV) is one of the main risk factors associated with the development of cervical cancer and its precursor lesions. It has been reported that HPV16 and 18 types cover approximately 70% of cervical cancer worldwide; however, significant variation in percentages of HPV infections could be related to specific populations. MATERIALS AND METHODS Purified DNA of 67 cervical samples were analyzed by Linear Array® HPV genotyping kit. These analyzed samples correspond to 19 cervical tumors, 15 high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions, 20 low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions, and 13 cervical samples without injury were studied, all of them previously diagnosed. RESULTS In general, 16 different HPV types were found with differences in their frequencies, cervical invasive cancer being the richest in HPV sequences, followed by the low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions and then high-grade lesions. HPV16 was the most frequently distributed type in neoplastic lesions of the cervix, followed by the HPV52, suggesting viral type variability, probably associated to the geographical region studied. CONCLUSIONS The results could indicate variability in HPV presence in Mexico, underlining the important role for HPV52 among others in the Mexican population. This would also potentially have an impact on the current anti-HPV vaccination schemes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Multiple infections</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infecciones múltiples</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virus del papiloma humano</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Human papilloma virus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer cervicouterino</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cervical cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 11 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genotipificación del virus del papiloma humano en un grupo de mujeres mexicanas atendidas en un hospital de alta especialidad: las infecciones múltiples y su potencial trascendencia en el esquema actual de vacunación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genotyping of the human papilloma virus in a group of Mexican women treated in a highly specialist hospital: Multiple infections and their potential transcendence in the current vaccination programme.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
