<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28440775</identifier>
<setSpec>2530-0172</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Chocarro-Calvo, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Martínez, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Salmerón, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>de la Vieja, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Jiménez, Custodia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association between diabetes and cancer was hypothesized almost one century ago. Today, a vast number of epidemiological studies support that obese and diabetic populations are more likely to experience tissue-specific cancers, but the underlying molecular mechanisms remain unknown. Obesity, diabetes, and cancer share many hormonal, immune, and metabolic changes that may account for the relationship between diabetes and cancer. In addition, antidiabetic treatments may have an impact on the occurrence and course of some cancers. Moreover, some anticancer treatments may induce diabetes. These observations aroused a great controversy because of the ethical implications and the associated commercial interests. We report an epidemiological update from a mechanistic perspective that suggests the existence of many common and differential individual mechanisms linking obesity and type 1 and 2 diabetes mellitus to certain cancers. The challenge today is to identify the molecular links responsible for this association. Classification of cancers by their molecular signatures may facilitate future mechanistic and epidemiological studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Epidemiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glucose</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glucosa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mecanismos moleculares</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hiperglucemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hyperglicaemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Insulina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular mechanisms</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases epidemiológicas y mecanismos moleculares implicados en las asociaciones de obesidad y diabetes con cáncer.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological bases and molecular mechanisms linking obesity, diabetes, and cancer.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Endocrinologia, diabetes y nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
