<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28443993</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Resck, Zelia Marilda Rodrigues</dc:author>
<dc:author>Terra, Fábio de Souza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva, Luiz Almeida da</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Sérgio Valverde Marques Dos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Macedo, Flávia Ribeiro Martins</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nogueira, Denismar Alves</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to analyze the occurrence of work accidents and the self-esteem of nurses in hospitals of a municipality of Minas Gerais. METHOD descriptive-analytical and cross-sectional study developed with 393 nursing professionals from three hospitals of a municipality in southern Minas Gerais. The Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale and a questionnaire to characterize the population and work accidents were used for data collection. Data analysis was performed using Person's chi-squared test, Fisher's exact test, Cronbach's alpha, odds ratio and logistic regression. RESULTS of the professionals studied, 15% had suffered an accident at work and 70.2% presented high self-esteem. Through the analysis, it was observed that smoking, religious belief and an outstanding event in the career were significantly associated with work accidents. In relation to self-esteem, family income, length of time working in the profession and an outstanding event in the career presented significant associations. CONCLUSION factors such as smoking, religious belief, family income, length of time working in the profession and an outstanding event in the career can cause professionals to have accidents and/or cause changes in self-esteem, which can compromise their physical and mental health and their quality of life and work.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Apr 20 </dc:date>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             analizar la ocurrencia de accidentes de trabajo y la autoestima de profesionales de enfermería en ambientes hospitalarios en un municipio de Minas Gerais. 
             estudio descriptivo, analítico y transversal, desarrollado con 393 profesionales de enfermería de tres hospitales de un Municipio del sur de Minas Gerais. Para recolección de datos se utilizó la Escala de Autoestima de Rosenberg y un cuestionario de caracterización de la población y de accidente de trabajo. Para analizar los datos fueron utilizadas las pruebas de Person, Exacta de Fisher, Alfa de Cronbach, odds ratio y regresión logística. 
             de los profesionales investigados, 15% sufrieron accidente de trabajo y 70,2% poseía autoestima alta. Por medio del análisis, se observó que el tabaquismo, la creencia religiosa y el evento excepcional en la carrera presentaron asociación significativa con accidente de trabajo. En relación a la autoestima, la renta familiar mensual, el tiempo de actuación en la profesión y el evento excepcional en la carrera, tuvieron asociación significativa. 
             factores como tabaquismo, creencia religiosa, renta familiar, tiempo de actuación en la profesión y evento excepcional en la carrera, pueden ocasionarle al profesional un accidente y/o provocar alteraciones en la autoestima, lo que puede comprometer su salud física y mental y su calidad de vida y trabajo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Work accidents and self-esteem of nursing professional in hospital settings.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
