<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28454990</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díez-Ascaso, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lubrini, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martín-Montes, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díez-Tejedor, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Our conception of the mind-brain relationship has evolved from the traditional idea of dualism to current evidence that mental functions result from brain activity. This paradigm shift, combined with recent advances in neuroimaging, has led to a novel definition of brain functioning in terms of structural and functional connectivity. The purpose of this literature review is to describe the relationship between connectivity, brain lesions, cerebral plasticity, and functional recovery. DEVELOPMENT Assuming that brain function results from the organisation of the entire brain in networks, brain dysfunction would be a consequence of altered brain network connectivity. According to this approach, cognitive and behavioural impairment following brain damage result from disrupted functional organisation of brain networks. However, the dynamic and versatile nature of these circuits makes recovering brain function possible. Cerebral plasticity allows for functional reorganisation leading to recovery, whether spontaneous or resulting from cognitive therapy, after brain disease. CONCLUSIONS Current knowledge of brain connectivity and cerebral plasticity provides new insights into normal brain functioning, the mechanisms of brain damage, and functional recovery, which in turn serve as the foundations of cognitive therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Brain plasticity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cognitive therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mental disorders</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia cognitiva</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Behaviour disorders</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Brain damage</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Daño cerebral</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Alteraciones del comportamiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trastornos mentales</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Plasticidad cerebral</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Apr 25 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad cerebral, conectividad, plasticidad y terapia cognitiva. Una visión neurológica del trastorno mental.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Brain disease, connectivity, plasticity and cognitive therapy: A neurological view of mental disorders.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
