<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28453131</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Curiel-Ballesteros, Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Ceja, Faustino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zumaya-Leal, María Del Rocío</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To analyze the pathologies generated by motorized transportation in the context of urban expansion. Methodology This is a documental study based in the beginning on specialized scientific articles, followed by consultations of book-sources and databases and, thirdly, in local newspaper articles. In addition, it involved a systematic reflection on the judgment of experts in environmental health and risk studies. Results 20 diseases, physical and mental, associated with motorized transport in the context of urban expansion are shown. We found that not only are drivers vulnerable to the risks of transport but children and pregnant women are also highly vulnerable groups. Discussion Considering the acute and chronic effects of urban sprawl and some social and environmental determinants associated with socio- organizational, technological and climatic health risks of cities, transportation is the subsystem with the greatest risk present in large cities, and main area of opportunity to improve wellness.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El transporte motorizado como presión al bienestar en ciudades en expansión.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Motorized transportation as a pressure on wellness in expanding cities].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
