<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28453124</identifier>
<setSpec>0124-0064</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Trujillo-Maza, Elena M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lema-Vélez, Mariana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Londoño-Martínez, Alicia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Suárez-Acevedo, Daniel E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective This study shows perceptions of alcohol drinking (AD) and its relationship with the media among adolescents 12 to 14 years old. Methods We performed a qualitative study with adolescents 12 to 14 years old from two public schools in Bogotá (Colombia), using focus groups, semi-structured interviews and participant observation as the primary data collection methods. Results The participants repeatedly referred to AD in this age group as a highly prevalent behavior with a positive valuation. It was also evident that teenagers 12 to 14 years old have frequent contact with alcohol-related publicity; they remember clearly and bring into the conversation many commercials and advertisements from TV, fences, posters, and websites from social networks and many brands. For participants, all of these advertising methods associate AD with enjoyable topics such as soccer, parties and friends. Discussion Our results are consistent with quantitative studies showing a high prevalence of AD among Colombian teenagers. We present a clear relationship between positive valuations of consumption among teenagers 12 to 14 years old, social normalization of consumption and contact with alcohol-promoting publicity. Our results question the efficacy of the current law regulations on alcohol advertising, and they should be taken into account for the design of new public policies on that matter.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2015 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la publicidad en el consumo de bebidas alcohólicas en escolares de Bogotá.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Media influence on adolescent alcohol consumption in schoolsin Bogotá].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
