<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28474701</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fuentes-Orozco, Clotilde</dc:author>
<dc:author>Irusteta-Jiménez, Leire</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardoza-Macías, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rendón-Félix, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chávez-Tostado, Mariana</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Rentería, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Ojeda, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Agundez-Meza, José Juan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras-Hernández, Guadalupe Ivette</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mascareño-Franco, Héctor Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez-Villaseñor, Andrea Socorro</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Pregnancy and the postpartum period are risk factors for developing biliary sludge, gallstones, and any of their complications. OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence, presentation, and consequences of cholestasis during pregnancy and postpartum in a referral hospital of Baja California Sur. MATERIAL AND METHODS This was a retrospective, observational study that enrolled pregnant or postpartum patients diagnosed with gallstones with any presentation. RESULTS 137 patients were included, with 22 ± 4 years of age; 33 were pregnant and 104 in the postpartum period. Only 14% of the group had a history of cholelithiasis, and overweight/obesity was observed in 66.7 and 66.3% of pregnant and postpartum patients, respectively (p = 0.94). Of pregnant patients, 33.3% presented with acute cholecystitis, a condition observed in 16.3% of the postpartum patients (p = 0.04). Pancreatitis and choledocholithiasis were slightly more common in pregnant women (21.23% vs. 19.2%; p = 0.56). There was no maternal mortality and one case of spontaneous abortion was exclusively observed. CONCLUSIONS It is a priority to diagnose and monitor cholelithiasis in pregnant women because the acute cases observed occurred more frequently, but choledocholithiasis and pancreatitis occurred similarly in both groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Mar - Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colelitiasis en el embarazo y posparto. Prevalencia, presentación y consecuencias en un hospital de referencia en Baja California Sur.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cholelithiasis during pregnancy and postpartum: prevalence, presentation and consequences in a Referral Hospital in Baja California Sur].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
