<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28479004</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fioravantti, Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruano, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Illade, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lassaletta, Álvaro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cormenzana, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernandez-Marques, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andión Catalán, Maitane</dc:author>
<dc:author>Madero López, Luis</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Wilms' tumour is the most frequent renal tumour in children. Multi-modal treatment includes chemotherapy and surgery, with or without radiotherapy. The survival is excellent, with rates exceeding 90%. A review is presented on our experience over the last 15 years of treating Wilms' tumour in Hospital Niño Jesús, Madrid. PATIENTS AND METHODS A retrospective study was conducted on 40 consecutive paediatric patients diagnosed with nephroblastoma between 2002 and 2016 in the Hospital Niño Jesús in Madrid. The clinical characteristics, diagnostic methods, treatment, and follow-up were analysed. RESULTS Of the 40 patients, 23 were boys, with a median age at diagnosis of 2.5 years (range, 4 months-15 years). Three patients underwent initial nephrectomy, three received a fine needle aspiration biopsy, followed by chemotherapy, and 34 patients started pre-operative chemotherapy directly. The median follow-up of the patients was 6.75 years (range, 10 months - 13.92 years). Two patients died from disease progression. There were no treatment-related deaths. Overall survival and event-free survival at 5 years was 94.6±3.7% and 89.4±5%, respectively. CONCLUSION Wilms' tumour treatment is a success of modern medicine, currently achieving a survival rate of 95% in our series.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Nefroblastoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Renal tumour</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Niños</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Wilms</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nephroblastoma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tumor renal</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May 03 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de Wilms: revisión de nuestra experiencia en los últimos 15 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Wilms' tumour: A review of 15 years recent experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
