<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28495125</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López Martín, M Beatriz</dc:author>
<dc:author>Erice Calvo-Sotelo, Alejo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare presurgical hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution following the WHO protocol with traditional presurgical hand hygiene. METHODS Cultures of the hands of surgeons and surgical nurses were performed before and after presurgical hand hygiene and after removing gloves at the end of surgery. Cultures were done in 2different days: the first day after traditional presurgical hand hygiene, and the second day after presurgical hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution following the WHO protocol. The duration of the traditional hand hygiene was measured and compared with the duration (3min) of the WHO protocol. The cost of the products used in the traditional technique was compared with the cost of the hydroalcoholic solution used. The variability of the traditional technique was determined by observation. RESULTS Following presurgical hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution, colony-forming units (CFU) were detected in 5 (7.3%) subjects, whereas after traditional presurgical hand hygiene CFU were detected in 14 subjects (20.5%) (p &lt; 0.05). After glove removal, the numbers of CFU were similar. The time employed in hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution (3min) was inferior to the time employed in the traditional technique (p &lt; 0.05), its cost was less than half, and there was no variability. CONCLUSIONS Compared with other techniques, presurgical hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution significantly decreases CFU, has similar latency time, a lower cost, and saves time.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hydroalcoholic solution</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Presurgical hand hygiene</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Solución hidroalcohólica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Higiene de manos prequirúrgica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infecciones relacionadas con la atención sanitaria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health care-associated infections</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jul - Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo sobre la higiene de manos prequirúrgica con solución hidroalcohólica frente a la higiene prequirúrgica tradicional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of presurgical hand hygiene with hydroalcoholic solution versus traditional presurgical hand hygiene.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
