<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28504486</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferraris, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Contreras, Maritza</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrais, Verónica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Raddavero, Claudia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Busaniche, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kozak, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ghezzi, Lidia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blazquez, Juliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Beneitez, Gonzalo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coccia, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Vitamin D (25(OH)D) deficiency is common among patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD). Our objective was to establish the prevalence of 25(OH)D deficiency among children with CKD and identify risk factors. A correlation was observed between 25(OH)D and parathormone intact molecule. POPULATION AND METHODS Cross-sectional study conducted between January 2013 and December 2015. Patients younger than 19 years old with and without CKD were included. RESULTS One hundred and sixty-seven patients were included. Group 1 (healthy controls): 32 participants; group 2 (stage 2-4 CKD, glomerular filtration rate between 89 and 15 mL/min/1.73 m2): 34 patients; group 3 (stage 5 CKD, dialysis): 46 patients; and group 4 (kidney transplant recipients): 55 patients. Deficiency of 25(OH)D was detected in 12.5% of healthy controls and 32% of CKD patients (p= 0.025). Also, 23% of patients in group 2, 51% in group 3, and 22% in group 4 had 25(OH)D deficiency; the mean 25(OH)D level of dialysis patients was significantly lower than that of the rest of the groups. Predictors of 25(OH)D deficiency included hypoalbuminemia, advanced CKD, and place of origin from the Northwest region of Argentina. The parathormone intact molecule was significantly higher in the group of patients with deficiency and was inversely correlated with 25(OH)D levels. CONCLUSION Among CKD patients, 32% had 25(OH)D deficiency, which reached 51% among those with stage 5 CKD (dialysis). Predictors of deficiency included hypoalbuminemia, advanced CKD, and place of origin from the Northwest region of Argentina.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>dialysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>chronic kidney disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>hyperparathyroidism</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>vitamin D deficiency</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 06 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alta prevalencia de deficiencia de vitamina D en niños con enfermedad renal crónica y trasplante renal.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La deficiencia de vitamina D (25OHD) es muy común en pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica (ERC). Los obj etivos de este trabajo fueron determinar la prevalencia del déficit de 25OHD en niños con ERC e identificar factores de riesgo. Se estableció la correlación entre 25OHD y paratohormona molécula intacta. 
             Estudio transversal realizado entre enero de 2013 y diciembre de 2015. Se incluyeron pacientes menores de 19 años con y sin ERC. 
             Se incluyeron 167 pacientes. Grupo 1 (controles sanos): 32 participantes; grupo 2 (ERC, estadios 2-4, filtrado glomerular entre 89 y 15 ml/ min/1,73 m2): 34 pacientes; grupo 3 (estadio 5, en diálisis): 46 pacientes; y grupo 4 (trasplantados renales): 55 pacientes. Presentaron deficiencia de 25OHD 12,5% de los controles sanos y 32% de los pacientes con ERC (p= 0,025). El 23% de los pacientes del grupo 2, el 51% del grupo 3 y el 22% del grupo 4 presentaron deficiencia de 25OHD; el valor medio de 25OHD de los pacientes en diálisis fue significativamente menor que en el resto de los grupos. Los predictores de deficiencia de 25OHD fueron la hipoalbuminemia, ERC avanzada y la procedencia de la región Noroeste. La paratohormona molécula intacta fue significativamente más elevada en el grupo de pacientes con deficiencia y mostró una correlación inversa con los valores de 25OHD. 
             El 32% de los pacientes con ERC presentó deficiencia de 25OHD; en el estadio 5 (diálisis), alcanzó el 51%. Los predictores de deficiencia fueron hipoalbuminemia, ERC avanzada y la procedencia del noroeste. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High prevalence of vitamin D deficiency among children with chronic kidney disease and kidney transplant.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
