<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28504493</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González García, María B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conde-Guzon, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcalde Martín, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velasco Zúñiga, Roberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conde-Guzon, María J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although with early treatment phenylketonuria patients may have average intelligence levels, it is important to optimize the nutritional management to maintain adequate phenylalanine levels, so that patients can develop their intellectal potential free of abnormalities in their daily activities due to deficits of cognitive executive functions. This study presents a series of 26 patients, diagnosed and treated early, who underwent a psychometric evaluation together with phenylalanine determinations along their lives, and at the time of doing the tests. A trend is observed towards a reverse relationship between IQ and concurrent phenylalanine concentration, phenylalanine median and phenylalanine/tyrosine ratio. Likewise, a trend towards a negative relationship is observed between executive functions and concurrent phenylalanine values along patients' lives.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>phenylalanine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>phenylketonuria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>executive function</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>intelligence</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 06 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación neuropsicológica en niños y adolescentes con fenilcetonuria e hiperfenilalaninemia y su relación con los niveles de fenilalanina plasmática.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Aunque, con tratamiento precoz, los pacientes con fenilcetonuria pueden presentar niveles de inteligencia normales, es importante optimizar el control dietético para mantener niveles de fenilalanina adecuados y poder desarrollar su potencial intelectual sin alteraciones en sus tareas diarias por déficits en las funciones ejecutivas. Se presenta una serie de 26 pacientes, diagnosticados y tratados precozmente, a quienes se realizó una evaluación psicométrica junto con determinaciones de fenilalanina a lo largo de su vida y en el momento de realización de los tests. Se observa una tendencia a la relación inversa entre el cociente intelectual y la fenilalanina concurrente, la mediana de fenilalanina y el cociente fenilalanina/tirosina, así como una tendencia a la relación negativa entre las funciones ejecutivas y los valores de fenilalanina concurrentes y durante la vida. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological assessment among children and adolescents with phenylketonuria and hyperphenylalaninemia and its relationship with plasma phenylalanine levels.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
