<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28522305</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Batlle, Pau</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nuñez, Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bosch, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz de Morales, Ester</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brugada, Ramon</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aboal, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olivet, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brugada, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramos, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Onaga, Hisao</dc:author>
<dc:author>Loma-Osorio, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, Alex</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES In recent years, public access defibrillation programs have exponentially increased the availability of automatic external defibrillators (AED) in public spaces but there are no data on their performance in our setting. We conducted a descriptive analysis of the performance of AED since the launch of a public defibrillation program in our region. METHODS A retrospective analysis was conducted of electrocardiographic tracings and the performance of AED in a public defibrillation program from June 2011 to June 2015 in the province of Girona, Spain. RESULTS There were 231 AED activations. Full information was available on 188 activations, of which 82% corresponded to mobile devices and 18% to permanent devices. Asystole was the most prevalent rhythm (42%), while ventricular fibrillation accounted for 23%. The specificity of the device in identifying a shockable rhythm was 100%, but there were 8 false negatives (sensitivity 83%). There were 47 shockable rhythms, with a spontaneous circulation recovery rate of 49% (23 cases). There were no accidents related to the use of the device. CONCLUSIONS Nearly half of the recorded rhythms were asystole. The AED analyzed showed excellent safety and specificity, with moderate sensitivity. Half the patients with a shockable rhythm were successfully treated by the AED.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Desfibrilación pública</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asistolia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiopulmonary resuscitation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrilación ventricular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public defibrillation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiopulmonary arrest</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reanimación cardiopulmonar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asystole</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Parada cardiorrespiratoria</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ventricular fibrillation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Girona Territori Cardioprotegit Project: Performance Evaluation of Public Defibrillators.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
