<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28545739</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moya-Ruano, Luis A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Fernández, Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Rasero, Francisco J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vela-Ríos, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Candau-Bejarano, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the tool developed in Andalusia (Spain) to conduct an analysis and prospective assessment of health impacts from urban planning projects as well as the process followed to design it. METHOD On the one hand, direct and indirect relationships between urban setting and health were identified in light of the best scientific evidence available; and, on the other hand, methods and tools in impact assessment were reviewed. After the design of the tool, it was tested via both internal and external validation processes (meetings, workshops and interviews with key informants). RESULTS The tool consists of seven phases, structured in two stages. A first descriptive stage shows how to obtain information about goals, objectives and general points pertaining the project and also to characterise the potentially affected population. The second one indicates, in several phases, how to identify and sort out potential impacts from the project using different supporting tools. CONCLUSIONS Both in the testing phase and through its implementation since the entry into force of Andalusian Decree 169/2014 (16 June 2015) and forced all urban planning projects to be subjected to an Health Impact Assessment, this methodology has proved responsive, identifying major potential health impacts from the measures included in those projects. However, the tool has been shaped as a living tool and will be adapted in line with the experience acquired in its use.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Evaluación del impacto en la salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Salud pública</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health equity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Health impact assessment</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>City planning</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Equidad en salud</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Methods</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Métodos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Public health</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Planificación de ciudades</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep - Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología de la valoración del impacto en salud de instrumentos de planeamiento urbanístico en Andalucía.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Health impact assessment methodology for urban planning projects in Andalusia (Spain)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
