<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28554559</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alobid, Isam</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The management of septal perforations is a challenge for the surgeon. A wide variety of surgical techniques have been described, with different approaches. There is no scientific evidence to support a particular approach. The objective of this review is to present a practical guide on the technique of choice for each case of septal perforation. DISCUSSION Inspection of the nasal mucosa, the size of the perforation, the location and especially the osteo-cartilaginous support, are the pillars of a successful surgery. For the sliding or rotating flaps of the mucosa of the septum it is essential to know in advance if the elevation of the mucopericondrio or mucoperiosteo of the septum is possible, otherwise the use of these flaps would not be indicated. The flaps of the lateral wall or nasal floor are the alternative. The pericranial flap may be indicated in total or near total perforations. CONCLUSION The remnant of the nasal septum and status of osteo-cartilaginous support are the determining factors in the management of septal perforations. Each case should be evaluated individually and the approach chosen according to the size and location of the perforation, mucosal quality, personal history, previous surgery and the experience of the surgeon.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pedicle flaps</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cierre quirúrgico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Perforación septal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colgajos pediculados</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Endoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Surgical closure</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Septal perforation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May 26 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cierre endoscópico de las perforaciones septales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic closure of septal perforations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
