<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28552215</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torregrosa Andrés, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pacheco Usmayo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rogel Bertó, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luján Marco, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores Méndez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the types of penile prostheses and their components, to review the appropriate magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) acquisition protocol, and to describe the normal imaging findings and possible complications in patients with inflatable penile implants. CONCLUSION Three-piece inflatable penile prostheses are the last link in the treatment chain for erectile dysfunction. They can develop complications, which are classified as non-infectious related to the surgical technique, infectious, or due to mechanical failure of the device. MRI is the most appropriate imaging technique for the postsurgical evaluation of penile prostheses. Images are acquired in three planes using sequences with high spatial resolution, first with the prosthesis at rest and then with the prosthesis activated.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Resonancia magnética</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prótesis de pene</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones postoperatorias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Erectile dysfunction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Disfunción eréctil</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Penile prosthesis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones posquirúrgicas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Magnetic resonance imaging</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postsurgical complications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postoperative complications</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la resonancia magnética en la valoración postquirúrgica de pacientes con prótesis hidráulica de pene.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of magnetic resonance imaging in the postsurgical assessment of patients with inflatable penile prostheses.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
