<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28562719</identifier>
<setSpec>1606-7916</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernández-Vicente, Irma Alejandra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rojas-Lima, Elodia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lumbreras-Guzmán, Marivel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cervantes-Rodríguez, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Méndez-Hernández, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez-Flores, Clara Arlina</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To validate a scale for assessing the labour quality of life in public hospitals (LQL-PH) from Tlaxcala, Mexico. Materials and methods: The instrument was validated among 669 health workers from six hospitals from the Ministry of Health of Tlaxcala, Mexico. Content validity was by inquiry to experts, construct validity by factor analysis, criterion validity by comparing with other scales, and reliability with Cronbach's Alpha. Results: The factor analysis uncovered four dimensions: "individual welfare", "conditions and labour environment", "organization", and "well-being accomplished by the work"; reliability was 0.921. Workers who perceibed better LQL-PH were: under 50 years old, with temporary contract, with less seniority in job, with work schedule at daytime of weekends, and those with academic degree. Conclusions: LQL-PH showed to be an instrument phsycometrically valid and reliable. It's recommendable to prove this scale in other public and private health institutions, as well as its relationship with key health care indicators of labour performance and management.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de una escala para medir la calidad de vida laboral en hospitales públicos de Tlaxcala.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Validation of a scale to assess the labour quality of life in public hospitals from Tlaxcala].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
