<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28562730</identifier>
<setSpec>1851-8265</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Salazar, Lina Marcela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernal, Iván Darío Vélez</dc:author>
<dc:author>Patiño-Londoño, Sandra Yaneth</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acero, Catalina Tovar</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article focuses on the conceptions, attitudes and practices of the inhabitants from four villages (veredas) in Tierralta and Valencia (Cordoba, Colombia), who have suffered from or are aware of the existence of cutaneous leishmaniasis. A mixed methodology was implemented based in a qualitative design using interviews and focus groups (n=45) and an epidemiological design which included applying the Montenegro test (n=251), uncovering suspected cases of cutaneous leishmaniasis in humans, (n=5) and applying epidemiological surveys (n=409). Among the results, a lack of knowledge regarding the vector was found; although respondents could identify the Lutzomyia (known as "alú"), they did not correlate it with cutaneous leishmaniasis. In addition, traditional home treatments were more frequently used, increasing the underrecording of cases. With respect to healthcare personnel, flaws in diagnosis and treatment were found, which reinforces adherence to home treatments. This scenario calls for a reflection upon the challenges of the health care system in relation to the interventions of health personnel in communities situated in endemic areas.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jan-Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos socioepidemiológicos y culturales de la leishmaniasis cutánea: concepciones, actitudes y prácticas en las poblaciones de Tierralta y Valencia, (Córdoba, Colombia).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Socio-epidemiological and cultural aspects of cutaneous leishmaniasis: conceptions, attitudes and practices in the populations of Tierralta and Valencia (Cordoba, Colombia)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud colectiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
