<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28583725</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ranea, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Falgueras, Laia</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Ben, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albiol, M Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro, Ernesto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueras, Joan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Codina-Barreras, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casellas, Margarida</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Compared to other surgical areas, laparoscopic liver resection (LLR) has not been widely implemented and currently less than 20% of hepatectomies are performed laparoscopically worldwide. The aim of our study was to evaluate the feasibility, and the ratio of implementation of LLR in our department. METHODS We analyzed a prospectively maintained database of 749 liver resections performed during the last 10-year period in a single centre. RESULTS A total of 150 (20%) consecutive pure LLR were performed between 2005 and 2015. In 87% of patients the indication was the presence ofprimary or metastatic liver malignancy. We performed 30 major hepatectomies (20%) and (80%) were minor resections, performed in all liver segments. Twelve patients were operated twice and 2 patients underwent a third LLR. The proportion of LLR increased from 12% in 2011 to 62% in the last year. Conversion rate was 9%. Overall morbidity rate was 36% but only one third were classified as severe. The 90-day mortality rate was 1%. Median hospital stay was 4 days and the rate of readmissions was 6%. CONCLUSIONS The implementation of LLR has been fast with morbidity and mortality comparable to other published series. In the last 2 years more than half of the hepatectomies are performed laparoscopically in our centre.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopic liver resection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Caudal approach</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Extraglissonean</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Learning curve</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Abordaje dorsal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Conversión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatectomía laparoscópica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Extraglissoniano</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Conversion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Curva de aprendizaje</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dorsal approach</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Abordaje caudal</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la cirugía laparoscópica en una unidad hepatobiliar de alto volumen: 150 hepatectomías laparoscópicas consecutivas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of laparoscopic surgery in a high volume hepatobiliary unit: 150 consecutive pure laparoscopic hepatectomies.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
