<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28606692</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-178X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro Cutillas, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallego Herrero, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Analyze statistically the success, number of sessions required and complete duration of treatment of agents used in pediatric percutaneous sclerotherapy of lymphatic malformations, to determine the most suitable. MATERIAL AND METHODS Retrospective study based on outcomes from percutaneous sclerotherapy performed on lymphatic malformations of 56 patients conducted by pediatric interventional radiologist for 14 years. As first approach, the procedure consists of ultrasound-guided introduction of sclerosing agent. Sessions were repeated until clinical resolution. Success, number of sessions and the duration of treatment were recorded and statistical treatment of the data was performed to obtain further conclusions. RESULTS Lost patients in follow up and other minority agents used were excluded from the data. Eventually, 52 patients treated with OK432 (n=29), Ethibloc (n=5) and combination therapy (n=18) were included. The average number of sessions and duration in months of treatment was respectively 2.38 and 8.6 for OK432, 1.4 and 5.6 for Ethibloc, and 1.83 and 2.30 for dual therapy. The results were statistically significant for the difference in duration between OK432 and dual therapy. Also, 60-80% of patients reached proper results related to success, but the difference was no significant among the agents. Other demographic and anatomical variables were analyzed, not showing any difference, which supports the homogeneity of the sample. CONCLUSIONS Despite of no significant difference in success and number of sessions among agents, longer duration of treatment with OK432 than dual therapy could mean greater health costs and probably greater disturb for patient and family.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Esclerosis percutánea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cabeza y cuello</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Polidocanol</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Interventional radiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lymphatic malformation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Malformación linfática</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vascular malformation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Radiología intervencionista</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>OK 432</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Malformación vascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Head and neck</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Craniofacial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Percutaneous sclerotherapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Craneofacial</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep - Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento percutáneo de las malformaciones linfáticas en edad pediátrica: experiencia y resultados según el esclerosante empleado.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous sclerotherapy of pediatric lymphatic malformations: experience and outcomes according to the agent used.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Radiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
