<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28625339</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-6749</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alonso, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miró, Ò</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gené, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rimbau, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escalada, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casarramona, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jacob, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zorrilla, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Netto, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To know the implementation and characteristics of non-invasive ventilation (NIV) in the Emergency Departments (EDs) of public hospitals in Catalonia (Spain) and analyze possible differences based on the typology, degree of activity and the availability of an Intensive Care Unit (ICU) in the hospital. DESIGN A non-interventional, descriptive study was carried out, using a structured questionnaire divided into 3sections: 1) professional experience and training; 2) devices used; and 3) clinical scenarios and the use of NIV. SETTING Persons responsible for public EDs in Catalonia. RESULTS Fifty-two of the 54 public EDs in Catalonia responded (96.3%). Fifty-one perform NIV, which is mainly initiated by emergency care physicians (78.5%); 66.7% maintain the patient in the ED until discharge; and in 43.1% of the cases the length of stay is&gt;24h. Of the EDs, 39.2% have their own protocol, 35.3% of which are established by consensus with other departments (more frequently in non-county hospitals [P=.012], and centers with an ICU [P=.014]), while 25.5% have no protocol, and 43.1% register the activity. Training represents the greatest difficulty for the implementation of NIV, but 19.6% do not provide specific training. When support is needed, the main physician of reference is the intensivist (35.3%) (more frequently in non-county hospitals [P=.012], and centers with an ICU [P=.002]). CONCLUSIONS In most EDs in Catalonia, NIV is performed by emergency care physicians. Areas needing improvement include drainage of patients once NIV has been started, the promotion of protocols, registry of activity, and training of the healthcare professionals.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Emergency care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Non-invasive ventilation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Critical care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ventilación no invasiva</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidados intensivos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urgencias</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jun 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventilación no invasiva en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios públicos de Cataluña. Estudio VENUR-CAT.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive ventilation in emergency departments in public hospitals in Catalonia. The VENUR-CAT study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina intensiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
