<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28643671</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Lanteri, Martín E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ariza Bolivar, Alexander</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Adriana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cícero, Carla Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puchulu, Félix M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Health literacy (HL) is a measure of a patient ability to read, understand and to take decisions on medical instructions. Patients with inadequate HL have poorer health outcomes than those with adequate HL. There is little information on HL levels in diabetic patients in Argentina. The aim of this study was to explore the association between HL and glycemic control in diabetic patients from a university hospital in Argentina. HL was assessed with the Short Assessment of Health Literacy for Spanish-speaking Adults (SAHLSA), glycemic control through glycosylated hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c); 156 patients (58% women) took part in the study. Average SAHLSA score was 35 (range: 11-50). Patients with inadequate values of HL had HbA1c of 8.15% vs. 7.15% among those with adequate HL (p = 0.0001). The multiple linear regression shows that inadequate HL was significantly associated with poorer glycemic control (β = -0.05 IC 95% -0.07; -0.02, p &lt; 0.001). Efforts should focus on developing interventions to improve glycemic control among patients with inadequate HL.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>health literacy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>glycated hemoglobin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>diabetes</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alfabetización en salud y control de la diabetes en pacientes de un hospital universitario de Argentina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Health literacy and diabetes control in patients attending a university outpatient clinic in Argentina].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
