<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28658726</identifier>
<setSpec>0002-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ortiz-Peregrina, José Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velarde-Rivera, Fernando Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robles-Figueroa, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bedolla-Barajas, Martín</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Padilla, Lourdes Fabiola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales-Romero, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Hernández, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Hypovitaminosis D has been associated with various chronic diseases such as infections, autoimmune diseases, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cancer and asthma Objective: The objective at hand is to determine the prevalence of vitamin D (VD) insufficiency and deficiency in adults with allergic asthma. OBJECTIVE Objective: The objective at hand is to determine the prevalence of vitamin D (VD) insufficiency and deficiency in adults with allergic asthma. METHODS Through a cross-sectional study, we analyzed corresponding data amongst 135 patients. VD concentration was categorized as sufficient (≥ 30 ng/mL), insufficient (21-29 ng/mL), and deficient (≤ 20 ng/mL). The level of VD deficiency was measured through chemo-luminescence. We estimated the prevalence of VD alterations and their respective confidence intervals at 95 % (CI 95 %). RESULTS Within the analyzed population, there were 99/135 women (73.3 %); the mean age was 34.5 ± 10.3 years. The mean concentration of VD was 17.9 ± 6.9 ng/mL and the median was 17 ng/mL. The prevalence of VD insufficiency and deficiency was 25.2 % (CI 95 %, 18.6-33.2 %) and 71.1 % (CI 95 %, 62.9-78.1 %), respectively; VD concentrations ≤ 10 ng/mL had 13.3 % (CI 95 %, 8.5-20.2 %) and ≥ 30 ng/mL at 3.7 % (CI 95 %: 1.4-8.6 %). When we contrasted the men to the women, the median concentration of VD did not differ significantly (16 ng/mL vs. 18 ng/mL, p = 0.71). CONCLUSION In this study, patients with allergic asthma had distinctively reduced VD concentration levels; future research will determine if and how VD affects the severity of asthma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Vitamin D</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adult</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Asthma</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Apr-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de insuficiencia y deficiencia de vitamina D en adultos mexicanos con asma alérgica.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Antecedentes: La hipovitaminosis D ha sido asociada con diversas enfermedades crónicas como infecciones, enfermedades autoinmunes, enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica, cáncer y asma. Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de insuficiencia y deficiencia de vitamina (VD) en adultos con asma alérgica. Métodos: Estudio transversal en el que se analizaron los datos de 135 pacientes. La concentración de VD fue categorizada en suficiente (≥ 30 ng/mL), insuficiente (21-29 ng/mL) y deficiente (≤ 20 ng/mL). La concentración de VD se midió por quimioluminiscencia. Se estimaron las prevalencias de las alteraciones de la VD y sus respectivos intervalos de confianza a 95 % (IC 95 %). Resultados: En la población analizada, 99 fueron mujeres (73.3 %), con edad media de 34.5 ± 10.3 años. La concentración media de VD fue 17.9 ± 6.9 ng/mL (mediana de 17 ng/mL). La prevalencia de insuficiencia y deficiencia de VD fue de 25.2 % (IC 95 %, 18.6-33.2 %) y 71.1 % (IC 95 %, 62.9-78.1 %), respectivamente; las concentraciones de VD ≤ 10 ng/mL representaron 13.3 % (IC 95 %, 8.5-20.2 %) y ≥ 30 ng/mL, 3.7 % (IC 95 %, 1.4-8.6 %). Al contrastar hombres y mujeres, la concentración mediana de VD no difirió significativamente (16 ng/mL versus 18 ng/mL, p = 0.71). Conclusiones: En este estudio, los pacientes con asma alérgica tuvieron concentraciones de VD notoriamente disminuidas. Con futuras investigaciones se podrá evaluar el papel de la VD en la gravedad del asma. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of vitamin D insufficiency and deficiency in Mexican adults with allergic asthma].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista alergia Mexico (Tecamachalco, Puebla, Mexico : 1993)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
