<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28704023</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cruchet Muñoz, Sylvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Dewaele Olivera, María Rita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarmiento Quintero, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Heller, Solange</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tarazona Cote, María Consuelo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mayor Oxilia, Rosa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barboza García, Fabiola</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, Adriana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, Sonia Miriam</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro Benavides, Mayra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ladino Meléndez, Liliana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía Castro, Milton</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanabria, Marta Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado Carbajal, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera Chamorro, José Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canal de Molano, Nelly</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ariza, Adolfo J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero Brens, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is an epidemic with important health repercussions in addition to high treatment-related costs. Between 2006 and 2007 the WHO developed new assessment tools, which aren't being globally used. In fact, there is no unified problem management across the hemisphere. Objectives To update obesity epidemiology, to promote application of WHO’s standards, to review new findings on physiopathology (i.e., fatty tissue as endocrine organ, intestinal microbiota), to update epidemiological information, and to provide management guidelines that can be integrated in clinical care. Methods LAPSGHAN called up its members to collaborate in preparing this review article under the direction of an editor/coordinator, who selected the contents and literature with the best evidencetogether with the members. Each member prepared a separate document for each content. The chosen contents were later collated, unified, and edited. Results. This documents highlights the following: 1) Although extreme obesity is increasing in the US, overweight and obesity prevalence has stabilized, while in other countries it is alarmingly increasing; 2) New information regarding role of fatty tissue as endocrine organ and self-regulator of obesity; 3) The promising role of microbiota; and 4) Guidelines for children handling during consultation and follow-up. Conclusions There is no widespread implementation of standards and guidelines from the World Health Organization (WHO). There is no agreement as to whether z-scores or percentiles should be used, especially regarding children under 2 due to their changing body complexion. The most accepted tool to assess overweight, obesity and severe obesity is the Body Mass Index (BMI). This document provides recommendations on how to approach clinical care with affected children.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2016 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobrepeso y obesidad: revisión y puesta al día de la Sociedad Latinoamericana de Gastroenterología, Hepatología y Nutrición Pediátrica (SLAGHN.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Overweight and obesity: review and update].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta gastroenterologica Latinoamericana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
