<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28712681</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tallo Aldana, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Dávila, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Méndez Abad, Manuel E</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Reig, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vílchez de León, Patricia Inés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Álvarez-Sotomayor, M Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Pulido, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero Estebaranz, Nayra</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess the effectiveness of an individual placement and support (IPS) strategy in people with severe mental disorders in Tenerife Island (Spain). METHODS Patients of Community Mental Health Services with severe mental disorders were randomly assigned to two groups. One of them received IPS (n=124), and the control group (n=75) was advised in the usual job search. Patients were followed up for an average of 3.4 years and an analysis was made of how many patients worked at least one day, working hours, wages, the number of contracts and the number of hospital admissions. Non-parametric methods were used to compare the results (Mann-Whitney U test). RESULTS The percentage of patients who worked at least one day was 99% in the IPS group compared with 75% in the control group; they worked on average 30.1 weeks per year vs 7.4; the monthly salary was € 777.9 vs € 599.9; the number of contracts per person was 3.89 vs 4.85, and hospital admissions were 0.19 vs 2.1. CONCLUSIONS The IPS strategy is effective for the labour integration of people with severe mental illness getting them to work longer, have higher wages and fewer hospital admissions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Rehabilitación psiquiátrica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Employment, supported</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mental health</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psychotic disorders</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>People with disabilities</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Trastornos psicóticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psychiatric rehabilitation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Empleos con apoyo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Salud mental</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Personas con discapacidad</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jul 13 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de una estrategia de apoyo individualizado al empleo para personas con trastornos mentales graves.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectiveness of individual supported employment for people with severe mental disorders].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
