<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28724000</identifier>
<setSpec>1678-4561</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gatto, Giuseppe Cesare</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodrigues, Cibele Isaac Saad</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferraz, Fábio Humberto Ribeiro Paes</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sá, Natan Monsores de</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">End-stage renal disease (ESRD) is an important public health problem, especially in developing countries due to the high level of economic resources needed to maintain patients in the different programs that make up renal replacement therapy (RRT). To analyze the differences and inequalities involved in access to RRT in the BRICS countries (Brazil, Russian Federation, India, China and South Africa). This is an applied, descriptive, cross-sectional, quantitative and qualitative study, with documentary analysis and a literature review. The sources of data were from national censuses and scientific publications regarding access to RRT in the BRICS countries. There is unequal access to RRT in all the BRICS countries, as well as the absence of information regarding dialysis and transplants (India), the absence of effective legislation to inhibit the trafficking of organs (India and South Africa) and the use of deceased prisoners as donors for renal transplants (China). The construction of mechanisms to promote the sharing of benefits and solidarity in the field of international cooperation in the area of renal health involves the recognition of bioethical issues related to access to RRT in the BRICS countries.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferenças e desigualdades no acesso a terapia renal substitutiva nos países do BRICS.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences and inequalities in relation to access to renal replacement therapy in the BRICS countries.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ciencia &amp; saude coletiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
