<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28734523</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moreno-Portillo, Mucio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuendis-Velázquez, Adolfo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosales-Castañeda, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>E Trejo-Ávila, Mario</dc:author>
<dc:author>A Sanjuan-Martínez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>E Rojano-Rodríguez, Martin</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cárdenas-Lailson, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Loera, Sujey</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Today's options for biliary bypass procedures, for difficult choledocholithiasis, range from open surgery to laparo-endoscopic hybrid procedures. The aim of this study was to analyze the outcomes of patients with difficult choledocholithiasis treated with laparoscopic choledochoduodenostomy. METHODS We performed a prospective observational study from March 2011 to June 2016. We included patients with difficult common bile duct stones (recurrent or unresolved by ERCP) in which a biliary bypass procedure was required. We performed a laparoscopic bile duct exploration with choledochoduodenostomy and intraoperative cholangioscopy. RESULTS A total of 19 patients were included. We found female predominance (78.9%), advanced mean age (72.4±12 years) and multiple comorbidities. Most patients with previous episodes of choledocholitiasis or cholangitis, mode 1 (min-max: 1-7). Mean common bile duct diameter 24.9±7mm. Mean operative time 218.5±74min, estimated blood loss 150 (30-600)mL, resume of oral intake 3.2±1 days, postoperative length of stay 4.9±2 days. We found a median of 18 (12-32) months of follow-up. All patients with normalization of liver enzymes during follow-up. One patient presented with sump syndrome and one patient died due to nosocomial pneumonia. CONCLUSIONS Laparoscopic choledochoduodenostomy with intraoperative cholangioscopy seems to be safe and effective treatment for patients with difficult common bile duct stones no resolved by endoscopic procedures. This procedure is a good option for patients with advanced age and multiple comorbidities. We offer all the advantages of minimally invasive surgery to these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Colédoco-duodeno anastomosis laparoscópica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cholangioscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Síndrome del sumidero</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Difficult common bile duct stones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coledocoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coledocolitiasis compleja</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopic choledochoduodenostomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Colangioscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sump syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Aug - Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colédoco-duodeno anastomosis laparoscópica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic Choledochoduodenostomy.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
