<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28737859</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ysla-Marquillo, Marlit</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cornejo-Monthedoro, Angela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Del Águila, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negreiros-Sánchez, Isel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mayta-Tristán, Percy</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE To study the association between the metabolic syndrome (MS) and the glycemic load (GL) of food intake among obese children and adolescents seen in consultation by the endocrinology team in a pediatric referral hospital in Lima, Peru. POPULATION AND METHOD Cross-sectional study among obese children and adolescents (body mass index ≥ 95 percentile), 10-15 years old. The MS was classified according to criteria of the International Diabetes Federation. A 24 hour reminder was used, and the overall and per meal GL was calculated. The association between the GL tertiles (comparison with the lower tertile) and the MS was assessed using prevalence ratios adjusted by demographic outcome measures, family history, physical activity and total carbohydrate consumption in Poisson regression models with a robust variance. RESULTS Out of 273 obese children and adolescents, 52.4% were male and 94.9% did not engage in any physical activity. Glycemic load median value was 213 (164.8-287.4) and the daily calorie intake value was 2275 (1851-3024) kcal, consisting mainly of carbohydrates (62%). MS prevalence was 22.3%; the most prevalent components were abdominal obesity (81.7%) and low values of high density lipoprotein (HDL) (63.7%). Lastly, an association was observed between a high consumption of GL and the risk of developing MS (aRP 4.5; 95% CI: 1.3-15.3). CONCLUSIONS There is an association between a high consumption of GL and the presence of MS among obese children and adolescents.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>metabolic syndrome</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>adolescentS</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>glycemic load</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>food intake</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Aug 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre la carga glicémica de la ingesta alimentaria y el síndrome metabólico en niños y adolescentes obesos.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Evaluar la asociación entre síndrome metabólico (SM) y carga glicémica (CG) de la ingesta alimentaria en niños y adolescentes obesos atendidos en consulta endocrinológica de un hospital de referencia pediátrica en Lima, Perú. 
             Estudio transversal en niños y adolescentes obesos (índice de masa corporal ≥ percentil 95) de 10 a 15 años. Se clasificó como SM según los criterios de la International Diabetes Federation. Se aplicó un recordatorio de 24 horas y se calculó la CG total y por comida. Se evaluó la asociación entre los terciles de CG (comparación con el inferior) y SM usando razones de prevalencia ajustadas (RPa) por variables demográficas, antecedentes familiares, de actividad física y consumo total de carbohidratos en modelos de regresión de Poisson con varianza robusta. 
             De 273 niños y adolescentes obesos, 52,4% fueron varones y 94,9% fueron físicamente inactivos. La mediana de CG fue de 213 (164,8-287,4) y la de ingesta calórica diaria fue 2275 (1851-3024) kcal, dada principalmente por carbohidratos (62%). La prevalencia de SM fue de 22,3%; los componentes con mayor prevalencia fueron la obesidad abdominal (81,7%) y los valores de lipoproteínas de alta densidad (HDL, del inglés high density lipoprotein) bajos (63,7%). Por último, se encontró una asociación entre el consumo elevado de CG y el riesgo de presentar SM (RPa 4,5; IC 95%: 1,3-15,3). 
             Existe una asociación entre el alto consumo de CG y la presencia de SM en niños y adolescentes con obesidad. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between dietary glycemic load and metabolic syndrome in obese children and adolescents.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
