<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28734880</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Nardin, Matteo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Suryapranata, Harry</dc:author>
<dc:author>De Luca, Giuseppe</dc:author>
<dc:author>Verdoia, Monica</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barbieri, Lucia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES There is uncertainty on the correct management of antithrombotic therapies after transcatheter aortic valve replacement (TAVR), with dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT) being currently recommended on an empirical basis. The aim of the present meta-analysis was to assess the safety and effectiveness of DAPT in patients undergoing TAVR. METHODS Studies comparing different antithrombotic regimens after TAVR were included. The primary endpoint was 30-day overall mortality. RESULTS We included 9 studies, 5 comparing DAPT with aspirin monotherapy and 4 comparing DAPT with monoantiplatelet therapy (MAPT) + oral anticoagulation. Among 7991 patients, 72% were on DAPT. The median follow-up was 3.5 months. Mortality was significantly lower in the DAPT group (12.2% vs 14.4%; OR, 0.81; 95%CI, 0.70-0.93; P = .003; Phet = .93), with similar benefits compared with aspirin monotherapy (OR, 0.80; 95%CI, 0.69-0.93; P = .004; Phet = .60), which were not statistically significant when compared with MAPT + oral anticoagulation (OR, 0.86; 95%CI, 0.55-1.35; P = .51; Phet = .97). A similar trend for DAPT was observed for stroke (OR, 0.83 95%CI, 0.63-1.10; P = .20; Phet = .67), with no increase in the rate of major bleedings (OR, 1.69; 95%CI, 0.86-3.31; P = .13; Phet&lt; .0001). On indirect comparison analysis, no benefit in survival, stroke, or bleedings was identified for additional oral anticoagulation. CONCLUSIONS The present meta-analysis supports the use of DAPT after TAVR, reducing mortality and offering slight benefits in stroke, with no increase in major bleedings compared with MAPT. The strategy of aspirin + oral anticoagulation did not provide significant benefits compared with MAPT or DAPT.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Antiplatelet therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Transcatheter aortic valve implantation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metan치lisis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Implante percut치neo de v치lvula a칩rtica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Meta-analysis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia antiagregante</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jul 19 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dual Versus Single Antiplatelet Regimen With or Without Anticoagulation in Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement: Indirect Comparison and Meta-analysis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
