<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28760227</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gorgojo Martínez, Juan José</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent decades, there has been a worldwide parallel increase in the prevalence of obesity and type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), which is not surprising, given that increased visceral fat is the main risk factor for the development of T2DM in genetically predisposed individuals. An intervention focused on intensive blood glucose control in T2DM with classic drugs increases the risk of weight gain and the rate of hypoglycaemia. In contrast, weight loss through lifestyle changes, drugs and/or surgery simultaneously improves most cardiovascular (CV) risk factors, including hyperglycemia. Intensive intervention on lifestyle induces an overall benefit in patients with T2DM, but long-term weight loss is modest and has not been shown to reduce CV morbidity and mortality. The emergence of new therapeutic classes for T2DM and obesity, which simultaneously improve HbA1c, weight and other CV risk factors without inducing hypoglycaemia, represents a major change in the management of patients with diabesity. A sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibitor and a GLP-1 receptor agonist have recently been shown to decrease CV and total mortality in type 2 diabetic patients with CV disease. Furthermore, bariatric surgery rapidly induces remission or improvement of T2DM in a large percentage of patients and reduces diabetes-related mortality. The emergence of new therapies raises the possibility of changing the current glucose-centred therapeutic strategy for a weight-centred approach.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Lorcaserina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Topiramate-phentermine</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía bariátrica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Topiramato-fentermina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bariatric surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Weight loss</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lorcaserin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bupropion-naltrexone</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inhibidores del cotransportador sodio-glucosa tipo 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Agonistas del receptor del péptido similar al glucagón tipo 1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibitors</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pérdida de peso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Bupropión-naltrexona</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia del peso en el control del paciente con diabetes mellitus tipo 2: hacia una visión adipocéntrica del abordaje de la diabetes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relevance of weight in the management of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: towards an adipocentric approach to diabetes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
