<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28793127</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Galán González-Serna, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arribas-Marín, Juan Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferreras-Mencia, Soledad</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to develop and validate a scale to evaluate nursing attitudes in relation to hospitality for the humanization of nursing care. Participants: the sample consisted of 499 nursing professionals and undergraduate students of the final two years of the Bachelor of Science in Nursing program. Method: the instrument has been developed and validated to evaluate the ethical values related to hospitality using a methodological approach. Subsequently, a model was developed to measure the dimensions forming the construct hospitality. Results: the Axiological Hospitality Scale showed a high internal consistency, with Cronbach's Alpha=0.901. The validation of the measuring instrument was performed using factorial, exploratory and confirmatory analysis techniques with high goodness of fit measures. Conclusions: the developed instrument showed an adequate validity and a high internal consistency. Based on the consistency of its psychometric properties, it is possible to affirm that the scale provides a reliable measurement of the hospitality. It was also possible to determine the dimensions or sources that embrace it: respect, responsibility, quality and transpersonal care. Objetivo: desenvolver e validar uma escala que permita avaliar a atitude dos enfermeiros em termos de hospitalidade, visando a humanização da enfermagem.Participantes: a amostra foi constituída por 499 profissionais e estudantes de enfermagem dos dois últimos anos do curso de graduação em Enfermagem. Método: utilizando-seuma abordagem metodológica, foi desenvolvido e validado um instrumento para avaliar os valores éticos relacionados com a hospitalidade. Subsequentemente, foi formulado um modelo para mediras dimensões que constituem o construto hospitalidade. Resultados: a Escala Axiológica de Hospitalidade mostrou uma consistência interna elevada, com Alfa de Cronbach=0,901. A validação do instrumento de medição foi realizada usando-se métodos de análise fatorial, exploratória e confirmatória, que apresentaram bons índices de qualidade de ajuste. Conclusões: o instrumento desenvolvido apresentou uma validade adequada e uma consistência interna elevada. Com base na consistência de suas propriedades psicométricas, é possível afirmar que a escala proporciona uma medida confiável da hospitalidade. Também foi possível determinar as dimensões ou fontes que a compõem: o respeito, a responsabilidade, a qualidade e o cuidado transpessoal. Objetivo: desarrollar y validar una escala que permita evaluar la actitud enfermera ante la hospitalidad para la humanización de enfermería. Participantes: la muestra la componen 499 profesionales de enfermería y estudiantes de los dos últimos niveles académicos de la titulación de Grado en Enfermería. Método: mediante abordaje metodológico, se ha desarrollado y validado un instrumento para evaluar valores éticos relacionados con la hospitalidad. Posteriormente, se ha formulado un modelo de medida de las dimensiones que conforman el constructo hospitalidad. Resultados: la Escala Axiológica de la Hospitalidad ha mostrado una alta consistencia interna, con un Alfa de Cronbach=0.901. La validación del instrumento de medida se realizó mediante las técnicas de análisis factorial, exploratorio y confirmatorio, que presentaron unos buenos índices de bondad de ajuste. Conclusiones: el instrumento desarrollado ha presentado una adecuada validez y una alta consistencia interna. Sus adecuadas propiedades psicométricas permiten afirmar que la escala aporta una medición fiable de la hospitalidad. También ha permitido determinar las dimensiones o fuentes que la conforman: el respeto, la responsabilidad, la calidad y el cuidado transpersonal.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Aug 03 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and validation of the Hospitality Axiological Scale for Humanization of Nursing Care.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
