<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28793123</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7167</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Prado, Marta Lenise do</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kempfer, Silvana Silveira</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guerrero-Castañeda, Raúl Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vargas, Maria Guadalupe Ojeda</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective is to reflect on historicity and temporality as paths for the transcendence of being elderly, based on the phenomenological concepts of Martin Heiddeger. A review of the concepts of transcendence, historicity and temporality was carried out in the work of Martín Heidegger, integrating them in the perspective of nursing for the elderly. The transcendence of the elderly adult is feasible by accessing the temporality of self in the path of its historicity to arrive at the understanding of itself that he has achieved: transcending, which is but a process of the Being itself. Being is time in itself existing in the world, existence given by the encounter of the past (to have been), present and future (becoming), the same encounter that determines the historicity of the Being. The encounter has been consummated and the Being is transcendence, with the understanding of the Being itself as a supreme point. RESUMEN El objetivo es reflexionar en la historicidad y temporalidad como caminos para la trascendencia del ser adulto mayor, basado en los conceptos fenomenológicos de Martín Heiddeger. Se llevó a cabo una revisión de los conceptos de trascendencia, historicidad y temporalidad en la obra de Martín Heidegger, realizando su integración en la perspectiva de enfermería al adulto mayor. La trascendencia del ser adulto mayor es factible accediendo a la temporalidad del mismo en el camino de su historicidad para llegar a la comprensión de sí a la que ha llegado: trascendiendo, que no es sino un proceso del mismo ser. El ser es el tiempo en sí mismo existiendo en el mundo, existencia dada por el encuentro del pasado (haber sido), presente y futuro (devenir), mismo encuentro que determina la historicidad del ser. El encuentro se ha consumado y el ser es trascendencia, como punto supremo la comprensión del ser mismo.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transcendence, historicity and temporality of being elderly: nursing reflection-using Heidegger.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista brasileira de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
