<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28802484</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-2190</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Motta, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, L F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rhinophyma, a rare and progressive disfiguring condition, is thought to be the final stage of rosacea. Several surgical treatments are available, including dermabrasion, cryosurgery, scalpel excision, electrosurgery, and carbon dioxide laser. The last 2 techniques are the most effective for the management of rhinophyma. We describe a series of cases of moderate or severe rhinophyma treated with high-frequency electrosurgery in the dermatology department of Hospital Simón Bolivar and in private clinics in Bogota, Colombia, between 2012 and 2016. The cosmetic result, as assessed by both the clinicians and the patients, was satisfactory in all cases. Three patients presented hypertrophic scars that were treated with steroid injections and silicone gel sheeting. Two patients presented persistent erythema. However, there were no serious infections and none of the patients required further surgery. Electrosurgery is one of the simplest and most cost-effective techniques currently available for the treatment of rhinophyma by dermatologists.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Rhinophyma</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Rinofima</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hiperplasia sebácea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sebaceous hyperplasia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electrosurgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electrocirugía</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Aug 09 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con electrocirugía del rinofima moderado-grave.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrosurgery for the Treatment of Moderate or Severe Rhinophyma.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas dermo-sifiliograficas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
