<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28818290</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-147X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calatayud, David</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Cabús, Santiago</dc:author>
<dc:author>Resendiz, Aridai</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Valdecasas, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fondevila, Constantino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuster, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sampson, Jaime</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, Victor</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION We analyze major liver resections performed in 10 years, with the objective of evaluating perioperative results. As secondary objectives, factors related to major complications and comparative analyses of 25-year periods are evaluated. METHODS Retrospective analysis of patients undergoing major hepatic resection (3 or more segments) from January 2005 to December 2014, from pre, intra and postoperative data. The Clavien classification is used for postoperative morbidity. RESULTS A total of 416 major hepatectomies were performed. Transfusions were performed in 38 patients (9.1%). A Pringle maneuver was used in 47.7% of the cases. Half of the patients had no complications, and only 96 patients (23%) had a major complication. Bile leakage was the most frequent complication (n=72, 17.3% of patients), especially due to malignant disease and biliary reconstruction, high risk ASA (III-IV) and prolonged surgical time. Thirteen patients met criteria for liver failure, of which 7died (5 associated a bacterial infection). The mean hospital stay was 12.5 days, with an 11,8% readmission rate. When comparing 25-year periods, at present more complex patients are operated on, with a lower incidence of transfusions and complications (ns). CONCLUSIONS Liver surgery has increased significantly in recent years. Surgical management of the liver now allows safe and effective surgery, with a very low complication rate. The limit of resectability depends on the residual hepatic volume.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hepatectomía mayor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Complicaciones postoperatorias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Major hepatectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Laparoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postoperative complications</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resección hepática mayor: una cirugía segura y eficaz.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatic resection: a safe and effective surgery.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
