<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28825234</identifier>
<setSpec>2386-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Colás Oros, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arribas Entrala, Belén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodero Álvarez, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caudevilla Martínez, Aranzazu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferreras Amez, José María</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Noain, Alberto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarrat Torres, Marco Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aladrén Pérez, Belén</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To study the effect of an emergency department sepsis code on the degree of compliance with measures recommended by the Surviving Sepsis Campaign and short-term mortality in the Spanish Autonomous Community of Aragon. MATERIAL AND METHODS Quasi-experimental study of 2 case cohorts, one including of cases before implementation of the sepsis code and one included cases managed afterwards. We extracted retrospectively data from hospital records for infectious processes and organ failures between December 2012 and January 2013 for the pre-code group and between December 2014 and January 2015 for the post-code group. Staff training sessions on the campaign recommendations were provided and the code, which specified clinical pathways, was activated electronically on inputting clinical variables at the moment of triage. Outcome measures were the percentage of compliance with the campaign's recommendations in the first 3 hours after a patient's arrival at the emergency department in-hospital mortality, and 30-day mortality. RESULTS A total of 222 cases were included in each group. Compliance with the following campaign recommendations improved after implementation of the sepsis code: antibiotic therapy in the first hour (P=.100), extractions for blood cultures (P 001), lactic acid measurement (P 001), and recommended fluid loading (P 001). In-hospital mortality was 31.1% in the pre-code cohort and 20.7% post-code; 30-day mortality rates were 30.1% and 19.8%, respectively (P=.016, all comparisons). CONCLUSION Use of a sepsis code led to short-term improvement in how often the measures recommended by a sepsis survival campaign were put into practice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento antibiótico en la primera hora</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Emergency department</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urgencias médicas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Improvement strategies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estrategias de mejora</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sepsis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibiotics, first hour</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de los resultados antes y después de la implantación del Código Sepsis en Aragón.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Estudiar el grado de cumplimiento del grupo de medidas de la Campaña Sobrevivir a la Sepsis (CSS) y su efecto en la mortalidad a corto plazo y tras la implantación de un código sepsis (CS) en Aragón. 
             Estudio cuasiexperimental que comparó dos cohortes antes (grupo pre-CS) y después (grupo pos-CS) de la implantación de un CS. Se seleccionaron retrospectivamente, a través de un registro administrativo, los episodios correspondientes a procesos infecciosos o con disfunción orgánica entre diciembre de 2012 y enero de 2013 (pre-CS) y entre diciembre de 2014 y enero de 2015 (pos-CS). El CS consistió en la activación electrónica desde triaje a partir de parámetros clínicos alterados, la definición de rutas de atención específica y la formación basada desde el triaje en la CSS. Las variables de resultado fueron porcentaje de cumplimiento del grupo de medidas de las CSS en las tres primeras horas desde la llegada a urgencias, mortalidad intrahospitalaria y a los 30 días. 
             Se incluyeron 222 pacientes en cada grupo. El porcentaje de cumplimiento fue mayor tras la implantación del CS respecto la aplicación del antibiótico en la primera hora (p = 0,100), la extracción de hemocultivos (p 0,001), la determinación del ácido láctico (p 0,001) y la aplicación de volumen aplicado/indicado (p 0,001). La mortalidad intrahospitalaria fue de 31,1% en el grupo pre-CS y de 20,7% en el grupo pos-CS (p = 0,016) y la mortalidad a los 30 días fue de 30,1% en el grupo pre-CS y de 19,8% en el grupo pos-CS (p = 0,016). 
             La implantación de un CS ha mostrado una mejora en la aplicación de las medidas recomendadas y en la supervivencia a corto plazo. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Before-after study of the effect of implementing a sepsis code for emergency departments in the community of Aragon].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Emergencias : revista de la Sociedad Espanola de Medicina de Emergencias</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
