<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28865709</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>García-Baquero, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Lanzac, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">CONTEXT There has been a boom in recent years in urological procedures using minilaparoscopy (ML). OBJECTIVE To conduct a systematic review of the published evidence on ML and its current role in urology. ACQUISITION OF EVIDENCE We performed a search on MedLine spanning October 1983 to December 2016 according to PRISMA criteria. A total of 6 comparative articles and 13 series were selected for this manuscript. SUMMARY OF THE EVIDENCE Only 1 study was randomised, 4 studies were prospective and comparative, and most were case series in which the operations were performed with 3-mm instruments. The most common procedures were adrenalectomy, followed by nephrectomy, living donor and pyeloplasty. Other minor conditions were also operated on, including cyst decortications, pyelolithotomies, lymphadenectomies, varicocelectomies and orchiectomies. DISCUSSION There have been significant technical improvements in recent years in the materials of ML. Most procedures were for reconstructive surgery and by transperitoneal approach, with a gradually increasing number of cases of oncologic surgery. Only 36.8% of the series assessed the cosmetic results with validated questionnaires, and 68.4% of the studies used the visual analogue scale to measure pain during the postoperative period. CONCLUSIONS The level of evidence of most published studies is low. ML is a reproducible technique for urological surgery and is safe even for operations on large surgical masses. The procedure's cosmetic and pain results after surgery are superior to those of conventional laparoscopy, although these conclusions should be taken with caution given the limitations of the current studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Revisión</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Minilaparoscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Review</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Minilaparoscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urology</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Aug 30 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Minilaparoscopia en urología: revisión sistemática.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minilaparoscopy in urology: Systematic review.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
