<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28865758</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1860</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Guerrero-Santillán, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zapatero-Gaviria, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda-Camino, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernal-Bello, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canora-Lebrato, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García de Viedma-García, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Velázquez-Ríos, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Duarte-Millán, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cristóbal-Bilbao, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To assess the effect of high doses of corticosteroids in patients hospitalised for exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). PATIENTS AND METHODS A prospective cohort study was conducted on patients hospitalized with COPD between January and March 2015, grouped according to the glucocorticoid dosage administered (cutoff, 40mg of prednisone/day). We compared the results of hospital stay, readmission and mortality at 3 months of discharge. RESULTS We analysed 87 patients. The median daily dose was 60mg of prednisone (interquartile range, 46.67-82.33mg/day), and the administration route was intravenous in 96.6% of the cases. We established a relative risk (RR) for hospital stays longer than 8 days of 1.095 (95% CI 0.597-2.007; P=.765) when steroid dosages greater than 40mg/day were employed. In these patients, the hazard ratio (HR) for readmission in the 3 months after discharge was 0.903 (95% CI 0.392-2.082; P=.811), and the mortality was 1.832 (95% CI 0.229-16.645; P=.568). Neither the RR nor the HR varied in a statistically significant manner after adjusting for confounding factors. CONCLUSIONS A daily dose greater than 40mg of prednisone in patients hospitalised for COPD exacerbation was not associated with a shorter hospital stay or a reduction in readmissions or mortality at 3 months.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Glucocorticoids</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mortality</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mortalidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hospitalización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Glucocorticoides</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hospitalisation</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dosis altas de corticoides sistémicos en pacientes ingresados por exacerbación de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica. Un estudio de cohortes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High doses of systemic corticosteroids in patients hospitalised for exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. A cohort study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
