<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28870422</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yubero-Serrano, Elena M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramirez-Lara, Irene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lopez-Miranda, Jose</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marin, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanchez-Garcia, M Esther</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alcala-Diaz, Juan F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perez-Martinez, Pablo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ordovas, Jose M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco-Molina, Angeles</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leon-Acuña, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lopez-Moreno, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camargo, Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado-Lista, Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tinahones, Francisco José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gomez-Delgado, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Microcirculation disturbances have been associated to most of the cardiovascular risk factors as well as to multiple inflammatory diseases. However, whether these abnormalities are specifically augmented in patients with coronary heart disease is still unknown. We aimed to evaluate if there is a relationship between the presence of coronary heart disease and the existence of functional and structural capillary abnormalities evaluated in the cutaneous microcirculation by videocapillaroscopy. MATERIAL AND METHODS Two matched samples of 30 participants with and without coronary heart disease but with similar clinical and anthropometric characteristics were evaluated by videocapillaroscopy at the dorsal skin of the third finger of the non-dominant hand. We calculated basal capillary density as well as capillary density after a period of arterial and venous occlusion in order to evaluate functionality and maximum capillary density. We also measured capillary recruitment. RESULTS Microvascular capillary density at rest was significantly lower in patients suffering from coronary heart disease than in controls. This fact was also found after dynamic tests (arterial and venous occlusion), suggesting functional impairments. Capillary recruitment of the samples was not different in our sample. CONCLUSIONS In our study, patients with coronary heart disease exhibit functional and structural microvascular disturbances. Although this is a very preliminary study, these findings open the door for further studying the microvascular functionality in coronary patients and how it relates to the response to treatment and/or the prognosis of the disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Densidad capilar</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>CORDIOPREV clinical trial</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ensayo clínico CORDIOPREV</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Capillaroscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Capillary density</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Microvascular dysfunction</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Capilaroscopia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiopatía isquémica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cutaneous microcirculation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Coronary artery disease</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Disfunción microvascular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Microcirculación cutánea</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2018 Feb 23 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación cuantitativa de los cambios microvasculares capilaroscópicos en pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica establecida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantitative evaluation of capillaroscopic microvascular changes in patients with established coronary heart disease.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
