<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28882616</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Juanola Roura, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Seoane-Mato, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz Sanz, Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gomollón, Fernando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montoro, Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To define clinical screening criteria for spondyloarthritis (SpA) in patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) and vice versa, which can be used as a reference for referring them to the rheumatology or gastroenterology service. METHOD Systematic literature review and a two-round Delphi method. The scientific committee and the expert panel were comprised of 2 rheumatologists and 2 gastroenterologists, and 7 rheumatologists and 7 gastroenterologists, respectively. The scientific committee defined the initial version of the criteria, taking into account sensitivity, specificity, standardization and ease of application. Afterwards, members of the expert panel assessed each item in a two-round Delphi survey. Items that met agreement in the first or second round were included in the final version of the criteria. RESULTS Positive screening for SpA if at least one of the following is present: onset of chronic low back pain before 45 years of age; inflammatory low back pain or alternating buttock pain; HLA-B27 positivity; sacroiliitis on imaging; arthritis; heel enthesitis; dactylitis. Positive screening for IBD in the presence of one of the major criteria or at least two minor criteria. Major: rectal bleeding; chronic diarrhea with organic characteristics; perianal disease. Minor: chronic abdominal pain; iron deficiency anemia or iron deficiency; extraintestinal manifestations; fever or low grade fever, of unknown origin and duration &gt;1week; unexplained weight loss; family history of IBD. CONCLUSION Screening criteria for IBD in patients with SpA, and vice versa, have been developed. These criteria will be useful for early detection of both diseases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Diagnóstico precoz</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedades inflamatorias del intestino</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Screening</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Early diagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Inflammatory bowel diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Espondiloartropatías</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spondyloarthropathies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cribado</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2018 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios de cribado de enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal y espondiloartritis para derivación de pacientes entre Reumatología y Gastroenterología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening of Inflammatory Bowel Disease and Spondyloarthritis for Referring Patients Between Rheumatology and Gastroenterology.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
