<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28888401</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López-Calleja, Ana Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iglesia, Berta María Pilar Vela</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómara-Lomero, Marta María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cerón, Isabel Ferrer</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pinilla, María José Revillo</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Antonio Rezusta</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Our objective was to characterize the enzymatic β-lactam resistance in clinical Enterobacteriaceae isolates with diminished susceptibility to carbapenems from 2013 to 2014 at Hospital Universitario Miguel Servet. MATERIAL/METHODS A total of 63 clinical isolates were analyzed for the presence of carbapenemases (KPC, OXA-48 and MBL), ESBLs and AmpC enzymes by combined disk methods and PCR detection of carbapenemase-encoding and beta-lactamase-encoding genes. RESULTS Fifteen isolates had a phenotypic test compatible with carbapenemase production; two of these were confirmed by PCR as OXA-48 producers. ESBL detection was positive in 27 isolates (43%); plasmid-mediated AmpC was detected in nine isolates (14.2%) and derepressed AmpC β-lactamase was present in 18 isolates (28%). CONCLUSION During the study period, the decreased susceptibility to carbapenems in Enterobacteriaceae in our area was not due to true carbapenemases but rather to β-lactamase activity (82.5% were ESBL or AmpC producers), probably in combination with decreased permeability of the outer membrane.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Biología molecular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antibiotic resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Carbapenemase</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Carbapenemasa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Molecular biology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resistencia antibiótica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enterobacteriaceae</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Sep 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of carbapenemases and other mechanisms of enzymatic resistance to β-lactams in Enterobacteriaceae with diminished susceptibility to carbapenems in a tertiary care hospital.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
