<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28891797</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>León-Medina, Paula</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artiles-Ortega, Carolina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artiles-Hernández, José Luis</dc:author>
<dc:author>Armas-Molina, José Vicente</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the overall survival rate and renal function in our series after radical nephrectomy (RN) and partial nephrectomy (PN) in renal tumors in an early stage. METHODS We retrospectively reviewed the medical records of 229 patients who underwent RN or PN for renal cancer T1-T2N0M0 in our center between 1995 and 2015. We described demographic factors, first symptom, TNM, histology, post-surgery data, recurrence rate and renal function. We utilized Fisher test, Chi square test and T-Student and we considered statistical significance when p&lt;0.05. RESULTS 203 patients underwent RN and 26 PN. 39.4% of the tumors who received RN were T1bN0M0 and 76.92% of PN were T1aN0M0. We report nine complications grade II of modified Clavien System for RN and only one grade I for PN. We detected an 11.3% recurrence in RN and none in PN. 66%of patients from RN are alive today, 12.81% died as result of renal cancer and 22.7% suffered a non-cancer-specific death. No deaths were observed in PN group. We observed similar mean preoperative serum creatinine (Cr) in both groups. Creatinine after the first post-operative month was 1.81mg/dL and 1.06mg/dL for RN and PN, respectively; At one year post-operative we registered Cr 1.82mg/dL and Cr 0.97mg/dL, respectively. CONCLUSIONS Both methods provide excellent oncologic results for renal carcinoma in an early stage. PN is safe and reduces the incidence of renal dysfunction with a lower rate of non-cancer-specific death.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia y función renal tras nefrectomía parcial y radical en tumores renales malignos localizados.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Overall survival and renal function after partial and radical nephrectomy in malignant localized renal tumors.]</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
