<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28895694</identifier>
<setSpec>1668-3501</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Özdemir, Fatih M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kara, Ahu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Düzgöl, Mine</dc:author>
<dc:author>Devrim, İlker</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bayram, Nuri</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Linezolid may cause adverse effects such as thrombocytopenia, which were found to be dependent on receiving linezolid for longer than 2 weeks. There are limited studies concerning the safety and timing of linezolid-related adverse effects in children. Objective of this study was to evaluate the incidence of adverse effects associated with linezolid, with especially focusing on the time of occurrence. POPULATION AND METHODS All children (&lt;18 years of age) who received &gt;3 days of linezolid therapy were included in this study. Adverse effects attributed to linezolid and time of occurrence of side effects was evaluated. RESULTS A total of 179 children were enrolled to the study. The patients' median age was 4 years (6 days to 17 years). During linezolid treatment, 36 (20.1%) patients experienced adverse effects. The most common adverse effect was thrombocytopenia that was detected in 26 patients (14.5%). Other adverse effects were as following; elevated liver enzymes in 4 patients, leucopenia and anemia in 2 patients, renal function impairment in one patient, and serious skin reactions in 3 patients. Adverse effects were detected within median 7.5 days of therapy (ranging from 4 to 18 days). Among 36 patients, 26 (72.2%) patients had adverse effect on the first 10 days of therapy. CONCLUSION Transient adverse effects were detected in 20.1% of the patients during linezolid therapy. These adverse effects may be detected earlier than ten days of treatment. Linezolid should be prescribed safely in children with monitoring adverse effects especially platelet count and level of liver enzymes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Linezolid</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Thrombocytopenia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adverse effects</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Child</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 01 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos adversos relacionados con la linezolida en la práctica clínica pediátrica.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La linezolida puede causar efectos adversos, como trombocitopenia, que, según lo observado, se relacionan con la administración de linezolida durante más de 2 semanas. Se ha realizado una cantidad limitada de estudios sobre la seguridad y el momento de aparición de los efectos adversos relacionados con la linezolida en los niños. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la incidencia de los efectos adversos asociados con la linezolida, especialmente en relación con el momento de su aparición. 
             Se incluyeron a todos los niños (&lt; 18 años de edad) que recibieron tratamiento con linezolida durante &gt; 3 días. Se evaluaron los efectos adversos atribuidos a la linezolida y el momento de aparición de los efectos secundarios. 
             En total, se incluyeron 179 niños. La mediana de edad de los pacientes fue 4 años (entre 6 días y 17 años). Durante el tratamiento con linezolida, 36 (20,1%) pacientes tuvieron efectos adversos. El efecto adverso más frecuente fue la trombocitopenia, detectada en 26 (14,5%) pacientes. Los demás efectos adversos fueron: elevación de las enzimas hepáticas en 4 pacientes, leucopenia y anemia en 2 pacientes, disfunción renal en 1 y reacciones cutáneas graves en 3 pacientes. Los efectos adversos se detectaron dentro de una mediana de 7,5 días de tratamiento (intervalo: de 4 a 18 días). Entre los 36 pacientes, 26 (72,2%) presentaron un efecto adverso en los primeros 10 días de tratamiento. 
             Se detectaron efectos adversos transitorios en el 20,1% de los pacientes durante el tratamiento con linezolida. Estos efectos adversos podrían detectarse antes de los 10 días de tratamiento. La linezolida debe recetarse de manera segura a los niños siempre que se vigilen los efectos adversos, en especial el recuento de trombocitos y el nivel de enzimas hepáticas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linezolid-related adverse effects in clinical practice in children.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
