<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>28965962</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cano Pérez, Óscar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pombo Jiménez, Marta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Coma Samartín, Raúl</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fidalgo Andrés, María Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorente Carreño, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES This report describes the results of analysis of implanted pacemakers reported to the Spanish Pacemaker Registry. METHODS The analysis was based on information provided by the European Pacemaker Identification Card. RESULTS Information was received from 115 hospitals, with a total of 12 697 cards, representing 32.3% of the estimated activity. Use of conventional and resynchronization pacemakers was 818 and 79 units per million inhabitants, respectively. A total of 200 leadless pacemakers were implanted. The mean age of the patients receiving an implant was 77.8 years, and 52% of devices were implanted in persons older than 80 years. In all, 74.9% were first implants and 23.4% corresponded to generator exchange. Endocardial leads were bipolar, 82.9% with active fixation, and 16.1% had magnetic resonance imaging protection. Most patients received bicameral sequential pacing, although single chamber pacing VVI(R) was used in 26.7% of the patients with sick sinus syndrome and in 23.8% of those with atrioventricular block, despite sinus rhythm. CONCLUSIONS Total use of pacemaker generators in Spain has increased by 1.6% compared with 2015. Most implanted leads have active fixation and less than 20% have magnetic resonance imaging protection. Age and sex directly influenced pacing mode selection, which could be improved in around 32% of patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Biventricular pacing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Registro</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Marcapasos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Permanent cardiac pacing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cables marcapasos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Registry</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pacemaker leads</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estimulación biventricular</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Pacemaker Registry. 14th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Cardiac Pacing (2016).</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
