<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29029763</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vergara, Andrea</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cepas, Virginio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Xercavins, Mariona</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, Yuly</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juncosa, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanfeliú, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez, Josefa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra, Elena</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bosch, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz, Sergi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soto, Sara Maria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Andreu, Antonia</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Streptococcus agalactiae, or group B streptococci (GBS), is the main aetiological agent of early neonatal sepsis in developed countries. This microorganism belongs to the gastrointestinal tract microbiota wherefrom it can colonize the vagina and be vertically transmitted to the child either before or at birth, and subsequently cause infection in the newborn. Approximately, 50% of newborns born to women with GBS become colonized, with 1-2% developing early neonatal infection if no preventive intervention is performed. The aim of this study was to characterize and compare serotypes, virulence factors and antimicrobial resistance of GBS isolates collected from pregnant women and newborns in several hospitals in Catalonia. METHODS 242 GBS strains were analyzed including 95 colonizers and 68 pathogenic strains isolated from pregnant women, and 79 strains isolated from neonates with sepsis in order to determine serotype, virulence and antimicrobial resistance. RESULTS Serotype distribution was different among the three groups, with serotypes Ia and II being significantly more frequent among colonizing strains (p=0.001 and 0.012, respectively). Virulence factors bca and scpB were significantly more frequent among neonatal strains than pathogenic or colonizing strains (p=0.0001 and 0.002, respectively). Pathogenic strains were significantly more resistant to erythromycin, clindamycin and azithromycin than their non-pathogenic counterparts. CONCLUSIONS Taking into account that neonatal sepsis represents a significant problem on a global scale, epidemiological surveillance, antimicrobial resistance and GBS virulence at the local level could provide important knowledge about these microorganisms as well as help to improve treatment and prevent invasive infection caused by this microorganism.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Virulence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Virulencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resistencia antimicrobiana</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Serotypes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antimicrobial resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Serotipos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Streptococcus agalactiae</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serotype, virulence profile, antimicrobial resistance and macrolide-resistance determinants in Streptococcus agalactiae isolates in pregnant women and neonates in Catalonia, Spain.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
