<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29033123</identifier>
<setSpec>1988-3013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jáudenes-Casaubón, Carmen</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sequí-Canet, Jose Miguel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vivanco-Allende, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez-Batalla, Faustino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zubicaray-Ugarteche, Jose</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence and the prevalence rates of otitis media with effusion (OME) are high. However, there is evidence that only a minority of professionals follow the recommendations provided in clinical practice guidelines. For the purpose of improving diagnosis and treatment of OME in children to prevent and/or reduce its impact on children's development, the Commission for the Early Detection of Deafness (CODEPEH) has deeply reviewed the scientific literature on this field and has drafted a document of recommendations for a correct clinical reaction to of OME, including diagnosis and medical and surgical treatment methodology. Among others, medication, in particular antibiotics and corticoids, should not be prescribed and 3 months of watchful waiting should be the first adopted measure. If OME persists, an ENT doctor should assess the possibility of sugical treatment. The impact of OME in cases of children with a comorbidity is higher, so it requires immediate reaction, without watchful waiting.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Clinical practice guideline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tympanostomy tubes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Guía de práctica clínica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Otitis media with effusion</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tubos de drenajes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adenoidectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Otitis media secretora</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adenoidectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 13 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento de la otitis media secretora infantil: recomendaciones CODEPEH.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and treatment of otitis media with effusion: CODEPEH recommendations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
