<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29069267</identifier>
<setSpec>1518-8345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pereira, Silviane Galvan</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos, Claudia Benedita Dos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Doring, Marlene</dc:author>
<dc:author>Portella, Marilene Rodrigues</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE to identify the prevalence of falls among older adults and the extrinsic factors associated with them. METHOD population-based cross-sectional study with 350 older adults. A household survey was conducted using a questionnaire addressing socio-demographic, clinical, and environmental characteristics. Data were analyzed using Stata Software V.10. Pearson's chi-square test and logistic regression analysis were used with stepwise criteria for selection of variables in the model, with measures of effect expressed in Prevalence Ratio. For input into the multiple model, the variables with p ≤ 0.20 were considered. All ethical care regarding research on human beings has been observed and respected. RESULTS the prevalence of falls was 46.9%. The extrinsic factors associated with falls were: stairs, uneven floor and pets in the main entrance, lack of anti-slip loose throw rugs and slippery floor in the kitchen, lack of anti-slip loose throw rugs and objects on the floor in the room, lack of grab bars in the shower, lack of grab bars in the toilet and switch away from the bathroom door (p &lt;0.05). CONCLUSION falls are frequent in long-lived adults. The identification of the extrinsic factors associated with the occurrence of this event can help in its prevention.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 19 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of household falls in long-lived adults and association with extrinsic factors.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
