<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29077293</identifier>
<setSpec>2386-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pi-Figueras Valls, María</dc:author>
<dc:author>Supervía Caparrós, August</dc:author>
<dc:author>Clemente Rodríguez, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pallàs Villaronga, Oriol</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aranda Cárdenas, María Dolores</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cirera Lorenzo, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To compare cases of poisoning according to age to detect differences in frequency of visits to the emergency department, patient characteristics, case management, and immediate outcome in terms of related mortality. MATERIAL AND METHODS Descriptive study of a retrospective series of patients who visited a university hospital emergency department for treatment of poisoning between 2009 and 2014. We collected patient characteristics and data related to the event, case management, and poisoning-related death. Patients were grouped according to age (cut-off 65 y). RESULTS Of a total of 3847 poisoning episodes, 341 (8.9%) were in patients aged 65 years or older. The percentage of women among these older patients (61.3%) was greater than among younger patients (36.3%; P&lt;.001). Poisoning was accidental in older patients more often than younger ones (64.4% vs 9.5%, respectively; P&lt;.001), occurred more often in the home (82.1% vs 37%, P&lt;.001), and more often required active treatment (73.3% vs 57.4%; P&lt;.001) and admission to hospital (21.4% vs 7.3%, P&lt;.001). The related mortality rate was also higher in the older patients (2.1% vs 0.1% in younger patients, P&lt;.001). CONCLUSION The percentage of poisonings in patients aged 65 years or older is not negligible. Poisoning in patients of advanced age tends to be accidental and take place in the home. Older patients more often require active treatment and hospital admission; poisoning-related death is more common in older patients than younger ones.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Drug abuse</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Medications</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Servicio de urgencias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Drogas de abuso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Poisoning</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ancianos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Advanced age</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Intoxicaciones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fármacos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Emergency health services</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características diferenciales de las intoxicaciones en los pacientes ancianos atendidos en un servicio de urgencias.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Evaluar si existen diferencias, en función de la edad, en la frecuencia, las características, el manejo y el resultado inmediato en los episodios con diagnóstico de intoxicación en un servicio de urgencias (SU). 
             Estudio descriptivo de una serie de casos retrospectivo de las visitas por intoxicaciones atendidas en el SU de un hospital universitario entre 2009 y 2014. Se recogieron datos demográficos, referentes a la intoxicación y su manejo y la mortalidad inmediata relacionada con el episodio. La serie se dividió en función de la edad (punto de corte: 65 años). 
             De total de 3.847 episodios de intoxicación, 341 (8,9%) casos fueron en los pacientes de 65 o más años. La mayoría de estos casos, en comparación con los más jóvenes, fueron mujeres (61,3% vs 36,3%; p 0,001), de causa accidental (64,4% vs 9,5%; p &lt; 0,001), ocurrieron en el domicilio (82,1% vs 37%; p &lt; 0,001), precisaron más frecuentemente tratamiento activo (73,3% vs 57,4%; p &lt; 0,001) e ingreso (21,4% vs 7,3%; p &lt; 0,001) y tuvieron mayor mortalidad inmediata (2,1% vs 0,1%; p &lt; 0,001). 
             El porcentaje de intoxicaciones en pacientes de 65 años o más no es despreciable, suelen ser accidentales y en domicilio, y tienen mayor necesidad de tratamiento activo, hospitalización y mortalidad inmediata. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characteristics of emergency poisoning cases in elderly versus younger patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Emergencias : revista de la Sociedad Espanola de Medicina de Emergencias</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
