<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29074167</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dosal-Galguera, Angelina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Monllor-Nunell, M Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanchez-Lloansí, Meritxell</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The treatment of chronic hepatitis C with direct action antivirals has led to a radical change in the management of patients. The elderly or people with morbidities, for whom it was previously contraindicated, are currently candidates for this treatment due to its being well tolerated and safe. The nursing visit at the beginning of treatment is essential to reinforce adherence, to educate on the management of adverse effects, to resolve doubts and to emphasise the importance of pharmacological interactions, in order to promote correct therapeutic compliance. However, due to the new communication tools, it is possible to convey healthcare services without requiring the physical presence of the patient in the medical centre. The telephone has become a routine and indispensable work tool for the nursing professional. This paper describes the pilot test that was performed with 38 patients, previously selected, whose nursing visit at the beginning of treatment was by telephone instead of face-to-face, in order to evaluate the implementation of the telephone nurse consultation, for patients who started treatment with direct antivirals for the hepatitis C virus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Medication adherence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atención de enfermería</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Direct-acting antiviral agents</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nursing care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Patient education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Educación del paciente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Antivirales de acción directa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hepatitis C</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cumplimiento de la medicación</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov - Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento antiviral directo en pacientes con hepatitis virus C: implementación de una consulta telefónica enfermera.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Direct antiviral treatment in patients with hepatitis C virus: Implementation of a nurse telephone consultation.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermeria clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
