<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29089115</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruiz-Carrascosa, José Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz-Villaverde, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina-Leyva, Alejandro</dc:author>
<dc:author>Garrido-Pareja, Fermín</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES Psoriasis is associated to endothelial dysfunction, which causes impaired vascular functioning. TNF-α blockers have shown the ability to improve vascular functioning in psoriasis. The nailfold vessel resistance index (NVRI) assesses microvascular functioning at nailfold. The objectives of the study is to assess the effect of the TNF-α inhibition with adalimumab on NVRI. MATERIAL AND METHODS Quasi-experimental study. Fifteen patients with moderate-severe psoriasis received adalimumab 40mg sc according to label information. Participants were assessed at baseline and at 12, 24 and 52 weeks after study intervention. RESULTS A reduction of -0.09±0.02 (P&lt;.01) in NVRI and a -11.2±2,41ng/ml (P&lt;.001) in E-selectin was observed at week 52. CONCLUSIONS Adalimumab could produce a progressive and sustained reduction of vessel resistance at nailfold and E-selectin in patients with psoriasis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Nails/blood supply</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ecografía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psoriasis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Vascular resistance</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Uñas/aporte sanguíneo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Ultrasonography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Microvessels</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Microvascularización</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adalimumab</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Doppler</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resistencia vascular</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 28 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La inhibición del TNF-α puede disminuir los biomarcadores de disfunción endotelial en pacientes con psoriasis de moderada-grave: un estudio cuasiexperimental eco doppler a 52 semanas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">TNF-alpha inhibition could reduce biomarkers of endothelial dysfunction in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis: A 52-week echo-Doppler based quasi-experimental study.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
