<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29094825</identifier>
<setSpec>2386-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Quesada Redondo, Loreto</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barceló Martín, Bernardino</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morell García, Daniel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Puiguriguer Ferrando, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">EN To identify analytical factors associated with mortality in patients with type-2 diabetes under long-term treatment with metformin who come to the emergency department with acute symptoms of lactic acidosis. Retrospective observational analysis of patient records in a referral hospital. We collected clinical data and laboratory results for a series of metformin-treated patients with type-2 diabetes who developed lactic acidosis, stratified by severity. Factors related to the episode were analyzed for associations with mortality or survival. Of 16 patients studied (mean age 70 years; range, 60-77 years), 75% had gastrointestinal symptoms in the 5 days before they came to the emergency department. Mortality (19%) was associated with sepsis on arrival; elevated white blood cell counts, particularly neutrophil counts; low platelet counts; high C-reactive protein (CRP) and procalcitonin levels; and 1 or more chronic concomitant diseases. Metformin concentration was not significantly associated with mortality. Signs of sepsis, high neutrophil counts with low platelet counts, elevated CRP and procalcitonin levels, and the presence of 1 or more concomitant diseases may be risk factors for death in metformin-treated patients with lactic acidosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Acidosis láctica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metformina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prognosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pronóstico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metformin</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Lactic acidosis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 02 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a mortalidad por acidosis láctica en pacientes diabéticos tratados con metformina.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             El objetivo de este estudio es la detección de parámetros analíticos asociados a la mortalidad en los pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) con tratamiento crónico con metformina que acuden a urgencias por un cuadro clínico agudo con presencia de acidosis láctica. Se trata de un estudio observacional-analítico retrospectivo realizado en un hospital de tercer nivel. Se recogieron datos clínicos y analíticos en una serie de pacientes con acidosis láctica, estratificada por gravedad, y tratamiento con metformina para DM2. Se compararon los resultados en función de la mortalidad o supervivencia del episodio. De 16 pacientes estudiados, con una edad media de 70 años (rango de 60 a 77), el 75% presentó sintomatología gastrointestinal los 5 días previos a su ingreso. La mortalidad total observada fue del 19%, que se asoció a la presencia de sepsis al ingreso, leucocitosis con neutrofilia, plaquetopenia, elevación de proteína C reactiva (PCR), valores altos de procalcitonina y la comorbilidad con una o más patologías crónicas. Las cifras séricas de metformina no se correlacionaron significativamente con la mortalidad. Se concluye que en pacientes con acidosis láctica y tratamiento con metformina pueden ser factores asociados a la mortalidad la presencia de criterios de sepsis, neutrofilia con plaquetopenia, elevación de PCR y de procalcitonina y la existencia de una o más patologías comórbidas. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors associated with death due to lactic acidosis in patients with type-2 diabetes treated with metformin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Emergencias : revista de la Sociedad Espanola de Medicina de Emergencias</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
