<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29095002</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vasquez, Fabián</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burrows, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Diaz, Erik</dc:author>
<dc:author>Curi, Katherine</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lera, Lydia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Meza, Jorge</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Insulin resistance is the most common metabolic disorder associated with obesity and highest cardiometabolic risk in children. If the inadequate physical condition is added, they have a high risk of developing cardiometabolic complications at an early age. OBJECTIVE To evaluate physical fitness and insulin sensitivity in obese school children of 8-13 years of age from three public schools in the Metropolitan Region of Santiago. METHODS the study was carried out in 61 obese school children (25 Tanner I-II y 36 Tanner III-V). Anthropometric measures, Tanner stages, body composition (using 4-compartment model), physical fitness with the six-minute test and laboratory indicators, glucose, insulin and HOMA-IR, were measured. Metabolic syndrome was diagnosed according to the criteria of Cook. RESULTS Obese prepubertal and pubertal children and adolescents showed inadequate physical fitness, refl ected in the distance and heart rate during and after the six-minute test. In turn, the sample has a high prevalence of insulin resistance in conjunction with metabolic syndrome. CONCLUSIONS Regardless of the pubertal status, obese schoolchildren have a poor physical fitness and decreased insulin sensitivity reflected in a compensatory hyperinsulinemia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jul 28 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condición física y sensibilidad insulínica en un grupo de escolares obesos de 8 a 13 años según estado puberal.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             INTRODUCCIÓN: la resistencia a la insulina es la alteración metabólica más común relacionada con la obesidad y se asocia a un mayor riesgo cardiovascular en la edad pediátrica. Si a esto se suma una inadecuada condición física, existe un alto riesgo de desarrollar complicaciones cardiometabólicas tempranamente. OBJETIVO: evaluar la condición física y la resistencia insulínica en escolares obesos de 8 a 13 años de edad, seleccionados en tres establecimientos públicos de la Región Metropolitana de Santiago. MÉTODOS: el estudio se llevó a cabo en 61 escolares obesos (25 Tanner I-II y 36 Tanner III-V). Se realizaron mediciones antropométricas, etapas de Tanner, composición corporal con el modelo de cuatro compartimentos, condición física con el test de seis minutos (TM6min) e indicadores de laboratorio, glicemia, insulinemia y HOMA-IR. Se diagnosticó síndrome metabólico según criterio de Cook.RESULTADOS: los escolares y adolescentes obesos prepúberes y púberes presentan una inadecuada condición física, reflejada en la distancia recorrida y en la frecuencia cardiaca durante y posterior al TM6min. A su vez, la muestra presenta una alta prevalencia de resistencia a insulina en conjunto con síndrome metabólico. CONCLUSIONES: independientemente del estado puberal, los escolares obesos presentan una baja condición física y una disminución de la sensibilidad a la insulina, que se refleja en un hiperinsulinismo compensatorio. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Physical fitness and insulin sensitivity in a group of obese children from 8 to 13 years of age by puberal state].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
