<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29105427</identifier>
<setSpec>2386-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torres-Degayón, Virginia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Faus-Dáder, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baena-Parejo, María Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montero-Pérez, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Murillo, José Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calleja-Hernández, Miguel Angel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To detect the frequency of negative outcomes associated with medication in patients with permanent atrial fibrillation (AF) who are attended in a hospital emergency department, and to assess type and severity of such outcomes related to AF medications as well as the rate of preventable negative outcomes. MATERIAL AND METHODS Descriptive, observational cross-sectional study in patients with permanent AF who were attended in the emergency department of a tertiary care hospital during a 3-month period. A pharmacist interviewed the patients to record demographic characteristics, health problems, degree of functional impairment, and current drug treatments. An emergency physician and a pharmacist reviewed the patients' questionnaires and medical histories and evaluated them using the Dader method of pharmacotherapeutic follow-up. RESULTS Of the 210 patients assessed, 198 entered the final analysis. They had a mean (SD) age of 80.5 (7.3) years, and 114 (57.5%) were women. One handred and thirty-four (67.7%) patients had medication-related negative outcomes; 61 (45.5%) of the outcomes were related to treatment for permanent AF. Twenty-four of these 61 patients (39.3%) had problems affecting safety; 36 (59%) of the problems were caused by drugs to control heart rate. Of the 73 patients with negative outcomes unrelated to AF medication, 34 (46.6%) were related to necessary medications and 38 (52.1%) were taking antibiotics. The frequencies of avoidable negative outcomes were significantly different between the group of patients with problems related to drug therapy for AF (where 55.7% were due to medications considered unnecessary) and those with problems unrelated to AF medications (where 78.1% were from avoidable medications) (P=.010). However, the level of seriousness was similar. CONCLUSION Nearly two-thirds of patients with permanent AF who come to the emergency department have a medication- related negative outcome that may or may not be related to AF treatment. Problems from drugs taken for reasons other than AF could more easily be avoided.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Fibrilación auricular permanente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Resultados negativos asociados a la medicación</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Método Dáder</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pharmacotherapy, negative outcomes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Servicio de urgencias</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Permanent atrial fibrillation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento farmacológico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Emergency health services</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2016 Abr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados negativos asociados a la medicación en los pacientes con fibrilación auricular permanente atendidos en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Detectar la frecuencia de resultados negativos asociados a la medicación (RNM) en los pacientes con fibrilación auricular permanente (FAP) atendidos en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario (SUH), y evaluar su tipología, evitabilidad y gravedad en función de su relación con la terapia farmacológica para la fibrilación auricular (FA). 
             Estudio observacional descriptivo de una serie de casos con análisis transversal que incluyó a los pacientes atendidos con FAP en un servicio de urgencias (SU) de un hospital de tercer nivel durante 3 meses. Un farmacéutico entrevistó a los pacientes recogiendo datos demográficos, problemas de salud, grado de dependencia y terapia farmacológica. Un grupo evaluador, formado por un urgenciólogo y un farmacéutico, revisaron los cuestionarios y las historias clínicas para la evaluación de los RNM según el método Dáder. 
             Del total de 210 pacientes evaluados se incluyeron finalmente 198 pacientes con una edad media de 80,5 (DE 7,3) años, de los cuales 114 (57,5%) fueron mujeres. Ciento treinta y cuatro (67,7%) pacientes sufrieron un RNM, de los cuales 61 (45,5%) estaban relacionadas con el tratamiento de la FA (RNM-RTFA). De los 61 pacientes con RNM-RTFA, 24 (39,3%) fueron RNM de seguridad y 36 (59%) estaban causados por los fármacos para el control de la frecuencia. De los 73 pacientes con RNM no relacionadas con el tratamiento de la FA (RNM-NRTFA), 34 (46,6%) fueron RNM de necesidad y 38 (52,1%) eran por antibióticos. Entre los dos grupos, hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en cuanto a la evitabilidad (RNM-RTFA 55,7% vs RNM-NRTFA 78,1%; p = 0,010), pero no para la gravedad (p = 0,265). 
             Casi dos tercios de los pacientes con FAP que acuden a un SUH sufren un RNM relacionado o no con la medicación específica para la FA, siendo más evitables los RNM del grupo de fármacos no relacionados con el tratamiento de esta enfermedad. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Medication-related negative outcomes in patients with permanent atrial fibrillation attended in a hospital emergency department].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Emergencias : revista de la Sociedad Espanola de Medicina de Emergencias</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
