<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29108660</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1968</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Santos Lasaosa, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bellosta Diago, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Bravo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viloria Alebesque, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mauri Llerda, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Electroencephalography (EEG) is an essential diagnostic tool in epilepsy. Its use in emergency departments (ED) is usually restricted to the diagnosis and management of non-convulsive status epilepticus (NCSE). However, EDs may also benefit from EEG in the context of other situations in epilepsy. METHODS We conducted a retrospective observational study using the clinical histories of patients treated at our hospital's ED for epileptic seizures and suspicion of NCSE and undergoing EEG studies in 2015 and 2016. We collected a series of demographic and clinical variables. RESULTS Our sample included 87 patients (mean age of 44 years). Epileptic seizures constituted the most common reason for consultation: 59.8% due to the first episode of epileptic seizures (FES), 27.6% due to recurrence, and 12.6% due to suspected NCSE. Interictal epileptiform discharges (IED) were observed in 38.4% of patients reporting FES and in 33.3% of those with a known diagnosis of epilepsy. NCSE was confirmed by EEG in 36.4% of all cases of suspected NCSE. Presence of IED led to administration of or changes in long-term treatment in 59.8% of the patients. CONCLUSIONS EEG is a useful tool for seizure management in EDs, not only for severe, sudden-onset clinical situations such as NCSE but also for diagnosis in cases of non-affiliated epilepsy and in patients experiencing the first episode of epilepsy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Neurological emergencies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epilepsia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>First seizure</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Urgencias neurológicas</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epilepsy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electroencephalography</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Seizure</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estado epiléptico no convulsivo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Primera crisis epiléptica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Non-convulsive status epilepticus</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Crisis epiléptica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Electroencefalograma</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 03 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del electroencefalograma en el manejo de la epilepsia en el Servicio de Urgencias.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of electroencephalography for the management of epilepsy in emergency departments.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
