<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29111261</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz Del Campo Fontecha, Petra</dc:author>
<dc:author>Plasencia-Rodríguez, Chamaida</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, Mireia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez García, Julio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almodóvar, Raquel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Queiro, Rubén</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cañete, Juan D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torre Alonso, Juan Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montilla Morales, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The main purpose of this recommendation statement is to provide clinicians with the best available evidence and the best opinion agreed upon by the panelists for a rational use of synthetic disease modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs) and biologicals in psoriatic arthritis (PsA) patients. The present document also focuses on important aspects in the management of PsA, such as early diagnosis, therapeutic objectives, comorbidities and optimization of treatment. METHODS The recommendations were agreed by consensus by a panel of 8 expert rheumatologists, previously selected by the Spanish Society of Rheumatology (SER) through an open call. The phases of the work were: identification of key areas for updating the previous consensus, analysis and synthesis of scientific evidence (modified Oxford system, Centre for Evidence-based Medicine, 2009) and formulation of recommendations based on this evidence and by consensus techniques. RESULTS Seventeen recommendations were issued for the treatment of PsA patients. Six of them were of general nature, ranging from the early diagnosis and treatment to the importance of assessing comorbidities. The other 11 were focused on the indications for DMARDs and biological therapy in the distinct clinical forms of the disease. Likewise, the situation of failure of the first biological is addressed and treatment algorithms and a table with the different biological therapies are also included. CONCLUSIONS We present the update of SER recommendations for the treatment of PsA with DMARDs and biologics.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Recommendations</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spanish Society of Rheumatology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Disease modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fármacos antirreumáticos modificadores de la enfermedad (FAME) sintéticos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sociedad Española de Reumatología</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Treatment of psoriatic arthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tratamiento artritis psoriásica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Terapia biológica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Artritis psoriásica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recomendaciones</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Biologic therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Psoriatic arthritis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 27 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología sobre el tratamiento y uso de terapias sistémicas biológicas y no biológicas en artritis psoriásica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations of the Spanish Society of Rheumatology on treatment and use of systemic biological and non-biological therapies in psoriatic arthritis.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
