<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29126829</identifier>
<setSpec>1579-2129</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Acosta, Orlando</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viladot, Margarita</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barril, Silvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aparicio, Francisco</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero-Ortiz, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, Ana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo, Diego</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez-Portal, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Giner, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Interstitial lung diseases (ILD) and, in particular, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, may have a significant impact on patient survival. Recent studies highlight the need for palliative care (PC) in the management of ILD patients. The aim of this study was to determine the current situation of PC in patients in Spain. METHODS A 36-question survey addressing the main aspects of PC in ILD patients was designed. The survey was sent via email to all members of the Spanish Society of Pulmonology and Thoracic Surgery. Participation was voluntary. RESULTS One hundred and sixty-four participants responded to the survey. Ninety-eight percent said they were interested in PC, 46% had received specific training, and 44% reported being responsible for PC in their ILD patients. Symptom control and end-of-life stage were the most frequent reasons for referral to PC teams. Regarding end-of-life, 78% reported consensual agreement with patients on the limitation of therapeutic efforts, 35% helped prepare an end-of-life advance directive, and 22% agreed on the place of death. CONCLUSION Despite the well-known need for PC in patients with ILD and the notable interest of the survey participants in this subject, there are clear formative and organizational gaps that should be addressed to improve care in this area in ILD patients in Spain.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>End-of-life</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidados paliativos</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Final de vida</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedad pulmonar intersticial difusa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Palliative care</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Interstitial lung disease</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados paliativos en la enfermedad pulmonar intersticial difusa: resultados de una encuesta de ámbito nacional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palliative Care in Diffuse Interstitial Lund Disease: Results of a Spanish Survey.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
