<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29126909</identifier>
<setSpec>1405-9940</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Almeida-Gutiérrez, Eduardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Yáñez-Gutiérrez, Lucelli</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Gallegos, Diana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera-May, Jimena Lucely</dc:author>
<dc:author>Márquez-González, Horacio</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Congenital heart disease (CHD) has an incidence of 8-10 cases per 1000 live births. In Mexico, there are 18,000-20,000 new cases per year. Most tertiary care centers for CHD attend only pediatric population; the Mexican Institute of Social Security (IMSS) has a clinic that attends pediatric and adult population. OBJECTIVE To analyze the demographic aspects of the CHD clinic of IMSS. METHODS From 2011 to 2016 a cross-sectional study of the CC clinic of a third level hospital of the IMSS, including all patients with confirmed structural heart disease of recent diagnosis was carried out. The sex, age, reference entity, antecedent of pregnancy and treatment were registered. The population was divided into age ranges (&lt;2 years, 2.1-6 years, 6.1-10 years, 10.1-17 years and &gt;17.1 years). Descriptive statistics and χ2 test were used in qualitative variables. RESULTS 3,483 patients with CHD (male:female ratio, 0.8:1.2) were included. Increased pulmonary flow acyanogenic cardiopathies were the most frequent CHD group (47.2%), with atrial septal defect being the most frequent diagnosis overall; 25.6% were adults and 35% of women with a history of pregnancy. Chiapas was Federal entity with greater proportion of patients diagnosed in the adult stage (33.82%); 7% were not candidates for any treatment for complications of the disease. CONCLUSIONS CHD is a late diagnosis; it is necessary to create a national register to promote new health policies and a rational distribution of resources for these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Pregnancy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pediátrico</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Embarazo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Congenital heart diseases</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adulto</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Adult</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>México</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Enfermedades congénitas del corazón</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Epidemiology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Pediatric</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 07 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis demográfico de una clínica de cardiopatías congénitas del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, con interés en el adulto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Demographic analysis of a congenital heart disease clinic of the Mexican Institute of Social Security, with special interest in the adult].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
