<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29132842</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-9531</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Fresneda Gutiérrez, Reyes</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Castilla, José Domingo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Carapeto, Isabel</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To compare plasma glucose levels and incidence of hyperglycaemia in the post-operative period after general surgery using fluids with different glucose. METHODOLOGY A randomised, open-label, non-blind, clinical trial was conducted on patients admitted to Paediatric Intensive Care Unit after elective surgery. The inclusion criteria were from 6 months to 14 years of age, with a weight greater than 6kg, onset glucose level &gt;60mg/dL, and a signed informed consent, with no oral intake and maintenance intravenous fluid therapy using fluids with 3.3% or 5% glucose. Plasma glucose levels were measured before surgery, on admission, and 8, 24, and 48h, with the mean glucose levels and incidence of hyperglycaemia (glucose level &gt;150mg/dL) in both groups being compared. RESULTS A total of 60 patients received glucose/saline 1/3 (51mEq/L sodium and 33g/L glucose), and 70 glucose/saline 5/0.9% (154mEq/L sodium and 50g/L glucose). Mean glucose levels were higher in the group receiving glucose 5%, with no statistical difference. There was no significant difference in the incidence of hyperglycaemia; 8h: 26% in the 3.3% group vs. 21.3% in the 5% group (P=.63); 24h: 20% vs. 22.7% (P=.8); and 48h: 19% vs. 23.1% (P=.78). CONCLUSIONS The use of fluids with 3.3% glucose in the post-operative period of general surgery maintains mean glucose levels in a similar range to that of patients receiving fluids with 5% glucose, with no difference in the incidence of hyperglycaemia.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Hyperglycaemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Hiperglucemia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Maintenance intravenous fluid therapy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postoperatorio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fluidoterapia intravenosa de mantenimiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Post-operative</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 11 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de niveles de glucemia postoperatoria usando sueros con diferente concentración de glucosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[A comparison of post-surgical plasma glucose levels in patients on fluids with different glucose concentrations].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de pediatria (Barcelona, Spain : 2003)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
