<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29130707</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-5198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Casajús Mallén, José Antonio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ara Royo, Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznar Laín, Susana</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Blanco, Cristina</dc:author>
<dc:author>Artiga González, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabanillas Cruz, Esther</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Sarcopenic obesity (SO) is a term that refers to an increase of fat mass together with a decrease of muscle mass, which is suffered by a high percentage of elderly population. Physical activity seems to be a good strategy to prevent it getting worse. However, genetic factors related to the aging process and to elderly's physical fitness could have an influence on it. AIM To determine if elderly women &gt; 60 who practice physical activity regularly had differences in sarcopenic obesity according to the I/D polymorphism from the ACE (angiotensin converter enzyme) gen. METHODS Cross-sectional study of 300 elderly women who have practiced physical exercise at least twice a week for the past two years. Anthropometric data, physical activity and sedentary behaviour questionnaire, sarcopenic obesity (determining the percentage of fat mass and total muscle mass by electrical impedance and grouping the quintiles of these values into four groups) and physical fitness assessment, as well as ACE gen genotype measured by oral mucosa sample, were evaluated. RESULTS There were significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) in sarcopenic obesity according to ACE I/D genotype (SO values: 2.18 ACE DD vs 2.48 ACE II + ACE ID). CONCLUSIONS Women who were ACE DD presented lower risk of sarcopenic obesity than those in the ACE II and ACE ID groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Oct 24 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad sarcopénica en mujeres mayores: influencia del polimorfismo I/D de la enzima convertidora de angiotensina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sarcopenic obesity in elderly women: influence of I/D polymorphism of the angiotension converter enzyme].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
