<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29146482</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pessoa-Amorim, Guilherme</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fontes-Carvalho, Ricardo</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mancio, Jennifer</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribeiro, José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bettencourt, Nuno</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vouga, Luís</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gama, Vasco</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Left atrial dysfunction in aortic stenosis may precede atrial enlargement and predict the occurrence of atrial fibrillation (AF). To test this hypothesis, we assessed left atrial function and determined its impact on the incidence of AF after aortic valve replacement. METHODS A total of 149 severe aortic stenosis patients (74±8.6 years, 51% men) with no prior AF were assessed using speckle-tracking echocardiography. Left atrial function was evaluated using peak atrial longitudinal strain (PALS), peak atrial contraction strain (PACS), and phasic left atrial volumes. The occurrence of AF was monitored in 114 patients from surgery until hospital discharge. RESULTS In multiple linear regression, PALS and PACS were inversely correlated with left atrial dilation, left ventricular hypertrophy, and diastolic function. Atrial fibrillation occurred in 36 patients within a median time of 3 days [interquartile range, 1-4] after aortic valve replacement. In multiple Cox regression, PALS and PACS were independently associated with the incidence of AF (HR, 0.946; 95%CI, 0.910-0.983; P=.005 and HR, 0.932; 95%CI, 0.883-0.984; P=.011, respectively), even after further adjustment for left atrial dimensions. Both reduced PALS and PACS were associated with the incidence of AF in patients with nondilated left atria (P value for the interaction of PALS with left atrial dimensions=.013). CONCLUSIONS In severe aortic stenosis, left atrial dysfunction predicted the incidence of postoperative AF independently of left atrial dilation, suggesting that speckle-tracking echocardiography before surgery may help in risk stratification, particularly in patients with nondilated left atria.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Recambio de válvula aórtica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aortic stenosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estenosis aórtica</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estudio EPICHEART</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Estenosis aórtica grave</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Atrial fibrillation</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>EPICHEART study</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Aortic valve replacement</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Strain de la aurícula izquierda</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Fibrilación auricular</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Left atrial strain</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Severe aortic stenosis</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 13 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impaired Left Atrial Strain as a Predictor of New-onset Atrial Fibrillation After Aortic Valve Replacement Independently of Left Atrial Size.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
