<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29158075</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-5857</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero, Bernat</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferrer, Marc</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berastegui, Elisabet</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruyra, Xavier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Labata, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliveras, Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serra, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-García, Cosme</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rueda, Ferran</dc:author>
<dc:author>Camara, Maria-Luisa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Just, Maria-Soledad</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bayes-Genis, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVES Current postoperative management of adult cardiac surgery often comprises transfer from the intensive care unit (ICU) to a conventional ward. Intermediate care units (IMCU) permit hospital resource optimization. We analyzed the impact of an IMCU on length of stay (both ICU and in-hospital) and outcomes (in-hospital mortality and 30-day readmissions) after adult cardiac surgery (IMCU-CS). METHODS From November 2012 to April 2015, 1324 consecutive patients were admitted to a university hospital for cardiac surgery. In May 2014, an IMCU-CS was established for postoperative care. For the purposes of this study, patients were classified into 2 groups, depending on the admission period: pre-IMCU-CS (November 2012-April 2014, n=674) and post-IMCU-CS (May 2014-April 2015, n=650). RESULTS There were no statistically significant differences in age, sex, risk factors, comorbidities, EuroSCORE 2, left ventricular ejection fraction, or the types of surgery (valvular in 53%, coronary in 26%, valvular plus coronary in 11.5%, and aorta in 1.8%). The ICU length of stay decreased from 4.9±11 to 2.9±6 days (mean±standard deviation; P&lt;.001); 2 [1-4] to 1 [0-3] (median [Q1-Q3]); in-hospital length of stay decreased from 13.5±15 to 12.7±11 days (mean±standard deviation; P=.01); 9 [7-13] to 9 [7-11] (median [Q1-Q3]), in pre-IMCU-CS to post-IMCU-CS, respectively. There were no statistically significant differences in in-hospital mortality (4.9% vs 3.5%; P=.28) or 30-day readmission rate (4.3% vs 4.2%; P=.89). CONCLUSIONS After the establishment of an IMCU-CS for postoperative cardiac surgery, there was a reduction in ICU and in-hospital mean lengths of stay with no increase in in-hospital mortality or 30-day readmissions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Intermediate care unit</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cirugía cardiaca</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cuidado posoperatorio</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Unidad de cuidados intermedios</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cardiac surgery</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Postoperative care</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 17 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intermediate Care Unit After Cardiac Surgery: Impact on Length of Stay and Outcomes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de cardiologia (English ed.)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
