<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29169902</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Surià Sonet, Sònia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bibiloni, Maria Del Mar</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Blanco, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pujol-Puyané, Maria Cèlia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pujol-Plana, Noemí</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mercadé Fuentes, Sílvia</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ojer Fernández de Soto, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tur, Josep A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To assess a 6-month nutritional and physical activity intervention program on the nutritional status of overweight or obese and not very active 8-14 years old children by means of a controlled pre-post design (ACTIVA'T program). METHOD Pre-post study in 8-14 years old overweight or obese and low active children from Vilafranca del Penedès (Barcelona, Spain) randomized in control group (n = 51, 47.1% girls, nutritional intervention and ≤3h/wk physical activity) and ACTIVA'T group (n = 45, 37.8% girls, nutritional and physical activity ≥5h/wk intervention). Body mass index, waist/height index, and diet quality by means of KIDMED test at the beginning and at the end of the program were assessed. During the intervention, each participant was accompanied by a relative (father or mother) who performed the same activities as the children. RESULTS Dietary recommendations have positively changed the habits of both ACTIVA'T and control group. The reversion in the prevalence of overweight and obesity was 93.8% and 58.6%, respectively, in the ACTIVA'T group, compared to 25.0% and 35.8% in the control group. Abdominal obesity was decreased from 42.2% to 17.8% in the ACTIVA'T group and from 47.1% to 27.5% in the control group. CONCLUSIONS The program ACTIVA'T (nutritional education and physical activity promotion) improves the quality of diet and reverses the prevalence of overweight and obesity in the underactive child population.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Obesidad</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Obesity</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sedentarismo</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Mediterranean diet</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Dieta mediterránea</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sobrepeso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Overweight</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nutritional education</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Educación nutricional</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Activa’t</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Children</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Población infantil</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sedentary</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 20 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reversión de sobrepeso y obesidad en población infantil de Vilafranca del Penedès: Programa ACTIVA’T (2012).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reversion of overweight and obesity in Vilafranca del Penedès child population: ACTIVA'T Program (2012)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
