<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29174630</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Manso, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Antunes-Lopes, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martins-da-Silva, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alexandre, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Urinary incontinence (UI) is a complication of radical prostatectomy (RP) and transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP). The gold-standard treatment is the artificial urinary sphincter, however, new treatments have been investigated. OBJECTIVE To examine the outcome of an adjustable transobturator male system (ATOMS®) in men with UI after prostatic surgery in a low to medium volume continence center. MATERIALS AND METHODS Twenty-five men with UI were implanted with ATOMS® system between 2012 and 2014. The most common indication was UI after RP (92%), followed by UI after TURP (8%). Eleven patients (44%) had received adjuvant external beam radiotherapy (RT). Patients were considered to be 'dry' if they stopped wearing pads or needed just one protective pad per day; and improved if the daily number of pads used decreased by at least half. The Incontinence Quality of Life questionnaire (ICIQ-SF) was used, adding a verbal question about the satisfaction of the patient considering the outcome. RESULTS After a mean follow-up of 21.56 months, 64% were dry and 8% revealed a significant improvement. The success of the procedure was negatively correlated with the severity of the previous UI and with previous treatment with RT. Concerning patients satisfaction, 84% of the patients would repeat the procedure. CONCLUSION ATOMS® offers good rates of cure and improvement of UI after prostatic surgery with a reasonable rate of minor complications. The results of this study, performed in a low to medium volume continence center, are comparable to the results achieved in high volume continence centers.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Adjustable transobturator male system</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sistema masculino transobturatriz ajustable</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>ATOMS(®)</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Incontinencia urinaria masculina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Male urinary incontinence</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Nov 21 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es útil el sistema transobturatriz ajustable ATOMS® para el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria masculina en centros urológicos de bajo y medio volumen?</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the adjustable transobturator system ATOMS® useful for the treatment of male urinary incontinence in low to medium volume urological centers?</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
