<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29216689</identifier>
<setSpec>2306-4102</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gil-Orbezo, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acuña-Tovar, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trueba-Vasavilbaso, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Sanabria, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trueba-Davalillo, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The severity and progression of rotator cuff tears have forced research on new treatment pathways such as metalloprotease inhibition, which has shown a reduction in healing time and improvement in the structure of collagen fibers. OBJECTIVE To evaluate the use of doxycycline as a healing enhancer in rotator cuff tears after surgical treatment. MATERIAL AND METHODS 20 patients were included; they were divided into two groups, 10 with the use of doxycycline and 10 without it after arthroscopic repair with one-year follow-up. Doxycycline was given orally, 100 mg once a day for one month. Every subject in the test was diagnosed with rotator cuff tear confirmed by MRI with Patte and Goutallier scores below 2. We used the arthroscopic double row technique. Post-op follow-up was 12 months with clinical scales (UCLA, Constant and forward flexion strength). RESULTS Both groups reported almost complete healing of rotator cuff tears after surgical treatment during the twelve months of follow-up; forward flexion strength was the only score that reported improvement in the doxycycline group during every check-up. DISCUSSION Doxycycline use after arthroscopic cuff tear repair could improve the clinical outcome, but we do not know how yet; however larger sample and randomized trials should be developed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>healing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>rotator cuff</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>metalloprotease inhibitor</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Doxycycline</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>arthroscopy</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de doxiciclina como adyuvante en la recuperación postquirúrgica de las lesiones del manguito rotador. Seguimiento a un año.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La severidad y progresión inevitable de la lesión del manguito rotador ha llevado a experimentar con adyuvantes terapéuticos para disminuir el tiempo de recuperación postquirúrgica, así como mejorar la estructura del tendón en recuperación al inhibir la matriz de metaloproteasas. 
             Evaluar el uso de la doxiciclina como adyuvante en la cicatrización de lesiones hueso-tendón en la reparación quirúrgica del manguito rotador. 
             Se reclutaron 20 pacientes con lesión del manguito rotador corroborada por imagen con retracción del supraespinoso grado II (Patte) e infiltración grasa de 50% (Goutallier). Fueron divididos en dos grupos: a 10 se les administró doxiciclina, 100 mg cada 24 horas durante un mes, y el resto fueron un grupo control sin doxiciclina. Ambos fueron tratados quirúrgicamente con técnica de doble hilera vía artroscópica, con seguimiento periódico hasta 12 meses mediante escalas de UCLA, Constant y potencia de flexión anterógrada. 
             Se encontró recuperación clínica de la lesión en ambos grupos a los 12 meses, mayor potencia de flexión anterógrada en cada uno de los intervalos de medición para el grupo donde se administró la doxiciclina. Durante la evolución del estudio, se mantuvo constante Constant y UCLA; se encontró mejoría considerable con la potencia de flexión anteró grada como valor independiente. 
             El uso de doxiciclina podría mejorar de una forma considerable el pronóstico clínico de la reparación artroscópica de mango rotador con el uso de doble hilera, pero aún no sabemos cómo, aunque deberán realizarse estudios adicionales con una muestra mayor. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Doxycycline as an adjuvant in postsurgical recovery of rotator cuff injuries. One-year follow-up].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta ortopedica mexicana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
