<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29223317</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-1852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ascaso, Carlos</dc:author>
<dc:author>Molina, Israel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serre-Delcor, Núria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tórtola, M Teresa</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espasa, Mateu</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Quevedo, Manuel</dc:author>
<dc:author>Soriano-Arandes, Antoni</dc:author>
<dc:author>Oliveira-Souto, Inés</dc:author>
<dc:author>Treviño-Maruri, Begoña</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Some studies indicate high prevalences of latent tuberculosis infection (LTBI) in the immigrant population, which is relevant because 5-10% of cases will develop active tuberculosis. The objective of this study is to describe the results of a sequential strategy in the newly-arrived immigrant population for the diagnosis of LTBI using the tuberculin skin test (TST) and IGRAs. METHODS A retrospective descriptive study was carried out with immigrants between 6 and 35years of age from shelters, referred to an international health unit between July 2013 and June 2016. The TST was performed and when it was ≥5mm, IGRAs were conducted. LTBI was defined as an IGRA ≥0.35IU/ml and normal chest X-ray. RESULTS Of the 184 cases, 138 (75.0%) were men, 23.0 years of age. The most common geographical areas were: 63 (34.2%) from Asia, 42 (22.8%) from Eastern Europe and 41 (22.3%) from sub-Saharan Africa. The TST was ≥10mm in 79 cases (42.9%). The prevalence of LTBI using the sequential strategy was 33/184 (17.9%). Cohen's Kappa index (between TST≥10mm and IGRAs) was 0.226. CONCLUSION Basing LTBI screening on the TST alone could give rise to an overestimation. Some studies show that sequential screening would be the most cost-effective; this seems most evident in BCG-vaccinated populations.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Inmigrantes</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Interferon Gamma Release Assays</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Prueba de tuberculina</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Screening</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis skin test</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Tuberculosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Infección tuberculosa latente</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cribado</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Latent tuberculosis infection</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Immigrants</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Dec 06 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia secuencial para el cribado de la ITBL en inmigrantes recién llegados en situación social vulnerable.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sequential strategy for the LTBI screening of newly-arrived immigrants in vulnerable social situations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
