<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29251281</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9110</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Casabona I Barbarà, Jordi</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribas Baltrons, Josep</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernàndez-López, Laura</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The COBATEST network (European network of community-based voluntary, counselling and testing centers) allows standardized collection of information to monitor HIV testing at these centers. The objective was to describe the performance of the Spanish centers of the COBATEST network and the epidemiological profile of its users, and to analyze the factors associated with having an earlier HIV test. METHODS Descriptive analysis of the data collected in the 19 Spanish centers that used the common information collection tools during the year 2015. A multivariate logistic regression model was used to identify factors associated with having an earlier test. RESULTS A total of 6,077 HIV rapid tests were performed and 1.8% were reactive (3.0% MSM, 3.1% SW, 2.3% PWID, 0.6% heterosexual). 82.1% of the reactives were referred to perform a confirmatory test and 94 (97.9%) were HIV positive, of whom 54% were diverted to the health system. 38% said they had never been tested for HIV. Factors associated with having a previous HIV test were: being over 20 years old; being HSH, SW, or PWID; being foreign; having used condoms at the last penetration; having had an STI in the last year; and having been in jail. CONCLUSIONS The results show the great potential of these services to reach people who have never been tested for HIV. The HIV cases are concentrated in vulnerable groups. It is necessary to improve the linkage of diagnosed people to health care services.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Point-of-care testing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>HIV infections/diagnosis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>HIV</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>VCT</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Community testing</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Risk behaviour</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Spain</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2017 Dec 18 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Red COBATEST: Características de los usuarios de los centros comunitarios de diagnóstico y orientación para el VIH en España.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La red COBATEST (red europea de centros comunitarios de cribado del VIH) permite la recogida estandarizada de información para monitorizar las pruebas de VIH realizadas en estos centros. El objetivo fue describir el rendimiento de los centros españoles de la red COBATEST y el perfil epidemiológico de sus usuarios, y analizar los factores asociados a tener una prueba de VIH anterior. 
             Análisis descriptivo de los datos recogidos en los 19 centros españoles que usaron las herramientas comunes de recogida de información durante el año 2015. Se realizó un modelo multivariado de regresión logística para identificar factores asociados a tener una prueba anterior. 
             Se realizaron un total de 6.077 pruebas rápidas de VIH y de éstas un 1,8% fueron reactivas [3,0% HSH (hombres que tienen sexo con hombres); 3,1% TS (trabajadores/as sexuales); 2,3% UDI (usuarios/as de drogas inyectables); 0,6% heterosexuales)]. El 82,1% de los reactivos se realizaron la prueba confirmatoria y 94 (97,9%) fueron diagnosticados de VIH siendo derivados al sistema sanitario el 54%. El 38% afirmó no haberse realizado nunca la prueba del VIH. Los factores asociados a tener una prueba del VIH anterior son: ser mayor de 20 años; ser HSH, TS, o UDI; ser extranjero; haber usado preservativo en la última penetración; haber tenido una ITS en el último año; y haber estado en prisión. 
             Los resultados muestran el gran potencial de estos servicios para llegar a personas que nunca se han realizado la prueba del VIH. Los casos de VIH se concentran en colectivos vulnerables. Es necesario mejorar la vinculación de las personas diagnosticadas a los servicios sanitarios. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cobatest network: users' characteristics of community-based voluntary,counselling and testing centres in Spain.]</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
