<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29267761</identifier>
<setSpec>1726-4642</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Tejada, Romina A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanabria, César</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bolaños-Díaz, Rafael</dc:author>
<dc:author>Escobedo-Palza, Seimer</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVES To compare in terms of cost-effectiveness to entecavir (ETV) and tenofovir (TDF) in the treatment of hepatitis B virus (HBV) in public hospitals in Peru. MATERIALS AND METHODS We structured a Markov model. We define effectiveness adjusted life years for quality (QALY). We include the direct costs of treatment in soles from the perspective of the Ministry of Health of Peru. We estimate the relationship between cost and effectiveness ratios (ICER). We performed sensitivity analyzes considering a range of willingness to pay (WTP) from one to three times the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per capita, and a tornado analysis regarding Monetary Net Profit (BMN) or ICER. RESULTS Treatment with TDF is more effective and less expensive than ETV. The ETV had a cost per QALY of PEN 4482, and PEN 1526 TDF. The PTO maintains a progressively larger with increasing WTP BMN. The discount rate was the only variable with a significant effect on model uncertainty. CONCLUSION Treatment with TDF is more cost-effective than ETV in public hospitals in Peru.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costo-efectividad de dos terapias antivirales para Hepatitis B crónica en el Perú: Entecavir y tenofovir.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Comparar en términos de costo-efectividad a entecavir (ETV) y tenofovir (TDF) en el tratamiento del virus de la hepatitis B (HBV) en hospitales públicos del Perú. MATERIALES Y MÉTODOS: Estructuramos un modelo de Markov, definimos la efectividad en años de vida ajustados a calidad (AVAC). Incluimos los costos directos del tratamiento en soles desde la perspectiva del Ministerio de Salud del Perú. Calculamos la relación entre costo y efectividad incrementales (ICER). Realizamos análisis de sensibilidad determinístico y probabilístico, considerando un rango de disponibilidad de pago (WTP) desde uno hasta tres veces el producto bruto interno (PBI) per-cápita, y el beneficio monetario neto (BMN) o ICER en el caso del análisis de tornado. 
             El tratamiento con TDF es más efectivo y menos costoso que ETV. El ETV tuvo un costo por AVAC de S/ 4482, y de S/ 1526 para TDF. El TDF mantiene un BMN progresivamente mayor conforme aumenta la WTP. La tasa de descuento fue la única variable con efecto significativo en la incertidumbre del modelo. 
             El tratamiento con TDF es más costo-efectivo que ETV en hospitales públicos del Perú. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Cost-Fffectiveness of Two Antiviral Therapies for Chronic Hepatitis B in Peru: Entecavir and Tenofovir].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista peruana de medicina experimental y salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
