<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29340443</identifier>
<setSpec>1851-8265</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ramírez, Pedro Alberto Hernández</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz, Omar Alejandro Olvera</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cosme, José Arturo Granados</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The World Health Organization and the American Psychological Association consider transsexuality a pathology and suggest sex-gender reassignment for the biopsychic adjustment of trans people. Through the discursive analysis of experience, this study describes the processes of medicalization and gender performativity in relation to the health of a group of trans women from Mexico City. For this purpose, a qualitative study was conducted in which 10 semi-structured interviews were carried out in 2015. As part of medicalization, the pathologization of transsexuality generated psychic suffering; on the other hand, sex-gender reassignment also entailed additional risks. It is possible to conclude that in trans women, violence and exclusion constitute the primary experiences explaining their foremost health problems. Therefore, it is suggested that it is necessary for discrimination be reduced and for advancements to be made in safer medical interventions.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>2017 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Performatividad del género, medicalización y salud en mujeres transexuales en Ciudad de México.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             La Organización Mundial para la Salud y la American Psychological Association consideran que la transexualidad es una patología y plantean la adecuación sexogenérica para el ajuste biopsíquico de las personas trans. Mediante el análisis discursivo de la experiencia, en este estudio se describen los procesos de medicalización y performatividad del género en su relación con la salud de un grupo de mujeres trans de la Ciudad de México, para lo cual se desarrolló un estudio cualitativo en el que se realizaron, en el año 2015, diez entrevistas semiestructuradas. Como parte de la medicalización, la patologización de la transexualidad generó sufrimiento psíquico; por su parte, la adecuación sexogenérica también implicó riesgos adicionales. Se puede concluir que, en las mujeres trans, la violencia y la exclusión resultan las principales experiencias que explican los problemas de salud más relevantes por lo que se sugiere disminuir la discriminación, así como avanzar en intervenciones médicas más seguras. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Gender performativity, medicalization and health in transsexual women in Mexico City].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud colectiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
