<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29368900</identifier>
<setSpec>2448-5667</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aguado-Benedí, María José</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vicente-Herrero, María Teófila</dc:author>
<dc:author>Capdevila-García, Luisa M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ramírez-Íñiguez de la Torre, María Victoria</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres-Alberich, José Ignacio</dc:author>
<dc:author>Terradillos-García, María Jesús</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguilar-Jiménez, Encarna</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-González, Angel Arturo</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Spanish, the concepts of discapacidad (disability leave) and incapacidad (sick leave) jointly refer to the impairment of a person due to injuries, diseases or deficiencies that limit their activity in a social, personal or occupational field. However, this common link does not imply that both concepts are the same. Statistical data from INE (Instituto Nacional de Estadística: Statistic National Institute) show that Spain had in 2015 3.85 million persons with a disability (59.8% were women). Statistical data from 2015 from INSS (Instituto Nacional de Seguridad Social: Social Security National Institute) show high levels in the number of processes and in workers affected by temporary sick leave, with social costs to the social security system. Both concepts have been updated: about disability leave, Law 39/2006 adjusted terminology by avoiding the use of concepts with discriminating or pejorative connotation. Regarding sick leave, the Ley General de Seguridad Social (General Social Security Law)has been amended and came into effect in January, 2016. It is necessary to know and distinguish these aspects for a better administrative management, and a more oriented information to the affected patient.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Disabled persons</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Sick leave</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2018 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discapacidad e incapacidad laboral en España. Actualización legislativa 2016.</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">
             Los conceptos de discapacidad e incapacidad hacen referencia conjuntamente al menoscabo de una persona por lesiones, enfermedades o deficiencias que limitan su actividad en el ámbito social, personal o laboral. Pero este nexo común no implica equiparación entre ambos. Datos estadísticos del 2015 del Instituto Nacional de Estadística (INE) muestran en España 3.85 millones de personas con alguna discapacidad, el 59.8% mujeres. Datos estadísticos del 2015 del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social (INSS), tanto en número de procesos, como de trabajadores afectados por incapacidad muestran cifras elevadas, con costos sociales en prestaciones a cargo de la seguridad social. Ambos conceptos han sido objeto de actualización legislativa: en discapacidad, la Ley 39/2006 ajusta la terminología y evita el uso de conceptos con connotación peyorativa o discriminativa. En incapacidad, la Ley General de la Seguridad Social ha sido modificada y ha entrado en vigor en enero de 2016. Es necesario conocer y diferenciar estos aspectos para una mejor gestión administrativa, e información más orientada al paciente afectado. 
        </dc:description>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Disability leave and sick leave in Spain. 2016 legislative update].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
