<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29398094</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-7980</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vázquez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cózar, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez, Á</dc:author>
<dc:author>Álvarez-Ossorio, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carballido, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Llarena, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES This document was developed to establish directives for the follow-up of patients with renal cell carcinoma (RCC) based on the best available scientific evidence and on expert opinions, which can help urologists in the decision-making process and standardise the criteria at the national level. MATERIAL AND METHODS The methodology is based on the RAND/UCLA method. A panel of 9 experts on RCC participated in designing a thematic index, identifying and reading the available evidence, formulating recommendations and drafting the content. A validating group of 25 experts, who did not participate in the previous phases, assessed the recommendations through anonymous voting in a face-to-face consensus meeting. The recommendations that were agreed upon by 75% or more of the participants in this vote were accepted as consensus. The recommendations that did not achieve this consensus were rejected. RESULTS A total of 25 recommendations were accepted as consensus. These recommendations cover the laboratory tests, clinical assessment tests and imaging tests that should be performed for patients with RCC. The presented recommendations have been adapted according to relapse risk. The current document also outlines the frequency and duration of follow-up for each patient profile. CONCLUSIONS The current document enables standardisation of the follow-up criteria for patients with RCC treated in the Spanish healthcare setting, according to the patients' relapse risk.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Recurrence</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Recurrencia</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nephrectomy</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Renal cancer</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Cáncer renal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Consensus meeting</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Nefrectomía</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Reunión de consenso</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Seguimiento</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Follow-up</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2018 Feb 02 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento nacional de recomendaciones sobre el seguimiento del paciente con carcinoma de células renales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">National recommendations document on the follow-up of patients with renal cell carcinoma.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
