<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>29396013</identifier>
<setSpec>1885-1398</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Toyos Sáenz de Miera, Francisco Javier</dc:author>
<dc:author>Melguizo Madrid, Enrique</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Pérez, Berta</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Riejos, Patricia</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Rodríguez, Concepción</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Idiopathic inflammatory myopathies are a heterogeneous group of potentially treatable myopathies. They are classified, on the basis of clinical and histopathological features, into four subtypes: dermatomyositis, polymyositis, necrotizing autoimmune myositis and inclusion-body myositis. Myositis-associated antibodies and myositis-specific autoantibodies are frequently found in patients with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies, and are useful in the diagnosis and classification. Anti-histidyl transfer RNA synthetase antibody is the most widely prevalent and is highly specific for polymyositis. Signal recognition particle antibody is also a specific autoantibody for polymyositis, but it is infrequent and rarely found in patients having other myositis-specific autoantibodies. We present a man with polymyositis who had both antibodies in serum, which is considered an extremely rare clinical situation. Here we analyze the clinical course and findings, and examine the effect of the coexistence and possible interaction on prognosis.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:subject>Anti-histidil-tRNA-sintetasa</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Polymyositis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anti-partícula de reconocimiento de la señal</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Polimiositis</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anti-Jo-1</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Myopathies</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Miopatías</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Anti-SRP</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2018 Jan 25 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coexistencia de anticuerpos anti-histidil-tRNA-sintetasa y anti-partícula de reconocimiento de la señal en un paciente con polimiositis.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coexistence of anti-Jo1 and anti-signal recognition particle antibodies in a polymyositis patient.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Reumatologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
