<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>2952084</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Esquivel-Avila, J G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barragán García, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Galván Infante, P B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Varela Sadurní, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Friedland, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández de la Reguera, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canepa Campos, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We studied 28 patients to whom a prosthestic valve of bovine pericardium manufactured in the Instituto Nacional de Cardiología Ignacio Chávez (INCICH) were implanted in aortic position, from February 1983 to May 1985. We analyzed the clinic follow-up and the prosthetic function was studied by Phonocardiography, Echocardiography M mode, Two-Dimensional and pulsed wave Doppler recordings obtained before and after surgery. The patient were 26 males, 2 females whose age varied from 12 to 66 years. The aortic valve disease was rheumatic in 12, congenital in 11 and of other type in 5. After surgery 26 patients are in functional class I, one in class II and one died, but death was not related to prosthetic valve function. In the Phonocardiogram we observed significant diminution of the ventricular ejection time of 32 +/- 2 msec. to 29 +/- 2 msec. (P less than 0.05), the aortic valve opening sound was of less intensity than the valve closure sound, with relation between both of 0.53. All of them had a systolic ejection murmur. In the Echocardiogram we observed a significant decrease of the end diastolic diameter of 53 +/- 11 mm to 45 +/- 10 mm (P less than 0.05), the end systolic diameter decreased from 37 +/- 13 mm to 33 +/- 10 mm., but the difference was not significant. The aortic prosthetic flow by pulsed Doppler Echocardiography had a maximum velocity of 137 +/- 23 cm/sec., it represents a valvular gradient of 7.5 +/- 0.02 mmHg. Early diastolic regurgitant flow was recorded in two patients.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1987 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio por procedimientos no invasivos de las prótesis de pericardio bovino en posición aórtica manufacturadas en el Instituto Nacional de Cardiología Ignacio Chávez.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study using non-invasive methods in prostheses of bovine pericardium in aortic position manufactured at the Ignacio Chávez National Institute of Cardiology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
