<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>313800</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vildosola, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herrera, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prenzel, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">22 consecutive cases of pleural empyema due to H. influenzae in children are reported. An increment of its incidence during the 1975-76 period is observed. All cases were in children under 3 years of age, with a mean of 15.5 months. The presenting syndrome at admission was varied. In 50% of cases, pleuropulmonary infection was ignored. Nearly one half of cases of pleural empyema due to H. influenzae had simultaneous purulent meningitis caused by the same microorganism. This type of empyemas, though having a prolonged evolution, apparently appear to have a good prognosis, compared with that produced by S. aureus. There are some differences, being the most outstanding: low frequency of pyoneumothorax and the lack of radiological evidences of abscesses and or pneumotoceles, in any phase of the clinical course. Stress is placed on the value of the bacteriological study of blood and CSF in children under 3 years of age with pleural empyema. A high rate of positive blood cultures was found. (75%). Pieuropulmonary complications, as a frequent event during severe infections (septicemic disease) due to H. influenzae is considered. A clinical characterization of children in whom a pleural empyema could occur is proposed. A discussion is made about diagnostic, therapeutic and prognostic implications of these complications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1979 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empiemas pleurales por Hemophilus influenzae en niõs.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pleural empyemas in children due to Hemophilus influenzae].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
