<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>3154299</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González de Mejía, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valencia, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Celada, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grajeda Cota, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The chemical, physical, antiphysiological and biological quality of the protein of three varieties (white, brown and black) of tepary bean (Phaseolus acutifolius) were studied. Its proximate composition was determined, as well as water absorption, hardness of the seed, tannin content, trypsin inhibitors and lectins. Beans were also submitted to differential scanning calorimetry of the starch. The biological quality of its proteins was also established, based on the protein efficiency ratio (PER) and protein apparent digestibility. It was found that the protein content of the bean was high (25%). The white variety had the highest water absorption and the lowest hardness of the seed when compared with the other varieties (p less than 0.05). The black variety had a lower starch gelatinization energy and a higher cooking time than the white and brown varieties. The tannin content of the three varieties was low, particularly in the white one. The trypsin inhibitor and lectin content were relatively high in the raw beans, but disappeared almost totally during cooking. The biological quality of the tepari proteins was higher than that of the common bean cultivated under the same conditions, More evidently so in the white bean (PER = 1.48 as compared to 1.23 in pinto bean). It can be concluded that the tepary bean is a potentially good protein source and has also a great potential ad donor of genes for the obtention of better bean varieties from the culinary, nutritional and toxicological points of view.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1988 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización del potencial nutricional del frijol tepari (Phaseolus acutifolius) cultivado en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Characterization of the nutritional potential of tepari bean (Phaseolus acutifolius) grown in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
