<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>470495</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gaztambide Sáenz, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Franco Vicario, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miguel de la Villa, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sadaba Garay, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bustamante Murga, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Macías, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors review the problem of active pulmonary tuberculosis in the clinics of the Social Security in Biscay. The high number of cases offers a wide panorama and the possibility of arriving at general conclusions within the Biscayan demographic structure. It is rather disturbing to discover an average of 24.37 cases per 100,000 inhabitants per year in this partial study of the situacion. The indexes for 1967 and 1974 were practically the same. Although the disease occurs with greatest frequency in persons between 30 and 60 years of age, there is a marked tendency for it to appear at increasingly lower ages. The disease is much more common in men than in women, and immigrates seem to be more susceptible than the native population. Pulmonary tuberculosis was reported as the cause of 1.12 percent of the 61,341 deaths registered in Biscay during the 8-year period under study (1967-1974). In view of this situation the authors insist on the urgent need for strategic methods to erradicate this serious menace to public health. They consider the role of tuberculosis sanatoriums in the state to be of outmost importance.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1979 Apr 25 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La tuberculosis pulmonar en la práctica ambulatoria de la Seguridad Social en Vizcaya.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary tuberculosis in the outpatients clinics of the Social Security in Biscay (author's transl)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
