<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>507575</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vázquez Pérez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marqués Defez, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tomás Collado, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribera Otero, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eighteen infants carrying pulmonary stenosis with a complete interventricular wall whose most frequent clinical data are: precocius cyanosis, congestive cardiac insufficiency and in 25% of them hypoxic crises are presented. Complementary explorations of this entity are not definitive, but clinical diagnosis described with evolutional cardiomegaly at the expense of the right cavities and pulmonary ischemia forces authors to think that there is a severe obstruction of the infumdibulum with complete interventricular septum. The different parameters which have been proposed to evaluate severity of the stenosis are discussed and compared, finding among them significative differences. Authors consider the concept of the right diminutive ventricle, finding in these cases the electrocardiographic pattern rS in V1 and observing a great mortality both spontaneous and postsurgical. The high mortality of this heart disease, both in its' natural evolution as well as after surgery is to be pointed out as in most published series.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1979 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obstrucción severa del tracto de salida del ventrículo derecho.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Critical pulmonary stenosis in infants (author's transl)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
