<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>522526</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vivancos, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vives, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ingelmo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ardiaca, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Balcells, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Elías, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study reported a group of 168 chronically alcoholic patients with a daily ingestion superior to 80 grams. Twenty of these patients (10 percent) did not have liver disease, and 148 (68.5 percent) had different forms of liver disease classified by histopathologic examination. Considering a 97 fi MCV as macrocytosis, we have found in the group of alcoholics without hepatopathy a 50 percent rate of macrocythemia with a mean value of 97.9 fl. In the group of chronic alcoholics with liver disease there was a 64.2 percent macrocytosis with a mean value of 100 fl. We have also studied 43 (21.5 percent) patients with cryptogenetic cirrhosis with a 32.6 percent macrocytosis and a mean value of 93.9 fl. With respect to the alcoholic hepatopathy subgroups, macrocytosis is more frequent in portal fibrosis and acute alcoholic hepatitis, the mean value being higher in the latter. We consider macrocytosis to be frequent among alcoholics, and a good persistence indicator of alcoholic ingestion, pathogenically linked to the now proven dyserythropoietic factor of the alcohol upon the bone marrow. There is no statistically significant correlation between anemia and reticulocytes. We consider macrocytosis to be a more precocious data, and believe that the positive correlation with certain intraerythrocitary enzymes in the juvenile population of red cells corroborates this fact. With respect to the rest of parameters studied there was a correlation with gammaglutamiltranspeptidase, glutamic-oxalacetic transaminase, and the value of prothrombin. The values of mean macrocytosis and elevations of gammaglutamiltranspeptidase and glutamic-oxalacetic transaminase are good persistence indicators of alcoholic ingestion.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1979 Nov 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Macrocitosis en el alcoholismo crónico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Macrocytosis in chronic alcoholism (author's transl)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
