<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>542887</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-2174</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Arechavala, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costa, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Golfera, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>de María Rosa, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negroni, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of skin tests with two antigens of the yeast phase of Histoplasma capsulatum are presented. Both antigens were able to fix complement and form precipitating bands in the presence of sera from patients with active histoplasmosis. Their sensitivity was lower than the metabolic antigen usually employed in serology. Results of skin tests obtained with both yeast phase antigens and a standard histoplasmin coincided in animals infected with H. capsulatum. Only one cross reaction was observed in animals inoculated with Paracoccidioides brasiliensis. Skin tests in humans were conducted on patients with and without mycotic disease. The percentages of positive reactions in patients with histoplasmosis were not significantly different between control histoplasmin and whole cell extracts. In the patients with non mycotic diseases the frequency of positive tests varied between 28.8% and 32%, which agrees with previous statistical data for the general population of the area. Equally the positive percentage of 55% and 68% in patients with paracoccidioidomycosis coincided with the results of previous studies. The histological patterns of these skin tests showed that they were produced by cell mediated hypersensitivity. The sensitivity of a whole yeast cell extract was similar to histoplasmin L48, but its preparation was quicker and easier to perform and it had no foreign substances from the culture medium, so we think that it would be easier to standardize it chemically.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1979 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de dos antigenos de la fase levaduriforme del Histoplasma capsulatum para pruebas cutaneas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of yeast phase Histoplasma capsulatum antigens used for skin tests].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Sabouraudia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
