<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>629831</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Garza Villarreal, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez Neria, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gardida Chavarría, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Investigation of the vital capacity, maximum expiratory flow and maximum mean expiratory flow was carried out in children living in two areas of Mexico City, one of them with a high degree (azcapotzalco) and the other one with low degree (Tizapán) of air pollution. Timed spirometry was carried out on children attending 4th, 5th and 6th grades in two official grammar schools so both groups were as uniform as possible in their social-economical level and nutritional and health conditions. This goal was attained quite satisfactorily and groups turned similar, after comparing results and analysing statistically somatometric data, together with scholarship of the parents, economical income, history of respiratory diseases and physical examination. However, quite a significant statistical difference (p less than 0.001) was found between the parameters involving measurements of ventilation in favor of Tizapán children. The difference between Azcapotzalco and Tizapán children in terms of the three ventilatory parameters analyzed was possibly due to the fact the former lived in a greater polluted area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1978 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contaminación atmosférica y espirometría en niños sanos del Distrito Federal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Atmospheric pollution and spirometry in healthy children of the Distrito Federal].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
