<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>6437382</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>De Paiva, V J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Subirana, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Subirana, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a total of 560 different epileptics visited during 16 months, we have practiced 140 plasmatic dosifications of antiepileptic drugs according to EMIT technic. The antiepileptic drugs studied were: PB, DPH, PRM, VPA, CBZ and ESM. In this study only the 70 patients treated with PB in monotherapy or combined with DPH, CBZ, VPA and PRM are considered. From the 70 patients, 45 have been controlled; from them 21 (46,5%) did not reach efficient levels from anyone of the used antiepileptics. From the 70 patients 25 have been partially or bad controlled, 20 of them (80%) had PB in efficient levels, 13 (52%) had the other antiepileptic in efficient levels, 12 (47%) had both antiepileptics in efficient levels and 4 (16%) had no antiepileptic drug in efficient levels in spite of using the efficient dose in mg/Kg/day. The conclusions of this results are: we reached a good effect by using PB alone or combined under the considered efficient levels in a 46.5% of the patients; the bad controlled patients, kept on being bad controlled in spite of having 80% of them PB, the other antiepileptic or both in efficient levels.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1984 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de los niveles plasmáticos de los antiepilépticos en el tratamiento de la epilepsia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Plasma levels of antiepileptic agents in the treatment of epilepsy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Arquivos de neuro-psiquiatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
