<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>6605015</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vadra, J E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kischinefsky, J S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Altrudi, R D</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The experience obtained over 226 cases of endoscopically diagnosticated acute, bleeding, gastroduodenal lesions (A. B. G. D. L.), is submitted. The close relation among authors concerning diagnosis, treatment, and follow-up of patients, may allow them to offer the following results: 1) To elaborate an anatomopathological-endoscopic classification of the A. B. G. D. L., this being composed of five groups: a) microerosive or petechial form; b) macroerosive; c) acute ulcerous and d) fissurate form. The macroscopic, endoscopic and microscopic features of each of the forms, have being designated. 2) To present an entity: the Hemorrhagic Gastroenteropathy (HGP) pointing on the alarming possibility that, the denominated Hemorrhagic Gastroduodenitis (HDG), do not be such, but a simply high lesional constituent of a picture extending also to other digestive area (politopic disease) (HGP). This proposal is supported by clinic, endoscopic and experimental findings. 3) To propose the treatment now we consider the suitable one, based on the clinical prospective research fulfilled over 186 cases. This therapeutic consists on the psiquic disconnection achieved by the use of a lithic mixture combined with H2 and H1 blockers. Since the results are invariably effectives, we think that this disease is a medical entity and most exceptionally surgical.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1983 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones agudas sangrantes digestivas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Acute bleeding digestive lesions].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta gastroenterologica Latinoamericana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
