<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>6751181</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ruza Tarrió, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albajara Velasco, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solorzano, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mar Molinero, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IV catecholamines are a very important therapy in the Pediatric ICU. Their application is very discussed, principally in the pediatric age, where effects, beginning by a remembrance of its physiology (endogenous production, storing, destruction, with an explanation of the adrenergic system, according with Ahlquist). Pharmacologic activity and clinical characteristics of their application and basic requirements for its IV use (monitorization, exact dosification, permeable venous way) are revised. Authors analyse independently the three catecholamines of more common use: isoproterenol, dopamine and dobutamine, discussing systematically its' actions on three levels: a) heart; b) systemic circulation, and c) pulmonary circulation. They discuss their indications, contraindications, risks and precaution in their use and dosification concluding that the more common catecholamines are dopamine and dobutamine, being the last one more recommended in the future, by its' more selective effects on the heart. Isoproterenol has very specific indications, in acute phases and during short periods of time. Adrenaline and noradrenaline are also considered. Finally, association of different drugs looking for improvement of positive effects and reduction of negative ones is mentioned.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1982 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catecolaminas en patología intensiva pediátrica.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Catecholamines in pediatric intensive care].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
