<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7332401</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Araya, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arroyave, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The distribution of the protein energy ratio indicators (Pe%), amino acid score and protein value (NDpCal%) in the three daily meals (breakfast, lunch and dinner) of the diet of pregnant women from Santa María Cauqué, Guatemala, was studied. The results were compared with those obtained for the total daily food intake. The differences observed were not significant, confirming the validity of the determination of amino acid score, Pe% and NDpCal% in the foods consumed during the whole day in this type of populations. It also reflects the nutritional benefit of the food pattern, since protein utilization would not be decreased by a different distribution of protein quality and concentration throughout the three daily meals. The variability among individuals of Pe% intake, amino acid score and NDpCal% gave the following values: 16.0, 9.3 and 15.6, respectively. It is noteworthy to add that the variability of Pe% observed is similar to that reported for populations of developed countries.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1981 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio deitético en embarazadas de Santa Maria Cauque, Guatemala. I Variabilidad de los indicadores proteínicos y su análisis por tiempo de comidas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dietetic study of pregnant women of Santa Maria Cauqué, Guatemala. I. Variability of protein indicators and analysis by the time of meals].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
