<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7347322</identifier>
<setSpec>0100-3283</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jonquières, D L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Caballero, H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors compare the bacilloscopic involution in 37 dimorphous Virchowian (DS) patients and in 47 Virchowian (V) patients with definite polarity treated with 200 mg daily of DDS during up to 20 years. After 5 years of treatment the DV patients presented negative bacilloscopy of the nasal mucus in 93% of the cases and of the skin in 81%. The control group of V patients showed, at the same time, negative bacilloscopy of the nasal mucus in 81% of the cases and of the skin only in 29,7%. After 10 years of treatment 19,21% of the DV patients and 32% of the V cases showed positive skin bacilloscopy. It was concluded that the DV patients presented better responses to the sulphone therapy although a Virchowian aggravation had been observed in about one fifth of the DV cases. Considering that the DV patients represent 25% of the group of 150 D patients studied and that the DD and DT did not present a Virchowian aggravation, it was concluded that of the whole D group (DV, DD, DT) 4% of the patients presented Virchowian aggravation in spite of the sulphone treatment.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1981 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Involución baciloscópica en dimorfos virchowianos tratados con sulfonas - Comparición c on pacientes virchowianos tratados con iguales dosis.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bacilloscopic involution in dimorphous Virchowians treated with sulfones - Comparison with Virchowian patients treated with identical dosage].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Hansenologia internationalis</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
