<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7412438</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Hernando, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Blas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez del Barrio, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cubells, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bovine cerebral cortex gangliosides were given to 71 patients following surgical intervention for radicular compression of different etiologies. The extract was given for 20-25 days at daily doses of 20 mg for the first 15 days and 10 mg thereafter until completion of treatment. H reflexology was shown to be a good method for evaluating the response to therapy. Most information was gained by the use of the following parameters: AM/AH, AH/IE, and AH/number of stimulation pulses. The results have been compared with those obtained prior to surgical therapy, those collected in a series of 68 normal individuals and, finally, with those found in another series of 71 patients that were treated postoperatively with conventional measures (B vitamins, analgesics, antiinflammatory drugs, corticoids, etc.). The statistical analysis of the final data shows that the reflexologic parameters tested revert to normal quicker in the patients treated with gangliosides than in those not receiving such therapy. The authors consider the use of gangliosides of great interest in the postoperative period after surgical relief of radicular compression.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1980 Sep 10 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los gangliósidos de corteza cerebral bovina en el tratamiento de las lesiones radiculares.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bovine cerebral cortex gangliosides in the treatment of radicular lesions (author's transl)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
