<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7481021</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cárceles, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castaño, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez-Rincón, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alfaro, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To determine the possible antiemetic effect of propofol as the single agent for intravenous anesthesia in children undergoing strabismus surgery, in comparison with other techniques. PATIENTS AND METHOD Eighty ASA I and II patients between 3 and 10 years, divided into 4 groups of 20, were studied prospectively. Groups I, II and III were premedicated with dehydrobenzylperidol (90 micrograms/kg) i.m. Group I then received sleep doses of thiopental and N2O. Group II received propofol, sleep doses, and N2O. Groups III and IV received sleep doses of propofol followed by intravenous perfusion (10 mg/kg/h). RESULTS Half the patients in group I experienced postoperative vomiting, more than in groups II, III and IV (p &lt; 0.05). The incidence of vomiting in group II was 30%. Groups III and IV experienced less vomiting (5-10%) than did groups I and II (p &lt; 0.05). The incidence of bradycardia during surgery was higher in groups III and IV (p &lt; 0.05); medical treatment was not required. CONCLUSIONS Propofol used as the single agent for induction and maintenance of anesthesia offers clear advantages in reducing emesis after strabismus surgery.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Aug-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infusión de propofol como fármaco anestésico y antiemético.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infusion of propofol as anesthetic and antiemetic drug].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
