<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>753181</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Schneider, R E</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Ibáñez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viteri, F E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Schoeller, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosenberg, I H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solomons, N W</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lizarralde, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pineda, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calloway, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Klein, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tests based on the analysis of the gaseous components of expired air have been developed to study intestinal absorption and intermediary metabolism of various nutrients. This paper reviews the breath-analysis tests based on the measurement of CH4, H2, and isotopically-labelled CO2 for studying the intestinal absorption of carbohydrates, fats, and bile salts, and intrahepatic metabolism. New technology employing mass spectrometry allows the use of the stable isotope, carbon-13, instead of the radioactive isotope, carbon-14, for CO2 breath tests. The nutritional application of the breath-analysis tests is discussed, and the advantages of the non-radioactive, non-invasive procedures, especially for use in children and pregnant women in whom standard investigational methods represent a discomfort or a radioactive hazard, are emphasized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1978 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso de pruebas basadas en el análisis del aire espirado, en estudios nutricionales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of tests based on the analysis of expired air in nutritional studies].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
