<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7542898</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Taxonera Samsó, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Real Martínez, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rey Díaz-Rubio, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz-Rubio, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM To study, through the pathology diagnosis obtained, the current use of percutaneous liver biopsy and its change with time. MATERIALS AND METHODS Pathology diagnosis of 759 liver biopsies performed during last 5 years are reviewed and compared with our previously published experience. RESULTS Neoplasms have decreased from 16% of all pathologic diagnosis obtained in 1961-81 to less than 1% in the last 5 years. In 1985-87, liver cirrhosis was the final diagnosis in 60% of all biopsies, while currently it is only 18%, with a steady absolute number of cirrhosis each year. The most remarkable change is the number of biopsy diagnosis of chronic hepatitis, which has increased from 19% in 1985-87 to 51% in the last 5 years. Ten percent of all biopsies was performed in HIV-positive patients; granulomatous hepatitis and tuberculosis were more prevalent in them. CONCLUSIONS Percutaneous liver biopsy has been displaced for the diagnosis of liver cirrhosis and has been focussed on the diagnosis of chronic hepatitis. HIV-positive patients represent an important population for those who perform liver biopsy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la utilización de la biopsia hepática percutánea con el tiempo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Changes in the use of percutaneous liver biopsy over time].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
