<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7569462</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Massardo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Figueroa, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivero, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jacobelli, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cyclosporine may be useful in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis refractory to other immunosuppressive agents, in doses of less than 10 mg/kg/day to minimize its nephrotoxic potential, that is enhanced with prolonged use or concomitant administration of anti-inflammatory drugs. We report 15 patients aged 50 +/- 12 years with erosive rheumatoid arthritis lasting 5 +/- 4 years and refractory to other immunosuppressive agents. They were studied during one year and received cyclosporine in initial doses of 2.5 mg/kg/day that were increased to 5 mg/kg/day, assessing clinical response, blood pressure and serum creatinine. Nine patients, that received a maximal dose of 3.4 +/- 0.7 mg/kg/day during 7 +/- 4 months, improved; a 30% increase in creatinine was observed in 3, blood pressure raised in six and two had hepatic toxicity. In the six patients that did not improve, the mean treatment lapse was 4 +/- 3 months and the maximal dose achieved was 2.7 mg/kg/day; creatinine increased in one and blood pressure increased in 4. It is concluded that although the clinical response to cyclosporine was good, only 4 patients completed one year of treatment, due to the frequent secondary effects of the drug.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con ciclosporina de la artritis reumatoídea refractaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment with cyclosporine of refractory rheumatoid arthritis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
