<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7577119</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Parra Blanco, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juanco Pedregal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silvan Delgado, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the changes in the Doppler waveform of the hepatic veins in patients with cirrhosis. DESIGN We analyzed prospectively with Doppler ultrasound the flow of the hepatic veins and we compared the different Doppler waveform patterns with the degree of liver failure according to the Child-Pugh score. PATIENTS Forty three patients with cirrhosis and 60 normal individuals with similar age and sex. RESULTS Abnormal hepatic vein waveforms were found in 40 of 43 patients with cirrhosis and in none of the 50 controls subjects. No statistically significant differences were detected between the different Doppler waveform patterns and the Child-Pugh score (p = 0.063). CONCLUSIONS Our findings indicate that an alteration of the Doppler waveform pattern of hepatic veins suggest the presence of cirrhosis and that there is no association between the degree of the liver failure and the waveform patterns.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraci칩n en el flujo de las venas suprahep치ticas en pacientes con cirrosis. (Estudio Doppler venas hep치ticas en cirr칩ticos).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Changed hepatic vein flow in patients with cirrhosis. A Doppler study of hepatic veins in patients with cirrhosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
