<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7627821</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Velicia Llames, M R</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Hernández, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Barrero, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sanz Santa Cruz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Orcajo, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Twenty-one asymptomatic patients presenting isolated elevations of gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase (GGT) were studied over the previous 10 years with all the findings being accidental. No other analytical alterations were demonstrated. Ingestion of alcohol, drugs or another type of toxic substance, diabetes, neurologic disease or neoplasm were discarded. Echography of the liver and the biliary tract was normal. In the first nine patients studied, liver biopsy was performed being normal or with minimum unspecific alterations. In two patients endoscopic retrograde cholangiography was carried out with no alterations being observed. Lipid study was performed in all the patients with alpha hypolipoproteinemia being found in 15 patients, compensated type II lipid profile in 5 and a normal lipid profile in one. To the author's knowledge there have been no reports of this lipid disorder causing elevations in GGT. However, on being the only abnormality found in these patients the authors believe that this may be the cause although the mechanism is unknown.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elevación de gammaglutamiltranspeptidasa en pacientes con hipoalfalipoproteinemia y dislipemias tipo IIa compensadas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Increase of gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase in patients with compensated hypoalphalipoproteinemia and type IIa dyslipidemias].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
