<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7654924</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Altimir, M R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torrens, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serras, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Description of drug-dependent patients who attend a primary care centre (PCC). DESIGN A prospective study. SETTING Barceloneta PCC, located in a waterside area of Barcelona's old quarter. PATIENTS AND OTHER PARTICIPANTS The analysis was carried out on 43 drug-dependent patients who attended the PCC over a two-year period requesting detoxication treatment as well as on patients who attended for treatment of other organic pathologies or to request medication and in whom an addiction problematic was detected. Patients who were already following a course of treatment in a specialised drug dependency centre or who were dependent on alcohol were excluded. INTERVENTIONS Detection and evaluation of drug dependency and of hygienic-dietary problems. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS A structured interview which looked at the drug history, sociodemographic characteristics and hygienic-dietary habits was employed. It was observed that 90.7% of the drug-dependent patients used heroin and 44% of these had not been previously treated for addiction. 88.4% were male and 51.2% had a criminal record. 72% practised one of the types of behaviour putting them at risk of HIV infection. CONCLUSIONS The majority of patients addicted to drugs who were identified at a PCC are dependent on heroin as their primary drug. 44% of them had received no previous treatment for their addiction.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Mar 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección y evaluación de los pacientes toxicómanos atendidos en un centro de asistencia primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Detection and evaluation of drug addict patients seen at a primary care center].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
