<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7709095</identifier>
<setSpec>0187-4640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Flores-Crespo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flores-Crespo, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibarra-Velarde, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vera-Montenegro, Y</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the aim to evaluate the efficacy of four vermicides, praziquantel, mebendazole, nitroscanate and triclorfon in the control of Bothriocephalus acheilognathi in carps, one hundred and sixty, two year-old carps (Ctenopharyngodon idellus) with an average weight of 120 g and a mean parasitic burden of 115.5 parasites/fish were used. Five groups of 30 fish each were randomly formed. Each group was then subdivided in three groups, each of 10 individuals/pond. The three subgroups of group A received 30, 50 and 70 mg/Kg of praziquantel, respectively. Groups B and C received 2.2, 4.4, and 6.8 mg/Kg of mebendazole suspension and mebendazole solution respectively; groups D and E received 10, 30, 50 mg/Kg; and 2.0, 4.0, 6.0 mg/Kg of nitroscanate and trichlorfon respectively. Group F of 10 fish remained as non-treated control. Praziquantel showed 100% of efficacy for all doses, therefore it was excluded from the statistical analysis. The subgroups B, C, D and E compared with the non-treated control were statistically significant (P &lt; 0.01); showing in all treatments an additive effect, the higher the dose the better efficacy, except trichlorfon which showed a different tendency, having no explanation on that matter.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jul-Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de cuatro vermicidas contra Bothriocephalus acheilognathi en carpas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of 4 vermifuges against Bothriocephalus acheilognathi in carp].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista latinoamericana de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
