<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7716408</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8899</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Haro Ramos, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lázaro de la Escosura, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez Madrazo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montes Gómez, J E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Many bibliographical references suggest reserves of Vibrio cholerae in the aquatic world, strains of both the serovariety no 01 and 01 having been isolated in different parts of the globe in fresh and extensive salt waters. METHODS Samples were taken monthly from January to May and from October to December, and every fortnight from June to September. The method of isolation applied is in accordance with the standard set down by the Institute of Health Carlos III, with some specific modifications. RESULTS During the period 90/91, routine analyses carried out by the Andalusian Service of Health of waters from the area of the Continental Basin in the province of Seville showed the presence of Vibrio cholerae 01. In the same way, during the complete annual cycle Vibrio cholerae no 01 was also isolated. CONCLUSIONS These isolations did not coincide with outbreaks or individual cases of cholera, so the authors, in agreement with what is described in the bibliography, consider that Vibrio cholerae no 01 forms a part of certain aquatic environments, which is in direct relation to environmental isolations of the serovariety 01.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aislamiento ambiental de Vibrio cholerae 01 en aguas continentales de la provincia de Sevilla.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Environmental isolation of Vibrio cholerae 01 in continental waters of the Province of Seville].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de sanidad e higiene publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
