<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7716416</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8899</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Menárguez Puche, J F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saura Llamas, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez-Calcerrada Berrocal, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Sánchez, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saturno Hernández, P J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To describe the Public Health in Primary Health Care practice for medical students Program objectives, quality of training evaluation method, and implementation results. METHODS 6 learning objectives were designed and training implemented in 3 Health Centers in the 90-91 academic course. Evaluation included the objectives level of difficulty, and homogeneity in achievement rates between objectives, within Centres and between Centres. Evaluation results were analyzed and used to design changes to increase homogeneity and achievement rates. Same evaluation was performed in the 91-92 academic course to document improvement. RESULTS In the first evaluation there were highly significant differences in overall (p. &lt; 0.00005) and by objectives (p. &gt; 0.01) achievement rates between centers. Within centres between objectives difficulty was not homogeneous either (p. &gt; 0.001). After implementing remedial actions, differences in difficulty and achievement rates within and between centres decreased. Increased homogeneity affected mostly to two previously less homogeneous objectives. CONCLUSIONS Quality assurance methods can be successfully applied to improve training of clearly defined and quantified Primary Health Care learning objectives.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y mejora de la calidad de las prácticas de Atención Primaria realizadas en Centros de Salud de Murcia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation and improvement of quality during practical training in primary health care at health centers of Murcia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de sanidad e higiene publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
