<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7747073</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8899</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jiménez Jiménez, F J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Domínguez Hernández, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castro Lareo, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosales Rodríguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Tuberculosis represents a major public health problem. In Spain, the incidence of tuberculosis is among the highest in the European Community, and shows an increasing trend. The aim of this study is to determine the incidence and temporal trends of tuberculosis in the catchment area of the "Hospital Juan Canalejo" (La Coruña, Spain), between 1982 and 1991. METHODS Revision of all case records of tuberculosis with positive bacteriology and detected by the Epidemiological Vigilance System of the Preventive Medicine Unit of the "Hospital Juan Canalejo", diagnosed between January 1982 and December 1991. The incidence of tuberculosis as a function of age, sex, period, and county, was modeled with Poisson regression. RESULTS 1120 cases were studied. The relative risk of tuberculosis in females with respect to males was 0.50 (95% confidence interval 0.44 to 0.56; p &lt; 0.001) with a peak of increased risk between 15 and 35 years of age in both genders. With respect to temporal trends, the risk of tuberculosis increased from 1986 in females and from 1987 in males. CONCLUSIONS Over the last decade, the incidence of tuberculosis has increased in the study area, with higher risk in males and young adults.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la incidencia de enfermedad tuberculosa en el área sanitaria de La Coruña.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The evolution of the incidence of tuberculosis in the La Coruña health area].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de sanidad e higiene publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
