<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7766481</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vázquez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Daimiel, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez de Segura, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gámez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Miguel, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Paz, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Murcia, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montejo, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernanz, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aiming at investigating biochemical markers of Primary Graft Nonfunction (PNF) in Orthotopic Liver Transplantation (OLT) an experimental work is made on 21 Large-White pigs randomly distributed in three groups of seven, and two additional groups of seven donors each. In Group I the supra and infrahepatic cava, the portal vein and the hepatic artery were clamped. After 30 minutes the caval and portal clamps were released and 30 minutes later the arterial clamp was also removed. In Group II (viable), OLT was performed. The Collins solution was used as preservation fluid, keeping the cold ischemia time under 2 hours. In Group III (Non-Viable), an OLT was carried out 24 hours of cold ischemia with Collins solution. Blood samples are taken in 8 different moments along the procedure to determinate the values of AST, ALT, LDH, FA, Bilirubin, Uric Acid, Cholesterol, Triglycerides, Urea, Creatinine, Glucose, Total Protein, Calcium, Phosphorus, CPK and Aldolase. The last 5 samples were drawn after reperfusion. In the Group III we found, in the samples drawn after reperfusion of the graft, significant increases in 5 of these parameters, AST, ALT LDH, Aldolase and Uric Acid. We consider that these 5 parameters may be of value in the early diagnosis of PNF of the graft, being the AST and ALT the most reliable, with the higher specificity for the same sensitivity.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores bioquímicos de fallo primario del injerto en trasplante ortotópico de hígado experimental.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Biochemical indicators of primary graft dysfunction in experimental orthotopic liver transplantation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
