<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7779872</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pontón, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lipperheide, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>San Millán, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barturen, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Burgos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quindós, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tellaetxe, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Candida albicans is the most frequently species isolated in patients with candidiasis. This species may be antigenically divided in serotypes A and B, which have a different pathogenic behavior and antifungal susceptibility pattern. METHODS The antifungal susceptibility of 443 clinical isolates from both serotypes of C. albicans to 5-fluorocytosine (5FC), amphotericin B, nystatin, econazole, miconazole and ketoconazole has been tested by means of the ATB Fungus method. RESULTS Both serotypes showed a similar in vitro susceptibility to amphotericin B, nystatin, econazole, miconazole and ketoconazole. All the isolates were susceptible to amphotericin B and nystatin. A small number of in vitro resistant isolates were observed to azole compounds. However, serotype B was significantly more resistant than serotype A (p = 0.0001) to 5FC. CONCLUSIONS C. albicans serotype B shows a lower susceptibility than serotype A to 5FC, an antifungal product not marketed in Spain. Serotyping of C. albicans does not offer additional information on antifungal susceptibility of clinical isolates from this species.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la sensibilidad a los antifúngicos de aislamientos clínicos de los serotipos A y B de Candida albicans mediante el método ATB Fungus.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Assessment of the sensitivity to antifungal agents of clinical isolates of Candida albicans serotype A and B by the ATB Fungus method].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
