<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7864668</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Aragona, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cisternino, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Passerini Glazel, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Perineo-scrotal hypospadias and the severe sequelae of a failed repair procedure are complicated cases. The present study describes our experience in the treatment of complex hypospadias, the new therapeutic possibilities, their indications and results. From 1981 to 1992, 93 children with complex hypospadias underwent surgery (53 underwent surgery for the first time and 40 for severe sequelae of a failed procedure). Excellent cosmetic results were achieved by surgery. For those undergoing hypospadias repair for the first time, we used a pedicled preputial flap following the Duckett (12 cases) or Standoli (41 cases) technique. For those with severe sequelae from a failed procedure, we utilized a pedicled skin flap (18 cases) or free flap of bladder mucosa or penile skin (22 cases). The overall complication rate was 50% (47 patients). Surgical repair of complex hypospadias is a relatively long and complicated procedure with a long learning curve and a high complication rate in the initial phase. Fistula is the most common complication, although closure is very simple due to the abundant, well vascularized, healthy tissue. Overall our results have been satisfactory, considering the severity of these cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cirugía reconstructiva de los hipospadias complejos: indicaciones terapéuticas y consideraciones técnicas en 93 casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reconstructive surgery in complex hypospadias: therapeutic indications and technical considerations in 93 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
