<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7865652</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Mourente, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baraibar, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santi, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorenzo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Osle, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Calzado, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mangas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Barba, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Millán, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is one of the main causes of death in developed countries. Its incidence may be modified through dietary changes, this being supported by the low incidence of the disease among populations with high intake of fatty fishes. The aim of this work was to study the modifications on plasmatic levels of polyunsaturated fatty acids omega 3 after an additional supply of fish oils and to assess its effect on the metabolism of lipids and lipoproteins. The study was conducted on 8 healthy volunteers, their age ranging between 24 and 37 years. They received, during 30 days and in tablets of 500 mg, 7.5 gr/24 h of fish oil concentrate which supplied 2.5 gr/24 h of fatty acids omega 3. After 12 hours of fasting, blood samples were taken before and after the intake of this concentrate. Methyl esters from fatty acids omega 3 were assessed through gas chromatography; cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL, VLDL, HDLt, HDL2 and HDL3, through several enzymatic techniques; and lipoprotein(a) Lp(a), through ELISA. The statistical analysis was conducted using the Student's method for matched data. After 30 days of supplement, we observed: a significant increase in the plasmatic percentage of fatty acids omega 3 (EPA + DHA) along with a significant decrease of triglycerides, VLDL and HDL3 and a significant increase of HDL2, We did not observe any significant changes in cholesterol, LDL and HDLt. With respect to Lp(a), after one month of dietary supplement, its plasmatic levels did not change. Our results supports the clinical usefulness of the dietary supplementation with fatty acid omega 3 for the management of hypertriglyceridemias.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las dosis farmacológicas de ácidos grasos poliinsaturados de la serie-3 sobre la concentración de lipoproteínas plasmáticas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effects of pharmacological doses of polyunsaturated fatty acids of the series 3 on the concentration of plasma lipoproteins].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
