<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7938860</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Llamas, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Echevarría, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olmedo, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cruz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caba, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To compare the incidence of postdural puncture headache after subarachnoid anesthesia with a 24G Sprotte needle among full-term obstetric patients as compared to non-obstetric patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS A total of 200 patients were studied prospectively, divided into 2 groups. Group 1 (n = 100) patients were delivered by cesarean section and group 2 (n = 100) patients underwent infraumbilical or traumatological surgery. All were ASA I-II and under 40 years of age. Hydration was accomplished with lactated Ringer's solution 400-1,000 ml before mid-line puncture. The anesthetic used in both groups was isobaric bupivacaine 0.5% with a vasoconstrictor. The incidence of arterial hypotension and accompanying symptoms was recorded; perioperative administration of vasoactive amines and anticholinergics and liquids administered was measured. Twenty-four to 48 hours later the patients were asked when they started walking and if postdural puncture headache was experienced. RESULTS Group 1 received smaller doses of bupivacaine (p &lt; 0.05) and the incidence of arterial hypotension was greater (p &lt; 0.01) and required increased administration of amines (p &lt; 0.01) and perioperative fluid therapy (p &lt; 0.001). No difference was found between the two groups either for time of start of ambulation or for incidence of headache, which was 1% in both groups. CONCLUSIONS The incidence of postdural puncture headache in obstetric patients is low and similar to that of non-obstetric patients when the 24G Sprotte needle is used.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cefalea pospunción dural en gestantes a término. Estudio comparativo con pacientes no obstétricas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Headache following dural puncture in pregnant patients at term. Comparative study with non-obstetric patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de anestesiologia y reanimacion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
