<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>7999519</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blesa Sánchez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz Montes, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez Alvarez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Núñez Núñez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the aim of describe a typology that will result in a more precise diagnostic which in turn will permit the selection of the most direct method approach, an analysis was made of the clinical characteristics of patients we treated due to the presence of torsion of the testicular and epididymal appendages. A retrospective review was made of 91 patients, taking into account this age, time of appearance, time of evolution, symptoms, physical examination, histological study and effects. The average age was 9.47 years with a greater incidence occurring between the eight and twelve years old. No influence due to a seasonal phase was detected. The time span between the initial appearance of the symptoms and the time of admittance was 39.5 hours, being somewhat less in patients below the age of six. The common symptom was pain. In addition, 58.2% of the patients also suffered scrotal affectation. In 31 patients the hydatid was palpable and in 19 the "blue dot sign" rendered positive. In 83 cases, surgery was done via the scrotum, resulting in the confirmation of the initial diagnosis. The affectation of the left side was more frequent (62.5%). The hospital discharge was possible in less than 48 hours with no visible long-term effects. Thus, we believe that it is possible to almost always make a diagnosis based on the clinical data, and the type of treatment to be applied should be the extirpation of the hydatid to be carried out via the scrotum.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características clínicas en pacientes con torsión de los apéndices testiculares y epididimarios.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The clinical characteristics of patients with torsion of the testicular and epididymal appendages].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Cirugia pediatrica : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Cirugia Pediatrica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
