<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8025797</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Díaz López, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez de Castro, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caminero Luna, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Acosta Fernández, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cabrera Navarro, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Campos-Herrero, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pavón Monzó, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juliá Sardá, G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to analyze the usefulness of bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) for conventional microbiological diagnosis of tuberculosis (TB) and other mycobacteria, and to assess the need to use it or not as a routine diagnostic technique in these diseases, we studied 30 patients with mycobacteria (26 TB and 4 Mycobacterium avium-intracellulare infections) by bronchoscopy, with BAL and bronchoaspirate (BAS) bacteriological analyses also available. The results were compared with those obtained for sputum taken before and after bronchoscopy when these specimens were available. The overall yield for BAL and BAS cultures was 90%, with BAL (83.3%) specimens being more productive than BAS (73.3%) specimens. Both performed far better than the 53.8% recorded for cultures of pre-bronchoscopy sputum and 60% for post-bronchoscopy sputum. BAL was the only diagnostic specimen from 7 patients, while BAS the only one from 4. Sensitivity was similar for the two mycobacteria studied. The results for direct bacilloscopy, however, at 30% for the two specimens, rose to 36.6% when they were analyzed together with BAS and BAL. We conclude that bronchoscopy should be performed on all patients suspected of mycobacterial infection when sputum bacilloscopy is negative and patients have no expectoration. Performance of BAL should be routine since this simple and usually uncomplicated technique produces the most productive specimens.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rentabilidad del lavado broncoalveolar en el diagnóstico de la tuberculosis pulmonar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The efficacy of bronchoalveolar lavage in the diagnosis of pulmonary tuberculosis].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
