<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8056364</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cortés Gallegos, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Alonso Uriarte, Q</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Horta, J L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to establish a relationship between hyperprolactinemia and FSH-LH associated to the ovarian physiology postpartum, a clinical/endocrinological follow-up was performed during a period of twelve months in a cohorte of seventeen women beginning pregnancy resolution. The study had two phases: Lactancy (LAC) and Post-lactancy (LAC) and Post-lactancy (POST-LAC). In both phases blood samples were obtained every week from the first one through the 52nd, to quantitate FSH, LH, prolactin (PRL) and estradiol (E-2). PRL levels were significantly higher during LAC as compared to POST-LAC: an inverse relationship in E-2/PRL was seen through the study. No significant changes for LH and FSH were attained in both phases. Concentrations of these gonadotropins were at the physiological levels and no differences in either one of the two phases were shown when compared to a nonlactating subject. There was a negative association in prolactin levels and the weeks postpartum, and on the contrary, a positive one for E-2. Thus, ovarian follicular development apparently is independent to the gonadotropic-hypophysis stimulus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiología ovárica postparto. Gonadotropinas hipofisarias, estradiol y prolactina durante 12 meses a la resolución del embarazo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Postpartum ovarian physiology. Pituitary gonadotropins, estradiol and prolactin during 12 months of postpartum physiology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
