<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8059677</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Arrieta, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sarrió Amorós, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández García, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Negro Alvarez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miralles López, J C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of adequate technics, in the Allergology case-mix evaluation, is a necessity in the present, and an aim to the future. Doing so, we shall be able to guarantee the quality of medical assistance. This article's objective is to introduce the reader, with a clear language, in the diverse procedures employed, in the actuality, to evaluate the diverse Health Services productive processes. We point out their advantages and disadvantages, and make a final proposal about the use of some of them in Allergology. Firstly, we analyze and describe the International Disease Classification (IDC-9-CM), the Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs), the AS-SCORE, the Patients Severity Illness, the Staging Disease, the APACHE, and the Patients Management Categories. In the second part, we review the Generic Algorithms, the RUGs and the Ambulatory Visits Groups (AVGs). Finally, we propose some methods to improve activities in our specialty, to increase our knowledge, and to educate our colleagues under training in the basic concepts they need, to carry out their activities. In this way, we'll be able to guarantee a good assistance for the allergic patients, and to present objective data to the society, about the efficacy and efficiency with which public funds are used.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnicas de medición del "Case-Mix" y su aplicación a la Alergología (1a parte).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Techniques for determining case mix and their application to Allergology. 1].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Allergologia et immunopathologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
