<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8059030</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carmona-Bernal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borderas, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Reyes, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Irigoyen, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iglesias, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Escudero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Mejías, M E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malign small cell tumors in the thoracopulmonary region is a tumor of neuroectodermic origins with polymorphous and infrequent presentation. It is mostly found among young people, developing an aggressive and severe course. It is a small cell tumor involving small quantities of cytoplasm without glucogen, round or oval nucleus with disperse chromatin, and little prominent nucleolus without tendency of manifesting pseudo red spots, being PAS negative. Two cases which initially resembled pleuropulmonary infection are presented. Case 1: Sixteen year old male. Presented with a high fever, pleuritic thoracic pain, and a cough with little expectoration. He was diagnosed with severe pulmonary infection and parapneumonic right pleural discharge. His condition improved with antibiotic treatment, but the cough persisted. Thoracoabdominal echography showed right pleural discharge and possible hepatic mass. Surgical intervention was performed. Askin's tumor was detected by biopsy. He began treatment with chemotherapy. Case 2: Thirty-four year old woman. Presented with non-productive cough, pleuritic thoracic pain, and high fever. In the thoracic TAC, there was right pleural discharge along with images suggesting hypodense mass. Given the patient's lack of response to antibiotics, a thoracotomy was performed. The anatomopathological diagnosis was Atkin's tumor. After beginning treatment, the patient died after ten days.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de Askin de presentación clínica infrecuente.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infrequent clinical presentation of Askin's tumor].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista clinica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
