<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8154235</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-5504</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gerónimo, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Saura, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Perea, S E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alpha Interferon (IFN) membrane receptor expression was studied in four human tumor cell lines from several origins: Burkitt's lymphoma (Daudi cells), cervix adenocarcinoma (HeLa cells), larynx carcinoma (HEp-2 cells) and a grade III-IV glioblastoma (GL-5 cells). The number of receptors per cell expressed in each case did not correlate with the sensitivity of the cytostatic effect of IFN alpha-2b. However, the Scatchard analysis of the affinity of the IFN-receptor complex did correlate with this effect. Daudi cells, which expressed 1927 receptors/cells with a high affinity (Kd = 3.30 x 10(-10) M) were the most sensitive to the antiproliferative effect. Growth inhibition was 30% with only 1.6pg/ml of IFN. HeLa cells expressed a mixture of high (Kd = 3.36 x 10(-10) M) and low (Kd = 3.21 x 10(-9) M) affinity binding sites and were also sensitive to the antiproliferative effect but less than Daudi. HEp-2 and GL-5 cells, on the contrary, were very little sensitive to the antiproliferative effect of IFN and only expressed low affinity binding sites (Kd = 1.20 x 10(-8) M and Kd = 8.33 x 10(-9) M) respectively. On the other hand, IFN alpha-2b binding assays to peripheral blood lymphocytes from 8 healthy individuals were also carried out as normal cells for comparison. The values obtained were 433 +/- 166 receptors per cell and Kd = 3.68 2.66 x 10(-10) M.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión de receptores para el interferón alfa en líneas celulares procedentes de tumores humanos. Relación con el efecto antiproliferativo.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Expression of interferon alpha receptors in cell lines from human tumors. Relationship with the antiproliferative effect].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta cientifica venezolana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
