<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8159908</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferat, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mier, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castellanos, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute Pancreatitis is a complex clinical problem. The mexican experience in the Acute Pancreatitis treatment was analyzed, from the papers published between 1970-1990. During the first decades of the 20th century. Acute Pancreatitis was usually diagnosed at operation or at autopsy. Because a significant proportion of those diagnosed at surgery survived, early intervention was recommended. With the introduction of laboratory test, surgical diagnosis was regarded as unnecessary. In the past 30 years in has become clear that patients with severe forms of Pancreatitis do not survive without surgery and interest in the value of surgical measures has been renewed. We reviewed the papers of the surgical treatment of Acute Pancreatitis and its complications, only articles with documented surgical treatment were selected for analysis. From 1970 through 1990, 41 articles were published by Mexican Journals, only 10, fulfill the criteria, 632 patients with operative management. Patients with gall-stone associated Pancreatitis were the most frequent, 70-72%, and alcoholic Pancreatitis the second 20%; significant hospital morbidity occurred, recurrent sepsis was frequently identified; mortality rate was 52.6%. Available data do not provide any reasonable approach, therefore, we urge to develop clinical trials, with control groups for better results.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de la pancreatitis aguda. La experiencia mexicana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Surgical treatment of acute pancreatitis. The Mexican experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
