<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8185996</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rodríguez García, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Floriano Alvarez, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Rodríguez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Flórez, L J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Navarrete Guijosa, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between January-73 and February-92 twelve patients with digestive hemorrhage due to primary jejunoileal tumors were treated. Eight cases had rectal bleeding and four chronic gastrointestinal hemorrhage as first clinical manifestation. Patients underwent upper endoscopy, colonoscopy and barium enema. Three out of nine barium meals (33%), two out of four ultrasonographies (50%) and eight out of nine arteriographies (89%) were abnormal. The barium meals showed submucosal lesions on two occasions and a jejunal luminal mass. The ultrasonography detected two intrabdominal masses. All arteriographies, except one with extravased intestinal contrast and other which showed a hypovascular zone, depicted homogeneous hypervascular images. All patients were operated on. Seven segmental enterectomies, four limited resections and a polipectomy were performed. Seven tumours were found in the jejunum, three in the jejunoleum and two in the ileum. There were four leiomyosarcomas, three leiomyomas, two polyps, one leiomyoblastoma, one adenocarcinoma and one lymphoma. Rebleeding and mortality were absent.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia digestiva por tumoraciones yeyunoileales.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Digestive hemorrhage caused by jejunoileal tumors].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de enfermedades digestivas : organo oficial de la Sociedad Espanola de Patologia Digestiva</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
