<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8218764</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Liceras, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno-Osset, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Añón, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benages, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mínguez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mora, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 20 patients with diagnosis of functional dyspepsia due to dysmotility and/or reflux, the effectivity and tolerance of two prokinetic drugs--metochlopramide (MCP) (10 mg. three daily doses, vo) and cinitrapide (CTP) (1 mg., 3 daily doses, vo)--were assessed using a protocol of a propective and cross-sectional study after a blank period. Following the treatment with MCP and CTP, statistically significant improvements were observed in the intensity/severity of postprandial epigastric fullness, flatulence, epigastralgia, pyrosis, active regurgitations and anorexia. The MCP was more effective for the improvement of vomiting in these patients; however, the number of defecations per week increased significantly only after the CTP therapy. The therapeutical effectivity of both drugs, according to a subjective and objective global assessment was similar, with good results of 60-65% for MCP and 55-60% for CTP. Tolerance of both drugs was good. None of the patients spontaneously referred to the presence of side effects and only 3 patients (15%) treated with MCP and 2 patients (10%) treated with CTP mentioned some of the suggested side effects, which were absent before the onset of treatment. Both drugs produced an increase in the levels of Prolactine, but their average values were within the normal range. Only in two patients treated with MCP and in one patient treated with CTP, values slightly higher than the upper normal limit were observed. No significant differences were observed when comparing the results obtained with MCP therapy and CTP therapy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metoclopramida vs cinitaprida en el tratamiento de la dispepsia funcional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Metoclopramide versus cinitapride in the treatment of functional dyspepsia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
