<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8225787</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Borrell i Thió, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arias i Enrich, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study is aimed to describe the differences in mortality among the 38 wards of the city of Barcelona for the period 1983-89. Mortality data for years 1983 to 1989 came from the death certificates. The indicators used for the 38 city wards and the 10 city districts were: Comparative Mortality Figure, Ratio, Ratio of Potential Years of Life Lost, and Life Expectancy at birth. A descriptive analysis of these indicators by wards and district is offered; a cluster analysis based on these indicators was also performed. Wards from the same district are considered homogeneous for a given indicator, when all ward's values are higher, equal or lower to district average. The ward with the most unfavourable indicators and worst situation was Montjuïc, an exponent of shanty town problems until few years ago and located near the centre. Next in ranking, from worst to best situation, did appear the four wards of the city centre district, the old historical quarter. Other wards with high mortality rates were some peripheral areas, nearly all built recently such as Ciutat Meridiana, Bon Pastor and Zona Franca, and also other old wards, such as Poble Sec. Cluster analysis classified the wards with higher mortality in several different clusters, clearly split from the other more homogeneous wards. Five of 10 districts have been considered as homogeneous. This study has allowed a deeper knowledge of the geographical distribution of mortality in the city of Barcelona, until now analysed by city districts.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualtats de mortalitat en els barris de Barcelona, 1983-89.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Inequalities in mortality in the barrios of Barcelona, 1983-89].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
