<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8295533</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Luque, E H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muñoz de Toro de Luque, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Langhi, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Acuña, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romero Acuña, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of breast cancer is 25-30% of all malignant female tumors and represents the highest rate of mortality. To define those breast cancer patients at higher risk several prognostic factors are routinally evaluated in the primary tumor. Among them, the presence and degree of tumor involvement in axillary lymph node is one of the most powerful prognostic indicator. However, around 30% of node negative patients (good prognosis group) have recurrences and die within the next 10 years from diagnosis. Therefore, there is a need for markers to better discriminate biologic differences in the primary tumors. The techniques of molecular biology are shedding new insight into the subcellular pathology of malignancy. The crucial events of carcinogenesis, tumor progression, and metastatic spread are coming into focus at a molecular level. In some tumors, these advances in the laboratory are beginning to have applications at the bedside. Recently, abnormalities in the copy number and expression of several genes have been correlated with prognosis of individual patients with selected types of cancer. Molecular biology laboratories can provide useful predictive information that can be used to influence decision on the selection of treatment and to estimate a better risk stratification. Among these new markers are: oncongene amplification and/or over-expression, growth factors, cellular proliferation rate and ploidy, estrogens induced proteins, expression of metastasis related molecules, drug resistance associated proteins, etc. In this article we attempt to present a brief evaluation of a new technology that promises to add greater precision in evaluating molecular tumor markers and we mention some of its clinical applications.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores moleculares para predecir el pronóstico del cáncer de mama.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Molecular markers to predict the prognosis of breast cancer].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
