<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8297972</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calvo Martín, Y</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ontoria Maeso, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Merino Senovilla, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Sebastián, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pacheco, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The prevalence of habitual tobacco use in our area and its relationship to other epidemiological variables. DESIGN A highly structured interview was given to a random sample from the area in order to make a descriptive study of smokers' characteristics. Beforehand there had been: a pre-interview, training of the interviewers, reliability. SETTING The Arturo Eyries Base Health Area in Valladolid. PARTICIPANTS A random sample of 246 people over 14, extracted from a sampling background numbering 14,200. INTERVENTION Items related to tobacco addiction and included in the interview. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS 43.9% +/- 5 of our population smoked, consuming an average of 16.4 +/- 10 (mean +/- SD) cigarettes per day. The average starting age was 17.2 +/- 5.4, with males starting earlier. The highest percentage of smokers was found in the 30-39 age group, where female smokers exceeded female non-smokers. The typical smoker's profile is that of a married middle-aged man or woman, of average education and able to work. CONCLUSIONS We obtained a section of the population at risk, clearly defined for health purposes.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Oct 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabaquismo y su relación con unas variables en una ZBS urbana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Tobacco dependence and its relation to certain variables in an urban basic health area].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
