<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8318626</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Meana, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tamargo, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Muruzábal, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández-Tejada, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Moreno, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To discover the prevalence and the characteristics of the population group affected by infantile asthma and attended at a Health Centre. DESIGN Descriptive crossover study, conducted throughout 1991. SETTING Primary Care. PATIENTS Patients between 2 and 14 attending the Health Centre. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS We identified 349 children suffering from asthma (9.6% of the child population). 206 (59%) were male and 143 (41%), female. 45% of these children had shown symptoms suggesting asthma before their first birthday; 74% before they were 3; and 90% before 7. Family histories of asthma existed in 72%, of allergic rhinitis in 45% and atopic dermatitis in 17%. Out of the asthmatic children, 58% had allergic rhinitis and 20% atopic dermatitis. As to severity, 55% suffered light asthma, 31% moderate asthma and the remaining 14%, severe asthma. 79% had follow-up control of their asthma at the Health Centre. The rest were controlled by professionals outside the Centre (allergologists, pneumologists, hospital paediatricians etc.). 70% of the asthmatic children were passive smokers. CONCLUSIONS Infantile asthma has 9.6% prevalence among the children attending our Health Centre. These patients are generally cared for in Primary Care. Usually their symptoms have started in very early infancy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Jun 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asma infantil en una zona de salud: población afecta y características de la misma.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Infantile asthma within a health area: the population affected and its characteristics].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
