<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8333318</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-5062</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Navarro Celma, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cobo Plana, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aso Escario, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We review 312 suicide cases autopsied in the Forensic Institute of Zaragoza (Spain) during 1988-1991. Suicide rate was notabily higher than official statistics (15.01/100,000 habs. in Zaragoza vs. 4.3/100,000 Habs. from the National Statistic Institute). Reasons for this discrepancy are discussed emphasizing the role of suicide underrecording in the official statistics. Forensic Institute data are considered as a precise source for suicide epidemiologic study in Spain. Profiles for each different suicide type are described according to the results of our study concerning to age, sex, seasonal and month distribution, and other epidemiological data. A National Forensic Suicide Data Bank is proposed to approach properly the problematic of suicide epidemiology, based in the desirable informatic support to the Forensic Institutes. A modification in the Death Certificates is essential to include medico-legal etiology (suicide, accidental or criminal) which is essential in Forensic Reports but is not included, at the present, in the usual Death Certificates.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El suicidio consumado en Zaragoza (1988-1991). Aspectos epidemiológicos y perfiles suicidas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Suicides in Zaragoza (1988-1991). Epidemiology and outline of suicides].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas luso-espanolas de neurologia, psiquiatria y ciencias afines</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
