<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8337539</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8376</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>González Villalpando, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mitchell, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>Stern, M P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Haffner, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the results of a population based survey in a low income area of Mexico City. The equivalent of three census tracts were identified and enumerated. The age eligible population (35-64 yrs) in the zone comprised 2253 subjects. A household interview was obtained in 94.8% and a physical exam with laboratory determinations was performed in 62.6% of the total population. The total number of cases studied was 1411 of which 565 were males and 846 were females. Age group distribution was as follows: group 1 (35-44 y) 235 men, 367 women; group 2 (45-54 y) 203 men, 289 women; and group 3 (55-64 y) 127 men, 190 women. The physical exam included the following measurements: height, weight, blood pressure measured with a random zero sphygmomanometer, subscapular and triceps skinfold measurements, and waist and hip circumferences. The body mass index (BMI) was calculated according to a standard formula; the subscapular/triceps ratio was used as centrality index and the waist/hip ratio was used to indicate upper/lower body fat distribution. In addition, the following blood lipids were measured following a 12 hr fast: total and HDL, LDL, VLDL-cholesterol as well as triglycerides. The mean BMI for women was 28.9 kg/m2, for men it was 27 kg/m2. The subscapular/triceps skinfold ratio revealed a predominantly central fat distribution pattern in both sexes. The waist/hip circumference ratio showed a predominantly lower fat distribution pattern also in both sexes.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de lípidos sanguíneos y riesgo aterogénico en población abierta urbana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Blood lipid levels and atherogenic risk in an open urban population].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de investigacion clinica; organo del Hospital de Enfermedades de la Nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
