<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8347053</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Spíndola, M del C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villavicencio, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mar Chavira, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez Trigos, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izaguirre Avila, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ruiz de Chávez Cervantes, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casanova, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this trial was to estimate changes in the coagulation and fibrinolysis systems during the thrombolytic treatment with recombinant human tissue-type plasminogen activator (rt-PA) in patients with acute myocardial infarction and correlate with hemorrhagic complications. We studied 17 patients with a 3 hours-continuous systemic infusion of 100 mg of rt-PA. Prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, thrombin time, fibrinogen splits products, plasminogen, alfa-2-antiplasmin (a-2AP) and antithrombin III (AT-III) were performed before, during and after infusion. Most patients showed lengthening coagulation times. Fibrinogen and plasminogen were decreased and PDF was increased. No variations in alpha-2AP or AT-III were observed. The recuperation of fibrinogen levels occurred in 3 hours and there was hyperfibrinogenemia after day 3. No hemorrhagic complication was observed in patients with abnormalities in these coagulation or fibrinolytic tests.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variaciones en la hemostasia y fibrinolisis durante el tratamiento del infarto agudo del miocardio (IAM) con activador tisular del plasminógeno (atPIG). Estudio de 17 casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Variations in hemostasis and fibrinolysis during the treatment of acute myocardial infarct (AMI) with tissue-type plasminogen activator (TTPA). A study of 17 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
