<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8349135</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Molina Sosa, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales Garcia, V E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ectopic pregnancy (EP) treated by traditional methods, signifies an approximate lose of fertility capacity of the patient, of 50%. The early diagnosis allows conservative treatment with metotrexate (MTXE), with the objective of preserving the affected tube (salpynx) and its function. Early detection of EP, intact, was done, in 11 cases, with the following parameters: clinical picture, ultrasonography (Us) (empty uterus, adnexial mass and free fluid; adnexial ring or extrauterine embryo); quantitative determination of beta fraction of chorionic gonadotropin (CGH b) and laparoscopic observation, when the following characteristics were met: tubal pregnancy, no greater than 30 mm, intact tubarian serosa, lack of active bleeding and visualization of all pelvic cavity. MTXE 12.5 mg, intrasacularly via laparoscopy in eight patients, and three by laparotomy. The ulterior control of the procedure was: careful surveillance during eight days, Us daily and CGH b in two occasions; ten patients evolutionated satisfactorily, two of them required additional dosis of MTXE, parenterally, 0.5 mg/kg and citovorum factor, 0.1 mg/kg/4 days. The obtained conclusions are: 1. Conservative treatment with MTXE may be carried out provided the conditions established before, are met. 2. The patient's follow up must be precise and because of the high cost of the determination every third day of CGH b, Us may be used. Hysterosalpingography was done in five patients after six months of the procedure, and tubal permeability was seen.(ABSTRACT TRUNCATED AT 250 WORDS)</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento conservador del embarazo ectópico con metotrexate.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Conservative therapy of ectopic pregnancy with methotrexate].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
