<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8466992</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ortega de la Cruz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Martínez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Gallardo, L C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Damas Fernández-Figares, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The physical and chemical compatibility of an enteral diet (standard Precitene) with a series of liquid preparations included in the hospital's formulary was evaluated. These preparations are included in the following groups: vitamins, antibiotics and chemotherapeutic drugs, analgesics, antiepileptic drugs, neuroleptics, bronchodilators, expectorants, antihistamines, immunosuppressors and short chain triglycerides. Phase separation, particle growth pH variation, osmolality increase and viscosity increase were studied. The results obtained indicate that the majority of the drugs studied are compatible from a physical and chemical point of view with the enteral diet used, at least during a 24 hour period, with the exception of those drugs which, because of their pH, acidify the mixture, causing problems of increased viscosity and particle growth, and of those liquid preparations of continuous oleous phase where phase separation is unavoidable. Lastly, a series of recommendations are given on cases where joint administration of drugs with enteral nutrition is suitable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Compatibilidad físico-química de medicamentos con nutrición enteral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Physico-chemical compatibility of drugs with enteral nutrition].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
