<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8471169</identifier>
<setSpec>0539-6115</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bacardi-Gascón, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez-Cruz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez-Martínez, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Reyes-Rodríguez, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment of skinfold thickness has been used to estimate protein reserve through arm muscle area (AMA) and through arm fat area (AFA) it can assess caloric reserve. The aim of this paper is to compare trends of AMA in pre-school children living in Tijuana with american children of the same ages. This study has been accomplish in pre-school children attending to the Federal Education System. Through a randomly sample it was chosen 30 school, afterwards in systematic was done to assess 900 children aged 48 to 78 months old. This studied variables were: weight, height, arm circumference and triceps skinfold thickness, obtained according to accepted techniques at the international literature. From which were created AMA and AFA, according to formulas already described. A multiple regression model was obtained from AMB to height, between expected and experimental values. Using analysis of variance to determined differences between slopes and intercepts. In this paper are shown the statistics and distributions for AMA and AFA. Correlations for reference and experimental values were linear and no significant differences were observed between the slopes and intercepts of the set of data. These results suggest that form the point of view considering AMA, growth rate between Tijuana children and American similars are apparently the same at this ages.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Areas grasa y muscular de brazo: indicadores para la evaluación nutricional del preescolar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Fatty and muscular areas of the arm: indicators for the nutritional evaluation of pre-school children].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Boletin medico del Hospital Infantil de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
