<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8494957</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Orgaz Gallego, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tojeiro Lorente, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pinnel Muñoz, M F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Laín Terres, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lozano Alvarez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres Martínez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez Gómez, M H</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Using criteria based on the bibliography, to assess drugs prescription in a Health Centre, in order to put forward corrective measures in line with the defects identified. DESIGN Descriptive and retrospective study. SETTING Santa Maria de Benquerancia Health Centre (Toledo). PARTICIPANTS A sample of 40% of the clinical records of patients over 14 produced records of patients treated with drugs for psychic disorders between October 1990 and October 1991. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS 248 prescriptions for these drugs were found. The most common diagnoses were: neurotic depression (33.1%), anxiety (25.8%) and insomnia (10.1%). Benzodiazepines made up 78.2% of the prescriptions. Of 8 quality criteria assessed, the compliance level was acceptable by WHO standards except in the recording in the notes of the diagnosis or problem for which the drug was prescribed (74.2% non-compliance); Alprazolam and Triazolam were not considered first-choice benzodiazepines (31.3% non-compliance); and there was 44.5% non-compliance by Primary Care physicians with the non-prescription of anti-psychotic or stimulant MAO inhibitor antidepressants. CONCLUSIONS Quality-control studies, such as this one, in order to identify problems, to take corrective measures and subsequently assess them, are useful in improving care procedures.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1993 May 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicofármacos en atención primaria: calidad de la prescripción.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Psychopharmaceuticals in primary care: prescription quality].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
