<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8523926</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Zuazu, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Candela, M J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vicente, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacios, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND The aim of the present controlled study was to assess the effect of subcutaneous administration of desmopressin acetate (DDAVP) on the yield of Factor VIII (FVIII) and von Willebrand Factor (vWF) obtained in cryoprecipitates after plasmapheresis collection. SUBJECTS AND METHODS Fifteen plasma donors underwent twice plasmapheresis collections using an "Autophereses C. model A-201" and cryoprecipitates were prepared using standard methods. In every subject of study one of the procedure was performed 35 min after subcutaneous administration of DDAVP (0.3 micrograms/kg), obtained from a highly concentrated preparation of the drug (40 micrograms/ml). Prior to the other apheresis procedure no chemicals were administered. Evaluation of FVIII and vWF levels was performed in peripheral blood samples obtained at different time points and cryoprecipitates product samples. RESULTS Administration of DDAVP led to two-fold increase the yield of FVIII and vWF immediately before the performance of plasmapheresis. DDAVP stimulation resulted in an increase in the yield of FVIII and vWF in cryoprecipitates, compared with levels in the absence of the drug (703 +/- 53 and 768 +/- 51 U versus 227 +/- 12 and 362 +/- 20 U, respectively). No adverse effects but flushing were observed after DDAVP administration. CONCLUSIONS Subcutaneous administration of DDAVP prior to plasma collection is a safe method to improve drastically the content of FVIII and vWF in cryoprecipitates. This procedure should be considered as an useful tool to help in providing self-sufficiency of plasma.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Oct 28 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Administración subcutánea de desmopresina a donantes de plasma: estudio controlado.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Subcutaneous administration of desmopressin to plasma donors: a controlled study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
