<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8555389</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vilalta Franch, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Auquer, K</dc:author>
<dc:author>Franch, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Legazpi Rodríguez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Chocrón Bentata, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To determine the prevalence of psychopathology among those attending a primary care centre and discover its diagnostic distribution using the criteria of the DSM-III-R. DESIGN A crossover study of the prevalence of psychopathology. A two-phase study was performed by systematic sampling of one of every four visits. In the first phase the GHQ-28 was used. For those with suspected psychopathology (cut-off point 5/6) a semi-structured interview, Goldberg's CIS, was performed. They were assigned a diagnosis from the DSM-III-R. SETTING Maluquer Salvador Health Centre, Girona. PATIENTS A sample of 400 patients between 15 and 65 who attended the Centre for any reason. There were only 2.9% losses (2.1% in the first phase and 0.8% in the second). MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS Overall prevalence of psychopathology was 38.8% (Cl 34.05-43.55), with depression accounting for 10.3% (major depression 6% and dysthymia 4.3%), anxiety 13.8% (generalised 7.3%, panic 3% and obsessive/compulsive 3%) and adaptive disorder 9.5%. CONCLUSIONS One of every three patients attending a health centre suffers from some kind of psychiatric disorder.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de psicopatología en un centro de atención primaria.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Prevalence of psychopathology at a primary care center].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
