<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8599621</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bermejo, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Juana, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hidalgo, F J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the results of a study done in the departments of hospital pharmacy of our country with the aim of knowing their participation in the use and clinical follow up of patients with enteral nutrition. 293 questionnaires were sent out, and 121 were filled out and returned (41.3%). The responses were classified into three groups, according to the number of hospital beds, considering &gt; or = 1000 (large), 500-1000 (medium), and &lt; or = 500 (small). The data were analyzed by means of a statistical program (R-Sigma Horus). 79% (68) of the small hospitals have a unitary dose drug dispensation system, and the Enteral Nutrition was distributed through this system in 53% (50) of them; only 29% (27) of them have a stock of these preparations on the wards. 93% (14) and 65% (54) of the large and small hospitals respectively, prefer the use of enteral nutrition as opposed to parenteral nutrition. 85% (11) of the large hospitals have protocols for the use of enteral nutrition, this being 62% (10) and 59% (47) in medium and small hospitals. The committees for artificial nutrition are present in 75% of the large hospitals, in addition to which, in 66% of these there is a nutritional support team. A pharmacist from the department of pharmacy participates in both multidisciplinary groups. If it is necessary to manipulate the enteral nutrition preparations, in 30% of the departments of pharmacy of the smaller hospitals, this is centralized, being done by personnel of the department itself; in 59% of them (19) there is a specific area for the elaboration, which is not the case in large hospitals. Drugs are mixed with the enteral nutrition in 25% (1), 12% (1), and 9% (4) of the large, medium and small hospitals respectively. There is great, active participation of the hospital pharmacists in the activities of the multidisciplinary nutritional support systems, although at the present time, the involvement of the departments of pharmacy in the centralization of the manipulation of the enteral nutrition is reduced. It is necessary therefore, to implement the development of enteral nutrition programs with a quality guarantee from the departments of pharmacy.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Participación de los servicios de farmacia hospitalarios en la nutrición enteral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The participation of hospital pharmacy services in enteral nutrition].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
