<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8600555</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gallardo-Díaz, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kageyama-Escobar, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Erviti-Erice, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lara-Rodríguez, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leyva-Flores, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To analyze primary health care service (PHCS) utilization by febrile patients in a malarial area of Mexico. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional study was carried out in September, 1993, in 32 communities of Tabasco (decentralized health services) and Campeche (non-decentralized) states. Predictors of utilization were analyzed using descriptive statistics and logistic regression analysis. RESULTS 817 febrile patients received care at home 55% of all febrile patients received care at home (SELF), 16.5% by PHCS and 17% by volunteer collaborators, with no significant differences in health services utilization between states. Febrile patients living in communities where PHCS was available used these facilities 11 times more than those without PHCS (C.I. 95%: 7.0-18.2%). Severely febrile patients used PHCS 2.8 times more than mild-moderate cases (C.I. 95%: 1.7-4.6%). Febrile patients under 13 years of age used PHCS 1.9 times more than older patients. Two per cent of febrile patients consisted of malaria cases. CONCLUSIONS There was no difference between decentralized and non-decentralized health services regarding the utilization of PHCS. Fever symptoms must be evaluated as a single screening indicator of malarial disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de servicios de salud por febriles en un área de transmisión de paludismo en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Utilization of health services by febrile patients in a malaria transmission area in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
