<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8693351</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Avila-Burgos, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>OFFtos-Burgoa, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Silva-Aycaguer, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gutiérrez-Zúñiga, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández-Peña, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To construct a comprehensive model to evaluate the social or overall impact of a chronic disease. MATERIAL AND METHODS Case studies of a convenience sample of 28 patients seen at secondary and tertiary levels of health care services. Bronchitis was selected for evaluation. Among the variables included in the model are the direct costs of health care for bronchitis, the indirect costs or costs of opportunity, and the intangible costs or loss of quality of life. Information on costs estimated by the home institution was also included. RESULTS The social costs attributable to this condition are as high as $ 14 761.60 each case per year; 53% of this cost corresponds to case-management at health care services; 5% to household economic costs; 14% to intangible costs and 28% to production costs. CONCLUSIONS The model allowed the identification of variables necessary to evaluate production, household and intangible costs, which have been seldom utilized in our country. Including these variables results in a more comprehensive economic evaluation of social costs of disease.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Mar-Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El costo social de la bronquitis crónica en la Ciudad de México: una experiencia piloto.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The social cost of chronic bronchitis in Mexico City: a pilot study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
