<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8695147</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Viader Farré, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blanco Ollero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Robledo Strauss, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Domínguez, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casado Chocán, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz Espejo, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Familial amyloidotic polyneuropathy type I (FAF-I) is caused by a specific genetic mutation that gives rise to a transthyretin anomaly whose presence in serum constitutes the biochemical marker for this disease. We studied the serum of 7 patients and 16 asymptomatic members of their immediate families using ELISA with FD-6 monoclonal antibody to detect the transthyretin anomaly. Positive results were found for the 7 patients, including the 2 patients whose disease was apparently sporadic, and 12 carriers were detected among the family members. This technique makes sural nerve biopsy unnecessary for establishing a diagnosis in patients whose clinical signs are consistent with FAP-I. Asymptomatic carriers are also detected, facilitating appropriate genetic counseling.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del anticuerpo monoclonal FD-6 para el diagnóstico y la detección de portadores en la polineuropatía amiloidótica familiar tipo I.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The use of FD-6 monoclonal antibody in diagnosing and detecting the carriers of familial amyloidotic polyneuropathy type I].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
