<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8702343</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Cañellas Engel, S</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To underscore the importance of psychological evaluation in erectile dysfunction. METHODS Different methods of psychological evaluation (questionnaires, tests, directive interview, etc.) are utilized in erectile dysfunction. We use a flexible approach since different patients require different treatments. RESULTS The curative process is directly related with the psychotherapist's interpretation of the information given by the patient and the analysis of the resistance to the resolution of the underlying conflict that may arise. CONCLUSIONS Erectile dysfunction may be organic or psychogenic. Although it may arise from organic causes, the physical symptoms cannot be separated from the psychological components. The membrane that separates the conscious from the subconscious becomes permeable through psychotherapy. The success of treatment largely depends on the patient's desire to be cured. Correct diagnosis is essential to treatment by behavioural, psychoanalytical or combined and adaptable therapy. The importance of strict observation of the protocol and a multidisciplinary approach, which includes the intervention of a psychotherapist, is emphasized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El proceso psicoterapéutico de la disfunción eréctil.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Psycho-therapeutic process of erectile dysfunction].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
