<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8712040</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Torres, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Rodríguez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Puche, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cueto Ladrón de Guevara, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castillo Pérez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zuluaga Gómez, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Treatment of infiltrant vesical cancer has traditionally been the grounds for intense controversy. Transurethral resection (TUR) followed by high voltage radiotherapy (RT) in selected cases of locally advanced vesical urothelial tumours can be a valid alternative for the treatment of this condition. This paper discloses the experience of our center in the treatment of this type of tumours over the last few years (1979-1993) on 85 selected patient, with a considerable percentage of living patients and with no evidence of disease after the follow-up period; taking into account the influence on these results of the cytologic grade, tumoral size, gross appearance of the tumour, and tumoral stage. Additionally, these results are compared with those from other authors using similar therapeutic method as well as with the results from different therapeutical approaches, illustrating one more the intense controversy that exists relative to the management of these patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioterapia post RTU en el tratamiento de tumores vesicales localmente avanzados.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Post-TUR radiotherapy in the treatment of locally advanced bladder tumor].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
