<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8715262</identifier>
<setSpec>0864-0319</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>dos Santos, B R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Boettcher Schneider, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Duarte de Oliveira, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Krilow, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Santos de Souza, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Brandt Funcke, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of microcomputers in medical education to assess the training process in Primary Health Care is analyzed. The experimental study consisted of 8 modules related to immunization campaigns, nursing care of healthy children, sanitation, nursing care of women, epidemiology and statistics, and nursing care of those diseases presenting the highest prevalence. The program is based on the basic software "Evaluation of Training", and designed in basic language. Each module consisted of a set of questions and each set had 3 different forms of feedback: the given form, the controlled form, and the form for searching. The independent variable of this investigation was the evaluation of training by microcomputers, and the dependent variable was the cognitive domain and development. The sample comprises 16 individuals studying on the eighth semester of a nursing course, and each group is made up by 8 students (a control group and an experimental group). Data obtained from this investigation were assessed by the test of nonparametric indicators. Results evidenced that the evaluation of training by a microcomputer provided a significantly higher performance in comparison with noncomputer assisted evaluation. Students were satisfied regarding the interaction with the microcomputer and with the performance of the evaluation. Further investigations in this field are recommended.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Jul-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La educacion de cuidados primarios de salud. Avaluacion diagnostica y de la formacion mediante microcomputadores.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Education in primary health care. Diagnostic evaluation of teaching using microcomputers].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de enfermeria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
