<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8728767</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Noguera, E C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wafa Hames, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">UNLABELLED Quantitative hepatobiliary scintigraphy (Q.H.S.), with 99m Tc-DISIDA was performed on 15 control subjects and 32 alcoholic cirrhotic patients (A.C.). We used a dynamic planar scintigraphy (30 seg/frame, up to 45 min) technique following injection intravenously of 99m Tc-DISIDA. Time/activity curves were obtained from the right upper lobe of the liver and the: 1) slope uptake, 2) half-time (T 1/2 min) uptake, 3) excretion half-time (T1/2 min), were measured from the curve. The A.C. were divided in two groups, IIA (n = 32) and IIB (n = 6) if the excretory curve show negative slope or not respectively. RESULTS The mean value (+/- 1 D.S. 95% coinfidence interval) of the slope uptake of the A.C. IIB (1.2 +/- 0.40) was significantly slower than a.C. IIA (2.8 +/- 0.39) and control (4.5 +/- 1.17, p = 0.0001 respectively). The difference also was significantly when the mean of A.C. IIA was compared to control (p = 0.007). The mean of T1/2 uptake of A.C.IIB (62.2 +/- 22.2) was significantly longer than A.C. IIA (28.4 +/- 4.4 p = 0.011) and control (17.9 +/- 3.87, p = 0.003). The mean T1/2 excretory of the A.C. IIA (90.0 +/- 17.8) was also significant delayed compared to the mean of normal control (35.6 +/- 7.6 p = 0.001). In the A.C. IIB the excretion plateau curve was associated with visualization of the gallbladder and bowel activity suggesting that the excretion of the IDA preferentially came from the left hepatic lobe. We conclude that alcoholic cirrhotic patients have impaired the mechanism related with the uptake/excretion transport of organic anion, and suggest that noninvasive Q.H.S. with 99m Tc-DISIDA, can be a useful clinical technique to be used for the quantification of hepatic function in cirrhotic alcoholic patients.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Centellografía hepatobiliar cuantitativa con 99m Tc DISIDA en sujetos normales y en cirróticos alcohólicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quantitative Tc 99m - DISIDA hepatobiliary scintigraphy in normal and cirrhotic alcoholic subjects].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
