<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8731276</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-8910</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Battellino, L J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Azcurra, A I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kremer, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lamberghini, F C</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Cattoni, S T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calamari, S E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a cross sectional epidemiological survey for the purpose of evaluating the state of dental health of schoolchildren (aged 6-7 and 12-13) living in Sampacho and Porteña, two towns in the Province of Córdoba (Argentina), supplied with drinking water containing quite different levels of fluoride, are described and analized. In Sampacho, F- level is 9.05 mg/l. while in Porteña the concentration is of 0.19 mg/l. The proportion of schoolchildren (aged 6-7 and 12-13) without caries was significaticantly higher in Sampacho than in Porteña, while the dmf-t, dmf-s, DMF-T and DMF-S indexes were considerably higher in the latter place. The severity of caries in children (age 12-13) living in Sampacho ranged from low to moderate (DMF-T = 2.53), whilst in Porteña the range went from moderate to high (DMF-T = 4.41). No cases of dental fluorosis were recorded in Porteña; but in Sampacho, there was a high proportion of children with mild fluorosis (aged 6-7) and mild or severe fluorosis (aged 12-13). Calcium, phosphate, thiocyanate, protein and secretory Ig A salivary levels were similar not only among schoolchildren of both towns but also among those with different experience of caries and different degrees of severity of fluorosis. It is concluded that urgent (preventive and/or curative) sanitary measures are necessary for the purpose of reducing or controlling caries in Porteña as well as dental fluorosis in Sampacho.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de salud bucodental de escolares residentes en localidades abastecidas con agua de consumo humano de muy alto y muy bajo contenido de fluoruros.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Dental health status of students living in places supplied with drinking water of very high and very low levels of fluorides].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de saude publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
