<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8731295</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-5504</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Padrón-Nieves, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodriguez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lamanna, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-González, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We measured the activity of the Na,K ATPase, Mg dependent and inhibited by ouabain, in microsomal fractions obtained from guinea pig myocardium and kidney, as weel as red cell ghosts. A group of animal was treated with beta-methyl digoxin (0.2 mg intraperitoneally) about one hour before obtaining the tissues. The control group received no medication. The plasma of both group, control and treated, had similar potassium concentrations (4.3 +/- 0.87 mM and 4.3 +/- 0.66 mM, respectively). The plasma digoxin concentrations from treated animals was always high (76.4 +/- 34.1 ng/ml). The Na,K-ATPase activity in the microsomal fraction from treated animals decreased by 28.7% in myocardium and by 27.7% in red cell ghosts, in comparison to the enzime activity measured in control animals. On the other hand, the Na/K activity obtained in kidney microsomal fraction did not change with treatment. We then measured the Na,K-ATPase activity in the red cell ghosts and microsomal fractions obtained from myocardium and kidney of untreated Guinea pigs. Adding digoxin in vitro (1 x 10(-9) M to 1 x 10(-3) M) we obtained, in myocardial fractions, a 50% maximal inhibition; the digoxin concentration causing half maximal effect (DI50) was 7 x 10(-5) M. In the kidney microsomal fraction we measured a 66% maximal inhibition of the enzime activity and DI50 was 2 x 10(-6) M. For red cell ghosts the maximal enzime inhibition was 34% and the DI50 was 1 x 10(-5) M. In conclusion, in the Guinea pig, the acute in vivo administration of beta-methyl digoxin causes a parallel inhibition of the Na,K-ATPase from myocardial fractions and red cell ghosts. We measured no significant change in the kidney microsomal fractions. We propose the determination of red cell Na,K-ATPase activity as possible indicator of digitalis effect on humans treated with these drugs.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Effecto de la beta-metil digoxina, administrada in vivo, sobre la actividad de la Na,K-ATPasa de diferentes tejidos de acure.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effect of the in vivo administration of beta-methyldigoxin on the Na, K-ATPase measured in different tissues of guinea pigs].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta cientifica venezolana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
