<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8762623</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Buckel, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aguiló, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Herzog, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morales, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pefaur, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosenfeld, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zavala, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report two insulin dependent diabetic patients with a past history of 21 and 30 years complicated with retinopathy, neuropathy and nephropathy with arterial hypertension and kidney failure. Simultaneous pancreas-kidney transplantation was done 8 and 18 months after starting hemodialysis, performing a double intraperitoneal implant with pancreato-duodeno-vesical anastomosis and contralateral kidney grafting with uretero vesical anastomosis using antireflux techniques. In the second case, a second kidney transplant from the same donor was needed, due to a thrombosis of renal vein. There was one rejection episode in each case but renal or pancreatic function was not impaired. Other observed complications were metabolic acidosis and hyperkalemia due to urine loss of bicarbonate, moderate arterial hypertension and bacterial and fungal infections. There was a graft dysfunction due to the association of vancomycin and cyclosporin. In conclusion, in the two presented patients, simultaneous pancreas-kidney transplantations were successful and they remain free of insulin or dialytic therapy 4 and 9 months after the operation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante simultáneo páncreas riñón. Primeros casos en Chile.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Simultaneous pancreas-kidney transplantation. First cases in Chile].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
