<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8766083</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Banús Gassol, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ribas, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Eres, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casado Cobo, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Albanell, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lorente Garín, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bellmunt Molins, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Solé Calvo, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Palacios, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Torres Mateos, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Morote Robles, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES The combination of carboplatin, methotrexate and vinblastine (M-CAVI) is an active and well-tolerated regimen for patients with bladder cancer who are ineligible for cisplatin-based regimens. We have prospectively randomized patients with locally advanced (T2-4 N0 M0) or locoregional (Tx N1 M0) bladder cancer suitable for subsequent surgical treatment to M-VAC or M-CAVI chemotherapy. METHODS M-CAVI consisted of carboplatin (300 mg/m2 on day 1 and later adjusted to 4.5 mg/dl/min according to Calvert's formula), methotrexate (30 mg/m2 on days 1, 15 and 22) and vinblastine (3 mg/m2 on days 1, 15 and 22). After 3-4 cycles, the patients were assessed for surgical resection. RESULTS To date, 60 patients have been included. There were 58 completely evaluable patients, 27 were randomized to M-VAC and 31 to M-CAVI. The overall response rates were similar for M-VAC (48%; confidence interval 95%, 26%-67%) and M-CAVI (45%; confidence interval 95%, 28%-62%). The pathological complete responses were similar for the M-VAC and M-CAVI regimens for both the group with locally advanced (27% vs 39%, p = NS) and locoregional (14% vs 14%, p = NS) bladder cancer. The median actuarial survival for the M-VAC treated group was 23 months and 18 months for the M-CAVI. M-VAC therapy was statistically significantly associated with more events of granulocytopenic fever, grade 2-3 nausea and vomiting, grade 2 alopecia and grade 3-4 mucositis. CONCLUSIONS The results achieved in the 60 patients included in the study indicate that M-CAVI is better tolerated than M-VAC, although both treatment regimens have similar overall response rates, pathological response rates and survival in patients with locally advanced and locoregional bladder cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados preliminares de un ensayo randomizado en fase II comparando M-VAC y M-CAVI en pacientes con cáncer de vejiga (T2-4 N0-1 M0).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Preliminary results of a phase II randomized controlled trial comparing M-VAC and M-CAVI in patients with bladder cancer (T2-4 N0-1 M0)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
