<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8768652</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez Astorga, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Piñera Palacio, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Noguerol Alvarez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Díaz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>de Aláiz Rojo, A T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdés Gómez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berrocal Varela, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To study the prevalence of sexual activity (SA), its characteristics and associated variables in a rural population-group of the over-60s. DESIGN A descriptive crossover study. SETTING Health Centre in the town of Pravia. PARTICIPANTS Residents who were 60 or over on March 1, 1995: 3,173 (1,362 men and 1,811 women). SOURCE Municipal roll (9,986 inhabitants). By simple randomised sampling, n = 177 (significance 5%, accuracy 7%). MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS A closed questionnaire administered by professional staff at the Centre measured: gender, age, socio-cultural data, functional capacity, pathologies and medicines depressing SA (MDSA), coital sexual relations (SR), other types of SA (OTSA), sexual dysfunctions, age at and reason for giving up SR (GSR). 181 questionnaires were filled in: 75 men and 106 women. Maintaining SR was significantly associated (p &lt; 0.05) with: being male, being younger, marriage, OH, functional independence. Not maintaining them was associated with vasculopathies, arthrosis and MDSA. Applying logistical regression analysis gave as predictive variables only: marital status, functional capacity and gender. CONCLUSIONS Half of the participants maintained some kind of SA. The presence of SR was basically linked to having a partner, being functionally independent and being male. We found a high percentage of sexual dysfunctions. We believe it is relevant to include evaluation of sexual function in overall evaluation of the elderly.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad sexual en ancianos en un medio rural.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sexual activity in the elderly in a rural environment].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
