<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8920030</identifier>
<setSpec>0535-5133</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montero-Ojeda, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arraga-Alvarado, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bernardoni, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Anderson, B E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Parra, O</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human ehrlichiosis is a zoonotic disease, caused by a rickettsia that infects leukocytes. It was described for the first time in the United States of America in 1986. More than 300 cases have been reported in that country. One case has been reported in Portugal, two in France and one more in a tourist coming from Mali (Africa). In Venezuela, a tropical country, where ehrlichiosis is endemic in dogs and horses, the first case of human ehrlichiosis is reported in a seventeen month old girl. She initially had symptoms compatible with a viral illness. Then she developed a rash, acute respiratory failure, hepato-splenomegaly, neurologic abnormalities, renal failure and hematologic alterations including pancytopenia and disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC). Different diagnoses were given before it was concluded that it was a case of ehrlichiosis. She was treated with tetracycline and very soon recovered. The initial diagnosis was made using buffy coat blood smears stained with Diff Quick Stain. Indirect Immunofluorescence (IFA) test was used to detect antibodies against Ehrlichia chaffeensis (1:126) but not to other rickettsias. Also the presence of platelets with ehrlichia bodies similar to E. platys from dogs, it was demonstrated, in peripheral blood from the child. The presence of these bodies in human platelets has not been previously reported. In this case, it could not be proved that the disease was transmitted by a tick bite. The presence of ehrlichia bodies in platelets from the girl's peripheral blood is also described.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Mar </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ehrlichiosis humana: reporte del primer caso en Venezuela.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Human ehrlichiosis: report of the 1st case in Venezuela].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Investigacion clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
