<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8948897</identifier>
<setSpec>0016-3813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Villatorio, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berenzon, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Mora, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, E K</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carreño, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Juárez, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes the results from a drug use survey conducted among high school students of the Federal District. The analysis suggested that being male and attending the last three years of high-school, differentiated significantly users from non users. These two variables, along with an older age, differentiated students that had used one substance from those that had used more than one. These variables had no effect on the decision of stopping the use after experimenting or continuing the use of substances. Significant variables were also perception of availability, having friends, parents or brothers that use substances, or to knowing drug users; peer approval and low perception of risk. Depression symptoms differentiated only users from non users but suicidal tendency grew with use; receiving information from friends influenced the decision of experimenting and of using more than one substance. Finally, the more severe patterns were related to the perception that there are no consequences for drug use in the school.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1995 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los factores que se relacionan con el inicio, el uso continuado y el abuso de sustancias psicoactivas en adolescentes mexicanos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Factors associated with initiation, continued use, and psychoactive substance abuse among Mexican adolescents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta medica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
