<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8948882</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gimferrer Garolera, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Callejas Pérez, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Canalís Arrayás, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Baldó Padró, X</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catalán Biel, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belda Sanchis, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work was to evaluate and compare the results of lung biopsies performed by videothoracoscopy (VT) and minithoracotomy (MT) in diffuse interstitial disease between 1992 and 1994, during which period 45 lung biopsies were performed on patients (20 women) with a mean age of 56 years. Thirty-one biopsies were performed by VT (group I) and 14 by MT (group II). For all patients we recorded duration of procedure, days to discharge after surgery, total time with a pleural drain in place, and volume of tissue sample. Diagnosis was possible in all cases. Mean duration of surgery was 49.3 minutes for group I and 58.2 minutes for group II. Mean time to discharge was 6.7 days for group I and 10.1 for group II. Mean time of pleural drainage was 3.8 days for group I and 5.9 days for group II. Mean volume of tissue sample was 6.5 cm3 for group I and 5.18 cm3 for group II. One patient died in group I from causes unrelated to surgical technique. In conclusion, lung biopsy with VT is effective and useful for diagnosing diffuse interstitial lung diseases. The sample obtained is in every way comparable to that obtained by thoracotomy. Mean hospital stay and mean time of postoperative drainage decreases significantly (p &lt; 0.05) with VT.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biopsia pulmonar en la enfermedad intersticial difusa: videotoracoscopia frente a toracotomía.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Pulmonary biopsy in diffuse interstitial disease: videothoracoscopy versus thoracotomy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos de bronconeumologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
