<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8966629</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Calderón-Ortiz, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejía-Mejía, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the results of a vaccination strategy on children under one year of age, aimed at increasing the coverage of the complete vaccination scheme, and at improving early entry into the program. MATERIAL AND METHODS In Tixtla, Guerrero, Mexico, from April to December 1994, two basic geo-statistical areas (BGSA) were studied. Each area had an average number of 100 children under one year of age. In the area of intervention, people from the community were hired on a permanent basis for early recruitment of children (under two months of age) and for appropriate vaccination of children with incomplete vaccination schemes. In the control area vaccination campaigns were offered periodically. RESULTS It was found that the strategy of intervention increased the percentage of completed vaccination schemes, from 21.1% to 93.5% among children under one year of age, as well as the recruitment rate. CONCLUSIONS This strategy can help to achieve a better coverage of vaccination programs in urban areas where coverage is low.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia de contratación permanente dentro del programa de vacunación universal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Strategy for permanent contracting within the program of universal vaccination].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
