<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8967643</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sánchez Echániz, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benito Fernández, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mintegui Raso, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montejo Fernández, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine if culture specimens of urine collected in perineal bags is reliable in detecting urinary tract infections in infants. MATERIAL AND METHODS A prospective study was carried out in a pediatric emergency room of an urban teaching hospital. Forty-eight infants, 12 months old or less, requiring an uncontaminated urine specimen due to the evaluation of febrile illness, suspected urinary tract infection or to a previously contaminated urine culture specimen. Two consecutive urine specimens were collected for culture. A urine specimen was collected in a perineal bag and afterwards all patients underwent suprapubic bladder aspiration. Cultures were considered positive if pure growth of more than 1.000 colonies/ml developed in the suprapubic aspiration urine specimen. RESULTS Thirty-two infants had coincident cultures in both urine specimens. A positive culture specimen of urine collected in a perineal bag (pure growth of more than 100,000 colonies/ml) had high sensitivity (100%) and high specificity 88.6% in predicting positive cultures from urine obtained by suprapubic aspiration. CONCLUSION A urine culture specimen meticulously collected with a perineal bag is a good screening method for detecting urinary tract infection in low risk infants.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección urinaria en el lactante: comprobación por punción suprapúbica del rendimiento del cultivo de orina obtenido por bolsa perineal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Urinary tract infection in infants: use of urine specimens obtained by suprapubic bladder aspiration in order to determine the reliability of culture specimen of urine collected in perineal bag].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
