<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8991703</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Echevarría, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prieto, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Izuel, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arnedo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rosario Pac, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>León, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montaner, M D</dc:author>
<dc:author>López, J A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND To document an outbreak of Hepatitis B in a gypsy community in the Upper Aragón region, as well as the control measures adopted. METHODS Documented study of Hepatitis B cases and families, including an epidemiological survey and the determining of hepatitis B viral indicators (MVHB) using immunoenzymatic methods. RESULTS 84.8% participation (39/45). During the months of February and March 1988, 5 cases of Hepatitis B were detected in a gypsy community in the Upper Aragon region (12.8% attack rate, 5/39), with an average age of 13.0 + 7.3, (4 women and one man). Four of the cases detected had previously undergone tatooing. The fifth case was due to direct transmission from mother to a recently born child. The MVHB study of families showed a further two cases. MVHB rate being 17.9% (7/39). Vaccinations were given to all persons susceptible to the disease. CONCLUSIONS It is suggested that tatooing could be a significant factor to be considered in relation to the transmission of Hepatitis B in gypsy communities. Due to the high rate of incidence of the disease in this ethnic group, general vaccination is prescribed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote epidémico de hepatitis B por tatuaje en familias de étnia gitana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Epidemic outbreak of hepatitis B from the tattoo in gypsy families].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
