<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>8998689</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vargas Marcos, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Increasing exposure to chemical products and substances could be affecting the changes that are being observed in the epidemiological pattern of illnesses. An estimation of the scale and seriousness of exposure, its effects and consequences, cannot be measured exclusively in terms of the classical indicators of mortality and morbidity. The prevention and control of risks associated with the use of chemical products requires a more integral approach, which studies the effects of chemical products in both the short- and long-term. A proposal is made for a "Risk Evaluation" strategy, based on the collection of exhaustive data, the estimation of response dosage, evaluation of exposure, identification of bio-indicators and risk characterisation. Reference is made to both European and national legislation with regard to the question of classification and labelling of chemical products, specific risk phrases and cautionary advice, files on safety and classification data, in accordance with the specific effects on human health (substances whose effects are carcinogenic, mutagenic and toxic to reproduction). A description is provided of the main organisations devoted to the development and implementation of chemical risk prevention and control programmes. Finally, reference is made to the most relevant sources of information for consultation and studying chemical products.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y control del riesgo de los productos químicos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The prevention and control of the risks with chemical products].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista espanola de salud publica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
