<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9005727</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Dalmau Serra, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aznar Lucea, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vayá Montaña, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blesa Baviera, L C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez Silvestre, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Recent studies in adults have shown that hemorrheological alterations are predictive of early cardiovascular disease, but it is unknown if they are related to hyperlipemia or are secondary to an established atherosclerotic process and if they appear during childhood. PATIENTS AND METHODS Several rheological parameters have been studied in 36 patients with familial hypercholesterolemia (FH). These patients were between 2 and 16 years of age and 12 of them were being treated with cholestyramine. Thirty-five controls (CG) were individually matched for age and sex. RESULTS The FH patients treated with cholestyramine did not show significant differences in any of the six rheological parameters that were studied when compared to the other patients. Therefore, the results of the FH group were analyzed as a whole when they were compared with the CG. The following significant differences were found: Index of erythrocyte aggregation at stasis 5.0 +/- 1.2 vs 3.6 +/- 1.0 (p &lt; 0.001), index of erythrocyte aggregation at low rate of blood shears 8.1 +/- 1.7 vs 6.9 +/- 1.4 (p &lt; 0.001) and plasma viscosity 1.19 +/- 0.11 vs 1.16 +/- 0.04 mPA/s (p &lt; 0.01). There were no significant differences in the plasma fibrinogen nor in the blood viscosity at shear rats of 230/s and 23/s. Carotic echo-doppler was taken in the HF patients which was normal, indicative of the absence of atherosclerosis lesions in the fibrous plaque phase. CONCLUSIONS These results indicate that there are hemorrheological alterations in absences of established atherosclerotic lesions, which are associated with hypercholesterolemia and that emerge in the pediatric population. Therefore, research in FH patients offers new data to evaluate the atherogenic risk and its complications.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuvos marcadores de riesgo aterogénico: perfil hemorreológico en niños y adolescentes con hipercolesterolemia familiar.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[New markers of atherogenic risk: hemorrheological profile in children and adolescents with familial hypercholesterolemia].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
