<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9020008</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Torres Jiménez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Puig, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mateos Antón, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Buño Soto, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Urolithiasis is one of the most frequent causes of morbidity in developed countries and its incidence is close to 5%. In our experience, 67.4% of urinary stones contain calcium oxalate as the main component, and hyperoxaluria plays an important role in the pathophysiology of this type of stone. The mechanisms responsible for the increment in urinary excretion of oxalate could involve oxalic acid synthesis. This increase could be due either to an increment of its endogenous formation or to an exogenous load of its precursors. Furthermore, an increased intestinal oxalate absorption is a frequent cause of hyperoxaluria and urolithiasis. Ingestion of oxalate rich foods, imbalance in the supply of other nutrients that influence oxalic acid absorption and GI disorders with malabsorption and/or decreased degradation of intraluminal oxalate can increase intestinal oxalate transport and cause hyperoxaluria. In this article we review the physiological mechanisms that control the oxalate pool: endogenous synthesis, exogenous supply, intestinal absorption and renal excretion of oxalic acid. We analyze the causes and the pathophysiological mechanisms that increase urinary oxalate excretion. We describe a protocol for the biochemical study of patients with hyperoxaluria and the therapeutic measures to reduce urinary oxalate are reviewed. Finally, possible research that may provide further insight into oxalate metabolism in patients with hyperoxaluria are discussed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperoxaluria y litiasis renal.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Hyperoxaluria and renal calculi].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
