<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9053033</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jiménez Torres, N V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poveda Andrés, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Font Noguera, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The care of patients with parenteral nutrition is made up of the care provided by the different members of a multidisciplinary team. This cooperative participation is translated into the establishment and the application of a therapeutic protocol as a frame for the use of parenteral nutrition. It is usual for these protocols to include the normalization of the formulations of parenteral nutrition units, as well as containing logistical processes such as prescription, preparation, dispensation, and administration. Also, the classical review studies on the use of parenteral nutrition aim to know the degree of compliance with the protocols and/or the variability in the application of this therapy. However, this model aims to re-direct itself towards the improvement of the effectiveness and the therapeutic quality obtained in patients treated with parenteral nutrition. The objective of the present study is to present explicit criteria to be included in the parenteral nutrition protocols and the constitute action guidelines for the identification of problems and taking decisions in the resolution and prevention of the same. Also, they are elements for the evaluation of the applied processes and of therapeutic results obtained in patients fed intra-venously.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación a una propuesta de criterios terapéuticos para nutrición parenteral.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Approximation of a proposal of therapeutic criteria for parenteral nutrition].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Nutricion hospitalaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
