<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9072787</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0906</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Güitrón, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Adalid, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Endoscopic sphincterotomy (ES) by itself is safe and effective, with acceptable rates of morbidity and mortality. However, for various reasons ES cannot be successfully completed in all cases, and other treatment options must be considered, including precut or guided sphincterotomy. Results from studies evaluating precut sphincterotomy are conflicting. AIM The aim of this prospective trial was to assess the safety and efficacy of standard, guided and precut endoscopic sphincterotomy. PATIENTS AND METHODS During a period of 5 years, endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) was performed 1,000 times. Of five hundred seven patients, 364 were women and 143 men, had biliary obstruction and were candidates for ES, which was successful in 477 (94%). Sixteen (3.3%) complications occurred, but only 6 (1.25%) were serious. Procedure-related mortality occurred in one patient (0.2%). RESULTS In 346 patients (68.2%) we performed standard ES, in 86 (16.9%) precut, in 45 (8.9%) guided and in 30 (6.0%) ES cannot be successfully completed. Morbidity rate for endoscopic management of three-sphincterotomy types is similar, with 3.7% in standard ES, 2.3% in precut and 2.2 in guided sphincterotomy. CONCLUSIONS Standard ES, precut and guided sphincterotomy are safety and efficacy and complication rate can be lowered if the procedure is strictly focused to local anatomy and therapeutic requirements.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad y eficacia de la esfinterotomía guiada y con técnica de precorte. Experiencia de 5 años.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Safety and efficacy of sphincterotomy using guided and precut techniques. A 5-year experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de gastroenterologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
