<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9072513</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alberquilla Menéndez-Asenjo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Rodríguez-Salinas, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pilas Pérez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rivera Guzmán, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ugalde Díez, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To describe the Work Disability (WD) Profiles Lengths issued according to diagnostic in Usera's Sanitary District of Madrid, and compare them with recommended standards obtained with different methodology (consensual-practical experience) by several authors. METHOD A descriptive study of 3555 WD informed by 31 general practitioners during 1992. Variables were achieved from P-14 registers, using by Medical Inspection. Diagnoses were processed according to CIPSAP-2-Def. The results were compared with recommended standards lengths proposed by INSALUD Experts Commission, (consensus) and with another obtained by practical experience by others. RESULTS Grate variability in day's lengths of WD were observed (mean average = 45.1 +/- 79.7 days; medium = 16 days; mode = 4 days). Respiratory diseases score for the highest frequency (20.6%) while Muscle skeletics accounts for more days out of work (23.1% of working days lost). Applying to our study the intervals of lengths days proposed by the INSALUD (consensus), up to 75% of potential long-lasting and only 25% of short-lasting processes could be included. Nevertheless, a higher concordance is observed when they are compared with other authors with a similar methodology. CONCLUSIONS The recommended lengths standards of work disability established by the INSALUD are difficult to be achieved in actual practice.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Nov-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfiles de duración de incapacidad laboral transitoria en un distrito sanitario y su comparación con algunos estándares propuestos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Profiles of the duration of temporary work incapacity in a health district and its comparison with some proposed standards].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gaceta sanitaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
