<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9091027</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sanz Guajardo, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Espejo Martínez, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Doxazosin, an alfa-1 adrenoceptor antagonist, was compared with nitrendipine, a calcium antagonist, to evaluate their efficacy and safety in 61 patients with mild to moderate hypertension. 31 patients were assigned randomly to receive 1-16 mg of doxazosin and 30 patients were assigned to 10-20 mg of nitrendipine during 14 weeks (10 weeks of titration and 4 weeks of maintenance). Mean final dose was 6.1 mg for doxazosin and 15.6 mg for nitrendipine. Both treatments reduced supine and standing diastolic and systolic blood pressure (p &lt; 0.01 for all comparisons). 22 patients in the doxazosin group (78.6%) and 18 in the nitrendipine group (78.3%) were considered therapy successes. There were not clinically significant changes in laboratory tests for both groups. Global assessment of adverse events was similar for both treatments (46.7% for doxazosin and 44.8% for nitrendipine), although patients treated with nitrendipine presented facial rush (20%) against none of the doxazosin group (p &lt; 0.05). Withdrawals due to adverse events were higher in the nitrendipine group than in the doxazosin one (20.7% versus 6.7%, p = 0.14). The results of this study confirms that both antihypertensives reduced blood pressure in patients with mild to moderate hypertension. Furthermore, doxazosin treatment demonstrates a fewer number of withdrawals caused by adverse events.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio randomizado, comparativo, sobre la eficacia y seguridad de doxazosina frente a nitrendipino en el tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial ligera a moderada.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Randomized, comparative study to evaluate efficacy and safety of doxazosin versus nitrendipine in the treatment of mild to moderate hypertension].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
