<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9103164</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Colín Lizalde, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>González Hermosillo, J A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kershenovich, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Picos Bovio, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lara, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Iturralde Torres, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Radiofrequency ablation were performed in 465 consecutive patients with Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome. We demonstrated evidence of multiple accessory pathways in 18 patients (3.9%); 17 had two, and one had three accessory pathways. In three of these there was additional right atrio-fascicular connection. There were 27 manifest and 10 concealed accessory pathways. Six patients had Ebstein's anomaly associated with accessory pathways. The location of the accessory pathways was in the right posterior portion of the ventricular septum in 16, the left posterior portion of the ventricular septum in 5, the right free wall in 5, the left wall in 7, the right anteroseptal in 3, the midseptum in 1, and one right anterolateral. Of the 37 pathways, 32 (86%) accessory pathways were ablated successfully without complications. Duration of the procedure was 100 +/- 58 minutes, and fluoroscopic time 40 +/- 17 minutes. The mean applications were 26 +/- 17 and the power level of the radiofrequency current 41 +/- 6 W. A follow-up of 80 +/- 40 days after ablation demonstrated incidence of recurrent conduction in 3 accessory pathways (8%). In conclusion, patients with multiple accessory pathways can be treated by radiofrequency ablation in a single session with a high success rate although slightly less than that in patients with a single accessory pathway.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ablación con radiofrecuencia en vías accesorias múltiples.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Radiofrequency ablation in multiple accessory pathways].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
