<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9132037</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Alejo Pedrero, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ambrojo, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>García de la Llana, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mota Vargas, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pazlasso, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rovira Farré, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">T-cell lymphomas in human immunodeficiency virus infections are rare, first case have being described in 1987, by Presant. Our purpose is to report the first T-cell Lymphoma case without epidermotropism in an HIV patient in Extremadura, and pioneer in Spain. Clinic extensive and histopathologic studies of cutaneous lesions were realized, including monoclonal antibodies tests. Peculiar clinical features were small bowel disease (MALT), gingiva, pericardium and skin involvement, with spontaneous resolution of skin nodules. Polychemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine and prednisone was not effective, causing serious myelotoxicity. We outline the rarity of T-cell Lymphomas, the predominance of T4 phenotype, its relation with Epstein-Barr virus, the increase in 6-interleukin production, and the prognostic value of these factors, in correlation with advanced clinical status and unfavorable outcome.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presentación de un caso de linfoma linfoblástico periférico de células T en paciente VIH.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Report of a case of T-cell peripheral lymphoblastic lymphoma in an HIV patient].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales de medicina interna (Madrid, Spain : 1984)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
