<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9273167</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vanaclocha-Vanaclocha, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Saiz-Sapena, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of our article is to underline the cutaneous lesions accompanying spinal disraphysm. We would like to stress the responsibility of physicians, particularly dermatologists, pediatricians, orthopedic surgeons, urologists, neurologists and neurosurgeons to recognize as early as possible these cutaneous stigmata. In this way patients will be studied and treated as soon as possible. No cutaneous lesion in the posterior middle line of the back or close to it should be removed until any possibly associated malformation has been thoroughly studied. Otherwise the diagnosis of a subyacent spinal disraphysm might be unduly delayed and thus allow the appearance of irreversible neurological deficits. Cutaneous lesions associated with spinal disraphysm are: areas of atrophic skin, aplasia cutis congenita, congenital skin scars, dermal pits, dermal sinuses, dyschromic lesions, hyperpigmented lesions, abnormal pilifications, vascular lesions, subcutaneous lipomas, polipoid lesions simulating tails, neurofibromas, melanocitic nevus and some lesions of tumoral origin. Of there the most common cutaneous lesion associated with spinal disraphysm is the lipoma, followed by the dermal sinuses, the anomalus pilifications and the angiomas.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Defectos del tubo neural y lesiones cutáneas.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Neural tube dysfunction and cutaneous lesions].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
