<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9312515</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-9041</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>López Luna, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>García Lara, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tena Suck, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fuentes, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fabian San Miguel, M G</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ovarian cystoadenofibroma are tumors not very frequently of superficial epithelium. It can appears at all ages. It can form fibrotic nodules of strong consistency that initially appear with the papillae and it forms nodule when the time goes by; generally, they are unilateral. We studied 10 cases of cystoadenofibromas in a period of 5 years, the patients' age was from 18 to 68 years old being more frequent in the adult age; seven cases were unilateral, three were bilateral, two of these appeared clinically as acute abdomen due to rupture of the tumor the third one was a hysterectomy is finding. In seven cases there was association with uterine leiomiomatosis mainly in older patients. Macroscopically it was seen that in younger patients these tumors were cystic with small papillae, and in older patients they formed fibrotic nodules. The immunohystochemical study with Vimentin and Desmin showed that the Desmin was focally immunopositive in form of fine fibers at the union with superficial epithelium and greatly positive fibrous portion for Vimentina.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistoadenofibroma de ovario. Experiencia de cinco años en el Hospital General "Dr. Manuel Gea González" S.S.A. Informe de 10 casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Ovarian cystadenofibroma. 5-year experience at the "Dr. Manuel Gea González" General Hospital S.S.A. Report of 10 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Ginecologia y obstetricia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
