<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9324594</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Jou, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vinuesa, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valls, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pous, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Corachán, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Biarnés, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vilana, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mejías, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Almeda, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gascón, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Swimming in rivers or lakes is a risk activity, in areas where the life cycle of schistosomiasis occurs. This report presents and analyzes the clinical presentation and epidemiological data of 80 Spanish travellers. PATIENTS AND METHODS Descriptive longitudinal and retrospective study that includes clinicoepidemiological and the laboratory data and imaging diagnosis. Patients were seen at the Section of Tropical Medicine, Hospital Clínic i Provincial, Barcelona. RESULTS Most patients acquired the infection in the Dogon country of Mall. 25% of them presented with symptoms related to the genital tract. In some groups, 45% of travellers that swam, contracted the infection. The most prevalent species diagnosed was S. haematobium and 10 travellers presented with mixed infections. CONCLUSIONS The trip to the Dogon country should be considered as "a risk activity". Travellers Advice Clinics should include the subject of swimming in infected waters in their routine counselling. Genital tract localizations were registered for three species of schistosome. The classical clinical presentation of schistosomiasis in the endemic areas differs considerably from that seen in travellers.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 May 17 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esquistosomiasis importada por viajeros españoles: estudio clínico epidemiológico de 80 casos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Schistosomiasis imported by Spanish travelers: clinico-epidemiologic study of 80 cases].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
