<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9376133</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pinilla, M T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Górriz, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trinidad, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arellano, B</dc:author>
<dc:author>González, F M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Cortijo, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Internet is considered by some as one of the most important advances of the late 20th century. The Internet is the functional linking of personal computers via telephone lines to a worldwide network of millions of other computers, which enables them to exchange information freely. Although the Internet crops up in daily conversation, many persons are not aware of its usefulness and relevance for ear, nose and throat specialists. The Internet is accessed by special software that maximizes the potential of this vast computer network. The most important tools are e-mail and the World Wide Web. These tools make it possible to consult multimedia medical publications, access Medline, and carry out information searches, etc. The Internet and its most important uses in otolaryngology are summarized and a list of useful addresses is given. Although its advantages still are not widely appreciated, widespread Internet use is imminent and we think that it is a useful technology to know and use. Moreover, access is becoming easier and cheaper.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicaciones del internet a la otorrinolaringología.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Use of the Internet in otorhinolaryngology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta otorrinolaringologica espanola</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
