<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9379728</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Urbano-Ispizua, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rozman, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Carreras, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rovira, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Viguria, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sierra, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vela, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Montserrat, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Leukemia relapse is an important cause of treatment failure after allogeneic progenitor cells transplantation. A minority of patients achieve a long-term disease free survival with a second transplant, but the majority die of toxicity or relapse. We report our experience with second allogeneic transplant for leukemia relapse. PATIENTS AND METHODS Ten patients were treated with a second transplant. Their diagnosis were chronic myelogenous leukemia (n = 5) and acute leukemia (n = 5). The interval between transplants ranged from 4 to 59 months (median 26 months). Conditioning regimens were busulfan alone (n = 1), associated to cyclophosphamide (n = 6) or to cyclophosphamide plus etoposide (n = 3). Acute graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) prophylaxis consisted of cyclosporin (CSA) (n = 4), CSA plus methotrexate (n = 4), CSA plus prednisolone (n = 1), or CSA, methotrexate plus partial T cell depletion (n = 1). RESULTS All patients engrafted after second transplant. Seven developed acute GVHD. Four out of the nine patients at risk (44%) developed chronic GVHD. Three had clinical criteria of hepatic veno-occlusive disease. Three patients died in complete remission due to treatment-related toxicity: pulmonary invasive aspergillosis during an acute GVHD, interstitial pneumonitis plus chronic GVHD, and, hepatic veno-occlusive disease, respectively. Two patients relapsed 4 and 5 months after second transplant. Five remained alive in complete remission after a median follow-up of 27 months. In all of them acute or chronic GVHD incidence and severity after second transplant was higher than after the first transplant. All surviving patients were transplanted more than 12 months after the first transplant. CONCLUSIONS A proportion of patients that relapse after an allogeneic progenitor cells transplant may benefit from second transplant; especially, young patients having a good performance status, and with a long interval between transplants.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Oct 04 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Segundo trasplante alogénico de progenitores hematopoyéticos como tratamiento de la recaída leucémica: resultados en 10 pacientes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Second allogeneic progenitor cell transplantation for leukemia relapse: results in 10 patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
