<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>938152</identifier>
<setSpec>0020-3785</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Macías, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Correa-Suárez, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Luna, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rotberg, T</dc:author>
<dc:author>Malo, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">1. A study was made of 34 cases (33%) of myocardial infarction trans and immediately postoperative which occurred in 11,210 surgical interventions with and without extracorporeal circulation. 2. This presents a statistical relation of the frequency of myocardial infarction in realtion to the heart disease acquired with or without extracorporeal circulation with the mitral, aortic, and double prosthesis of the mitral and aortic valves. A correlation was also made with the ischemic heart disease subjected to revascularization. The same analysis was carried out in the congenital heart disease with or without extracorporeal circulation. 3. In all cases the antecedents, precipitating factors, and the clinical picture were studied and in 12 cases the necropsy was analized. The principal finding was transmural myocardial infarction with electrocardiographic proof and serial enzymes. 4. The group was divided into two sub-groups; Group "A" with acute myocardial infarction transoperative, and Group "B" with acute myocardial infarction in the first eight postoperative days. The electrical and mechanical complications were analized. 5. A correlation was made of the causes of mortality related to the type of congenital or acquired heart disease with or without extracorporeal circulation. 6. The frequency of this entity was studied with the total time of aortic clamping, and the complications such as the low cardiac output syndrome, rupture of the wall, aneurysms, acute pulmonary edema, and with the disturbances of rhythm and conduction. 7. The presence of 33.3% of normal coronaries in these of necropsy was emphasized. 8. The importance of the coronary profile of this group in relation to the consequences of a stress from anesthesia, surgery, extracorporeal circulation, and aortic clamping is mentioned. 9. The diagnostic parameters such as arterial hypotension with or without the low cardiac output syndrome, enzyme levels, and the action of the potassium ion are mentioned. 10. An analysis is made of the possible etiological factors of the precipitation of the myocardial necrosis in the cases with normal coronaries and those in which there was no important obstruction of the coronary macrocirculation. 11. In the subgroup "A" it was found that the frequency of myocardial infarction was less than in the subgroup "B", but there was greater mortality in group "A". The possible causal factors are analized.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1976 Jan-Feb </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El infarto del miocardio trans y postoperatorio en la cirugía cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Trans and postoperative myocardial infarct in heart surgery].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos del Instituto de Cardiologia de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
