<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9381957</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-5062</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Otero, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Nieto, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colom, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gastó, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Benabarre, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vieta, E</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION Bipolar II disorder seems to be more than a mild form of classic manic-depressive illness. Differences with bipolar I concern genetic, biological, clinical and pharmacological aspects. Nevertheless, studies on suicidal behavior in both groups have resulted in inconsistent results PATIENTS AND METHOD Twenty-two patients fulfilling Research Diagnostic Criteria for the diagnosis of bipolar II disorder and 38 bipolar I were evaluated with the Schedule for Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia by two independent interviewers, and compared. RESULTS Bipolar II patients had significantly more previous episodes (p = 0.001), including both depressive (p = 0.003) and hypomanic switches (p = 0.006), but had been hospitalized (p = 0.001) and presented psychotic symptoms (p &lt; 0.001) less frequently. CONCLUSIONS There were no significant differences between both groups regarding suicidal behavior variables. These results suggest that bipolar II disorder is less severe than bipolar I regarding symptoms intensity, but more severe with respect to episodes frequency, and that suicide attempts rates are not useful to discriminate between both groups.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 May-Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno bipolar II: curso y conducta suicida.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Bipolar II disorder: course and suicidal behavior].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas luso-espanolas de neurologia, psiquiatria y ciencias afines</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
