<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9429627</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Biolley, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Catalán, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Wittig, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Miranda, H</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villarroel, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Full fat sweet lupin flour (Lupinus albus c.v. Multolupa) with 39.6% protein and 13.0% lipid content, and carrageenan were used to incorporate them to commercial pudding formula with the specific purpose to prepare an optimized pudding for diabetic people. Using response surface methodology, several experimental pudding trails were prepared and sensorially assessed to optimize the variables that may influence the overall sensory quality of pudding meals. Different concentrations of lupin flour and carrageenan were tested simultaneously at three levels each parameter, requiring nine combinations to be analyzed for a panel of eleven trained judges. Appearance, aroma, taste, color, texture were tested to determine total sensory quality using a composite scoring test. It was concluded that appropriate concentration of lupin flour range from 7% to 11%, and carrageenan from 0.4% to 0.5% to be added to the pudding formulation. This result was confirmed by hedonic test of acceptability.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1996 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización sensorial del budin de lupino utilizando la metodología superficie respuesta.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Sensory characterization of lupin pudding using surface response methodology].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
