<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9432220</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Castillo Otí, J M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE This study aims to discover the individual, microsocial and macrosocial factors and the milieu which lead to today's pattern of adolescent alcohol consumption. DESIGN A descriptive, crossover study without randomisation. SETTING Primary Care. School population from the Bajo-Asón Centre 1 Health Area, Cantabria. PATIENTS AND OTHER PARTICIPANTS Adolescents between 11 and 15 in school. A group of key people from the population was also included. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS The PRECEDE health education model was applied to three groups of adolescents. A discussion group with key people connected with adolescents and alcohol was formed. The main results were the wrong information recognised by those involved, the easy access of minors to alcohol, the influence of social acceptance, scant social skills and the lack of alternatives. CONCLUSIONS In view of these results it is clear that action must be taken. Therefore, a community-based prevention programme for adolescents was set up, its key points being information to parents and pupils, ways of communicating and social skills, creation of alternatives and the creation of a local committee to monitor the rules on provision of alcohol to minors.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Oct 31 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de factores de riesgo del consumo de alcohol en adolescentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of risk factors of alcohol consumption by adolescents].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
