<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9435362</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7680</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pizzimenti, M C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Belli, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Famiglietti, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Costa, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Griemberg, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marcenac, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Casco, R H</dc:author>
<dc:author>García, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vay, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cardinalli, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Syphilis and gonorrhea are two sexually transmitted diseases (STD) which still persist in spite of the existence of effective treatment. In this paper the incidence of these two diseases was evaluated between 1985-1994, a decade during which the problem of HIV infection arose. Every patient who attended the STD Program at the Hospital and was suspected of having syphilis and/or gonorrhea was clinically evaluated and was subjected to the following tests: a) search for Neisseria gonorrhoeae (Ng) and penicinilase producers (PPNG) identification, b) search for Treponema pallidum (Tp) by darkfield microscopy, c) serological studies for syphilis. From 1985 to 1991 the average of positive cases for Ng was 14.8% while from 1992 to 1994 it was 4.0% (p &lt; 0.0001) showing a dramatic decrease between 1991 and 1992. PPNG increased from 8.7% in 1985 to 44.6% in 1988 and then slowly decreased down to 26.9% in 1994. From 1985 to 1990 the average of positive darkfield examinations was 20.7% while from 1991 to 1994 it was 12.2% (p &lt; 0.0001). Between 1985 to 1988 syphilis serological studies showed 45.7% positive cases dropping to 34.3% between 1989 and 1994 (p &lt; 0.0001). HIV infection appearance had a wide repercussion throughout the world generating behavioral and sexual habit changes which have probably helped to prevent these two STD. Gonorrhea incidence was also influenced by the appearance of new effective treatments, even against PPNG, such as fluorated quinolones and third generation cephalosporines. The population studied belongs to the most crowded area in Argentina, so that these observations should not be extrapolated to the rest of the country.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El impacto del HIV sobre la incidencia de sífilis y gonorrea en un Hospital Universitario (1985-1994).</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The impact of HIV infection on the incidence of syphilis and gonorrhea at a university hospital (1985-1994)].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
