<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9471874</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rioja Sanz, L A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gonzalvo, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Blas Marín, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ibarz, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Borque Fernando, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Valdivia Navarro, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To evaluate the quality of life of our prostatectomized patients relative to the following factors: continence, mictional quality, sexual potency and psychological repercussion. MATERIAL AND METHODS The study includes a series of 204 patients undergoing radical prostatectomy between June 1986 and October 1996, where a personal questionnaire was administered to 112 of them. The questionnaire consisted of 25 questions dealing with various aspects related to their quality of life. RESULTS The overall rating on continence shows the following results: total continence 59.8%, minimal incontinence grade I 17.8%, moderate incontinence grade II 13.3% and total incontinence grade III 8%. Only 2.6% retains sexual potency after surgery. 29.3% of impotent patients consulted for their dysfunction. 91% declared to be satisfied with the results of the surgical procedure. CONCLUSIONS In our experience, continence (total + grade I incontinence) is acceptable for 77.6%, the level of mictional satisfaction being very high. There is a high index of impotence after surgery. However, most patients appear to be impervious to this fact. Overall, quality of life of our patients has not changed significantly as a result of the intervention.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida tras prostatectomía radical.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Quality of life after radical prostatectomy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
