<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9472139</identifier>
<setSpec>0325-7541</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Bello, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a study on enterovirus as causal agents of viral meningoencephalitis from 1990 to 1995 are described. From the 1458 samples of patients studied, 586 were from feces, 108 from cerebrospinal fluid and 1095 were paired sera. The samples for viral isolation were inoculated in two different cellular systems. A total of 225 samples (32.42%) were found to be positive; the highest number of isolations (n = 217) was found in feces and in diploid human lung fibroblast cells (PHuE-1). Antibody determination were carried out using neutralization by micromethod test with 10 enterovirus antigens (Echovirus 4, 6, 9, 11 and Coxsackievirus B1-6). The isolated virus was also used as antigen during epidemic periods. There were 3 epidemic outbreaks: Coxsackievirus A9 (1990-1991), Echovirus 30 (1994), and Coxsackievirus B5 (1995). Coxsackievirus A9 and Echovirus 30 have been related to viral meningoencephalitis epidemics in Cuba since 1970. In paired sera 66.84% were positive, Echovirus 6 and 11 exhibited higher positivity. When positive results by isolation and serology were considered together, more than 80% of the studied cases were associated to enterovirus infection. These results show the importance of enteroviruses as cause of viral meningoencephalitis in our country.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Oct-Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningoencefalitis virales por enterovirus en Cuba en el período 1990-1995.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Viral meningoencephalitis caused by enterovirus in Cuba from 1990-1995].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista Argentina de microbiologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
