<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9494213</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Martínez Cortés, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cantero Real, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zorrilla Torras, B</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES To describe the frequency, clinical features and therapeutic management of diagnosed diabetics not dependent on insulin, who were controlled in Primary Care in the Community of Madrid. DESIGN The study was performed through a network of sentinel doctors, which covered about 2% of Madrid's total population. The sentinel doctors had to notify on each known diabetic patient once (new cases), on their first consultation during the study period. SETTING Community of Madrid. Information on 1,449 diabetic patients not dependent on insulin and diagnosed in Primary Care was obtained. Their personal and clinical data and prior history of chronic complications were gathered. RESULTS Average number of notified diabetics was 28.4 per doctor (18.7 per 1,000 registered patients &gt; 14 years old). About 4.1 new cases (1.46 per 1,000) were diagnosed each year. CONCLUSIONS Diabetic patients not dependent on insulin represent an enormous burden on Primary Health Care in the Community of Madrid.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la diabetes mellitus no insulinodependiente en atención primaria el la Comunidad de Madrid a través de la red de médicos centinelas. Red de Médicos Centinelas de la Comunidad de Madrid.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Study of non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus in primary care in the community of Madrid using the network of sentinel physicians].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
