<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9504181</identifier>
<setSpec>0327-6309</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Yankilevich, E R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Battellino, L J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Azcurra, A I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Colantonio, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Calamari, S E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cattoni, S T</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work describes and analyzes the results of a randomized clinical trial on adolescents (age 18.2 +/- 0.6) carried out in order to evaluate the effects of a twice daily mouthrinse application containing xylitol, sorbitol, sacarine, ciclamate, aspartame, chlorhexidine, hexetidine or NaF for 14 days on amylase, peroxidase, thiocyanate, hypothiocyanite, secretory IgA and total proteins in whole saliva. No significative changes were observed in health and bucodental parameters nor in flow salivary rate, protein, secretory Ig A, or thiocyanate levels as a consequence of the mouthrinses application. On the other hand, NaF treatment (0.02%, 0.05% or 0.1%) did cause an increase in salivary peroxidase and hypothiocyanite, being the former increase higher than the second one. Peroxidase increase was proportional to the mouthrinse dose (r = 0.78; p &lt; 0.01), but not to the hypothiocyanite increase (r = 0.407; p = 0.12). Since the adolescents' health condition was the adequate, it is suggested that the peroxidase increase was due to a higher enzyme synthesis and/or secretion by the parotid and/or submaxillar glands. It is concluded that the increases in salivary peroxidase and hypothiocyanite caused by the NaF treatment favour the host, as they potentiate one of the mechanisms that modulate dental plaque composition, preventing in such a way the colonization by cariogenic pathogens.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del tratamiento local con enjuagatorios de fluoruro de sodio sobre los niveles de peroxidasa e hipotiocianito salivales en adolescentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effects of local treatment with sodium fluoride mouthrinse on peroxidase and hypothiocyanite saliva levels in adolescent]/.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Acta physiologica, pharmacologica et therapeutica latinoamericana : organo de la Asociacion Latinoamericana de Ciencias Fisiologicas y [de] la Asociacion Latinoamericana de Farmacologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
