<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9527372</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Barberis, I L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Aichino, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Godino, S D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pájaro, M C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND Pseudomonas aeruginosa with inhibitory capacity in vitro was studied on Gardnerella vaginalis strains. METHODS Antimicrobial activity was demonstrated by inhibitory halos of bacterial growth on solid media by two methods: crossed streak and agar well diffusion. The inhibitory activity of this substance produced by P. aeruginosa was characterized as bacteriocin by: activity spectrum sensitivity proteolytic enzyme, chloroform, heat, pH, ultraviolet, irradiation effect and molecular weight. RESULTS Four strains of P. aeruginosa producers of bacteriocins were chosen for this study and contacted with 40 strains of G. vaginalis. The producing strain D inhibited 70% of these G. vaginalis strains. The strains B and C inhibited 55% and 52.5%, respectively. The 3 strains presented a wide rank of action but the strain A had effect on a few strains of G. vaginalis. CONCLUSIONS This work showed the inhibitory in vitro effect of bacteriocins of P. aeruginosa on strains of G. vaginalis. The results obtained suggest the probable topic application of bacteriocins as an alternative of conventional therapeutic on this infection biological control.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inhibición in vitro del crecimiento de Gardnerella vaginalis por bacteriocinas producidas por cepas de Pseudomonas aeruginosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[In vitro inhibition of the growth of Gardnerella vaginalis by bacteriocins produced by strains of Pseudomonas aeruginosa].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Enfermedades infecciosas y microbiologia clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
