<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9609031</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Vega, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vega, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torres, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marchetti, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Kopplin, E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Delgado, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Frenz, P</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND In Chile, there are several sources of environmental lead exposure. However, the few studies about lead levels in Chilean infants, do not allow to establish the prevalence of high lead levels in this population. AIM To measure blood lead levels in nursing infants, living in rural and urban areas, from birth until two years of age. SUBJECTS AND METHODS Newborns from public maternity hospitals in Santiago and a rural area were selected for the study. An umbilical cord blood sample was obtained at birth and venous blood samples thereafter, every 6 months until the age of 24 months. Lead levels were measured by atomic absorption spectrophotometry. Atmospheric lead was measured simultaneously every week in Santiago and the rural area. RESULTS Three hundred twelve children from Santiago and 113 from the rural area completed the 24 months follow-up. The mean lead exposure for infants living in Santiago and in the rural area was 1.23 +/- 0.66 and 0.19 +/- 0.15 micrograms/m3 respectively (p &lt; 0.001). Mean blood levels were always higher in infants from Santiago, compared to those from the rural area. At 24 months, 4.5% of children from Santiago and 0.7% of children from the rural area had blood lead levels over 10 micrograms/dl. Significant risk factors for high lead levels were recent painting of the house where the infant lives, eating soil, biting banisters and familiar labor exposure to lead. CONCLUSIONS Infants living in an urban area and exposed to increased atmospheric lead levels have higher blood lead levels than infants living in a rural area.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1997 Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición crónica a plomo ambiental en lactantes chilenos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic exposure to environmental lead in Chilean infants].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
