<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9629754</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Montaño, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Flaskamp, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Prado, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Haristoy, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zemelman, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Castrillón, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sepúlveda, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cumsille, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND There is no consensus about the ideal antimicrobial agent and duration of treatment for urinary tract infection in women. AIM To assess the efficacy of a five days course of ciprofloxacin for the treatment of urinary tract infection in women. PATIENTS AND METHODS Women with urinary tract infection were treated with ciprofloxacin (Baycip, Bayer) 250 mg bid during 5 days. Patients were evaluated three to four days after treatment start, two to seven days and one month after treatment end. RESULTS Of 101 eligible women, 96 aged 18 to 65 years old, coming from three major Chilean cities, participated in the study and 80 completed the follow up period. There was a 95% clinical success, 2.5% partial improvement and 2.5% treatment failure. The causal microorganism was erradicated in 90% of cases, in 1.2% treatment failed and in 8.7% a re-infection occurred. Adverse effects attributable to the drug were observed in 12 patients (headache in 3, gastrointestinal disturbances in 8, somnolence in 1 and irritability in 1). CONCLUSIONS Ciprofloxacin is an useful antimicrobial for the treatment of lower urinary tract infection in women.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Jan </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y tolerancia de ciprofloxacina por 5 días en mujeres con infección urinaria. Estudio multicéntrico.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Efficacy and tolerance of a five day course of ciprofloxacin in the treatment of urinary tract infection in women. Multicenter study].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista medica de Chile</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
