<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9633137</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Carasusan, M G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Romea, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Torras, M G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Ferré, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guarga, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Grenzner, V</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lemonche, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Olivet, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lacasa, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vilurbina, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE Analysis of the results obtained in terms of improvement in the continuity of care, its resolutive capacity and accessibility, in the framework of the organisational change brought about by the reorganisation of specialist care (RSC) in the Ciutat Vella Health Sector. DESIGN A descriptive study of the reorganised model of specialist care introduced in 1995 and comparison between this and the previous model (1993) in terms of activity, further tests made, referral to hospital, filling in the clinical history and waiting-list. T SETTING: The experience involved 4 PCTs in the Ciutat Vella Health sector of Barcelona (covering 74,449 people). MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS The volume of visits was in general less in 1995, while other types of activity had been incorporated: minor surgery, cryotherapy, consultations and sessions. CONCLUSIONS The model of RSC satisfies the basic objectives for which it was designed. It increased the specialist's ability to resolve the case within Primary Care. It improved user accessibility to specialist care in terms of waiting time. Finally, the model favours ongoing care, thanks to a single clinical history for both levels.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Apr 15 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reordenación de la atención especializada en el Sector Sanitario Ciutat Vella: análisis de una experiencia.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Reorganising specialist care in the Ciutat Vella Health Sector: analysis of an experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Atencion primaria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
