<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9634657</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Blanco, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sánchez, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palacio, L G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Villa, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>López-Gardner</dc:author>
<dc:author>Mora, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Jiménez, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Uribe, C S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Isaza, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Zuluaga, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Arcos-Burgos, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE AND METHODS An experimental study about the predictions from the multifactorial threshold model created by Falconer is presented, assuming that this model may explain the genetic mechanisms underlying the family aggregation of idiopathic epilepsies. RESULTS We failed to confirm the following predictions from the falconer model: decreased prevalence of disease in relatives, proportional to decreased family links, and the order of birth effect. An heredity greater than 100% was calculated which is concordant with the presence of at least a locus with a major gen affect. CONCLUSION Our results reject the multifactorial threshold effect and suggest the presence of a major gen or Mendelian effect. An analysis of complex segregation is suggested for future studies.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contraste del modelo multifactorial como mecanismo hereditario de epilepsia idiopática generalizada no mioclónica y de epilepsia idiopática parcial.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Comparison of the multifactorial model as a hereditary mechanism of non-myoclonic generalized idiopathic epilepsy and partial idiopathic epilepsy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista de neurologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
