<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9644872</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Belda, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gómez, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pérez-Mateo, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Trigo, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Martínez, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Palazón, J M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Quílez, C</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic asymptomatic elevation of pancreatic enzymes is a well known entity although little has been reported. In most cases chronic asymptomatic elevation of amylase is due to a salival isoamylase increase or macroamylasemia. However, we have studied 10 cases with an increase in amylases due to pancreatic isoamylase and an increase in the remaining pancreatic enzymes which remained elevated during the follow up period ranging from 2 to 60 months. The amylase values ranged from 186 to 1,600; the lipase from 176 to 3,989, trypsin from 476 to 2,430 and pancreatic isoamylase from 122 to 1,263. In all patients CT and echography were carried out, which discarded structural damage. Nonetheless, an indirect test of pancreatic function presented unexplained pathologic values in 4 out of 10 patients. In conclusion, we suggest that chronic asymptomatic elevation of pancreatic enzymes is of unknown etiology with no associated structural pancreatic pathology demonstrable by the usual study methods.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 May </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elevación crónica de las enzimas de origen pancreático en pacientes asintomáticos.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Chronic elevation of enzymes of pancreatic origin in asymptomatic patients].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Gastroenterologia y hepatologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
