<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9646269</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sáenz, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cobo, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Leturcq, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Poza, J J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Urtasun, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gallano, P</dc:author>
<dc:author>García-Bragado, F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lasa, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López de Munain, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Linkage studies have confirmed the existence of clinical an genetic heterogeneity among the muscular dystrophies due to adhalin deficiency. We present the clinical, histological and genetic characteristics in a case of primary adhalinopathy (deficiency of the 50 kD subunit or alpha-sarcoglycan). It was a 19 years-old woman, born of non consanguineous parents, who shows a long evolution myopathy with onset before age 7, a severe evolution and becoming wheelchair bound at 10 years. She showed evident calf pseudohypertrophy and serum creatinkinase (CK) levels were elevated (40-180 times the standard level). The histological pattern showed a destructed fascicular architecture in agreement with severe muscular dystrophy, normal staining with anti-dystrophin monoclonal antibodies and abnormal staining pattern with anti-adhalin antibodies. The molecular study evidenced an homozygous point mutation (Arg--&gt;Cys) at position 77 of exon 3 of the gene coding for the 50 kD subunit of the alpha-sarcoglycan complex localised in chromosome 17. In the light of this case, we suggest a revision of the diagnostic orientation in the muscular dystrophies and we review the new taxonomy of the limb-girdle muscular dystrophies, remarking the clinical signs which could indicate a given genetic locus.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Case Reports</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Apr 25 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distrofia muscular por déficit de la subunidad alfa-sarcoglucano del complejo de proteínas relacionadas con la distrofina.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Muscular dystrophy due to a mutation in the gene of alpha-sarcoglycan subunit of dystrophin associated protein complex].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina clinica</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
