<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9658642</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Moncada Iribarren, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Rodríguez Vela, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Sáenz de Tejada y Gorman, I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Gonzalvo Ibarra, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intracavernous injection of vasodilators has been the greatest diagnostic and therapeutical breakthrough in erectile dysfunction (E.D.). After 15 years experience, these vasodilators have demonstrated efficacy rates over 85%. This suggests that most cases of E.D. are the result of and inability of the smooth muscle to relax. This paper presents an overview of the diagnostic and therapeutic use of intracavernous vasodilating drugs. It includes an extensive review of the literature and our personal series with regard to efficacy, indications, contraindications and side-effects of these compounds. Alprostadil i.c. injection (PGE1) is an effective (&gt; 70%) and safe treatment, and its use has been accompanied by an increased quality of life of patients, with very few side effects. Currently, PGE1 is a first choice drug in the treatment of impotence. When no response is seen, or pain develops after PGE1 administration, a number of vasoactive compounds associations can be used instead (phentolamine + PGE1, papaverine + phentolamine, and papaverine + phentolamine + PGE1). The phentolamine + VIP association has shown encouraging results. Prior to prescribe IC treatment with vasoactive drugs it is necessary to conduct a basic diagnostic study, and advise the patient. If treatment is finally accepted, the performance of adequate training and detailed medical follow-up is crucial.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Journal Article</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Apr </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la disfunción erectil mediante farmacoterapia intracavernosa.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Treatment of erectile dysfunction using intracavernous pharmacotherapy].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
