<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9734123</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Padilla León, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Marchal Escalona, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Caballero Alcántara, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lucas de Vega, I M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Padilla León, F</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The high prevalence of Benign Prostate Hyperplasia and the increased demand for care of this condition, should compel us to plan for shared care models in parallel to Primary Care, in the way it has happened with entities such as HBP and Diabetes. The set of measurements to be adopted when sharing services with primary care is known as "shared care". This paper presents the first national experience of "shared care" with primary care in BPH. The project has consisted in a series of steps to increase awareness, train and make available for family physicians, a clinical practice guide defining the criteria for initial evaluation, medical treatment and referral of patients to Urology surgeries, including with the referral document the appropriate diagnostic tests. A Quality Commission has been created to study the level of compliance of the documentation used for referral to the specialist and the clinical histories of patients treated in primary care. The results obtained are significant and most studies carried out fulfill the requirements in 60% cases, which has allowed to reduce overcrowding in the Urology outpatient offices (4200 surgery visits saved/year in our environment), has provided easy access of patients to adequate diagnosis and treatment, as well as significant financial savings (30 million pesetas/year). In short "shared care" is a reality in our environment that allows a more effective, fast medical assistance and improved access to specialist care by reducing the demand of specialized surgery hours.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Jun </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados compartidos en HBP. Primera experiencia nacional.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Shared care in BPH. First national experience].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas urologicas espanolas</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
