<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9734199</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Gramunt-Fombuena, N</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cejudo-Bolívar, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Peña-Casanova, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guardia-Olmos, J</dc:author>
<dc:author>Serra-Mayoral, A</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION By abstract abilities is understood the ability of comprehend relations identifying the essential components and taking out from them a common feature. Its evaluation constitutes a great challenge for neuropsychology. Several studies have showed the influence of age and formal education in the performance of tests assessing these abilities. AIM To analyse the WAIS-style abstract abilities included in the abbreviated version of the Barcelona Test determining the influence of and formal education and obtaining more normative data for a Spanish population. METHOD A sample of 264 subjects was randomly selected. The subtests of the Barcelona Test were administered in a single session to every subject. We selected the scores obtained in Arithmetic Problems (raw and timed), Similarities, Digit Symbol and Block Design (raw and timed). RESULTS The analysis of the variance showed statistically significant results of the selected items according to age and formal education. The formal education, as the lineal regression showed, resulted significant for all the items, being the Arithmetic Problems the only subtests not influenced significantly by the formal education. CONCLUSION The results obtained in this study are in general concordant to the ones of the reviewed bibliography.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Jun-Jul </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capacidades abstractas: normas ampliadas del Test Barcelona.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Abstract abilities: amplified norms for the Barcelona Test].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Neurologia (Barcelona, Spain)</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
