<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9768216</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Savón, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Roges, G</dc:author>
<dc:author>Goyenechea, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Masa, A M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bello, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During 1991, 2,400 serum samples from subjects under 15 years, and 2,400 serum samples from subjects with the same age or over 15 years were assessed against antigens of 7 respiratory viruses by the complement fixation test or by the haemagglutination inhibition technique. The results from these investigations allowed to determine the little circulation of the respiratory syncytial virus which may result in an increase of a susceptible population and the occurrence of outbreaks. The endemic state of Adenoviruses was determined and the subtype H1N1 of influenza viruses was found to have a little circulation with a raise in the population under 1 year old age during November. The subtype H3N2 of influenza A was the most important agent within the population studied, followed by Influenza B virus during September and November. All viral agents were found to have circulated in the different age groups of the population assessed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1992 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio serológico para determinar la circulación de virus respiratorios en Ciudad de La Habana.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Serologic study for determining the circulation of respiratory viruses in Havana City].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
