<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9768243</identifier>
<setSpec>0375-0760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rico Cordeiro, O</dc:author>
<dc:author>Bravo González, J R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Díaz González, M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The effectiveness or post-license efficacy of the BC antimeningococcal vaccine (VA-MENGOC-BC) was assessed 1 year after the end of the immunization campaign in children aged 0 to 5 years. Occurrence of the disease before and after intervention is described and effectiveness is estimated following the recommendations described by Orenstein et al. We used 2 case definitions to compare results in groups formed following different criteria, according to the employed diagnostic tests. Two formulas are used to assess efficacy: one, estimating the rates among vaccinated and non-vaccinated; and the other one, estimating the ratio of cases per vaccinated population. The increase of the relative annual decrease of the incidence occurring since 1985--a decrease of 10% or less--which in 1990 reached 34.6% should be stressed; the ratio of new cases prevented by the intervention was higher than 75%. Effectiveness or post-license efficacy was close to 90%, independently from the case definition variant or formula employed.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1994 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de VA-MENGOC-BC de 0 a 5 años en Cuba. Primer año de observación.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Effectiveness of VA-MENGOC-BC in children from 0 to 5 years of age in Cuba. First year of observation].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Revista cubana de medicina tropical</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
