<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9807856</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-5062</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Pérez Prieto, J F</dc:author>
<dc:author>Guillén Miralles, J L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Cuquerella Benavent, M A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Lacruz Silvestre, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Hernández Viadel, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Vila Gómez, M L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Conesa Burguet, L</dc:author>
<dc:author>Raya Chamorro, N</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION In this paper, a collective of Psychiatry Residents from Valencia surveys the degree of achievement and satisfaction with the Spanish programme. METHOD Every resident received an enquiry and a letter with instructions to fill it. Colleagues who did not answer back, were contacted and sent a new enquiry. RESULTS We received a total of 142 enquiries from 52 institutions (80% of the total). The results are distributed in supervision, theoretical training, research, rotatories, assistential pressure, staff-resident ratio, training out of the programme and satisfaction. CONCLUSIONS This work show that the programme is not being carried out properly. There are still some deficiencies in many rotatories, even though they have been improved. In spite of it, the level of satisfaction with the residence is acceptable.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Jul-Aug </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la formación de psiquiatría en España: resultados de una encuesta.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Evaluation of psychiatric training in Spain: results of a questionnaire].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Actas luso-espanolas de neurologia, psiquiatria y ciencias afines</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
