<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9842281</identifier>
<setSpec>0036-3634</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Facio-Flores, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>González-Forteza, C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Berenzon-Gorn, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Medina-Mora Icaza, M E</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tello-Granados, A M</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the prevalence of suicidal ideation and the symptomatic profile as well as to identify the sociodemographic characteristics highlighting female adolescents with the highest scores on suicidal ideation in adolescents living in Mexico City: students and suicidal patients. MATERIAL AND METHODS A cross-sectional and ex-post-facto study was carried out in order to analyze information from two samples: 1,712 junior and junior high school women students (representative student sample in Mexico City), and 30 adolescents inpatient hospitalized for her suicide attempts (clinical sample). RESULTS Prevalence of presence as well as persistence of suicidal ideation were higher in the clinical sample, nevertheless 11.8% of the school sample had everyone of the symptoms in a range of 1 to 7 days. The most persistent of the ideation symptoms was: "My family would be better if I were dead"; and in the clinical sample it was "I thought about killing myself". Finally, the sociodemographic characteristics that best matched the student girls having the highest scores in suicidal ideation were: to be on junior high school, to get low grades, to acknowledge school performance as bad and to have interrupted her studies. The characteristics that highlight the girls with a first attempt were analyzed in the clinic sample in comparison with those ones with two or more attempts. It was significant that girls in the second group were living only with one parent and they thought in the last attempt that their dead would be possible or certain. CONCLUSIONS The prevalence of suicidal ideation was important in the school sample. If it is considered that this psychological construct has a strong association with suicidal attempt, and multiple suicide conduct, then is a priority to detect adolescents in risk and to make preventive efforts, considering the sociodemographic characteristics that configurate in risk for suicidal ideation.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Sep-Oct </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ideación suicida y características asociadas en mujeres adolescentes.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Suicidal ideation and associated characteristics in adolescent women].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Salud publica de Mexico</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
