<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>988446</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Ferrando, J</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thirty six specimens of normal human skin were obtained from persons of both seces, diferent ages and localizations. Each lipid extract (Ex L) was analyzed by thin layer chromatography. After separation and development, the areas were determined by densitometry. The results are given in percentages for each development. Statistical studies were carried out for each variant (sex, age, and localization) and for each lipid fraction. According to results, the following data are of interest: 1) Underlined results on table V, are significative. 2) The variant: sex, does not change the results. 3) Squalene (Esc) is absent on plasma. 4) Cholesterol esters (EC) are age and localization dependant. 5) The total amount resulting from the addition of monoenoics (EM) and dienoics (ED) esters, is constant (approximatively the 75 % of EC). 6) EM are prevalent in skin, and the ED in plasma. 7) Phospholipids (FL) are not constant. 8) The results depend particularly on the localization of each specimen. Thin layer chromatography is a good qualitative method, but the densitometry is not an exact method, as a 5-10 % of error is usually accepted. Our results gave only an idea of the lipid components of normal human skin, but this data can be applied as a tentative pattern por subsequent studies in pathological cases.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1976 </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la composición lipídica de la piel normal</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Lipid composition of the normal skin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Medicina cutanea ibero-latino-americana</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
