<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9887565</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Romero-Tejada, J C</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Borrell, A</dc:author>
<dc:author>Fernández Arjona, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pereira Sanz, I</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE To determine the intracavernous partial oxygen pressure in different etiological groups of erectile dysfunction: psychogenic (control group), arterial and veno-occlusive and the value of intracavernous gasometry as an indicator of the degree of severity of impotence. METHODS A total of 16 patients were evaluated according to the diagnostic protocol utilized to determine the etiology of erectile dysfunction. Intracavernous blood samples were obtained during the initial phase of gasometry and PO2 was determined by standard gasometric methods. RESULTS After injection of the vasoactive drug, the mean intracavernous PO2 was 92.4 +/- 1.27 for the control group, 62.2 +/- 0.85 for the group with arterial impotence, and 76.8 +/- 1.45 for the group with venous impotence, demonstrating a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.01). CONCLUSIONS Intracavernous gasometry, in combination with other diagnostic tests, is useful for evaluating the degree of severity of erectile dysfunction. The reduction in cavernous oxygen tension, which induces cavernous tissue fibrosis, can be considered to be a common mechanism in arterial and venous impotence.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Comparative Study</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Nov </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de la tensión de oxígeno cavernosa con la disfunción eréctil de origen vascular.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The relationship of cavernous oxygen tension with erectile dysfunction of vascular origin].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos espanoles de urologia</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
