<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9951534</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0622</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Rascón Pacheco, R A</dc:author>
<dc:author>López Carrillo, L</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To assess the consumption of food prepared with corn, wheat or rice, in relation to the risk of developing gastric cancer (GC). We analyzed information about cereal consumption using data from a study of diet and GC for which 220 histologically confirmed incident GC cases and 752 population-based controls, were recruited. All subjects were interviewed using a food frequency questionnaire in which the consumption of 11 foods prepared with corn, wheat or rice, 54 additional food items and 4 alcoholic beverages was assessed. Adjusting by age, gender and total caloric intake, the results did not show an increased risk for gastric cancer incidence in regard to the consumption of foods prepared with corn (O.R. q4 vs. q1 = 0.97 C.I. 95% 0.58-1.63), wheat (O.R. q4 vs. q1 = 1.07 C.I. 95% 0.62-1.84) or rice (O.R. q4 vs. q1 = 1.36 C.I. 95% 0.96-1.90). These results remained similar after stratifying by histological type of GC (i.e. intestinal vs. diffuse). Our results do not lend support to the hypothesis that the consumption of foods prepared with corn, wheat or rice increase the risk of being diagnosed with gastric cancer.</dc:description>
<dc:type>English Abstract</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Sep </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo de alimentos preparados con maíz, trigo y arroz, y su relación con la incidencia de cáncer gástrico en México.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[Consumption of foods prepared with corn, wheat and rice and its relationship to gastric cancer incidence in Mexico].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Archivos latinoamericanos de nutricion</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
