<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<pubmed-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>9972624</identifier>
<setSpec>0302-4342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:author>Sauleda Oliveras, S</dc:author>
<dc:author>Pich Rosal, M</dc:author>
<dc:author>Tormo Carnice, R</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteban Mur, J I</dc:author>
<dc:author>Infante Pina, D</dc:author>
<dc:author>Esteban Mur, R</dc:author>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE The efficacy of recombinant alfa-2b interferon therapy in C-virus (HCV) and G-virus (HGV) in children with chronic hepatitis C was evaluated. PATIENTS AND METHODS Fifteen patients, between 6 and 16 years of age and positive for HCV of which four were also infected with HGV, were treated with interferon (3 M three times a week for 6 months). The responders were treated for 12 months. HCV RNA, antibodies to HCV, HVC viral genome (expressed as 1000 copy equivalents of HCV genome = 1 keq), HGV RNA (RT/PCR, 5'NCR-NS5), and E2-HGV antibodies were determined before treatment and at 3 and 6 months in all patients and at 12-24 months in the responders. RESULTS Four HCV patients (27%) with low viral load (mean 36 keg/ml) showed good results after interferon treatment and two of them (13%) with genotypes 1b and 3 according to Simmond's classification showed a maintained response. The four HGV children also showed the same good results and the RNA was negative without sero-conversion to anti-E2 after 12 months of interferon treatment. In the post-interferon treatment period, the HGV RNA appeared again in the serum in 3 of the 4 children. In the child with a maintained response, serum conversion to anti-E2 was not detected. CONCLUSIONS 1) The current results, with only 13% of the patients reaching a sustained response, question the systematic treatment of all children affected with hepatitis C virus. Since the cost-benefit ratio is not yielding the expected results, such therapy may be reserved for patients with genotype other than 1b and a low level of viral genome. 2) HGV is sensitive to treatment with interferon, although the infection frequently appears again once the treatment is over.</dc:description>
<dc:type>Clinical Trial</dc:type>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:date>1998 Dec </dc:date>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta del virus de la hepatitis C y del virus de la hepatitis G al tratamiento con interferon alfa-2b recombinante.</dc:title>
<dc:title xml:lang="en">[The response of the hepatitis C and hepatitis G viruses to treatment with recombinant interferon alfa-2b].</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>Anales espanoles de pediatria</dc:publisher>
</metadata>
</record>
</pubmed-document>
