<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041975</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urodynamic functional tests in diagnosis of neurogenic bladder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Urodynamic tests are a combination of functional examination techniques of the lower urinary tract whose objective is to characterize vesical-sphincter dysfunction suffered by the patient. They include uroflowmetry, cystometry, pressure and flow study, urethral pressure profile and different combined studies (cystomanometer with electromyography and videourodynamic studies). With these studies, we could characterize the alterations of the detrusor (hyperactive, hypoactive or acontractile) and the urethra (obstructive or incompetent), accurately defining what functional mechanism explains urinary incontinence or emptying dysfunction suffered by the patient. A urodynamic study should not be interpreted alone. It is very important to assess it together with the symptoms presented by the patient, his/her personal background, and the findings of the directed physical examination. This article aims to review the different urodynamic functional tests, their results and interpretation as fundamental tool to characterize vesicouretral functioning</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cerdá, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Agulló, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis Guzmán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las pruebas urodinámicas son un conjunto de técnicas de exploración funcional del tracto urinario inferior que tienen como objeto caracterizar la disfunción vesicoesfinteriana que padece el paciente. Incluyen la flujometría, cistomanometría, estudio de presión y flujo, perfil de presión uretral y los distintos estudios combinados (cistomanometría con electromiografía y estudios videourodinámicos). Con estos estudios podremos caracterizar las alteraciones del detrusor (hiperactivo, hipoactivo o acontráctil) y de la uretra (obstructiva o incompetente), definiendo con precisión qué mecanismo funcional explica la incontinencia urinaria o la disfunción de vaciado que padece el paciente. Un estudio urodinámico no debe interpretarse de forma aislada, sino que es muy importante valorarlo de forma conjunta con la clínica que presenta el paciente, sus antecedentes personales y los hallazgos de la exploración física dirigida. Este artículo pretende revisar las distintas pruebas funcionales urodinámicas, sus resultados e interpretación como herramienta fundamental para caracterizar el funcionamiento vesicouretral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(6): 343-357, nov.-dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041975</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las pruebas funcionales urodinámicas en el diagnóstico de la vejiga neurógena</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8537</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
