<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79835</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lymphomatoid granulomatosis with a neurological presentation. Case report and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lymphomatoid granulomatosis is a rare form of EBV related large B-cell lymphoma, with an angiocentric and angiodestructive growth pattern in extranodal sites. Brain involvement is relatively frequently found, but not as the initial and unique clinical manifestation. When it occurs, brain stroke is the most frequent clinical picture. Moreover, in that setting, patient can die without a definitive diagnosis, and autopsy is then required for a definitive diagnosis purpose(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torné, Ariadna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanpere, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alameda, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellosillo, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baró, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munné, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comerma, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrón, Andreina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La granulomatosis linfomatoide es un tipo poco frecuente de linfoma de célula B grande de afectación extranodal con un crecimiento angiocéntrico y angiodestructivo característico. En una cuarta parte de los casos se asocia a afectación cerebral, pudiendo dar lugar a una constelación de síntomas, si bien lo más frecuente es que se presente en forma de accidente cerebral vascular (AVC). Cuando la enfermedad se presenta únicamente con afectación cerebral y de forma catastrófica, llegar al diagnóstico de esta entidad resulta altamente complicado, siendo prácticamente imposible sin el estudio autópsico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(2): 114-119, abr.-jun.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Granulomatosis linfomatoide con presentación neurológica. A propósito de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d305^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d305^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d309^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d314^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31289^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31289^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
