<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047021</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breakthrough pain. Advances in treatment: oral transmucosal fentanyl citrate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breakthrough or incidental pain is the most widely feared symptom in cancer patients. Because there is little preventive treatment for this symptom, it is a frequent cause of visits to emergency departments. The aim of this study was to increase nurses' knowledge of this type of treatment. Learning to manage potent opioids (such as fentanyl citrate) would allow nurses to provide health education to patients and their families on specific recommendations for their use. Currently, the only drug specifically design to treat breakthrough pain is oral transmucosal fentanyl, which is easily and simply administered, with fast onset of action and a good safety profile. As an additional characteristics, satisfaction surveys have demonstrated that oral transmucosal fentanyl is preferred by patients as routine rescue therapy for pain exacerbations. Because of its simple and painless administration and rapid absorption, this drug is the most effective analgesic in controlling pain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés-Ibáñez, José Antonio de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayona-Bauset, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Honrubia-Gozálvez, Estela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio-Samper, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva-Pérez, Vicente Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor irruptivo o incidental es el síntoma más esperado y temido en pacientes con cáncer. El escaso tratamiento preventivo para el síntoma convierte las consultas a las unidades de urgencias en un hecho frecuente. El objetivo de este trabajo consiste en ampliar los conocimientos de enfermería sobre este tipo de tratamiento. Aprender a manejar opioides potentes (como el citrato de fentanilo) permite realizar una adecuada educación sanitaria sobre recomendaciones concretas para su uso. Actualmente el único fármaco diseñado específicamente para tratar el dolor irruptivo es el fentanilo oral transmucosa, de fácil y sencilla administración, importante rapidez de acción y con un buen perfil de seguridad. Como característica adicional, en las encuestas de satisfacción realizadas es el preferido por los pacientes como rescate habitual para las crisis álgidas. Su forma de administración sencilla e indolora, sumada a la rápida absorción, lo convierte en la analgesia con mayor efectividad en el control del dolor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(3): 155-159, mayo 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor irruptivo. Avances en su tratamiento: citrato de fentanilo oral transmucosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27231</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
