<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88892</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of noise exposure in working places on quality of life and performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: Occupational noise exposure could produce extra-auditory effects. The purpose of this study was to investigate whether occupational noise exposure can influence human behaviour, performance and development of psychosomatic symptoms. Methodology: Cross-sectional study, from the Data-base of Spanish VI National Survey on Working Conditions, "noise exposure" has been analyzed as independent variable and: "symptoms self-reportered by workers" as effect variable, considering them independently or grouped variables in behavioural, psychosomatic and performance symptoms. The relationship between exposure and effect was analyzed by X2 test. Prevalence adjusted Odds Ratio by work rhythm (95% CI), were estimated to measure the association between perceived noise annoyance and grouped symptoms in the population and in the different branches of activity. Results: 36.5% of the working population is exposed to noise in their workplace. There is a higher prevalence of behavioural symptoms group, psychosomatic and performance (p &lt;0.001) among workers exposed to noise compared to unexposed. Health Care Sector reported the highest risk for behavioural (OR=2,53 [1,71-3,75]) and performance symptoms(OR=2,26, [1,43-3,56]) . Chemical Industry had a prevalence ratio between noise and psychosomatic symptoms of (OR=5,37 [1,13-25,55]). Conclusions: Our results found and statistic significant association between noise annoyance exposure and behavioural, performance and development of psychosomatic symptoms in the Spanish working population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Mato, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordaz Castillo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo García, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamo González, María Fe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Barragán, Rosa Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Blasco, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asúnsolo Del Barco, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La exposición laboral a ruido origina efectos sobre la salud de carácter no auditivo. El objetivo de este estudio es estimar la asociación entre exposición a ruido en entornos laborales y la aparición de alteraciones en la conducta, rendimiento y síntomas psicosomáticos. Metodología: Estudio de prevalencia a partir de datos de la VI Encuesta Nacional de Condiciones de Trabajo analizando como variable independiente la exposición a ruido y como variables dependientes los "síntomas que manifiesta el trabajador" tratados de forma individual o por grupo de síntomas según su naturaleza: conductual, psicosomáticos y rendimiento. La asociación entre exposición y efecto se analizó mediante la prueba de X2 y se calculó el OR de prevalencias ajustado por ritmo de trabajo (IC95%) para medir la asociación entre "exposición a ruido" y grupos de síntomas de forma cruda en el conjunto de la población y de forma estratificada por ramas de actividad. Resultados: El 36,5% de la población trabajadora está expuesta a ruido en su puesto de trabajo. Se observa una mayor prevalencia de los grupos de síntomas conductuales, psicosomáticos y de rendimiento (p&lt;0,001) entre los trabajadores expuestos a ruido frente a no expuestos. La rama de Actividades Sanitarias presenta los mayores valores de OR para el grupo de síntomas conductuales (OR=2,53 [1,71-3,75]) y de rendimiento (OR=2,26, [1,43-3,56]) y la Industria Química presenta el mayor grado de asociación entre exposición a ruido y síntomas psicosomáticos (OR=5,37, [1,13-25,55]). Conclusiones: Se observa una asociación estadísticamente significativa entre exposición a ruido y alteraciones de conducta, rendimiento y síntomas psicosomáticos en la población trabajadora española (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;55(216): 35-45, jul.-sept. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la exposición a ruido en entornos laboralessobre la calidad de vida y rendimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9809^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9809^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
