<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139094</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Couple relationships and social skills: the interpersonal respect</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Couple relationships and social skills are closely related. Love components (intimacy, desire and commitment) have nuclear issues in the area of interpersonal relationships. A key aspect in relationships and in the social skills area is Interpersonal Respect, the ability to harmonize personal rights with the other&#146;s rights. Respect is related with submissive, dominant, passive-aggressive and fair response styles. This study compared three groups of people (one with a tendency to submission, a second with a tendency to dominance, and a third of balanced people) to check perceptions of couple relationship. The results indicate that submissive and dominant people attach a more negative value to their relationship (and their partners) than balanced people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dolores Sosa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capafóns, Juan I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las relaciones de pareja y las habilidades sociales están estrechamente relacionadas. Los componentes del amor (intimidad, deseo y compromiso) presentan aspectos nucleares en el ámbito de las relaciones interpersonales. Y un aspecto clave en las relaciones de pareja y en el ámbito de las habilidades sociales es el respeto interpersonal, la capacidad de armonizar los derechos propios con los de la otra persona. El respeto está relacionado con los estilos de respuesta sumiso, dominante, pasivo-agresivo y equilibrado. En este estudio se han comparado tres grupos de personas (con tendencia a la sumisión, a la dominancia y personas equilibradas) para comprobar la percepción que tienen de su relación de pareja. Los resultados indican que las personas sumisas y dominantes valoran de forma más negativa su relación (y a su pareja) que las personas equilibradas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(1): 25-34, ene.-abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones de pareja y habilidades sociales: el respeto interpersonal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1250</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
