<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10913</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementation of specialized pharmaceutical care hospital outpatient clinics in a hospital pharmacy department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the organization of patient care into Specialized Pharmaceutical Care Hospital Outpatient Clinics in a Hospital Pharmacy Department, to evaluate their healthcare quality, and the quality perceived by outpatients. Method: A retrospective observational study in a High-Level Hospital Pharmacy Department during three periods (years 2010, 2013 and 2016); description of the organization at the levels of structure, human resources, material resources and working procedures; evaluation of healthcare quality through the analysis of three variables in terms of procedure: prior appointment compliance, waiting time and documentation of pharmaceutical care; evaluation of quality perceived by outpatients through a satisfaction survey; comparative statistical analysis of means (Student's t) and proportions (Pearson's chi square). Results: Fifteen (15) specialized outpatient clinics were opened and managed by 18 pharmacists; between the initial and final periods of the study (2010 vs. 2016), the compliance with previous appointments was of 61.3% vs. 88.8% (p &lt; 0001), waiting time was 27.6±12.1 vs. 12.1±5.4 minutes (p &lt; 0.0001), documentation of pharmaceutical care in the clinical record was of 2.3% vs. 9.81% (p &lt; 0.0001), and the overall satisfaction perceived by the patients was 6.63±2.36 vs. 9.16±1.27 (p&lt; 0.01). Conclusions: The model of Specialized Pharmaceutical Care Hospital Outpatient Clinics exposed, focused on the patient and with continuity of care, has improved the quality of care and the quality perceived by the patients and it´s in optimal conditions to investigate its contribution on health outcomes and on the health system through a better quality, safety and efficiency of pharmacotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedreira-Vázquez, María Isaura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Herranz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Margusino-Framiñán, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabuñal-Álvarez, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Queiruga, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gabriel, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid-Silva, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Salvador, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Roca, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la organización asistencial de Consultas Externas Monográficas de Atención Farmacéutica de un Servicio de Farmacia Hospitalaria, evaluar su calidad asistencial y la calidad percibida por los pacientes externos. Método: Estudio observacional retrospectivo en un servicio de farmacia de un hospital de nivel terciario durante tres períodos (años 2010, 2013 y 2016); descripción de la organización asistencial a nivel de estructura, recursos humanos, recursos materiales y procedimientos de trabajo; evaluación de la calidad asistencial mediante el análisis de tres variables de procedimiento: cumplimiento cita previa, tiempo de espera y documentación de la atención farmacéutica; evaluación de la calidad percibida por los pacientes externos mediante encuestas de satisfacción; análisis estadístico comparativo de medias (t Student) y proporciones (chi cuadrado Pearson). Resultados: 15 consultas monográficas abiertas atendidas por 18 farmacéuticos; entre el período inicial y el período final del estudio (2010 vs. 2016) el cumplimiento de cita previa fue del 61,3% vs. 88,8% (p&lt; 0001), el tiempo de espera fue 27,6±12,1 vs. 12,1±5,4 minutos (p&lt; 0,0001), la documentación de la atención farmacéutica en la historia clínica del 2,3%  vs. 9,81% (p&lt; 0,0001) y la satisfacción global percibida por los pacientes del 6,63±2,36 vs. 9,16±1,27 (p&lt; 0,01). Conclusiones: El modelo de Consulta Externa Monográfica de Atención Farmacéutica expuesto, centrado en el paciente y con continuidad asistencial, ha mejorado la calidad asistencial y la calidad percibida por los pacientes y se encuentra en condiciones óptimas para investigar su aportación a los resultados en salud del paciente y al sistema sanitario a través de una mejor calidad, seguridad y eficiencia de la farmacoterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;41(6): 660-666, nov.-dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de consultas externas monográficas de atención farmacéutica en un servicio de farmacia hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
