<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151367</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationships between emotional intelligence and sales performance in Kuwait</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study investigates the relationship between emotional intelligence (EI) and Total Sales Performance (TSP), and whether EI contributes to predicting the performance of sales professionals in Kuwait. The sample was 218 sales professionals working for 24 different car dealerships. An ability model of EI was measured using the Assessing Emotions Scale (AES) developed by Schutte et al. (1998) and its Arabic version. The trait model of EI was assessed using the Effective Intelligence Scale (EIS). The findings showed a negative but weak correlation between TSP and the AES and all its subscales. No correlation was found between TSP and the EIS. A weak positive correlation existed between Objective Sales Performance and each of total EIS, Accuracy, and Patience subscales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anderson, Neil</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>AlDosiry, Kholoud S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alkhadher, Othman H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>AlAqraa&#146;, Elsayed M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio indaga en la relación entre inteligencia emocional (IE) y productividad en el total de ventas (PTV) y si la primera contribuye a predecir la actuación de los comerciales profesionales en Kuwait. La muestra estaba compuesta por 218 comerciales profesionales que trabajaban en 24 concesionarios diferentes de automóviles. Se siguió el modelo de habilidades de inteligencia emocional, utilizándose la versión árabe de la Escala de Evaluación de Emociones (EEE) de Schutte et al. (1998). La IE de rasgo se evaluó mediante la Escala de Inteligencia Eficaz (EIE). Los resultados indican una correlación negativa débil entre PTV y la EEE y todas sus subescalas. No se obtuvo correlación entre PTV y EIE. Se dio una correlación positiva débil entre ventas objetivas y cada una de las subescalas del EIE, precisión y paciencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);32(1): 39-45, ene.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre inteligencia emocional y productividad en ventas en Kuwait</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7906^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
