<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129821</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis in children and adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Low back pain is a common cause of lost playing time in young athletes, and spondylolysis is its most common identifiable cause. Despite technological advances in radiology, which can lead to an early diagnosis with better prognosis, progression to spondylolisthesis is sometimes asymptomatic and may not be detected until late stages. There are wide variations, suggesting lack of consensus as regards the objective of treatment, which consists of clinical, radiological, biomechanical or functional improvement. There is also a lack of agreement regarding the ideal conservative treatment, surgical indications and need of slip reduction, and most of the established recommendations are not evidence based. We present a review of literature, which summarizes the current knowledge of spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis in children and adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora-de Sambricio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Stratenwerth, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor lumbar es causa frecuente de cese de actividades deportivas en atletas jóvenes, y la espondilolisis es su causa identificable más común. Aunque los avances en las técnicas radiológicas permiten su diagnóstico en fases precoces, en algunos casos la progresión a espondilolistesis es asintomática y no se detecta hasta fases avanzadas. No hay consenso en el objetivo del tratamiento, que consiste en la resolución clínica, radiológica, biomecánica o funcional, según autores. También hay falta de acuerdo en el tratamiento conservador ideal, en las indicaciones quirúrgicas y en la necesidad de reducción de la espondilolistesis, y muchas recomendaciones establecidas no están avaladas por la evidencia. Presentamos una revisión de la bibliografía que resume el conocimiento actual de la espondilolisis y espondilolistesis en niños y adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(6): 395-406, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espondilolisis y espondilolistesis en niños y adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7915^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8317^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22680^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7915^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22680^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7915^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
