<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66419</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Frey&#146;s syndrome may occur as a complication following parotid gland surgery. The aim of this article is to analyze the prevention of this syndrome after parotid surgery during which a superficial musculoaponeurotic system (SMAS) flap is elevated.Material and Methods. A retrospective study is presented of 81 patients who underwent parotid gland surgery in the department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery of the Hospital Infanta Cristina, Badajoz, from October 1997 to February 2005.Results. The most common technique used in our department was the superficial conservative parotidectomy (68%). The most numerous group was made up of patients with SMAS flaps who did not go on to develop Frey&#146;s syndrome, with a total of 56 cases (69%).Conclusion. We consider carrying out a SMAS flap in parotid surgery appropriate for reducing the frequency with which Frey&#146;s syndrome appears (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Laza, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo Sánchez, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo Arias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Herrero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Vázquez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monje Gil, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Gil, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El síndrome de Frey puede surgir como complicación tras cirugía de la glándula parótida. Este artículo pretende analizar la prevención de dicho síndrome tras cirugía parotídea cuando se realiza laelevación de un colgajo de sistema músculo aponeurótico superficial (SMAS).Material y Método. Presentamos un estudio retrospectivo con 81 pacientes a los que se realizó cirugía sobre la glándula parótida, en el Servicio de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial del Hospital Infanta Cristina de Badajoz desde Octubre de 1997 hasta Febrero de 2005.Resultados. La técnica más comúnmente realizada en nuestro Servicio fue la parotidectomía superficial conservadora (68%). El grupo más numerosolo formaron aquellos pacientes en los que se realizó colgajo de SMAS y no desarrollaron posteriormente síndrome de Frey con un total de 56 casos (69%).Conclusión. Consideramos adecuada la realización de colgajo de SMAS en cirugía parotídea, para disminuir la frecuencia de aparición del síndrome de Frey (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;28(3): 182-187, mayo-jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66419</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13928^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10495^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
