<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057740</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflections in regard to health care management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The evolution of management models in the health care centers has often been motivated by an initial change in the head manager of the site and parallelly to an increase in their area of business interest. This way of promoting change is subjected to the risk of detaining and discouraging the human team responsible for attaining good results in the final product of the health care sector. There are signs and symptoms in the organization that make it possible to detect the separation of interests between directors and non-directors in order to avoid an evolution to a non-efficient organization</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grau Amorós, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evolución de los modelos de gestión de los centros sanitarios ha sido impulsada en muchas ocasiones por un cambio inicial en su dirección y paralelamente a un aumento en su área de competencia empresarial. Este sistema de promover el cambio está sujeto al riesgo de frenar y desmotivar al equipo humano responsable de la consecución de unos buenos resultados en el producto final del sector sanitario. Existen signos y síntomas en las organizaciones que permiten detectar la separación de intereses entre directivos y no directivos para evitar la evolución a una organización no eficiente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(8): 416-417, sept. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057740</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones en torno a la gestión sanitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32497</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
