<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049481</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Possum scoring system: an instrument for measuring quality in surgical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The POSSUM scale (Physiological and Operative Severity Score for the enUmeration of Mortality and Morbidity) is a scoring system that is used to predict risk-adjusted mortality and morbidity rates in a wide variety of surgical procedures. In this prospective study, the validity of the POSSUM scale was evaluated in patients undergoing laparotomy in a general surgery department. Patients and methods. The POSSUM scale was prospectively applied in all patients undergoing elective and emergency laparotomy in the general surgery department of a level II hospital over 8 months. A total of 105 patients were included, of which 24 underwent emergency laparotomy and 81 underwent elective surgery. Predicted mortality and morbidity rates were calculated by using the POSSUM scale. These results were compared with actual outcomes by using Fisher's test. Results. The mean physiological score was 23.4 points (range: 12-40 points), while the mean surgical score was 11.3 points (range: 6-24 points). Three patients died during the postoperative period and 47 had morbidity. When the observed results for mortality were compared with those predicted by the POSSUM scoring system, no significant differences were observed in the analysis by risk groups, except in the risk group &lt; 20 %, in which the POSSUM scale overestimated mortality. The risk of morbidity was underestimated by the POSSUM scale in the risk group &lt; 20 %.                 Conclusion. The POSSUM scoring system is a useful predictor of morbidity and mortality in patients undergoing emergency and elective laparotomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candel-Arenas, Marife</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillo-Soto, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Pastor, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo-Albasini, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés-García, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gervasio Martín-Lorenzo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria-Aledo, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La escala POSSUM (Physiological and Operative Severity Score for the enumeration of Mortality and Morbidity) es un sistema de clasificación de pacientes que se utiliza para predecir la mortalidad y la morbilidad ajustada a riesgo en gran variedad de procesos quirúrgicos. El objetivo de este trabajo es valorar su utilidad en los pacientes quirúrgicos de un servicio de cirugía general. Pacientes y métodos. La escala se ha aplicado, de forma prospectiva, a los pacientes intervenidos por laparotomía programada y urgente en nuestro departamento de cirugía general (hospital nivel II) durante un período de 8 meses. Se han incluido 105 casos de los que 81 fueron operados de forma programada y los 24 restantes, de forma urgente. Posteriormente, se han comparado, utilizando el test exacto de Fisher, los resultados predichos por la escala con los observados en la realidad. Resultados. La puntuación fisiológica media fue de 23,4 puntos (rango: 12-40 puntos), y la quirúrgica de 11,3 puntos (rango: 6-24 puntos). Fallecieron 3 pacientes y 47 presentaron morbilidad. Al comparar los resultados observados con los predichos por el sistema POSSUM, en cuanto a mortalidad, no se hallaron diferencias significativas en el análisis por grupos de riesgo, excepto en el grupo de riesgo &lt; 20%, en el que el POSSUM sobreestimó la mortalidad. En cuanto a la morbilidad, el POSSUM la infravaloró para el grupo de riesgo &lt; 20%.   Conclusión. El sistema POSSUM es una herramienta útil para los análisis de morbimortalidad en nuestros pacientes quirúrgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);80(6): 395-399, dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049481</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistema POSSUM. Un instrumento de medida de la calidad en el paciente quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
