<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148344</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Our vital profession</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Occasionally it is useful to remind ourselves of the vital role psychoanalysis plays in helping our patients regain what is basic to their humanity. At the same time the vitality of our methods can be seen in important paradigm changes in the psychoanalytic method in the last forty years. In our continual search to help patients find, or re-find the core of what it means to be human, this paper explores multiple paradigm changes in the psychoanalytic method that form a new common ground amongst seemingly diverse perspectives. This leads to fresh views of: how we listen and interpret; the goals of treatment; and how change takes place. This is not to underestimate that significant differences exist amongst schools of thought. A key challenge to our individual and collective growth is the difficulty in engaging with the ever-expanding knowledge posed by different perspectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Busch, Fred</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De vez en cuando es útil que recordemos el papel vital que juega el psicoanálisis en ayudar a nuestros pacientes a volver a obtener lo que es básico para su humanidad. Al mismo tiempo, la vitalidad de nuestros métodos puede verse en los importantes cambios de paradigma en el método psicoanalítico que se dieron en los últimos cuarenta años. En nuestra continua búsqueda de ayudar a los pacientes a encontrar o reencontrar el núcleo de lo que significa ser humano, este trabajo explora los múltiples cambios de paradigma en el método psicoanalítico que forman un nuevo terreno común entre perspectivas notablemente diversas. Esto lleva a visiones nuevas sobre: cómo escuchamos e interpretamos, los objetivos del tratamiento y cómo se produce el cambio. Esto no es para subestimar las diferencias significativas que existen entre diferentes escuelas de pensamiento. Un desafío clave para nuestro crecimiento individual, colectivo es la dificultad en comprometemos con el conocimiento en permanente expansión planteado por diferentes perspectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(75): 131-153, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuestra profesión vital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12465</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
