<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131293</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resilience in sport: Theoretical foundations, instruments and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The construct of resilience, defined as the capacity to cope and adapt, in a positive way, to highly stressful situations has been studied for more than 60 years ago. However, it seems that only in the last two decades Psychology of Sport and Exercise has led a justified and special interest on it. That is why the demand for these researches that are able to compile all this new information are growing. Therefore, our paper pursues the general aim of reviewing advances in sport context resilience, trying to offer an integrated, current and synthetic vision of conceptualization and results of researches developed. More specifically, the most referenced assessment instruments and future investigations are also shown. In conclusion, this review highlights the most interesting findings on resilience and its relationship with other psychological and/or performance factors, in order to facilitate the development of intervention strategies to optimize sport performance and provides a holistic view of the construct and its future research outlooks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Secades, Xabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinero, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Barquín, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veja, Ricardo de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El constructo de resiliencia, definido como la capacidad de hacer frente y adaptarse, de manera positiva, a las situaciones altamente estresantes, ha sido estudiado desde hace más de 60 años, sin embargo, parece que solo en estas últimas dos décadas ha suscitado un justificado y especial interés por parte de la Psicología del Deporte y del Ejercicio. Es por esto que, cada vez más, crece la demanda por artículos que sean capaces de compilar toda esta novedosa información. Nuestra investigación, por tanto, persigue el objetivo general de revisar los avances entorno a la resiliencia en el contexto deportivo, tratando de ofrecer una visión integradora, actualizada y sintética de la conceptualización del término y de los resultados delas investigaciones realizadas hasta el momento. De manera más específica, también se muestran los instrumentos de evaluación más referenciados y las posibles líneas de investigación a seguir entorno al constructo. Como conclusión, esta revisión subraya los descubrimientos más interesantes sobre la resiliencia y otros factores psicológicos y/o de rendimiento, facilitando la elaboración de estrategias de intervención para la optimización del resultado deportivo y aporta una visión holística del constructo y de sus perspectivas de investigación futuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(3): 83-98, sept.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131293</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La resiliencia en el deporte: fundamentos teóricos, instrumentos de evaluación y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
