<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78819</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Keloid Scarring: New Treatments Ahead</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Keloid disease presents a healthcare challenge: patients suffer from pruritus, pain, inflammation, and cosmetic disfigurement. There is no single effective therapeutic regimen for keloids. Numerous treatment options have been described including occlusive dressings, compression therapy, intralesional steroid injections, laser and radiation therapy, cryosurgery, 5-fluorouracil, interferon, and imiquimod cream, but managing keloid disease still is a considerable problem for clinicians. Better understanding of the molecular mechanisms behind keloid disease led to the development of new promising therapies like the application of recombinant TGF-b3, interleukin 10, and imatinib mesylate. This review provides an overview of the existing therapeutic options for keloid disease and summarizes upcoming future therapies with a special focus on blocking the transforming growth factor-beta pathway (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mrowietz, Ulrich</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seifert, Oliver</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los queloides representan un reto de atención sanitaria: los pacientes padecen prurito, dolor, inflamación y desfiguración cosmética. No existe ningún tratamiento efectivo para los queloides. Se han descrito numerosas opciones terapéuticas que incluyen vendajes oclusivos, terapia de compresión, corticoides intralesionales, láser, radioterapia, criocirugía, 5-fluorouracilo, interferón e imiquimod, pero el tratamiento continúa siendo un problema considerable para los clínicos. Se han desarrollado nuevas y prometedoras terapias, como la aplicación de TGF-b3 recombinante, interleuquina 10 y mesilato de imatinib gracias a un mayor conocimiento de los mecanismos moleculares responsables de los queloides. Esta revisión ofrece una visión de conjunto de las opciones terapéuticas disponibles para los queloides y resume las futuras terapias, haciendo especial énfasis en los bloqueadores de la vía del factor de crecimiento transformador beta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(supl.2): 75-83, dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queloides: Nuevos tratamientos en el Futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7796^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7796^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30030^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
