<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111102</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on heart failure, heart transplant, congenital heart disease, and clinical cardiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the year 2012, 3 scientific sections&#151;heart failure and transplant, congenital heart disease, and clinical cardiology&#151;are presented together in the same article. The most relevant development in the area of heart failure and transplantation is the 2012 publication of the European guidelines for heart failure. These describe new possibilities for some drugs (eplerenone and ivabradine); expand the criteria for resynchronization, ventricular assist, and peritoneal dialysis; and cover possibilities of percutaneous repair of the mitral valve (MitraClip®). The survival of children with hypoplastic left heart syndrome in congenital heart diseases has improved significantly. Instructions for percutaneous techniques and devices have been revised and modified for the treatment of atrial septal defects, ostium secundum, and ventricular septal defects. Hybrid procedures for addressing structural congenital heart defects have become more widespread. In the area of clinical cardiology studies have demonstrated that percutaneous prosthesis implantation has lower mortality than surgical implantation. Use of the CHA2DS2-VASc criteria and of new anticoagulants (dabigatran, rivaroxaban and apixaban) is also recommended. In addition, the development of new sequencing techniques has enabled the analysis of multiple genes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Subirana, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Molina, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, Vivencio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zunzunegui, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Doblas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barón, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comín, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el año 2012 se presentan, por primera vez de forma conjunta y agrupadas en la misma área de conocimiento, las novedades de tres secciones científicas: insuficiencia cardiaca y trasplante, cardiopatías congénitas y cardiología clínica. Las novedades más relevantes en el área de insuficiencia cardiaca y trasplante están en la publicación de las guías europeas de insuficiencia cardiaca de 2012. En ellas, se considera las nuevas posibilidades de algunos fármacos (eplerenona e ivabradina), la ampliación de los criterios de resincronización y de utilización de la asistencia ventricular, la diálisis peritoneal y las nuevas posibilidades de reparación percutánea de la válvula mitral (MitraClip®). En las cardiopatías congénitas se ha mejorado de manera significativa la supervivencia de los niños con síndrome del corazón izquierdo hipoplásico. Se han revisado indicaciones y se han modificado las técnicas percutáneas y los dispositivos para el tratamiento de la comunicación interauricular ostium secundum y los defectos septales ventriculares. Cada vez son más frecuentes los procedimientos híbridos en el abordaje de defectos cardiacos estructurales congénitos. En el área de cardiología clínica, hay estudios en que la implantación percutánea de prótesis obtendría menor mortalidad que la implantación quirúrgica. También se recomiendan los criterios CHA2DS2-VASc y utilizar los nuevos anticoagulantes orales. Por otro lado, se están desarrollando nuevas técnicas de secuenciación que permiten el análisis de multitud de genes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(4): 290-297, abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en insuficiencia cardiaca, trasplante cardiaco, cardiopatías congénitas y cardiología clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
