<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114131</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care levels and minimum recommendations for neonatal care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A policy statement on the levels of care and minimum recommendations for neonatal healthcare was first proposed by the Standards Committee and the Board of the Spanish Society of Neonatology in 2004. This allowed us to define the level of care of each center in our country, as well as the health and technical requirements by levels of care to be defined. This review takes into account changes in neonatal care in the last few years and to optimize the location of resources. Facilities that provide care for newborn infants should be organized within a regionalized system of perinatal care. The functional capabilities of each level of care should be defined clearly and uniformly, including requirements for equipment, facilities, personnel, ancillary services, training, and the organization of services (including transport) needed to cover each level of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Hernando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botet Mussons, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rite Gracia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lorenzo, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Carrillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echániz Urcelay, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el año 2004 fue elaborado por el Comité de Estándares y la Junta Directiva de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología (SEN) un primer documento sobre niveles asistenciales y recomendaciones de mínimos para la atención neonatal, a partir del cual se pudo definir el nivel asistencial de cada centro en nuestro país, así como los requerimientos técnico-sanitarios según niveles. La presente revisión pretende tener en cuenta los cambios experimentados en la asistencia neonatal en los últimos años y optimizar la localización de recursos. Las unidades que proporcionan asistencia a los recién nacidos deben estar organizadas dentro de un sistema de regionalización de los cuidados perinatales. Las características funcionales de cada nivel asistencial deben ser definidas de forma uniforme y clara, y esto incluye requerimientos de equipamiento, instalaciones, personal, servicios de apoyo, formación y organización de servicios (incluyendo el transporte) necesarios para cubrir las prestaciones de cada nivel de cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(1): 51-51[e1-e11], jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles asistenciales y recomendaciones de mínimos para la atención neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12462^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12462^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12462^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12462^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12462^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
