<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143111</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health education strategies for older people: experiences and challenges</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This is an integrative review which aims to assess the scientific literature related to health education for elderly in Brazil, between 2007 to 2013. How to search databases used the Virtual Health Library - VHL, Scielo, Redalyc and from the intersection of descriptors: aged and health education. Rose 14 articles that responded to the goals and, that after reading it he elucidated three categories, namely: Experiences in health education with elderly people, Experiences of training and capacity-building Needs related to health education and physical activity as a tool for health education for the elderly. It turns out that one of the main gaps are the extension of studies and experiences with didactic approaches further, the appreciation of aspects beyond diseases, as well as the importance of physical activity, but also issues such as leisure, income generation, family relationships, in addition to better training of health professionals to deal with health education activities for the elderly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Filipe, Elvira Maria Ventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silveira, Rodrigo Euripedes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Álvaro da Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendonça, Francielle Toniolo Nicodemos Furtado de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta es una revisión integrativa que pretende evaluar las publicaciones científicas relacionadas con la educación de salud para ancianos en Brasil entre 2007-2013. Cómo bases de búsqueda de datos se utilizó la Biblioteca Virtual en Salud - BVS, Scielo, Redalyc y con los descriptores: educación en salud y anciano. Se evidenciaron 14 artículos que respondieron a los objetivos y, que después de leerlos se ha dilucidado tres categorías, a saber: experiencias en educación para la salud con personas mayores, experiencias de formación y necesidades de capacitación relativas con educación para la salud y la actividad física como una herramienta para la educación de salud para los ancianos. Las principales necesidades de investigación y experiencias son la ampliación de estudios y experiencias con enfoques didácticos más lejos, la apreciación de los aspectos más allá de enfermedades, así como la importancia de la actividad física, pero también temas como la generación de ingresos, el ocio, las relaciones familiares, además de mejor formación de los profesionales de salud para hacer frente a las acciones de educación en salud para ancianos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;19(42): 154-163, mayo-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de educación en salud para ancianos: experiencias y desafíos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
