<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132094</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of anxiety and depression in COPD patients, diagnosed with psychiatric confirmation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the association between COPD and anxiety or depression is an important dimension of the disease but frequently those comorbidities are undiagnosed. The available studies about anxiety and depression prevalence usually achieve small numbers of patients y lack of a certain diagnosis based on a structured psychiatric schedule. Objective: the primary objective of the study is to estimate the frequency of the association between anxiety or depression and COPD and to determinate the underdiagnosis level in our sample. The clinical, functional and social and demographics factors that characterize the COPD patients with anxiety or depression to identify possible risk factors for these comorbidities that should be considered both in clinical practice and future studies. Patients and method: 204 out-patients with stable COPD were screened for anxiety and depression with the self-administered «Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale» (HADS) and if positive, a psychiatric interview was made to confirm the diagnosis. The anxiety or depression final diagnosis was made according the ICD 10 criteria. Results: the presence of psychiatric comorbidity (anxiety or depression) was confirmed in a 36% of the patients. At de beginning of the study only an 8% of the patients included were already diagnosed with anxiety or depression. The prevalence of anxiety or depression associated with COPD lies between 32-45% with a 95% confidence. Conclusions: using the self-administered HADS in the clinical practice may correct the high underdiagnosis of anxiety and depression in COPD patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Gutiérrez , MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Vargas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Maldonado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Velázquez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Martínez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la asociación de la EPOC a ansiedad o a depresión constituye una dimensión importante de la enfermedad, pero sin embargo, a menudo, estas comorbilidades no son diagnosticadas. Los estudios disponibles sobre prevalencia de ansiedad y depresión, con frecuencia, disponen de tamaños de muestra pequeños y carecen de un diagnóstico de certeza mediante entrevista psiquiátrica estructurada. Objetivo: el objetivo principal del estudio es calcular la frecuencia de asociación entre ansiedad o depresión y EPOC y determinar el grado de infradiagnóstico en nuestra muestra. Del mismo modo, se analizarán qué factores clínicos, funcionales y sociodemográficos distinguen a los pacientes EPOC con ansiedad o depresión del resto de la muestra, para identificar posibles factores de riesgo para estas comorbilidades, a tener en cuenta tanto en la práctica clínica como en sucesivos estudios. Pacientes y método: se han estudiado 204 pacientes ambulatorios con EPOC estable, a los que se realizó un cribado de síntomas de ansiedad o depresión, mediante el cuestionario autoadministrable «Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale» (HADS) y una confirmación posterior, mediante diagnóstico psiquiátrico. El diagnóstico final de ansiedad o depresión se ajustó a los criterios de la clasificación ICD 10. Resultados: se confirmó la presencia de comorbilidad psiquiátrica (ansiedad o depresión) en un 36% de los pacientes. Al inicio del estudio, sólo un 8% de los incluidos había sido diagnosticado de ansiedad o depresión. Se constató un alto grado de acuerdo entre el HADS positivo y el diagnóstico psiquiátrico. La prevalencia de ansiedad o depresión asociadas a la EPOC se sitúa entre el 32-45%, con una confianza del 95%. Conclusiones: el  uso  del  cuestionario  autoadministrado HADS en la práctica clínica habitual puede corregir el alto infradiagnóstico de la ansiedad y la depresión en los pacientes EPOC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;26(4): 234-243, oct.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de ansiedad y depresión en pacientes con EPOC, calculada mediante diagnóstico psiquiátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
