<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85088</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary infiltrates in immunocompromised patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary disease is a common complication in immunocompromised patients and in many cases to a large extent determines the patient&#146;s evolution. In view of the high morbidity and mortality of pulmonary complications, its early diagnosis and an appropriate therapeutic approach are a true challenge for paediatricians faced with the care of these patients on a daily basis. In recent decades, the development of new therapeutics for the treatment of oncological disease, the usual practice of organ transplants and the increased survival of many of these patients, mean that paediatricians, independently of their field of action, must know how to approach immunocompromised patients and their complications. We aim for this article to be a useful tool for the appropriate management of respiratory complications in those patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cimadevilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berroya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La afección pulmonar es una complicación frecuente en los pacientes inmunodeprimidos, y en muchas ocasiones condiciona de forma significativa su evolución. Teniendo en cuenta laalta morbimortalidad de las complicaciones pulmonares, un diagnóstico precoz y un abordaje terapéutico adecuado son un auténtico reto para los pediatras que se enfrentan diariamente al cuidado de estos pacientes. En las últimas décadas, el desarrollo de nuevas terapéuticas en el tratamiento de la enfermedad oncológica, la práctica habitual de trasplantes de órganos y la mayor supervivencia de muchos de estos pacientes han condicionado que el pediatra, con independencia de su ámbito de actuación, deba conocer el abordaje del enfermo inmunodeprimido y sus complicaciones. Pretendemos que este artículo sea una herramienta útil para el adecuado manejo de las complicaciones respiratorias de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(3): 111-118, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infiltrados pulmonares en pacientes inmunodeprimidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
