<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90264</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What are the pharmacological costs of a well-controlled diabetic?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the cost of glucose lowering treatment (GLT) in our diabetic patiients(DP).Design: Cross-sectional descriptive study.Setting: Urban primary health care centre.Participants: Random sample of 294 DP with HPT.Measurements: Principal variable: annual cost of GLT. Secondary Variables: age, sex, type ofdiabetes (DM), prescribing doctor, level of control, number of glucose lowering drugs, cardiovascularrisk factors and complications.Results: A total of 294 diabetic patients were included, with a mean age 71.7+/&amp;#8722;13.3 years;52.7% women; 93.2% DM2; Annual cost of GLT: 82.979 euros ,(281.9 euros /patient/year). General practitioner(GP) originated 32.3% of the treatments (17.7% of the costs). Annual average expenditurewas significantly higher in DM1 patients, patients on treatment with triple therapy and patientscontrolled by an endocrinologist in a reference hospital. In the multiple linear regressionthe variables that explained the variation in the cost were the type of Diabetes mellitus(P&lt;0.0001), prescription by hospital endocrinologist (p=0,002), number of glucose loweringdrugs(P&lt;0.0001), diabetic retinopathy(P: 0.019) and chronic renal failure (P: 0.027). Thesevariables explained 44.5% of the annual cost variation of the GLT (R2:0.445).Conclusions: There is a wide variation in the costs arising from GLT of our diabetic patients.We conclude, it is essential to improve coordination between levels of care, encourage thedesign and use of clinical guidelines to achieve more efficient control of our patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojas Blanc, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Férriz Villanueva, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera Nadal, Natàlia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera Nadal, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado Jodar, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el coste del tratamiento farmacológico hipoglucemiante (TFH) de los pacientesdiabéticos atendidos en un centro de atención primaria.Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal.Emplazamiento: Centro de Salud urbano.Participantes: Muestra aleatoria de 294 pacientes diabéticos con TFH.Mediciones principales: Variable Principal: coste anual TFH. Variables secundarias: edad, sexo,tipo de DM, médico prescriptor, grado de control de la diabetes, número de fármacos hipoglucemiantes,factores de riesgo cardiovascular y complicaciones.Resultados: Se incluyen 294 diabéticos. Edad media 71,7±13,3 años; 52,7% mujeres; 93,2%DM2; coste total TFH: 82.979 euros/año, (281,9 euros/paciente/año). El médico de familiaoriginaba el 32,3% de los tratamientos (17,7% del gasto). Presentaron un gasto medio anualsignificativamente mayor los pacientes diabéticos tipo 1, los que recibían triple terapia y loscontrolados por endocrinólogo hospitalario. En el estudio de regresión lineal múltiple las variablesque explicaron la variación en el coste fueron el tipo de DM (p&lt;0,0001), origen de laprescripción por endocrinólogo hospitalario (p:0,002), número de fármacos hipoglucemiantes(p&lt;0,001), presencia de retinopatía diabética (p:0,019) y daño renal (p: 0,027).Estas variables explicaron el 44,5% de la variación del coste farmacológico hipoglucemianteanual (R2: 0,445).Conclusiones: Existe gran variabilidad en el gasto originado por el TFH de nuestros pacientesdiabéticos. Es necesaria una mayor coordinación entre todos los profesionales implicados en elmanejo de los pacientes diabéticos, y además la elaboración de guías clínicas y terapéuticascompartidas, conseguiría un control más eficiente de los pacientes diabéticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(4): 169-174, abr. 2011. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90264</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué gasto farmacológico genera un diabético bien controlado?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30355^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
