<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153305</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alterations in tone of voice in patients with restrictive anorexia nervosa: A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article is about the tone of voice (acoustic perception) in patients with restrictive anorexia nervosa (AN-R). Our goal was to study whether or not there is an alteration of the tone in restrictive anorexia nervosa when the disease has started in the puberty. The total sample consisted of 148 subjects divided in two groups: control (n=102) and AN-R (n=46). The voice's fundamental frequencies (F0) were determined based on the repetition of two phonemes ('a' and 'i') and measured by a microphone Plantonic 300 and a digital recorder. We analyzed the voice's F0 using Praat software. We present the first data for the normal range of the F0 in Spanish healthy women from 9 to 17 years old who were Spanish native speakers. Finally, we show a comparison of data between AN-R patients and control group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Santana, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capilla, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza un estudio sobre el tono (percepción acústica) de la voz en la anorexia nerviosa restrictiva (ANR). El objetivo es valorar la alteración en la voz de las pacientes con ANR cuando el trastorno se inicia en la pubertad. La muestra total son 148 sujetos distribuidos en dos grupos: grupo control (n=102) y ANR (n=46). Se determinó la frecuencia fundamental de la voz (F0) utilizando dos fonemas ('a' e 'i') mediante un micrófono Plantronic 300 y grabador digital. Se analiza la voz con el programa Praat. Se presentan los primeros datos para la lengua española de los valores normales de la F0 de voz en población femenina sana de 9 a 17 años. Posteriormente se muestran los datos comparativos con el grupo de pacientes con ANR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;27(2): 73-80, jul. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones en la voz de las pacientes con anorexia nerviosa restrictiva: un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22242^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22242^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
