<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2323</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shattered paradigms: epistemologies for a post?psychiatry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Feminist and postcolonial epistemologies have hugely contributed to different theorical fields. Postpsychiatry, as a field born during the postmodern period, and also intended to restore some part of the theory and praxis that sustain contemporary psychiatry, is one of the areas where the consideration of different approaches and the experience from other questioned and even rejected paradigms could prove illuminating. Starting from parallel points of conflict we investigate the analogies and differences between different theoretical fields with the aim of finding solutions which contemporary psychiatry could incorporate in order to be defined as postpsychiatry (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carmona Osorio, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las epistemologías feministas y poscoloniales han hecho importantes aportaciones a múltiples campos teóricos. La postpsiquiatría, en tanto que nacida durante el periodo posmoderno y orientada a rehacer parte de la teoría y la práctica psiquiátrica, es uno de los campos donde otras miradas y la experiencia de otros paradigmas asimismo cuestionados y ampliamente debatidos resultan enriquecedoras. A partir de puntos de conflicto paralelos se estudian las analogías y diferencias entre los distintos campos teóricos, buscando qué soluciones puede incorporar la psiquiatría contemporánea si quiere definirse como postpsiquiatría (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;37(132): 509-528, jul.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paradigmas en estallido: epistemologías para una ¿post?psiquiatría</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
