<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112190</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional problems perceived by pediatricians in Spanish children younger than 3 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Parents are most responsible for nutritional education of children, and pediatritians must advise and help them with their doubts. The purpose of this study was to know the relevance of nutritional topics in daily practice and the main nutritional problems perceived by pediatritians in children under 3 years of age. Methods: Descriptive, cross-sectional study performed in 2 stages. First stage consisted on discussion meetings with 30 random-selected pediatritians from Madrid and Barcelona. Results were used to design the on-line questionnaire of the second stage (76 questions related to nutrition in children under 3 years). A random and representative sample of Spanish pediatritians was selected for this stage. Results: One hundred and fifty one pediatritians, among 258 sampled, completed the questionnaire. They referred to see a mean of 588 patients/month. The main perceived nutritional problems in the first year of life were iron and vitamin deficiencies and poor weight gain. In the next months, excess in carbohydrates and lipid intake and overweight were the main problems perceived. Parents were considered the main actors regarding their children's nutritional health, but their concern in these questions significantly reduced with children's age (p &lt; 0,0001). Factors considered to have the greatest relevance in the acquisition of good nutritional habits were to provide a diet adjusted for children's requirements and to observe the appropriate sleeping hours. The proportion of children who receive nutritional counseling varied from 88% (0-6 months) to 61% (24-36 months). Conclusions: Despite of the relevance given by pediatritians, educational intervention regarding nutritional health is not ideal. Nutritional problems perceived by pediatritians varied with children's age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalmau Serra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Suárez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moráis López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Quintana, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Gómez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varea Calderón, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los padres son los principales responsables de la educación nutricional de sus hijos y es labor del pediatra orientar y resolver problemas al respecto. En este estudio se pretende conocer la relevancia de las cuestiones nutricionales en la consulta del pediatra y los principales problemas nutricionales percibidos en los menores de 3 años. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal en dos fases. La primera consistió en entrevistas y grupos de discusión con 30 pediatras seleccionados aleatoriamente en Madrid y Barcelona. Los resultados se utilizaron para diseñar el cuestionario online (76 preguntas relacionadas con la nutrición en niños de 0-3 años) de la siguiente fase, en la que participaron pediatras seleccionados de forma aleatoria y representativa del territorio nacional. Resultados: De 258 pediatras seleccionados, completaron el cuestionario 151, que atendían a una media de 588 pacientes/mes. Los principales problemas nutricionales percibidos hasta los 12 meses fueron las deficiencias de hierro y vitaminas y la escasa ganancia de peso, y posteriormente la ingesta excesiva de carbohidratos y lípidos y el sobrepeso. Los padres fueron considerados los actores principales en la salud nutricional de sus hijos, pero su preocupación por esta cuestión se reduce significativamente (p &lt; 0,0001) con la edad del niño. Los aspectos considerados más importantes para obtener unos buenos hábitos alimentarios fueron la alimentación adaptada a las necesidades del niño y respetar el tiempo de sueño. El porcentaje de pacientes que recibe recomendaciones de hábitos nutricionales varió del 88% (0-6 meses) al 61% (24-36 meses). Conclusiones: A pesar de considerar la salud nutricional importante, la intervención educativa del pediatra al respecto no es óptima. Los problemas nutricionales percibidos fueron distintos según la edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 2028-2047, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112190</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemas nutricionales percibidos por los pediatras en niños españoles menores de 3 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
