<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71244</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To identify the prevalent learning styles among students beginning Medical School and to compare these preferences with those found at the end of the carrier and during the residency program. The relationship between learning style and academic performance, as well as the association between learning preferences and postgraduate specialty selection were additionally studied. Subjects and methods. The Honey-Alonso learning style questionnaire was administered to 102second-year students (pregraduate initial group), 52 last year students (pregraduate final group) and 45 physiciansat a cardiology residency program (postgraduate group).Learning styles were compared within and between groups. The relationship between learning styles and academic performance in anatomy was assessed in the pregraduateinitial group). The association between learning preferences and postgraduate specialty selection was studied in the pregraduate final group. Results. Learning preferences in the pregraduate initial group was theoretic (70%) for acquiring information and reflexive (86%) for using information respectively. In postgraduate group, preferences were theoretic(67%) and reflexive (70%), showing a marked decrease of the last style with respect to pregraduate initial (p = 0.069),at expense of an increase in active style. pregraduate initial showed a tendency towards &#145;assimilator&#146; style (70.6%), while &#145;convergent&#146; one was the rarest (6.9%). When comparing pregraduate final to postgraduate group, a reduction of &#145;assimilator&#146; style (p = 0.040) and an increase of &#145;convergent&#146; one (p = 0.034) was observed. Conclusions. Students&#146; learning preferences for acquiring and using information were theoretic and reflexive (assimilator) predominantly at the beginning of the carrier. At the end and at the postgraduate period, &#145;assimilator&#146; style decreased at expense of an increase of the rest, especially at &#145;convergent&#146; (theoretic and active)one. Although the &#145;assimilator&#146; was the commoner, increase of &#145;convergent&#146; style showed that at residency, individuals learn by solving problems and using knowledge in practice; this increase was done at expense of the active over the reflexive style. On the other hand, no relationship between learning style and academic performance in anatomy was found. Finally, an association between learning styles and postgraduate specialty selection showed that the last was more related to genre than to learning preferences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guthman, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribalzaga, E. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borracci, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir los estilos de aprendizaje a los que recurren los estudiantes de medicina al ingresar en la universidad, compararlos con los estilos al finalizar la carrera y en el posgrado inmediato, analizar la relación entre estilo de aprendizaje y desempeño académico, y estudiar la asociación entre estilos y la tendencia a elegir una especialidad al finalizar la carrera. Sujetos y métodos. Durante2006 se incluyeron de forma prospectiva 102 estudiantes de medicina de segundo año (grupo pregrado inicio), 52estudiantes del último año (grupo pregrado final) y 45médicos de segundo año de residencia (grupo posgrado).Se determinó el estilo de aprendizaje con el cuestionario de Honey-Alonso. En la muestra pregrado final se incluyó la preferencia por una especialidad clínica o quirúrgica al finalizar la carrera, datos que fueron relacionados con los estilos preponderantes. Resultados. En pregrado inicio, la preferencia para adquirir información fue teórica en el77% y el uso fue fundamentalmente reflexivo en el 86%. En posgrado, la adquisición de información fue predominantemente teórica en el 67% y el uso reflexivo en el 70%. La comparación demostró la disminución del modo reflexivo y el aumento del activo cuando se empleó la información al acercarse al posgrado (p = 0,069). En pregrado inicio hubo una tendencia al estilo &#145;asimilador&#146; (70,6%), mientras que el &#145;convergente&#146; fue el más raro (6,9%). Al comparar pregrado final y posgrado se demuestra en este último una reducción del estilo &#145;asimilador&#146;(p = 0,040), a expensas del crecimiento &#145;convergente&#146; (p = 0,034). Conclusiones. Los estudiantes tuvieron un estilo preponderantemente teórico y reflexivo (asimilador) al comenzar la carrera. Al finalizarla y en el posgrado disminuyó el estilo &#145;asimilador&#146;, en especial a expensas del crecimiento &#145;convergente&#146;. No se pudo demostrar una relación entre los estilos de aprendizaje y el desempeño académico en anatomía. Al evaluar la presunta asociación entre estilo de aprendizaje y preferencia por una especialidad, se encontró que esta relación estaba más vinculada al efecto &#145;confundidor&#146; del género; así, en las mujeres preponderó el estilo &#145;divergente&#146; y la especialidad clínica, mientras que en los varones se observó un perfil &#145;asimilador&#146; y la opción por una especialidad quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 229-238, dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71244</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6432^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
