<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130256</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Between complexity and art: the qualitative data analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Qualitative analysis is a complex process that concerns among researchers. Some of the main features of the analysis are creativity, uncertainty, unpredictability; circumstances that contributing to the idea that it is one of the most complex activities of research. The aim of this paper is to support junior researchers, so that they have a description as detailed as possible of how you can perform the analysis in qualitative research. The intention, therefore, is to present some guidelines to help with the difficulties that arise throughout the entire process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina Moya, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El análisis cualitativo es un proceso complejo que genera inquietud en los investigadores. Algunas de las características principales del análisis son la creatividad, la incertidumbre, la imprevisibilidad; circunstancias que contribuyen a que sea valorado como una de las actividades más complejas de la investigación. El objetivo de este artículo es servir de apoyo a los investigadores noveles, de forma que cuenten con una descripción lo más detallada posible de cómo se puede realizar el análisis en una investigación cualitativa. La pretensión, por tanto, es presentar unas pautas con la finalidad de que sirvan de apoyo en las dificultades que se vayan presentando a lo largo de todo el proceso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(3): 157-161, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entre la complejidad y el arte: el análisis de datos en cualitativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
