<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041928</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of the quality agenda in primary care consultations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Heavy caseload is a significant concern to primary care physicians. The use of consultations can be reduced through the application of strategies directed at the user, the health professional and the organization. One of these strategies is consultation management. Objective: To improve the dynamics of family medicine consultations through demand rationalization, improved accessibility and user satisfaction. Material and method: An intervention plan was implemented. The intervention consisted of appointment organization, evaluation of caseload before and after the intervention, the degree of user satisfaction with the adopted measures, and evaluation with the care received. Results: Consultation management decreased demand and increased scheduled consultations (activity was maintained constant), while users perceived a decrease in waiting time. Conclusions: Healthcare activity can be rationalized through appropriate consultation management. Moreover, improved accessibility to the system leads to good user satisfaction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáenz, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Dulce</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escortell, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La presión asistencial elevada es un problema que preocupa a los médicos de atención primaria (AP). Se puede optimizar la utilización de las consultas mediante la aplicación de estrategias dirigidas al usuario, los profesionales y la organización. Entre ellas está la gestión de la consulta. Objetivo: Mejorar la dinámica de una consulta de medicina de familia mediante la racionalización de la demanda, mejora de la accesibilidad y satisfacción del usuario. Material y método: Se establece un plan de intervención consistente en: organización de la cita, evaluación de la actividad asistencial antes y después de la intervención, de la satisfacción de los usuarios con la medida adoptada y de la atención recibida. Resultados: Con la gestión de la agenda de consulta, disminuye la consulta a demanda, aumenta la concertada (la presión asistencial se mantiene) y el usuario percibe que disminuye el tiempo de espera. Conclusiones: Se racionaliza la actividad asistencial y se consigue una adecuada satisfacción del usuario, al mejorar su acceso al sistema</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(7): 363-369, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la agenda de calidad en una consulta de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
