<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053715</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drainage in thyroid and parathyroid surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The use of suction drains in thyroid and parathyroid surgery is common practice in order to avoid haematoma or seroma, as well as to identify promptly the onset of haemorrhaging that might compromise the patient's airway. The goal of this study is to evaluate the experience on 79 thyroid and parathyroid procedures, in 50 % of which a drain was used.         Results: No differences were found in terms of the presence of infections, seromas, or haemorrhage. Post-operative haemorrhage was found in 2.3 % of cases, haematoma in 2.5 %, and seroma in 1.2 %. The mean hospital stay was longer in patients with drains, 1.8 days, than in patients without, 1.2 days.         Conclusions: Meticulous haemostasis and adequate surgical technique are the key for avoiding haemorrhage and haematoma formation. Extensive dead space, intrathoracic or retrosternal goiters, and excessive tissue manipulation are our indications for suction drain placement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herranz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El empleo de drenajes tras la cirugía de tiroides y paratiroides busca evitar hematomas o seromas e identificar con prontitud la aparición de hemorragias que pudieran comprometer la vía aérea del paciente. Su empleo se asume como una medida habitual. El objetivo de este estudio es describir la experiencia obtenida en 79 cirugías de tiroides y paratiroides, en el 50 % de las cuales se ha utilizado drenaje.         Resultados: No hemos encontrado diferencia en cuanto a infecciones, seromas o hemorragias. Tuvimos un 2,3 % de hemorragias postoperatorias, un 2,5 % de hematomas y un 1,2 % de seromas. La estancia media fue mayor en los pacientes con drenaje, 1,8 días, que sin drenaje, 1,2 días.         Conclusiones: Una correcta técnica quirúrgica y la meticulosa hemostasia evitan la aparición de hemorragias y hematomas. La presencia de amplios espacios muertos, los bocios intratorácicos o retroesternales y la manipulación excesiva de los tejidos son nuestras indicaciones para la colocación de drenajes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(1): 7-9, ene. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053715</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Drenajes en cirugía de tiroides y paratiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10468^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
