<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134570</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of phenotypic and genotypic drug resistance patterns of Mycobacterium tuberculosis isolates from a city in Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The emergence of multidrug-resistant (MDR) Mycobacterium tuberculosis strains has become a worldwide health care problem, making treatment of tuberculosis difficult. The aim of this study was to determine phenotypic resistance and gene mutations associated with MDR of clinical isolates ofMycobacterium tuberculosis from Guadalajara, Mexico. Methods: One hundred and five isolates were subjected to drug susceptibility testing to first line drugs using the proportion and Mycobacteria Growth Indicator Tube (MGIT) methods. Genes associated with isoniazid (inhA, katG, ahpC) and rifampicin (rpoB) resistance were analyzed by either pyrosequencing or PCR-RFLP. Results: Resistance to any drug was detected in 48.6% of isolates, of which 40% were isoniazid-resistant, 20% were rifampicin-resistant and 19% were MDR. Drug-resistant isolates had the following frequency of mutations in rpoB (48%), katG (14%), inhA (26%), ahpC (26%). Susceptible isolates also had a mutation in ahpC (29%). Conclusions: This is the first analysis of mutations associated with MDR of M. tuberculosis in Guadalajara. Commonly reported mutations worldwide were found in rpoB, katG and inhA genes. Substitution C to T in position -15 of the ahpC gene may possibly be a polymorphism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raúl Pérez-Gómez, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garza-González, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Díaz, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Treviño, Samantha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morfín-Otero, Rayo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María González, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza-Olazarán, Soraya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Noriega,  Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balderas-Rentería, Isaías</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La emergencia de cepas de Mycobacterium tuberculosis multifarmacorresistentes (MFR) se ha convertido en un problema de salud mundial, dificultando el tratamiento de la tuberculosis. El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar la resistencia fenotípica y las mutaciones en genes asociados a MFR en aislamientos clínicos de M. tuberculosis de Guadalajara, México. Métodos: Se determinó la susceptibilidad a fármacos de primera línea de 105 aislamientos, usando los métodos de proporciones y MGIT. Los genes asociados a resistencia a isoniazida (inhA, katG, ahpC) y a rifampicina(rpoB), se analizaron por pirosecuenciación o por PCR-RFLP. Resultados: Se detectó la resistencia a cualquier fármaco en 48.6% de los aislamientos, 40% fueron resistentes a isoniazida, 20% fueron resistentes a rifampicina y 19% fueron MFR. Los aislamientos farmacorresistentes presentaron la siguiente frecuencia de mutaciones en rpoB (48%), katG (14%), inhA (26%), ahpC (26%). Además, los aislamientos susceptibles también mostraron una mutación en ahpC (29%). Conclusiones: Este es el primer análisis de mutaciones asociadas con MFR de M. tuberculosis en Guadalajara. Se detectaron mutaciones comúnmente reportadas a nivel mundial en los genes rpoB, katG e inhA. La sustitución de C por T en la posición -15 del gen ahpC posiblemente puede ser un polimorfismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;33(3): 181-185, mar. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de los patrones de farmacorresistencia fenotípica y genotípica de aislamientos de Mycobacterium tuberculosis de una ciudad de México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
