<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133733</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outpatient laparoscopic cholecystectomy and pain control: A series of 100 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction We present our experience of 100 consecutive cases that underwent ambulatory cholecystectomy using a standard protocol of anesthesia and surgery. Patients and method Prospective study of 100 consecutive patients assessed in the surgery outpatient clinic in Torrevieja Hospital (September 2008-september 2009). Both anesthetic and surgical techniques were protocolized, standardized. The protocol included the use of intraperitoneal and parietal anesthesia. Results One hundred patients were included. Average age was 53 years and average surgical time was 29 ± 12 min. Day-case surgery rate was 96%. Postoperative pain (VAS scale) was less than 4 in all cases. Six patients complained of nausea that eased with the administration of ev metoclopramide. Average length of stay in the day-case surgery unit was 7.4 h (maximum 9.6, minimum 7). Morbidity and mortality rates were 0%. No re-admission was registered and conversion rate was 0%. Postoperative follow-up was 100%. A total of 97% of the cases were fully satisfied with the procedure. Conclusion Ambulatory laparoscopic cholecystectomy is a feasible and safe technique. Postoperative pain has classically been the reason to not perform day-case surgery, but we achieved an excellent control by the combined use of local anesthetics and warm intraperitoneal (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa Navarro, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Fuertes, Montiel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Describimos la experiencia de nuestro grupo en la colecistectomía laparoscópica ambulatoria en una serie de 100 casos consecutivos sometidos a un proceso protocolizado de anestesia y cirugía. Pacientes y método Estudio prospectivo de 100 pacientes consecutivos remitidos a consultas externas de Cirugía General del Hospital de Torrevieja (septiembre de 2008 y septiembre de 2009). La técnica anestésica y quirúrgica fue protocolizada incluyendo el uso intraperitoneal y parietal de anestesia local. Resultados La media de edad fue de 53 años. El tiempo quirúrgico medio fue de 29 ± 12 min. La tasa de ambulatorización fue del 96%. La media del dolor postoperatorio en ningún caso superó el valor de 3 en la escala EVA. Seis pacientes sintieron náuseas que cedieron tras la administración de metoclopramida iv. La estancia media en el hospital de los pacientes ambulatorizados fue de 7,4 h (mínimo de 7 y máximo de 9,6). La morbilidad de la serie fue (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(3): 181-186, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133733</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colecistectomía laparoscópica ambulatoria y control del dolor postoperatorio: presentación de una serie de 100 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
