<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12964</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceived quality of life assessment in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study summarizes features and results of a research developed to identify key quality of life dimensions for children in Argentina and Spain, and to assess their perceived quality of life. Open questions about satisfaction experiences, dissatisfaction and desires of change were presented to 199 children between eight and twelve years old. In addition, 16 children with learning disabilities from 8 to 14 years old were asked as well. The KINDL questionnaire (Bullinger y Ravens-Sieberer, 1997) was also applied to the first group. Six dimensions of quality of life were identified and defined: leisure and recreation, achievement, interpersonal relations, physical and emotional well-being, community well-being and values, and material well-being. Data from questionnaire relating to gender, age and nationality were examined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verdugo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabeh, Eliana Noemi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se resumen las características y resultados de una investigación cuyos objetivos fueron identificar dimensiones de calidad de vida relevantes para los niños en Argentina y España, y valorar la calidad de vida percibida por ellos. Se presentaron preguntas abiertas sobre experiencias de satisfacción, insatisfacción y deseos de cambio a 100 niños de 8 años y a 99 de 12 años, y de manera exploratoria a 16 niños con discapacidades en el aprendizaje entre 8 y 14 años. También se aplicó el cuestionario KINDL (Bullinger y Ravens-Sieberer, 1997) al primer grupo. Se identificaron y definieron 6 dimensiones de calidad de vida: ocio y actividades recreativas, rendimiento, relaciones interpersonales, bienestar físico y emocional, bienestar colectivo y valores, y bienestar material. Los datos del cuestionario se analizaron considerando diferencias existentes en función del género, la edad y la nacionalidad. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(1): 86-91, ene. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la percepción de calidad de vida en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
