<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166134</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention program with coaches and parents: effects of the coach´s behavior and the team´s motivational climate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the application of an intervention program with coaches and parents of youth soccer teams in Mexico, for the promotion task-involving motivational climate. The intervention with coaches was based on the strategies postulated by the Mastery Approach to Coaching (MAC) program. In addition, educational strategies were implemented with parents. It involved the participation of 81 male soccer players between 12 and 15 years old, 4 male coaches and 34 parents. Behavioral changes were obtained in the coaches; however, the intervention did not produce a motivational climate of greater involvement towards the task (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruz Feliu, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa Alvarez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, María del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo muestra la aplicación de un programa de intervención con entrenadores y padres de familia de equipos juveniles de futbol en México, para la promoción de climas motivacionales de implicación a la tarea. La intervención con entrenadores se basó en las estrategias postuladas por el programa Mastery Approach to Coaching (MAC). Asimismo, estrategias de corte educativo se implementaron con padres de familia. Se contó con la participación de 81 futbolistas varones entre los 12 y 15 años, 4 entrenadores del sexo masculino y 34 padres de familia. Se obtuvieron cambios conductuales en los entrenadores, sin embargo, la intervención no produjo un clima motivacional de mayor implicación hacia la tarea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.2): 181-187, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de intervención con entrenadores y padres de familia: Efectos en las conductas del entrenador y el clima motivacional del equipo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
