<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166332</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac pacing in specific situations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac pacing is a well-known therapeutic approach. In practice, making the best use of the technique depends fundamentally both on accurate disease assessment in the individual patient who requires a pacemaker and on understanding the range of options offered by the devices available on the market. There are a number of specific situations that, because of their clinical significance and the uncertainties associated with the use of pacing in them, are worthwhile treating on an individual basis. This article summarizes current understanding of five of these situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan Montiel, Jesús de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tascón Pérez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Álvarez, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roda Nicolás, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ferrer, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fidalgo Andrés, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estimulación cardiaca es un procedimiento terapéutico ampliamente conocido. En la actualidad su utilización óptima depende fundamentalmente de la valoración individualizada de la afección del paciente que precisa un marcapasos y de conocer las múltiples posibilidades de los dispositivos disponibles en el mercado. Existen algunas situaciones especiales que, por su relevancia clínica y las dudas que pueden generar en cuanto a estimulación, merece la pena tratar de forma individualizada. En este trabajo se exponen los conocimientos actuales en cinco de esas situaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.G): 82g-101g, 2007. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación cardiaca en situaciones diversas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1708^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38829^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
