<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159815</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Difference in fatty acids composition of breast adipose tissue in women with breast cancer and benign breast disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Breast cancer is the second most common cancer in the world, and the most frequent cancer among women. Moreover, there are factors that influence the risk for breast cancer including the age, genetic and endocrine factors, and lifestyle. Objectives: To evaluate the consumption of fatty acids; compare the fatty acids composition in the breast adipose tissue of women with breast cancer and benign breast disease as well as potential risk factors; and describe the genotypic frequency of the Pro12Ala PPAR&amp;#947; polymorphism. Material and methods: A hospital-based case-control study was conducted including incident cases (n = 38 breast cancer; n = 75 benign breast disease; n = 166 control). Lifestyle features, socioeconomic issues, dietary intake, anthropometry, and blood and tissue data were assessed. Results: No differences were observed for fatty acids intake. Interestingly, lauric acid (p = 0.001), myristic acid (p = 0.036), stearic acid (p = 0.031), and total saturated fatty acids (SFAs) (p = 0.048) had lower concentrations in BC than in BBD women, while palmitoleic acid (p = 0.022), erucic acid (p = 0.002), total monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) (p = 0.039) and oleic acid/stearic acid ratio (p = 0.015) increased. There was no significant association between PPAR&amp;#947; polymorphism and studied groups (p = 0.977). The age at first full pregnancy (p = 0.004) was significantly associated with the development BC, whereas BMI (p = 0.005); percentage of body fat (p = 0.024); physical activity (p = 0.036); and age at menarche (p = 0.008), at first full pregnancy (p &lt; 0.001), and of first mammogram (p = 0.018) were significantly associated with the development of BBD. Conclusion: The results suggest a different fatty acids composition of breast adipose tissue, a biomarker of long-term dietary intake, particularly for SFAs, MUFA and 18: 1 n-9/18: 00 ratio. Our findings also show that are differences in the factors related to the development of BC and BBC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pena, Geórgia das Graças</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pessoa, Milene Cristine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moura e Dias, Mariana de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermsdorff, Helen Hermana Miranda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Renata Nascimento de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conceição, Lisiane Lopes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendes, Maria Carolina Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peluzio, Maria do Carmo Gouveia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neves, Cristiane Vilas Boas</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el cáncer de mama (CM) es el segundo cáncer más común en el mundo, y el cáncer más frecuente entre las mujeres. Por otra parte, hay factores que influyen en el riesgo de padecer CM, entre los que se encuentran la edad, factores genéticos y endocrinos, y el estilo de vida. Objetivos: evaluar el consumo de ácidos grasos; comparar la composición de ácidos grasos en el tejido adiposo de mama de las mujeres con CM y enfermedad benigna de mama (EBM), así como los posibles factores de riesgo; y describir la frecuencia genotípica del polimorfismo Pro12Ala PPAR&amp;#947;. Material y métodos: se llevó a cabo un estudio caso-control basado en hospitales, incluyendo casos incidentes (n = 38 cáncer de mama, n = 75 enfermedad benigna de mama, n = 166 control). Se evaluaron las características del estilo de vida, las cuestiones socioeconómicas, la ingesta dietética, la antropometría y los datos de sangre y tejidos. Resultados: no se observaron diferencias para la ingesta de ácidos grasos. Curiosamente, ácido láurico (p = 0,001), ácido mirístico (p = 0,036), ácido esteárico (p = 0,031) y los ácidos grasos totales saturados (AGS) (p = 0,048) tenían concentraciones más bajas en CM que en mujeres EBM, mientras ácido palmitoleico (p = 0,022), ácido erúcico (p = 0,002), los ácidos totales grasos monoinsaturados (MUFA) (p = 0,039) y la relación ácido oleico/ácido esteárico (p = 0,015) aumentó. No hubo asociación significativa entre el polimorfismo PPAR gamma y los grupos de estudio (p = 0,977). La edad al primer embarazo (p = 0,004) se asoció de forma signifi cativa con el desarrollo de CM, mientras que el IMC (p = 0,005), porcentaje de grasa corporal (p = 0,024), la actividad física (p = 0,036) y la edad de la menarquia (p = 0,008), al primer embarazo (p &lt; 0,001), y de la primera mamografía (p = 0,018), fueron significativamente asociados con el desarrollo de EBM. Conclusiones: los resultados sugieren una composición diferente de ácidos grasos del tejido adiposo de la mama, un biomarcador de la ingesta dietética a largo plazo, particularmente para SFA, MUFA y 18: 1 n-9/18: 00. Nuestros hallazgos también muestran que existen diferencias en los factores relacionados con el desarrollo de CM y EBM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(6): 1354-1360, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencia en la composición de ácidos grasos del tejido adiposo de la mama en mujeres con cáncer de mama y enfermedad benigna de la mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5484^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38771^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5331^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
