<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73777</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Learning and teaching in rehabilitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine what type of theoreticaltraining methodology for residents in Physical Medicineand Rehabilitation (PM&amp;R) provides better results forlearning, attaining clinical skills and knowledge, and relevanceto professional life.Material and methods. Prospective longitudinal study, performedduring the 2006-2007 resident training program inPM&amp;R. At the end of each class, a questionnaire designedfor the study was distributed to residents for their evaluationof the class model (lecture-based master class or interactiveclass) as related to learning, clinical skills, knowledge,and professional life. The hypothesis was that the interactiveclass would give better satisfaction in these areas thanthe master model. Qualitative values were compared usingchi-square distributions.Results. Among the 183 questionnaires administered,50.3 % were for master classes and 49.7 % for interactiveclasses. For the recodified question on learning (We gainedknowledge in this class) 48.6 % agreed for the master classmodel and 51.4 % for the interactive model. For skills, positiveresponses were 38.5 % and 61.5 %, respectively; forknowledge, 37.7 % and 62.3 %, respectively; and for professionallife, 33.9 % and 66.1 %, respectively. There were noassociations between learning and type of class. There was,however, an association between skills, knowledge and professionallife with class model (p &lt; 0.05), such that the interactivemodel gave better results than the master class.Conclusion. According to the subjective opinion of PM&amp;Rmedical residents, the interactive teaching method providesa better outcome for acquisition of clinical skills, knowledge,and usefulness in clinical practice, but does not differfrom lecture-based methods for learning(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Viejo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesinos-Magraner, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Garrido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Eizmendi, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar qué metodología formativateórica podría dar mejores resultados en el aprendizaje,habilidades clínicas, conocimientos teóricos adquiridos yutilidad en la vida laboral en los MIR en medicina física y rehabilitación(MFR).Material y método. Estudio longitudinal prospectivo, realizadodurante las clases del programa formativo de residentes2006-2007, con la participación de los MIR en MFR. Alfinalizar las clases se administró un cuestionario para valorarel modelo de clase (magistral e interactivo). Valoraba elaprendizaje, la habilidad, el conocimiento y la vida laboralbajo la percepción del residente. La hipótesis era que elmodelo interactivo daba mayor satisfacción en los camposde aprendizaje, habilidades, conocimiento y vida laboral queel modelo magistral. Se realizó un estudio bivariante con elpaquete estadístico SPSS® 15.Resultados. De los 189 cuestionarios, 95 se consideranclases magistrales y 94 clases interactivas. No existen diferenciasentre aprendizaje y modelo de clase. Existe asociaciónentre habilidades y modelos de clase a favor delmodelo interactivo (desacuerdo 8,7 frente a 91,3 %, parcial43,9 frente a 56,1 % y de acuerdo 61,5 frente a 50,3 %). Existeasociación entre conocimiento y modelos de clase a favordel interactivo (desacuerdo 9,1 frente a 90,9 %, parcial35,6 frente a 64,4 % y de acuerdo 62,3 frente a 37,7 %). Existeasociación entre utilidad de la vida laboral y modelos declase, a favor del interactivo (desacuerdo 18,2 frente a81,8 %, parcial 29,1 frente a 70,9 % y de acuerdo 66,1 frentea 33,9 %).Conclusión. El modelo interactivo da mejores resultadosen habilidades, conocimiento y utilidad de la vida laboral,pero no en el aprendizaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(5): 204-210, sept.-oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprender y enseñar en rehabilitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
