<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86103</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Increased primary care consultations for upper respiratory tract infections and fever coinciding with a wave of influenza(H1N1) 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background:Awave of influenza A(H1N1)2009 was registered in the summer of 2009. We evaluated its repercussion on primary care consultations not diagnosed as influenza. Methods: We analysed primary care consultations in the Navarre Health Service from 21 June to 21 September 2009 with a diagnosis of influenza (International Classification of Primary Care, code R80), febrile syndrome (code A03), acute upper respiratory tract infection (code R74), or acute bronchitis (code R78); these consultations were then compared with those occurring in the same period in the three previous years. Results: In the summer of 2009, 3,417 cases of influenza syndrome (5.5 per 1000 population) were reported. An flu outbreak occurred between week 27 and 31, with over the mild (87/160) of swabs from patients with influenza syndrome positive for the virus A(H1N1), with no other influenza types detected. Coinciding with the wave of influenza syndromes, we observed increases in consultations for febrile syndrome and upper respiratory tract infection. In comparison with the mean for the three previous years, in the summer of 2009 consultations for febrile syndrome increased by 44% (3.6 to 5.3 per 1000; p&lt;0.001), consultations for upper respiratory tract infection by 6% (13.2 to 14.1 per 1000; p&lt;0.001), and consultations for bronchitis by 8% (6.3 to 6.9 per 1000; p&lt;0.003). These diagnoses represented 3.2 additional consultations per 1000 population attributable to influenza, that is, 58% more consultations. Conclusions: Influenza gives rise to increased primary care consultations for influenza syndrome as well as for other less important processes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oscariz, Miren</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Apezteguía, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldaz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dronda, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loayssa, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagredo, Mirian</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En verano de 2009 se registró en Navarra una onda de gripe A (H1N1) 2009. Evaluar su repercusión en consultas de atención primaria con diagnóstico diferente al de gripe. Métodos: Estudiamos las consultas en atención primaria del Servicio Navarro de Salud desde el 21 de junio y al 21 de septiembre de 2009 con diagnósticos de gripe (Clasificación Internacional de Atención Primaria, código R80), síndrome febril (código A03), infección respiratoria aguda de vías altas (código R74) y bronquitis aguda (código R78), y las comparamos con las registradas en el mismo periodo en los tres años previos. Resultados: En verano de 2009 se notificaron 3417 casos de síndrome gripal (5,5 por 1.000 habitantes). Entre las semanas 27 y 31 se produjo un brote de gripe, con más de la mitad (87/160) de los frotis de pacientes con síndrome gripal positivos para el virus (H1N1) 2009 sin detectarse otros tipos de virus gripal. Coincidiendo con la onda de síndromes gripales observamos aumentos de consultas por síndrome febril e infección respiratoria de vías altas. En comparación con la media de los tres años anteriores, en el verano del 2009 se produjo un incremento del 44% en consultas por síndrome febril (de 3,6 a 5,3 por 1000: p&lt;0,001), del 6% en consultas por infección de vías altas (de 13,2 a 14,1 por 1000; p&lt;0,001) y del 8% en consultas por bronquitis aguda (de 6,3 a 6,9 por 1000; p=0,003). Estos diagnósticos supusieron 3,2 consultas adicionales por 1.000 habitantes atribuibles a la gripe, es decir, un 58% de consultas adicionales. Conclusiones: La gripe se acompaña de aumento en el número de consultas por síndrome febril y por infección respiratoria de vías altas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(1): 121-128, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de consultas en atención primaria por infección respiratoria de vías altas y fiebre coincidiendo con la epidemia de gripe (H1N1) 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
