<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118402</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Venous catheter-related infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Venous catheter-related infections are a problem of particular importance, due to their frequency, morbidity and mortality, and because they are potentially preventable clinical processes. At present, the majority of hospitalized patients and a considerable number of outpatients are carriers of these devices. There has been a remarkable growth of knowledge of the epidemiology of these infections, the most appropriate methodology for diagnosis, the therapeutic and, in particular, the preventive strategies. Mutimodal strategies, including educational programs directed at staff and a bundle of simple measures for implementation, applied to high-risk patients have demonstrated great effectiveness for their prevention. In this review the epidemiology, the diagnosis, and the therapeutic and preventive aspects of these infections are updated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almirante, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones relacionadas con los catéteres vasculares son un problema de especial relevancia por su frecuencia, por su morbimortalidad y por ser procesos clínicos potencialmente evitables. En la actualidad, la mayoría de pacientes hospitalizados y un número considerable de enfermos en régimen ambulatorio son portadores de este tipo de dispositivos. El conocimiento sobre la epidemiología de estas infecciones, sobre la metodología más apropiada para su diagnóstico y sobre las estrategias terapéuticas y, sobre todo, preventivas ha experimentado un notable crecimiento. Las estrategias multimodales, que incluyen actividades educativas dirigidas al personal y un paquete de medidas sencillas para su aplicación de manera conjunta, aplicadas a pacientes de alto riesgo han demostrado una gran eficacia para su prevención. En esta revisión se actualizan los aspectos epidemiológicos, diagnósticos, terapéuticos y preventivos de este tipo de infecciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(2): 115-124, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118402</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones relacionadas con el uso de los catéteres vasculares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
