<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78619</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rolations between images and violence, and its incidence on adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We are currently witnessing a rise in the images to be found in the most intimate areas of the human subject, images are often blamed for the disturbing increase in the number of acts of pointess violence. In order to understand the relationship   between image and violence, we first and foremost need to concern ourselves with the very nature of the image. This will enable us to reflect upon the psychological, difficulties that adolescents must bear with on becoming adults in a society in which a particular facet of the image has acquired a dominant role (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sunyé Barcons, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Asistimos en la actualidad a un auge de las imágenes que pueblan los rincones más íntimos del sujeto humano, imágenes a las que frecuentemente se les inculpa del preocupante aumento de los actos de violencia gratuitos. Para poder entender la relación entre imagen y violencia ante todo hemos de  interesados  por la propia naturaleza de la imagen. Ello nos permitirá una faceta de la imagen ha adquirido un papel predominante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(11): 65-74, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de las imágenes con la violencia y su incidencia en los adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
