<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134144</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Barriers and difficulties perceived for the management of violent situations: design and validation of a questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to assess the barriers and/or difficulties perceived by the Nursing staff in the Psychiatric Hospital Dr. Rodríguez Lafora regarding the management of violent situations, through a questionnaire previously designed and validated to this aim. Method: the study was conducted in two phases. During the first stage, a board of experts was held for the subsequent preparation and validation of a 22-item questionnaire about the perception of barriers and/or difficulties in the management of violent situations. For construct validation, an exploratory factor analysis was conducted. In the second stage, a transversal descriptive study was conducted, through the administration of the questionnaire to the Nursing team in the above-mentioned hospital (n= 308). A bivariate analysis(Student&#146;s t and ANOVA) was conducted. Results: 179 questionnaires were collected. Cronbach&#146;s &amp;#61537;Coefficient was 0.925. The exploratory factor analysis conducted showed five dimensions which explained the 67.01%variance. The validated questionnaire included 21 items, which obtained high scores (between 6.60 and 8.33), with the highest scores obtained in those items associated with team work and individual characteristics of the professionals. Conclusions: after the design and validation of a questionnaire about perceived barriers and/or difficulties in the management of violent situations, the following were identified as the main difficulties in management: team work, training, regular changes of staff in the units, or the specificity of management according to each patient. It is necessary to continue the process of tool validation  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardilla Laparra, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pozo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar las barreras y/o dificultades que perciben los profesionales de Enfermería del Hospital psiquiátrico Dr. Rodríguez Lafora (Madrid) en el manejo de situaciones violentas, para lo que previamente se diseñó y validó un cuestionario. Método: el estudio se llevó a cabo en dos fases. En la primera se realizó un panel de expertos para la posterior elaboración y validación de un cuestionario de 22 ítems sobre la percepción de barreras y/o dificultades para el manejo de situaciones violentas. Para la validación de constructo se hizo un análisis factorial exploratorio. En la segunda se hizo un estudio descriptivo transversal mediante la administración del cuestionario al equipo de Enfermería del mencionado hospital (n= 308). Se llevó a cabo un análisis bivariante (t de Student y ANOVA). Resultados: se recogieron 179 cuestionarios. El coeficiente &amp;#61537;de Cronbach fue de 0,925. El análisis factorial exploratorio realizado arrojó cinco dimensiones que explicaban el 67,01% de la varianza. El cuestionario validado se compuso de 21 ítems, que obtuvieron altas puntuaciones (entre 6,60 y 8,33), siendo aquellos relacionados con el trabajo en equipo y con las características individuales del profesional los que puntuaciones más altas obtuvieron. Conclusiones: tras el diseño y validación de un cuestionario sobre barreras y/o dificultades percibidas para el manejo de situaciones violentas, se identificaron como principales dificultades en el manejo: el trabajo en equipo, la formación, los cambios habituales de personal en las unidades o la especificidad de manejo según el paciente. Es preciso continuar el proceso de validación de la herramienta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(2): 19-26, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Barreras y dificultades percibidas para el manejo desituaciones violentas: diseño y validación de un cuestionario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12004^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
