<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128662</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric orbital emphysema caused by a compressed-air pistol shot: A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: We report the case of a 2 year-old child with orbital emphysema secondary to a compressed-air gun shot in the malar region, with no evidence of orbital wall fracture. Conservative treatment was applied, and no complications were observed. Discussion: Orbital emphysema in the absence of an orbital wall fracture is a rare situation. Orbital emphysema is usually seen in facial trauma associated with damage to the adjacent paranasal sinuses or facial bones. To our knowledge there have been very few reports of orbital emphysema caused by a compressed-air injury (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reyes-Dominguez, S. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-León, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Mingorance, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de un escolar de 2 años con un enfisema orbitario tras disparo con pistola de aire comprimido en la región malar. Se aplicó tratamiento conservador y presentó buena evolución sin complicaciones. Discusión: El enfisema orbitario en ausencia de fractura de la pared orbitaria es una entidad muy rara. Normalmente se observa enfisema orbitario asociado a traumatismos que causan fracturas de los senos paranasales o los huesos faciales. En la literatura consultada hay pocos casos de enfisema orbitario secundarios a lesiones producidas por aire comprimido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(9): 373-375, sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfisema orbitario pediátrico secundario a disparo con pistola de aire comprimido: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15347^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4722^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15347^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10096^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19168</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
