<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86725</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between fibrinolytic system and neurological diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The fibrinolytic system, also named plasminogen system is formed by a group of molecules that transforms plasminogen in its active form plasmine, which is able to participate in a number of pathophysiological processes. Aim. To carry out a review of the literature and an analysis of the relationship between fibrinolytic system and neurological  diseases and its potential therapeutic implications.Development. The fibrinolytic system has been involved in many different pathologies. Although its role in neurological  diseases has always been thought to be scarce, many relations have been recently established. This way, fibrinolytic system seems to be involved not only in cerebrovascular diseases but also in epilepsy, inflammatory diseases such as multiple sclerosis, alterations of the dopaminergic system, learning disorders and several lesions of the peripheral nervous system. Different genotypes of several components of this system have been related as risk or protector factors to the development of these neurological diseases and information to this respect is rapidly increasing.  Conclusions. A better knowledge about the relations between the fibrinolytic system and neurological diseases could clarify several aspects about their pathophysiology and it could suppose future prevention and treatment lines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zea, Maria Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, P. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El sistema fibrinolítico, o sistema del plasminógeno, se compone de una serie de moléculas que convierten el plasminógeno en su forma activa plasmina, la cual es capaz de participar en múltiples procesos fisiopatológicos. Objetivo. Realizar una revisión de la bibliografía y analizar la relación entre el sistema fibrinolítico y las enfermedades neurológicas y sus posibles implicaciones terapéuticas al respecto. Desarrollo. El sistema fibrinolítico se ha involucrado en muy diversas patologías. Aunque tradicionalmente se pensaba que su relación con las enfermedades neurológicas era escasa, en los últimos años se han establecido importantes nexos  de unión. De esta forma, el sistema fibrinolítico parece estar involucrado no solamente en enfermedades cerebrovasculares, sino también en la epilepsia, enfermedades neurodegenerativas, como la enfermedad de Alzheimer, enfermedades de perfil inflamatorio, como la esclerosis múltiple, alteraciones del sistema dopaminérgico, trastornos del aprendizaje o enfermedades del sistema nervioso periférico. Diferentes genotipos de los componentes de este sistema se han mostrado como factores protectores o de riesgo para el desarrollo de estas enfermedades, y la información acumulada a este respecto está aumentando sustancialmente.  Conclusiones. Un mayor conocimiento de las relaciones entre el sistema fibrinolítico con las enfermedades neurológicas  podría aclarar ciertos puntos sobre su fisiopatología y también suponer futuras líneas de prevención y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(5): 295-301, sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el sistema fibrinolítico y las enfermedades neurológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30438^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24875^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5453^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
