<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74824</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Access to cervical cytology in Medellín, Colombia during 2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The burden of illness of cervical cancer hasnot decreased enough in developing countries. For that reasonis important to improve coverage, access and effectiveness ofcervical cancer screening programs. The objective of this paperis to analyze women's access to the cervical cytologyprogramme of the Secretary of Health of Medellín (Colombia).Methods: An analysis was made of 1.519 records of womenfrom a cross-sectional study conducted in an urban area ofMedellín (Colombia). Descriptive analysis was conducted and aLogit model was estimated for analysing recent cervical cytology(cytology performed less than 36 months prior to the survey).Results: 68,7% of women had a recent cytology, 17,2%did not have recent cytology and 14,2% of women attended forthe first time to the service. The probability of having a recentcytology increased with age, women with family history ofcervical cancer, women with personal history of sexuallytransmitted infections, women with some education andwomen who are (or were) married or in a stable union.Conclusions: The demand for cytology appears to beconcentrated; a limited number of women assist frequentlywhile others don&#146;t practice it or stop assisting(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Restrepo Zea, Jairo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo Acevedo, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia Arredondo, Marleny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas Zapata, Walter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejía Mejía, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: en países en desarrollo no se han logradosuficientes avances en reducción de la carga de la enfermedadpor cáncer cervical, por lo que es importante mejorar la cobertura,condiciones de acceso y efectividad de los programas detamizaje. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar el acceso realde mujeres usuarias del tamizaje citológico ofrecido por laSecretaría de Salud de Medellín (Colombia).Métodos: se analizaron 1.519 registros de mujeres, provenientesde un estudio transversal realizado en un área urbanade Medellín (Colombia). Se realizó un análisis descriptivo y seestimó un modelo de regresión logística para explicar la prácticade citología reciente (aquélla realizada hace máximo 36meses, previos a la aplicación de la encuesta).Resultados: El 68,7% de las mujeres se habían practicadouna citología recientemente, el 17,2% tenía citologías previaspero no recientes, y el 14,2% era la primera vez que acudíaal servicio. La probabilidad de haberse realizado unacitología reciente es mayor para mujeres con más edad, antecedentefamiliar de cáncer cervical, antecedente personal deinfecciones de transmisión sexual, mujeres con algún grado deeducación y las que se encuentran en unión estable o están (oestuvieron) casadas.Conclusiones: hay indicios de que la demanda por la citologíaestá concentrada, con una buena frecuencia para unnúmero limitado de mujeres, mientras otras no la practican odejan de hacerlo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;81(6): 657-666, nov.-dic.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74824</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accesibilidad a la citología cervical en Medellín, Colombia en 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15029^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
