<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108097</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Suppurative hidradenitis with carcinomatous transformation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hidradenitis Suppurativa or Verneuil´s disease is a chronic inflammatory recurring process that affects the apocrine glands of the armpit, groin, perineal area, scalp and an operineal area. Its accurate ethiology is unknown. It is a rare disease, it is misdiagnosed and its incidence rate is estimated in 1 every 300 adults. It affects mainly women and black race people. However the perianal localization disease affects mainly men. The medical treatment would mitigate the symptoms but most patients have chronic lesions that would require surgical treatment. The squamous cell carcinoma is a rarely reported complication which develops in the chronic lesions of Hidradenitis Suppurativa of long-term evolution. We present a case of a male patient, 51 years old, who has, on old scar lesions, a centrally ulcerated multilobulated tumor formation of 3 months of evolution localized in the left gluteo-perineal area. Complementary methods were used which led to the diagnostics of Hydradernitis Suppurativa with Carcinomatose Transformation (Squamous cellcarcinoma). Surgical treatment followed by skin graft was used with excellent evolution.  The reason for this presentation is the infrequent localization and the unusual complication.  Something important to point out is that publications on this topic are rare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Michelena, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pianzola, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arena, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maradeo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiavassa, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Hidradenitis Supurativa o Enfermedad de Verneuil es un proceso inflamatorio crónico, recurrente que afecta las glándulas apócrinas de axila, ingle, periné, cuero cabelludo y región anoperineal. Se desconoce la etiología precisa. Es una enfermedad poco frecuente, mal diagnosticada, se estima la incidencia en 1 cada 300 adultos. Afecta más a mujeres y personas de raza negra, sin embargo la enfermedad de localización perianal afecta más a varones. El tratamiento médico mitigaría los síntomas pero la mayoría de los pacientes presentan lesiones crónicas que requerirán tratamiento quirúrgico. El Carcinoma de Células Escamosas es una complicación rara vez informada que se desarrolla en las lesiones crónicas de Hidradenitis Supurativa de larga evolución. Presentamos un caso de un paciente de sexo masculino, de 51 años de edad, que presenta sobre antiguas lesiones cicatrizales formación tumoral multilobulada, ulcerada centralmente localizada en región glútea-perineal izquierda de 3 meses de evolución. Se realizaron métodos complementarios arribando al diagnóstico de Hidradenitis Supurativa con Transformación Carcinomatosa (Carcinoma de Células Escamosas). Se realizó tratamiento quirúrgico con posterior injerto cutáneo con excelente evolución. Motiva ésta presentación la localización infrecuente y la complicación inusual. Como dato relevante cabe destacar las escasas publicaciones sobre dicho tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;40(6): 184-190, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hidradenitis supurativa con transformación carcinomatosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29585^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30699^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
