<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055178</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intracranial hemorrhage during pregnancy is a rare complication,    but with high morbidity and mortality. Although the causes    are similar to those in the general population, pregnancy presents    some physiological changes as well as its own pathology    predisposes it to hemorrhage.    The most frequently identified cause is arterial hypertension.    Pre-eclampsia is specific to pregnancy, cerebral hemorrhage    being the first cause of maternal death in the hypertension    induced by pregnancy.    Secondary hemorrhage to a ruptured aneurysm or arteriovenous    malformation is a very serious, although fortunately rare,    complication. Physiological changes in pregnancy may predispose    to the formation, growth and rupture of an aneurysm    On the other hand, secondary hematomas from spinal subdural    anesthesia or accidental puncture of the dural sack during    an epidural anesthesia is not very frequent, but can potentially    cause very serious alterations with significant neurological    deficits. Prolonged headache should be regarded as a warming    sign of subdural hematoma.    This update reviews different aspects related to the etiology,    physiopathology, diagnosis and therapeutic measures of cerebral    hemorrhage in the pregnant patient</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Cortés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Betancor, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemorragia intracraneal durante el embarazo es una complicación    poco frecuente pero con una alta morbilidad y mortalidad.    Aunque las causas de hemorragia son similares a las de la    población general, la embarazada presenta unos cambios fisiológicos    así como una patología propia que pueden predisponer a    las mismas.    La causa más frecuente identificada es la hipertensión arterial.    La preeclampsia es específica de las gestantes, siendo la hemorragia    cerebral la primera causa de muerte materna en la hipertensión    inducida por el embarazo.    La hemorragia secundaria a una rotura de aneurisma o una    malformación arteriovenosa es una complicación grave pero    afortunadamente rara. Cambios fisiológicos asociados al embarazo    predisponen a la formación, crecimiento y rotura del aneurisma.    Los hematomas secundarios a anestesia subaracnoidea o tras    una punción accidental del saco dural durante una anestesia epidural    no es muy frecuente pero pueden provocar graves alteraciones    con déficit neurológicos significativos. La cefalea prolongada    representa un signo de alarma de hematoma subdural.    En este trabajo, revisamos distintos aspectos relacionados con    la etiología, fisiopatología, diagnóstico y las medidas terapéuticas    de la hemorragia intracraneal en la mujer embarazada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;15(2): 83-89, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragias y hematomas intracraneales en el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
