<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AMB-4626</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adequacy of the dietary intake of total and added sugars in the Spanish diet to the recommendations: ANIBES study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The WHO published in 2015 its recommendations for added sugars intake: &lt; 10% of the total energy (TE) intake in both adults and children. No updated information is available in Spain. Objectives: To examine total sugar intake, mainly focused on added, and food and beverage sources. To analize fulfillment with WHO recommendations. Methods: The ANIBES Study of a representative sample of the Spanish population (9-75 yr) was used. Food and beverage records were obtained by a three-day dietary record by using a tablet device. Results: The median total sugar intake was 17% Total TE: 7.3% for added, and 9.6% for the intrinsic sugar intake. Differences were observed for added sugar which was much higher in children and adolescents. For the intrinsic sugar, however, a higher contribution to TE was observed in the elderly. A 58.2% of children fullfill WHO recommndations (&lt; 10% TE), lower for the adolescents (52.6%),and higher for adults (76.7%) and the elderly (89,8%). The mayor sources of total sugar were milk and dairy products (23.2%), non-alcoholic beverages (18.6%), fruits (16.8%) and sugars and sweets (15.1%) and grains (12.0%). The major sources of intrinsic sugars were fruits (31.8%), milks (19.6%), juices and nectars (11.1%), vegetables (9.89%), yogurt and fermented milk (7.18%), low-alcohol-content beverages (4.94%), bread (2.91%), and sugar soft drinks (2.24%). As for free sugars, sources were sugars and sweets (34.1%), non-alcoholic beverages (30.8%, mainly as sugar soft drinks, 25.5%) and grains (19.1%, principally as bakery and pastry, 15.2%). Conclusion: The present study demonstrates that only a moderate percentage of the Spanish population adhered to the present recommendations for total and added sugar intake, and urgent efforts are needed to improve diet quality in the youngest populations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela-Moreiras, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) en el año 2015 recomendó que el consumo de azúcares añadidos se debería reducir a menos del 10% de la ingesta calórica total, pero no hay datos actualizados en España. Objetivos: evaluar la ingesta de azúcares totales, con especial énfasis en los añadidos, sus fuentes alimentarias, y el grado de adherencia a las recomendaciones de la OMS. Métodos: se ha utilizado la muestra ANIBES (9-75 años), representativa de la población española. La estimación de la ingesta ha sido mediante registro de 3 días («Tablet»). Resultados: los hidratos de carbono proporcionan un 41,1% de la energía total consumida (ETC): 24,1% de los almidones, y el 17% del total de azúcares (9,6% para azúcares intrínsecos y el 7,3% a los azúcares añadidos). El aporte de azúcares intrínsecos es mayor en las poblaciones de mayor edad; por el contrario, el consumo de azúcares añadidos es significativamente mayor en edades más tempranas. Un 58,2% de la población infantil cumpliría con la recomendación de la OMS (&lt; 10% ETC), menor para los adolescentes (52,6%), y aumenta la adherencia con la edad: 76,7% (18-64 años) y 89,8% en personas mayores. En cuanto a los azúcares totales, las principales fuentes de la dieta son leche y derivados (23,2%), bebidas sin alcohol (18,6%), frutas (16,8%), azúcares y dulces (15,1%) y cereales y derivados (12,0%). La principal fuente de azúcares intrínsecos fueron las frutas (31,8%), leche (19,6%), zumos y néctares (11,1%), vegetales (9,89%), yogurt y leche fermentada (7,18%), bebidas de bajo contenido alcohólico (4,94%), pan (2,91%), y bebidas azucaradas (2,24%). Para azúcares añadidos: azúcares y dulces (34,1%), bebidas sin alcohol (30,8%, básicamente como refrescos con azúcar, 25,5%) y cereales y derivados (19,1%, un 15,2% como bollería y pastelería). Conclusión: hay diferencias importantes en el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones de la OMS, dependiendo de la edad, por lo que es necesario un especial énfasis y concienciación en población infantil y adolescente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(supl.4): 45-52, 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AMB-4626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de la ingesta de azúcares totales y añadidos en la dieta española a las recomendaciones: estudio ANIBES</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
