<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77439</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Skin Manifestations of Toxic Syndrome Due to Denatured Rapeseed Oil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article offered an extensive description of the clinical and pathological features and time-course of the skin manifestations of toxic syndrome caused by denatured rapeseed oil, also known as toxic oil syndrome. This new condition occurred in Spain in 1981 and was due to the ingestion of rapeseed oil intended for industrial use that had been denatured with anilines and subsequently refined and sold fraudulently as olive oil. In total, 20 000 cases and 400 deaths were reported. The disease affected mainly women, particularly in the late stages. In the acute phase, the predominant skin manifestations were toxic-allergic rashes reminiscent of allergic urticaria in the dermatopathologic study. In approximately 25% of cases, the patients&#146; skin subsequently took on an edematous appearance, with pigmentary abnormalities shown to be related to cutaneous mucinosis. Finally, a characteristic sclerodermatous condition would develop that tended to improve spontaneously. The constant presence of mast cells in all biopsies and the development of mastocytosis in several patients pointed to an important role for these cells in the pathogenesis of the condition. This was subsequently confirmed in other sclerodermatous processes. In 1989, eosinophilia-myalgia syndrome caused by toxins present in tryptophan food supplements was reported in the United States. This syndrome resembled toxic oil syndrome in many ways and demonstrated that mucinosis and toxic sclerodermatous processes do exist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fonseca, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se efectuó una amplia descripción clínico-patológica y cronológica de las manifestaciones cutáneas del síndrome tóxico por aceite de colza adulterado o síndrome tóxico por aceite. Esta nueva enfermedad se produjo en España en 1981, debida a la ingesta de aceite de colza destinado a uso industrial, que había sido coloreado con anilinas y posteriormente decolorado de forma fraudulenta y vendido como aceite de oliva. En total se produjeron unos 20.000 casos y unos 400 fallecimientos. Existía un predominio por el sexo femenino, sobre todo en la fase tardía. En la fase aguda las manifestaciones cutáneas predominantes fueron exantemas toxoalérgicos, con un patrón dermatopatológico de erupción alérgica urticariforme. Alrededor de un 25% de los casos desarrolló posteriormente un aspecto edematoso de la piel, con trastornos de la pigmentación, que demostró estar relacionado con mucinosis dérmica. Finalmente se produjo un cuadro esclerodermiforme peculiar, que tendió a mejorar de forma espontánea. La presencia constante de mastocitos en todas las biopsias y el desarrollo de mastocitosis en varios pacientes sugirieron un papel importante del mastocito en la patogenia del cuadro, que luego ha sido ratificada en otros procesos esclerodermiformes. En 1989 apareció en EE.UU. el síndrome mialgia-eosinofilia, relacionado con sustancias tóxicas presentes en suplementos alimentarios de triptófano y que compartía muchos aspectos con el síndrome tóxico por aceite. Esto corroboró la existencia de mucinosis y cuadros esclerodermiformes de origen tóxico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(10): 857-860, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones cutáneas del síndrome tóxico por aceite de colza adulterado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5656^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22584^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30124^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38058^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19240^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5312^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30651^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
