<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044914</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expenditure on the elderly: the challenge of dependency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes expenditure on social protection in Spain compared with that in other EU countries through the ratio of public expenditure/gross national product according to SEEPROS statistics. The figures for social and health care can be used to estimate total expenditure on the elderly. The results reveal that in Spain total expenditure on social protection is seven points lower and expenditure on the elderly is nearly three points lower than the average for EU countries. The recently published white book on dependency is the starting point for the implementation of a Spanish national law on dependency. The present article focuses on the extra costs generated when a person becomes dependent. Elderly individuals relying only on their pensions are unlikely to be able to afford the costs of long-term care. In addition, current levels of expenditure on long-term care in Spain are much lower than the average for EU countries. This article reviews other Spanish research on public expenditure on long-term care, as this issue is crucial for developing a social protection system for long-term care. It is estimated that public expenditure should increase to about 0.5% of GNP</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montserrat-Codorniu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este articulo describe el esfuerzo financiero en protección social en España comparado con la media de la Unión Europea mediante el indicador del gasto público/PIB según el sistema de estadísticas SEEPROS. El gasto en las funciones vejez y atención sanitaria proporciona datos para estimar el estado actual del esfuerzo financiero público en la atención de las personas mayores. Se pone en evidencia que España está 7 puntos por debajo en el gasto total en protección social y casi 3 puntos por debajo en el gasto público en la función vejez, comparados con la media de la Unión Europea. La aparición del Libro Blanco de la atención a la dependencia inicia el debate para la implantación de un Sistema Nacional de Dependencia. Se describe como la aparición de la dependencia en el individuo genera unos costes adicionales que difícilmente pueden ser afrontados con los niveles actuales de las pensiones; asimismo, el nivel actual de gasto público en la atención a la dependencia es bastante inferior a la media de los países de nuestro entorno. Son objeto de revisión los estudios realizados sobre la estimación del coste de la dependencia, ya que es un dato crucial para que el Estado asuma el reto de un sistema público universal; se estima que es necesario un esfuerzo adicional del gasto público del orden del 0,5% del PIB</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);41(1): 39-47, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El gasto en los mayores: el reto de la dependencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10011^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30355^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
