<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97876</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimally invasive radical prostatectomy: transition from pure laparoscopic to robotic-assisted radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The robotic-assisted laparoscopic approach to radical prostatectomy is increasingly utilized and has become well documented as an effective oncologic treatment modality. In this study, we report the initial experience of a single surgeon at a single institution with robotic-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy (RALP) drawing a comparison to his prior experience with pure laparoscopic prostatectomy (LRP).METHODS: This is a retrospective review of surgical results from a single surgeon performing LRP and transitioning to RALP. Baseline characteristics and outcomes of two hundred seventy five patients undergoing RALP by a single, fellowship-trained, urologic oncologist were analyzed and compared to 45 patients undergoing LRP by the same surgeon. Patient, tumor, and operative characteristics as well as functional outcomes were evaluated. Validated questionnaires, including the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) and International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF), were utilized in the assessment of urinary and sexual parameters. RESULTS: Preoperative patient and tumor characteristics (age, PSA, Gleason score) were similar in both the LRP and RALP groups. Mean operative time (195 vs. 299 minutes), estimated blood loss (223 vs. 299 mL), need for blood transfusion (1.5% vs. 4.4%) and mean length of stay (1.95 vs. 2.63 days) were significantly reduced among patients undergoing RALP as compared to those undergoing LRP. In terms of functional outcomes, continence at 12 months was better among patients undergoing RALP as compared to LRP (94% vs. 82%). In preoperatively potent men undergoing bilateral nerve sparing procedures, RALP conferred 82% potency at 24 months as opposed to only 62% following LRP.CONCLUSIONS: The combination of adjustment in surgical technique from LRP to RALP along with a concurrent institutional commitment to a successful robotic surgery program, has yielded superior operative, oncologic, and functional results(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arturo Colon-Herdman, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heckman, Jennifer E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomella, Leonard G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zola, Joseph C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lallas, Costas D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">RESULTADOS: Las características preoperatorias de los pacientes y de los tumores incluidos (edad, PSA, índice de Gleason) fueron similares en ambos grupos, PRL y PRAR. El tiempo quirúrgico promedio (195 vs 299 minutos), la pérdida estimada de sangre (223 vs 299 ml), la necesidad de transfusión de sangre (1,5% vs 4,4%) y la estancia media (1,95 vs 2,63 días) se redujeron significativamente entre pacientes sometidos a PRAR en comparación con aquellos sometidos a prostatectomía radical laparoscópica. En cuanto a los resultados funcionales, la continencia a los 12 meses fue superior en los pacientes sometidos PRAR con respecto a la PRL (94% vs 82%). Entre aquellos sujetos potentes preoperatoriamente sometidos a procedimientos de preservación neurovascular bilateral, el 82% de los tratados con PRAR mantienen la potencia a los 24 meses en comparación con sólo el 62% de los sometidos a PRL.CONCLUSIONES: La combinación de ajustes en la técnica quirúrgica entre la PRLy la PRAR, junto con un compromiso institucional concurrentes a un exitoso programa de cirugía robótica, ha generado unos resultados funcionales, oncológicos y quirúrgicos superiores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(8): 823-829, oct. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prostatectomia radical minimamente invasiva: transición de laparoscopia pura a laparoscopia asistida por robot</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
