<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111606</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No association between perception of family functioning and treatment modality for chronic renal disease secondary to diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: This work was undertaken with the aim of studying the association between perception of family functioning and mode of medical treatment in Mexicans between 40 and 65 years whose suffer from chronic kidney disease. Material and methods: Participants 37 patients, 22 men, 40 to 65 years of age with chronic renal disease secondary to diabetes mellitus. Patients were assigned to three groups, diet, diet + dialysis and diet + hemodialysis, they responded to four self-administered questionnaires, a demographic questionnaire and three questionnaires to assess family functioning, the Apgar family test, the family functioning perception test, and the scale of Garcia et al. Results: There was no relationship between perception of family functioning of patients with chronic kidney disease secondary to diabetes mellitus and type of medical treatment. Conclusions: The perception of family functioning was not associated with the type of medical treatment of adults with chronic renal failure secondary to diabetes mellitus. The use of various instruments to explore family functioning is important to identify areas to address the psychotherapeutic management of the family (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Alonso, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polina-Carrillo, Rosalinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista de la Cruz, Julieta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kanán-Cedeño, Esther G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Orozco, Alain R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Este trabajo se hizo con el objetivo de estudiar si existe relación entre percepción del funcionamiento familiar y modalidad de tratamiento médico en mexicanos entre 40 y 65 años con enfermedad renal crónica. Material y métodos: Participaron 37 pacientes, 22hombres, entre 40 y 65 años de edad con enfermedad renal crónica secundaria a Diabetes Mellitus. Los pacientes fueron asignados a tres grupos, uno dieta, otro dieta + diálisis y otro dieta + hemodiálisis, estos respondieron a cuatro cuestionarios autoaplicados, uno sociodemográfico y otros tres para estimar funcionamiento familiar, el apgar familiar, la prueba de percepción del funcionamiento familiar FF-SIL y la escala de funcionamiento familiar de García y colaboradores. Resultados: No hubo relación entre percepción del funcionamiento familiar de pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica secundaria a Diabetes mellitus y modalidad de tratamiento médico. Conclusiones: La percepción del funcionamiento familiar no estuvo asociada con el tipo de tratamiento médico de adultos con insuficiencia renal crónica secundaria a Diabetes Mellitus. El uso de varios instrumentos para explorar funcionamiento familiar permite identificar áreas a las que dirigir prioritariamente el manejo psicoterapeútico de estas familias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;41(2): 63-66, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">No asociación entre percepción del funcionamiento familiar y modalidad de tratamiento de la enfermedad renal crónica secundaria a diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50092</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
