<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039016</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">FOXP2: from the specific disorder to the molecular biology of language. II. Implications for the ontogenesis and phylogenesis of language</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cloning FOXP2, the first gene linked to a hereditary variant of specific language impairment (SLI),has allowed researchers to conduct more precise studies into the nature and developmental path of the molecular basesgoverning the organisation and functioning of the neuron centres responsible for language processing. Development. TheFOXP2 gene codes for a transcriptional repressor that regulates the proliferation and/or migration of certain neuronalpopulations in the basal ganglia, cortex, cerebellum and thalamus, and presumably plays a part in the organisation and/orfunctioning of the fronto-thalamic-striatal system. Moreover, the analysis of the developmental history of the gene suggeststhat the transcriptional factor FOXP2, although it is quite old, has undergone certain modifications in its secondary structureand has acquired a potential site for phosphorylation for protein kinase C during the recent developmental history of thehuman species. Conclusions. The evidence discussed in this article allows us to suggest FOXP2 plays a significant role in theontogenetic and phylogenetic development of language. On the one hand, it seems to validate certain general models oflinguistic processing that call for a more important role of the subcortical structures (above all for the basal ganglia) in thatprocessing. On the other hand, it seems to suggest that the modifications undergone by FOXP2 would have also allowedcertain regions (such as Broca&#146;s area) to be recruited for language, either by facilitating the appearance of syntax and/orverbal working memory or by transferring control of articulation to those regions, thereby laying down the foundations for theappearance of spoken language</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Burraco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La clonación de FOXP2, el primer gen ligadoa una variante hereditaria del trastorno específico del lenguaje(SLI), ha permitido indagar de forma más precisa en la naturalezay la trayectoria evolutiva de las bases moleculares de la organizacióny el funcionamiento de los centros neuronales responsablesdel procesamiento lingüístico. Desarrollo. El gen FOXP2 codificaun represor transcripcional que parece regular la proliferación y/ola migración de determinadas poblaciones neuronales de los gangliosbasales, el córtex, el cerebelo y el tálamo, participando presumiblementeen la organización y/o el funcionamiento del sistemafrontotalamoestriatal. Por otra parte, el análisis de la historia evolutivadel gen sugiere que el factor transcripcional FOXP2, a pesarde ser bastante antiguo, ha sufrido una cierta alteración de suestructura secundaria y ha adquirido un sitio potencial de fosforilaciónpara la proteincinasa C durante la reciente historia evolutivade la especie humana. Conclusiones. Las evidencias discutidas enesta revisión permiten aventurar un papel significativo para FOXP2en lo concerniente al desarrollo ontogenético y filogenético del lenguaje.Por un lado, parecen validar determinados modelos generalesde procesamiento lingüístico que reclaman un papel más relevantedurante éste para las estructuras subcorticales (fundamentalmentepara los ganglios basales). Por otro, parecen sugerir que lasmodificaciones experimentadas por FOXP2 habrían permitido adicionalmenteel reclutamiento de determinadas regiones (como elárea de Broca) para el lenguaje, bien facilitando la emergencia dela sintaxis u optimizando el procesamiento fonológico y/o la memoriade trabajo verbal, bien transfiriendo a dichas regiones el controlde la articulación, sentando, en definitiva, las bases para la aparicióndel lenguaje hablado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(1): 37-44, jul. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039016</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">FOXP2: del trastorno específico a la biología molecular del lenguaje. II. Implicaciones para la ontogenia y la filogenia del lenguaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14549^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32752</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
