<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047807</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiotherapy in the prevention of skin metastases in patients with pleural mesothelioma underwent invasive diagnostic and therapeutic processes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malignant seeding of cancer cells by pleuralliquid spreading through the pathway of perforatingdiagnostic and therapeutic procedures is a commoncomplication appearing in patients with malignantpleural mesothelioma.Prophylactic radiotherapy seems to reduce theincidence of chest wall metastases at the incisionsites. However, no agreement has been reachedamong the specialists about its usefulness orefficacy.The purpose of the case we report is to review therole of radiotherapy in preventing the metastaticskin nodules appearing at the sites of invasivediagnostic or therapeutic procedures in patients withmalignant pleural mesothelioma</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu Martínez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Mateu, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las metástasis cutáneas, por difusión de líquidopleural a lo largo de los trayectos de los diferentesprocesos diagnósticos y terapéuticos, es una complicaciónque suele presentarse con cierta frecuenciaen pacientes con mesotelioma pleural maligno.La radioterapia profiláctica parece prevenir laaparición de estas metástasis cutáneas. Sin embargo,no queda bien establecido su utilidad o eficacia paratodos los especialistas.El objetivo de presentar este caso clínico es valorarel papel preventivo o profiláctico que juega laradioterapia en la aparición de los nódulos cutáneostras técnicas invasivas sobre la pared costal de pacientescon mesotelioma, haciendo una revisión dela literatura</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;29(6): 259-262, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioterapia en la prevención de las metástasis cutáneas, en pacientes con mesotelioma pleural, sometidos a procesos diagnósticos y terapéuticos invasivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
