<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128335</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dual-energy contrast-enhanced mammography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The degree of vascularization in breast lesions is related to their malignancy. For this reason, functional diagnostic imaging techniques have become important in recent years. Dual-energy contrast-enhanced mammography is a new, apparently promising technique in breast cancer that provides information about the degree of vascularization of the lesion in addition to the morphological information provided by conventional mammography. This article describes the state of the art for dual-energy contrast-enhanced mammography. Based on 15 months&#146; clinical experience, we illustrate this review with clinical cases that allow us to discuss the advantages and limitations of this technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega Benítez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alayón Hernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luzardo, O. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Travieso Aja, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Es bien conocido que el grado de vascularización de las lesiones mamarias se relaciona con su malignidad. Por ello, las técnicas de diagnóstico por imagen que estudian funcionalmente las lesiones han cobrado mucha relevancia en los últimos años. La mamografía con medio de contraste y energía dual es una técnica de reciente aparición, aparentemente prometedora en el cáncer de mama, que informa del grado de vascularización de la lesión junto con la información morfológica habitual. El propósito de este artículo es presentar el estado actual de esta nueva técnica de imagen. Basándonos en una experiencia de 15 meses, ilustramos esta revisión con casos clínicos que nos permiten presentar también sus ventajas y limitaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(5): 390-399, sept.-oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mamografía con realce de contraste mediante técnica de energía dual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23596^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31805^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
