<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89747</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of adalimumab in patients with Crohn's disease and failure to infliximab therapy: a clinical series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: adalimumab, a human anti-TNF, is an effective induction and maintenance therapy for patients with moderate to severe Crohn&#146;s disease. It seems to be effective in patients with resistance to infliximab, too, though the experience is more limited. Aim: to evaluate the efficacy of adalimumab, in patients with Crohn&#146;s disease (CD) and failure to previous treatment with infli - ximab. Methods: twenty-five patients with CD and failure to previous treatment with infliximab were enrolled; they were treated with 160/80 (24 patients) and 80/40 (1 patient) induction doses. We analyze clinical response to treatment with adalimumab by the Crohn&#146;s disease Activity Index (CDAI) and plasma concentration of C-reactive protein (CRP), steroid sparing and complete fistula closure at week 48. Results: eighteen out of twenty-five patients (72%) achieved clinical remission (CDAI score &lt; 150) at week 24 and 15/25 (60%) patients at week 48. There was a statistically significant difference (p &lt; 0.01) in CRP serum levels from 21 to 8 mg/dl at week 48. Nine out of fifteen patients (60%) treated with corticosteroids were able to discontinue steroids. Three out of eleven patients (27%) with fistulizing Crohn&#146;s disease had complete fistula closure after the treatment. Seventy two percent of the patients (18/25) needed to increase adalimumab to weekly dose, in order to maintain clinical response. Five out of twenty-five patients (20%) had adverse events; two of them (8%) with serious adverse events (tuberculous meningitis and abdominal abscess) that forced the withdrawal of treatment. Conclusions: according to these data, adalimumab provides a clinical and analytical improvement in patients with CD and failure to previous therapy with infliximab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Márquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Rufián, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caunedo Álvarez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Vázquez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrerías Gutiérrez, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero Ruiz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Laria, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: adalimumab, un anti-TNF humano, ha demostrado ser efectivo en la inducción y tratamiento de mantenimiento de la enfermedad de Crohn moderada-grave. Existe menos experiencia, pero este fármaco parece también eficaz en los pacientes con pérdida de respuesta o intolerancia al infliximab. Objetivo: evaluar la eficacia de adalimumab durante un año, en nuestra serie de pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn (EC) y fracaso en el tratamiento previo con infliximab. Métodos: se incluyen 25 pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn y fracaso previo a la terapia con infliximab, que son tratados con adalimumab. Se utilizaron dosis de inducción de 160/80 mg en 24 pacientes y dosis de 80/40 en un paciente. Analizamos la respuesta clínica al tratamiento con adalimumab mediante el Índice de actividad de la enfermedad de Crohn (CDAI) y las concentraciones plasmáticas de proteína C reactiva (PCR), el cese de la corticoterapia y el cierre completo de las fistulas en la semana 48. Resultados: dieciocho de veinticinco pacientes (72%) alcanzan la remisión clínica (CDAI &lt; 150) en la semana 24 y 15/25 pacientes (60%) en la semana 48. Esto se acompañó de un descenso de los niveles de PCR de 21 a 8 mg/l en la semana 48. En nueve de quince pacientes (60%) que tomaban corticoides, se consiguió su retirada. Tres de once pacientes (27%) con enfermedad fistulosa presentaron un cierre completo de las fístulas tras el tratamiento con adalimumab. Un 72% de los pacientes (18/25) necesitaron, a lo largo del seguimiento, acortar el intervalo de tratamiento a una semana para mantener la respuesta. Cinco de veinticinco pacientes (20%) presentan efectos secundarios y en 2 de ellos (8%) fue precisa la retirada del fármaco (meningitis tuberculosa y absceso abdominal). Conclusiones: el tratamiento con adalimumab proporciona una mejoría clínica y analítica en un número significativo de pacientes con EC y fracaso previo a la terapia con infliximab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;103(6): 294-298, jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de adalimumab en pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn y fracaso previo a la terapia con infliximab: resultados de una serie clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30472</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
