<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161443</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of intestinal microbiota in the development of multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a demyelinating disease that affects young adults; in that age group, it represents the second leading cause of disability in our setting. Its precise aetiology has not been elucidated, but it is widely accepted to occur in genetically predisposed patients who are exposed to certain environmental factors. The discovery of the regulatory role played by intestinal microbiota in various autoimmune diseases has opened a new line of research in this field, which is discussed in this review. Development. We reviewed published studies on the role of the microbiota in the development of both MS and its animal model, experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE). In mice, it has been shown that intestinal microorganisms regulate the polarisation of T helper cells from Th1-Th17 up to Th2, the function of regulatory T cells, and the activity of B cells; they participate in the pathogenesis of EAE and contribute to its prevention and treatment. In contrast, evidence in humans is still scarce and mainly based on case-control studies that point to the presence of differences in certain bacterial communities. Conclusions. Multiple evidence points to the role of microbiota in EAE. Extrapolation of these results to MS is still in the early stages of research, and studies are needed to define which bacterial populations are associated with MS, the role they play in pathogenesis, and the therapeutic possibilities this knowledge offers us (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Álvarez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzo-Sola, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La esclerosis múltiple (EM) es una enfermedad desmielinizante que afecta a adultos jóvenes, grupo en que supone la segunda causa de discapacidad en nuestro medio. Su etiología precisa no está dilucidada, pero se acepta que se presenta en pacientes predispuestos genéticamente que se ven expuestos a determinados factores ambientales. El descubrimiento del papel regulador de la microbiota intestinal en diversas enfermedades autoinmunes ha abierto una nueva línea de investigación en este campo, lo que se discute en esta revisión. Desarrollo. Revisamos los estudios publicados acerca del papel de la microbiota en el desarrollo de la EM y su modelo animal, la encefalomielitis autoinmune experimental (EAE). En ratones, se ha demostrado que los microorganismos intestinales regulan la polarización de las células T helper de Th1-Th17 hasta Th2, la función de las células T reguladoras y la actividad de las células B, participando en la génesis de la EAE, así como en su prevención y tratamiento. Por el contrario, en humanos la evidencia es aún escasa, fundamentalmente en base a estudios de casos control que apuntan a la existencia de diferencias en determinadas comunidades bacterianas. Conclusiones. Existe múltiple evidencia del papel de la microbiota en la EAE. La extrapolación de los resultados a la EM está en las primeras fases de investigación, y hacen falta estudios que definan qué poblaciones bacterianas se asocian a la EM, su papel en la patogenia y las posibilidades terapéuticas que esto nos ofrezca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(3): 175-184, abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la microbiota intestinal en el desarrollo de la esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55394^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56119^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23774^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4760^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
