<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040565</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Group A Streptococcus: a study of carrier status. Implications for the diagnostic value of throat culture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Group A streptococcus, Streptococcus pyogenes (SP). is the major cause of acute bacterial pharyngitis in children. Some infected patients remain asymptomatic, acting as healthy carriers.        Objective. Our objective was to examine the carrier rate of SP and its influence on the diagnostic value of throat culture for streptococcal pharyngitis.        Patients and methods. The presence of SP in throat specimens from healthy children ranging in age from 6 months to 14 years in a primary health care center was studied in the summer (n= 185) and in the winter (n= 228). At the same time, children from the same population with clinical signs of pharyngitis were studied in summer (n= 120) and in winter (n= 162). Throats specimens were obtained and cultured in blood agar, and SP was identified by the bacitracin test. The rates of SP in healthy and sick children during the two seasons were compared.        Results. The incidence of SP in healthy individuals was 10wer in the summer than in winter (5.9% versus 17.1 %; p&lt;0.000l). The incidence of SP in children with clinical pharyngitis was also lower in summer than in winter (16.6% versus 29%; p &lt;0.05). Most of the positive cultures in both healthy and ill groups corresponded to the group comprised of 3 to 14year-olds. The difference between the rate of positivity in healthy carriers and the incidence of positive throat cultures in children with clinical signs of pharyngitis was greater in summer than in winter (5.7%/16.6% versus 17.1 %/29%).        Conclusions. The incidence of SP in healthy and ill individuals varies according to season and age. Implications for the diagnostic value of throat culture may exist. since said value decreases as the difference between the two rates is reduced. However, this circumstance does not invalidate the clinical usefulness of throat culture</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fleitas Quintero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piedra Antón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Sánchez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unceta-Barrenechea Aguirre, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuerno Ríos, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Santa María, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El estreptococo del grupo A o Streptococcus pyogenes (SP) es la causa más importante de faringitis aguda bacteriana en la población pediátrica. Algunos pacientes infectados pueden permanecer asintomáticos como portadores sanos.        Objetivo: Analizar la tasa de portadores de SP y su influencia sobre el cultivo faríngeo (CF) para el diagnóstico etiológico de faringitis estreptocócica .        Pacientes y métodos: Se estudió la presencia de SP en muestras de garganta de niños sanos de edades comprendidas entre 6 meses y 14 años, en 185 individuos en verano y 228 en invierno de entre la población adscrita a un centro de atención primaria. De forma simultánea, se estudiaron, de entre esa misma población, 120 individuos con clínica de faringitis en verano y 162 en invierno. Se les efectuó una toma de exudado faríngeo, cultivándose en agar-sangre e identificando S. pygenes mediante el test de la bacitracina. Se compararon las tasas de SP en sanos y enfermos en estas dos épocas del año.        Resultados: La incidencia de S. pyogenes en individuos sanos fue menor en verano que en invierno (5,9-17,1%) (p &lt;0,0001); de igual forma, su incidencia en niños con faringitis fue menor en verano que en invierno (16,6-29%) (p &lt;0,05). En ambos casos, la mayoría de los positivos se encontró en el grupo de 3-14 años. La tasa de portadores se alejó más de la de enfermos con CF positivo a S. pygenes en verano que en invierno (5.7-16,6% frente a 17,1-29%).        Conclusión: La incidencia de S. pyogenes en niños sanos varía en relación con la estación del año y la edad. También varía la tasa de enfermos de faringitis con cultivo faríngeo positivo a este microrganismo. Ello puede suponer implicaciones para la valoración clínica del CF, ya que será de menos valor cuanto más se aproximen ambas tasas. Sin embargo, estas implicaciones no invalidan el cultivo faríngeo como método diagnóstico para el manejo de las faringitis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(9): 358-362, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040565</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estreptococo del grupo A: un estudio sobre el estado de portador. Implicaciones en el valor diagnóstico del cultivo faríngeo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15179^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
