<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163892</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomedical perspective of the surrogate motherhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The subrogated motherhood takes place when an embryo created by in vitro fertilization (IVF) technology is implanted in a surrogate, sometimes called a gestational mother, by means a contract with her. It can imply to natural families (woman and man) with or without infertility problems, or to monoparental or biparental families of the same sex. Concerning the origin of the gametes used in the IVF emerges different implications on the genetic relationship of the resulting child with the surrogate and the future parents. The subrogated motherhood was initially considered an option to solve infertility problems. Nevertheless this practice has become a possible and attractive option as a source of economic resources for poor women. The cases of benefit of a pregnancy without mediating a contract are exceptional and they are not properly cases of &#145;subrogated maternity&#146; but of &#145;altruistic maternity&#146; and must be considered as heterologous in vitro fertilization. In this article are analyzed the medical, genetic and bioethics aspects of this new derivation of the fertilization in vitro. As points of special attention are considered the following questions: Is it the surrogate motherhood used preferably to solve infertility problems? Is not this actually a new form of exploitation of the woman? Does not suppose an attack to the natural family? Does not suppose in addition an attack to the dignity of the human being? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jouve de la Barreda, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La maternidad subrogada se refiere a la implantación de un embrión creado por la tecnología de la fecundación in vitro (FIV) en una madre sustituta, o madre gestante, mediante un contrato con ella. Puede implicar a las familias naturales (mujer y hombre) con problemas de infertilidad o no, o a familias monoparentales o biparentales del mismo sexo. Atendiendo al origen de los gametos usados en la FIV surgen diversas situaciones en la relación genética del niño con la madre gestante y los padres comitentes. La maternidad subrogada se planteó en principio como una opción para solucionar problemas de infertilidad. Sin embargo, se ha convertido en una práctica posible y atractiva como fuente de recursos económicos para mujeres pobres. Los casos de maternidad por acuerdo, sin mediar un contrato, son excepcionales y no son apropiadamente &#145;maternidad subrogada&#146; sino de &#145;maternidad altruista&#146; debiendo ser considerados como casos de fertilización in vitro heteróloga. En este artículo se analizan las indicaciones sobre la utilización de la maternidad subrogada. También se tratan los aspectos médicos, genéticos y bioéticos que plantea esta nueva derivación de la fecundación in vitro. Como puntos de especial atención se plantean una serie de preguntas: ¿Se utiliza preferentemente para solucionar problemas de infertilidad?, ¿No es esto en la práctica una nueva forma de utilización de la mujer?, ¿no supone un atentado a la familia natural?, ¿No supone además un atentado a la dignidad de los seres humanos? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;28(93): 153-162, mayo-ago. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectivas Biomédicas de la maternidad subrogada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37617^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12519^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36320^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
