<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037655</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use os oral anticholinergic therapy in children under 1 years of age with high risk bladder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">THE AIM: To assess the effectiveness and safety of the treatment with oral anticholinergic agents (Oxybutin clorure) in patients under 1 year old, and who aree carriers of high risk bladder secondary to neurological illness as well as no neurological one. MATERIAL AND METHODS: Since 1989, we have indicated treatment with anticholinergic agents to 16 patients: 9 patients had neurogenic bladder secondary to: myelomeningocele (n=7) and sacrocoxigeal teratoma (n=2). Others 7 patients had non neurogenic bladder secondary to: posterior urethral valvulas (n=1), valvula-like syndrome (n=4), post-surgery of neonatal giant bladder diverticulum (n=1) and Prune-Belly syndrome (n=1). The urodinamic study was performed during the first six months of life, being "high risk bladder" defined according to the parameters of compliance vesical and pressure of leak at point (PER). Five of the patients showed neonatal cronic renal failure (CRF), who were treated by cutaneus temporary derivation. All patients at treatment with anticholinergic agents at a 0.2 mg/kg/day dose was established; other early adjunctive treatment prior to the closure of the urinary derivation in children with CRF(n=5); or as a part of the conservative treatment (n=3), alone or associate to intermittent bladder catheterization (IBC) (n=8). During the treatment with anticholinergic agents, the cardiac frequency was controlled by EKG registration in 6 patients, being the rest of the children clinicaly controled (skin colour, mouth dryness, cardiac frequency and intestinal function). RESULTS: In all the cases, the minimum duration of the treatment was one year, until the functional stabilization of the urinary tract. It is to underline the absence of secondary complications which would have caused the suspension or the reduction of the treatment at long term. Conventional studies of urologicals image and urodinamic studies, showed the stabilization of the urinary tract and also the preservation of kidney function and not only was demonstrated in those patients with oral anticholinergic agent as their unique treatment, but also in those patients who had previously been derivated. The previous vesical stabilization allowed the optimum result of subsequent corrective surgeries in five patients (ureteroneocystostomy and vesiscotomy clousure. In cases with previous derivation, the treatment with oral anticholinergic agents made easier vesicostomic clousure in the forth quarter of the first year old wih the maintenance of the vesical stability. CONCLUSIONS: The use of oral anticholinergic agents at a dose of 0.2 mg/kg/day, has resulted to be safe as well as effective in the treatment of high risk bladder in infancy those with less than one year of life. In those patients with serious dysplasia by reflux, it contributes to the preservation of kidney function, it makes easier the early desderivation and it also stabilizes in a functional way the bladder as a previous step to subsequent reconstructive surgeries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aparicio, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañizo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Crespo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrían, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Mialdea, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Evaluar la eficacia y seguridad del tratamiento con anticolinérgicos orales (cloruro de oxibutinina) en pacientes menores de 1 año de edad, portadores de vejiga de alto riesgo secundaria a enfermedad neurológica y no neurológica. Material y Métodos. Desde 1989 hemos indicado tratamiento con anticolinérgicos en 16 pacientes: 9 con vejiga neurógena secundaria a mielomeningocele (n=7) y teratoma sacrococxígeo (n=2), y 7 con vejiga no neurogénica secundaria a válvulas de uretra posterior (n=1), micción no coordinada fetal (n=4), poscirugía de divertículo vesical gigante neonatal (n=1) y síndrome de Prune-Belly (n=1). El estudio urodinámico se realizó durante el primer semestre de vida, definiéndose "vejiga de alto riesgo" según los parámetros de compliance vesical y presión de escape en reposo (PER). Cinco de los pacientes presentaron insuficiencia renal (IR) neonatal que fueron tratados mediante derivación urinaria temporal. En todos los pacientes se instauró tratamiento con  anticolinérgicos a dosis de 0,2 mg/kg/día, bien como tratamiento coadyuvante previo al cierre de la derivación urinaria en los niños con IR (n=5), o bien como parte del tratamiento conservador (n=11), sólo o asociado a cateterización vesical intermitente (CVI) (n=8). Durante el tratamiento con los anticolinérgicos se monitorizó la frecuencia cardíaca mediante registro electrocardiográfico en 6 pacientes siendo el resto de los niños controlados clínicamente (coloración de la piel, sequedad de boca, frecuencia cardíaca y función intestinal). Resultados. En todos los casos, la duración mínima del tratamiento fue de una año, hasta la estabilización funcional del tracto urinario. Es de destacar la ausencia de complicaciones secundarias al uso de anticolinérgicos orales que hayan provocado la suspensión o reducción del tratamiento a largo plazo. Los estudios convencionales de imagen urológicos así como los estudios urodinámicos, han demostrado estabilización del tracto urinario y preservación de la función renal tanto en los pacientes  en los que instauró el anticolinérgico oral como único tratamiento, como en los pacientes que previamente habían derivado. En 5 pacientes la estabilización vesical  previa ha favorecido el resultado óptimo de cirugías correctoras posteriores (ureteroneocistostomía y cierre de vesicostomía). En los casos con derivación previa, el tratamiento con anticolinérgicos orales facilitó la desderivación precoz en el cuarto trimestre de vida con mantenimiento de la estabilidad vesical tras el cierre de la derivación. Conclusiones. Los anticolinérgicos orales a dosis de 0,2 mg/kg/día han resultado seguros y eficaces en el tratamiento de la vejiga de alto riesgo en el lactante menor de un año de vida. En los lactantes con nefropatía grave, contribuyen a la preservación de la función renal, facilitan la desderivación precoz y estabilizan funcionalmente la vejiga como paso previo a cirugías reconstructivas posteriores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;18(1): 3-7, ene. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de anticolinérgicos orales en menores de 1 año portadores de vejiga de alto riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32307^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8505^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32307^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8505^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
