<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039386</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between chronic use of oral fentanyl citrate and teeth decay and loss</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of this study was to determine whether the use of oral fentanyl citrate can be related to teeth decay and loss, and if so, whether such effect can be prevented or minimized. A case seen in our unit is reported. Patients and methods: We studied the case of a 53-years old male admitted in our Pain Clinic that was taking oral fentanyl citrate for the management of chronic pain caused by cervical and lumbar postlaminectomy syndrome and in which teeth decay andloss occurred. Seventy seven patients that were also receiving chronic treatment with the same drug were reviewed in order to determine the frequency and magnitude of this potential association.Results: Dental hygiene of patients did not changed throughout the treatment with oral fentanyl citrate. No other patient developed odontal disorders after the beginning of the treatment. This single patient had a poor dental hygiene. Conclusion: Chronic use of oral fentanyl citrate is a factor that may contribute, although in rare cases, to teeth decay and loss. An appropriate dental hygiene can prevent or at least minimize the impact of chronic use of oral fentanyl citrate on dental health</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo de este estudio ha sido conocer si el uso crónico de citrato de fentanilo oral puede guardar relación con la aparición de caries y con la pérdida de piezas dentales, y deser así, si hubiera forma de evitar o minimizar este efecto, a propósito de la aparición de un caso en nuestra unidad. Pacientes y métodos: Se estudió el caso de un varón de 53 años en tratamientopor nuestra Clínica del Dolor, que tomaba citrato de fentanilo oral para el tratamiento de un dolor crónico en el contexto de un síndrome postlaminectomía cervical y lumbar, y en el que aparecieron varias caries y pérdida de piezas dentales. Se revisaron los 77 pacientes a los que en la actualidad, también tratábamos de forma crónica con este fármaco, para estudiar la frecuencia y magnitud de esta posible asociación. Resultados: La higiene dental de los distintos pacientes no varió durante el tratamiento con citrato de fentanilo oral. La existencia de trastornos odontógenos añadidos con posterioridad al inicio del tratamiento, no apareció en ningún otro caso. Este único paciente presentaba un aseo dental defectuoso. Conclusión: El uso crónico de citrato de fentanilo oral es un factor que puede contribuir, aunque de forma infrecuente, a la aparición de caries y pérdida de piezas dentarias. Una adecuada higiene dental podría evitar, o al menos minimizar, larepercusión del uso crónico de citrato de fentanilo oral sobre la salud dentaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(3): 154-157, abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación del uso crónico del citrato de fentanilo oral con la aparición de caries y pérdida de piezas dentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14460^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29135^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
