<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166515</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgery in times of crisis: conservative treatment of pectus carinatum by static corset</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Dynamic compression system is the elective treatment for chondrogladiolar pectus carinatum. Nevertheless, its high cost poses a problem for its prescription in places where it is not subsidized. This article analyzes the experience of the Paediatric Plastic Surgery Service at a third grade hospital in the treatment of this deformity with a static compression system. Materials and methods. The study presents a descriptive, retrospective analysis of 30 patients with pectus carinatum treated with a static compression system. Furthermore, we describe the protocol of treatment used at our unit, and we analyse the satisfaction with bracing therapy, and its relation to therapeutic compliance. Results. The study includes 28 boys and 2 girls. 93% of the patients presented a chondrogladiolar pectus carinatum. At the moment of finishing the study, 11 patients have completed the treatment, 14 still bracing, and 5 were lost in the follow-up. Satisfaction questionnaires were answered by 19 patients. Conclusion. Bracing therapy with static compression system is the treatment of choice for chondrogladiolar pectus carinatum in our unit, because of its effectiveness and lower price. Quality of life questionnaires show better marks in patients that are in the second phase of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Muñoz, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Carrera, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fraile, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Sedano, JV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El corsé de compresión dinámica constituye el tratamiento de elección de las formas condrogladiolares de pectus carinatum. Sin embargo, su elevado coste supone un problema para su prescripción en las comunidades en las que no se encuentra subvencionado. El presente trabajo analiza la experiencia de la Unidad de Cirugía Plástica Infantil de un hospital terciario en el manejo de esta patología mediante tratamiento ortopédico con corsé de compresión estática. Material y métodos. Se realiza un estudio descriptivo, de carácter retrospectivo, de 30 pacientes afectos de pectus carinatum tratados mediante ortesis estática. Además, se expone el protocolo de actuación de la unidad, y se analiza la satisfacción de los pacientes con el tratamiento, y su relación con la adherencia terapéutica. Resultados. La muestra incluye 28 varones y 2 mujeres. El 93% de los pacientes presentaban una malformación de tipo condrogladiolar. En el momento de finalización del estudio, 11 pacientes habían completado la terapia, 14 continuaban en tratamiento, y 5 fueron pérdidas en el seguimiento. Las encuestas de satisfacción pudieron ser realizadas a 19 pacientes. Conclusión. La terapia con corsé de compresión estática resulta eficaz, con un coste asociado más bajo al de la terapia dinámica, convirtiéndose en el tratamiento de referencia de nuestra unidad. Los cuestionarios de calidad de vida empleados muestran mejores puntuaciones en pacientes en fase de mantenimiento, respecto a pacientes en fase de corrección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(2): 83-88, abr. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía en tiempos de crisis: tratamiento conservador del pectus carinatum mediante corsé estático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55559^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
