<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152777</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the perception of risk in the nursing staff in care of patients with suspected biological hazard</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Healthcare personnel is especially vulnerable to the risks derived from their job. The complexity that has the care of patients with Ebola justifies the study of the perception of risk of such professionals. Objective. To know the perception of risk in the nursing staff that takes care of patients suspected of suffering the Ebola virus. Material and methods. Transversal study carried out in the Hospital Clínic of Barcelona. 19 professionals of nursing staff that attended suspected Ebola patients were included in the study. The data was collected through a questionnaire of dimensional evaluation of the perceived risk along with sociodemographic variables and a subsequent statistics analysis. Results. A percentage of 68 % of the nursing staff refereed having a high level of knowledge of the risk associated with the factor of this study. A percentage of 42 % determined that there was a very high possibility of being harmed. A percentage of 63 % considered that the most harmful consequences would appear in short term, and finally a percentage of 48 % considered that there was a very high risk of accident or illness associated to the factor of this study, whereas a percentage of 5 % considered the risk to be very low. Conclusions. The answers obtained showed not only that nursing staff had a very high level of knowledge regarding the risk associated to the factor of this study, but also that the emotional fear was very high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez Mora, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moragas Bayés, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ruiz, M José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert Cases, Ángels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornieles Moreira, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau Giner, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El personal sanitario es una población especialmente vulnerable a los riesgos derivados del ejercicio de su profesión. La complejidad que tiene la atención de los pacientes con virus Ébola lleva al estudio de la percepción de riesgo de este colectivo. Objetivo. Conocer la percepción de riesgo en el personal de enfermería que atendió a los pacientes con sospecha de Fiebre Hemorrágica Virus Ébola (FHVE). Material y métodos. Estudio transversal realizado en el Hospital Clínic de Barcelona. Se incluyeron 19 profesionales de enfermería que atendieron directamente a pacientes con sospecha de FHVE. Los datos se recogieron mediante un cuestionario de evaluación dimensional del riesgo percibido junto a variables sociodemográficas y un posterior análisis estadístico. Resultados. Un 68 % del personal de enfermería refirió tener un nivel de conocimiento elevado del riesgo asociado al factor de estudio. Un 42 % determinó que había una posibilidad muy alta de experimentar un daño. Un 63 % apreció que las consecuencias más nocivas se experimentarían a corto plazo y, finalmente, un 48 % valoró que había un riesgo muy alto de accidente o enfermedad asociado al factor de estudio, frente a un 5 % que lo valoró muy bajo. Conclusiones. Las respuestas obtenidas ponían de manifiesto que los profesionales de enfermería poseían un nivel de conocimiento muy alto sobre el riesgo asociado al factor de estudio, y que el temor emocional era también muy elevado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(5): 320-325, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la percepción de riesgo en el personal de enfermeraí en la atención de pacientes sospechosos de riesgo biológico IV</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53400^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53400^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32733^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32733^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
