<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77648</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical experience with tigecycline in the treatment of nosocomial infections caused by isolates exhibiting prevalent resistance mechanisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the clinical experience with tigecyclinein the treatment of infections caused by microorganismswith prevalent resistance mechanisms amongnosocomial microbiota, as methicillin-resistant Staphylococcusaureus, vancomycin-resistant enterococci, multidrug-resistant Acinetobacter baumannii and enterobacteriaproducing extended spectrum ß-lactamases. Mostof articles found in the literature describe the use of tigecyclinein the treatment of severe infections (sepsisand septic shock, nosocomial pneumonia and ventilador-associated pneumonia&#133;) produced by multidrug-resistantmicroorganisms, in patients with multiple comorbidities(admitted in ICU, with malignancies, transplantsand/or immunodepressed&#133;) and in many occasions afterfailures of previous antibiotic treatments. Favourableoutcomes with tigecycline are reported in most articles.However, an accurate global assessment is difficult since,in addition to the described confounding factors, thereare concomitant or sequential antibiotic treatments inseveral communications, and lack of relevant clinical (ascomorbidities), microbiological (as susceptibility) andoutcome (different criteria by different authors) data inothers. More even, the described series are retrospectiveand lack of control groups. Nevertheless the usefulnessof this revision is based on the fact that in daily clinicalpractice the use of tigecycline will increase, since epidemiologyof specific hospital medical units shows multidrugresistance among nosocomial isolates and tigecy cline can be one of the scarce available compounds activeagainst multidrug-resistant strains/clones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barberán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rey, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo incluye una revisión de la experiencia clínicacon tigeciclina en infecciones por microorganismos con losfenotipos de resistencia más prevalentes en la microbiotanosocomial, como Staphylococcus aureus resistente a lameticilina y enterococos resistentes a la vancomicina dentrode los gram positivos, y Acinetobacter baumannii multirresistentey enterobacterias productoras de betalactamasasde espectro extendido dentro de los gram negativos nosocomiales.La mayoría de los artículos encontrados en la literaturadescriben la utilización de la tigeciclina en el tratamientode infecciones graves (sepsis y shock séptico,neumonía nosocomial y neumonía asociada a ventilaciónmecánica, etc.) producidas por estos microorganismos multirresistentes,en pacientes que presentan comorbilidadesgraves (pacientes ingresados en la unidad de cuidados intensivos(UCI), oncológicos, inmunodeprimidos, etc.) y enmuchas ocasiones tras el fracaso de otros tratamientos. Apesar de estas circunstancias, tigeciclina presenta unos datosde eficacia favorables. Hacer una evaluación global precisaresultaría muy difícil, ya que aparte de los factores deconfusión descritos, se añade la presencia de tratamientosantibióticos concomitantes o secuenciales, así como la faltaen algunas comunicaciones de datos clínicos (como comorbilidades),microbiológicos (como sensibilidad antibiótica) yde respuesta terapéutica (como criterios de valoración distintospor distintos autores) relevantes. Por otra parte lasseries son retrospectivas sin grupo control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;22(1): 48-56, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia clínica con tigeciclina en el tratamiento de infecciones nosocomiales producidas por aislados con mecanismos de resistencia prevalentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30068^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30068^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30068^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
