<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94525</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ustekinumab in a patient with Crohn's disease and anti-TNF-¦Á-induced psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Treatment with anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-¦Á for Crohn's disease is relatively safe, although various cutaneous adverse effects have been reported such as the development or exacerbation of anti-TNF- ¦Á-induced psoriasis, which can sometimes lead to treatment withdrawal. Therefore, new alternative treatments with new mechanisms of action are required. Ustekinumab, a monoclonal antibody against the p40 subunit of interleukin 12/23, could induce response in patients with Crohn's disease and has demonstrated efficacy in patients with psoriasis. We present the case of a woman with Crohn's disease who developed psoriasis after treatment with two anti-TNF- ¦Á drugs (infliximab and adalimumab). The patient was subsequently treated with ustekinumab with resolution or psoriasis lesions and maintenance of remission of Crohn's disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Royo Escosa, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanso Sureda, Andres</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sapiña Camaro, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocamora Duran, Vicenç</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosque Lopez, Maria Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento con farmacos antifactor de necrosis tumoral alfa (TNF-¦Á) en la enfermedad de Crohn es relativamente seguro aunque se han comunicado diferentes efectos secundarios cutaneos como la aparicion o exacerbacion de una psoriasis secundaria al tratamiento con anti-TNF-¦Á que, en ocasiones, puede llevar a la suspension del tratamiento. Por ello, son necesarias nuevas alternativas terapeuticas con nuevos mecanismos de accion. Se ha publicado que ustekinumab, un anticuerpo monoclonal que se une a la subunidad p40 de la interleucina 12/23, podrea inducir repuesta en pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn y ademas ha demostrado su eficacia en pacientes con psoriasis. Presentamos un caso de una paciente con enfermedad de Crohn que desarrollo psoriasis tras el tratamiento con 2 farmacos anti-TNF-¦Á (infliximab y adalimumab) que fue posteriormente tratada con ustekinumab con resolucion de las lesiones de la psoriasis y mantuvo la remision de la enfermedad de Crohn (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(8): 546-550, Oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94525</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ustekinumab en paciente con enfermedad de Crohn y psoriasis inducida por anti-TNF-¦Á</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
