<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043542</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Generalized eruptive histiocytoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 64-year-old male who developed multiple asymptomatic papules over a four-month period, distributed symmetrically on the trunk and proximal regions of the limbs, while the scalp, palms, soles and mucous membranes were spared. The lesions were discrete papules, brownish-erythematous, rounded, ranging from slightly raised to hemispherical, from 1 to 3 mm in diameter and firm to the touch. Clinical, histopathological, immunohistochemical and ultrastructural studies were consistent with generalized eruptive histiocytoma. Laboratory tests and radiological studies did not show any abnormal findings. After being subjected to photochemotherapy, the lesions regressed, but later on new outbreaks of papules appeared. Generalized eruptive histiocytoma belongs to a spectrum of diseases that may overlap; some may even develop into others. As the disease may progress into a more serious ailment, regular checkups with clinical, histological and immunohistochemical examinations should definitely be considered</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Blanco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peteiro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un varón de 64 años que desarrolló, a lo largo de un periodo de 4 meses, múltiples pápulas asintomáticas distribuidas simétricamente por el tronco y las regiones proximales de las extremidades, respetando cuero cabelludo, palmas, plantas y mucosas. Las lesiones eran discretas, eritematoparduscas, redondeadas, desde ligeramente elevadas a hemisféricas, de 1 a 3 mm de diámetro, y firmes al tacto. Los estudios clínicos, histopatológicos, inmunohistoquímicos y ultraestructurales fueron de histiocitoma eruptivo generalizado. Las pruebas de laboratorio y los estudios radiológicos no mostraron hallazgos anormales. Tras someterse a fotoquimioterapia, las lesiones remitieron, pero más adelante aparecieron nuevos brotes de pápulas. El histiocitoma eruptivo generalizado pertenece a un espectro de enfermedades que pueden solaparse e incluso progresar las unas a las otras. Puesto que la enfermedad podría progresar hacia una dolencia más grave, habría que considerar seriamente revisiones regulares con exámenes clínicos, histológicos e inmunohistoquímicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;97(1): 35-38, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitoma eruptivo generalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8434^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28151^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28151^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
