<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82690</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inherited aplastic anemias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The inherited aplastic anaemias are a heterogeneous group of disorders characterized by bone marrow failure, frequent association with one or more somatic anomalies and increased risk of cancer. They are rare disorders, usually diagnosed at paediatric age, and have significant premature mortality.The authors report 11 cases of inherited aplastic anaemias, 8 of Fanconi&amp;#8242;s anaemia and 3 of Dyskeratosis congenita. These cases were diagnosed in the last 14 years in the Dona Estefânia Hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteves, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las aplasias medulares congénitas constituyen un grupo heterogéneo de enfermedades que se caracterizan por insuficiencia medular, asociadas frecuentemente a una o más anomalías somáticas y con riesgo elevado de neoplasias. Son enfermedades raras, generalmente diagnosticadas en la edad pediátrica, y con una mortalidad prematura importante.Los autores presentan 11 casos de aplasia medular congénita, 8 de anemia de Fanconi y 3 de disqueratosis congénita. Estos casos fueron diagnosticados en los últimos 14 años en el Hospital de Dona Estefânia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(2): 84-87, ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82690</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplasias medulares congénitas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22434^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33362^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5303^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22542^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
