<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158911</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of light overloads on countermovement vertical jump performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to determine the effect of different light overloads on the vertical impulse, velocity of center of mass and peak power during two consecutive maximum vertical jumps. 28 athletes practicing different sports where vertical jump is a basic skill have participated. A force platform, operating at 500 Hz, temporally synchronized to a video camera, which recorded at 210 Hz the sagittal plane of the jumps were used for the analysis. The results have shown that when overloads of 7,5% of body weight  were used , the time used for the counter- phase increased. The vertical impulse and peak power did not vary with the use of different levels of light overloads used in this study, however, the take-off velocity the CM was reduced with a similar percentage that increased the overload (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Dávila, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giles, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este estudio ha sido determinar el efecto de diferentes sobrecargas ligeras sobre el impulso vertical, la velocidad del centro de masas y el máximo pico de potencia, durante la realización de dos saltos verticales máximos consecutivos. Han participado 28 deportistas practicantes de modalidades deportivas donde el salto vertical constituye una habilidad básica. Se ha utilizado una plataforma de fuerza, operando a 500 Hz, sincronizada temporalmente a una cámara de vídeo, que registraba a 210 Hz el plano sagital de los saltos realizados sobre la plataforma. Los resultados indican que, cuando se utilizan sobrecargas del 7,5% del peso corporal, el tiempo utilizado durante la fase de contramovimiento se incrementa. El impulso vertical y el pico de potencia no varían con el uso de los diferentes niveles de las sobrecargas utilizadas, sin embargo, la velocidad de despegue se reduce un porcentaje similar al incremento de la carga (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;16(64): 633-648, dic. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158911</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de sobrecargas ligeras sobre el rendimiento del salto vertical con contramovimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14532^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
