<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94979</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection and specific studies in procedural learning difficulties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. The main disabilities in non-verbal learning disorder (NLD) are: the acquisition and automating of motor and cognitive processes, visual spatial integration, motor coordination, executive functions, difficulty in comprehension of the context, and social skills. Aims. To review the research to date on NLD, and to discuss whether the term &#145;procedural learning disorder&#146; (PLD) would be more suitable to refer to NLD. Development. A considerable amount of research suggests a neurological correlate of PLD with dysfunctions in the &#145;posterior&#146; attention system, or the right hemisphere, or the cerebellum.  Even if it is said to be difficult the delimitation between NLD and other disorders or syndromes like Asperger syndrome, certain characteristics contribute to differential diagnosis. Intervention strategies for the PLD must lead to the development of motor automatisms and problem solving strategies, including social skills. Conclusions. The basic dysfunction in NLD affects  to implicit learning of routines, automating of motor skills and cognitive strategies that spare conscious resources in daily behaviours. These limitations are partly due to a dysfunction in non-declarative procedural memory. Various dimensions of language are also involved: context comprehension, processing of the spatial and emotional indicators of verbal language, language inferences, prosody, organization of the inner speech, use of language and non-verbal communication; this is why  the diagnostic label &#145;PLD&#146; would be more appropriate, avoiding the euphemistic adjective &#145;non-verbal&#146; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Magallón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narbona, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. Los déficit que caracterizan el trastorno de aprendizaje no verbal (TANV) afectan a la automatización de procedimientos motores y cognitivos, la integración visuoespacial, la coordinación motora, las funciones ejecutivas, la comprensión contextual y las habilidades sociales. Objetivos. Revisar el estado de la cuestión del TANV y justificar la mayor adecuación del término &#145;trastorno de aprendizaje procesal&#146; (TAP) para referirse a este trastorno. Desarrollo. Aunque los límites entre el TANV y otros trastornos o síndromes como el síndrome de Asperger son a veces difusos, ciertas características  específicas contribuyen al diagnóstico diferencial. Numerosas investigaciones sugieren, en cuanto a su correlato neurológico, disfunciones del sistema atencional &#145;posterior&#146;, hemisferio derecho, y cerebelo. Los recursos de intervención en el TAP deben ir encaminados al entrenamiento de los automatismos motores y de las estrategias de resolución de problemas. Conclusiones. La disfunción básica que subyace al TANV es una dificultad para el aprendizaje implícito de rutinas, de la automatización de procesos motores y de estrategias cognitivas que facilitan gran parte de las conductas habituales ahorrando costo de recursos  conscientes. Estas limitaciones se deben en parte a una disfunción en la memoria procedimental. Además, diversas dimensiones del lenguaje están afectadas: comprensión contextualizada, procesamiento de los indicadores espaciales y emocionales en la producción verbal, realización de inferencias lingüísticas, organización del discurso, prosodia, uso del lenguaje y comunicación gestual, entre otras; de este modo, quedaría justificado evitar el adjetivo &#145;no verbal&#146; en la denominación de esta  agrupación sindrómica y adoptar la etiqueta diagnóstica de &#145;TAP&#146; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(supl.2): 71-76, feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección y estudios específicos en el trastorno de aprendizaje procesal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
