<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123621</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurses and action policy: a historical and current lack</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Both in the past and at present, we see a very weak presence of nurses both in Spanish Parliament and in the parliaments of the seventeen autonomous communities that constitute the kingdom of Spain. The present study, focused on the current legislature (X Legislature, 2011-2015), aims to give the exact number of deputies nurses in each of the mentioned legislative chambers, and size their position in them and identify their coordinates of identity, gender, age, educational qualification and political party they belong to, in order to specify the exact percentages of participation of nurses. The conclusion of this research presents a picture so bleak that has been diagnosed, quite rightly, as «political anorexia of the nurse power» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ávila Olivares, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tanto en tiempos pasados como en la actualidad, se constata una muy precaria presencia de enfermeros tanto en las Cortes Generales como en los parlamentos de las diecisiete autonomías que constituyen el reino de España. El presente trabajo, centrado en la actual legislatura (X Legislatura 2011-2015), se propone dar a conocer el número exacto de diputados enfermeros en cada una de las cámaras legislativas mencionadas, así como dimensionar su posicionamiento en las mismas e identificar sus coordenadas de identidad, sexo, edad, titulación académica y partido político al que pertenecen, para pasar a establecer los porcentajes exactos de participación de los profesionales de enfermería. La conclusión de esta investigación presenta un panorama tan desolador que ha sido diagnosticado, con toda razón, como «la anorexia política del poder enfermero» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(5): 374-377, mayo 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermeros y acción política. Una carencia histórica y actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36465</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
