<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77812</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the reasons for visits to a Neurology office in Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In recent years, the out-patient neurologicaldemand has been growing constantly. Many studies exist on thecharacteristics of this in our country. However, up to date, noneof them have been made in the Principality of Asturias. We haveproposed to learn the characteristics of the out-patient neurologicalcare in our area and consequently to contribute to an improvementin medical care planning.Patients and methods. The requests for consultation receivedwere collected prospectively over 18 months. Annual demandwas calculated using the population data. One thousandpatients were finally included in the study. The following datawere gathered: age, gender, origin, reason for consultation, anddestination.Results. Demand for first visits was 11.94 per 1.000 inhabitants/year. Average age was of 62.04 years, the highest publishedto date. More women (59 %) than men consulted. The mostfrequent age range was 75-80 years. Headache was the mostcommon condition. Cognitive problems were the most commonone in patients over 65 years. Non-neurological problems werethe third reason for consultation. A total of 50.4% of the patientswere not given an appointment for follow-up.Conclusions. Mean age of the patients seem in Neurologyseems to be progressively increasing and consequently, consultationsfor cognitive problems, which together with headaches, arethe most frequent reason of consultation. A high percentage ofnon-neurological conditions can be related with a high percentageof discharges (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado Menéndez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los últimos años, la demanda neurológica ambulatoriaha ido creciendo constantemente. Existen numerosos estudiossobre las características de la misma en nuestro país, pero hastaahora ninguno realizado en el Principado de Asturias. Nos planteamosconocer las características de la asistencia neurológica ambulatoriaen nuestra área y con ello contribuir a una mejor planificaciónde la asistencia sanitaria.Pacientes y métodos. Se recogen de modo prospectivo las peticionesde consulta recibidas durante 18 meses. Con los datos de poblaciónse calcula la demanda anual. Se incluyen 1.000 pacientes enel estudio, de los cuales se recogen los siguientes datos: edad, sexo,procedencia, motivo de consulta y destino.Resultados. La demanda de primeras visitas se situó 11,94 por1.000 habitantes/año. La edad media fue de 62,04 años, la más altapublicada hasta la fecha. Consultaron más mujeres (59%) que hombres.El rango de edad más frecuente estuvo entre 75 y 80 años.La patología más frecuente fue la cefalea. En los enfermos mayoresde 65 años, lo fueron los problemas cognitivos. Como tercer motivo deconsulta se sitúa la patología no neurológica. Un 50,4% de los pacientesno fue citado para revisiones posteriores.Conclusiones. La edad media de los pacientes que acuden aNeurología parece ir aumentando de modo progresivo, y, consecuentemente,las consultas por problemas cognitivos, que, junto a las cefaleas,son el motivo de consulta más frecuente. Existe un importanteporcentaje de patología no neurológica que puede estarrelacionado con un elevado número de altas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(5): 309-314, jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77812</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los motivos de consultaen una consulta de Neurología de áreaen Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
