<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138725</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term cognitive déficits in patients operated on for cerebral aneurysm by craniotomy and clipping</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. An important number of patients continue to present cognitive disorders after cerebral aneurysm surgeries, not only within the acute phase but also years after the subarachnoid hemorrhage and in spite of their good functional recovery. Goals. The percentage of patients who continues to present cognitive alterations after 4 years of cerebral aneurysm surgery is studied within a sample of people who had pterional craniotomy and ICA clipping (Intracranial Aneurysm Clips). The repercussions on their daily life activities and quality of life are also considered and we analyze how are these deficits related to the cerebral location of the aneurysm. Sample and Method. Twenty-nine adults of both sexes, without cognitive disorder or psychiatric precedents who had an aneurysm surgery in different cerebral locations. Results and conclusions. All the patients were independent in their daily life activities. The majority of the patients had good neurological resolution four years after the surgery and their cognitive performances were within the normality. Nevertheless, there is a small group that continues to present cognitive performances below what was expected for their age and educational level. The performances in cognitive tasks of attention, temporalspatial orientation, visual naming, memory, auditory verbal learning, visual-constructive skills and executive function do not depend on the cerebral location of the aneurysm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ladera Fernández, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Bartolomé, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maillo Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existe un número importante de pacientes que tras ser intervenidos de un aneurisma cerebral presentan alteraciones cognitivas tanto en la fase aguda como años después de la hemorragia subaracnoidea y a pesar de su buena recuperación funcional. Objetivos. En este trabajo se estudia el porcentaje de pacientes que presentan alteraciones cognitivas 4 años después de ser intervenidos de un aneurisma cerebral con un mismo abordaje quirúrgico (craneotomía pterional y clipaje), así como sus repercusiones en las actividades de la vida diaria y calidad de vida. Se analiza también si estos déficits están relacionados con la localización cerebral del aneurisma. Pacientes y métodos. Veintinueve sujetos adultos de ambos sexos, sin antecedentes de trastorno cognitivo ni psiquiátrico previo, intervenidos de un aneurisma de diferente localización cerebral. Resultados y conclusiones.Todos los pacientes son independientes para llevar a cabo sus actividades de la vida diaria. La mayoría de los pacientes con buena resolución neurológica, a los 4 años después de la cirugía, presentan rendimientos cognitivos dentro de la normalidad. Sin embargo, existe un pequeño grupo que continúa presentando rendimientos cognitivos por debajo de lo esperado para su edad y nivel educacional. Los rendimientos en tareas cognitivas de atención, orientación temporoespacial, denominación visual, memoria, aprendizaje auditivo verbal, habilidades visuoconstructivas y función ejecutiva no dependen de la localización cerebral del aneurisma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(6): 379-385, jul.-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficits cognitivos a largo plazo en pacientes intervenidos de un aneurisma cerebral mediante craneotomía y clipaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3415^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
