<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057445</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The excesive intake of macronutrients: does it influence the sportive performances of young cyclists?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose was to determine whether 34 young        Spanish males belonging to a cyclist team, follows the        optimal macronutrients intake based on the recommended        dietary guidelines. The deficits in nutrition jeopardise        the sportive performances, but what about the        diets with excessive intake of macronutrients? Furthermore,        is there an association between their sportive        achievements and the psychological profile? Surely, but        the problem is to determine which psychological variables        are involved.        Method: Nutritional evaluation based on Nutrients intake        questionnaire of 7 consecutive days.        Results: Cyclists consume an excessive quantity of        proteins and lipids in their diets. The average consumption        of proteins is 16,36% of their caloric intake (the recommended        quantity is less than 10%). The average        consumption of fats is 38,71% (the recommended is less        than 30%).        The same tendency is found in the homologous Spanish        young people of the enKID study, where the percentage        of energy from fat and saturated fat is much higher        than the recommended one.        The cyclists consume insufficient quantities of carbohydrates        (average is 44, 94% of their caloric intake,        the recommended is more than 60%), therefore the reload        of their glycogen stores may not be complete on each        competition stage.        No association has been found between the excessive        intake of referred macronutrients and the achieved        sport performances.        Conclusion: This work contributes to the knowledge        of the diets of very active young cyclists. Excessive intake        of proteins and fats do not jeopardise their sportive performances. The commonly studied psychological variables        in sport, are not determinant of sportive achievements        of young cyclists; additional work is needed to determine        the psychological profile playing a determinant        role in success of young cyclists</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Soriano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Benito, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito ha sido determinar si un equipo de 34 ciclistas        españoles jóvenes sigue las pautas recomendadas        en la ingesta de macronutrientes.        El déficit nutricional pone en peligro el rendimiento        deportivo, pero ¿Qué pasaría con las dietas con excesivo        contenido de proteínas y grasas? Mas aún ¿Existe una        relación entre el rendimiento deportivo y el perfil psicológico?        Seguramente es así pero el problema está en determinar        las variables psicológicas involucradas en dicha        asociación.        Método: Evaluación nutricional basada en la ingesta        reportada en un cuestionario de 7 días consecutivos.        Resultados: Los ciclistas estudiados consumen una        cantidad excesiva de proteínas (16,36% de la energía,        mientras que lo recomendado es menos del 10%) y de        grasas (38,71% de la energía, mientras que lo recomendado        es menos del 30%).        Esta tendencia es similar a la seguida por los jóvenes        españoles del estudio EnKID donde se muestra que el        consumo de grasas y en articular de grasas saturadas es        excesivo.        Contrariamente su ingesta media de hidratos de carbono        es insuficiente (44,94% , mientras que lo recomendado        es más del 60%) con lo cual sus depósitos de glucógeno        pueden no estar al máximo de su capacidad. No se        ha observado una asociación entre la excesiva ingesta de        macronutrientes citados y las prestaciones deportivas.        Conclusión: Este trabajo ayuda a conocer los hábitos        alimentarios de jóvenes muy activos físicamente.        Se muestra que el consumo excesivo de proteínas y        grasas no perjudica el rendimiento deportivo de estos        jóvenes estudiados. Las variables psicológicas comúnlemente        estudiadas para deportistas, no son suficientes        para explicar los resultados deportivos de jóvenes ciclistas.        Estudios adicionales son necesarios para identificar        las variables psicológicas que sean más representativas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(4): 461-470, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La excesiva ingesta de macronutrientes: ¿influye en el rendimiento deportivo de jóvenes ciclistas?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d600^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24379^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29598^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
