<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045673</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of the surgical treatment for severe epistaxis by endoscopic approach of sphenopalatine and ethmoidal arteries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To evaluate the efficacy and cost-effectiveness        of the treatments used for controlling epistaxis, particularly        compared with the surgical endoscopic ligation or        cauterization of sphenopalatine (SP) and anterior ethmoid        (AE) arteries, a intervention prospective-retrospective study        is presented with the aim of assessing the feasibility of these        surgical techniques as an alternative to conventional treatments.        Patients and methods: 184 consecutive patients admitted        in the ENT ward between the years 1997 and 2005 were        included in the study, and distributed into three groups depending        on the last treatment applied to control their bleeding:        AP group.- anterior packing (n=98); PP group.- posterior        packing (n=66), and ES group.- endoscopic ligation        and/or cauterization of SP or AE (n=20). Results: Highly significant        differences were found between the groups, not        only regarding the efficacy (90% for surgical treatment compared        with 41.3% for AP and 63.1% for PP), but also the        length of postreatment hospital stay (AP.- 4.92 days; PP.- 6.3        days; ES.- 2.15 days). Discussion and conclusions: the lack of        efficacy of conventional treatment and the increasing risk        factors that condition nasal bleeding, together with the advance        of endoscopic and anesthesic procedures have        brought along the possibility of a surgical solution for these        patients. Our results demonstrate the feasibility of these        techniques as alternative for nasal packing in the treatment        of posterior epistaxis, and even its ethical and economical        convenience as a substitutive to posterior packing</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trinidad Ruiz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Huelva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas Ugena, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Claver, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Domínguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Presentamos un estudio de intervención        (prospectivo-retrospectivo) para valorar la eficacia y relación        coste-beneficio de distintos tratamientos para el control        de la epistaxis posterior grave, y en especial para        determinar si la cirugía de ligadura/cauterización de las arterias        esfenopalatina (SP) y etmoidal anterior (EA) puede        emplearse como alternativa a los medios convencionales.        Pacientes y métodos: 184 pacientes consecutivos ingresados        en nuestro servicio por epistaxis posterior fueron incluidos        en el estudio entre los años 1997 y 2005, y asignados a uno        de los tres grupos en función del último tratamiento que recibieron        para el control de su sangrado: TA.- taponamiento        anterior (98 pacientes); TP.- taponamiento posterior (66 pacientes);        CE.- cirugía de ligadura/cauterización de las arterias        SP y EA (20 pacientes). Resultados: Se encontraron diferencias        altamente significativas entre los distintos        tratamientos tanto en la eficacia (90% de la cirugía comparada        con un 41,3% del taponamiento anterior y un 63,1%        del posterior), tanto en lo que se refiere a la estancia media        postratamiento (TA.-4,92 días; TP.- 6,3 días; CE.- 2,15 días).        Discusión y conclusiones: La necesidad de repetición de los        tratamientos en el control de la epistaxis posterior grave y        el aumento de los factores de riesgo que la condicionan,        junto con el avance de las técnicas endoscópicas y anestésicas,        hacen posible la aplicación de una solución quirúrgica        que demuestra una mayor eficacia y un acortamiento evidente        de la estancia hospitalaria de estos pacientes. Los resultados        de este estudio demuestran la viabilidad de estas        técnicas como alternativa a los tratamientos convencionales,        e incluso su conveniencia ética y económica como sustitutivas        del taponamiento posterior</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;57(5): 228-234, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del tratamiento quirúrgico de la epistaxis grave mediante abordaje endoscópico de las arterias esfenopalatina y etmoidal anterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30851</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28002^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
