<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044170</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Markers of poor prognosis in convulsive status epilepticus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To characterize the variables that might be associated with mortality and the development of neurological deficits in children with convulsive status epilepticus. Patients and methods: Children older than 1 month and younger than 15 years who were admitted to the pediatric intensive care unit of a university hospital between 2001 and 2004 were reviewed. Epidemiologic and clinical factors that might be related to neurological outcome at discharge from the unit were analyzed. Results: Forty-one patients (median age 24 months) were included. A total of 48.3 % developed refractory convulsive status epilepticus. Six patients died (mortality 14.6 %) during their intensive care unit stay and neurologic worsening was observed in 8.6 % of survivors (adverse outcome in 22 %). Symptomatic epilepsy was present in all patients who died and in 88.9 % of those who recovered with severe neurologic sequelae. Uni- and multivariate analysis showed that adverse outcome was related to symptomatic origin and refractory convulsive status epilepticus (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: Mortality and morbidity is high in childhood convulsive status epilepticus. Refractory convulsive status and symptomatic origin were markers of poor outcome. Children who did not have symptomatic epilepsy had a favorable outcome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Miralles, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almanza López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Lorenzo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Murillo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reig Sáenz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Salcedo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar las variables que se asocian a la mortalidad y al desarrollo de secuelas neurológicas en los niños con estado epiléptico convulsivo. Pacientes y métodos: Revisión de los casos con estado epiléptico convulsivo, en niños mayores de un mes y menores de 15 años, tratados en la unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos de un hospital universitario entre los años 2001 y 2004. Se analizaron factores epidemiológicos y clínicos en relación con el estado neurológico al alta de la unidad. Resultados: Se incluyeron 41 pacientes con una edad mediana de 24 meses. El 43,9 % desarrolló estado epiléptico convulsivo refractario. Fallecieron 6 pacientes (mortalidad: 14,6 %) y en el 8,6 % de los supervivientes se observó un deterioro neurológico con respecto a su situación previa (mala evolución en el 22 %). Todos los pacientes que fallecieron y el 88,9 % de los que presentaron secuelas graves eran portadores de formas sintomáticas. El análisis univariante y multivariante reflejaron que la etiología sintomática y el estado epiléptico refractario se asociaron con un mal pronóstico (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: La morbimortalidad del estado epiléptico convulsivo es elevada y se relaciona con la etiología sintomática y con el desarrollo de resistencia al tratamiento. Los niños que no presentan un estado epiléptico convulsivo de tipo sintomático presentan un pronóstico favorable</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(4): 307-313, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de mal pronóstico en el estado epiléptico convulsivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
