<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77182</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Molluscum contagiosum: descriptive study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Molluscum contagiosum is a cutaneous viral infection that often requires assistance. The aim of our study is to review the cases admitted in our clinic, evaluate the epidemiological features and the treatment prescribed. Patients and methods: We conducted a descriptive survey of the patients diagnosed of molluscum contagiosum in our clinic (Complexo Hospitalario Arquitecto Marcide-Novoa Santos, Ferrol, Spain) between June 16th 2008 and January 15th 2009. The following dates were recorded in all cases: age, sex, personal history of atopy, swimming pool attendance, number of lesions and treatment prescribed. Results: 140 cases of molluscum contagiosum were included in the study. Average age was 10.7 years. 51.43% of patients had a personal history of atopy and 72.1% used to attendance swimming-pool. Average number of lesions was 13.3, with a higher number of them in males, atopic and swimming-pool attendants. Curettage was the treatment performed in 86.4% of cases. Conclusions: Atopic dermatitis and swimming-pool attendance were associated in our study with a higher frequency and number of molluscum contagiosum. Although different therapeutic options must be evaluated depending on the patient and clinical skills, curettage is the most frequent treatment performed by dermatologists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acevedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Amor, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, C. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginarte, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El molusco contagioso (MC) es una infección cutánea viral causa frecuente de consulta. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar los casos vistos en nuestro Servicio, analizar los datos epidemiológicos y el tratamiento pautado. Pacientes y método: Estudio descriptivo, entre el 16 de junio de 2008 y el 15 de enero de 2009, de los pacientes que acudieron con MC al Servicio de Dermatología del Complejo Hospitalario Arquitecto Marcide-Novoa Santos, Ferrol, España. En cada caso se recogieron los siguientes datos: sexo, edad, atopia, asistencia a piscina, número de lesiones y tratamiento. Resultados: Se seleccionó a 140 pacientes con MC. La edad media fue de 10,7 años. El 51,43% de los pacientes presentaba atopia y el 72,1% acudía a la piscina. La media del número de lesiones fue de 13,3, mayor en varones, pacientes con atopia y usuarios de piscina. El tratamiento consistió en legrado en el 86,4% de los casos. Conclusiones: Los niños con dermatitis atópica y los que acuden a piscina presentan MC con más frecuencia y en mayor número. Aunque la opción terapéutica es individualizada en función del paciente y las capacidades del médico, el legrado es la más empleada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);72(2): 139-142, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Molusco contagioso: estudio descriptivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9426^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9426^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9165^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9165^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9165^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
