<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134146</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The impact of a learning-care project with nursing students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to assess the effectiveness of a Learning-Care Project (LC) conducted by Nursing students, on acquiring knowledge, attitudes and values towards blood donation in Compulsory Secondary Education (ESO) students. Method: quasi-experimental before-after study on 31 Nursing students who had received training on blood donation, and 171Compulsory Secondary Education students. A briefing with audiovisual support on blood donation, for small groups. Ad hoc questionnaires were designed to assess the intervention. In order to conduct the before-after comparisons (after the intervention and at three months), Student&#146;s t test was used for paired samples. Results: at the end of the intervention, 88.8% of Nursing students reported an increase in their knowledge about blood donation. 80.7% of ESO students reported a higher awareness about the importance of being a blood donor, and an increase in their knowledge about this matter; the knowledge acquired by ESO students remained stable three months after the intervention (p&lt; 0.05).Conclusions: the results obtained show an increase in knowledge and a higher positiveness in beliefs and values of both student groups regarding blood donation. Leaning-care can be a recommended educational strategy in Nursing training. For this aim, teachers must be able to explore the training needs and preferences of their pupils, and to link them with community needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramón Arbués, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Abadía, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez Vela, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la efectividad de un proyecto de aprendizaje-servicio (APS) llevado a cabo por estudiantes de Enfermería, sobre la adquisición de conocimientos, actitudes y valores hacia la donación de sangre en estudiantes de Educación Secundaria Obligatoria (ESO).Método: cuasi experimental antes-después sobre 31 estudiantes de Enfermería que recibieron formación sobre donación de sangre y 171 alumnos de Educación Secundaria Obligatoria. Charla informativa con apoyo audiovisual sobre donación de sangre, en grupos pequeños. Se diseñaron cuestionarios ad hoc para evaluar la intervención. Para hacer las comparaciones antes-después (tras intervención y a los tres meses) se utilizó la t de Student para muestras apareadas. Resultados: al finalizar la intervención, un 88,8% de los alumnos de Enfermería refirió haber aumentado sus conocimientos acerca de la donación de sangre. Un 80,7% de los alumnos de ESO refirió estar más concienciado de la importancia de ser donante de sangre y haber aumentado sus conocimientos en relación a la misma; los conocimientos adquiridos por los estudiantes de ESO permanecían estables a los tres meses de la intervención(p&lt; 0,05).Conclusiones: los resultados obtenidos muestran un aumento de conocimientos y una mayor positividad en las creencias y valores de ambos grupos de alumnos en relación a la donación de sangre. El aprendizaje-servicio puede ser una estrategia educativa recomendable en la formación en Enfermería. Para ello, los docentes deben ser capaces de explorar las necesidades y preferencias formativas de sus alumnos y conectarlas con las necesidades de la comunidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(2): 49-57, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de un proyecto de aprendizaje-servicio con estudiantes de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1809^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
