<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154713</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship among service experience, perceived value and behavioural intentions of customers in a group fitness class</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Understanding the importance of the customer perception during the experience in the fitness centre is fundamental to comprehend behavioural intentions for fitness centre managers. This study attempts to understand how important and necessary is consumer&#146;s assessment of service experience, perceived value, and behavioural intention, and the relationships among theses variables into group fitness class (GFC), and Virtual fitness class (VFC). Data was collected from 1.943 customers. The confirmatory factor analysis indicated an adequate goodness-of-fit-indexes for the model obtained. Structural equation modeling analysis revealed the positive and significant effect of service experience on customers&#146; perceived value and behavioural intention, but results show that perceived value has poor fit on behavioural intentions. The overall customer&#146;s perception of GFC and VFC can be a focus for fitness centre&#146;s managers aiming to improve fitness service supply related to new technologies in the fitness industry to increase intentions to repurchase (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baena Arroyo, Manuel Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Ruiz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Oliver, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal García, Ainara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Comprender la percepción del consumidor durante su experiencia dentro de un centro de fitness resulta fundamental para que los gerentes puedan entender las intenciones de comportamiento futuras de sus abonados. Este estudio pretende esclarecer la importancia y la necesaria evaluación de la experiencia de servicio, el valor percibido y la intenciones de comportamiento, así como la relación entre dichas variables dentro de las actividades dirigidas con técnico y las actividades dirigidas virtuales, utilizando para ello una muestra de 1.943 usuarios. El análisis factorial confirmatorio indica un adecuado ajuste para el modelo de medida propuesto. Por otro lado, el análisis de ecuaciones estructurales utilizado revela una relación positiva y significativa de las experiencias de servicio hacia el valor percibido y las intenciones de comportamiento respectivamente. Sin embargo, el modelo muestra un pobre ajuste entre el valor percibido y las intenciones de comportamiento. La percepción global del consumidor en ambas actividades puede resultar un elemento de estudio para los gerentes con el objetivo de mejorar la oferta de servicios de fitness utilizando las nuevas tecnologías para así incrementar las intenciones de compra (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(supl.1): 89-92, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La relación entre la experiencia de servicio, el valor percibido y las intenciones de comportamiento en clientes de actividades dirigidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
