<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116141</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">MEIT (Mobile Emotional Intelligence Test). A new methodology for assessing emotion perception using mobile devices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The evaluation of emotional perception inasmuch as a component of emotional intelligence has traditionally been carried out using ability tests. These tests assess the ability to perceive emotions expressed in pictures as well as video and/or audio files. They continue to possess, notwithstanding, certain limitations that restrict their ecological valid-ity. The present study, following a review of the the main features of these existing instruments, analyzes a new assessment tool for emotional perception us-ing mobile devices that mitigates some of these limi-tations. To do this, a mobile application was devel-oped using two platforms (iOS and Android) and was administered to 860 subjects from 4 countries (Spain, Germany, Colombia and the United States). The results of the reliability analysis of this new sur-vey method were satisfactory, opening the possibility for the use these devices to assess skills such as the ability to accurately perceive emotions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bresó, Edgar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Ainoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giorgi, Gabriele</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La percepción de emociones como componente de la inteligencia emocional se ha evaluado tradicionalmente mediante pruebas de habilidad. Éstas evalúan la habilidad para percibir emociones en imágenes fijas así como en vídeos y/o archivos de audio. No obstante, aún existen algunas limitaciones que condicionan su validez ecológica. El presente estudio, tras revisar las principales características de estos instrumentos previos, pone a prueba un instrumento de evaluación de la percepción emocional mediante dispositivos móviles que mejora algunas de estas limitaciones. Para ello se ha desarrollado una aplicación en dos plataformas (iOS y Android) que se ha administrado a 860 participantes de 4 países (España, Alemania, Colombia y Estados Unidos). Los resultados de los análisis de fiabilidad de este nuevo método de evaluación han sido satisfactorios y abren la posibilidad al uso de estos dispositivos en el ámbito de la evaluación de habilidades como la percepción de emociones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;19(2/3): 185-200, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">MEIT (Mobile Emotional Intelligence Test): Una novedosa metodología para evaluar la percepción de emociones haciendo uso de dispositivos móviles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
