<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112426</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acupuncture as a tool for the work of nurses: integrative literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is an integrative review that aims to synthesize the knowledge about use of acupuncture as a tool for nurse&#146;s work between 2007 and 2011, in the bases: Bdenf, Cinahl, Lilacs, Scielo and Redalyc. Among the nine references analyzed were drawn three thematic categories: Experiences of nursing care with the use of acupuncture; Ethical-legal aspects of the use of acupuncture as a tool for the work of nurses and The insertion of acupuncture in the nursing curriculum. Were declined the needs about research in the practice of nurses and acupuncture, as well as expansion in training, since graduation to post-graduate classes, as well the increase of its offer in the Unified Health System (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silveira, Rodrigo Eurípedes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Álvaro da Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges, Maritza Rodrigues</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simões, Ana Lúcia de Assis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se trata de una revisión integradora de la literatura que busca sintetizar el conocimiento sobre el uso de la acupuntura como una herramienta para el trabajo de la enfermera, entre 2007 y 2011, en bases: Bdenf, Cinahl, Lilacs y Scielo, Redalyc. De las nueve referencias analizadas fueron dibujadas tres categorías temáticas: Experiencias de cuidados con el uso de la acupuntura; Aspectos éticos-legales del uso de la acupuntura como herramienta para el trabajo de las enfermeras y La inserción de la acupuntura en el plan de estudios de enfermería. Se destaca la necesidad de más investigaciones acerca de la práctica de enfermería asociada a la acupuntura, así como la expansión en formación, desde la graduación, así como el aumento de su oferta en el sistema unificado de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(35): 96-105, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La acupuntura como herramienta de trabajo para las enfermeras: revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
