<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139950</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antipsychotic treatment switch in a bipolar patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the increasingly widespread use of antipsychotics in bipolar disorder, the switch between antipsychotics and between antipsychotics and mood stabilizers has become more usual, especially since the introduction of the atypical antipsychotics, some of which have mood stabilizer properties. The evidence-based medicine for antipsychotic switch in psychotic disorders has been broadly described, however, in bipolar disorder, is far more meager. Despite the extensive work in the field of antipsychotics in bipolar disorder and the expected prompt results of the ongoing clinical trials, a formally evaluated and clearly articulated approach of antipsychotic switch in bipolar disorder is still lacking. This case report is an opportunity to discuss the management of bipolar disorders and the suitability of the different pharmacological strategies presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grande, Iria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el uso creciente de los antipsicóticos en el trastorno bipolar, el cambio de estrategia farmacológica entre antipsicóticos y entre estos y los estabilizadores del ánimo se ha convertido en una práctica generalizada, sobre todo desde la introducción de los antipsicóticos atípicos, algunos de ellos con funciones estabilizadoras del ánimo. Esta cuestión ha sido ampliamente estudiada en los trastornos psicóticos, sin embargo, menos atendida en el trastorno bipolar. De momento solo existe evidencia indirecta o descripción de casos al respecto y en la mayoría de los ensayos clínicos aleatorizados controlados con placebo aparecen muestras mixtas. La presentación de este caso es una ocasión para discutir estrategias terapéuticas y su idoneidad en un caso concreto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);22(supl.1): 40-41, abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caso clínico. Cambio de tratamiento antipsicótico en un paciente con trastorno bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54217^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
