<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74093</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">UP-DATE IN FAMILY MEDICINE: Sudeck's syndrome (reflex sympathetic dystrophy syndrome)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since Mitchell coined the term causalgia in 1864 and PaulSudeck baptized it in 1909, this disease continues to be achallenge for the medical clinician. Its non-specific diagnosisas well as its large number of precipitating factors, this alladded to its etiopathogenesis that cannot be clearly clarifiedand its controversial treatment, makes this disease a complexclinical picture for both the patient and treating clinician.Reaching an early diagnostic is fundamental in the treatmentof Sudeck&#146;s syndrome. It can affect any age group andboth men as well as women, although it is more frequent inyoung women statistically.The incidence of the illness is variable, ranging from 2%to 25% of the population. Although there are no known valuesin our country, it is undoubtedly a condition that generallygoes unnoticed in our medical community (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fornos Vieitez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Díez, F. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciriza- Lasheras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde que Mitchel en 1864 la denominara causalgia y en1909 Paul Sudeck la bautizara, a día de hoy continúa siendoun reto para la clínica médica. Su inespecificidad diagnóstica,añadida al gran número de factores precipitantes y a suetiopatogenia no claramente esclarecida y de terapéuticacontrovertida hacen de esta enfermedad un cuadro clínicocomplejo tanto para el paciente como para quien lo asiste.Llegar a un diagnóstico precoz es el eje principal del tratamientodel síndrome de Sudeck.Puede afectar a cualquier edad y tanto a hombres como amujeres, aunque estadísticamente es más frecuente en mujeresjóvenes.La incidencia de la enfermedad es variable, oscilando entreel 2 y el 25% de la población, aunque en nuestro país noconocemos cifras. Indudablemente es una entidad que pasahabitualmente desapercibida para nuestra comunidad médicaen general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(9): 455-458, nov. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74093</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">ACTUALIZACIÓN EN MEDICINA DE FAMILIA: Síndrome de Sudeck (distrofia simpático refleja)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7028^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
