<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135223</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contributions of nuclear medicine to the diagnosis and follow-up of gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The optimal treatment of patients with gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors requires accurate staging. Nuclear medicine is an imaging technique that provides functional information. In gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors this information is obtained from radiotracers providing data on amine synthesis (MIBG) and/or somatostatin receptor expression (111-In-octreotide, 68Galio-DOTATOC) by the tumoral cell, both in primary and metastatic tumors. The accumulated experience shows that nuclear medicine techniques are essential in the management of these patients. The indications in the diagnosis, extension study and follow-up of these tumors, as well as the distinct radiotracers available, are reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mitjavila Casanovas, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento óptimo de los pacientes con tumores neuroendocrinos gastroenteropancreáticos requiere una adecuada estadificación de los pacientes. La medicina nuclear es una técnica de imagen que aporta una información funcional. En los tumores neuroendocrinos gastroenteropancreáticos dicha información se obtiene con la utilización de radiotrazadores que aportan información sobre la síntesis de aminas (MIBG) y/o expresión de receptores de somatostatina (111-In-octreotido, 68galio-DOTATOC) por la célula tumoral, tanto del tumor primario como sus metástasis. La experiencia acumulada demuestra que las técnicas de medicina nuclear son una herramienta fundamental en el manejo de estos pacientes. Se revisan las indicaciones en el diagnóstico, estudio de extensión y seguimiento de estos tumores con los diferentes radiotrazadores disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(supl.3): 14-19, jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones de la medicina nuclear al diagnóstico y seguimiento de los tumores neuroendocrinos gastroenteropancreáticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12288</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23785^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
