<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87026</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Active Principles authorized in Spain in 2006 (2ª part)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As a continuation of our previous article published with the same title as first part [Sanidad Militar 2007;64(2):118-127], we present the other drugs that have been commercialized in our country during 2006. They are presented in accordance with their different characteristics, some of them described in the technical data sheet and other commented in order to complement their knowledge. The active principles that we present in this second part represent, as has  already been stated previously, a reduced contribution from the innovation point of view. However for certain patients or group of patients, and in concrete circumstances, they may represent a specific solution for a case that might have a worse outlook without this contribution. The drugs that we present in order to complete those commercialized during 2006 are the following (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puerro Vicente, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galicia de Pedro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aleixandre de Artiñano, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como continuación de nuestro trabajo publicado con anterioridad de igual título como parte 1ª [Sanidad Militar 2007;64(2):118-127], presentamos el resto de fármacos que han sido comercializados en nuestro país durante el pasado año 2006, con atención a sus diversas características, algunas de ellas reflejadas en su ficha técnica, y otras comentadas para complementar su conocimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;63(4): 291-302, oct.-dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principios activos autorizados en España en 2006 (2ª parte)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12363</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24613^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51440</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30681</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
