<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147659</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug interactions in the treatment of alzheimer&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cholinesterase inhibitors and memantine are used for the symptomatic treatment of patients with Alzheimer&#146;s disease. This population often has numerous comorbidities and receives treatment with multiple medications, with the subsequent risk of drug interactions of differing clinical relevance. The aim of this article is to review the published literature on the pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic drug-drug interactions involving cholinesterase inhibitors and memantine. Pharmacodynamic interactions play a major role in the interactions among these drugs, particularly with those having anticholinergic properties. Commonly prescribed medications, such as antihistamines and tricyclic antidepressants, often have anticholinergic properties that, alone or in combination with other drugs, can antagonize the effects of cholinesterase inhibitors. Other classes of medications, such as antipsychotics and cholinergic agents, can also result in pharmacodynamics interactions. Donepezil and galantamine are metabolized by cytochrome P450 isoenzymes 3A4 and 2D6, creating a strong potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with inhibitors and inducers of these isoenzymes. Since rivastigmine is mainly metabolized by esterases rather than by cytochrome P450 enzymes, it is unlikely to be involved in pharmacokinetic drug-drug interactions. Due to its low potential for interaction, memantine can be combined with cholinesterase inhibitors and it is suitable in elderly patients receiving multiple drug therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Felipe Conde, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los inhibidores de la colinesterasa y memantina se utilizan en el tratamiento sintomático de los pacientes con enfermedad de Alzheimer. Esta población a menudo presenta numerosas comorbilidades y recibe tratamiento con múltiples fármacos, con el consiguiente riesgo de interacciones farmacológicas de diferente relevancia clínica. El objetivo de este artículo es proporcionar una revisión de la bibliografía sobre las interacciones farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas de los inhibidores de la colinesterasa y de memantina. Las interacciones de tipo farmacodinámico desempeñan una función fundamental en las interacciones de estos fármacos, principalmente con medicamentos que tienen propiedades anticolinérgicas. Medicamentos frecuentemente prescritos, como antihistamínicos y antidepresivos tricíclicos, presentan propiedades anticolinérgicas, por lo que solos o en combinación con otros fármacos pueden antagonizar los efectos de los inhibidores de la colinesterasa. Otros fármacos, como los antipsicóticos y los colinérgicos, también pueden dar lugar a interacciones farmacodinámicas. Donepezilo y galantamina son metabolizados por el citocromo P450 isoenzimas 3A4 y 2D6, generando un fuerte potencial de interacciones farmacocinéticas con inductores e inhibidores de dichas isoenzimas. Sin embargo, debido a que rivastigmina es metabolizada principalmente por esterasas más que por las enzimas del citocromo P450 es improbable que esté involucrada en interacciones farmacocinéticas. Debido a su bajo potencial de interacciones, memantina puede asociarse a los inhibidores de la colinesterasa y ser utilizada en pacientes ancianos que reciben terapia con múltiples fármacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(4): 173-178, dic. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147659</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones farmacológicas en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32309^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
