<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141487</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical practice guidelines in type 2 diabetes mellitus: similarities and discrepancies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A careful analysis of the therapeutic recommendations of the main clinical practice guidelines (CPGs) reveals that, although they appear to be highly diverse both in their form and content, they share more similarities than discrepancies. Metformin is the recommended first-line drug both in monotherapy and double oral therapy in the 5 CPGs included in this study. Sulphonylureas are also the standard of care for all the guidelines on dual oral therapy, although they also include glitazones and DPP-4 inhibitors at this stage as well, as a first or a second-line drug. Moreover, there is unanimous agreement on the recommendation of the use of insulin by all the CPGs when anti-diabetes combinations prove ineffective, initially advising the application of a basal insulin dose in conjunction with metformin. Other therapeutic alternatives are given less coverage. In relation to the aim of achieving good glycemic control, there are discrepancies amongst the different CPGs, as one recommends target HbA1c &amp;#8804; 6.5% and others &lt; 7%. Finally, one recommends target HbA1c 6.5% in the initial phases and &lt; 7.5% in advanced cases (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Soidán, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras el análisis pormenorizado de las recomendaciones terapéuticas de las principales guías de práctica clínica (GPC) podemos observar cómo, a pesar de parecer muy diferentes tanto en su forma como en su contenido, presentan más semejanzas que discrepancias. La metformina es un fármaco recomendado de primera elección tanto en monoterapia como en doble terapia oral en las 5 GPC incluidas. También las sulfonilureas son de elección para todas las guías en la doble terapia oral, aunque también todas incluyen en este escalón, ya sea como primera o segunda elección, a las glitazonas. Además, existe unanimidad en la recomendación del uso de insulina por todas las GPC cuando fracasan las combinaciones de antidiabéticos, aconsejando inicialmente la introducción de una dosis de insulina basal junto a metformina. El resto de alternativas terapéuticas tiene menor presencia. Con relación al objetivo de buen control glucémico, también existen discrepancias entre las distintas GPC ya que una recomienda una HbA1c &amp;#8804; 6,5%, otras HbA1c &lt; 7 %, y, por último, en una de ellas se recomienda en estadios iniciales una HbA1c 6,5% y en casos avanzados HbA1c &lt; 7,5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);135(supl.2): 6-8, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías de práctica clínica en diabetes mellitus tipo 2: concordancias y discrepancias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38089^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
