<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149286</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to international recommendations in the fight against antimicrobial resistance - Substantial difference between outpatient consumption in Spain and Denmark</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Increasing antibiotic resistance represents a major public health threat that jeopardises the future treatment of bacterial infections. This study aims to describe the adherence to recommendations proposed by the World Health Organization (WHO) Advisory Group on Integrated Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance (AGISAR), in Spain and Denmark, and to analyse the relation between the outpatient use of Critically Important Antimicrobials (CIA) and the bacterial resistance rates to these agents. Material and methods. The Antimicrobial consumption interactive database (ESAC-Net) and Antimicrobial resistance interactive database (EARS-Net) provided data on outpatient use (2010-2013) of CIA (fluoroquinolones, macrolides, and 3rd and 4th generation cephalosporins) and the percentages of isolates of the main pathogens causing serious infections, resistant to these agents. Results. The use of cephalosporins and fluoroquinolones, as well as the percentage of bacteria resistant, is higher in Spain than in Denmark. Although consumption of macrolides in both countries is similar, the proportion of Streptococcus pneumoniae resistant to macrolides is significantly higher in Spain. Conclusion. The high outpatient consumption of CIA agents in Spain deviates substantially from the WHO recommendations. Moreover, it has the effect of elevated rates of antimicrobial resistance, that are lower in Denmark (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bjerrum, Lars</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabanaque, María José Rabaneque</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malo, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El aumento de la resistencia a antibióticos representa una amenaza para la salud pública al poner en riesgo el tratamiento futuro de las infecciones bacterianas. Este estudio tiene como objetivo describir el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones del Advisory Group on Integrated Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance (AGISAR) de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS), en España y Dinamarca, en cuanto al uso ambulatorio de Critically Important Antimicrobials (CIA), así como analizar la relación entre éste y las resistencias bacterianas a ellos. Material y métodos. Los sistemas Antimicrobial consumption interactive database (ESAC-Net) y Antimicrobial resistance interactive database (EARS-Net) aportaron el consumo ambulatorio (2010-2013) de los CIA (fluoroquinolonas, macrólidos y cefalosporinas de 3ª y 4ª generación) y los porcentajes de aislamientos de los principales patógenos causantes de serias infecciones, resistentes a estos agentes, en ambos países. Resultados. En España, el uso de cefalosporinas y fluoroquinolonas, así como los porcentajes de bacterias resistentes a estos antibióticos son elevados, y superiores a los recogidos en Dinamarca. Aunque el consumo de macrólidos en ambos países es similar, la proporción de Streptococcus pneumoniae resistente a macrólidos es mayor en España. Conclusión. La elevada utilización de agentes CIA en atención primaria en España se aleja de las recomendaciones de la OMS de limitar su uso. Además tiene como consecuencia unas elevadas tasas de resistencias bacterianas, que son más moderadas en Dinamarca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(1): 40-43, feb. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de las recomendaciones internacionales en la lucha contra las resistencias bacterianas - Diferencias relevantes entre el consumo ambulatorio en España y Dinamarca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36060^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32315^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
