<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058134</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish catheter ablation registry. Sixth Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology working group on electrophysiology and arrhythmias (2006)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The findings of the 2006 Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry compiled by the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Electrophysiology and Arrhythmias are presented. Methods. As in previous years, data were collected in two ways: retrospectively using a standardized questionnaire sent to electrophysiology laboratories by the Working Group on Electrophysiology and Arrhythmias, and prospectively from a central database. Each participating center selected its own preferred method of data collection. Results. Forty-eight Spanish centers contributed data voluntarily. A total of 6568 ablation procedures were recorded, averaging 139±75 per center. As in previous reports, the three most frequently treated conditions were atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (n=1881, 28%), accessory pathways (n=1628, 25%), and typical atrial flutter (n=1507, 23%). Atrial fibrillation was the fourth most common condition treated (n=540, 8%). The overall success rate was 92.2%, major complications occurred in 1.4%, and the mortality rate was 0.015%. Conclusions. In 2006, the number of ablation procedures recorded in the Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry continued to grow, with more than 6500 procedures now being registered. The success rate increased and there were fewer complications. Atrial fibrillation remains the fourth most common condition treated by catheter ablation at Spanish arrhythmia units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Infante, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bolao, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías-Gallego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Se detallan los resultados del Registro Nacional de Ablación del año 2006, elaborado por la Sección de Electrofisiología y Arritmias de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología.  Métodos. Al igual que en anteriores registros, la recogida de datos se llevó a cabo mediante dos sistemas: bien de forma retrospectiva con la cumplimentación de un cuestionario que fue enviado desde la Sección de Electrofisiología y Arritmias a los laboratorios de electrofisiología, bien prospectivamente mediante una base de datos común. La elección de una u otra fue voluntaria por parte de cada uno de los centros.  Resultados. En el envío de datos participaron de forma voluntaria 48 centros. El número total de procedimientos de ablación analizado fue 6.568, con una media de 139 ± 75 procedimientos por centro. Como en registros previos, los 3 sustratos abordados con más frecuencia fueron la taquicardia intranodular (n = 1.881; 28%), las vías accesorias (n = 1.628; 25%) y la ablación del istmo cavotricuspídeo (n = 1.507; 23%). El cuarto sustrato abordado (n = 540; 8%) fue la ablación de fibrilación auricular. El porcentaje general de éxito fue del 92,2%; el de complicaciones mayores, del 1,4%, y el de mortalidad, del 0,015%.  Conclusiones. En el registro del año 2006 se mantiene una línea de continuidad ascendente en el número de ablaciones realizadas, con más de 6.500 procedimientos registrados, una elevada tasa de éxito y un número bajo de complicaciones. La ablación de fibrilación auricular supone ya el cuarto sustrato más frecuentemente abordado en las unidades de arritmias de nuestro país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(11): 1188-1196, nov. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Ablación con Catéter. VI Informe Oficial de la Sección de Electrofisiología y Arritmias de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (2006)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35391^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
