<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79169</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Kidney transplant complications in the Nephrology Institute. 2001-2005</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and Objectives: Despite the development of transplants our results are affected by the appearance of medical and surgical complications that hinder their evolution. Our aim was to identify the most frequent complications in the first week after a kidney transplant and their effects on patient and graft survival one month and one year after the transplant. Methods: retrospective cohort descriptive observational study at the Nephrology Institute, of patients who received transplants between the months of January 2001 and December 2005. The variables of interest were analysed. The statistical technique of frequency distribution analysis was used. For each category of variables, absolute and relative frequencies (percentages) were calculated. The homogeneity test was used to prove the null hypothesis (Ho), of equality of distribution of some variables with a significance level a = 0.05. Results: In 136 patients a total of 212 complications were found, of which 159 (75%) were medical and 53 (25%) were surgical. The most frequent medical complications were: non-infectious110 (51.8%); infectious 33 (15.5%). The most frequent surgical complications were: vascular 34 (16%), parenchymatosic 7 (3.3%). Only 30 patients (22%) showed no type of complication and in another 30 patients (22%) there were both medical and surgical complications. Conclusions: The occurrence of medical complications in the first week after the transplant determines poor survival of the kidney graft in the short-term. The fact of showing surgical complications reduces the survival of the kidney graft and of the transplanted patient in the very short and short-term</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bacallao Méndez, Raymed</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, Roynel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Hernández, Dianelys</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivos: A pesar del desarrollo del trasplante nuestros resultados se ven afectados por la aparición de complicaciones médicas y quirúrgicas entorpeciendo su evolución. Nuestro propósito fue identificar las complicaciones más frecuentes de la primera semana post-trasplante renal y su repercusión sobre la supervivencia del paciente y del injerto al mes y al año posterior al trasplante. Métodos: estudio observacional descriptivo de cohorte retrospectiva en el Instituto de Nefrología, de los pacientes trasplantados entre los meses de enero 2001 hasta diciembre 2005. Se analizaron las variables de interés. Se empleó la técnica estadística de análisis de distribución de frecuencias. Para cada una de las categorías de las variables fueron calculadas frecuencias absolutas y relativas (porcentajes). Se empleó el test de homogeneidad para probar la hipótesis nula (Ho), de igualdad de distribución de algunas variables con un nivel de significación a = 0,05. Resultados: En 136 pacientes se presentaron 212 complicaciones, de ellas 159 (75%) médicas y 53 (25%) fueron quirúrgicas. Las complicaciones médicas más frecuentes fueron: no infecciosas 110 (51,8%); infecciosas 33 (15,5%). Las complicaciones quirúrgicas más frecuentes fueron: vasculares 34 (16%), parenquimatosas 7 (3,3%). Solo 30 (22%) pacientes no presentaron ningún tipo de complicación y en otros 30 (22%) pacientes coincidieron tanto complicaciones médicas como quirúrgicas. Conclusiones: La ocurrencia de complicaciones médicas en la primera semana post-trasplante determina una pobre supervivencia del injerto renal a corto plazo. El hecho de presentar complicaciones quirúrgicas disminuye la supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;13(1): 7-15, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones del trasplante renal en el Instituto de Nefrología. 2001-2005</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
