<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115172</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dependent Care Act application in low vision patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The recent Promotion of Personal Autonomy and Care for Dependent Persons Act has opened up the opportunity to complete the social welfare system generated for the dependent and, perhaps only partly, to change the system of social networks that has meant, until now, their only support. The main goal of the present study is to know the characteristics of dependent people with low vision, the level of dependency and the personal, family and social impact of this situation. Materials and methods. Descriptive cross-sectional study after personal interview and clinical records review of a group of patients belonging to the Ophthalmology Service of the Hospital Clínico Universitario of Valencia. It is based on the results of an adapted questionnaire from the Disability, Deficiency and Health Survey conducted by the Spanish National Statistics Institute. Results. The mean age of the patients was 65.8 years, mostly women and occupied, with a mean age of 59.1 years at the beginning of the disability. The prevailing diagnose was corneal pathology and common disease as etiology. The mean visual acuity was 0.4. Clinical status of over 50% of the patients could worsen within time. Most of the patients had not applied for any assistance. Conclusion. The studied patients follow the same demographic profile as shown on previous studies over dependency. Facilities for paperwork issues, information, evaluation and assistance should be implemented in order to improve the attention to dependent people(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bayo Calduch, PAtricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert Grifo, Marina S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Ley de Dependencia surge en España como un reto de la política social, cuyo objetivo es atender las necesidades de las personas que requieren apoyo para realizar las actividades esenciales de la vida diaria. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer las características de la población que se encuentra en situación de dependencia por el padecimiento de una afección oftalmológica. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal a partir de la entrevista personal y revisión de la historia clínica de un grupo de pacientes atendidos en Consultas Externas del Servicio de Oftalmología del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia, partiendo de los datos vertidos por un cuestionario adaptado a partir de la Encuesta de Discapacidades, Deficiencias y Estados de Salud realizada por el Instituto Nacional de Estadística. Resultados. La media de edad de los pacientes es de 65,8 años, mayoritariamente mujeres y laboralmente activos, con una edad media al inicio de la discapacidad de 59,1 años. Predominó la afección corneal como diagnóstico y la enfermedad común como etiología. La media de la agudeza visual fue de 0,4. Más de la mitad de los pacientes presentaron una situación clínica que podría empeorar con el tiempo. La mayor parte de los pacientes no había solicitado ayuda alguna. Conclusiones. Los pacientes estudiados siguen el mismo perfil poblacional que los estudios precedentes sobre prevalencia de la dependencia. Sería necesario adoptar medidas para mejorar la información que reciben los pacientes sobre sus derechos en este marco, facilitar los trámites burocráticos para la percepción de ayudas, disminuir el tiempo de demora en la valoración de la situación de dependencia y reforzar los dispositivos asistenciales para las personas dependientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;39(3): 87-92, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115172</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la Ley de Dependencia en los pacientes con baja visión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33555^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28307^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28259^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30943^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52587^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
