<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106590</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of tomato juice intake on lycopene and short chain fatty acid content in faeces of Sprague Dawley rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A wide range of bioactive components are provided to the diet by vegetables intake, which can be absorbed by the intestinal cells during digestion process. Furthermore, some of these components are susceptible to be used as fermentative substrate by intestinal microbiota as well as playing a protective role on colon cells when maintain their original structure. The aim of this research was to evaluate the content of lycopene and short-chain fatty acids (SCFA) in faeces of Sprague Dawley (SD) rats. Twenty four 12 weeks old male SD rats, were selected and classified in three different groups (Control, Group A and Group B). The animals were introduced in metabolic cages and fed during a period of 21 days using a standard diet. Control Group was given ad libitum access to food and water, whereas Group B and Group A were given tomato juice with high (12 mg/100 g) and low (2.7 mg/100 g) lycopene content, respectively. Urine and faeces were picked up everyday. Both, faeces samples at the beginning and at the end of the research period were selected, analyzing lycopene content by colorimetric method and SCFA by gas-liquid chromatography. The results showed that tomato juice intake produces an increase in the amount of lycopene in faeces. This increment was directly proportional to the lycopene content in different juices. The presence of lycopene in faeces suggests that not all the lycopene ingested was absorbed. A change in the SCFA profile in faeces has been observed from the beginning to the end of the study. In this way, an increase in butyric acid level was detected in those rats which took tomato juice. This finding could be a consequence of the modification of substrates by fermentation. The antioxidant effect of lycopene through the large intestine until its excretion and the formation of butyric acid, could be able to make a positive effect on colon cells and, eventually, prevent carcinogenic processes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santaella, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, V. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Pozuelo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Periago, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de vegetales proporciona a la dieta una amplia variedad de compuestos bioactivos que pueden ser absorbidos en el intestino durante la digestión, o llegar al intestino grueso donde son utilizados como sustratos fermentativos por la flora colónica o se mantienen intactos ejerciendo un efecto beneficioso protector sobre las células del colon. El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido evaluar la presencia de licopeno y ácidos grasos de cadena corta (AGCC) en las heces de ratas Sprague Dawley (SD) sometidas a distintas dietas. Se seleccionaron 24 ratas machos SD adultas de 12 semanas, clasificándose en tres grupos (control, grupo A y grupo B). Los animales se introdujeron en jaulas metabólicas y fueron alimentados durante 21 días con una dieta estándar y agua ad libitum (grupo control), zumo de tomate con bajo (2.7 mg/100 g) contenido en licopeno (grupo A) y zumo de tomate con alto (12 mg/100 g) contenido en licopeno (grupo B). Diariamente se recogió la orina y las heces. Se seleccionaron las muestras de heces correspondientes al inicio y fin del estudio, determinándose en ellas el contenido de licopeno colorimétricamente y los AGCC por cromatografía gaseosa. Los resultados obtenidos mostraron que el consumo de zumo de tomate producía un aumento del contenido de licopeno en heces proporcional a la cantidad de licopeno presente en el zumo. La presencia de licopeno en heces nos indica que no todo el licopeno presente en la dieta es absorbido. En relación al perfil de AGCC en heces se observa un cambio desde el inicio al final del estudio, destacando un aumento en el ácido butírico, consecuencia de la modificación en los substratos de fermentación asociada al cambio de alimentación de las ratas que tomaron zumo de tomate. La acción antioxidante del licopeno a su paso por el intestino grueso hasta su excreción en las heces y la formación de ácido butírico, podrían ejercer una acción beneficiosa en las células del colon, pudiéndose prevenir posibles procesos cancerígenos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;27: 51-64, 2011. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la ingesta de zumo de tomate en el contenido de licopeno y ácidos grasos de cadena corta en heces de ratas Sprague Dawley</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2379^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32001^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32001^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
