<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160685</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current status of iron metabolism: clinical and therapeutic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hepcidin is the main regulator of iron metabolism and a pathogenic factor in iron disorders. Hepcidin deficiency causes iron overload, whereas hepcidin excess causes or contributes to the development of iron-restricted anaemia in chronic inflammatory diseases. We know the mechanisms involved in the synthesis of hepcidin and, under physiological conditions, there is a balance between activating signals and inhibitory signals that regulate its synthesis. The former include those related to plasmatic iron level and also those related to chronic inflammatory diseases. The most important inhibitory signals are related to active erythropoiesis and to matriptase-2. Knowing how hepcidin is synthesised has helped design new pharmacological treatments whose main target is the hepcidin. In the near future, there will be effective treatments aimed at correcting the defect of many of these iron metabolism disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Allende, Ricardo de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde García, Eulogio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Diez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hepcidina es el principal regulador del metabolismo del hierro y el factor patogénico más importante en sus trastornos. La deficiencia de hepcidina provoca sobrecarga de hierro, mientras que su exceso da lugar o contribuye al desarrollo de anemias por déficit o restricción de hierro en las enfermedades crónicas. Conocemos los mecanismos implicados en la síntesis de hepcidina y, en condiciones fisiológicas, hay un equilibrio entre las señales activadoras e inhibidoras que regulan su síntesis. Las primeras incluyen las relacionadas con la concentración plasmática de hierro y con las enfermedades inflamatorias. Las señales inhibidoras más importantes están relacionadas con la eritropoyesis activa y con la matriptasa-2. Conocer cómo se sintetiza la hepcidina ha servido para diseñar nuevos tratamientos farmacológicos cuya diana principal es la hepcidina. En un futuro próximo, se dispondrá de tratamientos eficaces dirigidos a corregir el defecto de muchos de los trastornos del metabolismo del hierro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(5): 218-224, mar. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160685</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual del metabolismo del hierro: implicaciones clínicas y terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30151^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5009^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34041^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55332^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53118^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
