<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153027</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of the initial state of nutrition on the lifespan of patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) during home enteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) is a chronic, neurodegenerative disease, which leads to development of malnutrition. The main purpose of this research was to analyze the impact of malnutrition on the course of the disease and long-term survival. Material and methods: A retrospective analysis has been performed on 48 patients (22 F [45,83%] and 26 M [54,17%], the average age of patients: 66,2 [43-83]) in 2008-2014.The analysis of the initial state of nutrition was measured by body mass index (BMI), nutritional status according to NRS 2002, SGA and concentration of albumin in blood serum. Patients were divided into two groups, depending on the state of nutrition: well-nourished and malnourished. The groups were created separately for each of these, which allowed an additional comparative analysis of techniques used for the assessment of nutritional status. Results: Proper state of nutrition was interrelated with longer survival (SGA: 456 vs. 679 days, NRS: 312 vs. 659 vs. 835 days, BMI: respectively, 411, 541, 631 days, results were statistically significant for NRS and BMI). Concentration of albumin was not a prognostic factor, but longer survival was observed when level of albumin was increased during nutritional therapy. Conclusions: The initial nutrition state and positive response to enteral feeding is associated with better survival among patients with ALS. For this reason, nutritional therapy should be introduced as soon as possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>K&amp;#322;ek, Stanis&amp;#322;aw</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sznajder, Janusz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Slefarska-Wasilewska, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: la esclerosis lateral amiotrófica (ELA) es una enfermedad crónica, neurodegenerativa que genera malnutrición. El objetivo principal de este estudio es analizar el impacto de la malnutrición en el curso de la enfermedad y la sobrevida a largo plazo. Materiales y métodos: se realizó un análisis retrospectivo de 48 pacientes (22 mujeres [45.83%] y 26 hombres [54.17%], con un promedio de edad de 66,2 [43-83]) del 2008 al 2014. El análisis del estado nutricional inicial se midió utilizando el índice de masa corporal (IMC), el estado nutricional de acuerdo al NRS 2002, la valoración global subjetiva (VGS) y la concentración sérica de albúmina. Los pacientes se dividieron en dos grupos, dependiendo del estado nutricional en el que se encontraban: bien nutridos o malnutridos. Los grupos se crearon por separado, lo que permitió un análisis comparativo adicional de las técnicas utilizadas para la evaluación del estado nutricional. Resultados: un estado nutricional adecuado se relaciona con mayor sobreviva a largo plazo (456 vs. 679 días, NRS 312 vs. 659 vs. 835 días, IMC respectivamente: 41, 541, 631 días, resultados estadísticamente significativos para NRS e IMC). Las concentraciones de albúmina no fueron un factor pronóstico, pero se observó mayor sobrevida si las concentraciones de albúmina incrementaban durante el tratamiento nutricional. Conclusiones: el estado nutricional inicial y la respuesta positiva a la alimentación enteral están asociados a mayor sobrevida en pacientes con ELA, razón por la cual, la terapia nutricional debe de iniciarse lo antes posible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(1): 3-7, ene.-feb. 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia del estado inicial de la nutrición en la esperanza de vida de pacientes con esclerosis lateral amiotrófica (ALS) durante la nutrición enteral en casa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
