<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75237</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traumatic aortic rupture is an injury found in 17% to20% of traffic accident casualties, when autopsied. It isassociated to high decceleration impacts, at high speedcrashes and run-over pedestrians, and though it is a verysevere injury, and if immediate death has not happened,survival is possible if it is suspected, and promptly diagnosedand treated. Therefore information related to crashand patient circumstances &#150;biomechanics and injurymechanism&#150; is very helpful to suspect it and actingaccordingly.Associated head, thorax, abdomen, and pelvic injuriesare very frequent, contributing to its high death toll.Treatment through surgical repair or endovascular prosthesis(stent) placement, gives some hope to patientincluded in the avoidable death group(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menchaca Anduaga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Lorenzo, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Nieto Gómez-Guillamón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wilhelmi Ayza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La rotura traumática de aorta es una lesión que seencuentra entre el 17 y el 20% de víctimas mortales deaccidentes de tráfico, cuando se realizan autopsias completas.Se asocia a accidentes con desaceleraciones elevadas,en colisiones y atropellos a alta velocidad y, aunque es unalesión muy grave, si no se ha producido la muerte in situ,puede sobrevivirse a ella si se sospecha, se diagnostica precozmentey se trata. Por ello, la información relativa a lascircunstancias del accidente y de la víctima &#150;biomecánicay mecanismo lesivo&#150; es muy orientadora para sospechar suexistencia y actuar en consecuencia.La asociación de lesiones en tronco y cabeza es frecuente,contribuyendo a su elevada mortalidad.El tratamiento, bien mediante reparación quirúrgica ocolocación de prótesis intravascular, suponen una esperanzapara pacientes que constituyen un grupo incluído en elde mortalidad evitable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;9(3): 134-145, 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traumatismo torácico y rotura aórtica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31496^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1024^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
