<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100793</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Papillary Thyroid Carcinoma synchronous with breast cancer: An incidental finding in an 18F-FDG PET-CT study carried out in a search for occult breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most common cause of metastatic involvement of axillary lymph nodes in women is ipsilateral breast cancer. The definition of occult breast malignancy has changed over time. Nowadays, it is considered to exist when it coincides with an isolated metastatic axillary abnormal lymph node in the absence of a palpable tumor in the ipsilateral breast, non-diagnostic breast tumor mammography and no detection of other malignancies outside the breast which could potentially affect the axillary nodes. The value of 18F-FDG PET/CT scan in these patients has not been established, but it could be useful in those patients with a non-diagnostic MRI. It is not uncommon in 18F-FDG PET/CT studies to identify incidental hypermetabolic focal image in the thyroid. The high prevalence of cancer in these lesions makes it recommendable to perform a US study and/or FNAP biopsy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prats, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ubieto, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rambalde, E. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tardín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santapau, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banzo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Razola, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La causa más frecuente de afectación metastásica de los ganglios linfáticos axilares en mujeres es una neoplasia en la mama ipsilateral. La definición de neoplasia oculta de mama se ha modificado con el tiempo. Actualmente, hay que considerar una neoplasia oculta de mama cuando coincide una linfadenopatía axilar metastásica aislada en ausencia de una tumoración palpable en la mama ipsilateral, una mamografía no diagnóstica para un tumor mamario y la no detección de una neoplasia primaria fuera de la mama, que potencialmente pudiera afectar a los ganglios axilares. En estos casos, el valor de la exploración 18F-FDG-PET-TAC no está establecido, aunque puede ser de utilidad en pacientes con una RM no diagnóstica. No es infrecuente que, en una exploración 18F-FDG-PET-TAC, se identifique de forma casual una imagen hipermetabólica focal en tiroides. La elevada prevalencia de cáncer en este tipo de lesiones, aconseja practicar una exploración con US y/o PAAF(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);31(4): 213-215, jul.-ago.2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma papilar de tiroides sincrónico con cáncer de mama: hallazgo casual en una exploración 18F-FDG PET-TAC por búsqueda de un cáncer oculto de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2334^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
