<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151586</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey for Spanish orthodontists on the use of self-llgation FIXED appllances AND individualization of archwires to the patient&#146;s arch form</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to determine the current situation in Spanish orthodontic clinics concerning the use of self-ligating brackets and the individualization of the archwire according to the palient's arch form. An online survey was distributed to orthodontists IN= 511) of the Spanish Society of Orthodontics ISEDOl. The questionnarie consisted of three parts, mainly containing multiple-choice questions. The data were analyzed using descriptive statistics and the groups were compared using the Chi-square test of independence. The results of the survey show that most participants work with both conventional and self-ligating brackets. The most widely used prescription in conventional lixed orthodontics was Roth' s with 57%, and the most widely used technique in sell-ligating brackets was Damon' s with 62%. Dental casts and wax records were the methods favored by orthodontists that individualized archwires. Although most participants considered it important to individualize the archwires to the patient's arch form, only half reported that they individualize archwires in all patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Costa, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Javier de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Vigo, Susana de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>El Khouly Castilla, Said</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue conocer la situación actual en las clínicas de ortodoncia españolas en el uso de brackets autoligables así como la individualización del arco a la forma de arcada del paciente. Una encuesta online fue distribuida a ortodoncistas [N= 5111 de la Sociedad Española de Ortodoncia [SEDO]. El cuestionario consistía en tres partes, principalmente constituida con preguntas multirespuesta. Los datos fueron analizados mediante el uso de estadísticas descriptivas y los grupos se compararon usando la prueba de independencia Chi-cuadrado. Los resultados de la encuesta muestran que la mayoría de los encuestados trabajan tanto con brackets convencionales como autoligables, siendo la prescripción más utilizada en ortodoncia fija convencional Roth con un 57% y la técnica autoligable más usada Damon con un 62%. Destacaron los modelos de estudio y los registros de cera como métodos por los cuáles los ortodoncistas individualizan los arcos. A pesar de que la mayoría de los encuestados consideraron importante la individualización de los arcos a la forma de arcada del paciente, únicamente la mitad de éstos dicen individualizar los arcos en todos sus pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);50(2): 413-418, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, mapas, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151586</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre el uso de aparatología fija autoligable e individualización de arcos a la forma de arcada del paciente en ortodoncistas españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29921^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3737^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10149^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
