<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137263</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between mnesic encoding strategies, learning capacity, and academic performance in psychology students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The goal of this research was to determine the relations between encoding memory strategies, learning capacity, and the academic performance of psychology students in Mar del Plata National University (UNMDP). The article defines and characterizes memory, its encoding processes, and its association with learning, and analyzes these variables with respect to the performance of a sample of students in a verbal learning test, the TAVEC (Test de Aprendizaje Verbal Complutense). For this purpose, a random sample of 83 regular students from UNMDP School of Psychology, from both genders, was used. Likewise, an analysis of the academic performance of these students was carried out. An exploratory approach showed that some variables turned out relevant in explaining university students&#146; academic performance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urquijo, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verónica del Valle, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue la determinación de las relaciones entre las estrategias de codificación mnésica, la capacidad de aprendizaje y el desempeño académico en estudiantes de la Facultad de Psicología de la Universidad Nacional de Mar del Plata. Bajo el supuesto de que el proceso de almacenamiento de información implica procesos de codificación que se relacionan íntimamente con el aprendizaje, es posible pensar que deberían vincularse al rendimiento académico. Para ello se trabajó con una muestra aleatoria de 83 estudiantes regulares de la Facultad de Psicología de la UNMP, de ambos sexos, a quienes se les administró el Test de Aprendizaje Verbal Complutense (TAVEC) y los resultados se vincularon a diferentes indicadores de desempeño académico en la universidad. Los resultados sugieren de forma exploratoria algunas variables que resultan relevantes a la hora de explicar el rendimiento académico de los alumnos universitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);21(1): 27-37, jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137263</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones de las estrategias de codificación mnésica y la capacidad de aprendizaje con el desempeño académico de estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
