<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038992</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of hemolysins of the ABO blood group system in children with ascariasis using a simple photometric technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heteroimmunization in the ABO system by animal or bacterial products can provoke the development of hemolysins of clinical importance in transfusions or pregnancy. We proposed to study the presence of ABO hemolysins in children with ascariasis using a simple photometric technique. Serum samples were collected from 23 children (19 prior to and 4 after treatment with antiparasitic agents). The ABO blood group was determined by conventional techniques. The photometric technique employed to demonstrate the presence of ABO hemolysins is a modification of tH 50. A hemolysis time of less than 300 seconds was considered to be clinically significant. We detected ABO hemolysins in 57.89% of the sera of untreated children, with hemolysis times ranging between 100 and 210 seconds. None of the sera from the treated children presented ABO hemolysins. The results suggest that parasitic infection may be the external stimulus that provokes the appearance of ABO hemolysins. The photometric technique employed is simple and rapid, and is available to any routine laboratory</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ponce de León, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La heteroinmunización en el sistema ABO, a través de sustancias de origen animal o bacteriano, puede provocar la aparición de hemolisinas de importancia clínica en transfusión o embarazo. El objetivo de este trabajo era estudiar la presencia de hemolisinas ABO en niños con ascariasis utilizando una técnica fotométrica simple. Se trabajó con sueros de 23 niños (19 antes del tratamiento antiparasitario y 4 después). Se determinó el grupo sanguíneo ABO por técnicas convencionales. La técnica fotométrica usada para demostrar la presencia de hemolisinas ABO es una modificación del tiempo hemolítico (tH) 50. El tiempo hemolítico medido tiene significado clínico cuando es inferior a 300 segundos. El 57,89% de los sueros de los niños sin tratamiento presentó hemolisinas ABO, con tiempos hemolíticos comprendidos entre 100 y 210 segundos. Ninguno de los sueros de los niños tratados presentó hemolisinas ABO. Los resultados sugieren que la infección parasitaria puede ser el estímulo externo para la aparición de hemolisinas ABO. La técnica fotométrica usada es simple, rápida y accesible al laboratorio de rutina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(6): 241-242, jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de hemolisinas del sistema ABO por técnica fotométrica simple en niños con ascariasis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6613^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10981^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10981^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10981^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6613^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6612^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1202^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10981^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
