<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141900</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary possibilities in attention deficit and hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is the most common neurodevelopmental disorder in children. There has been suggested various biochemical etiologies in relation to diets: food allergies and additives, heavy metals toxicity and other environmental toxins, low protein diets with high levels in carbohydrate, imbalances of minerals and micronutrients, inadequate intake of essential fatty acids and phospholipids deficit, aminoacids deficiencies, deficiencies in B vitamins and phytonutrients and thyroid disorders. The treatment of this disorder with stimulant drugs are not free of side effects on sleep and appetite. The occurrence of these side effects joined with a lack of response to medical treatment causes that many parents question and reject the medical treatment, using alternative treatments like the 'dietary treatments'. Therefore pediatricians should be familiar with these alternative therapies to advise and to assess the nutritional impact on the child (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juste Ruiz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canals Baeza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Escobar, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad (TDAH) es el trastorno del neurodesarrollo más frecuente en la edad pediátrica. Se han sugerido etiologías bioquímicas diversas en relación con la dieta: alergias a alimentos y aditivos, toxicidad por metales pesados y otros tóxicos ambientales, dietas bajas en proteínas con alto contenido en hidratos de carbono, desequilibrios de minerales y micronutrientes, ingesta inadecuada de ácidos grasos esenciales y déficit de fosfolípidos, deficiencias de aminoácidos, deficiencias en el complejo vitamínico B y fitonutrientes y trastornos de tiroides. El tratamiento de este trastorno con fármacos estimulantes no está exento de efectos secundarios, como los que ejercen sobre el sueño y el apetito. La aparición de estos efectos secundarios, junto con una falta de respuesta al tratamiento médico, hace que muchos padres lo cuestionen y rechacen, llegando a recurrir a terapias alternativas, como los «tratamientos dietéticos». Por este motivo, los pediatras debemos estar familiarizados con estas terapias alternativas para poder valorar y aconsejar acerca de sus repercusiones nutricionales sobre el niño (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(7): e171-e175, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141900</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posibilidades dietéticas en el trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
