<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32701</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enteric pathogens and soil: a short review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is known that soil is a recipient of solid wastes able to contain enteric pathogens in high concentrations. Although the role of soil as a reservoir of certain bacterial pathogens is not in question, recent findings show that soil may have a larger role in the transmission of enteric diseases than previously thought. Many of the diseases caused by agents from soil have been well characterized, although enteric diseases and their link to soil have not been so well studied. Gastrointestinal infections are the most common diseases caused by enteric bacteria. Some examples are salmonellosis ( Salmonella sp.), cholera ( Vibrio cholerae), dysentery ( Shigella sp.) and other infections caused by Campylobacter jejuni, Yersinia sp. and Escherichia coli O157:H7 and many other strains. Viruses are the most hazardous and have some of the lowest infectious doses of any of the enteric pathogens. Hepatitis A, hepatitis E, enteric adenoviruses, poliovirus types 1 and 2, multiple strains of echoviruses and coxsackievirus are enteric viruses associated with human wastewater. Among the most commonly detected protozoa in sewage are Entamoeba histolytica, Giardia intestinalis and Cryptosporidium parvum. This article reviews the existing literature of more than two decades on waste disposal practices that favor the entry of enteric pathogens to soil and the possible consequent role of the soil as a vector and reservoir of enteric pathogens (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Springer-Verlag Ibérica</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Es sabido que el suelo recibe desechos sólidos, y que puede contener patógenos entéricos en elevadas concentraciones. Aunque el papel del suelo como reservorio de ciertas bacterias patógenas está asumido, recientes descubrimientos parecen indicar que su importancia en la transmisión de enfermedades entéricas es mayor de lo que se creía hasta ahora. Muchas de las enfermedades causadas por agentes del suelo han sido caracterizadas exhaustivamente, aunque su relación con el suelo no se ha estudiado con igual detalle. Las infecciones gastrointestinales son las enfermedades más frecuentes causadas por bacterias entéricas. Algunos ejemplos serían la salmonelosis (Salmonella sp.), el cólera (Vibrio cholerae), la disentería (Shigella sp.), y otras infecciones causadas por Campylobacter jejuni, Yersinia sp. y Escherichia coli O157:H7 y muchas cepas más. Los virus son los patógenos más peligrosos, y muestran las dosis de infección más bajas de todos los patógenos entéricos. Hepatitis A, hepatitis E, adenovirus entéricos, poliovirus de tipo 1 y 2, múltiples cepas de ecovirus y coxsackievirus son virus entéricos asociados a las aguas residuales. Entre los protozoos detectados con más frecuencia en aguas residuales encontramos Entamoeba histolytica, Giardia intestinalis y Cryptosporidium parvum. Este artículo revisa la bibliografía existente a lo largo de más de dos décadas de depuración de aguas residuales que favorece la entrada de patógenos entéricos en el suelo, y el posible papel de estos suelos como vectores y reservorios de patógenos entéricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;6(1): 5-9, mar. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patógenos entéricos y el suelo: una breve revisión</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Toranzos, Gary A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, Johanna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32701</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7573^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7573^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27793</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15275</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
