<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99926</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardias and preexcitation syndromes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardias are fast and usually regular rhythms that require some structure above the bifurcation of the His bundle to be continued. The 3 most common types are atrial tachycardias, atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardias, and tachycardias mediated by an accessory pathway. The last two varieties are discussed in the present manuscript. Their prognosis is benign regarding life expectancy but typically they are symptomatic and chronically recurrent, producing a certain disability. They usually occur in people without structural heart disease. Pharmacologic therapy is possible, but given the high efficacy of catheter ablation, these procedures are frequently chosen. Ventricular preexcitation is due to the presence of an accessory pathway, usually atrioventricular. The clinical course can be asymptomatic, generating a characteristic electrocardiographic pattern, produce paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardias, or facilitate other types of arrhythmias. Very rarely, they can cause sudden cardiac death. The treatment of choice for symptomatic patients is catheter ablation of the accessory pathway. The therapeutic attitude towards asymptomatic preexcitation remains controversial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellanos, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almendral, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las taquicardias paroxísticas supraventriculares son ritmos rápidos y habitualmente regulares en los que alguna estructura por encima de la bifurcación del haz de His es necesaria para su mantenimiento. Los tres tipos más frecuentes son las taquicardias auriculares, las taquicardias reentrantes nodales y las taquicardias mediadas por una vía accesoria. Las dos últimas son las revisadas en este manuscrito. Son arritmias de pronóstico benigno en cuanto a la vida, aunque es típico que sean sintomáticas y crónicamente recidivantes, por lo que producen cierto grado de invalidez. Suelen aparecer en sujetos sin cardiopatía estructural. Su tratamiento puede ser farmacológico, pero dada la eficacia alcanzada por los procedimientos de ablación por catéter, con frecuencia se recurre a estos. La preexcitación ventricular se debe a la presencia de una vía accesoria, generalmente auriculoventricular. Puede cursar asintomática, produciendo un patrón electrocardiográfico característico, provocar taquicardias paroxísticas supraventriculares o propiciar otros tipos de arritmias. Muy rara vez pueden causar muerte súbita. El tratamiento de elección en los casos sintomáticos es la ablación por catéter de la vía accesoria. La actitud terapéutica en casos asintomáticos es motivo de controversia científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(5): 456-469, mayo 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99926</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taquicardias paroxísticas supraventriculares y síndromes de preexcitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20206^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13994^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19362^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19362^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20206^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20206^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
