<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048239</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A cost-effectiveness study of first-line hormone therapy in post-menopausal patients with metastatic breast cancer on neoadjuvant treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Breast cancer is a hormone-dependent tumor, which expands therapy options. The aim of this study was to perform a pharmacoeconomic assessment of these drugs in post-menopausal patients with metastatic breast cancer or on neoadjuvant therapy. Method: To assess the efficacy of both drug classes a meta-analysis was carried out from papers obtained in a Medline literature search (1997 - June 2004) using the following keywords: breast cancer, postmenopausal, aromatase inhibitors, antiestrogens, tamoxifen, neoadjuvant. Effectiveness parameters included: objective response, percentage with conservative surgery in neoadjuvancy; in metastatic breast cancer, time to progression. Costs were considered from drug acquisition data. To determine result strength a sensitivity analysis was undertaken, with modified costs and effectiveness. Results: Results show a higher effectiveness for aromatase inhibitors as compared to antiestrogens. In neoadjuvant therapy: 56.38% versus 36% for objetive response rate, and 47.64% versus 35% for conservative surgery. In metastatic cancer: 9.96 versus 6.61 months for time to progression (p = 0.05). The pharmacoeconomic analysis showed that selecting anastrozole represents a cost of e 969 and e 779 per extra effectiveness unit regarding objective response and conservative surgery, respectively, whereas in metastatic cancer patients it represents e 56,525 per extra effectiveness unit. Conclusions: Selecting an aromatase inhibitor is a valid option in neoadjuvancy, even if such selection would represent a very high cost for metastatic cancer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferriols Lisart, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magraner Gil, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Viéitez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue realizar una valoración farmacoeconómica de los antiestrógenos e inhibidores de la aromatasa en pacientes postmenopáusicas con cáncer de mama metastásico o en terapia neoadyuvante. Método: Para evaluar la eficacia de ambos grupos de fármacos se realizó un metaanálisis a partir de los trabajos obtenidos mediante búsqueda bibliográfica en MEDLINE (1997- junio 2004); palabras clave: breast cancer, postmenopausal, aromatase inhibitors, antiestrogens, tamoxifen, neoadjuvant. Los parámetros de efectividad fueron: respuesta objetiva y porcentaje de cirugía conservadora en neoadyuvancia, y en cáncer de mama metastásico, tiempo para la progresión. Los costes se consideraron según datos de adquisición de fármacos. Para determinar la robustez de los resultados se realizó un análisis de sensibilidad, modificando costes y efectividad. Resultados: Los resultados muestran una mayor efectividad para los inhibidores de la aromatasa que para los antiestrógenos. En terapia neoadyuvante: 56,38 frente a 36% en tasa de respuesta objetiva, y 47,64 frente a 35% en cirugía conservadora. En cáncer metastásico: 9,96 frente a 6,61 meses de tiempo para la progresión (p = 0,05). El análisis farmacoeconómico demostró que la elección del anastrozol supone un coste por unidad extra de efectividad de 969 y 779 euros para la respuesta objetiva y cirugía conservadora, respectivamente; mientras que en cáncer metastásico supone 56.525 euros por unidad extra de efectividad. El análisis de sensibilidad no modificó los resultados. Conclusiones: La elección de los inhibidores de la aromatasa es una opción válida en neoadyuvancia, aunque su elección en cáncer metastásico supondría un coste muy elevado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;30(2): 71-77, mar.-abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio coste-efectividad de la terapia hormonal en primera línea en pacientes postmenopáusicas en cáncer de mama metastásico y en tratamiento neoadyuvante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
