<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117747</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sex is good, but I can't. Representations of chronically wounded women and men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Perceive and analyze social representations about sex, elaborated by women and men who have been chronically wounded. Methods: Qualitative study. Data were collected from fifty-one adults, patients of a public hospital in Salvador, through the Free Word Association Test and the in-depth Interview, and subsequently through Theme Content Analysis. Results: Three apprehended categories, meaningful to understand the sexual behavior of wounded men and women will be discussed: sex is good and healthy; sex may worsen wounds and, sex is something prohibited. Wounded people avoid sexual relations because they believe it may imply loss of vitality or that they will be less healthy. Conclusions: Nursing professionals can interfere with therapeutic listening for a re-elaboration of those representations, demystifying taboos that may compromise the satisfaction of a sexual relation and the quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Paiva, Mirian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza de Santana Carvalho, Evanilda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Aparício, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Aprehender y analizar las representaciones sociales sobre el sexo, elaboradas por mujeres y hombres crónicamente heridos. Metodología: Estudio cualitativo. Análisis de contenido temático a partir de la aplicación del Test de Asociación Libre de Palabras y de Entrevistas en semi-estructuradas. Resultados principales: Surgieron tres categorías de análisis: el sexo es bueno y hace bien a la salud, el sexo puede empeorar la herida y el sexo es algo prohibido. Se concluye que las personas con heridas crónicas tienden a abstenerse de mantener relaciones sexuales por creer que podría conllevar implicaciones negativas para su salud y vitalidad. Conclusión principal: El personal de enfermería puede intervenir a través de la escucha terapéutica en la reelaboración de estas representaciones, desmitificando tabúes que comprometan la satisfacción de las necesidades sexuales de estas personas y su calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;22(3): 137-141, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El sexo es bueno, pero no puedo. Representaciones de mujeres y hombres con heridas crónicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
