<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15501</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ideal transpulmonary pressure for excised lungs. Morphometric study of the rat</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We carried out this study to propose a transpulmonary pressure (TPP) which will permit the utmost fixation of a lung in which artefacts are produced. 80 rats were used divided into two age groups: adults and older animals. These groups were then organised into four sub-groups according to the TPP used for the fixation: 20, 25, 30, and 35 cm H2O They were fixed by airway with formalin at 10% Lung volume was measured and a descriptive histological and morphometric study was made. The results obtained in the adult animals reveal a direct relation with the TPP. As the TPP was elevated, the pulmonary aerial volume and the internal alveolar surface increased significantly in the lungs fixed at 25, 30, and 35 cm H2O cm as compared to those fixed at 20 H2O. The alveolar cord diminished significantly in the three groups fixed at the higher pressure as compared with that of the 20 cm H2O group. The number of alveoli and the tissue volume increased significantly when the TPP was raised from 20 to 30 cm H2O and from 30 to 35 cm H2O. Only the older animals showed significant differences in the alveolar cord when the TPP was raised from 20 to 25 cm H2O. We propose that in the adult animals the TPP of 25 cm H2O is the most adequate for king fixation; the TPP of 35 cm H2O is that which most distended the lung. However, the increase in tissue volume suggests the possibility that tissue edema has occurred. In the lungs of older animals, the slight differences found suggest that any of the TPP utilised may be used since the lungs were barely modified by them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Llevamos a cabo este estudio con vistas a proponer una presión transpulmonar (PTP) que permitiese el mayor grado de fijación de un pulmón en el que se producen artefactos. Se emplearon 80 ratas, divididas en dos grupos de edad: adultos y animales más viejos. Estos grupos fueron ulteriormente divididos en cuatro subgrupos según la PTP empleada para la fijación: 20, 25, 30, y 35 cm H2O. Fueron fijados por aire con 10 por ciento formalina. Se midió el volumen pulmonar y se realizó un estudio histológico y morfométrico descriptivo. Los resultados obtenidos en los animales adultos apuntaron hacia la existencia de una relación directa con la PTP. Conforme se fuera elevando la PTP, el volumen arterial pulmonar y la superficie alveolar interna aumentaron significativamente en los pulmones fijados a 25, 30, y 35 cm H2O cm en comparación con los fijados a 20 H2O. El cordón alveolar disminuyó de una manera significativa en los tres grupos fijados a la presión superior en comparación con el del grupo de 20 cm H2O. El número de alvéolos y el volumen tisular aumentaron significativamente cuando la PTP fue elevada desde 20 hasta 30 cm H2O y desde 30 hasta 35 cm H2O. Solamente los animales más viejos mostraban diferencias significativas en el cordón alveolar cuando la PTP fue elevada desde 20 hasta 25 cm H2O.Proponemos que en los animales adultos una PTP de 25 cm H2O sería la más adecuada para la fijación pulmonar: la PTP de 35 cm H2O fue la que más distendió al pulmón. Sin embargo, el aumento en el volumen tisular sugiere la posibilidad de que haya tenido lugar un edema tisular. En los pulmones de los animales más viejos, las ligeras diferencias apreciadas sugieren que cualquiera de las PTP utilizadas podría ser usada puesto que los pulmones apenas fueron modificados por ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;4(1): 53-60, mayo 2000. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presión transpulmonar ideal para los pulmones escindidos. Estudio morfométrico en la rata</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Garisa, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escolar, Juan de Dios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escolar, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roques, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15501</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27866</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27867^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
