<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139098</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of methadone reduction in outpatients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Methadone reduction treatment after a substitutive maintenance treatment still has a clinical interest in the care of patients with opioid addiction. Recent studies about agonist drugs and success in methadone detoxification have provided relevant information, but it is also interesting to explore the possible influence of other factors. The main goal of this research was to analyze the variables that can better predict achieving a zero dose of methadone. Three years monitoring of methadone detoxification in a sample of 81 outpatients treated at 16 clinics is presented. The findings suggest that agreement between the clinic staff and the patient, low scores on perceived stress before starting dose reduction, drugs support and social care during the intervention are the group of variables with more advantages for achieving a zero dose of methadone. These results could facilitate a prognosis, guide clinicians in prescribing intervention, and improve procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almedros, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrobles, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La retirada de metadona tras un tratamiento sustitutivo de mantenimiento continúa siendo de interés clínico en la atención a pacientes con adicción a opiáceos. Estudios recientes sobre el empleo de fármacos agonistas y el éxito en la desintoxicación de metadona han aportado datos relevantes, pero también resulta de interés explorar la posible influencia de otros factores. Nuestro estudio tiene como principal objetivo analizar las variables que puedan predecir mejor el logro de dosis cero de metadona. Para ello, se presenta la evolución durante tres años de la retirada de metadona en 81 pacientes atendidos en 16 centros ambulatorios. Los resultados sugieren que el acuerdo entre el equipo terapéutico y el paciente, bajas puntuaciones en estrés percibido antes de iniciar la reducción de dosis, el empleo de fármacos de apoyo y la atención social durante la desintoxicación, forman el conjunto de variables con mayores ventajas para el logro de dosis cero de metadona. Estos resultados podrían facilitar el pronóstico de la intervención, orientar a los facultativos en la oportunidad de la prescripción y mejorar los  procedimientos empleados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(1): 85-106, ene.-abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables predictoras del tratamiento de retirada de metadona en pacientes ambulatorios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54217</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54222</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
