<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037373</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rigid painful shoulder. Involvement of suprascapular nerve in its etiology and assessment of treatment with selective blocks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Assess suprascapular nerve condition in patients with rigid painful shoulder and its course after block of suprascapular nerve and conventional treatment. Design. Prospective, comparative, double blind, both groups. Patients and methods. 37 patients with retractile capsulitis of poor evolution. There are 21 females and 16 males. Mean age 51.4 years. Electromyographic assessments and selective block of suprascapular nerve, assessment of pain by VAS and functional scale (Constant-Murley scale).Statistical analysis. SPSS program for Windows, version11.5, using the Student&#146;s T test for the analysis of paired data. Results. 21 patients had suprascapular nerve lesion. Greater incidence in patients with traumatic background(p &lt;= 0.01). Pain intensity abated to half on the VAS after the1st month and practically disappeared at the end (at 3rd-6thmonth) in both groups. Assessment with the Constant scale was significantly greater (p &lt;= 0.05) in patients with suprascapular nerve lesion (immediate assessment after block) and was not in assessments conducted at one month and the end of the treatment. Scores greater than 65 points were achieved after month 1 of treatment in both groups. A total of 14 % of the patients with suprascapular nerve lesion required surgical treatment. Conclusions. Supraescapular nerve lesion is frequent in rigid painful shoulders of poor evolution (56.7 %), especially if there is previous traumatism (80 %). Its selective block in the coracoid notch with approach technique is effective, both if there is an associated nervous lesion or not and should be considered in the programming of the treatments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Rebollo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rioja Toro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Andrés, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Poy, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre Climent, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar el estado del nervio supraescapular en pacientes con hombro doloroso rígido y su evolución tras el bloqueo del nervio supraescapular y el tratamiento convencional. Diseño. Prospectivo, comparativo doble ciego ambos grupos. Pacientes y métodos. 37 pacientes con capsulitis retráctil de mala evolución: 21 del sexo femenino y 16 del masculino; edad media: 51,4 años. Se han realizado valoraciones electromiografías y bloqueos selectivos del nervio supraescapular, valoraciones del dolor mediante la escala analógica visual y funcional (escala de Constant-Murley).Análisis estadístico. Programa SPSS para Windows, versión11.5, utilizando la t de Student para el análisis de los datos apareados. Resultados. Presentaban lesión del nervio supraescapular21 pacientes. Mayor incidencia en pacientes con antecedentes traumáticos (p&lt;=0,01). La intensidad del dolor remitió a la mitad en la escala analógica visual a partir del primer mes y prácticamente desapareció al finalizar (a los 3-6 meses), en ambos grupos. La valoración con escala de Constant fue significativamente mayor (p&lt;=0,05) en pacientes con lesión del nervio supraescapular(inmediata al bloqueo) y no lo fue en valoraciones realizadas al mes y al finalizar el tratamiento. Puntuaciones superiores a 65 puntos se consiguen a partir del primer mes de tratamiento en ambos grupos. El 14 % de los pacientes con lesión del nervio supraescapular precisó tratamiento quirúrgico. Conclusiones. La lesión del nervio supraescapular es frecuente en hombros rígidos dolorosos de mala evolución (56,7 %),máxime si hay traumatismo previo (80 %). Su bloqueo selectivo en la escotadura coracoidea con técnica de aproximación es efectiva, tanto si existe lesión nerviosa asociada como si no y debe considerarse en la programación de los tratamientos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(3): 103-112, mayo-jun. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hombro doloroso rígido: implicación del nervio supraescapular en su etiología y valoración del tratamiento con bloqueos selectivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2095^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s22037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9601^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
