<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155879</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polyarthritis and membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis as paraneoplastic manifestation of Hodgkin's lymphoma: a case report and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paraneoplastic syndromes can be presented in multiple ways, which include endocrinological, hematologic, rheumatologic and nephrologic manifestations. While most of the publications described solid tumors as responsible for these manifestations, hematologic neoplasms are important cause to consider as part of the differential diagnosis. We report the case of a 46 year-old man with seronegative symmetric polyarthritis of large and small joints associated with membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis with deposits of immune complexes and acute impairment of renal function, as part of a paraneoplastic syndrome secondary of a classical Hodgkin lymphoma with bone marrow invasion, which reversed completely with chemotherapy treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mella, Cristian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Angela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roessler, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valladares, Ximena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erlij, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los síndromes paraneoplásicos pueden presentarse de múltiples maneras, dentro de las cuales destacan las manifestaciones endocrinológicas, reumatológicas, hematológicas y nefrológicas. Si bien la mayoría de las publicaciones describen los tumores sólidos como responsables de dichos cuadros, las neoplasias hematológicas son causa importante a considerar como parte del diagnóstico diferencial. Se presenta el caso de un varón de 46 años con un cuadro de poliartritis simétrica seronegativa de grandes y pequeñas articulaciones, asociado a glomerulonefritis membranoproliferativa con depósitos de inmunocomplejos y deterioro agudo de la función renal, como parte de un síndrome paraneoplásico secundario a un linfoma de Hodgkin clásico con invasión medular, el cual revirtió completamente con el tratamiento de quimioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);12(5): 282-284, sept.-oct. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Poliartritis y glomerulonefritis membranoproliferativa como manifestaciones paraneoplásicas de linfoma de Hodgkin: presentación de un caso y revisión de literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10385^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6065^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24023^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6065^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22497^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15152^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
