<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109380</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strongyloidiasis in children: difficulty of diagnostic and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Strongyloidiasis is a parasitic endemic disease in tropical zones, usually asymptomatic but in immunodepressed patients can induce an hyperinfection and a serious disseminated disease. We report a case of an 18 months old girl from Ethiopia, that comes to consultation with abdominal bloating and diarrhea. Initially was diagnosed and treated as a giardiasis but a clinical improvement was not obtained. Because of the rise of eosinophilia and the persistence of the symptoms, the microbiological studies were repeated and Strongyloides stercoralis larvae were detected in stools. It was treated with albendazole achieving a good result. Strongyloidiasis is a disease that implies diagnostic difficulties, for his symptomatology, for the reliability of the diagnostic tests and for the low incident in our country. The treatment in adults is well established, but in children younger than 2-year-old there is scanty information about the drug of choice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Lombardía, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estrongiloidosis es una enfermedad parasitaria endémica en zonas tropicales, casi siempre asintomática, pero en pacientes inmunodeprimidos puede provocar una hiperinfección y una enfermedad diseminada severa. Presentamos el caso de una niña de 18 meses de edad, procedente de Etiopía, que acude a la consulta por presentar distensión abdominal y diarrea. Se diagnosticó inicialmente como una giardiasis, y se trató sin que se obtuviese mejoría clínica. Ante la aparición de eosinofilia y la persistencia de los síntomas, se repitieron los estudios microbiológicos y se aislaron larvas de Strongyloides stercoralis en heces. Fue tratada con albendazol, con buenos resultados. La estrongiloidosis es una enfermedad que plantea dificultades diagnósticas por su sintomatología, la escasa rentabilidad de las pruebas diagnósticas y su baja incidencia en nuestro medio. El tratamiento en adultos está bien establecido, pero en menores de 2 años hay cierta controversia en cuanto al fármaco de elección(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;70(10): 408-408[e31-e34], nov. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrongiloidosis en niños: dificultad de diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24511^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19221^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30492^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14204^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30492^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7574^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7574^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
