<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83425</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Watchful waiting in incidental adenocarcinoma of the prostate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To describe the outcome of patients diagnosed of incidental prostate adenocarcinoma managed by watchful waiting. Material and methods: We included patients with PSA&lt;4ng/mL or higher with previous negative biopsy, who underwent surgery for BPH being diagnosed of incidental prostate adenocarcinoma. We performed a descriptive and retrospective study in patients with this diagnosis between 1992 and 2007. Salvage curative treatment was offered to those patients who progressed. Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS program. Progression variables were: age, preoperative and postoperative PSA, stage, Gleason score, prostate volume, initial treatment, PSA evolution and salvage treatment if necessary. Results: 47 patients were diagnosed of incidental prostatic adenocarcinoma, finding an incidence of 4.25%. The medium follo up was 37 months. Of the patients who opted for watchful waiting, 72,5% remain on it. 11 patients progressed. Postoperative PSA and Gleason score showed up as prognostic variables of progression in T1a stage and postsurgery PSA did so in T1b patients. Conclusion: Watchful waiting is a useful option in patients with incidental prostate adenocarcinoma and favourable prognostic criteria. Postoperative PSA and Gleason score can predict progression in T1a stage and postoperative PSA in T1b stage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cerdá, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pontones Moreno, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trassierra Villa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dicapua Sacoto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán Pascual, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la evolución de los pacientes con adenocarcinoma de próstata incidental manejados mediante actitud expectante. Material y métodos: Se incluyen pacientes intervenidos de hiperplasia benigna prostática, con PSA &lt;4ng/ml o &gt; de 4 con biopsia previa negativa para tumor, diagnosticándose de adenocarcinoma prostático incidental al analizar la muestra. Se realiza un estudio retrospectivo y descriptivo, en pacientes con este diagnóstico entre 1992 y 2007. Se ofreció tratamiento curativo de rescate con prostatectomía radical/radioterapia a los pacientes que progresaron. El análisis estadístico se realiza mediante el programa SPSS. Las variables de progresión analizadas son: edad, PSA prequirúrgico y posquirúrgico, estadio, Gleason, volumen prostático, tratamiento inicial, evolución de PSA y tratamiento diferido. Resultados: 47 pacientes fueron diagnosticados de adenocarcinoma prostático incidental, encontrando una incidencia de 4,25%, con un seguimiento medio de 37 meses. De los pacientes que optaron por actitud expectante, el 72,5% permanecen en vigilancia. Once pacientes progresaron. El grado de Gleason y el PSA posquirúrgico resultaron variables de progresión en el estadio T1a y el PSA posquirúrgico en el estadio T1b. Conclusiones: La actitud expectante es una opción adecuada en pacientes con adenocarcinoma de próstata incidental con criterios de buen pronóstico. El PSA posquirúrgico y el grado de Gleason son variables que pueden predecir la progresión de pacientes en estadio T1a y el PSA posquirúrgico lo es en el estadio T1b (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(10): 854-859, nov.-dic. 2010. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83425</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitud expectante en el adenocarcinoma incidental de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
