<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140026</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteoporosis and body mass index in renal transplant recipients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: frequently after kidney transplantation there is an increase in weight with a resulting high percent of obesity in these recipients. This combined with a rapid loss of bone mass, a higher prevalence of osteoporosis and fractures is evident than in normal populations. Objectives: to explore the relationship between body mass index (BMI) and prevalence of osteoporosis in a population of renal transplant recipients. Methods: prospective longitudinal study design. The study was conducted on 306 kidney transplant recipients. The relationship between weigh and body mass index with femoral and lumbar osteopenia and osteoporosis prevalence at the moment of transplant and at 12 months post was explored. Results: there was a high prevalence of overweight (35.6%) and obese (14.1%) recipients after renal transplant and 1 year after (42.2% and 24.2% respectively). Significant differences were found(p=0.049) between the weight at the time of transplant and the presence of osteopenia or osteoporosis at the lumbar level one year after, the highest weights were in recipients with osteoporosis. The mean BMI was higher (p=0.028) in osteoporotic patients (26.59 kg/m2) than in patients with osteopenia (24.23 kg/m2). Conclusion: results seem to be consistent with recent studies in the general population showing excessive weight as a possible factor detrimental to the bone health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteban de la Rosa, Rafael José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Martínez, Ana Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Soto, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Castillo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ruiz, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: tras el trasplante renal es frecuente un aumento de peso, así como un elevado porcentaje de obesidad en estos pacientes. Por otro lado, tras el trasplante se produce una pérdida de la masa ósea, siendo la prevalencia de osteoporosis y fracturas óseas mayor que en la población general. Objetivos: explorar la relación entre el índice de masa corporal y la prevalencia de osteopenia y osteoporosis en una población de trasplantados renales. Material y método: estudio longitudinal prospectivo sobre una muestra de 306 trasplantados renales. Se exploraron las relaciones entre el peso y el índice de masa corporal con la prevalencia de osteopenia y osteoporosis a nivel femoral y lumbar en el momento del trasplante y a los 12 meses del mismo. Resultados: se halló una alta prevalencia de sobrepeso (35,6%) y obesidad (14,1%) tras el trasplante renal y al año del mismo (42,2% y 24,2%, respectivamente). Se hallaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas (p=0,049) entre el peso en el momento del trasplante y la presencia de osteopenia u osteoporosis al año del mismo a nivel lumbar, siendo el peso medio más elevado entre los pacientes con osteoporosis. La media del IMC fue más elevada (p=0,028) en los pacientes osteoporóticos (26,59 kg/m2) que en los pacientes con osteopenia (24,23 kg/m2). Conclusiones: nuestros resultados parecen estar en concordancia con recientes estudios realizados en la población general, que muestran el sobrepeso como un posible factor perjudicial para el hueso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(2): 872-877, ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteoporosis e índice de masa corporal en el trasplantado renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
