<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044132</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Case report of acute coronary syndrome due to cocaine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Cocaine consumption frequently produces cardiovascular problems. We analyse the case of a patient with cardiac symptoms after consuming cocaine. Material and methods: The case of a 41 year old male in A&amp;E with acute chest pain that does not cease spontaneously after sniffing cocaine is examined. Results: On admittance, a physical examination and electrocardiogram are carried out. The corresponding treatment is then given with a complete remission of the symptoms, the alterations in the ECG and a normalization of life signs. The diagnosis of secondary coronary vasospasm due to cocaine is established. Conclusions: Cocaine consumption, in some cases, provokes cardiac vasospasm, in both vessels with atheromatosis lesions visible in x-rays and apparently healthy coronary arteries. The greater the dosis or purity of the cocaine, the greater the vasospasm. The appearance of a deferred acute coronary syndrome (hours or days) following acute cocaine intoxication has also been described</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lloret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El consumo de cocaína desencadena con frecuencia problemas cardiovasculares. Se analiza el caso de un paciente varón de 41 años, con sintomatología cardíaca tras consumo de cocaína. Material y métodos: Se examina el caso clínico de un paciente que acude al servicio de urgencias por presentar dolor torácico agudo, que no cede espontáneamente, después de haber esnifado cocaína. Resultados: Se realiza una exploración física y electrocardiográfica al ingreso, tras la cual se instaura el tratamiento correspondiente, con remisión completa de la sintomatología, las alteraciones del electrocardiograma y normalización de los signos vitales. Se establece el diagnóstico de vasospasmo coronario secundario a cocaína. Conclusiones: El consumo de cocaína, en algunos casos, provoca vasospasmo cardíaco, tanto en vasos con lesiones ateromatosas visibles radiológicamente como en arterias coronarias aparentemente sanas. A mayor dosis o mayor pureza de la cocaína se produce mayor vasospasmo. También se ha descrito la aparición de síndrome coronario agudo de forma diferida (horas o días) después de una intoxicación aguda por cocaína</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;7(4): 219-225, oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome coronario agudo por cocaína. Manejo inicial en el servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30340^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d321^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
