<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048349</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Etiopathogenesis of Kallmann&#146;s syndrome: genotype-phenotype associations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Kallmann's syndrome is a congenital disease due to an alteration in the growth and migration of the embryonic cells of the olfactory placode (olfactory neurones and gonadotropin-releasing hormone-secreting neurones) and is characterized by the association of anosmia/hyposmia and hypogonadism. The alteration in the KAL-2 gene, which codifies for the fibroblast growth factor receptor (FGFR1), is responsible for most dominant autosomal transmissions; the less frequent alteration of the KAL-1 gene, which codifies for anosmin-1, is related to familial X-linked transmissions. These genetic alterations produce a failure in the fibroblast growth factor signal during morphogenesis of the olfactory bulbs. The lack of olfactory axon migrations results in an olfactory bulb aplasia and also affects the migration of gonadotropin-releasing hormone-secreting neurons, which usually follow the olfactory axons through the pituitary gland</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Udina Bonet, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras González, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Kallmann es una enfermedad congénita debida a una alteración en el crecimiento y migración de las células embrionarias de la placoda olfatoria (neuronas olfatorias y productoras de hormona liberadora de gonadotropinas), y que se caracteriza por la asociación de anosmia, hiposmia e hipogonadismo. El gen KAL-2 codifica el receptor de los factores de crecimiento de los fibroblastos (FGFR1) y su alteración causa la mayoría de las transmisiones autosómicas dominantes. La alteración del gen KAL-1, que codifica la anosmina-1, es menos frecuente y explica los casos ligados al X de transmisión familiar. Estas alteraciones genéticas comportan una insuficiencia en la señal de los factores de crecimiento del fibroblasto durante la morfogénesis de los bulbos olfatorios y una migración deficitaria de las células olfatorias. Asimismo, la migración de las células que secretan gonadotrofinas también se afectará, ya que, en condiciones normales, siguen el camino que marcan los axones olfatorios para llegar a la hipófisis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(8): 519-524, oct. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048349</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiopatogenia del síndrome de Kallmann. Relación genotípica-fenotípica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30678^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30678^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29311^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5481^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
