<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043589</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pregnancy in a patient with systemic lupus erythematosus on hemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of successful pregnancy in a 29-year-old woman who had been undergoing renal replacement treatment for 7 years due to systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). We describe the course of the pregnancy from diagnosis and its management. We conclude that pregnancy in patients with SLE on renal replacement with hemodialysis is a risk factor for the mother and fetus; nevertheless the number of successful pregnancies in patients on hemodialysis is increasing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Esteban, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Marfil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Parra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de gestación en una paciente de 29 años de edad en tratamiento sustitutivo renal durante 7 años en hemodiálisis por nefropatía lúpica, y que finalizó el embarazo con éxito. Describimos la evolución de la gestación desde su diagnóstico y el tratamiento seguido. Concluimos que el embarazo en pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico en tratamiento sustitutivo con hemodiálisis supone un riesgo para la madre y para el feto, aunque se observa un aumento del éxito en las gestaciones en pacientes en diálisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);33(1): 35-37, ene.-feb. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embarazo en una paciente con lupus eritematoso sistémico en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
