<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92702</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breakage of needles in clinical dentistry: causes and recommendations for action</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dental needles are a much used instrument in routine techniques such as anesthesia. The breakage of needles in dentistry has become an unusual complication since the introduction of disposable needles, none the less, the serious consequences that can result from leaving the end of a needle in the patient means we must consider a protocol for action. Symptoms that may appear following the breakage of a needle include pain, infection, inflammation, trismus, dysphagia and even hemorrhage. Locating the remains of a needle after the event of an accidental breakage is vita land is done using Computerized Tomography and auxiliary needles. The most effective methods to prevent these adverse circumstances are to ensure the adequate cooperation of the patient, select a needle of the appropriate length and caliber, apply a standardized procedure with great care and attention, and have hemostasis pincers at hand for the direct and immediate extraction of the pieces in the case that, despite precautionary measures, a break age were to occur (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobo Vázquez, Carlos M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Marín, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajo González, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago Sáez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Pérez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las agujas odontológicas son un instrumento muy empleado para técnicas de rutina como la anestesia. La rotura de agujas en odontología es una complicación poco frecuente desde el uso de agujas desechables, sin embargo, las graves consecuencias que provoca el abandono del extremo roto en el paciente, obliga a tener en consideración un protocolo de actuación. Tras la rotura de una aguja pueden aparecer síntomas como dolor, infección, inflamación, trismo, disfagia e incluso hemorragia. La localización de un resto de aguja diferido en el tiempo tras una rotura accidental es vital y se realizará mediante Tomografía Computerizada y agujas auxiliares. Las medidas de prevención más efectivas para evitar este evento adverso consisten en establecer una adecuada cooperación por parte del paciente, seleccionar una aguja de longitud y calibre suficientes, realizar una técnica estandarizada y cuidadosa y disponer de pinzas de hemostasia para la extracción directa e inmediata por si a pesar de estas medidas se produjera la rotura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);8(1): 41-49, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura de agujas en la clínica odontológica: causas y recomendaciones de actuación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d776^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
