<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152203</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New hybrid simulator to teach pain procedures for refractory pain management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper introduces a new simulator to be used in the training and evaluation of interventional techniques under fluoroscopic visualization in pain medicine, apt for repeating the most broadly used procedures in the head and neck, trunk, lumbosacral region and pelvis. This simulator is built using cadaveric bones in synthetic transparent material for training in nerve block procedures under combined ultrasonic and fluoroscopic guidance. The 'New Hybrid Simulator' comprises the use of cadaveric bones surrounded by synthetic material resembling human models in a highly realistic manner. The trainees that attended the workshops during 2014 expressed a high degree of satisfaction when comparing this model to practicing on real patients, fresh cadavers and synthetic simulators. The salient features of this development are: repeating the procedures as many times as necessary for each trainee to meet the minimum requirements and reduce the number and type of potential errors in each technique; conducting appropriate training for certification purposes; facilitating the evaluation of efficacy of training using these models as compared to training on real patients or other modalities (simulators or fresh cadavers); improving accessibility given its low cost, thus avoiding the complexity involved in the preservation of tissues and finally, in the author's opinion reducing the learning curve in a safe setting for patients, trainees, trainers and for the healthcare and university systems at large (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flores, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un nuevo simulador para el entrenamiento y evaluación de técnicas intervencionistas bajo visión fluoroscópica en medicina del dolor que permite realizar los procedimientos más utilizados a nivel de cabeza y cuello, tronco, región lumbosacra y pelvis. En el trabajo se desarrolló una inclusión de material óseo cadavérico en material sintético versión no transparente color piel y transparente para entrenamiento en bloqueos bajo visión ecográfica y fluoroscópica combinados. El Nuevo Simulador Híbrido se basó en la inclusión artesanal de material óseo cadavérico dentro de un tejido de material sintético emulando, con elevado realismo, el modelo humano. En la experiencia de los educandos que realizaron los talleres durante el año 2014 expresaron alta satisfacción comparando a pacientes reales, cadáveres frescos y simuladores sintéticos. Este desarrollo permite, como características principales: a) repetir cada procedimiento las veces necesarias para que cada educando alcance un estándar mínimo exigible y disminuya el número y tipo de errores posibles propios de cada técnica; b) entrenar adecuadamente para los procesos de certificación; c) facilitar evaluar la eficacia de entrenar con estos modelos frente al entrenamiento en pacientes reales u otras formas de entrenamiento (simuladores o cadáveres frescos); d) mejorar la accesibilidad por su bajo costo evitando la complejidad de la preservación de tejidos, y e) permitir, en opinión del autor, reducir la curva de aprendizaje en un medio seguro para paciente, educando, docente y el sistema de salud y universitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;23(2): 105-114, mar.-abr. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevo simulador híbrido cadavérico/sintético para la enseñanza de técnicas intervencionistas para tratamiento del dolor refractario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8479^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56169^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56169^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56169^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
