<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055787</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of streptococcal pharyngitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective        To determine the incidence of streptococcal pharyngitis        in patients younger than 2 years of age, and to evaluate        the role of group C streptococci as a pathogenic agent in        acute pharyngitis through throat culture in symptomatic        patients.        Material and methods        We performed a retrospective descriptive study of patients        with clinical symptoms of acute pharyngitis and fast        detection of streptococcal antigen and/or exudate culture        who attended the emergency department between February        2004 and February 2005.        Results        Group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus (GAS) was isolated        by pharyngeal culture in 85 patients aged less than        2 years (12.6 %). In these patients the fast test displayed        lower sensitivity and positive predictive value (PPV) (sensitivity:        78 %; PPV: 69 %, p &lt; 0.01). Patients aged less than        2 years had a greater frequency fever, exanthema and catarrhal        symptoms than older children (p &lt; 0.01). In the        younger age group, erythromycin resistance rates increased        to 24.7 % (p   0.08).        Group C streptococcus was isolated in 5,2% (43 patients).        The most frequent reason for consultation was        fever (74.4 %) and the most common findings on examination        were abnormal pharynx in 90.7 %, odynophagia        and adenopathies in 55.8 %. Two incidence peaks (in May        and September) were observed, with sporadic cases        throughout the year.        Conclusions        In our sample, the percentage of GAS in patients aged        less than 2 years was higher than that reported in other series.        In this age group, the sensitivity of the fast test is low-er than in other age groups and there is a higher rate of        erythromycin resistance. The percentage of tonsillitis due        to serotype C was also slightly higher than expected. Two        peaks of incidence were observed, similar to those occurring        with SGA, with sporadic cases throughout the year</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merello Godino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Míguez Navarro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riaño Méndez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez López, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalba Citores, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Soler, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marañón Pardillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo        Determinar la incidencia de infección estreptocócica en        pacientes menores de 2 años y la frecuencia y distribución        estacional del serotipo C mediante cultivo de exudado faríngeo        en pacientes sintomáticos.        Material y métodos        Estudio retrospectivo, descriptivo de los pacientes con        clínica faringoamigdalar aguda y positividad de test de        detección rápida de antígeno estreptocócico y/o cultivo        de exudado faríngeo, que acudieron a urgencias en el período        de un año (febrero de 2004-febrero de 2005).        Resultados        El estreptococo del grupo A (SGA) se aisló mediante cultivo        faríngeo en 85 pacientes menores de 2 años (12,6 %).        En estos pacientes el test rápido presentaba menor sensibilidad        (S) y valor predictivo positivo (VPP) (S 78%-VPP        69 %; p &lt; 0,01).        Los menores de 2 años presentaban con más frecuencia        fiebre, exantema y síntomas catarrales con respecto al grupo        de niños mayores (p &lt; 0,01). En este grupo de edad aumentan        las tasas de resistencia a eritromicina hasta el        24,7 % (p   0,08).        El estreptococo del grupo C se aisló en un 5,2 % (43). La        fiebre fue el motivo de consulta más frecuente (74,4 %),        los hallazgos más habituales en la exploración fueron la        faringe anormal en un 90,7 %, odinofagia y adenopatías        en un 55,8 %. Observamos 2 picos de incidencia en mayo        y en septiembre, con casos esporádicos durante todo el        año.        Conclusiones        En nuestra muestra hemos encontrado un porcentaje        superior a otras series de SGA en pacientes menores de        2 años. En este grupo de edad, se observa menor sensibilidad        del test rápido, así como mayor tasa de resistencia a        eritromicina.        El porcentaje de amigdalitis por serotipo C encontrado,        es también ligeramente superior al esperado. Se observan        2 picos de incidencia similares a los presentados por SGA,        con casos esporádicos durante todo el año</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(3): 220-224, sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de faringitis estreptocócica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
