<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113612</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reference values of waist circumference and waist/hip ratio in children and adolescents of Mérida, Venezuela: Comparison with international references</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo collect regional reference values of waist circumference (WC), and waist/hip ratio (WHR) in children and adolescents from Merida, Venezuela, and to compare them to international references.Subjects and methodsA total of 919 students aged 9-17 years from public and private educational establishments were assessed. Weight, height, WC, and WHR were measured. Outliers (± 3 SD Z-Score) were excluded from the data collected. Percentile distribution of the tested variables was done by age and sex.ResultsFifty-one percent of subjects were female, and 52.7% were from public institutions. WC (p=0.001) and WHR (p=0.0001) were statistically higher in boys. With advancing age, WC increased in both sexes, while WHR showed the opposite behavior (p=0.0001 for both). The 90th percentile (pc) for WC ranged from 69.7 and 83.6cm in girls and from 69.2 and 86.7cm in boys. The 90th pc values of WHR ranged from 0.79 and 0.91 in girls and from 0.86 and 0.93 in boys. Overall, our WC and WHR values were lower than North American values and similar to those of some Latin American references.ConclusionPercentile reference charts for WC and WHR specific for age and sex, obtained from a representative sample of children and adolescents from Mérida, Venezuela, are provided. They may be used regionally, both for individual assessment and to implement prevention policies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de trabajo CREDEFAR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoObtener valores de referencia regionales de la circunferencia de la cintura (CC) e índice de la cintura/cadera (Ci/Ca) en escolares y adolescentes de la ciudad de Mérida (Venezuela) y comparar con referencias internacionales.Materiales y métodosSe evaluaron 919 estudiantes de 9 a 18 años de unidades educativas públicas y privadas. Se tomaron medidas de peso, talla, CC y Ci/Ca. Los datos obtenidos fueron explorados excluyendo los valores atípicos (± 3 DE Z-Score). Se realizó la distribución por percentiles (pc) de las variables estudiadas según edad y sexo.ResultadosEl 51% eran de sexo femenino y el 52,7% pertenecían a instituciones públicas. La CC (p=0,001) y el índice Ci/Ca (p=0,0001) fueron significativamente mayores en los niños. Con el avance de la edad la CC aumentó en ambos sexos. Comportamiento inverso tuvo la relación Ci/Ca (p=0,0001 para ambos). El pc90 para la CC osciló entre los 69,7 y los 83,6cm en las niñas y entre los 69,2 y los 86,7cm en los niños. Los valores de Ci/Ca del pc90 en las niñas estuvieron entre 0,79 y 0,91 y en los niños entre 0,86 y 0,93. En general, nuestros valores de la CC fueron más bajos que los norteamericanos y similares a algunos de Latinoamérica.ConclusiónSe presentan tablas de referencia por pc específicas por edad y sexo para la CC y Ci/Ca en una muestra representativa de niños y adolescentes de la ciudad de Mérida (Venezuela) que pueden ser usadas regionalmente tanto para la evaluación individual como para la implementación de políticas preventivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(5): 235-242, mayo 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia de la circunferencia de la cintura e índice de la cintura/cadera en escolares y adolescentes de Mérida, Venezuela: comparación con referencias internacionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
