<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139891</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Degree of psychological commitment to exercise in young athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective was to analyze the effects of affective, personal and demographic variables in the degree of psychological commitment to exercise (DPCE). 286 athletes aged between 10 and 19 years of both sexes participated in the study. We used the Commitment Exercise Scale, the Body Shape Questionnaire and the &#147;Criterion of Economic Classification Brazil&#148; to assess the DPCE, body dissatisfaction and socioeconomic status, respectively. The results showed significant effects for females (p = .001). These same analyzes for males showed no significant effects. It was concluded that affective, personal and demographic factors promoted effects in DPCE only in females (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortes, Leonardo S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, Sebastião S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Maria EC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgado, Fabiane FR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo fue analizar los efectos de los variables afectivos, personales y demográficos en el grado de compromiso psicológico para ejercer (GCPE). 286 atletas de edades comprendidas entre 10 y 19 años de ambos sexos participaron en el estudio. Se utilizó la Commitment Exercise Scale, la Body Shape Questionnaire y el &#147;Criterio de Clasificación Económica Brasil&#148; para evaluar el GCPE, la insatisfacción corporal y nivel socioeconómico, respectivamente. Los resultados mostraron efectos significativos para las mujeres (p = .001). Estos mismos análisis para los machos no mostraron efectos significativos. Se concluyó que la afectiva, factores personales y demográficos promovió efectos en GPCE sólo en las mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(2): 225-232, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grado de compromiso psicológico para ejercer en los atletas jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
