<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91162</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the management of non-ST segment elevation myocardial infarction during emergency care according to sex of the patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The atypical characteristics of acute coronary syndrome in women lead to differences in management and treatment. We investigated these differences in the urgent management of non-ST-segment acute myocardial infarction (NSTEMI). Data on 39 variables were collected from 539 patients with NSTEMI treated at 97 Spanish emergency departments. After adjustment for 10 baseline differences, the only significant differences were that time-to-arrival at the emergency department was longer for women (odds ratio [OR]=0.52; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.28-0.95) and that they received more clopidogrel (OR=1.65; 95% CI, 1.06-2.56). The trend to fewer admissions to coronary or intensive care units (42.9% vs 55.6%) and fewer catheterization procedures (29.7% vs 40.7%) disappeared after adjustment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riesgo, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-de-Sá, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las características atípicas del síndrome coronario agudo en las mujeres favorecen las diferencias en su manejo y su tratamiento. Por ello nos propusimos indagar sobre estas diferencias en el manejo urgente del infarto agudo de miocardio sin elevación del ST (IAMSEST). Se recogieron 39 variables de 539 pacientes con IAMSEST de 97 servicios de urgencias españoles y, tras ajustar por las 10 diferencias basales, las únicas diferencias significativas fueron que las mujeres tardaban más en acudir a urgencias (odds ratio [OR]=0,52; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,28-0,95) y recibían más clopidogrel (OR=1,65; IC del 95%, 1,06-2,56). La tendencia a menos ingresos en coronarias-intensivos (el 42,9 frente al 55,6%) y menos práctica de cateterismo (el 29,7 frente al 40,7%) desapareció tras el ajuste (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(11): 1060-1064, nov. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91162</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación del manejo del infarto de miocardio sin elevación del ST durante la asistencia urgente en función del sexo del paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
