<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165972</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a game program based on cardiac biofeedback techniques in cognitive development of children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The cardiac biofeedback is an electronic technique that aims to improve the individual's physiological and psychological well-being. Objective. Study the chronic effects, on children's cognitive development, of a game program intervention based on the principle of self-regulation. Method. Fifty-two children of both sex, with a mean age of 9.57 (±0.80) composed the sample, randomized into experimental and control groups. The experimental group held an intervention with breathing pacer sessions and cardiac biofeedback sessions. The control group didn&#146;t make any kind of breathing intervention. Heart rate variability and cognitive indeces were analyzed in both groups. Heart rate variability indices were obtained by lineal time and frequency domain, and nonlinear methods. The data was generated through the reports provided by Kubios(R) and software in MATLAB(R) format. Data analysis was performed using SPSS 22.0 software and Spearman correlation was used to assess the degree of association of variables, considering p&amp;#8804;0.05. Results. The experimental group had an increased of the parasympathetic activity at rest represented by a decrease in the heart rate (p&lt;0.008), increased the interval between R waves of the QRS complex (p&lt;0.008), increased the index derived directly from RR (p&lt;0.026), the number of adjacent intervals that vary by more than 50ms (p&lt;0.038) and the cardio vagal index (p&lt;0.031). Besides the experimental group had better cognitive performance than the control group: greater accuracy (p&lt;0.012), stability (p&lt;0.012) and speed (p&lt;0.01). Conclusion. The cardiac biofeedback technique brings effective results regarding autonomic regulation and cognitive development of children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amaral, FV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dawid-Milner, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marques, JLB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El biofeedback cardíaco es una técnica electrónica que tiene por finalidad mejorar el bienestar fisiológico y psicológico. Objetivo. Estudiar los efectos crónicos en el desarrollo cognitivo de niños, de un programa de intervención en formato de juego, basado en el principio de aprendizaje de la autorregulación cardiovascular. Método. Cincuenta y dos niños de ambos sexos, con una edad promedio de 9.57 (±0.80) años, distribuidos de manera aleatoria en grupo experimental y control. El grupo experimental realizó una intervención con sesiones de respiración controlada y biofeedback cardíaco. El grupo control no realizó ningún tipo de intervención. Fueron analizados índices de variabilidad de la frecuencia cardíaca e índices cognitivos, de los grupos, en el mismo intervalo de tiempo. Los índices de variabilidad de la frecuencia cardíaca se obtuvieron mediante métodos lineales en el dominio tiempo, y métodos no lineales. Los datos se han generado a través de los informes proporcionados por Kubios(R) y por software en formato MATLAB(R). El análisis de datos se realizó con el software SPSS 22.0 y se utilizó la correlación de Spearman para evaluar el grado de asociación de variables, considerando p&amp;#8804;0.05. Resultados. El grupo experimental tuvo un aumento de la actividad parasimpática representada por disminución de la frecuencia cardíaca (p&lt;0.008), aumento de los valores del intervalo entre las ondas R del complejo QRSRR (p&lt;0.008), aumento del índice derivado directamente del RR (p&lt;0.026), del número de intervalos adyacentes que varían por más de 50ms (p&lt;0.038) y del índice cardíaco vagal (p&lt;0.031). Además, el grupo experimental tuvo mejor rendimiento cognitivo, representado por mayor precisión (p&lt;0.012), estabilidad (p&lt;0.012) y velocidad (p&lt;0.01). Conclusión. La técnica de biofeedback cardíaco produce resultados efectivos en relación con la regulación autonómica y el desarrollo cognitivo de los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;10(3): 100-105, sept. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de juego basado en técnicas de biofeedback cardíaco en el desarrollo cognitivo de niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
