<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161593</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study analyzes the mediator role of work-team trust (i.e., horizontal trust) in the relationship between transformational leadership, as a social resource, and team performance (i.e., in and extra role performance), as suggested by HERO Model (HEalthy &amp; Resilient Organizations Model; Salanova, Llorens, Cifre, &amp; Martínez, 2012). The sample corresponds to 388 workers nested in 54 teams from four organizations in the healthcare sector. Horizontal trust and transformational leadership were assessed by the work teams, and performance was assessed by the supervisors of these teams. Structural equation models revealed, as expected, that horizontal trust has a fully mediating role between transformational leadership perceived at the team level and team performance assessed by the supervisor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorens, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salanova, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Hedy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olvera, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio analizamos el rol mediador de la confianza en el equipo de trabajo (i.e., confianza horizontal) entre el liderazgo transformacional, como recurso social, y el desempeño en equipo (i.e., desempeño intra y extra rol), tal como sugiere el Modelo HERO (HEalthy &amp; Resilient Organizations Model; Salanova, Llorens, Cifre, &amp; Martínez, 2012). La muestra corresponde a 388 trabajadores/as agrupados/as en 54 equipos de trabajo pertenecientes a cuatro organizaciones del sector sanitario. La confianza horizontal y el liderazgo transformacional fueron evaluados por los equipos de trabajo y el desempeño fue evaluado por los/as supervisores/as de esos equipos. Los modelos de Ecuaciones Estructurales revelaron, tal como se esperaba, que la confianza horizontal, tiene un papel mediador entre el liderazgo transformacional percibido por el equipo y el desempeño en equipo evaluado por el/la supervisor/a (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(2): 365-375, mayo 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161593</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
