<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114204</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Orthotopic liver transplantation (OLT) is the treatment of choice and in most cases the definitive treatment in end-stage liver disease. Since the introduction of the technique in Spain, in 1984, to the present day survival in the first year after OLT has increased approximately 10 %, reaching 85.9 % (1). This increase in survival is associated with improvements in the surgical technique, immunosuppressive therapy and perioperative care. In order to ensure the survival and quality of life of patients undergoing OLT it is crucial to know all factors that may interfere with the graft outcome. These include indication for OLT, preoperative state of patients, surgical technique and phases of OLT, immunosuppressive therapy and postoperative complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arranz Duran, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho de Ávila, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano y Benítez de Lugo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante hepático ortotópico (THO) es el tratamiento de elección y en muchos casos definitivo de la patología hepática terminal. Desde la introducción de la técnica en España, en 1984, hasta la actualidad la supervivencia en el primer año posterior al THO ha aumentado aproximadamente un 10 %, situándose en el 85,9 % (1). Dicho aumento de la supervivencia se asocia a mejoras en la técnica quirúrgica, en el tratamiento inmunosupresor y en los cuidados perioperatorios. Es por tanto crucial, para asegurar la supervivencia y la calidad de vida de los pacientes sometidos a THO el conocimiento de todos los factores que pueden interferir en la evolución del injerto. Entre ellos se encuentran la indicación del THO, el estado basal de los pacientes antes del THO, la técnica quirúrgica y las distintas fases del THO, el tratamiento inmunosupresor y las probables complicaciones posoperatorias tanto precoces como tardías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;23(1): 16-23[1], ene.-mar. 2013. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante hepático ortotópico: visión global</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
