<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136182</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Combined treatment with antiepileptic drugs. Andalusian Epilepsy Guide 2015</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To draw up a set of recommendations based on scientific evidence and in agreement with authors and reviewers, which address fundamental issues concerning the combination of antiepileptic drugs. Development. A committee of 11 experts belonging to the Sociedad Andaluza de Epilepsia (SAdE &#150; Andalusian Epilepsy Society), of whom seven were neurologists, three were neuropaediatricians and one was a neurologist-neurophysiologist, all of them with long experience in epilepsy, promoted a comprehensive literature review among 55 experts in epilepsy who were members of the SAdE, with the aim of searching for any evidence that might be available on diagnostic or therapeutic matters in epilepsy. The guidelines were set out in 35 chapters. One of the chapters addressed the combination f antiepileptic drugs in the treatment of epilepsy. Taking 77 bibliographical references and the consensus view of authors and reviewers as their starting point, a set of easily applicable recommendations were drawn up. Conclusions. Combining antiepileptic drugs in patients with epilepsy whose seizures are not controlled with a single drug can, on many occasions, result in their going back into remission. There are a series of factors related with the type of epilepsy and characteristics of the patient and with the antiepileptic drugs to be used in combination that may favour a successful therapeutic outcome. Over-treatment with the combination of antiepileptic drugs must be avoided as far as possible. The results of this review provide a set of recommendations regarding combined treatment with antiepileptic drugs, based on scientific evidence and the agreement of authors, that are simple, useful and easy to apply at the different levels of healthcare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Machado Casas, Irene S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Giménez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Antón, Jacinto L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Lizana, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Álvarez, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Elaborar unas recomendaciones basadas en evidencias científicas y en consenso de los autores y revisores, que aborden las cuestiones básicas acerca de la combinación de fármacos antiepilépticos. Desarrollo. Un comité de 11 expertos pertenecientes a la Sociedad Andaluza de Epilepsia (SAdE), constituido por siete neurólogos, tres neuropediatras y un neurólogo-neurofisiólogo, todos con especial competencia en epilepsia, promovieron la realización de una revisión bibliográfica exhaustiva entre 55 expertos en epilepsia pertenecientes a la SAdE, en busca de evidencias disponibles relacionadas con temas diagnósticos o terapéuticos en epilepsia. La guía se estructuró en 35 capítulos. Uno de los capítulos abordó la combinación de fármacos antiepilépticos en el tratamiento de la epilepsia. Basándose en 77 citas bibliográficas y en la opinión consensuada de autores y revisores, se confeccionó una serie de recomendaciones de fácil aplicación. Conclusiones. La combinación de fármacos antiepilépticos en los pacientes con epilepsia cuyas crisis no están controladas con un solo fármaco puede conseguir en numerosas ocasiones que entren en remisión. Existe una serie de factores relacionados con el tipo de epilepsia y características del paciente y con los fármacos antiepilépticos que se van a utilizar en combinación que pueden favorecer el éxito terapéutico. Se debe evitar en lo posible el sobretratamiento con la combinación de fármacos antiepilépticos. Los resultados de esta revisión proveen unas recomendaciones sobre el tratamiento combinado con fármacos antiepilépticos, basadas en evidencias científicas y en el consenso de los autores, útiles, sencillas y aplicables en los diferentes niveles asistenciales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(8): 365-379, 16 abr., 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento combinado con fármacos antiepilépticos. Guía Andaluza de Epilepsia 2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
