<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043079</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Narcolepsy in the unit for respiratory sleep disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Narcolepsy is a syndrome of unknown cause that is characterizedby daytime hypersomnia, cataplexy, sleep paralysis, hypnogogicor hypnopomapic hallucinations and alterations of night time sleep.In spite of the fact that is has a relatively low prevalence, we havediagnosed several cases of narcolepsy in patients who were referredto our department to be studied for obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome.Due to this very fact, it is always good to consider narcolepsywhen establishing a differential diagnose of daytime hypersomnia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antona Rodríguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Pérez, F. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Vinuesa Calvo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Otero, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Lara, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos Caballero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La narcolepsia es un síndrome de etiología desconocida que secaracteriza por la tétrada clínica de hipersomnia diurna, cataplejía,parálisis de sueño, alucinaciones hipnagógicas o hipnapómpicasy alteraciones del sueño nocturno. A pesar de presentar unaprevalencia baja, en nuestro servicio se han diagnosticado varioscasos de narcolepsia en pacientes que inicialmente fueron derivadospara estudio de síndrome de apnea obstructiva del sueño. Deaquí la importancia de pensar siempre en la narcolepsia a la horade realizar el diagnóstico diferencial de las hipersomnias diurnas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);17(3): 211-213, sept.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Narcolepsia en una unidad de trastornos respiratorios del sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2429^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34368^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
