<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123115</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iron (FeSo4) bioavailability in obese subjects submitted to bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Iron bioavailability in obese subjects after the ingestion of a nutritional supplement was the aim of this work. Methods: Fourteen persons were studied before and after bariatric surgery after the ingestion of a nutritional formulation containing 25 mg iron, 25 g fiber and 800 mg calcium. Results: The following ferremia values (median and minimum - maximum) were obtained before and after bariatric surgery, respectively: Fasting, 105 (70 - 364) &amp;#956;g/dL and 198 (38 - 617) &amp;#956;g/dL; 1 hour, 103 (63 - 305) &amp;#956;g/dL and 160 (11 - 207) &amp;#956;g/dL; 2 hours, 103 (62 - 150) &amp;#956;g/dL and 141 (10 - 412) &amp;#956;g/dL; 3 hours. 97 (63 - 190) &amp;#956;g/dL and 153 (6 - 270) &amp;#956;g/dL; 4 hours, 91 (58 - 163) &amp;#956;g/dL and 156 (40 - 251) &amp;#956;g/dL (p&gt;0.05), with no association of serum iron levels with time. There was a difference in total triglycerides (95 ± 29 mg/dL and 60 ± 10 mg/dL) which were correlated with a decrease in serum ferritin levels (r = 0,926, p = 0.008), UIBC (r = 0.910, p = 0.01), total cholesterol (r = 0,918, p = 0.01) and LDL-c fraction (r = 0.830, p = 0.04), with an increase in HDL-c fraction (r = 0,807, p = 0.05). Conclusion: Iron bioavailability in obese subjects was affected by the ingestion of the nutritional formulation containing calcium and fiber, a fact that may cause these patients to develop iron deficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dutra-de-Oliveira, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizzo, Juliana C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, José Ernesto Dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marchini, Julio Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa Junior, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, Luciana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Obesos sometidos a cirugía bariátrica muestran la utilización de deterioro de hierro. Evaluar la biodisponibilidad del hierro en los obesos por el consumo de suplemento nutricional que contiene múltiples nutrientes antes y después de seis meses de la cirugía bariátrica. Material y Métodos: El estudio incluyó a 14 voluntarios antes y después de la cirugía bariátrica que recibieron formulaciones que contienen múltiples nutrientes y medir las concentraciones séricas de hierro en ayunas y cada 1 hora después de la ingestión de formulaciones, con un total de cuatro horas. Resultados: Ferremia por el consumo de entre dos formulaciones de pre-y post-operatorios fueron: El ayuno 104.50 (70,00-363,00) mg / dl y 198.00 (38.00 a 617.00) mg / dl, 103.00 horas (63,00 a 305,00) mg / dl y 160.00 (11,00-206,90) mg / dL, 2 horas 102.50 (62.00 a 150.00) mg / dL y 141.30 (10.00 a 412.20) mg / dl, 3 horas 97.00 (63.00 a 190.00) mg mg / dl y 153,00 (6,00 hasta 269,60) / dl , 4 horas 91,00 (58,00 a 163,00) mg / dl y 156.10 (40.00 a 250.50) mg / dl y no hubo asociación estadísticamente significativa entre los dos períodos para los niveles de hierro suero. Los valores de la zona de las curvas en el suero fueron 453,50 ± 202,80 mg / dl / hora, p = 0,000 y 579,00 ± 380,30 mg / dl / hora, p = 0,007 y fue estadísticamente diferente entre los dos períodos. La biodisponibilidad del hierro en soluciones que contienen múltiples nutrientes se vio afectada antes y después de seis meses de la cirugía bariátrica. Conclusión: Se encontró que los niveles se redujeron ferremia con la cirugía, que puede poner en peligro estos pacientes presentaron deficiencia de hierro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(1): 100-104, ene.-feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biodisponibilidad de hierro (FeSO4) de los sujetos obesos sometidos a cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32967^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
