<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67987</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To present our experience in 80 patients with intraorbital tumours and lesions who underwent87 osseous orbitotomies with coronal incision during a12 year period.Material, methods and results. Hemangioma wasthe most frequent histologic diagnosis, being the intraconical retrobulbar compartment the most commonlocation. Bilateral presentation of lesions occurred in 7patients. Lateral and supero-lateral orbitotomies werepreferably applied (87.35%). In 90.80% of cases somekind of osteosynthesis was employed, 51.75% withbio-resorbable plates. Intraoperative exposure or duramater breakage occurred in 10 patients. 45 transitoryand 21 permanent postoperative complications wereseen, being the nervous ones (diplopia and ptosis) themost frequent. Most of these were spontaneously solvedin a short time period. 15 patients required multi-disciplinary collaboration with neurosurgery.Conclusions. Coronal incision allows any bone orbitotomy,with security, guarantee and good aesthetic andfunctional results. Lateral and supero-lateral orbitotomies provide an ideal extradural approach to the retrobulbar compartment. An approach to the apex, orbitalchannel and medial compartment to the optic nerve,usually requires a combined neurosurgical approachthrough anterior cranial fossa. Orbitotomy fixationwith bio-resorbable ostheosynthesis is an alternative totitanium plates. They can even be a first choice in paediatric age. The morbidity of this surgical technique is low</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Infante-Cossío, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Perla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Arce, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espín-Gálvez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez- Pérez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Presentar nuestra experiencia en 80 pacientes con tumores y lesiones intraorbitarias en los que se realizaron 87 orbitotomías óseas mediante abordaje coronal, durante un período de 12 años. Material, métodos y resultados. El diagnóstico histológico más frecuente fue el hemangioma, y la localización anatómica más frecuente la retrobulbar intracónica. La presentación bilateral de lesiones ocurrió en 7 pacientes. Las orbitotomías más utilizadas fueron la lateral y supero-lateral (87,35%). En un 90,80% de los casos se realizó algún tipo de osteosíntesis, un 51,75% con placas bio-reabsorbibles. La exposición o rotura de la duramadre intraoperatoria ocurrió en 10 pacientes. Se recogieron 45 complicaciones postoperatorias transitorias y 21 permanentes, las más frecuentes fueron las nerviosas (diplopia y ptosis) que se resolvieron espontáneamente en su mayoría en un corto intervalo de tiempo. En 15 pacientes se requirió colaboración multidisciplinar con neurocirugía.Conclusiones. La incisión coronal permite realizarcualquier orbitotomía ósea con seguridad, garantía ybuen resultado estético y funcional. Las orbitotomíaslateral y supero-lateral proporcionan un abordaje idealextradural al espacio retrobulbar. El acceso al ápex,canal orbitario y zona medial nervio óptico requierecomúnmente un abordaje combinado neuroquirúrgicoa través de fosa craneal anterior. La fijación de las orbitotomías mediante osteosíntesis biorreabsorbible constituye una alternativa a las placas de titanio, incluso puede ser de primera elección en la edad pediátrica. La morbilidad de esta cirugía es baja</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);19(4): 322-331, jul.-ago. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67987</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22589^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
