<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94089</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Revisiting Florence Nightingale from a gender perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 2010 we commemorated the centenary of the death of Florence Nightingale. By the time he lived the situation of women was difficult with an ideal of femininity which imposed the exclusion of women from public life and work, restricted to men, despite the social situation Nightingale was a leading figure among merit include the demonstration of the importance of other sciences, such as statistics, provided to monitor, learn and improve hospital care. Pioneered the collection, storage and use of information for analyzing and managing patient care; harbinger of a sustainable health and ubiquitous computing. Florence shaped a new profession for women drawn from centuries of ignorance and superstition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Galiano, Juan Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Martín, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narváez-Traverso, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En 2010 conmemoramos el centenario de la muerte de Florence Nightingale. En la época en la que vivió, la situación de la mujer era difícil con un ideal de feminidad que imponía su exclusión de la vida pública y laboral, reservada al varón; a pesar de esta situación social Nightingale fue una figura destacada, entre sus méritos destacan la demostración de la importancia que otras ciencias, como la estadística, proporcionaban para controlar, aprender y mejorar la asistencia hospitalaria. Fue pionera en la recogida, almacenamiento y uso de la información para analizar y gestionar la atención al paciente; precursora de una informática sanitaria sostenible y ubicua. Florence modeló una nueva profesión para las mujeres extraída de siglos de ignorancia y superstición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(4): 299-302, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94089</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisitando a Florence Nightingale desde una perspectiva de género</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
