<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151833</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the new smoke-free legislation (law 42/2010) on levels of second-hand smoke in hospitality venues</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate pollution by second-hand smoke in a sample of hospitality venues before and after the implementation of smoke-free legislation. Methods: A cross sectional, before-after study was conducted in 2008 and 2011 after the total ban. A SidePack Aerosol monitor was used both inside and outside the hospitality venues to measure fine breathable particles (PM2.5). A total of 43 places with pre- and post-legislation measurements were included. Results: The median indoor pollution in hospitality venues was 204.2Mig/m3 in 2008 and 18.82Mig/m3 in 2011; the average outdoor PM2.5 concentration was 47.04Mig/m3 in 2008 and 18.82Mig/m3 in 2011. Pollution was higher in bars and cafeterias, followed by pubs and discos. Before the law was implemented, pollution was 4.34 times higher indoors than outdoors; in 2011 the average indoor PM2.5 concentration decreased by 90.88%.  Conclusions: Only a complete ban is able to protect workers and customers against the health risks of second-hand smoke exposure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galindo, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde-Royo, M Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nerín, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alayeto, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la contaminación por humo ambiental de tabaco en una muestra de locales de hostelería antes y después de la nueva legislación sobre tabaquismo. Métodos: Estudio evaluativo antes-después realizado en 2008 y 2011, tras la prohibición total. Medición de partículas respirables (PM2,5) mediante SidePack Aerosol Monitor en el interior de los locales y en el exterior. Se incluyeron 43 locales con mediciones antes y después de la legislación. Resultados: La concentración mediana de PM2,5 en el interior de los locales en 2008 fue 204,2Mig/m3, y en 2011 fue 18,62Mig/m3; en el exterior, en 2008 fue 47,04Mig/m3 y en 2011 fue 18,82Mig/m3. Las concentraciones más altas se encontraron en bares y cafeterías, seguidos de los locales de ocio nocturno. La contaminación en 2008 era 4,34 veces más alta en el interior de los locales que en el exterior; en 2011, la concentración de PM2,5disminuyó un 90,88% en el interior.  Conclusiones: La prohibición total de fumar en los locales de hostelería protege a trabajadores y clientes de los riesgos para la salud de la exposición al humo ambiental de tabaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(2): 161-163, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la nueva legislación sobre tabaquismo (Ley 42/2010) en los niveles de humo ambiental de tabaco en locales de hostelería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30272^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30272^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30272^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
