<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77882</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Manpower of Rheumatology in Catalonia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the changes in Rheumatology provision and working practice that have occurred on the basis of the 1990, 1996 surveys carried out to update the Catalan Society for Rheumatology register Methods: The register includes all rheumatologists in Catalonia (Spain) who are registered and who do clinical work. Questionnaires were sent to all rheumatologists on the register. The questionnaires asked about location and clinical commitments. Results: One hundred twenty-four rheumatologists work at the public system in Catalonia, 80 (65%) work at hospitals. The majority of rheumatologists (105; 84,6%) are located in the province of Barcelona. One fith of the rheumatologists have a temporal work. Ten general hospitals are still lacking of rheumatologists. Conclusion: Although the number of rheumatologists in Catalonia has increased there are ongoing inequalities in the provision of Rheumatology, especially between Barcelona and the rest of provinces(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Santamaría, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivé, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Actualizar el registro de reumatólogos que trabajan en Cataluña, basándose en los estudios previos hechos en los años 1990 y 1996 por la Societat Catalana de Reumatologia. Métodos: El registro incluye a todos los reumatólogos que trabajan en Cataluña (España). Se enviaron cuestionarios a todos los reumatólogos incluidos en el registro; los cuestionarios preguntaban el lugar de trabajo, el tipo de trabajo y el contrato laboral. Resultados: Ciento veinte y cuatro reumatólogos trabajaban en el sector público en Cataluña, 80 (65%) trabajaban en hospitales. Ciento cinco reumatólogos (84,6%) se localizaban en la provincia de Barcelona. Una quinta parte de los reumatólogos tiene un trabajo temporal. Diez hospitales generales carecían de reumatólogo. Conclusión: Aunque el número de reumatólogos en Cataluña ha aumentado, hay diferencias importantes en la localización de éstos, especialmente entre Barcelona y el resto de las provincias. Aún existen hospitales sin reumatólogo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);1(4): 211-217, nov.-dic. 2005. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77882</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de la asistencia reumatológica en el sector sanitario público de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
