<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81855</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prediction of fetal anemia in red blood cell alloimmunization after intrauterine transfusions. Review of the cases treated in our unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive. Evaluate the intrauterine blood transfusions performed in fetuses with anemia due to red blood cell alloimmunization in our unit and the detection rate of the middle cerebral artery Doppler to predict anemia after the first transfusion. Material and methods. Ee performed 53 intrauterine blood transfusions in 15 patients with red blood cell alloimmunization. We analyze the characteristics of the cases and the value of the middle cerebral artery Doppler to predict fetal anemia. Results. The detection rate of fetal anemia with the peak systolic velocity Doppler in the middle cerebral artery was 85% after the first transfusion and 72% after the second or more. There were no false positive results of the test in our series. Conclusions. Doppler evaluation of the middle cerebral artery as predictor of fetal anemia has a lower detection rate after consecutive transfusions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Terra Valdés, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina García, Francisca Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oyonarte Gómez, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Badillo, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrote Fernández de Santos, Aranzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar las transfusiones de sangre intrauterinas realizadas en fetos con anemia por isoinmunización a Rh en nuestra unidad y la sensibilidad del estudio con Doppler de la arteria cerebral media para predecir anemia fetal tras la primera transfusión. Material y métodos. Se realizaron 53 transfusiones de sangre intrauterinas en 15 pacientes afectados por isoinmunización a Rh. Se analizan las características de los casos y la capacidad del estudio Doppler de la arteria cerebral media como factor predictivo de anemia fetal. Resultados. La tasa de detección de anemia fetal de la velocidad sistólica pico de la arteria cerebral media fue del 85% tras la primera transfusión y del 72% tras la segunda y sucesivas, no se detectaron falsos positivos de la prueba en nuestra serie. Conclusiones. La valoración Doppler de la arteria cerebral media como predictor de anemia fetal presenta menor tasa de detección tras sucesivas transfusiones sanguíneas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(9): 335-340, sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predicción de anemia fetal por isoinmunización tras transfusiones intrauterinas. Revisión de los casos tratados en nuestra unidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1945^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1945^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12615^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30770^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30770^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1833^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1833^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1833^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
