<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054843</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Difficulties and opportunities for research as perceived by nurses in Asturias (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify, through communicative consensus, the difficulties and opportunities for research perceived by nurses in Asturias (Spain). Method. The Regional Ministry of Health and the Health Service of Asturias made an open call and 80 nurses from all fields (clinical, teaching, and management) were assigned to 10 groups. Using a nominal group technique, these nurses identified and prioritized the difficulties and opportunities they perceived for research. Through independent pairs, the research group analyzed the content of the contributions made. Results. In order of priority, the difficulties perceived were related to training deficit, lack of resources, lack of available time, little acknowledgement and support, and professional idiosyncrasy and sociology. The opportunities perceived were grouped into training opportunities, material resources ­when known to exist­, support from experts, access to information resources, the existence of financial support, and time available when working in primary care. Conclusions. The nurses identified the difficulties and opportunities that should be taken into account if strategies to stimulate nursing research are to be established. The situation should continue to be analyzed in order to provide possible solutions to the difficulties encountered, especially those related to professional idiosyncrasy and sociology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oltra-Rodríguez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguélez-López, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Suárez, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riestra-Rodríguez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Pérez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Valle, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer, a partir del consenso comunicativo, las dificultades y oportunidades percibidas por las enfermeras de Asturias para investigar. Método. Desde la Consejería de Salud y Servicios Sanitarios de Asturias se realizó una convocatoria abierta, y 80 enfermeras provenientes de todos los ámbitos asistenciales, docentes y de gestión, se reunieron en 10 grupos. Mediante la técnica de grupo nominal se aportaron, priorizadas, las dificultades y oportunidades percibidas para investigar. El equipo investigador realizó por pares independientes, un análisis del contenido de las aportaciones. Resultados. Las dificultades, por orden de priorización, se relacionaron con: déficit de formación, falta de recursos, escasez de tiempo, escaso reconocimiento y apoyo, idiosincrasia y sociología profesional. Las oportunidades percibidas se agruparon en: oferta formativa, recursos materiales existentes cuando son conocidos, apoyo de expertos, acceso a fuentes de información, existencia de ayudas económicas y tiempo en atención primaria. Conclusiones. Las enfermeras identificaron las dificultades y las oportunidades que se deben considerar si se pretende instaurar estrategias potenciadoras de la investigación enfermera. Queda pendiente continuar analizando la situación para plantear posibles soluciones a las dificultades encontradas, especialmente a las relacionadas con la idiosincrasia y sociología profesional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);17(1): 3-9, ene. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dificultades y oportunidades para investigar percibidas por las enfermeras en Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23781^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
