<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058526</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey of the Spanish Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology. Treatment of threatened preterm labor in Spanish hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine how threatened preterm labor is treated in Spanish hospitals. Material and method: Under the aegis of the Spanish Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology, an Internet questionnaire on basic aspects of the treatment of threatened preterm labor was sent to 41 Spanish hospitals (37 public and four private hospitals). Results: All hospitals use tocolysis in threatened preterm labor before 34th weeks. The most widely used tocolytic agent is atosiban (73,7%), followed by betamimetics (21.9%) and nifedipine (4.9%). Only 7.3% of the hospitals use tocolytics in threatened preterm labor after 34 weeks. All the hospitals use corticosteroids to accelerate lung maturation: 92.7% use betamethasone and 7.3% prefer dexamethasone. In 90% of the hospitals, steroid therapy is not repeated. In multiple pregnancies, the same steroid dose as that used in single pregnancies is administrated in all centers. Conclusions: The most widely used tocolytic agent in Spanish hospitals is atosiban and the preferred corticosteroid is betamethasone</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuente, Laura de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, Pedro de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer cómo se trata la amenaza de parto pretérmino (APP) en los hospitales españoles. Material y método: Con el patrocinio de la Sociedad Española de Ginecología y Obstetricia, se realizó una encuesta por Internet sobre aspectos básicos del tratamiento de la APP en 41 hospitales españoles, 37 públicos y 4 privados. Resultados: Todos los hospitales realizan tocólisis en la APP antes de las 34 semanas. El tocolítico más empleado es el atosiban (73,7%), seguido de los betamiméticos (21,9%) y el nifedipino (4,9%). En las APP de más de 24 semanas sólo el 7,3% de los hospitales realizan tocólisis. El 100% de los hospitales administra corticoides para acelerar la madurez pulmonar. El 92,7% utiliza betametasona y el 7,3% restante, dexametasona. El 90% de los hospitales no realiza corticoterapia de repetición. En los embarazos múltiples todos emplean la misma dosis que en las APP con feto único. Conclusiones: El tocolítico más utilizado en los hospitales españoles es el atosiban y el corticoide preferido, la betametasona</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);51(1): 28-37, ene. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058526</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta SEGO. Tratamiento de la amenaza de parto pretérmino en los hospitales españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21031^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23849^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
