<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83048</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent cannabis consumption and schizophrenia: epidemiological and experimental evidences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Marijuana is consistently the most widely used illicit drug among teenagers and most users first experiment it in adolescence. Adolescence is a critical period between childhood and adulthood, including not only reproductive maturation, but also cognitive, emotional and social maturation. In this period adolescent brain is still in transition differing anatomically and neurochemically from the adult&#146;s one. The endocannabinoid system is an important determinant for cerebral maturation, therefore its strong stimulation by the delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol, that acts through the endocannabinoid system, might lead to subtle but lasting neurobiological changes that can affect adult brain functions and behaviour. We summarize the more recent researches investigating the relationships between adolescent exposure to cannabinoids and increased risk for psychotic disease such as schizophrenia, as highlighted by both human and animal studies. Epidemiological evidence suggests that cannabis use is a risk factor for schizophrenia, and an exacerbation of symptoms and worsening of the schizophrenic prognosis may occur in individuals with a predisposition for schizophrenia. The characteristic of adolescent brain probably makes it more vulnerable to cannabis effect producing psychotic like symptoms and possibly cause schizophrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parolaro, Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La marihuana es la droga ilegal más utilizada entre los adolescentes. La mayoría de los usuarios comienzan además a experimentar con ella durante este período. La adolescencia es una etapa crítica, que incluye no sólo la maduración reproductiva, sino también la cognitiva, emocional y social de maduración. El cerebro del adolescente está aún en transición, difiriendo tanto anatómica como neuroquimicamente del adulto. El sistema endocannabinoide es un determinante importante para la maduración cerebral, por lo que su importante estimulación a través del delta-9-tetrahidrocannabinol, que actúa a través del sistema endocannabinoide, podría conducir a cambios neurobiológicos sutiles pero duraderos, que pueden afectar las funciones cerebrales y el comportamiento incluso cuando ya es adulto. Resumimos las más recientes investigaciones acerca de la exposición de los adolescentes a los cannabinoides y el riesgo de trastornos psicóticos como la esquizofrenia, como se desprende de los estudios tanto humanos como animales. La evidencia epidemiológica sugiere que el consumo de cannabises un factor de riesgo para la esquizofrenia, y contribuye a la exacerbación de los síntomas y al empeoramiento del pronóstico en individuos con predisposición. Las características del cerebro adolescente, probablemente lo hace más vulnerable a los efectos del cannabis produciendo síntomas similares a los psicóticos y posiblemente causando la esquizofrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(3): 185-190, jul.-sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de cánnabis de los adolescentes y esquizofrenia: evidencias epidemiológicas y experimentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
