<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133457</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body image and weight status of children from rural areas of Valparaíso, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the relation between the perceived and the real nutritional status in children from rural areas. Participants: The study comprehends 206 students from first to eighth year of primary school from ruralinstitutions of the Valparaiso region, Chile (43% females). Methods: The real nutritional status was measured using the Body Mass Index (BMI), and the perceived status by means of corporeal figures. The Socioeconomic Status (SES) was determined using the modified Graffar scale. The analysis was carried out using the concordance correlation coefficient kappa, and the chi-square test was used for the association of variables. Results: The subjects are concentrated in the low SES (82% male; 72% female). 49.5% of the students present  overweight and obesity. Boys show higher prevalence of obesity (29%) than girls (20%). 62.5% of the females underestimate their weight, which surpasses the percentage of males (52.5%). 98.10% of the obese individuals underestimate their weight, as well as the 100% of the evaluated children with an overweight condition. Conclusions: Boys and girls from rural areas in conditions of overweight and obesity present a higher prevalence rate of an inappropriate perception of body image (underestimation), which has an important impact when recognizing their own condition of over nutrition. This status can have significant repercussions in public health, since it can be maintained to adult life and develop non-transmissible chronic diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simpson, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizana, Pablo A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra, Karime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yáñez, Lily</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad en niños es un problema multifactorial, entre ellos se encuentra la percepción que tienen de su propio peso. Objetivo: Determinar la concordancia entre el estado nutricional percibido y el real en escolares de áreas rurales. Métodos: Comprenden 206 estudiantes de primer a octavo año de enseñanza primaria de establecimientos rurales de la región de Valparaíso, Chile (43% mujeres). El estado nutricional real se evaluó a través del índice de masa corporal (IMC) y la percibida mediante figuras corporales. El nivel socioeconómico (NSE) se determinó mediante la escala de Graffar modificada. Los análisis se realizaron utilizando el coeficiente de concordancia kappa y para la asociación de variables se utilizó la prueba X2. Resultados: Los sujetos se concentran en el NSE bajo (82% hombres; 72% mujeres). 49.5% de los escolares  presenta sobrepeso y obesidad. Los hombres presentan una mayor prevalencia de obesidad (29%) que las mujeres (20%). El 62,5% de las mujeres subestiman su peso, cifra mayor que en el caso de los hombres (52,5%). El 98,10% de los individuos obesos subestiman su peso y el 100% de los niños estudiados en condición de sobrepeso también lo subestiman. Conclusiones: Los niños y niñas de contextos rurales en condición de sobrepeso y obesidad son los que presentan  la mayor prevalencia de una inadecuada percepción de la imagen corporal (subestimación) lo cual tiene un importante impacto al no reconocer su condición de malnutrición por exceso. Esta condición puede tener importantes repercusiones en salud pública, puesto que esta condición se puede mantener hasta la vida adulta, desarrollando enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 698-703, feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autopercepción del estado nutricional en escolares de contextos rurales de Valparaíso, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
