<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159324</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposal for nursing diagnosis: Post Female Genital Mutilation Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To develop a nursing diagnosis for the detection and prevention of FGM. Methods: The creation of this diagnosis is based on exhaustive bibliographic research of databases such as LILACS, CUIDEN, TESEO y Web of Sciencie; as well as other documentary sources from international entities. Results: Post Female Genital Mutilation Syndrome is defined as: Deterioration of a range of health domains as a result of female genital mutilation.This diagnosis belongs to domain 11: safety/protection and class 3: violence. The following defining characteristics are established for this diagnosis: Acute phase, chronic responses physical, sexuality, chronic obstetric alterations and psychological responses. Conclusions: Via the diagnosis presented herein, early detection might be procured by nursing professionals of those women and young girls having undergone this traditional practice, thereby being able to treat any possible resultant sequelae (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juall Carpenito, Lynda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Ruiz, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almansa Martínez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Desarrollar un diagnóstico enfermero para la detección y prevención de la MGF. Metodología: La creación del presente diagnóstico se basa en un exhaustivo estudio bibliográfico en bases de datos como LILACS, CUIDEN, TESEO y Web of Sciencie; y otras fuentes documentales de organismos internacionales. Resultados principales: Síndrome post Mutilación Genital Femenina se define como: el deterioro de una serie de dominios de la salud como consecuencia de una mutilación genital femenina. Este diagnóstico se sitúa en el dominio 11, seguridad/protección y se posiciona en la clase 3: violencia. Se establecen para él las siguientes características definitorias: fase aguda, respuestas físicas crónicas, respuestas relacionadas con la sexualidad, alteraciones obstétricas crónicas y respuestas psicológicas. Conclusión principal: La creación del presente diagnóstico de síndrome facilita a los y la profesionales de enfermería el abordaje de las consecuencias sobre la salud de la Mutilación Genital Femenina y sitúa a Enfermería como una pieza clave para su abordaje y erradicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(45): 51-59, ene. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de diagnóstico de Síndrome Post Mutilación Genital Femenina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32805^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38804^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
