<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83065</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From the science to the practice in the community intervention. The transfer of the scientific knowledge to the professional action</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The scientific investigation and the social intervention have appeared often as two separated worlds. In this article we propose a model of application centred in lapráctica that tries to save the gap between scientific knowledge and the professional practice. Departing from the model of Wandersman (2003), we propose eight strategies to facilitate the transfer of the knowledge. Close to the habitual activities of dissemination of the scientific information, we will defend the putting in practice of strategies of (a) systematizing and management of lapráctica professional, (b) collaboration between investigators and professionals of laintervención socially, and (c) community involution. To illustrate the model, we resort to the case of the programs of prevention of drogodependencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maya Jariego, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación científica y la intervención social se han presentado con frecuencia como dos mundos separados. En este artículo proponemos un modelo de aplicación centrado en lapráctica que pretende salvar la brecha entre conocimiento científico y la práctica profesional. Partiendo del modelo de Wandersman (2003), proponemos ocho estrategias para facilitar la transferencia del conocimiento. Junto a las actividades habituales de diseminación de la información científica, defenderemos la puesta en práctica de estrategias de (a) sistematización y gestión de lapráctica profesional, (b) colaboración entre investigadores y profesionales de laintervención social, y (c) potenciación comunitaria. Para ilustrar el modelo, recurrimos al caso de los programas de prevención de drogodependencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;28(1): 121-141, ene.-abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">De la ciencia a la práctica en la intervención comunitaria. La transferencia del conocimiento científico a la actuación profesional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3187^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
