<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055943</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The amygdaloid complex and its implication in psychiatric disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The amygdaloid complex is a group of nuclei located deep    in the temporal lobe and closely involved in the limbic system.    Its alteration has been associated with some psychiatric    processes. In this article, an overall review was made of the    published data concerning the amygdaloid complex in the most    common psychiatric diseases. A damaged amygdaloid complex    is commonly observed, that in the Klüver-Bucy syndrome    presents the fullest expression. A decrease in the amygdaloid    complex of schizophrenic patients has been observed. This    finding was found bilaterally in men whereas in women it was    only located in one hemisphere. This finding suggests that    morphometric alterations in the amygdaloid complex are more    diffuse and more severe in men with schizophrenia. This    subcortical complex is larger in children with autism, but not in    adolescents, in whom the amygdaloid complex volume matches    the normal volume of an adolescent or an adult without this    pathology. However, neuroanatomical studies have shown    microscopic alterations. In patients with mood disorders, it has    been reported that the left amygdaloid complex presents a    lesser volume. Moreover, in frontotemporal dementia and    Alzheimer disease a slight amygdaloid atrophia was found    related to the healthy controls. It can be concluded that the    amygdaloid complex is involved in several psychiatric    processes, due to structural or functional damage. However,    more studies are still needed in order to delimitate the real    influence of the amygdaloid complex in these disorders</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Amaya, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledo-Varela, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El complejo amigdalino es un conjunto de núcleos que se    localizan en la profundidad del lóbulo temporal, y que guardan    estrecha relación con el sistema límbico. Su alteración se ha    asociado a un gran número de procesos psiquiátricos. En este    artículo se pretende hacer una revisión de lo publicado en referencia    a la implicación amigdalina en trastornos psiquiátricos    comunes. En ellos se observa un complejo amigdalino alterado,    siendo su máxima expresión el síndrome de Klüver-Bucy. En    pacientes esquizofrénicos se ha observado una reducción del    volumen amigdalino, bilateral en varones y unilateral en mujeres.    Esto sugiere que las alteraciones morfométricas del complejo    amigdalino están más extendidas en varones esquizofrénicos.    El complejo amigdalino está aumentado en niños autistas,    no siendo así en adolescentes, donde se iguala al volumen de    cualquier adolescente o adulto sano. Sin embargo, estudios neuroanatómicos    han demostrado patología microscópica. En los    pacientes con trastornos en el estado de ánimo, se observa una    cierta tendencia a presentar un complejo amigdalino izquierdo    de menor volumen. El volumen amigdalino de los grupos con    demencia frontotemporal y enfermedad de Alzheimer era diferente    a los del grupo de control, y se ha visto una predisposición    al incremento de la atrofia amigdalina. Se puede afirmar    que el complejo amigdalino está implicado en numerosos procesos    psiquiátricos, tanto por daño estructural de dicho complejo    como por daño funcional. Sin embargo, hacen falta más    estudios para delimitar la influencia real del complejo amigdalino    en dichos trastornos</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;30(1): 61-74, ene.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El complejo amigdalino humano y su implicación en los trastornos psiquiátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34271^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
