<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135183</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anti-IgE ( omalizumab) in the treatment of allergic rhinitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Omalizumab is a recombinant humanized monoclonal antibody which specifically bind to the Ce3 dornain of IgE, the site of binding to the high-affinity IgE receptor. Objective: To carry out a revision of the main randomized double blind clínica] tria] , controlled with placebo that have been carried out with Omalizumab in patients with sea onal or perennial allergic rhinitis in order to determine the efficacy and safety of this monoclonal antibody.  Methods: We earched until April 2004 Medline. IME. EMBASE. and Data Base of Cochrane Library. Results: Eight randomized clinical trials were included, which are commented, and their main results are exposed. Conclusions: Patients with seasonal and perennial allergic rhinitis treated subcutaneously with Omalizumab get an evident clinica1 benefit, with few and mild adverse events, what become it in a promising drug for the treatment of this allergic disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Félix Toledo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Hernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mérida Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negro Álvarez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El omalizumab es un anticuerpo monoclonal recombinante humanizado que se une específicamente al dominio C3e de la IgE, el lugar de unión al receptor de afinidad alta de la IgE. Objetivo: Realizar una revisión de lo principales estudios clínicos con distribución aleatoria, a doble ciego y controlado con placebo realizado con omalizumab en pacientes con rinitis alérgica estacional o perenne para determinar la eficacia y seguridad de este anticuerpo monoclonal. Métodos: Se realizó una búqueda bibliográfica hasta abril de 2004 en Medline, IME, EMBASE y la base de datos de Ja Cochrane Library. Resultados: Se incluyeron 8 estudio clínicos con distribución aleatoria en rinitis alérgica, que se comentan y cuyos principales resultados se exponen. Conclusiones: Los paciente con rinitis alérgica e racional y perenne tratados con omalizumab por vía subcutánea presentan un claro beneficio clínico, con poco y leves efectos adversos, lo que le convierte en un fármaco prometedor para el  tratamiento de esta enfermedad alérgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);19(4): 133-139, ago. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anti-IgE (omalizumab) en el tratamiento de la rinitis alérgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27802^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22205^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
