<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037436</identifier>
<setSpec>0482-5985</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term evolution of subtalar arthroereisis in flat foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Prospective clinical radiologic study to evaluate the results of the Giannini subtalar prosthesis. The evolution of the flat feet treated surgically was followed up for a mean of 13 years. Materials and methods. Between 1987 and 1990, 23 children(41 feet, mean age 10 years) underwent surgical treatment. The surgical indication was flexible flat foot with clinical and radiologic deformity associated with persistent pain and functional limitation after conservative treatment. A preliminary study was made at 2.1 years of mean follow up(results have been published). We made a new assessment of 16 of the initial patient group after 13 years of follow-up (12-14 years), 10 men and 6 women (mean age22.5 years, range 20-25 years). The evaluation criteria in both revisions were the same: clinical classification of Smith and Millar and measurement of 5 radiographic angles(Costa-Bartani, Méary, plantar flexion of the talus, talo-calcaneus, and talo-navicular). Subtalar arthroereisis was carried out with a Giannini implant that was removed after at least 18 months. Results. Clinical results were excellent in 22 feet, good in 5,and poor in 3. The Costa-Bartani angle showed a mean 13°correction and the final mean angle was 4°. No bone disorders producing impaired mobility or long-term arthroereisis were observed except in the case of poor results. In one of these cases, triple arthrodesis was performed and two of the patients had spastic flat foot after the implant was introduced. None of the good preliminary results deteriorated. Conclusions. This surgical method is simple and quick, with few complications, and can achieve a good correction that is maintained long term without causing bone or mobility disorders of the tarsal joints derived from the technique</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Crespo, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez-García, O. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Suárez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Montaña, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudio clínico-radiológico de carácter prospectivo, con el objetivo de evaluar los resultados de la endoprótesis subastragalina de Giannini. El estudio lo hemos basado en la evolución de los pies planos intervenidos y seguidos alargo plazo con una media de evolución de 13 años. Material y método. Entre 1987-1990 fueron intervenidos 23niños (41 pies y 10 años de edad media). La indicación quirúrgica fue de pie plano flexible, con deformidad clínica y radiológica acompañada de dolor persistente y limitación funcional tras tratamiento conservador. Se realizó un estudio preliminar a los 2,1 años de evolución media (resultados ya publicados). Realizamos una nueva valoración actual a16 pacientes de los iniciales, tras 13 años de evolución (12-14), 10 varones y 6 mujeres, con edad media de 22,5 años(20-25). Los criterios de evaluación en las 2 revisiones han sido los mismos: la clasificación clínica de Smith y Millar y la medición de 5 ángulos radiográficos (Costa-Bartani, Méary, flexión plantar del astrágalo, astrágalo-calcáneo y astrágalo-escafoideo). La técnica quirúrgica empleada fue una artrorrisis subastragalina con prótesis de Giannini, la cual se retiró tras un tiempo mínimo de 18 meses. Resultados. Clínicamente 22 pies excelentes, 5 buenos y 3malos. El ángulo de Costa-Bartani corrigió una media de12° y el ángulo medio final fue de 130°, la línea de Meáry corrigió una media de 13° y el ángulo medio final fue de 4°.No se han observado alteraciones óseas ni de la movilidad en las articulaciones implicadas en la artrorrisis a largo plazo, excepto en los malos resultados, en uno de ellos se realizó una triple artrodesis y los otros 2 sufrieron un pie plano espástico tras la introducción de la prótesis. Ninguno de los resultados buenos preliminares ha evolucionado a malo. Conclusiones. Se considera este método quirúrgico simple y rápido, con escasas complicaciones, capaz de conseguir una corrección buena y mantenida a largo plazo, y sin provocar alteraciones óseas ni de la movilidad derivadas de la técnica, en las articulaciones tarsianas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. ortop. traumatol. (Madr., Ed. impr.);49(2): 112-116, mar.-abr. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución a largo plazo de la artrorrisis subastragalina en el pie plano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23475^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23245^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14021^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
