<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96930</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bringing everyone and every subject into the research fold:  the Strategic Action for Health and the funding of biomedical research, development, and innovation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Biomedical research is an essential part of any strategy that seeks to improve the health of citizens. The research done in Spain today will provide the basis for developing our medical practices in the future. This paper considers the multilevel model that provides the basis for public policies on how biomedical research, development and innovation projects are funded. We discuss the situation of emergency medical specialists, who have traditionally focused on clinical practice rather than research. We also provide an overview of government biomedical research grants channeled through the Strategic Action for Health (AES), which is administered by the Carlos III Health Institute (ISCIII), the funding agency of the Ministry of Science and Innovation. Emphasis is placed on the goals of the AES and the research challenges the National Health Service faces. The life cycle of a research grant is described briefly. Finally, the AES subprograms in two lines, research and human resources, are described in detail (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ortega, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Formoso, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blazquez-Herranz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Martul, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación en biomedicina es una actividad necesaria para el éxito de cualquier estrategia que se proponga mejorar la salud de los ciudadanos. La investigación en salud que España pueda realizar hoy sentará las bases del desarrollo de nuestra biomedicina del mañana. En este artículo se tiene en cuenta el modelo multinivel en el que se desarrollan las políticas públicas en materia de I+D+i en biomedicina. Se toma en consideración que los profesionales de la medicina de urgencias y emergencias se han movido tradicionalmente en el área de la práctica clínica y han estado apartados de la investigación. Se ofrece un panorama global de las ayudas destinadas al fomento de la investigación biomédica desde la Administración General del Estado. Estas ayudas se articulan a través de la Acción Estratégica en Salud (AES) gestionada por el Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII), agencia financiadora de la investigación del Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación. Se hace énfasis en los objetivos de la AES y los retos a los que se enfrenta el Sistema Nacional de Salud en relación a la investigación. Se describe someramente el ciclo de vida de las ayudas a la investigación. Para finalizar se describen de forma pormenorizada los Subprogramas de la AES de la línea proyectos de investigación y de la Línea Recursos humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(6): 460-469, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Para que nada ni nadie se quede sin investigar: la Acción Estratégica en Salud (AES) en el contexto del fomento y promoción de la I+D+i biosanitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24459^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
