<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121050</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence for the use of topical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. To analyse the efficiency of topical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) in patients suffering from acute and chronic osteomuscular pain. METHOD. Analysis of available evidence. Literature search (September 2013) in Medline/Pub-Med, WOK and Cochrane Library. Key words: &#147;NSAIDs&#148;, &#147;topical administration&#148;, &#147;acute pain&#148;, &#147;chronic pain&#148;. RESULTS AND CONCLUSIONS. Nine systematic reviews and four meta-analyses were analysed, with the following conclusions:&#149; Topical NSAIDs afforded analgesia by the same acting mechanism as oral NSAIDs, but their effective activity takes place mainly at the site of application, and systematic exposure to the NSAID is substantially lower than with oral NSAIDs.&#149; Top level evidence exists to recommend the use of some topical NSAIDs in the treatment of mild or moderate acute osteomuscular pain (contusions, sprains and twists) for one week.&#149; Top level evidence exists to recommend the use of some topical NSAIDs in the treatment of local chronic osteomuscular pain in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee and of the hand for limited periods of time (2-8 weeks)&#149; There is insufficient evidence to recommend its use for lumbago, widespread pain or osteoarthritis of the hip.&#149; Topical NSAIDs for which there is more extensive and better evidence are ibuprofen, Ketoprofen and especially diclofenac (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Alcalá, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO. Analizar la eficacia de los AINE tópicos en pacientes con dolor osteomuscular agudo y crónico. MÉTODO. Análisis de la evidencia disponible. Búsqueda bibliográfica (Septiembre. -2013) en Medline/PubMed, WOK y Cochrane Library. Palabras clave: &#147;NSAIDs&#148;, &#147;topical administration&#148;, &#147;acute pain&#148;, &#147;chronic pain&#148;. RESULTADOS Y CONCLUSIONES. Se analizaron 9 revisiones sistemáticas y 4 meta-análisis, llegando a las siguientes conclusiones:&#149; Los AINE tópicos proporcionan analgesia por el mismo mecanismo de acción que los AINE orales, pero su actividad efectiva sucede principalmente en el lugar de aplicación, y la exposición sistémica al AINE es sustancialmente menor que con los AINE orales.&#149; Existen evidencias de máximo nivel para recomendar el uso de algunos AINE tópicos en el tratamiento del dolor osteomuscular agudo leve o moderado (contusiones, esguinces y torceduras),durante una semana.&#149; Existen evidencias de máximo nivel para recomendar el uso de algunos AINE tópicos en el tratamiento del dolor osteomuscular crónico localizado, en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla y de mano, durante períodos de tiempo limitados (2-8 semanas).&#149; No hay evidencias suficientes para recomendar su uso en lumbalgias, dolor extenso o enartrosis de cadera.&#149; Los AINE tópicos para los que existe más y mejor evidencia son ibuprofeno, ketoprofeno y sobre todo diclofenaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;6(3): 152-159, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencias para el uso de antiinflamatorios no esteroideos tópicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54517^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
