<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137933</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidisciplinary approach to addictive disorders: reflections on a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To use a clinical case to think about the main characteristics of addictive behaviour and the way health professionals may intervene on it. Material and methods. A clinical case is thoroughly analysed: its phases and the different treatments applied, its personal and familiar evolution. Results. Patient evolution depends on different variables, like age, which substance is consumed and in which way, the psychopathological traits or symptoms of the patients or of his/her family, the organic pathology associated, whether a social network is present or not,¿ It is suggested that ties with the therapeutic team are important in patient evolution, since its presence may help the patients to recognize and to express their feelings and may induce changes in their behaviour. Therapeutic alliances with other family members may also be useful. Team work may help to overcome the obstacles and difficulties associated with the treatment these patients and to avoid the burn-out syndrome, which is frequently observed in those professionals working in this field. Conclusions. Whenever one wants to confront the problems associated with the handling or treatment of addictive behaviour, both team work and a multidisplinary approach to these patients are needed. They may act as a protective factor to avoid the socalled burnt-out syndrome. In the addiction field, treatment must be considered as a long-term process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüello, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fomperosa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A través de un caso reflexionar sobre las características de las adicciones como un fenómeno nuevo que irrumpió en nuestra sociedad a mediados de los años 80 y sobre las formas de intervención. Material y métodos. Analizamos detalladamente el caso, fases, diferentes tratamientos, evolución personal y familiar. Resultados. La evolución de los pacientes depende de múltiples variables como la edad, el tipo de consumo y de sustancia, la psicopatología presente en el paciente y/o sus familiares, la patología asociada, la red social y el trabajo. Planteamos la hipótesis de que la evolución de los pacientes depende también del contacto con sus terapeutas, en la medida en que se ayuda al paciente a conocer y expresar sus sentimientos y a provocar cambios en su conducta y en sus hábitos, además de intentar alianzas terapéuticas con otros miembros de la familia. Por último, mostramos un modelo de funcionamiento en equipo para poder superar las enormes dificultades que presentan estos pacientes y tratar, en la medida de lo posible, de evitar el «síndrome del quemado» que se produce con frecuencia entre los profesionales que trabajamos con este tipo de personas. Conclusiones. El trabajo en equipo y un manejo multidisciplinario son necesarios para enfrentarse a los problemas planteados en el tratamiento ambulatorio de los trastornos adictivos. El trabajo en equipo como factor de prevención del «síndrome del quemado» de los profesionales. Los tratamientos de las adicciones son de larga duración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;11(1): 64-70, ene. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo multidisciplinario de los trastornos adictivos, a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9463^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
