<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043706</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Project for the implementation of a health education programme in the care of renal transplant patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, one of the relevant functions of the nursing role is teaching and educating, carrying out health promotion and education tasks for the population by encouraging selfcare. In the course of our clinical practice, we have detected the need to implement a health education programme for renal transplant patients, with the aim of preventing complications arising as a result of the treatment, adherence to treatment and lack of self care associated with renal transplants. To define the aims of our programme, we have used the PRECEDE method, one of the methods most widely used in health education. The duration of the study will be one year, and will be carried out by the Nursing team of the Nephrology Unit. Talks will be organized, at which leaflets will be handed out. The evaluation will be carried out on the basis of two tests, one to evaluate the knowledge acquired by patients and another to evaluate the methodology used by nursing staff and the educational content of the talks and leaflets. With the implementation of this programme, we want to reduce patient anxiety caused by a lack of information and knowledge, as well as the number of re-admissions due to deficient self care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arnau Vives, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilplana Molto, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pernas Pérez, Celsa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Jarque, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, una de las funciones relevantes del rol de enfermería es la docente y educadora, realizando promoción y educación para la salud de la población a través de una potenciación del autocuidado. A través de nuestra práctica asistencial hemos detectado la necesidad de implantar un programa de educación para la salud en el paciente trasplantado renal, con el objetivo de prevenir las complicaciones derivadas del tratamiento, de la adherencia al tratamiento y déficit de autocuidados asociados al trasplante renal. Para definir los objetivos de nuestro programa nos hemos basado en el método PRECEDE, uno de los más utilizados en educación sanitaria. La duración del estudio será de un año, llevado a la práctica por el equipo de Enfermería dela Unidad de Nefrología. Se realizarán charlas informativas, entregándose folletos. La evaluación se hará a partir de dos test, uno para valorar los conocimientos adquiridos por los pacientes y otro para valorar la metodología utilizada por enfermería y el contenido didáctico de las charlas y folletos. Con la implantación de este programa queremos disminuirla ansiedad del paciente derivada de la falta de información y conocimientos, así como los reingresos debidos al deficit de autocuidados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;8(3): 183-186, jul.-sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043706</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto de implantación de un programa de educacion para la salud en el proceso asistencial del paciente trasplantado renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23782</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
