<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039425</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Geriatric assessment in critical care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Important functional decline is detected in the majority of old patientsafter hospitalisation, and this is most pronounced in those patientsadmitted to an intensive care unit (ICU). Fifty percent or more of patientsadmitted in an ICU have more than 65 years old. Comprehensivegeriatric assessment is a recognized and useful instrument in themanagement of elderly patients. Conversely, there are not enough studiesto evaluate its efficacy in old patients admitted to an ICU.In this article, the author carries out a revision on many epidemiologicaland demographic factors, quality of life and functional outcome afterhospital discharge, ethic practices in elderly care and economical cost.Illness severity of disease responsible of admission, comorbidity andprevious functional level, more than age, are the most relevant factorsas well of inpatient mortality as long-term outcome. Nevertheless, it isnot available a well-defined score to predict which old patient willobtain a benefit from an ICU admission and which not. Prospectiveand controlled studies are necessary to analyse useful of comprehensivegeriatric assessment in these patients.In our opinion, the culture of geriatric assessment should be introducedin ICU. Accordingly, a minimal geriatric assessment is an inexcusableassistencial requirement in these units. Furthermore, we also believethat a full comprehensive geriatric assessment should be performed inall elderly patients discharged from ICU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Soto, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hospitalización en los ancianos conlleva a un deterioro funcionalimportante, que es más marcado en aquellos que precisan de unaunidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI). En la actualidad casi la mitad delos pacientes que ingresan en intensivos tienen más de 65 años. Lavaloración geriátrica integral es una metodología que ha demostradosu eficacia en el manejo de los pacientes ancianos, pero no disponemosde suficientes estudios prospectivos que avalen su utilidad de enlos ancianos que han ingresado en una UCI.En el artículo se hace una revisión de la bibliografía donde se analizanlos factores epidemiológicos y demográficos, factores pronósticos, calidadde vida y estado funcional tras el alta de una UCI, así comoconsideraciones éticas sobre la atención del anciano en intensivos yfinalmente los costes derivados de dicha asistencia.Como conclusiones, destacamos que la severidad de la enfermedadque condiciona el ingreso, la comorbilidad y la situación funcionalprevia, más que la edad, son los elementos determinantes tanto de lamortalidad intrahospitalaria como del pronóstico a largo plazo. Sinembargo, no disponemos de un instrumento bien definido, que nospermita predecir que paciente anciano va a beneficiarse y cual no de uningreso en una UCI. Son necesarios estudios prospectivos y controlados,que nos permitan evaluar la utilidad de la VGI en este colectivo depacientes.En nuestra opinión, la cultura de la valoración geriátrica debeimplementarse en las unidades de cuidados intensivos. De tal manera,que una mínima evaluación geriátrica es un requerimiento asistencialimprescindible en estas unidades. Además, creemos que una valoracióngeriátrica integral debe efectuarse a todo anciano que sea dado dealta de una UCI</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;15(1): 50-53, ene. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039425</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración geriátrica en una unidad de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32782^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
