<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056244</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ovarian myxoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ovarian myxoma is a rare ovarian tumor. We identified only 16 cases in the literature reviewed. This neoplasm presents as a unilateral mass in women of reproductive age and is usually asymptomatic. We report the case of a 24-year-old woman, with an unremarkable personal and familial history, in whom a right adnexal tumor was detected on routine ultrasound examination. A right ovarian complex mass was diagnosed and exploratory laparotomy was performed, showing a 10 3 10 irregular mucinous pediculated tumor of the right ovary. The mass was excised and an intraoperative biopsy specimen showed no signs of malignancy. Microscopic examination revealed edematous, myxomatous stroma positive for PAS-Alcian blue and colloidal iron staining. Fusiform and stellate cells without nuclear atypia or mitosis were observed, with no findings of conserved ovarian parenchyma. Abundant thin-walled vessels were identified. Immunohistochemical analysis was positive for actin, weakly positive for desmin and negative for cytokeratin. The patient is currently asymptomatic, with no evidence of recurrence after 9 months of follow-up. Ovarian myxoma is uncommon and should be distinguished from other entities such as massive ovarian edema, myxoid sarcoma and embryonic rhabdomyosarcoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avilés, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerrillo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mixoma de ovario es un tipo de tumor ovárico muy poco frecuente; sólo se han encontrado 16 casos con este diagnóstico en la bibliografía revisada. Se presenta como una masa unilateral en mujeres en edad reproductiva y normalmente es asintomático. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 24 años, sin antecedentes familiares ni personales de interés, a la que se le detectó una tumoración anexial derecha mediante ecografía de control rutinario. Ante el diagnóstico de tumoración compleja de ovario derecho se decidió realizar una laparotomía exploradora en la que se visualizó una tumoración irregular de aspecto mucinoso de 10 3 10 cm, dependiente del ovario derecho y pediculada. Se procedió a su extirpación y se remitió la pieza como biopsia intraoperatoria, que informó de ausencia de evidencia de malignidad. En el microscopio presentaba una estroma mixomatosa, edematosa, de coloración azulada con la tinción de Pas-azul alcián, y positiva para la tinción de hierro coloidal. Se observaban células fusiformes y estrelladas sin atipias nucleares ni mitosis y no se apreciaba parénquima ovárico conservado. Se identificaban abundantes vasos con finas paredes. El análisis inmunohistoquímico fue positivo para actina, débilmente para desmina y negativo para citoqueratinas. La paciente se encuentra asintomática y sin evidencias de recurrencia tras 9 meses de seguimiento. El mixoma de ovario es poco frecuente y debe distinguirse de entidades como el edema masivo de ovario, los sarcomas mixoides y el rabdomiosarcoma ebrionario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);34(5): 201-203, sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mixoma de ovario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13717^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31072^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13717^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31072^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12619^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13717^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12619^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31072^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31072^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23534^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
