<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106847</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pellegrini-Stieda syndrome as a cause of knee pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Calcification in the soft tissue next to the medial femoral condyle after a history of trauma around the knee is a recognized radiographic finding&#150;PS (Pellegrini-Stieda) sign. When this is associated with pain and a restricted range of motion it is known as the PS syndrome. We describe two cases of PS syndrome, treated conservatively with rest and physiotherapy, as well as the radiographic and ultrasound findings, and the many theories proposed in attempts to explain the pathogenesis of PS disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Pascua, L. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Sánchez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Casado, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calcificación de las partes blandas, adyacentes al cóndilo femoral medial, después de una historia de traumatismo en la rodilla, se denomina signo radiológico de Pellegrini-Stieda (PS), cuando se asocia a dolor y a disminución del rango de movilidad de la rodilla se conoce como síndrome de PS. Describimos dos casos de síndrome de PS, tratados mediante tratamiento conservador&#150;reposo y fisioterapia-, los hallazgos radiológicos y ecográficos, y algunas teorías propuestas para explicar la patogénesis de la enfermedad de PS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(8): 543-547, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Pellegrini-Stieda como causa de gonalgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31315^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31315^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31315^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31315^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
