<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047514</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-8927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity and physical activity in children and youth: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Until there is an advancement in gene therapy;detection and manipulation of genes involved inexcess weigh among children, it is only realistic topursue prevention activities. Multidisciplinary approachesin prevention of obesity are necessary forsuccessful outcomes.One of the principal strategies is to modify thechildren&#146;s behaviour involves reducing sedentaryhabits and increasing PA levels. Both these behaviourchanges are part of two major components ofenergy balance: energy expenditure and food intake.Data presented in this review suggests some ofthe most effective interventions to reduce the prevalenceof obesity in children. Adding 3 hours perweek of sport activities to the compulsory physicaleducation courses in prepubertal children seems tobe effective in reducing fat mass accumulation. Italso had an effect on lean mass accretion duringgrowth and improved physical fitness</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Rodríguez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calbet, J. A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ara Royo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hasta que los avances en genética permitan detectary manipular los genes implicados en el alarmanteaumento de la prevalencia de obesidad enniños y jóvenes, la única solución realista al problemade la obesidad infantil es la prevención. Intentospor mejorar a un solo nivel o en un solo escenarioel problema serán probablemente insuficientes.La solución pasa por actuar principalmentesobre los dos aspectos fundamentales del balanceenergético: la ingesta y el gasto energético. Portanto, uno de los principales objetivos es tratar demodificar las conductas de los niños, reduciendoel número de horas dedicadas a actividades sedentariasy aumentar los niveles de actividad física.Los datos presentados en esta revisión pretendencolaborar en la determinación de cuales son aquellasintervenciones más eficaces para promover undescenso de la prevalencia de obesidad en niños.Los resultados de los trabajos incluidos demuestranque añadir 3 horas a la semana de prácticadeportiva a aquellas horas que en la actualidadson obligatorias para niños prepúberes en la escuela,permite atenuar la acumulación de masagrasa durante el crecimiento, al tiempo que incrementala ganancia de masa muscular y mejora lacondición física de los niños</dc:description>
<dc:source>Selección (Madr.);15(2): 103-108, abr.-jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad y actividad física en niños y jóvenes: revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
