<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164016</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inter-gender differences in emotional dependency in youth  and adolescent population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this article is to provide a clinical analysis of emotional dependency and provide insights as to whether there are significant gender differences, defining this construct as a kind of sentimental or emotional dependence characterized by the manifestation of addictive behaviours of pathological attachment in the interpersonal relationship. The Inventory of Interpersonal Relations and Sentimental Dependencies (IRIDS-100, Sirvent and Moral, 2005) was applied in a young and adolescent population (N = 604) through a two-stage sampling with an intra-group random subsample. According to these results, significant differences were found in the differential clinical profile of the sample (teenagers) and there is a symptomatic presence of a similar clinical and psychosocial profile in men and women in the Emotional Dependency construct (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuetos González, Glenda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es ofrecer un análisis clínico de la Dependencia Emocional y comprobar si existen o no diferencias significativas teniendo en cuenta el género, definiendo este constructo como un tipo de Dependencia Sentimental o Afectiva caracterizada por la manifestación de comportamientos adictivos de apego patológico en la relación interpersonal. Se ha aplicado el Inventario de Relaciones Interpersonales y Dependencias Sentimentales (IRIDS-100, Sirvent y Moral, 2005), con respecto a población juvenil y adolescente (N= 604) recabada a través de un muestreo aleatorio intragrupo. Los resultados muestran que existen diferencias significativas en el perfil clínico diferencial en la muestra estudiada (jóvenes y adolescentes) y existe una presencia sintomática de un perfil clínico y psicosocial similar en varones y mujeres en cuanto al constructo de la Dependencia Emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;42(2): 56-66, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164016</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias inter-género en Dependencia Emocional en población juvenil y adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32017^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
