<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157031</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Additional primary malignancies in patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Proposal for a new classification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Additional primary malignancies in patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) is not only common but of growing interest in the scientific literature. This association is of great importance in terms of clinical challenge, diagnosis and therapy as well as for the prognosis impact it implies. In the published series there is a tendency to group these patients to determine the specific and distinguishable characteristics of GIST associated with other malignancies. On the other hand, there is no general consensus or unified classification. This classification would be of great interest, as it would unify criteria, agree groups to compare different series and demonstrate whether the aetiology underlying both tumours and the GIST&#146;s own characteristics really vary according to the type in question. We undertook a medical literature review and proposed a new classification for patients with GIST associated with other tumours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares Ripoll, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Hernández, Juan Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La asociación de gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST, «tumor del estroma gastrointestinal») con otras neoplasias primarias en un mismo paciente es un hecho no solo frecuente, sino con un interés creciente en la literatura científica. Esta asociación tiene una enorme importancia tanto por el desafío clínico, diagnóstico y terapéutico como por el impacto pronóstico que implica. En las series publicadas existe una tendencia a agrupar a estos pacientes para determinar que los GIST asociados a otras neoplasias tienen características concretas y diferenciables. Por el contrario, no existe un consenso general ni una clasificación unificada. Esta clasificación sería de gran interés, pues permitiría unificar criterios, consensuar los grupos para comparar las distintas series y demostrar si realmente la etiopatogenia subyacente a ambos tumores y las características del propio GIST varían según el tipo de que se trate. Realizamos una revisión de la literatura médica actual y una propuesta de nueva clasificación para pacientes con GIST asociados a otros tumores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);147(9): 405-409, nov. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación de tumores del estroma gastrointestinal con otros tumores primarios. Propuesta de una nueva clasificación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31302^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31302^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
