<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83784</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work, is performed a recopilation of bibliography about equinus foot and their differents treatments. It has a direct effect on the anatomical and functional structure of the foot, alterating the normal heal of the rearfoot, and making compensatory mechanisms in both midfoot and forefoot as consequence. It can modify normal gait phases too. By this reason, it&#146;s therefore necessary to do a good evaluation of the patient to perform adequate treatment to avoid any potential compensatory mechanisms. We present a clinical report of a young person suffering from this pathology(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Rivas, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viana García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se realiza una recopilación bibliográfica sobre la patología del pie equino y sus diferentes tratamientos. Esta patología repercute directamente en toda la estructura anatómica del pie, alterando el apoyo del retropié, provocando mecanismos compensatorios en mediopié y en antepié, modificando las fases normales de la marcha. Es necesario por tanto, realizar una buena valoración del paciente para poder realizar el tratamiento adecuado evitando todos los posibles mecanismos compensatorios. A continuación, se expone un caso clínico de una persona joven que padece esta patología(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;30(3): 138-144, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Equino bilateral de tobillo: tratamiento mediante soporte plantar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22893^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22898^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22898^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
