<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129523</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bipolar disorders in the new DSM-5 and ICD-11 classifications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The DSM-5 and ICD-11 classifications, the latter still under development, are aimed at harmonizing the diagnoses of mental disorders. A critical review is presented of the issues that can converge or separate both classifications regarding bipolar disorders, and those conditions &#150; included in depressive disorders &#150; with special relevance for bipolar (e.g. major depressive episode). The main novelties include the incorporation of dimensional parameters to assess the symptoms, as well as the sub-threshold states in the bipolar spectrum, the consideration of new course specifiers such as the mixed symptoms, the elimination of mixed episodes, and a more restrictive threshold for the diagnosis of hypo/mania. The most noticeable points of convergence are the inclusion of bipolar ii disorder in ICD-11 and the additional requirement of an increase in activity, besides mood elation or irritability, for the diagnosis of hypo/mania in both classifications. The main differences are, most likely keeping the mixed depression and anxiety disorder diagnostic category, maintaining bereavement as exclusion criterion for the depressive episode, and maintaining the mixed episode diagnosis in bipolar disorder in the forthcoming ICD-11. Conclusion. Since DSM-5 has already been published, changes in the draft of ICD-11, or ongoing changes in DSM-5.1 will be necessary to improve the harmonization of psychiatric diagnoses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colom, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goikolea, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dios, Consuelo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las clasificaciones DSM-5 y CIE-11, esta última en elaboración, pretenden armonizar los diagnósticos de los trastornos mentales. En este artículo hacemos una revisión crítica de los puntos que pueden aproximar y aquellos que pueden dificultar la convergencia de los trastornos bipolares, así como de aquellas condiciones clínicas single bondincluidas dentro de los trastornos depresivossingle bond con especial relevancia para los trastornos bipolares (p. ej., episodio depresivo mayor). Las principales novedades agregadas comprenden la incorporación de parámetros dimensionales para la evaluación de los síntomas, la posibilidad de diagnosticar cuadros subumbrales del espectro bipolar, la consideración de nuevos especificadores de curso como los síntomas mixtos, la desaparición del diagnóstico de episodio mixto, y el aumento del umbral para el diagnóstico de hipo/manía. Las convergencias destacables son la inclusión del trastorno bipolar ii en la CIE-11 y la exigencia adicional, además de la euforia o la irritabilidad, de un aumento de la energía o de la actividad para el diagnóstico de hipo/manía en ambas clasificaciones. El mantenimiento del diagnóstico de trastorno mixto ansioso-depresivo, del duelo como criterio de exclusión de depresión mayor, o el diagnóstico de episodio mixto en el trastorno bipolar, son algunas de las principales divergencias en la versión beta de la CIE-11 respecto al ya editado DSM-5. Conclusión. Dado que el DSM-5 ya ha sido publicado, serán necesarios cambios en el borrador de la CIE-11 o modificaciones del DSM-5.1 para armonizar los diagnósticos psiquiátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);7(4): 179-185, oct.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129523</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los trastornos bipolares en las nuevas clasificaciones: DSM-5 y CIE-11</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
