<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138386</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The mole or the difficult case of a passionate counter-transference</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The difficult case is difficult for whom? It is nevere the one you think. It solicits the counter.transference without the analyst realizing it. It is the case which, like 'a mole', infiltrates the organization of the session, of the cure, and of the analyst´s psychic life. Clinical illustration here attempt to illustrate this: a confusinal episode, nostalgia for the lost narcissistic paradise, loss of the primary object and identification (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cournut, Jean</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El caso difícil, ¿Para quién es difícil? No es nunca quien creemos. Él mismo solicita la contratransferencia sin que el analista se dé cuenta. Este es el caso, que de la misma manera que 'un topo', infiltra la organización de la sesión, de la cura, y de la vida psíquica del analista. Algunas ilustraciones clínicas intentan identificarlo: un episodio confusional, la nostalgia del paraíso narcisista perdido, pérdida del objeto primario e identificación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(74): 137-153, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El topo o el caso difícil de una contratransferencia apasionada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10457^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3245^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10457^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
