<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118655</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficiency analysis of corner kicks in the 2010 world cup. Trying to identifuyy the explanatory variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In soccer, dead-ball moves are those in which the ball is returned to play from a stationary position following an interruption of play. The aim of this study was to analyse the effectiveness of one such dead-ball move, namely corner kicks, and to identify the key variables that determine the success of a shot or header following a corner, thereby enabling a model of successful corner kicks to be proposed. We recorded 554 corner kicks performed during the 2010 World Cup in South Africa and carried out a univariate, bivariate and multivariate analysis of the data. The results indicated that corners were of limited effectiveness in terms of the success of subsequent shots or headers. The analysis also revealed a series of variables that were significantly related to one another, and this enabled us to propose an explanatory model. Although this model had limited explanatory power, it nonetheless helps to understand the execution of corner kicks in practical terms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rial Boubeta, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada López, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maneiro Dios, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardá Suárez, Toni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claudio A. Casal Sanjurjo, Claudio A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las acciones a balón parado (ABP) en fútbol son todas aquellas situaciones de juego que se inician con un saque desde parado después de una interrupción reglamentaria del mismo. En este trabajo se ha pretendido analizar la eficacia de una de estas acciones, el saque de esquina; identificar las variables más relevantes para conducir al éxito (el remate) a estas acciones y proponer un modelo de saque de esquina exitoso. Después del registro de 554 saques de esquina ejecutados en el Mundial de Sudáfrica 2010 y de realizar análisis a nivel univariado, bivariado y multivariado, los resultados indican una baja eficacia en el remate en este tipo de acciones, la identificación de una serie de variables que presentan una relación estadísticamente significativa y la propuesta de un modelo explicativo, que aunque presenta una capacidad explicativa limitada, ayuda a interpretar de forma práctica la ejecución de estas acciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(1): 165-172, ene.-jun. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la eficacia de los saques de esquina en la copa del mundo de fútbol 2010. Un intento de identificación de variables explicativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
