<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055344</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Roger Kornberg and RNApol II: unveiling the mechanism of ribonucleic acid synthesis half a century after Severo Ochoa and his polynucleotide phosphorylase</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2006 has been awarded to Prof. Roger Kornberg,    Head of the Department of Structural Biology, Stanford CA, USA. Prof. Kornberg    has been leading along years an exhaustive and rigorous research effort on RNApol    II, the protein complex responsible for the synthesis of messenger RNA in    eukaryotic cells. By means of biophysical approaches, X-ray crystallography in    particular, his work shows how ten of the twelve protein subunits of the whole    enzyme are coordinated in order to melt the two DNA strands, recognize the first    ribonucleotide to be incorporated on the template chain to be transcribed and    catalyze polymerization of successive nucleotide building blocks with astonishing    fidelity and processivity. Nearly half a century after the pioneering in vitro synthesis    of RNA by Severo Ochoa, the work now awarded unveils, with a wealth of intimate    details, the function of the macromolecular machinery essential for gene expression</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giraldo, Suárez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El premio Nobel de Química, en su edición de 2006, ha sido otorgado al Profesor    Roger Kornberg, del Departamento de Biología Estructural de la californiana    Universidad de Stanford. El Profesor Kornberg ha desarrollado durante años un    exhaustivo y riguroso trabajo sobre el complejo de proteínas responsable de la síntesis    del ARN mensajero en las células eucarióticas, la RNA polimerasa II. Aplicando    metodologías biofísicas, en particular la cristalografía de rayos-X, su trabajo    muestra cómo diez de las doce subunidades proteicas del enzima se coordinan    para separar las dos hebras de la molécula de ADN, reconocer el primer ribonucleótido    que debe incorporarse sobre el molde de la cadena que ha de ser transcrita    y catalizar la polimerización de sucesivos nucleótidos con gran fidelidad y procesividad.    Cerca de medio siglo después de que Severo Ochoa realizase la primera    síntesis bioquímica del ARN en un tubo de ensayo, el trabajo del ahora galardonado    desentraña, en sus detalles más íntimos, el funcionamiento de la maquinaria    macromolecular esencial para la expresión de los genes</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;73(1): 125-140, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Roger Kornberg y la RNApol II: el mecanismo de síntesis del ácido ribonucleico desvelado al medio siglo de Severo Ochoa y su polinucleótido fosforilasa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21058^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31535^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9800</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21058^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14550^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
