<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154667</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic myeloid leukaemia in Spain: Its presentation characteristics have changed. Spanish section of the EUTOS population-based registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To provide more reliable data on the epidemiology of chronic myeloid leukaemia (CML) in Spain than are currently available. Material and methods. The EUTOS population-based project of European LeukemiaNet is a population registry of new CML cases in patients 18 years of age or older from 22 European areas. The Spanish section included the autonomous communities of Madrid, Castilla-La Mancha and Aragon, from 1-2-2010 to 31-12-2012. Results. A total of 250 cases were recorded in 35 months. The overall incidence was 1.08 cases/105 inhabitants-year, with a predominance of men (58%) and clear differences among the communities. The incidence standardised by age was similar (overall, 1.04; men, 1.31; women, 0.81). The median age was 54 years. The incidence increased with age, reaching a peak at&gt;65 years, although 31.7% of cases appeared between the ages of 20 and 44 years. Four percent of cases were diagnosed in advanced stages (2.4% in accelerated phase, 1.6% in blast crisis), 56% were asymptomatic, 38% had splenomegaly, and the Sokal score was high in 11% (lower than what was previously reflected in the literature). Conclusions. The current incidence of CML in Spain is higher than previously reported and similar to that of the European studies. Unlike the classical descriptions, CML presented mostly in asymptomatic form, with no splenomegaly, less leucocytosis and in stages with better prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcia, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giraldo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gutiérrez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Steegmann, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Pretendemos aportar datos más fiables sobre la epidemiología de la leucemia mieloide crónica (LMC) en España que los disponibles hasta la fecha. Material y métodos. El registro poblacional EUTOS, de la European LeukemiaNet, es un registro de casos nuevos de LMC en pacientes &amp;#8805; de 18 años de 22 áreas europeas. La sección española incluyó las comunidades autónomas de Madrid, Castilla-La Mancha y Aragón, en el periodo comprendido entre el 1-2-2010 y el 31-12-2012. Resultados. Se registraron 250 casos en 35 meses. La incidencia global fue de 1,08 casos/105 habitantes-año, con predominio masculino (58% de varones) y claras diferencias entre comunidades autónomas. La incidencia estandarizada por edad fue similar (global 1,04, varones 1,31, mujeres 0,81). La mediana de edad fue de 54 años. La incidencia aumentó con la edad, siendo máxima en&gt;65 años, aunque un 31,7% de los casos aparecieron entre los 20 y los 44 años. Un 4% se diagnosticaron en fases avanzadas (2,4% en fase acelerada, 1,6% en crisis blástica), el 56% estaban asintomáticos, el 38% tenían esplenomegalia, y el score Sokal era alto en el 11% (inferior a lo previamente reflejado en la literatura). Conclusiones. La incidencia actual de LMC en España es superior a la previamente descrita y similar a la de los estudios europeos. A diferencia de las descripciones clásicas, la LMC se presenta mayoritariamente de forma asintomática, sin esplenomegalia, con menor leucocitosis y en estadios con mejor pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(6): 293-300, ago.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leucemia mieloide crónica en España: sus características de presentación han cambiado. Sección española del registro poblacional EUTOS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23724^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23724^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
