<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131449</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthcare education for self-monitoring in patients on oral anticoagulant drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, 800,000 people in Spain are being treated with oral anticoagulants for their conditions, and this figure keeps increasing due to the increase in life expectancy of the population. The importance of control and prevention of complications with these drugs is associated with patient follow-up and education, an essential aspect for preventing long-term problems. Healthcare Education, particularly in the Primary Care setting, is essential for patients on oral anticoagulant treatment, so that they can conduct self-monitoring at home. This is intended to improve their quality of life and lifestyle, achieving higher confidence and independence. We present in this article the design of a Healthcare Education Program (HEP) on self-management for oral anticoagulant treatment at home, which is developed in three stages: recruitment, scheduling of activities, evaluation and follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Higueras San Román, Blanca María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente 800.000 personas en España están siendo tratadas con anticoagulantes orales debido a su patología, cifra que sigue creciendo debido al aumento de la esperanza de vida de la población. La importancia del control y prevención de complicaciones de estos fármacos viene ligada al seguimiento y educación de los pacientes, aspecto imprescindible para evitar problemas a largo plazo. La educación para la salud, especialmente en el medio de la Atención Primaria, es fundamental para que los pacientes con trata-miento anticoagulante oral puedan realizar el autocontrol desde sus domicilios. De esta manera se pretende mejorar su calidad y estilo de vida, consiguiendo una mayor seguridad e independencia. En este artículo se presenta el diseño de un programa de educación para la salud (PES) sobre el automanejo del tratamiento con anticoagulantes orales en el domicilio, que se desarrolla en tres fases: captación, programación de actividades, y evaluación y seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(10): 28-32, dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educación para la salud para el autocontrol en pacientes con anticoagulantes orales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
