<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74987</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro antifungal activity of voriconazole: new data after the first years of clinical experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Voriconazole has been developed to meet the increasing need for new anduseful antifungal agents for the treatment of invasive mycoses. This reviewdescribes the in vitro spectrum of voriconazole antifungal activity based ondata from in vitro studies published during the last three years. This surveydemonstrates that voriconazole has a broad antifungal spectrum against themost common fungal pathogens being its action fungistatic for Candida andfungicidal for Aspergillus and other filamentous fungi. Overall, more than 95%of all Candida isolates tested are susceptible to voriconazole and less than3% are resistant. Similar or even better activity rates have been described forAspergillus, Cryptococcus and most of yeasts and moulds of medicalimportance. We also discuss the limitations related to the azolecross-resistance observed in some Candida glabrata isolates, the poor activityof voriconazole against Scedosporium prolificans, its activity against fungalbiofilms and the great potential usefulness of combination of voriconazole withother antifungal drugs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eraso, elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantón, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quindós, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo-Muñoz, Alfonso Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pemán, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Voriconazol se ha desarrollado para afrontar la necesidad creciente de nuevosy eficaces antifúngicos para tratar las micosis invasoras. Esta revisiondescribe el espectro de actividad in vitro de voriconazol basándose en losdatos obtenidos en estudios publicados en los últimos tres años.Esta valoración demuestra que voriconazol tiene un espectro antifúngico muyamplio que engloba a los patógenos fúngicos más comunes frente a los quedesarrolla una acción fungistática (Candida) y fungicida contra Aspergillus yotros hongos filamentosos. De forma global, más del 95% de todos losaislamientos de Candida son sensibles a voriconazol y menos del 3% sonresistentes. Tasas de actividades parecidas o mejores se han descrito paraAspergillus, Cryptococcus y el resto de levaduras y mohos de importanciamédica. También discutimos las limitaciones planteadas por la aparición deresistencias cruzadas a los azoles en algunos aislamientos de Candidaglabrata y la reducida actividad de voriconazol contra Scedosporiumprolificans, su actividad sobre las biopelículas fúngicas y de la gran utilidadpotencial de la combinación de voriconazol con otros antifúngicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(3): 198-208, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antifúngica in vitro de voriconazol: nuevos datos después de los primeros años de experiencia clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14625^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3471^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3903^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35306^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
