<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165740</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability in the measurement of body temperature with a tympanic thermometer in geriatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The determination of body temperature must be accurate, valid and reliable. Objectives: To evaluate the reliability of the body temperature measurement with a tympanic thermometer in hospitalized patients. To analyze the interobserver concordance in the determination of the temperature, in application of the correct technique and in habitual practice. Identify patient variables that could influence the temperature measurement. Methodology: Observational study of diagnostic tests in geriatric patients hospitalized for acute pathology. Three consecutive measurements of body temperature (clinical practice conditions vs. ideal conditions with two trained researchers) were performed. Results: The intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) among investigators for the same ear was 0.97 with a confidence interval (0.95-0.98) for the right ear and (0.96-0.98) the left ear. The ICC between ears for the same investigator, concordance was 0.89 (IC 0.84-0.93) investigator one and 0.92 (IC 0.87-0.94) investigator two. When comparing the plant measurements with the researchers, the concordance was 0.76 (CI 0.64-0.84). There was variation in all KICs by excluding &#145;lateral decubitus over ear rated&#146; with concordance between ears of 0.92 (IC 0.88-0.95) investigator one and 0.95 (IC 0.91-0.96) investigator two; As well as concordance 0.72 (CI 0.56-0.82) between the average of the researchers and the plant measurements. Conclusions: The tympanic device is reliable and reproducible, especially if the measurement is performed according to a technique based on scientific evidence. There are variables of the patient that are likely to influence the measurement, such as lateral decubitus over the assessed ear, so it is necessary to take into account certain factors and establish criteria in the measurement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rodríguez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viano Pérez, Elia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Álvarez, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorín Bayón, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La determinación de la temperatura corporal ha de ser precisa, válida y confiable. Objetivos: Evaluar la fiabilidad de la medición de la temperatura corporal con un termómetro timpánico en pacientes geriátricos ingresados. Analizar la concordancia interobservador en la determinación de la temperatura, en aplicación de la técnica correcta y en práctica habitual. Identificar las variables del paciente que podrían influir en la medición de la temperatura. Metodología: Estudio observacional de pruebas diagnósticas en pacientes geriátricos ingresados por patología aguda. Se realizaron tres mediciones consecutivas de la temperatura corporal (condiciones de práctica clínica vs. condiciones ideales con dos investigadoras adiestradas). Resultados: El coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI) entre investigadoras para el mismo oído fue 0,97 con un intervalo de confianza (0,95-0,98) para el oído derecho y (0,96-0,98) para el oído izquierdo. El CCI entre oídos para el mismo investigador tuvo una concordancia de 0,89 (IC 0,84-0,93) investigador uno y 0,92 (IC 0,87-0,94) investigador dos. Al comparar las mediciones de planta con las de las investigadoras, la concordancia fue 0,76 (IC 0,64- 0,84). Hubo variación en todos los CCI al excluir &#145;decúbito lateral sobre oído valorado&#146; con concordancia entre oídos de 0,92 (IC 0,88-0,95) investigador uno y de 0,95 (IC 0,91-0,96) investigador dos; así como concordancia 0,72 (IC 0,56-0,82) entre el promedio de las investigadoras y las mediciones de planta. Conclusiones: El dispositivo timpánico es fiable y reproducible, especialmente si la medición se realiza según una técnica basada en evidencia científica. Existen variables del paciente susceptibles de influir en la medición, como el decúbito lateral sobre oído valorado, por lo que es necesario tener en cuenta ciertos factores y establecer criterios en la medición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(2): 68-72, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165740</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad en la medición de la temperatura corporal con un termómetro timpánico en pacientes geriátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14198^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23479^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
