<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118360</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Major depression is one of the affective disorders with higher prevalence in clinical. Although major depression comprises many neurobiological pro cesses, the current treatment is focusing in the increase of NA and 5Ht neurotransmitters in the cNS, and even less dopamine. Both treatment and response of patients to antidepressants require high monitoring due to the fact that 25 % of population result resistant to the treatment, 25-50 % respond partially and only the 50 % improve the symptom of depression. Another pharmacological strategies used in patients resistant to depression, involves the administration of other agents in combination with antidepressants to enhance their effect. Depression is widely known by its affective component characterized by moods, feelings of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Micó, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrocoso, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La depresión mayor es uno de los trastornos afectivos con mayor prevalencia en clínica. A pesar de todos los procesos neurobiológicos implicados en esta patología, el tratamiento actual de la depresión se centra en los neurotransmisores NA y 5Ht a nivel de sistema nervioso central, y en menor medida, dopamina. el tratamiento con antidepresivos y su respuesta requiere una revaloración sistemática del paciente debido a que existe un 25 % de la población que no responde al tratamiento con estos fármacos, del 26-50 % responden solo parcialmente y tan solo un 50 % responde favorablemente, o al menos, disminuyen significativamente los síntomas más graves de la enfermedad. Las estrategias usadas en pacientes resistentes a la depresión, consiste en la administración de otros agentes en combinación con antidepresivos para aumentar su efecto. La depresión (..) (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(213): 261-273, sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicofarmacología y trastornos afectivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6783^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53316^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9607^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23566^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
