<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115682</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Narcolepsia y olor: resultados preliminares</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. This study has been carried out to test the clinical hypothesis of personal smell as a hint to the diagnosis of narcoleptic patients. Methods. Sweat samples from narcoleptic and healthy controls were tested independently by two trained dogs and their positive or negative detection compared to the gold standard diagnosis for narcolepsy. Neither trainer nor dog knew the source of the sample selected or its placement in the search device. Twelve narcoleptic patients, both sexes and various ages, recruited from April 2011 to June 2012 and diagnosed according to standard criteria, through their clinical records and nocturnal polysomnography plus multiple sleep latency test, made up the patient group. The control group was made up of 22 healthy volunteer without sleep disorders, both sexes and various ages. Sweat samples from both patients and controls were collected following the same protocol to avoid contamination, and tested independently by two trained dogs. Results. Eleven narcoleptic were detected positive by the dogs while only three controls. Conclusion. It seems that narcoleptic patients have a distinct typical odor that trained dogs can detect. The development of olfactory test could be a useful method in the screening of narcolepsy while opens a new research area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Gállego, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dominguez-Ortega, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dominguez-Sanchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Comino, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera García-Armenter, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de este estudio es probar la hipótesis de un olor corporal característico en narcolepticos como indicador de diagnóstico. Métodos: Se testan muestras de sudor de 12 narcolepticos y 22 controles sanos de forma independiente por dos perros entrenados y su detección, positiva o negativa, se compara con el diagnostico &#145;&#145;gold standard&#146;&#146; de narcolepsia. Ni adiestrador ni perros conocían el tipo de muestra seleccionada o su emplazamiento en el dispositivo de búsqueda. 12 pacientes con narcolepsia, de ambos sexos y distintas edades, reclutados entre abril de 2011 y junio de 2012, y diagnosticados de acuerdo a criterios estándar, a través de su historia clínica y polisomnografía nocturna seguida de test de latencia múltiple del sue&#152;no, conforman el grupo de pacientes. El grupo control está formado por 22 voluntarios sanos, de ambos sexos y distintas edades, sin trastorno del sue&#152;no. Las muestras de sudor, tanto de pacientes como de controles, se recogieron siguiendo el mismo protocolo para evitar contaminación y fueron testadas de forma independiente por dos perros entrenados. Resultados: 11 narcolepticos son detectados positivamente por los perros frente a solo 3 controles sanos. Conclusión: Parece que los pacientes con narcolepsia tienen un olor corporal típico que perros entrenados pueden detector. El desarrollo de un test de olfato para el diagnostico de narcolepsia abre nuevas áreas de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(7): e41-e46, oct. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Narcolepsy and odor: preliminary report</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34196^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53264^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34196^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53264^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
