<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89327</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current considerations on the prevention of vertical transmission of group B beta´hemolytic streptococcus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neonatal bacterial sepsis is a clinical syndrome characterized by signs of systemic infection accompanied by bacteriemia. Neonatal infection due to vertical transmission refers to that which is transmitted by the mother to the fetus or to the newborn (NB) during the pregnancy, delivery and neonatal period. The bacterias involved are those found in the delivery canal, which mostly have low virulence, but they may sometimes infect the mother or NB. Currently the primary agent of vertical transmission bacterial infection is the Streptococcus agalactiae (group B &amp;#946;-hemolytic streptococcus) (EGB) infection by Escherichia coli and other gram negative bacilli being less frequent and it is generally observed, above all, in premature very low weight NB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Abizanda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabero Roura, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Omeñaca Terés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa Fraile, M de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sepsis bacteriana del neonato es un síndrome clínico caracterizado por signos de infección sistémica acompañados de bacteriemia. Denominamos infección neonatal de transmisión vertical aquella que es transmitida por la madre al feto o al recién nacido (RN) durante el embarazo, el parto el período neonatal. Las bacterias implicadas son las que se encuentran en el canal del parto que en su mayoría son de baja virulencia, pero ocasionalmente pueden infectar a la madre o al RN. Actualmente el principal agente de infección bacteriana de transmisión vertical es el Streptococcus agalactiae (estreptococo &amp;#946; &#150; hemolítico del grupo B) (EGB), siendo menos frecuente la infección por Escherichia coli y otros bacilos gran negativos y se suele observar, sobre todo, en RN prematuros y de muy bajo peso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(3): 240-247, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones actuales sobre la prevención de la transmisión vertical del estreptococo &amp;#946; - hemolítico del grupo B</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32719^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13679^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
