<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132521</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of pain in the oncology patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain is a symptom with a high prevalence in patients with cancer and causes an important deterioration in their quality of life. With the measures laid out by the WHO in 1986, which divides the different therapeutic options available in three ascending steps, pain can be controlled in a high percentage of cases. Those patients who are difficult to control with these measures can benefit from the application of neuromodulation techniques by experts in the treatment of chronic pain. The correct employment of the different medicines (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medicines, opiates and coadjuvants), knowledge of the secondary effects, loss of fear in the face of opiates and knowledge of the different algic syndromes associated with the oncology patient, must be accompanied by a suitable evaluation of the pain according to the different scales, both in the phase of the treatment's initiation and in the follow-up of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borque, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araujo, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañeda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pezonaga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor es un síntoma de alta prevalencia en los pacientes con cáncer y deteriora de forma importante su calidad de vida. Con las medidas enunciadas por la OMS en 1986, que divide en tres escalones ascendentes las distintas opciones terapéuticas de las que disponemos, el dolor puede ser controlado en un alto porcentaje de casos. Aquellos pacientes difíciles de controlar con estas medidas, se pueden beneficiar de la aplicación de técnicas de neuromodulación por expertos en el tratamiento del dolor crónico.  El correcto manejo de los distintos fármacos (AINES, opiáceos y coadyuvantes), el conocimiento de sus efectos secundarios, la pérdida del miedo a los opiáceos y el conocimiento de los distintos síndromes álgicos asociados al paciente oncológico, deben ir de la mano con la adecuada valoración del dolor según las distintas escalas, tanto en la fase de instauración del tratamiento, como en el seguimiento del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;27(supl.3): 63-75, 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del dolor en el paciente oncológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
