<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62200</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic and preventive boarding of injuries in the soccer by means of functional bandages and orthosis: Knee sprain and atellofemoral pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PurposeTo analyze the evolution of research on the use of orthosis and functional bandages as preventive element of the injuries in the soccer.Search strategyA review of the documents and references was performed. The data bases consulted were Medline and Cochrane with Pubmed. Study and data selection: Searches were conducted with Pubmed, were classified by two search objectives. The objective was to analyze the use of functional bandages in the prevention of injuries and to give priority to soccer in the search.ResultsUse of prophylactic orthotics and bandages has not been demonstrated effective in the prevention of knee sprains and femoropatellar pain. Regarding orthosis and therapeutic bandages, use of functional therapeutic bandages in benign sprains as the only form of containment and in sprains of 2 or 3 degree in subacute phase has been shown to be effective. However, orthosis should be used the use of functional bandages is contraindicated and in serious injuries that require strict immobilization. The use of functional bandages and orthosis have been shown to be effective to avoid poorly recovered residual sequels and in those where other mechanisms of performance (force training, propioception, etc.) have been ruled out, especially the femoropatellar taping and the stabilization knee orthosis (in the first post-injury months).ConclusionsTherapeutic and functional knee bandages are effective, but only if they are well indicated(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Novoa Castro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar la evolución de la investigación en el uso de ortesis y vendajes funcionales como elemento preventivo de las lesiones en el fútbol. Estrategia de búsqueda: se realizó una revisión documental y bibliográfica. Las bases de datos consultadas fueron Medline y Cochrane mediante PubMed.Selección de estudios y datosLas búsquedas que se han realizado mediante PubMed y clasificadas por dos objetivos de búsqueda, teniendo como objetivo analizar el uso de vendajes funcionales en la prevención de lesiones y dando prioridad a la búsqueda en el fútbol.ResultadosEl uso de ortesis y vendajes profilácticos no se ha demostrado eficaz en la prevención de esguinces de rodilla y dolor femoropatelar. Respecto a las ortesis y a los vendajes terapéuticos, se muestra como eficaz el uso de vendajes funcionales terapéuticos en esguinces benignos como única forma de contención y en esguinces de grado 2 o 3 en fase subaguda. Pero se deben utilizar ortesis cuando está contraindicado el uso de vendajes funcionales y con lesiones graves que requieran inmovilización estricta. El uso de vendajes y ortesis funcionales se ha mostrado eficaz para evitar secuelas residuales en lesiones mal recuperadas y en las que se han agotado los demás mecanismos de actuación (entrenamiento de la fuerza, propiocepción, etc.), sobre todo el taping femoropatelar y las ortesis de estabilización de la rodilla (en los primeros meses postlesión).ConclusionesLos vendajes y ortesis de rodilla son eficaces desde el punto de vista terapéutico y funcional, pero sólo si está bien indicado su uso(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(3): 101-106, mayo 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje terapéutico y preventivo de lesiones en el fútbol mediante vendajes funcionales y ortesis: esguince de rodilla y dolor femoropatelar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38611^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
