<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92751</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To present a case of chylothorax secondary to Hodgkin&#146;s disease. Methods: We report a clinical case with a brief review of the literature about chylothorax secondary to classical Hodgkin&#146;s disease. The clinical features are stood out. The diagnostic and therapeutic implications are discussed focusing on the role of thoracentesis and histopathological studies. Results: A 69-year-old woman presented constitutional symptoms such as fever and loss of weight, associated to cough and dyspnea without evidence of involvement of lymph nodes on physical exam. Chylothorax was demonstrated in the study of pleural fluid after thoracentesis, while Hodgkin&#146;s disease was diagnosed through fine-needle aspiration of lymph nodes in the posterior mediastinum under CT scan guidance. Conclusion: Chylothorax secondary to Hodgkin&#146;s disease is a rare entity with unspecific manifestations. In the most of cases, it presents as a left-sided pleural effusion. A diagnosticthoracentesis should be performed to study of pleural fluid. CT scan, fine-needle aspiration biopsy and histopathological studies confirmed the diagnosis. Marked clinical improvement was achieved with radiotherapy and other procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Holguín Prieto, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pila Pérez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Batueca, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pila Peláez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Aportar a la literatura existente, un nuevo caso de quilotórax por enfermedad de Hodgkin tipo clásica. Métodos: Mediante el formato de caso clínico realizamos un breve análisis de la literatura sobre quilotórax por enfermedad de Hodgkin, señalando aspectos relacionados con la forma de presentación, diagnóstico y terapéutica, entre otros. Resultados: Mujer de 69 años con motivo de ingreso relacionado con síntomas constitucionales dados por fiebre y pérdida de peso, además de tos y disnea, sin manifestaciones primarias de ganglios u otros signos de afección linfoproliferativa. La toracocentesis con el aspecto del líquido y su estudio demuestran el diagnóstico de un quilotórax, mientras que la TAC y la CAAF confirman la presencia de un linfoma de Hodgkin. Conclusiones: El quilotórax por enfermedad de Hodgkin es una entidad de escasa incidencia, se presenta con una clínica inespecífica y silente, afectando preferentemente el pulmón izquierdo. Es una enfermedad que se detecta en la clínica por el estudio y aspecto del líquido del derrame pleural. El diagnóstico se confirma por TAC, CAAF y estudio histopatológico. Como terapéutica en nuestra paciente empleamos radioterapia junto con otros procederes propios de esta entidad y hasta el momento se encuentra asintomática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;12(3): 162-166, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quilotórax secundario a enfermedad de Hodgkin</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2941^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
