<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155078</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in physical activity after a COPD respiratory rehabilitation program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: inactivity is a permanent finding in COPD patients and it has clear prognostic implications associated with an increase in morbidity-mortality rate. Nevertheless, we do not have effective strategies to increase physical activity in our patients. The objective of this work was to assess the impact of a respiratory rehabilitation (RR) program on the physical activity level of COPD patients, measured with an accelerometer. Method: longitudinal, prospective and randomized study in two groups: control and intervention group, with a mixed, 12-week (3 weekly sessions) RR program with three month follow-up. Physical activity was measured with an accelerometer, baseline measurement and after three months in both groups. Results: n: 36 (RR 19 vs control 17). Most of the participants were men, with a mean age of 64 ± 3.6 in RR y 64.9 ± 10,1 in the control group, with serious obstruction (RR 45.5 ± 15.9% vs control 33.8 ± 7.3%) and accumulated tobacco consumption that was significantly higher in the control group (RR 49 vs Control 65.4 pack/yr.). In basal metabolism terms, the subjects in both groups were sedentary. Upon concluding the training program, no significant differences were found in the variables for physical activity analyzed in either group. In terms of exercise tolerance, the rehabilitation group presented better results than the control group. (PM6M: RR 478 ± 33.6 m vs Control 367.7 ± 106 m, p 0.01/Submaxim: RR 1,231.1 ± 640.4 vs 390 ± 155 sec., p 0.01. Conclusions: this study shows that a respiratory rehabilitation program improves tolerance to exercise in patients, but the benefits of physical activity continue to be controversial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Bastero Fernández, AP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón Masa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz Rodríguez, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montemayor Rubio, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almadana Pacheco, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la inactividad es un hallazgo permanente en los pacientes EPOC y tiene clara implicación pronóstica, asociándose con un aumento de la morbimortalidad. Sin embargo, aún no disponemos de estrategias eficaces para aumentar el nivel de actividad física de nuestros pacientes. El objetivo del trabajo fue evaluar el impacto de un programa de rehabilitación respiratoria (RR) en el nivel de actividad física en EPOC, medido por acelerómetro. Método: estudio longitudinal, prospectivo y randomizado en 2 grupos: control y de intervención, con programa de RR mixto de 12 semanas (3 sesiones/semana) con seguimiento a 3 meses. Se midió actividad física mediante acelerómetro, de forma basal y a los 3 meses en ambos grupos. Resultados: n: 36 (RR 19 vs control 17). La mayoría hombres, con edad media de 64 ± 3,6 en RR y 64,9 ± 10,1 en control, con una obstrucción grave (RR 45,5 ± 15,9% vs control 33,8 ± 7,3%) y un consumo acumulado de tabaco significativamente mayor en el grupo control (RR 49 vs control 65,4 paq/año). Basalmente, los sujetos de ambos grupos eran sedentarios. Tras finalizar el programa de entrenamiento, no se encontraron diferencias significativas en las variables de actividad física analizadas en ninguno grupo. En cuanto a tolerancia al ejercicio, el grupo de rehabilitación presentó mejores resultados que el control (PM6M: RR 478 ± 33,6 m vs control 367,7 ± 106 m, p 0,01/Submáximo: RR 1.231,1 ± 640,4 vs control 390 ± 155 seg, p 0,01. Conclusiones: en nuestro trabajo, un programa específico de rehabilitación respiratoria mejora la tolerancia al ejercicio de los pacientes, pero el beneficio en cuanto actividad física continúa siendo controvertido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;28(4): 214-221, jul. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en actividad física tras un programa de rehabilitación respiratoria en EPOC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55045^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1970^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
