<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71817</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Pancreatic cancer has the poorest prognosis of any common gastrointestinal malignancy, with a 5-year overall survival of less than 5%. A better knowledge of prognostic factors related to this neoplasia might help improve the survival of these patients. We evaluated the prognostic significance of different factors in both overall survival and tumor recurrence in patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma who had undergone pancreatic resection with curative intent. Patients and method: All patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma submitted to surgical resection in our unit from January 1995 to February 2005 were evaluated. Twenty-three pre-surgical, therapeutic, and histopathologic variables were analyzed. Univariate (Kaplan-Meier, log-rank test) and multivariate (Cox regression) analyses were performed to select independent prognostic factors. Results: Ninety-four patients were evaluated. The median age of patients was 63 years and 53% were woman. The probability of overall survival was 63% at 1 year, 18% at 3 years, and 8% at 5 years, with a median survival of 18 months. Univariate analysis identified performance of adjuvant therapy, histologic grade, percentage of involved-resected lymph nodes, pathologic N stage, and pathologic TNM stage as variables associated with overall survival. On the other hand, the probability of tumor recurrence was 52% at 1 year, 83% at 3 years, and 91% at 5 years, with a median time to tumor recurrence of 12 months. Predictive variables of tumor recurrence in the univariate analysis were preoperative N stage, preoperative TNM stage, postoperative CA 19.9 serum concentration, histological grade, percentage of involved-resected lymph nodes, pathologic N stage and pathologic TNM stage. Multivariate analysis identified histological grade and pathologic N stage as independent predictive factors of both overall survival (histologic grade: HR=2.341 [CI 95%, 1.342¿4.098; p=0.003]; pathologic N stage: HR=2.242 [1.213¿4.149; p=0.01]) and tumor recurrence (histological grade: HR=1.742 [CI 95%, 1.121¿3.086; p=0.05]; pathologic N stage: HR=2.096 [1.089¿4.032; p=0.027]). Conclusions: The histological grade and pathologic N stage predict the prognosis of patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma after surgical resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pellisé, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Izquierdo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nadal, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro,  Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maurel, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adet, Ana C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cruz, Laureano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bombí, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conill, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Boado, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piqué, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: el cáncer de páncreas tiene el peor pronóstico de los tumores gastrointestinales, con una supervivencia media a los 5 años de menos del 5%. Un mejor conocimiento de los factores pronósticos de esta neoplasia podría ayudarnos a mejorar la supervivencia de estos pacientes. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el significado pronóstico de diferentes factores en relación tanto con la supervivencia general como con la recurrencia tumoral en pacientes con adenocarcinoma pancreático intervenidos con intención curativa. Pacientes y método: se ha evaluado a todos los pacientes con adenocarcinoma pancreático intervenidos en nuestra unidad desde enero de 1995 a febrero de 2005. Se analizaron 23 variables prequirúrgicas, terapéuticas e histopatológicas. Para seleccionar los factores pronósticos independientes se realizó un análisis univariable (con curvas de Kaplan-Meier y prueba de rangos logarítmicos) y otro multivariable (regresión de Cox). Resultados: se evaluó a 94 pacientes. La mediana de edad de los pacientes fue 63 años y el 53% eran mujeres. La supervivencia general fue del 63% al año, del 18% a los 3 años y del 8% a los 5 años, con una mediana de supervivencia de 18 meses. El análisis univariable identificó como variables relacionadas con la supervivencia general el grado histológico, el porcentaje de ganglios afectados de los que fueron resecados, el estadio N patológico y el estadio TNM patológico. Por otro lado, la probabilidad de recurrencia tumoral fue del 52% al año, del 83% a los 3 años y del 91% a los 5 años, con una mediana para la recurrencia tumoral de 12 meses. Las variables predictivas de recurrencia tumoral en el análisis univariable fueron el estadio N preoperatorio, el estadio TNM preoperatorio, la concentración sérica postoperatoria de CA19.9, el grado histológico, el porcentaje de ganglios afectos de los que fueron resecados, el estadio N patológico y el estadio TNM patológico. El análisis multivariable identificó el grado histológico y el estadio N patológico como los factores predictivos independientes tanto de la supervivencia general (grado histológico: hazard ratio [HR]=2,341; intervalo de confianza[IC] del 95%, 1,342¿4,098; p=0,003; estadio N patológico: HR=2,242; IC del 95%, 1,213¿4,149; p=0,01) como de la recurrencia tumoral (grado histológico: HR=1,742; IC del 95%, 1,021¿3,086; p=0,05; estadio N patológico: HR=2,096; IC del 95%, 1,089¿4,032; p=0,027). Conclusiones: el grado histológico y el estadio N patológico predicen el pronóstico de los pacientes con adenocarcinoma pancreático después de la resección quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(5): 163-171, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71817</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
