<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133487</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Applicability of BMI in aolescent students living at moderate altitude of Peru</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and Objectives: The use of BMI is highly contested, especially in populations in which growth phase is characterized by short stature for his age. The aim is to verify if the BMI is applicable to a school sample of adolescents living in a region of moderate altitude of Peru. Material and Methods: A descriptive cross-sectional study in 319 adolescent students (181 men and 138 women) from 12.0 to 17.9 years of age. Anthropometric variables of height and weight were evaluated. Body Mass Index (BMI) was calculated. The CDC -2000 reference was used to compare weight and height from Z- score and BMI by mean difference. Results: The Z - score showed body weight to small variations (from -0.3 to 0.3 kg). In stature negative values for both sexes (men between -0.3 to -1.3 cm and women between -0.5 to 1.3 cm) is observed. For BMI, there were  significant differences in all ages and in both sexes (p &lt;0.05). Conclusion: The mean values of BMI in adolescents of both sexes are increased due to the observed low stature. These results suggest that BMI would not apply to school adolescents living in a region of moderate altitude of Peru (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Viveros Flores, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cossio Bolaños, Marco Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camargo, Cristiane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hespanhol, Jefferson Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Campos, Rossana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El uso del IMC es muy cuestionado, sobretodo, en poblaciones en fase de crecimiento que se caracterizan por presentar baja estatura para su edad. El objetivo es verificar si el IMC es aplicable a una muestra de escolares adolescentes que viven en una región de moderada altitud del Perú. Material y Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en 319 adolescentes escolares (181 hombres y 138 mujeres) de 12,0 a 17,9 años de edad. Se evaluó las variables antropométricas del peso y la estatura. Se calculó el Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC). Se utilizó la referencia del CDC-2000 para comparar el peso y estatura a partir del Z-score y el IMC por medio de diferencia de medias. Resultados: El Z-score para el peso corporal mostró pequeñas variaciones (entre -0,3 a 0,3 kg). En la estatura se observa valores negativos para ambos sexos (hombres entre -0,3 a -1,3 cm y mujeres entre -0,5 a 1,3 cm). Respecto  al IMC, hubo diferencias significativas en todas la edades y en ambos sexos (p&lt;0,05). Conclusión: Los valores medios del IMC en adolescentes de ambos sexos se ven incrementados debido a la baja estatura observada. Estos resultados sugieren que el IMC no sería aplicable a escolares adolescentes que viven en una región de moderada altitud del Perú (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 922-927, feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicabilidad del IMC en adolescentes escolares que viven a moderada altitud del Perú</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1852^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
