<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141080</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender inequalities in health deterioration as a result of informal care in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze differences in the characteristics of care provided by women and men to dependent persons, and their association with the perception of health deterioration in both sexes. Methods: We performed a nationwide cross-sectional study with data obtained from the 2008 Spanish Survey on Disability, Personal Autonomy and Dependence, based on a sample size of 7,512 principal caregivers. A descriptive analysis was performed of the characteristics of the care provided (tasks performed, intensity, frequency and duration) by sex. A multivariate logistic regression analysis was carried out to explore the association between the caregivers&#146; perceptions of deteriorated health and the variables related to care, adjusted by sociodemographic characteristics. Results: Most (74%) of the caregivers in the sample were women. Women more frequently perceived a deterioration in their health as a result of providing care than did men (37% and 21%, respectively). Women provided care with greater intensity and more frequently performed the tasks most associated with deteriorated health (personal hygiene, assistance in feeding, etc.). Men more frequently carried out tasks related to care outside the home (going to the doctor, shopping, etc.), all of which acted as a protective factor against health deterioration. The intensity of care was a risk factor for the perception of health deterioration in both sexes, while frequency and duration were also risk factors in women. Conclusions: The greater health deterioration perceived by women is related to gender inequalities in the characteristics of the care provided. Interventions in informal caregivers should be sensitive to these gender inequalities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, María del Río</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Marcos, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Calvente, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar las diferencias en las características del cuidado que prestan mujeres y hombres a personas dependientes, y su asociación con la percepción del deterioro de la salud como consecuencia de cuidar. Métodos: Estudio epidemiológico transversal de ámbito nacional sobre la muestra de 7.512 personas cuidadoras principales de la Encuesta de Discapacidad, Autonomía Personal y Dependencia 2008. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de características del cuidado (tareas realizadas, intensidad, frecuencia y duración) según sexo. Mediante regresión logística multivariada se analizó la asociación entre la percepción de deterioro de la salud y las variables de cuidado, ajustando por características sociodemográficas. Resultados: El 74% de las personas cuidadoras son mujeres y perciben con mayor frecuencia que los varones un deterioro de su salud como consecuencia de cuidar (37% y 21%, respectivamente). Ellas prestan un cuidado de mayor intensidad y asumen con mayor frecuencia tareas de ayuda para el aseo personal, comer y vestirse, asociadas a un mayor riesgo de percepción de deterioro de la salud. Los hombres realizan más tareas de cuidado fuera del hogar (ir al médico, hacer compras y gestiones), que resultan protectoras para la percepción de deterioro de la salud. La intensidad del cuidado es un factor de riesgo para la percepción de deterioro de la salud en ambos sexos, y en las mujeres se añaden la frecuencia y duración. Conclusiones: El mayor deterioro de la salud derivado del cuidado que perciben las mujeres está relacionado con desigualdades de género en las características del cuidado. Las intervenciones orientadas a personas cuidadoras deberían ser sensibles a las desigualdades de género existentes en el cuidado informal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(supl.2): 100-107, dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualdades de género en el deterioro de la salud como consecuencia del cuidado informal en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35418^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
