<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60232</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention in childhood cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite the various types of observational evidence, the establishment of a causal relationship between the environment and paediatric cancer (PC) has been fraught with inherent methodological difficulties. We have carry out an analysis of the nature of the problem to propose some of the useful and concrete paediatric aspects to prevent of the PC and the adult cancer form the childhood. In this paper, we emphasized the following: a) to create Paediatric Environmental Health Speciality Units; b) to integrate the paediatric environmental history for all children with cancer; c) to incorporate the &#147;green page&#148; to the well-child visit programs; d) to diminish the use of the ionizing radiation; e) to implement breastfeeding and smoking cessation services into paediatric department; f) to disclose and foment the intake of a more vegetarian diet; g) to develop of the guide of school environment health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Andreu, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrís i Tortajada, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriuso Lapresa, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista Sirvent, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega García, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berbel Tornero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de las numerosas evidencias basadas en la observación, el establecimiento de la relación causal entre medio ambiente y cáncer pediátrico (CP) ha estado lleno de dificultades metodológicas. Nosotros presentamos un análisis de la naturaleza del problema para proponer algunos de los aspectos relevantes y concretos de utilidad en la práctica pediátrica para la prevención del CP y del cáncer adulto desde la infancia entre los que se encuentran: a) crear unidades de salud medioambiental pediátrica; b) desarrollar la historia clínica medioambiental en el niño con cáncer; c) incorporar la &#147;hoja verde&#148; a los programas de atención del niño sano; d) programa de minimización en el uso de la radiación ionizante; e) implementar las consultas de lactancia materna y deshabituación del consumo de tabaco en pediatría; f) divulgar y fomentar el consumo de una dieta &#147;mas vegetariana&#148;; g) colaborar en el desarrollo de la guía de acción medioambiental escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(5): 389-401, sept.-oct. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60232</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención del cáncer pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23924^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15077</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
