<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041861</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thoracal epidural analgesia for the management of unstable angina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ischemic cardiomyopathy in patients with unstable anginarefractory to medical therapy is a difficult medical condition.Unfavorable anatomy or excessive surgical risk canadvise against the performance of angioplasty or coronarybypass surgery. This study has reviewed the use of thoracalepidural analgesia/anesthesia for the management and stabilizationof this type of patients, with a brief description ofthe physiopathology of cardiac ischemia, experimentalstudies in animals and human beings, use of cardiacsurgery and side effects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Atanassoff, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La miocardiopatía isquémica en pacientes con anginainestable refractaria al tratamiento médico constituye unescenario clínico complicado. Una anatomía desfavorableo un riesgo quirúrgico excesivamente alto pueden desaconsejarla realización de una angioplastia o de una cirugía dederivación coronaria. En este artículo se pretende revisar lautilización de la analgesia/anestesia epidural torácica parael tratamiento y estabilización de este tipo de pacientes, através de una breve descripción de la fisiopatología de la isquemiacardiaca, estudios experimentales en animales y humanos, uso en cirugía cardiaca y efectos secundarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(5): 283-288, jun.-jul. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041861</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia epidural torácica para el tratamiento de la angina inestable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33586^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
