<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113534</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioral activation therapy in cancer patients: An intervention proposal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to determine the  beliefs and emotions of hospitalized patients  in the Oncology Service of the Hospital  Juárez of Mexico and to design a program of  psychological intervention based on behavioral  activation therapy. We used modified natural  semantic networks (Reyes-Lagunes, 1993),  which started from a central concept (node),  which are produced specific words with  semantic value for its importance to patients.  Participants were 25 inpatients, 19 women  and 6 men in treatment for cancer were  interviewed between June and September of  2011. Data were analyzed using Microsoft  Office Excel version 2007 to further develop   a proposed psychological intervention based  on behavioral activation to control intrusive  thoughts, anxiety and depression. The results  showed that inactivity and long hospital stays  favor the presence of negative moods. So we  propose the implementation of behavioral  activation programs as a source of natural  reinforcement that favors an increase in  activities and a significant change in mood,  avoiding the continued presence of anxiety   and depression even outside the hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Becerra Gálvez, Ana Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lugo González, Isaías Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reynoso Erazo, Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo fue conocer las  creencias y emociones de pacientes hospitalizados en el Servicio de Oncología del Hospital  Juárez de México y así diseñar un programa de  intervención psicológica fundamentado en la  terapia de activación conductual. Se utilizaron  redes semánticas naturales modificadas (ReyesLagunes, 1993), las cuales partieron de un concepto central (nodo), del cual se producen palabras definidoras con valor semántico por su  importancia para los pacientes. Participaron 25  pacientes hospitalizados, 19 mujeres y 6 hombres en tratamiento oncológico los cuales fueron  entrevistados de junio a septiembre del 2011.   Los datos se analizaron con el programa Microsoft Office Excel versión 2007 para posteriormente desarrollar una propuesta de intervención  psicológica basada en la activación conductual  para el control de pensamientos intrusivos, ansiedad y depresión. Los resultados demostraron  que la inactividad y estancias hospitalarias largas  favorecen la presencia de estados de ánimo negativos. Por lo que se propone la implementación  de programas de activación conductual ya que   suponen una fuente de reforzamiento natural  que favorece un incremento de las actividades y  un cambio significativo en el humor, evitando así  la presencia sostenida de la ansiedad y depresión  aún fuera del contexto hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);10(1): 163-168, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de activación conductual en pacientes oncológicos: una propuesta de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
