<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103678</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry. 11th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Electrophysiology and Arrhythmias (2011)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The findings of the 2011 Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry are presented. Methods. Data were collected in two ways: retrospectively using a standardized questionnaire, and prospectively from a central database. Each participating center selected its own preferred method of data collection. Results. Sixty-six Spanish centers voluntarily contributed data to the survey. Some 9662 ablation procedures were analyzed, averaging 146 (104) per center. The three main conditions treated were atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (n=2537; 26%), typical atrial flutter (n=2205; 23%) and accessory pathways (n=1813; 19%). Atrial fibrillation was the fourth most common substrate treated (n=1535; 16%) and showed a slight increase over figures for 2010. Ventricular arrhythmia ablation has increased considerably. The overall success rate was 94%; major complications occurred in 2.2% and overall mortality was 0.04%. Conclusions. Data from the 2011 registry show a continued increase in the number of ablations performed with a generally high success rate and few complications. The use of complex substrate ablation continues to grow (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrero de Loma-Osorio, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Infante, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías Gallego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Se detallan los resultados del Registro Español de Ablación con Catéter del año 2011. Métodos. La recogida de datos se llevó a cabo mediante dos sistemas: retrospectivo, con la cumplimentación de un formulario, y prospectivo, a través de una base de datos común. Cada centro participante escogió su método de preferencia. Resultados. Se recogieron datos de 66 centros. El número total de procedimientos de ablación fue de 9.662, con una media de 146 ± 104 procedimientos. Los tres sustratos abordados con más frecuencia fueron la taquicardia intranodal (n = 2.537; 26%), la ablación del istmo cavotricuspídeo (n = 2.205; 23%) y las vías accesorias (n = 1.813; 19%). El cuarto sustrato fue la ablación de fibrilación auricular (n = 1.535; 16%), que mostró un incremento del 17% con respecto al registro de 2010. La ablación de arritmias ventriculares también se ha incrementado en un porcentaje considerable. La tasa total de éxito fue del 94%; la de complicaciones mayores, del 2,2% y la de mortalidad, del 0,04%. Conclusiones. En el registro de 2011 se mantiene una línea de continuidad ascendente en el número de ablaciones realizadas, que muestran, en líneas generales, una elevada tasa de éxito y bajo número de complicaciones. Continúa el aumento del abordaje de sustratos más complejos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(10): 928-936, oct. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Ablación con Catéter. XI Informe Oficial de la Sección de Electrofisiología y Arritmias de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (2011)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
