<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145097</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are drugs worth their cost?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Drugs constantly jeopardize the balance among Bioethical Principles governing Healthcare. Their correct use implies more than a correct clinical diagnosis and an academic prescription and demands thorough coordination among all healthcare levels (Regulatory Agencies, the State, the Pharmaceutical Industry and professionals) and the necessary incentive for the research and development process to provide true therapeutic innovations. The interannual growth of Pharmaceutical Expenditure in the public sector in the last few years has greatly exceeded growth in the consumer price index and the gross domestic product. The economic problem of drugs utilization therefore centers on their opportunity cost and on their impact on the sustainability of the system overall. Cost-utility, as an accepted principle for the incorporation and use of new technologies is not always taken into account in prioritization, decision-making and interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Conde, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tévar Alfonso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los medicamentos ponen en liza constantemente los principios bioéticos que rigen la atención sanitaria. Su correcta utilización implica algo más que un diagnóstico clínico preciso y una prescripción académica; exige una completa coordinación de todos los niveles asistenciales (agencias reguladoras, Estado, industria farmacéutica y profesionales) y el incentivo necesario para que el proceso de investigación y desarrollo aporte verdaderas innovaciones terapéuticas. Los crecimientos interanuales del gasto farmacéutico en el sector público durante los últimos años han superado con creces los del Índice de Precios al Consumo (IPC) y del Producto Interior Bruto (PIB). El problema económico de la utilización de medicamentos se centra, por tanto, en su coste de oportunidad y en su impacto en la sostenibilidad del sistema en su conjunto. El coste-utilidad, como principio aceptado para la incorporación y uso de nuevas tecnologías, no siempre es tenido en cuenta para priorizar, decidir y actuar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;35(supl.2): 32-39, 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Valen los medicamentos lo que cuestan?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
