<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72818</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the physical therapy laboratory class environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AimsThis study has aimed to construct, validate and apply a scale to evaluate the classroom environment called the Laboratory Environment Questionnaire (LEQ) in order to know the classroom environment existing in the laboratory practices of Physical Therapy of the University of Seville.Material and methodsthe sample was made up of 108 randomly obtained students (69 women and 39 men) who were studying the subjects of Electrotherapy, Physical Therapy in Geriatrics and Special Physical Therapy II. The inclusion criteria were to be registered in every subject and not to be a repeater. The methodology followed had a correlational and factorial analysis character. The statistical analysis was performed with the SPSS (14.00) program for windows.Resultsmeasurement of Keiser-Meyer-Olkin is 0.798, and Barlett's test 0.000 (p&lt;0.05). The variance explained by the first 5 factors represents almost 60% (59,201). These 5 factors correspond with 5 environmental dimensions (relationships of communication, motivation, participation, autonomy and learning), and object of study. Cronbach's alpha (0.878 and 0.893). Thus, The LEQ is valid and reliable. The mean evaluation obtained from the LEQ is 3.784±1.041. However, the mean score obtained for each dimension is: communication relationships (4.28); motivation (4.36); participation (3.48); autonomy (3.26) and learning (3.52).ConclusionsThe LEQ is valid and reliable, and appears to be effective for the analysis of the classroom environment of the laboratory practices in Physical Therapy. The classroom environment in the laboratory practices of Physical Therapy is good(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez Lugo, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albornoz Cabello, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosEl objetivo de este estudio es construir, validar y aplicar una escala que evalúe el ambiente de clase, denominada cuestionario de ambiente de laboratorio (CAL), con el fin de conocer el ambiente de clase que existe en las prácticas de laboratorio de Fisioterapia de la Universidad de Sevilla.Material y métodosLa muestra estaba constituida por 108 alumnos (69 mujeres y 39 hombres), obtenidos de forma aleatoria, que cursaban las asignaturas de Electroterapia, Fisioterapia en Geriatría y Fisioterapia Especial II. Los criterios de inclusión fueron estar matriculado en cada asignatura y no ser repetidor. La metodología seguida fue de correlación y análisis factorial. El análisis estadístico se realizó con el programa SPSS (14.0) para Windows.ResultadosLa medida de adecuación muestral de Keiser-Meyer-Olkin fue de 0,798 y la prueba de Barlett, 0,000 (p&lt;0,05). La varianza explicada por los 5 primeros factores representó casi el 60% (59,201%). Estos 5 factores se corresponden con las 5 dimensiones ambientales (relaciones de comunicación, motivación, participación, autonomía y aprendizaje) objeto de estudio. El alfa de Cronbach fue de 0,878 y 0,893. Por lo tanto, el CAL es válido y fiable. La valoración media obtenida del CAL fue de 3,784 ± 1,041; pero la puntuación media obtenida para cada dimensión fue: relaciones de comunicación, 4,28; motivación, 4,36; participación, 3,48; autonomía, 3,26, y aprendizaje, 3,52.ConclusionesEl CAL es válido y fiable y se muestra eficaz para el análisis del ambiente de clase de las prácticas de laboratorio en Fisioterapia. El ambiente de clase en las prácticas de laboratorio de Fisioterapia es bueno(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(4): 123-130, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del ambiente de clase en el laboratorio de Fisioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
