<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144146</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hans Jonas: nature conservation, conservation of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article discusses three of the problems that the German philosopher Hans Jonas studied. The first one addresses the need for a specific ethic dedicated to the moral dimension of environmental problems, from a different perspective to the traditional. The second problem is crucial in the discussion on environmental ethics: the value of the nature. Does the nature have an intrinsic value or an instrumental value only (to satisfy the interests of the human being)? The thesis of Jonas, which claimed that nature is a good in itself, were further elaborated here. And the third problem is the derivation of moral norms and the role of man in this ethic that recognizes a good in itself in nature. According to Jonas, the human being is not diminished by recognizing the intrinsic value of nature, since the man&#146;s uniqueness and value are unquestionable. From these three central issues, the paper highlights the importance of seeking the links between bioethics and environmental ethics to address the current environmental, social and economic crisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgui Burgui, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se tratan varios problemas relacionados entre sí que el filósofo alemán Hans Jonas estudió. El primero de ellos es la necesidad de una ética específica dedicada a la dimensión moral de los problemas ambientales, desde una perspectiva distinta a la tradicional. El segundo problema ocupa un lugar central en la discusión en ética ambiental: el valor de la naturaleza. ¿Tiene valor intrínseco o sólo un valor instrumental (para satisfacer los intereses del ser humano)? A este respecto se expone la tesis de Jonas según la cual la naturaleza no sólo tiene valor intrínseco, sino que constituye un bien en sí misma. Y el tercer problema es la derivación de normas morales y el papel del hombre en esta ética que reconoce un bien en sí en la naturaleza. Según Jonas, el ser humano no se ve devaluado al reconocer el valor intrínseco de la naturaleza, pues la excepcionalidad y el valor de aquel son incuestionables. A partir de estas tres cuestiones centrales, se resalta la importancia de buscar los lazos que unen la bioética y la ética ambiental para encarar la crisis ambiental, social y económica del momento presente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;26(87): 253-266, mayo-ago. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hans Jonas: conservación de la naturaleza, conservación de la vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36365^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36365^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36365^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36364^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
