<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167729</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Passionate kindness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author addresses the issue of romantic relationships in modern times from a Bion-Meltzer theoretical axis, on the basis of which he explores the various ways of avoiding emotional relationships, illustrated by several clinical vignettes. Passion, he maintains, makes it possible to sustain a truthful relationship with the world, while anti-links will create a pandemonium, where confusion and indifference prevail. Additionally, he notes that passion is not only falling in love, and that depending on the individual's mental states - be they infantile, narcissistic or adult-various types of intimate links may be traced, even in a single person. Drawing upon a fragment from A memoir of the future, by W. Bion, he asserts that the mystery of love is discovered only through passionate experience. To love is an experience that transforms both the one who loves as well as the one who is loved, and drives the desire to know the other. Here is where the modality of knowing, through imagination, or unknowing, through intrusion, will make the difference that is not always clear. The analyst's availability to establish a passionate relationship is essential in analysis, and will unfold in the transference-countertransference relationship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tabiia, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor se propone abordar la problemática de las relaciones amorosas en los tiempos actuales, desde la perspectiva teórica del eje Bion-Meltzer, a partir de la cual descubre los distintos modos de evitar las relaciones emocionales, presentando algunas viñetas clínicas. El apasionamiento, sostiene, permite una relación veraz con el mundo, mientras que los antivínculos crearán un pandemónium donde prevalece la confusión y la frialdad. Asimismo, señala que la pasión no corresponde solo al enamoramiento y que, según los estados mentales del individuo sean infantiles, narcisistas o adultos, se podrán describir distintos tipos de vínculos íntimos, aun en una sola persona. A partir de un fragmento de Memorias del futuro, de W. Bion, afirma que el misterio del amor se descubre solo a través de la experiencia apasionada. Amar es una experiencia que transforma tanto a quien ama como a quien es amado, e impulsa el deseo de conocer al otro. Aquí es donde la modalidad de conocer, a través de la imaginación, o desconocer, a través de la intrusión, marcará la diferencia no siempre clara. La disponibilidad del analista para establecer una relación apasionada es fundamental en el análisis y se desplegará en la relación transferencia-contratransferencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(80): 223-247, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bondad apasionada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32642^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
