<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73028</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary levels of B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) and ventricular systolic dysfunction in heart failure patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. It was aimed to compare urine B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) according toleft ventricular systolic dysfunction and to investigate its diagnostic value in heart failure(HF) patients.Material and methods. A total of 90 HF outpatients (61 men, age 66 ± 12) and 30 age- andgender-matched controls were studied.Results. An increase in urine BNP was observed in patients with EF&lt;= 40% compared toEF&gt; 40% (p &lt; 0.0001), and controls (p &lt; 0.0001). Signifi cant correlations between urinaryBNP and left ventricular functional parameters were obtained. A multivariate regressionanalysis was performed and the best model associated with urine BNP included plasmaBNP (p &lt; 0.0001), EF (p = 0.02) and LV volume indexes (p &lt; 0.0001). The ROC fordetection of EF &lt;= 40% using urine BNP levels showed an area under the curve of 0.74 ±0.05, (p &lt; 0.0001). From the ROC curve, the optimal cut-off value (2.30 ng/l) had a 60%sensitivity and 90% specifi city. Finally, we performed a binary logistic regression fordetection of EF &lt;= 40%, and urine BNP was shown to be a strong predictor with an oddsratioof 21.Discussion. Urine BNP levels correlated with left ventricular functional parameters. Thisbiomarker is a useful tool for detecting and diagnosing left ventricular systolic dysfunctionin heart failure(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roselló-Lletí, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Dolz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portolés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Tello, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Comparar niveles de péptido urinario tipo B (BNP) en orina según la presenciade disfunción sistólica ventricular izquierda e investigar su valor diagnóstico enpacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca (IC).Material y métodos. Hemos estudiado a 90 pacientes ambulatorios con IC (61 hombres,edad 66 ± 12) y 30 sujetos control apareados por edad y género.Resultados. Se encontró un aumento en los niveles urinarios de BNP en los pacientes con fracciónde eyección (FE) &lt;= 40% comparados con los de FE &gt; 40% (p &lt; 0,0001) y con los controles(p &lt; 0,0001). Se obtuvieron correlaciones signifi cativas entre los niveles urinarios de BNP ylos parámetros funcionales del ventrículo izquierdo. Se realizó un análisis multivariado y elmejor modelo asociado con los niveles urinarios de BNP incluyó a los niveles de BNP en plasma(p &lt; 0,0001), FE (p = 0,02) y volúmenes del ventrículo izquierdo (p &lt; 0,0001). La curvaROC para la detección de FE &lt;= 40% usando BNP urinario mostró un área bajo la curva de0,74 ± 0,05, (p &lt; 0,0001). A partir de la curva ROC, el punto óptimo de corte (2,30 pg/ml)tuvo una sensibilidad del 60% y una especifi cidad del 90%. Finalmente, se realizó unaregresión binaria logística para la detección de FE &lt;= 40%, y los niveles urinarios de BNPmostraron un buen valor predictivo con una odds-ratio de 21.Discusión. Los niveles urinarios de BNP se correlacionan con los parámetros funcionalesdel ventrículo izquierdo, demostrando que este marcador biológico es útil para el diagnósticode la disfunción ventricular izquierda en pacientes con insufi ciencia cardiaca(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;209(4): 168-175, abr.2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles urinarios de péptido natriurético tipo B (BNP) y disfunción ventricular sistólica en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52612^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33842^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
