<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166414</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypertension in Spanish women: analysis of data collected by the Spanish Society of Cardiology Section of Arterial Hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports the results of an analysis of the sex differences found in data from clinical and observational studies organized by the Section of Arterial Hypertension of the Spanish Society of Cardiology during the last 10 years in Spain (i.e., the VIIDA, VALYCOR, VALOR, KORAL-CARDIO, CAROL, REFRACVAS, CLYDIA and PAMISCA studies). The data collected covered around 50,000 hypertensive patients, of whom some 45% were female, and included almost all the different forms of hypertension encountered in patients with a wide range of cardiovascular disease. Although the studies analyzed had different objectives and, therefore, different designs, taken together they were very similar, and their results are therefore clinically comparable. Overall analysis indicated that the hypertensive women included in the different studies had a more unfavorable cardiovascular risk profile than men. However, there were a number of sex differences in diagnosis and therapy that could explain, at least in part, why cardiovascular disease has a poorer prognosis in women. Blood pressure control is poor in Spain, in both men and women. As a whole, these findings can provide the basis for devising specific programs or actions aimed at correcting this situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazón, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan los resultados del análisis por sexos de los registros y estudios de la Sección de Hipertensión Arterial de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología realizados en los últimos 10 años en España (VIIDA, VALYCOR, VALOR, KORAL-CARDIO, CAROL, REFRACVAS, CLYDIA y PAMISCA). Estos registros incluyen aproximadamente a 50.000 pacientes, de los que el 45% son mujeres, y abarcan casi todo el espectro de la hipertensión arterial en los diferentes escenarios de la enfermedad cardiovascular. Aunque los estudios analizados tienen diferentes objetivos y, por lo tanto, distintos diseños, en conjunto presentan una gran similitud, por lo que sus resultados son comparables desde el punto de vista clínico. Del análisis general se puede concluir que las mujeres hipertensas incluidas en los diferentes estudios tienen un perfil de riesgo cardiovascular más desfavorable que el de los varones. Además, hay diferencias en el enfoque diagnóstico y terapéutico que podrían justificar, al menos en parte, el peor pronóstico de la enfermedad cardiovascular en las mujeres. El grado de control de las cifras de presión arterial es pobre en nuestro país, tanto en varones como en mujeres. Todos estos datos pueden servir de base para desarrollar programas o acciones específicos para tratar de corregir esta situación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.D): 30d-37d, 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertensión arterial en la mujer en España: análisis de los registros de la Sección de Hipertensión Arterial de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26566</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d422^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
