<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153371</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is an effort needed in order to replace the punitive culture for the sake of patient safety?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Efforts to introduce a safety culture have flourished in a growing number of health care organisations. However, many of these organisational efforts have been incomplete with respect to the manner on how to address the resistance to change offered by the prevailing punitive culture of healthcare organisations. The present article is intended to increase the awareness on three reasons of why an effort is needed to change the punitive culture before introducing the patient safety culture. The first reason is that the culture needs to be investigated and understood. The second reason is that culture is a complex construct, deeply embedded in organisations and their contexts, and thus difficult to change. The third reason is that punitive culture is not compatible with some components of safety culture, thus without removing it there are great possibilities that it would continue to be active and dominant over safety culture. These reasons suggest that, unless planning and executing effective interventions towards replacing punitive culture with safety culture, there is the risk that punitive culture would still prevail (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Ubeda, SR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los esfuerzos dirigidos a introducir la cultura de seguridad han florecido en un número cada vez más creciente de organizaciones de salud. Sin embargo, muchos de estos esfuerzos han sido incompletos en cuanto a manejar la resistencia al cambio que ofrece la cultura punitiva actual que predomina en organizaciones de salud. Este artículo es una reflexión para incrementar la conciencia sobre 3 razones de porqué se necesita un esfuerzo para cambiar la cultura punitiva antes de introducir la cultura de seguridad. La primera razón es que para cambiar la cultura primero se necesita investigarla y entenderla. La segunda razón es que la cultura es un constructo complejo, bien arraigado en las organizaciones y sus contextos, por tanto difícil de cambiar. La tercera razón es que la cultura punitiva tiene incompatibilidad con algunos componentes de la cultura de seguridad, y mientras esta no se elimine hay grandes posibilidades de que siga activa y dominante sobre la cultura de seguridad. Estas razones sugieren que, a menos que se planifiquen y ejecuten intervenciones efectivas para lograr el reemplazo de la cultura punitiva por la cultura de seguridad, se corre el riesgo de que la cultura punitiva siga prevaleciendo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(3): 173-176, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153371</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se necesita un esfuerzo para reemplazar la cultura punitiva por la de seguridad del paciente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
