<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166102</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antithrombotic and antiinflammatory effects of omega-3 fatty acids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dietary polyunsaturated fatty acids can be classified into two main subtypes: omega-3 (n-3) fatty acids and omega-6 (n-6) fatty acids. Omega-3 fatty acids are metabolized in the body into a variety of other omega-3 fatty acids. From the point of view of cardiovascular disease, the most relevant are long-chain omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (omega-3 PUFAs). The cardioprotective effects of omega-3 fatty acids appear to result from three main mechanisms: anti-inflammatory, antithrombotic and anti-arrhythmic mechanisms. With regard to the compounds&#146; antithrombotic effects, experimental findings indicate that intake of omega-3 fatty acids reduces thromboxane A2 synthesis. The antiinflammatory properties of omega-3 PUFAs seem to be related to their ability to downregulate expression of adhesion proteins. However, these antithrombotic and anti-inflammatory effects have not been consistently observed in dietary modification studies in humans. In this review, we discuss the different mechanisms of action by which omega-3 fatty acids could exert their antithrombotic and anti-inflammatory effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Farré, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los ácidos grasos poliinsaturados de la dieta pueden clasificarse en dos tipos: ácidos grasos omega-3 (n-3) y ácidos grasos omega-6 (n-6). Los ácidos grasos n-3 se metabolizan en el organismo dando lugar a diferentes ácidos grasos n-3, y los de un mayor interés desde el punto de vista cardiovascular son los de cadena larga (PUFA n-3). Tres mecanismos principales parecen estar involucrados en el efecto protector cardiovascular de los ácidos grasos n-3: su efecto antiinflamatorio, su efecto antitrombótico y su acción antiarrítmica. En cuanto a su efecto antitrombótico, hay datos experimentales que indican que la ingesta de ácidos grasos omega-3 tiene un efecto antitrombótico principalmente mediado por una reducción en la formación de tromboxano. Se disponde de datos sobre su efecto antiinflamatorio que demuestran la reducción en la expresión de proteínas de adhesión. Sin embargo, en los estudios de intervención dietética en humanos estos 2 efectos no se repiten de forma consistente en todos los estudios publicados. En esta revisión se analizan los diferentes mecanismos de acción antitrombótica y antiinflamatoria de los ácidos grasos omega-3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.D): 31d-37d, 2006. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos antitrombóticos y antiinflamatorios de los ácidos grasos omega-3</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14314^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14314^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1819^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
