<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118160</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">L5 radiculopathy due to vertebral aneurysmal bone cyst. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aneurysmal bone cyst is an osteolytic expansive lesion with blood-filled cavities, that is more frequently located in the metaphysis of long bones. It represents 1-2 percent of primary bone tumors. Suspected diagnosis is made by imaging studies, the definitive one being histological. Treatment of choice is surgical extirpation if it is possible according to its localization. We report a case of a 13-year-old boy who came to the emergency department with low back pain radiating down his left leg and paresthesia. He was diagnosed with vertebral aneurysmal bone cyst that caused L5 radiculopathy. He was treated with several embolizations using ethanol injections and subsequent rehabilitation treatment. We stress the importance of this case because of the low incidence of this lesion seen in Rehabilitation -Departments and the unusual vertebral location, causing L5 radiculopathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, V. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moyano, D. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveros, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuda, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El quiste óseo aneurismático es una lesión osteolítica expansiva, con cavidades rellenas de sangre, localizado con mayor frecuencia en la metáfisis de los huesos largos. Representa el 1-2% de los tumores óseos primarios. El diagnóstico de sospecha se realiza mediante estudios de imagen, siendo el definitivo anatomopatológico. El tratamiento de elección es la extirpación quirúrgica si su localización lo permite. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 13 años que acudió a urgencias por cuadro de dolor lumbar irradiado por miembro inferior izquierdo con parestesias en el mismo. Fue diagnosticado de quiste óseo aneurismático vertebral que condicionó una radiculopatía L5 y fue tratado mediante varias embolizaciones con inyección de etanol y posterior tratamiento rehabilitador. Destacamos la importancia de este caso por la baja frecuencia de aparición en nuestras consultas de esta lesión en localización vertebral, comenzando y dejando como secuela una radiculopatía L5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(4): 249-252, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radiculopatía L5 por quiste óseo aneurismático de localización vertebral. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34254^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
