<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131727</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant breast hamartoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast hamartoma is a benign and rare tumor. It mainly affects women between the third and fifth decade of life. Usually not diagnosed before surgical removal, because they are often confused with fibroadenoma. We report the case of a 25- yearsold woman with a painful mass in the right breast 8 years of evolution. On physical examination, a mass soft, mobile, edge well-defined and 16 cm of diameter was found. On ultrasound and mammography a large benign tumor was visualized. Surgical excision and mammoplasty was performed. Histopathologic study confirmed a case of giant breast hamartoma. Afther six months of the folow-up the patient is free of the disease. We discuss the aspect related to clinical manifestations, diagnosis, treatment and diferential diagnosis of this pathology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal Balaguera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorgensen, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Gamarra, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerquella Hernández, C M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Garcá-Almenta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Morales, M L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Hamartoma de mama es una tumoración benigna y poco frecuente. Afecta principalmente a la mujer entre la tercera y la quinta década de la vida. Habitualmente no se diagnostica antes de la extirpación quirúrgica, debido a que se suele confundir con el fibroadenoma. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 25 años de edad que consultó por presentar una tumoración dolorosa en la mama derecha de 8 años de evolución. En la exploración física se encontró una masa blanda, móvil, de borde bien definidos de 16 cm. de diámetro. En la ecografía y en la mamografía se visualizó una gran tumoración de características benignas. Se realizó extirpación de la lesión y mamoplástia. El estudio anatomopatológico confirmó la presencia de un hamartoma mamario gigante. Tras 6 meses de seguimiento la paciente está libre de enfermedad. En este trabajo se discuten los aspectos relacionados con las manifestaciones clínicas, el diagnóstico, el tratamiento y el diagnóstico diferencial de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;17(4): 163-167, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hamartoma gigante de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31269^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31473^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31269^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
