<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17703</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">KEZKAK: a new bilingual questionnaire to measure nursing students' stressors in clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To develop a bilingual questionnaire (Basque-Spanish) to measure nursing students' stressors in clinical practice. Methods: Ideas were gathered from nursing students in group discussions. Initially, 287 nursing students from the School of Nursing in San Sebastián (Spain) completed the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) and the 55-item version of our questionnaire. After analyzing the items, we selected 41 items for the final version. Some of the subjects completed this final version two (198 = 198) and six months (n = 211) later. Results: The questionnaire presented high internal consistency (Cronbach's &amp;#945;: 0.95), considerable reliability (Spearman's correlation: 0.72 at two months and 0.68 at six months), and acceptable concurrent validity (Spearman's correlation with anxiety: 0.39). Factor analysis produced nine factors, with high internal consistency, which explained 64.4% of the variance. Based on these factors, the main stressors for nursing students in the workplace were produced by lack of competence (11.2%), contact with suffering (9.1%), relationships with tutors, workmates and classmates (8.9%), uncertainty and impotence (7.7%), lack of control in relationships with patients (7.6%), emotional involvement (5.8%), relationships with patients [being harmed by the relationship (5.2%) and patients seeking a close relationship (4.6%)], and overwork (4.3%). Methodological and practice aspects of the questionnaire are discussed, as well as its utility in planning the training of future nurses. Conclusion: The KEZKAK questionnaire is a useful instrument for measuring nursing students' stressors in clinical practice  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Construir y validar un cuestionario bilingüe (castellano/euskera) para medir los estresores que tienen los estudiantes de enfermería en las prácticas clínicas. Métodos: Se ha partido de las ideas recogidas fundamentalmente en reuniones realizadas con los alumnos. En un primer momento 287 estudiantes de enfermería de la Escuela de Enfermería de San Sebastián respondieron a la versión inicial de 55 ítemes y al cuestionario STAI de ansiedad. Tras la depuración por ítem-análisis, se ha obtenido la versión final de 41 ítemes. Algunos de los sujetos respondieron nuevamente la versión final a los 2 meses (n = 198) y a los 6 meses (n = 211).Resultados: El cuestionario presenta una alta consistencia interna ( de Cronbach, 0,95), una fiabilidad considerable (0,72 a los 2 meses y 0,68 a los 6 meses), y una validez concurrente aceptable (0,39 con ansiedad-rasgo). El análisis factorial arroja nueve factores que tienen una alta consistencia interna y explican el 64,4 per cent de la varianza. Según esos factores, los principales estresores para los estudiantes de enfermería en las prácticas clínicas se derivan de la falta de competencia (11,2 per cent), del contacto con el sufrimiento (9,1 per cent), de la relación con tutores y compañeros (8,9 per cent), de la impotencia e incertidumbre (7,7 per cent), de no controlar la relación con el enfermo (7,6 per cent), de la implicación emocional (5,8 per cent), de la relación con el enfermo (dañarse en la relación [5,2 per cent] y el enfermo busca una relación íntima [4,6 per cent]) y de la sobrecarga (4,3 per cent). Se discuten aspectos metodológicos y prácticos del cuestionario y su utilidad en la planificación pedagógica de futuras enfermeras. Conclusión: El cuestionario KEZKAK es un instrumento útil para medir los estresores de los estudiantes de enfermería en las prácticas clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;17(1): 37-51, ene.  -feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">KEZKAK: cuestionario bilingüe de estresores de los estudiantes de enfermería en las prácticas clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Zupiria Gorostidi, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barandiaran Lasa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberdi Erize, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uranga Iturriotz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17703</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
