<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84253</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking-related self-efficacy and smoking intention in young people: Factorial validity and structural association</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this research was to obtain, in a structural equation model, the factorial validity of smoking-related self-efficacy, as well as its structural association with behavior and smoking intention. The sample was made up of 1012 young people aged 14 to 22 (mean 16.76) from public high schools in Mexico City. These young people filled out a questionnaire that assessed tobacco use (current smokers&#146; age at first cigarette, smoking frequency and quantity of cigarettes smoked). They were also asked about intention to smoke in the future. Self-efficacy was assessed using items that measured one&#146;s capacity to avoid smoking. The results indicated the factorial validity of the smoking-related self-efficacy measure in this sample. Structural equation modeling analyses suggested (X2= 113.319, p&lt;0.001; CFI= 0.99; NFI= 0.99; GFI= 0.95; RMSEA= 0.05) that those young people with lower confidence in their ability to avoid smoking would have higher levels of smoking intention and smoking behavior; moreover, intention to smoke in the future predicts level of smoking. The discussion analyzes the utility of the results for the assessment of self efficacy, as well as the clinical implications for the people in treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios Delgado, Jorge Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la presente investigación fue obtener en un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales, la validez factorial de la autoeficacia ante el consumo de tabaco, así como su relación estructural con la conducta e intención tabáquica. Se seleccionó una muestra de 1012 jóvenes entre 14 y 22 años de la Ciudad de México. La conducta de fumar se midió considerando la edad de inicio del consumo de tabaco, la frecuencia y la cantidad de consumo. Además se preguntó la probabilidad de fumar cigarros en un futuro. La autoeficacia se evaluó con ítems que reflejan la capacidad para evitar consumir cigarros. Los resultados mostraron validez factorial de la medida de autoeficacia en esta muestra. El análisis de modelo de ecuaciones estructurales (X2= 113.319, p&lt;0.001;CFI= 0.99; NFI= .99; GFI= 0.95; RMSEA= 0.05) sugiere que los jóvenes que tienen una menor capacidad para evitar consumir tabaco tendrán una mayor intención y conducta de fumar, además la intención futura de fumar predice su consumo. La discusión analiza la utilidad de los resultados para la evaluación de la autoeficacia en adolescentes, así como las implicaciones clínicas para las personas que se encuentran en tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(4): 325-330, oct.-dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoeficacia e intención conductual del consumo de tabaco en adolescentes: validez factorial y relación estructural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
