<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88120</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance and learning in virtual work teams: comparing brazilians and argentineans</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to analyze virtual teams from Brazil and Argentina. 181 Brazilians and 84 Argentineans responded to an electronic survey. Differences were found regarding the use of learning strategies, the need for training, and the perceived quality of interactions and effectiveness of virtual teams. The belief that the differences are more easily overcome in virtual teams than in traditional (co-located) teams explains to a greater extent the variance in the responses of Brazilians than Argentineans(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borges-Andrade, Jairo Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente-Palacio, Katia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedes-Gondim, Sonia Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue el de llevar a cabo un análisis de los equipos virtuales de trabajo en Brasil y Argentina. 181 brasileños y 84 argentinos contestaron a un cuestionario on-line. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en el uso de estrategias de aprendizaje, en la necesidad de entrenamiento en relación a la percepción de la calidad de las interacciones, así como en la eficacia en el desempeño. La creencia de que las divergencias son más fácilmente superadas en los equipos virtuales que en los presenciales explica la mayor varianza encontrada en las respuestas de brasileños en comparación con los argentinos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);27(1): 31-41, 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desempeño y Aprendizaje en Equipos Virtuales de Trabajo: Comparando Brasileños y Argentinos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15339</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
