<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80411</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Communication and computer technology: what do these bring to nursing?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is essential to change the role for all those who participate in the teaching-learning process, the teachers and the learners. It is necessary that students acquire certain basic competencies in communication and computer technology in order to achieve the profile for a professional which today&#146;s society needs and calls for. To have a reflex-level use of technology is now essential if one hopes to be a protagonist in the process of convergence toward the European Higher Education Area. One objective of university education is to prepare students to exercise their citizenship duties responsibly; we live in a society characterized by the use of the Internet and an intensive use of new technologies. The author reflects from the viewpoint of a university professor on what the communication and computer technologies can bring to university teaching(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lleixà Fortuño, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Es imprescindible un cambio de rol de todos los participantes del proceso enseñanza-aprendizaje: docentes y discentes. Es necesario que el alumnado adquiera ciertas competencias básicas en TIC (Tecnología Información y Comunicación) para conseguir el perfil del profesional que la sociedad actual necesita y reclama. Resulta imprescindible un uso reflexivo de la tecnología, en cuanto protagonista del proceso de convergencia hacia el Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior (EEES). Uno de los objetivos de la educación universitaria es la preparación del alumno para ejercer responsablemente la ciudadanía, vivimos en una sociedad caracterizada por el trabajo en red y el uso intensivo de las nuevas tecnologías. Se reflexiona desde el punto de vista del profesor sobre qué pueden aportar las TIC a la docencia universitaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;30(7/8): 497-502, jul.-ago. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tecnologías de la Información y Comunicación. ¿Qué aportan a la docencia de enfermería?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
