<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143666</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors which influence the lean mass loss in cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: cancer is an important illness in the sanitary field due to phisic and functional consequences involved in it. Among these consequences there is the malnutrition which can cause a loss of lean mass and with it a decrease in the Quality of Life, an increase in hospital stays, social and health costs and so on. The aim of this research is to know which factors can influence in the loss of the lean mass. Material and methods: it is a cross-sectional study in a sample of 72 patients who receive a radiotherapy with curative intent during a period from February 07th and May 14th, 2014. Results: from this pattern Of the total 64 patients were studied, of which 43.7% of the patients presented loss of lean mass, with 21.8% the percentage of patients losing 5%, 17.2% of patients. Among the factors studied that can influence the loss of lean mass, only the presence of digestive symptoms have statistical significance (OR = 3.3 or 6.6, as we take as a reference the percentage loss). Conclusions: the aim of the health staff who are working with these patients is to avoid the consequences that accompanies the loss of lean mass. For all this, it is very important to act before the digestive symptoms, by anticipating to them, or early implementation of an individualized nutritional intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Alferez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el cáncer es una enfermedad de gran importancia sanitaria debido a las consecuencias físicas y funcionales que conlleva. Entre estas consecuencias está la desnutrición, que puede provocar una pérdida de masa magra y con ello una disminución de la calidad de vida, aumento de las estancias hospitalarias, costes sanitarios, etc. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer qué factores influyen en la pérdida de masa magra. Material y métodos: se trata de un estudio transversal en una muestra de 72 pacientes que reciben tratamiento radioterápico con finalidad curativa en un período comprendido entre el 7 de febrero y el 14 de mayo de 2014. Resultados: del total de pacientes se estudiaron 64, de los cuales el 43,7% presentan pérdida de masa magra, siendo el porcentaje de 21,8% los pacientes que pierden 5%, el 17,2% de los pacientes. De entre los factores estudiados que pueden influir en la pérdida de masa magra, solo la presencia de síntomas digestivos poseen significación estadísitca (OR = 3,3 o 6,6, según tomemos como referencia el porcentaje de pérdida). Conclusiones: el objetivo del personal sanitario que trabaja con estos pacientes de evitar las consecuencias que acompañan a la pérdida de masa magra. Por todo esto, es importante actuar antes de la aparición de síntomas digestivos, mediante la prevención de los mismos, o la aplicación precoz de una intervención nutricional individualizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(4): 1670-1675, oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores que influyen en la pérdida de masa magra en pacientes oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2134^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
