<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84584</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asymmetric dimethylarginine (ADMA) in different pathologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asymmetric dimethylarginine (ADMA) is formed as a metabolic byproduct of continuous protein turnover in the cytoplasm of all human cells. For more than a decade it was proposed that ADMA exerted its biological effects by inhibiting the synthesis of NO. The pathophysiological role of ADMA has been clarified in more detail by collaborative efforts of different research groups around the world. Today, it is recognized that the ADMA can play a prominent role in the pathogenesis and progression of cardiovascular diseases, specifically atherosclerosis. Asymmetrical dimethyl-arginine (ADMA) is a competitive inhibitor of endogenous eNOS, discovered in patients with renal insufficiency. Its name comes from the methyl groups bound to the guanidine nitrogen. ADMA is increased in kidney failure and other pathological situations such as hypercholesterolemia, atherosclerosis and hypertension. The increase in the concentrations of ADMA shows a significant inhibitory effect on the eNOS enzyme. Inhibition can be reduced by increasing the concentration of substrate available. Indeed, some intervention studies indicate that arginine supplements improve endothelial function in patients with coronary heart disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Miguel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Miguel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Gil, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dimetilarginina asimétrica (ADMA) se forma como subproducto metabólico del almacenamiento continuo de proteínas en las células del cuerpo. Hace más de una década se propuso que ADMA ejerce efectos biológicos sin inhibir la síntesis de NO. El papel fisiopatológico de ADMA ha sido elucidado según los esfuerzos de colaboración de diferentes grupos de investigación en el mundo. Hoy por hoy, se admite que ADMA puede desempeñar un papel prominente en la patogenia y en la progresión de enfermedades cardiovasculares, específicamente en la aterosclerosis. La ADMA es un inhibidor competitivo endógeno de la eNOS, descubierto en pacientes con insuficiencia renal. La denominación se debe a que los 2 metilos están unidos a un solo nitrógeno del grupo guanido. ADMA está aumentada en la insuficiencia renal y en otras situaciones patológicas como la hipercolesterolemia, la aterosclerosis y la hipertensión arterial. El aumento en las concentraciones de ADMA supone un importante efecto inhibidor en la enzima. Algunos estudios de intervención indican que la suplementación con arginina mejora la función endotelial en pacientes con enfermedad coronaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;1(3): 113-121, jul.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dimetilarginina asimétrica (ADMA) en diferentes enfermedades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1123^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1123^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
