<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82376</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positive sentinel node risk in relation to oestrogen receptors in breast cancer in premenopausal and postmenopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The influence of the relationship between pre- and post-menopausal stage of patients with breast cancer (BC) and the risk of sentinel lymph node (SLN) metastasis as well as the influence of oestrogen receptor (ER) status within each one of these groups were analyzed. Methods. A BC database with 1,388 patients was analysed. Three age groups were studied: A, elderly postmenopausal, 200 patients, &amp;#8805;70 years old; B, younger postmenopausal, 89 patients, 55&#150;69 years old; C, premenopausal, 85 patients, &lt;55 years old. In each group 2 subgroups were analyzed: positive ER and negative ER tumours. Data analysed: SLN-positive patients, non-sentinel node (NSN)-positive patients, non-surgical detections (NSD) and non disease-free (NDF) patients after a follow-up of 52 months. Statistical analysis: chi-squared test, significance: P&lt;=0.05. Results. SLN metastasis was significantly (P&lt;0.025) more common in premenopausal than in postmenopausal patients, and within those, mainly in negative ER tumours. Positive-NSN increases slightly in premenopausal patients (exclusively in negative ER tumours). NDF patients are similar in the 3 groups and in all of them it is much more frequent in negative ER tumours. Conclusion. SLN metastasis varies significantly according to hormonal state and not according to age, being more frequent in premenopausal patients and mainly in ER negative tumours(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bajén, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramal, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urruticoechea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Comin, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Notta, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domènech, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Investigar la relación entre el estado pre o posmenopáusico de la paciente con carcinoma de mama (CM) y el riesgo de metástasis en el ganglio centinela (GC) y dentro de cada uno de esos grupos el riesgo según el estado de los receptores de estrógeno (RE). Método. Análisis de la base de datos de GC con 1.388 pacientes. Se estudiaron tres grupos de edad: A) posmenopáusicas ancianas, 200 pacientes, &amp;#8805;70 años; B) posmenopáusicas más jóvenes, 89 pacientes, 55&#150;69 años, y C) premenopáusicas, 85 pacientes, &lt;55 años. En cada grupo se analizaron 2 subgrupos: tumores con RE positivos o negativos. Factores estudiados en cada grupo y subgrupo: pacientes con GC positivo, pacientes con ganglios no centinela (GNC) positivos, número de no detecciones quirúrgicas (NDQ) y pacientes no libres de enfermedad (NLE) tras 52 meses de seguimiento. Análisis estadístico: test de chi-cuadrado; significancia p&lt;=0,05. Resultados. En las premenopáusicas el número de GC positivos es significativamente (p&lt;0,025) mayor que en las posmenopáusicas y dentro de las premenopáusicas fundamentalmente en los tumores con RE negativos. El número de GNC positivos aumenta solo discretamente en las premenopáusicas y ocurre exclusivamente en tumores con RE negativos. El número de pacientes NLE es similar en los 3 grupos y en todos ellos es mucho más frecuente en pacientes con tumores con RE negativos. Conclusiones. El número de pacientes con GC positivo varía significativamente con el estado hormonal y no con la edad de la paciente, siendo más frecuentes en las premenopáusicas y fundamentalmente en tumores con RE negativos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;29(6): 289-292, nov.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el riesgo de metástasis en el ganglio centinela y los receptores estrogénicos en pacientes pre y posmenopáusicas con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34403^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
