<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64725</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) shunt infection is a cause of considerable morbidity and mortality. Shunt infection is produced mainly during surgery and by surgical wound infection. Staphylococcus spp. (&gt; 50% methicillin-resistant) are the most common causative bacteria, although gram-negative bacilli (10%-25%) and Propionibacterium acnes are becoming increasingly implicated. Shunt malfunction syndrome and fever are the most frequent clinical manifestations, whereas signs of meningeal irritation are uncommon. Other clinical manifestations depend on the location of the distal catheter. CSF should be obtained by puncture of the shunt reservoir or the distal catheter and processed for biochemical analyses, cell count, Gram stain, and aerobic and anaerobic cultures (lengthy incubation). Because of biofilm formation and to avoid recurrences, the recommended treatment is intravenous antibiotics plus removal of all components of the infected shunt, followed by placement of an external drainage catheter and a new shunt. Prophylaxis is important and can include antimicrobial prophylaxis and/or antibiotic-impregnated catheters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Mejías, Manuel E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cabrera, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones de las derivaciones del líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR) presentan morbilidad y mortalidad importantes. Éstas se producen principalmente durante la cirugía y por infección de la herida quirúrgica. Las bacterias que están más implicadas son Staphylococcus spp. (&gt; 50% resistentes a meticilina). Bacilos gramnegativos (10-25%) y Propionibacterium acnes se describen últimamente con frecuencia creciente. El síndrome de malfunción valvular y la fiebre son las manifestaciones clínicas más frecuentes. Los signos meníngeos son infrecuentes. Otras manifestaciones clínicas dependerán de la localización del catéter distal. El LCR debe ser extraído por punción del reservorio o del catéter externalizado, y procesado para bioquímica y recuento celular, tinción de Gram y cultivos aerobios y anaerobios (incubación prolongada). Debido a la formación de biocapa, y para evitar recurrencias, el tratamiento recomendado es antibióticos intravenosos más retirada de todo el shunt, colocación de drenaje ventricular externo y nuevo shunt. La profilaxis es importante y puede incluir antimicrobianos, y/o catéteres impregnados con antibióticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(4): 240-251, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64725</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2594^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
