<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85499</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention and care in pressure ulcers. Where are we?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have explored the knowledge (and its subsequent implementation) thatowns the nursing staff on the recommendations relating to prevention and treatment ofpressure ulcers, which are developed systematically in manuals and guides internationalcompanies and our country. The results found gaps in knowledge and related deficienciesin its application. This work aims to verify that we are the professional statusof Nursing in Hospital de Jaén (belonging to the Andalusian public health system)with respect to knowledge a) frequency of use of the guidelines recommended in clinicalpractice, b) existence of training or professional factors that may influence the level ofknowledge and its implementation, and c) to locate all the care they provide by comparingthe results with previous investigations. The methodology was descriptive cross.Data collection was performed using a validated questionnaire. These results are entirelycomparable with those published in our country and beyond our borders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Ortiz, Juan Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos estudios han explorado el grado de conocimiento (y su posteriorpuesta en práctica) que posee el personal de enfermería sobre las recomendacionesrelacionadas con la prevención y el tratamiento adecuado de las úlceraspor presión que aparecen desarrolladas de manera sistemática en guías y manualesde sociedades internacionales y de España. Los resultados hallaron lagunasen los conocimientos referidos y deficiencias en su aplicación. Este trabajopretende comprobar en qué situación nos encontramos los profesionalesde enfermería del Complejo Hospitalario de Jaén (perteneciente a la red sanitariapública andaluza), con respecto al conocimiento (a), frecuencia de utilizaciónde las directrices recomendadas en la práctica asistencial (b), existenciade factores profesionales o de formación que puedan influir en el nivel de conocimientoy en su puesta en práctica (c); todo ello para ubicar los cuidadosque prestamos comparando los resultados con investigaciones previas.La metodología fue descriptiva transversal. La recogida de datos se realizó através de un cuestionario validado. Los resultados obtenidos son totalmenteequiparables con los publicados tanto en España, como a nivel internacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(3): 132-140, sep. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y cuidados en úlceras por presión. ¿Dónde estamos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
