<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054788</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibiotic use in dental practice. A review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antibiotics are commonly used in dental practice. It has been estimated that 10% of all antibiotic prescriptions are related with dental infections. The association amoxicillin-clavulanate was the drug most frequently prescribed by dentists during 2005, at least in the Valencian Community (Spain). The use of antibiotics in dental practice is characterized by empirical prescription based on clinical and bacteriological epidemiological factors, with the use of broad spectrum antibiotics for short periods of time, and the application of a very narrow range of antibiotics. The simultaneous prescription of nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) can modify the bioavailability of the antibiotic. In turn, an increased number of bacterial strains resistant to conventional antibiotics are found in the oral cavity.Antibiotics are indicated for the treatment of odontogenic infections, oral non-odontogenic infections, as prophylaxis against focal infection, and as prophylaxis against local infection and spread to neighboring tissues and organs.Pregnancy, kidney failure and liver failure are situations requiring special caution on the part of the clinician when indicating antibiotic treatment.The present study attempts to contribute to rational antibiotic use, with a review of the general characteristics of these drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bagán, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poveda Roda, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis Bielsa, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell Pastor, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antibióticos son fármacos de uso cotidiano en odontología. Se estima que el 10% de las prescripciones antibióticas están relacionadas con la infección odontogénica. La asociación amoxicilina-clavulánico fue el fármaco más prescrito por dentistas durante 2005, al menos en la Comunidad Autónoma Valenciana. El uso de antibióticos en odontología se caracteriza por una prescripción empírica basada en epidemiología clínica y bacteriana, el uso de antibióticos de amplio espectro durante periodos breves de tiempo y el manejo de una batería muy reducida de antibióticos. La prescripción simultánea de AINES (antiinflamatorios no esteroideos) puede modificar la biodisponibilidad del antibiótico. Se detecta un aumento de número de cepas resistentes a los antibióticos convencionales en la cavidad oral.La indicación antibiótica se realiza para tratamiento de la infección odontogénica, de infecciones orales no odontogénicas, como profilaxis de la infección focal y como profilaxis de la infección local y la extensión a tejidos y órganos vecinos.El embarazo, la insuficiencia renal y la insuficiencia hepática son situaciones que requieren una especial atención del clínico antes de indicar un tratamiento antibiótico.El objetivo del presente trabajo es intentar contribuir a un uso racional de los antibióticos revisando sus características generales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(3): E186-E192, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de antibióticos en la práctica dental. Revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
