<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59860</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interleukin 8 Concentrations in Donor Bronchoalveolar Lavage: Impact on Primary Graft Failure in Double Lung Transplant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Results  Fifteen of the 20 donors were men. The cause of brain death was trauma in 9 donors, 7 were smokers, 13 required inotropic support, and pathogens were isolated in the BAL fluid of 18. The median age was 35 years (interquartile range [IQR], 23.5¨C51.25y), the median ventilation time was 1 day (IQR, 1¨C2d), the median PaO2/FiO2 was 459.5 (IQR, 427¨C510.25), and the median IL-8 concentration in BAL fluid was 49.01ng/L (IQR, 7.86¨C94.05ng/mL).Ten of the recipients were men and the median age was 48.43 years (IQR, 25.4¨C56.81y). The median ischemic time was 210minutes (IQR, 176.25¨C228.75min) for the first lung and 300minutes (IQR, 273.75¨C333.73min) for the second lung. The median PaO2/FiO2 ratio for the implant at 6, 14, and 48hours was 329 (IQR, 190.25¨C435), 363.5 (IQR, 249¨C434.75), and 370.5 (IQR, 243.25¨C418.25), respectively. The median intubation time was 39.5hours (IQR, 19.25¨C68.5h) and the correlation with IL-8 values was positive: higher IL-8 concentrations in BAL fluid correlated with longer ventilation times (Spearman rank correlation, P=.007; ¦Ñ=0.583). Five patients developed primary graft failure; IL-8 concentrations were significantly higher in these patients than in those whose grafts did not fail (Mann-Whitney test, P=.003).ConclusionHigh IL-8 concentrations in donor BAL fluid lead to longer ventilation time in the recipients and favor the development of primary graft failure after lung transplant(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, M José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenar, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerón, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalver, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disfunción primaria del injerto pulmonar (DPIP) contin¨²a siendo la principal causa de mortalidad perioperatoria y precoz en los receptores de un trasplante pulmonar (TP)1. La DPIP es una lesi¨®n pulmonar aguda, que acontece en el per ...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(1): 12-15, ene. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59860</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interleucina-8 en el lavado broncoalveolar del donante y su impacto en la disfunción primaria del injerto en el trasplante bipulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22853^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28995^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
