<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163363</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Solid paediatricians in fluid times: Reviving professionalism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Professionalism is rarely taught formally. It is learned by osmosis through the hidden curriculum: a set of attitudes that each one of us transmits unconsciously to students, medical residents, and colleagues. All of us are a model or counter-model of professionalism through a series of values that have been the pillars of our profession since Hippocrates. Values that do not seem to be strong enough to pass our time. There are specific factors of the 21st century such as the financial crisis, the highly technical nature of medicine, bureaucratisation or trivialisation of the medical process that could explain, but not justify, the decline in the values of our profession: Empathy, integrity, solidarity, the altruism, or confidentiality. That is why, from the Bioethics Committee of the Spanish Paediatrics Association we establish the need to revive professionalism. Building and maintaining the values of our profession by training scientifically competent paediatricians, as well as being excellent from an ethical point of view, is part of our responsibility (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Jacob, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riaño Galán, Isolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tasso Cereceda, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La profesionalidad apenas se enseña formalmente. Se aprende por ósmosis a través del currículum oculto: conjunto de actitudes que cada uno de nosotros transmite de forma inconsciente a estudiantes, residentes y compañeros. Todos somos modelo o contramodelo de profesionalidad a través de una serie de valores que han constituido los pilares de nuestra profesión desde Hipócrates. Valores que parecen soportar mal el paso del tiempo. Existen factores propios del siglo XXI como la crisis económica, el excesivo tecnicismo, la burocratización o la banalización del acto médico que pueden explicar, pero nunca justificar, el declive de los valores de nuestra profesión: la empatía, la integridad, la solidaridad, el altruismo o la confidencialidad. Por eso, desde el Comité de Bioética de la Asociación Española de Pediatría planteamos la necesidad de reanimar la profesionalidad. Construir y mantener los valores de nuestra profesión formando pediatras científicamente competentes, pero también excelentes desde el punto de vista ético, es parte de nuestra responsabilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(6): 354.e1-354.e4, jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pediatras sólidos en tiempos líquidos. Reanimando la profesionalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
