<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125084</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of times of emergency service transport of patients to a catheterization laboratory in the first year implementing a code of practice for attending acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction in Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: To assess the degree of compliance with time objectives for starting a primarypercutaneous coronary intervention in Asturias, Spain, and to determine whether there are differences between patients first treated by prehospital emergency medical services and taken directly to a catheterization laboratory and those first taken to hospitals without laboratories. Methods: Cross-sectional descriptive observational study of cases of acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction attended by the prehospital emergency services in Asturias in 2012. Cases were classified into 2 groups: in the first were patients taken directly to the catheterization laboratory (direct route) and in the second, patients first taken to emergency departments in hospitals without a laboratory (indirect route). We compared times between the onset of symptoms, first medical contact, activation of the catheterization laboratory, and balloon inflation in the laboratory. Results: We analyzed 359 cases (direct route, 238; indirect route, 121). The mean time between first medical contact and balloon inflation was 88.9 minutes; 87.7% of the patients were attended within 120 minutes or less (direct route,93.3%; indirect route, 76.7%). Patients who sought care within 2 hours of onset of symptoms experienced a mean delay of 87.8 minutes; 58.8% were attended within 90 minutes or less (direct route, 70.2%; indirect route, 32.3%).Conclusions: Time objectives are being met in Asturias. The best care scenario is for patients to be treated at the scene by the prehospital emergency service and taken directly to a catheterization laboratory. Efforts must be made to advise the population to call a local emergency number (112 or 061) as soon as chest pain suggests a coronary event. First responders should make the effort to diagnose the condition and transfer the patient quickly to a catheterization laboratory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peláez Fernández, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Houghton García, R. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eiroa Vallés, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laca García, S. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rancaño, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ordiales, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Camean, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar el grado de cumplimiento de los objetivos de tiempo establecidos en Asturias para angioplastia primaria y comprobar diferencias entre pacientes atendidos directamente por el servicio de atención médica urgente (SAMU) y aquéllos atendidos previamente en hospitales sin laboratorio de hemodinámica. Método: Estudio observacional descriptivo trasversal de los Código Infarto (CI) gestionados por el SAMU-Asturias en 2012. Se establecen dos grupos: pacientes atendidos a nivel prehospitalario (G1), y atendidos previamente en hospitales sin hemodinámica(G2). Se comparan los tiempos de demora entre inicio de síntomas, primer contacto médico, activación del CI e inflado del balón. Resultados: Se analizaron 359 casos (238 del G1 y 121 del G2). El retraso medio desde primer contacto médico e inflado del balón fue de 88,9 minutos, 87,7% de los pacientes con tiempo inferior o igual a 120 minutos (93,3% del G1 y 76,7% del G2). En los pacientes que consultaron en las 2 primeras horas de síntomas, el retraso medio fue de 87,8 minutos,58,8% de ellos con un tiempo inferior o igual a 90 minutos (70,2% del G1 y 32,3% del G2).Conclusiones: En Asturias se están cumpliendo los objetivos de tiempo establecidos para el CI. La mejor opción para el paciente es ser atendido in situ por el servicio de emergencias y trasladado directamente al laboratorio de hemodinámica. Son necesarias iniciativas de divulgación que aconsejen que ante un dolor torácico de características coronarias se llame al número de emergencias sanitarias (112, 061,&#133;). Aun así, deberían hacerse esfuerzos para acelerar el diagnóstico y traslado de los pacientes al laboratorio de hemodinámica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);26(4): 259-266, ago. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de tiempos en los pacientes trasladados por el SAMU para intervención coronaria percutánea primaria en el primer año de instauración del Código Infarto en el Principado de Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24519^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55032^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
