<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105553</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intramedullary nailing in proximal femur fracture: double breakage with different implants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a clinical report of a double failure in which errors in surgical technique can explain, in part, the cause of the breakage of the nails. Finally we resolved the fracture with an osteosynthesis plate with a strut. Although intramedullary nailing is one of the most frequent techniques in orthopedics, we have to use the most accurate technique and pay attention to avoid surgical problems that can complicate the evolution of the healing of the fractures of the hip (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jover Carrillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan Cerveró, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Ferrando, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso clínico de una doble rotura de clavo en el cual los errores en la técnica quirúrgica pueden explicar, en parte, la causa del fallo de los implantes. Finalmente se resolvió la fractura con el uso de una placa de osteosíntesis con un contrafuerte. Aunque el enclavado intramedular es una de las técnicas más frecuentemente realizadas en COT, tenemos que utilizar una técnica quirúrgica lo más cuidadosa posible, prestando atención para evitar problemas que puedan complicar la evolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(3): 168-171, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enclavado intramedular en fractura de fémur proximal: rotura doble con sistemas de implante distintos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5729^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
