<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88666</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experiences with students of vocational training: a step toward the master of compulsory secondary teachers, high school, training and teaching of languages</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The experience of the University of Granada in competition or training programs for professional non-university students is reduced or absent, however one of the goals of this is to collaborate in the training of teachers responsible for school level through the Master of Teaching Compulsory Secondary, High school, vocational training and language studies.We must also acknowledge that in working life are many similar skills among professionals from higher-level education and those who have not attended university.In this sense we should know first hand the needs and perspectives of our future students indirectly.For this reason the faculty of the Department of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Technology, University of Granada began hosting a program of vocational training students to carry out their practicum. This first experience will serve the future development planning and reflection of teachers with regard to participation in the master area(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clares Naveros, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Villena, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Martínez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Hernández, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Lara, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La experiencia de la Universidad de Granada en programas de competencia o formación profesional de alumnos no universitarios es reducida o nula, sin embargo uno de los objetivos de esta es colaborar en la formación de los profesores responsables de las enseñanzas medias a través del Máster de Profesorado de Secundaria Obligatoria, Bachillerato, Formación Profesional y Enseñanzas de Idiomas.Asimismo, debemos reconocer que en la vida laboral son muchas las competencias similares entre profesionales procedentes de enseñanza de grado superior y aquellos que no han cursado estudios universitarios.En este sentido deberíamos conocer de primera mano las necesidades y perspectiva de los que serán nuestros alumnos de forma indirecta.Por este motivo parte del profesorado del Departamento de Farmacia y Tecnología Farmacéutica de la Universidad de Granada inicia un programa de acogida de estudiantes de Formación Profesional para la realización de su practicum. Esta primera experiencia servirá para el desarrollo y reflexión de futuras planificaciones docentes en lo referente a la participación del área en dicho master(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 443-450, mayo 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencias con alumnos de formacion profesional: un paso mas hacia el master de profesorado de secundaria obligatoria, bachillerato, formacion profesional y enseñanzas de idiomas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
