<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111086</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence of the art in nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article I try to examine the evidence of the art of caring in nursing. The following question arises through the pattern of aesthetic knowledge (art), which we could communicate in different ways such as journal articles, educational experiences, critique of scientific articles and more. The arguments behind this thinking are linked to the formality of communication, the ways to explore aesthetic knowledge and finally the influence of the artist as maker and critic of the art of nursing care. We have a challenge to recognize our work as an art, to make it known and inquire about it, which can be the focus of qualitative research methodology as a tool for collecting comprehensive language that identifies us (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Ibacache, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se reflexiona sobre la evidencia del arte de cuidar en enfermería. La raíz de la pregunta surge a través del patrón de conocimiento estético (arte), el cual lo comunicamos de diferentes formas, artículos en revistas, experiencias educativas, la crítica de artículos científicos entre otras. Los argumentos que sustentan esta reflexión están enlazados con la formalidad de comunicar, las maneras de explorar el conocimiento estético y finalmente la influencia del artista, como hacedor y critico del arte de cuidar. Es un desafío reconocer nuestro quehacer como un arte, dar a conocerlo e indagar acerca de éste, el cual puede estar en el foco de la investigación con metodología cualitativa, como una herramienta para rescatar el lenguaje comprensivo que nos identifica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(30): 326-331, abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111086</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia del arte en enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1160^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8683</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
