<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115663</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrolytes content in parenteral drugs authorised in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Fluid therapy is one of the most common daily practices although knowledge is necessary on electrolytes and fluids intake and on all the pathophysiologic states leading to fluid homeostasis impairment in order to properly handle the electrolytes for both fluid therapy and parenteral nutrition. Objectives: To know the content and electrolyte type in those drugs administered through the parenteral route commercialized and authorized in Spain until February of 2012. Methods: Review of the technical sheets of all the drugs commercialized in Spain for usage through the parenteral route. Those drugs with content lower than 1 miliequivalent or 1 millimol per commercial presentation were excluded. Results: Of the 1,800 active ingredients studied, only 211 had a commercial presentation for parenteral route. Of these, 52 active ingredients met the study inclusion criteria and most of them (51; 98.07%) had sodium content higher than 1 miliequivalent per commercial presentation, potassium was present in 3 and calcium in only 1. Discussion: Most of the medications studied contained sodium as the main electrolyte; impairments in sodium concentration are one of the most common problems at the hospital setting and in some cases an indicator of quality of health care delivery. Therefore, it would be necessary to take into account the intake received through the medications prescribed to improve electrolyte reposition in both fluid therapy and parenteral nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias Rico, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirchandani Jagwani, J. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fluidoterapia es una de las prácticas más habituales en la práctica clínica diaria pero para un correcto manejo de electrolitos tanto en la sueroterapia como en la Nutrición Parenteral se deben conocer todos los aportes de electrolitos y fluidos y todas aquellas situaciones fisiopatológicos que conllevan alteraciones en la homeostasis de fluidos. Objetivos: Conocer el contenido y tipo de electrolitos de los medicamentos administrados por vía parenteral comercializados y autorizados en España hasta Febrero 2012. Métodos: Revisión de todas las fichas técnicas de todos aquellos medicamentos que estuvieran comercializados en España y con presentación comercial disponible por vía parenteral. Aquellos medicamentos con un contenido menor de 1 miliequivalente o 1 milimol por presentación comercial fueron excluidos. Resultados: De los 1800 principios activos estudiados, sólo 221 formaban parte de alguna presentación comercial por vía parenteral. De estos 221, 52 principios activos cumplían los criterios de inclusión del estudio y la mayoría (51-98,07%) tenían sodio en contenido mayor de un miliequivalente por presentación comercial, luego el potasio estaba presente en 3 y el calcio únicamente en uno. Discusión: La mayoría de medicamentos objeto del estudio contenían como principal electrolito el sodio, siendo la alteración de las concentraciones de este electrolito una de las más frecuentes en el entorno hospitalario y, en algunos casos, indicador de calidad en la atención del paciente. Por ello, para un mejor manejo de la reposición de electrolitos tanto en la sueroterapia como por Nutrición Parenteral es necesario tener en cuenta el aporte recibido por la medicación prescrita en los casos en que sea necesario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(2): 128-134, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115663</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contenido en electrolitos de medicamentos de uso parenteral autorizados por el Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4645^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7136^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
