<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77197</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary retroperitoneal tumors: review of our 10-year case series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To investigate our case series of patients with primary retroperitoneal tumors over the past 10 years, analyzing clinical symptoms, diagnostic tests, tumor pathology, surgical data, concomitant can-cer treatments, recurrence and survival rates. METHODS: Retrospective analysis of 37 patients with primary retroperitoneal tumors diagnosed at our hospital over the past 10 years. RESULTS: Computed tomography (CT) was the imaging technique used most often and the most accurate. Tumors were malignant in 83% of patients and benign in 17%. Complete tumor resection was performed in 73% of cases; the most common approach was midline la-parotomy. Neighboring organs were also removed in 51.8% of cases in which radical resection was performed. The recurrence rate was 45% in patients who un-derwent surgery. Median time to onset of recurrence following open surgery was 23 months. Repeat resec-tion was performed in 66% of cases with recurrence. Five-year survival following total resection of malignant tumors was 44%. The mean patient survival after repeat resection was 9.8 months. CONCLUSIONS: Primary retroperitoneal tumors are rare and usually malignant. Surgery is the treatment of choice and complete tumor resection is the main factor that determines prognosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrión López, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donate Moreno, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ruiz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virseda Rodríguez, Julio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perán Teruel, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sanchiz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Navarro, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Estudio de nuestra casuística de tumores retroperitoneales primarios en los últimos 10 años analizando clínica de presentación, pruebas diagnósticas utilizadas, anatomía patológica tumoral, datos quirúrgicos, tratamientos oncológicos complementarios, índices de recidiva y supervivencia. MÉTODOS: Análisis retrospectivo de 37 casos de tumores retroperitoneales primarios diagnosticados en nuestro hospital en los últimos 10 años. RESULTADOS: La TC fue la técnica de imagen más utilizada y con mejor rendimiento diagnóstico. El 83% de los tumores eran malignos y el 17% benignos. Se realizó cirugía de exéresis total del tumor en el 73% de los casos. La vía de abordaje más utilizada fue la laparotomía media. En el 51,8% de los casos en los que se realizó exéresis radical hubo que realizar una extirpación asociada de órganos vecinos. El índice de recidiva de los pacientes operados fue del 45%. El tiempo medio de aparición de la recidiva tras la cirugía exerética fue de 23 meses. Se realizó resección iterativa de las recidivas en el 66% de los casos. La supervivencia a 5 años después de la resección completa de los tumores malignos fue del 44%. La media de supervivencia de los pacientes tras la resección iterativa fue de 9,8 meses. CONCLUSIONES: Los tumores retroperitoneales primarios son poco frecuentes, siendo habitualmente malignos. La cirugía es el tratamiento de elección y la exéresis completa del tumor es el principal factor que determina el pronóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(1): 13-22, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores retroperitoneales primarios. Revisión de nuestros casos de los diez últimos años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
