<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76145</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac insufficiency-failure and life quality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac insufficiency-failure is a chronic cardiovascular disease whose prevalence, incidence, mortality rate and health system costs are increasing. Patients suffering from cardiac insufficiency-failure have co-life-threatening risks which lead to severe limitations in daily activities and decrease their perception of living a quality lifestyle. Their evaluation helps to plan out future treatment and serves to predict their response to treatment. Many patients give more importance to their lifestyle quality rather than their lifespan. In this review, the authors describe the variables which affect the life quality of patients who suffer cardiac insufficiency-failure and what are the instruments more commonly employed. The authors ran a bibliographical search on Medline and Cuiden. The authors analyze five articles; they prioritize publication date, distinct magazines, study sector, source of each article and the diverse profession the authors of each article has(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaqué Crusellas, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prat González, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Insuficiencia Cardiaca (IC) es una enfermedad cardiovascular crónica con una prevalencia, incidencia, mortalidad y carga sanitaria en aumento. Los pacientes aquejados presentan comorbilidades que ocasionan limitaciones graves en las actividades cotidianas y disminuyen la percepción de su calidad de vida. Su valoración ayuda a planificar los cuidados futuros y resulta predictiva de la respuesta al tratamiento. Muchos pacientes dan más importancia a su calidad de vida que a la duración de la misma. En esta revisión se describen qué variables afectan a dicho parámetro en las personas con IC y cuáles son los instrumentos más utilizados. Se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica en Medline y Cuiden. Se analizan cinco artículos priorizando año de publicación, revistas distintas, ámbito de estudio, procedencia de los artículos y profesión diversa de los autores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(4): 262-269, abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia cardiaca y calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
