<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144494</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How value the patients treatment with liraglutide?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increase of diabetes mellitus incidence and its substantial health, social and economic impact, has turned this chronic disease into a relevant issue in public health. One of the main burdens to achieve an adequate glycemic control is the lack of treatment adherence. The objective of this work is to review patients' preferences and satisfaction with the glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist, liraglutide. The results obtained in several clinical trials where liraglutide is compared with oral therapy, show a higher satisfaction with liraglutide. The expected negative effects of liraglutide (because it is an injectable therapy and due to its adverse effects, mainly, nausea) are neutralized by a lower risk of hypoglycemia (vs. glimepiride), better glycemic control (vs. sitagliptin) and weight reduction (vs. glimepiride and vs. sitagliptin). When liraglutide is compared with exenatide, another GLP-1 receptor agonist also injectable, patients´ preference for liraglutide seems to be driven by a higher glycemic control and less risk of nausea. In this case, the dose frequency and the episodes of hypoglycemia are less influent factors. The preconceived idea that patients prefer oral instead of injectable therapies, are not met in this case, where other factors (such as, glycemic control, weight reduction and lower risk of hypoglycemia) are likely to be more relevant for the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tinahones, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Huelgas, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aumento de la incidencia de la diabetes mellitus y su enorme impacto sanitario, social y económico, hacen de esta enfermedad crónica un importante problema de salud pública. Una de las principales barreras para alcanzar el control glucémico adecuado es la falta de adherencia de los tratamientos disponibles. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar las preferencias y satisfacción de los pacientes con el agonista del receptor del péptido similar al glucagón tipo 1 (GLP-1) liraglutida. Los resultados obtenidos en diversos ensayos clínicos en los que se compara liraglutida con tratamientos orales muestran una mayor satisfacción con liraglutida. Los efectos negativos esperados de liraglutida (por ser un tratamiento inyectable y por sus efectos adversos, principalmente náuseas) son neutralizados por un menor riesgo de hipoglucemias (frente a glimepirida), mejor control glucémico (frente a sitagliptina) y reducción de peso (frente a glimepirida y sitagliptina). Cuando se compara liraglutida con otro agonista del receptor de GLP-1, exenatida (también inyectable), la preferencia por liraglutida parece estar mediada por un mejor control glucémico y menor riesgo de náuseas. En este caso, la frecuencia de dosis y los episodios de hipoglucemia son factores menos influyentes. La idea preconcebida de que los pacientes prefieren optar por medicación oral en lugar de inyectable no se cumple en este caso, donde parece que priman otros aspectos más relevantes para el paciente, como son el control glucémico, la reducción de peso y el menor riesgo de hipoglucemias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(supl.2): 21-26, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144494</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué valoración hacen los pacientes del tratamiento con liraglutida?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52846^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50567^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
