<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153274</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical-surgical unit of Pediatric Cardiology and Congenital Heart Diseases of the Hospital Ramón y Cajal of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since its creation in 1977 by Dr. Manolo Quero, coinciding with the opening of the Hospital, the Ramon y Cajal Hospital Pediatric Cardiology and Congenital Heart Disease Unit has been and is a referral center where patients coming from any Spanish region can get specialized and personalized integral care for children with congenital heart disease. After almost 40 years, the Service has integrated also the care of our grown up patients with congenital heart defects, into a transversal care unit. This service is characterized by its healthcare activity and its teaching and research that have led it to be distinguished as a National Reference Center (CSUR) activity. Today we are 7 physicians who perform our functions in different sections and allowed to specialize and create units as Hemodynamics, pulmonary hypertension and arrhythmias among others. Our cardiology department is integrated into a also has a rnultidisciplinary team including cardiac surgeons, pediatric intensivists, anesthesiologists, radiologist, physiotherapist, among others that allow for comprehensive patient care nursing. Our outpatient visits are Organized with the philosophy of &#147;high resolution&#148; visits and all the complementary examinations and functional tests) EKG, echocardiography, Holter cardiopulmonary exercise testing, and sometimes in the MRI) are done in the same day of the external visit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pineda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pérez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamariz-Martel Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villagra Albert, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Lestache Rodríguez-Monte, MF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez Fuente, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerro Marín, MJ del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su creación, en el año 1977 por el Dr. Manolo Quero, coincidiendo con la apertura del Hospital, el Servicio de Cardiología Pediátrica y Cardiopatías Congénitas del Hospital Ramón y Cajal, ha sido y es centro de referencia donde se siguen enfermos de toda la geografia española. Se creó para dar atención especializada a la gran demanda existente en aquellos años. Y, después de casi 40 años, tenemos la gran satisfacción de poder seguir viendo a esos niños, ya convertidos en adultos, y seguimos ofreciéndoles la asistencia necesaria para tratar las cardiopatías complejas de la mayoria de ellos. Este Servicio se ha caracterizado, tanto por su actividad asistencial como por su actividad docente e investigadora, que ha propiciado que sea distinguido como Centro de Referencia Nacional (CSUR). Hoy en día, contarnos con un Servicio mixto de 7 facultativos, provenientes de la Pediatria y de la Cardiología y especializados en la Cardiología Pediátrica y las Cardiopatías Congénitas. El Servicio cuenta con varias Unidades especializadas como la de Hemodinámica Intervencionista Infantil y en Cardiopatías Congénitas, Hipertensión Pulmonar Pediátrica y Unidad de Arritmias Pediátricas y en Cardiopatias Congenitas, entre otros. Nuestro Servicio se integra en un equipo multidisciplinar, compuesto por cirujanos cardiacos, intensivistas pediátricos, anestesistas, obstetras, radiólogos, rehabilitadores y enfermería especializada, entre otros, que permiten la atención integral al enfermo. La gran mayoría de las consultas externas se organizan con la &amp;#64257;losofía de la consulta de alta resolución. Realizándose la mayoría de las exploraciones y técnicas complementarias (electrocardiograma, ecocardicigrafía, Holter, ergometría) en el mismo día de la consulta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;72(2): 99-104, mar.-abr. 2016. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Unidad médico-quirúrgica de Cardiología Pediátrica y Cardiopatías Congénitas del Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51544</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3341^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3341^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3341^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
