<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144079</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethical Issues in Clinical Reearh</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article the most important ethical issues surrounding human research are discussed. First, the difference between clinical research and clinical practice. The three ethical principles governing research on human studies: autonomy, beneficence and justice; the role of the ethics committee for clinical research as a safeguard in human research is presented. Second, the main characteristics of the participant informed consent, and patient  information sheet. Finally, we briefly discuss Helsinki declaration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Pablos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Figueredo, CG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Ortiz, CG</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se tratan los aspectos éticos más importantes relacionados con la investigación en humanos. En primer lugar, se diferencia entre práctica clínica e investigación clínica. Se refieren los tres principios éticos aplicables a la investigación en humanos: autonomía, beneficencia y justicia; se presenta el papel del Comité ético de Investigación Clínica como salvaguarda en la investigación en humanos. En segundo lugar, se presentan las principales características de la Hoja de Información al Paciente y de la Hoja de Firma del Consentimiento Informado. Finalmente, se comenta brevemente la Declaración de Helsinki (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;17(4): 482-493, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos éticos en Investigación Clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36366^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6957^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6957^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5085</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
