<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72776</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Literature review of the family care provided by immigrant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo quantify and characterize the scientific production on the family care provided by immigrant women.MethodsA literature search was performed in April 2008 with no date limits in the main national and international databases: Web of Science, Current Contents Connect, ISI Proceedings, MedLine, CINAHL, PsycoInfo, EMBASE, IME, ISOC and CUIDEN. Summaries were reviewed by excluding those that did not relate to the subject of this study and those that were not in English, French or Spanish. The references of all included articles were also reviewed to detect other relevant publications. Several variables were identified and analyzed: type of article, main topic, country of the first author, and year of publication. A content analysis was performed, using the topics as categories.ResultsA total of 191 articles were retrieved and 178 were excluded. The 13 included articles analyzed differences in formal and informal care (2), determinant factors (4), epistemological needs (3), the benefits of this kind of care (5), the need for health education/training (4), the need for political/institutional support (2), immigration and health (6), and the carer/cared for relationship (4). There were five non-systematic reviews, six descriptive studies, one qualitative study and one experience. Two articles were published before 2002, eight between 2003&#150;2005, and three between 2006&#150;2008. Most of the studies were performed in Spain (9/13).ConclusionsThe scarcity of articles confirms that recruitment of immigrants as caregivers is a new and invisible reality. Most of these studies highlight the benefits of this type of care. There is no dominant pattern of topics and the methodology varies widely. The few analytical studies may indicate that this topic is only beginning to be researched. Investigation into this form of care should be stimulated(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado-Mejía, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Arias, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano-Parés, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoCuantificar y caracterizar la producción científica sobre los cuidados familiares prestados por las mujeres inmigrantes.MétodosBúsqueda, en abril de 2008, sin límite de fechas, en las principales bases de datos nacionales e internacionales: Web of Science, Current Contents Connect, ISI Proceedings, MedLine, CINAHL, PsycInfo, EMBASE, IME, ISOC y CUIDEN. Se revisaron los resúmenes y se excluyeron los que no se refirieran al objeto de estudio o no estuvieran en inglés, francés o español. De los incluidos se revisó la bibliografía para detectar otros. Se identificaron y analizaron diversas variables: tipo de artículo, tema principal, país del autor principal y año de publicación. Se realizó un análisis de contenido, utilizando como categorías los temas tratados.ResultadosSe hallaron 191 trabajos y se excluyeron 178. Los 13 analizados tratan sobre diferencias entre cuidado formal e informal (2), factores determinantes (4), necesidad epistemológica (3), beneficios de este tipo de cuidados (5), necesidad de educación para la salud/formación (4), necesidad de apoyo institucional/político (2), inmigración y salud (6), y relación cuidadoras/cuidadas (4). Hay cinco revisiones literarias, seis estudios descriptivos, una investigación cualitativa y una experiencia. Dos fueron publicados antes de 2002, ocho entre 2003 y 2005, y tres entre 2006 y 2008. La mayoría son españoles (9/13).ConclusionesLa escasez de trabajos confirma que la contratación de personas inmigrantes para el cuidado es una realidad nueva e invisible. La mayoría destaca sus beneficios. No hay patrón dominante de temas. Existe una gran diversidad metodológica y los escasos estudios analíticos podrían indicar que es una investigación incipiente. Sería necesario potenciar estudios sobre estos cuidados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(4): 335-341, jul.-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72776</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la producción científica sobre cuidados familiares prestados por mujeres inmigrantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13073^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
