<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121569</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the preservation and good-for-use period of multi-dose containers after being opened</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this work is to establish the standard procedure for use and preservation of drugs, dietary products and cosmetic products in multi-dose containers. Method: A summary table containing all the drugs, dietary and cosmetic products included in the hospital vademecum available in multi-dose containers was elaborated and information on preservation and good-for-use periods was gathered from the products technical sheets, consultation to the pharmaceuticals companies, and literature search. Results: 205 pharmaceutical specialties and magisterial formulations elaborated at the hospital were reviewed. A standardized working procedure was created with general instructions and a table of recommendations in case of missing information. Conclusions: with the present study, the information on the good-for-use period and preservation of multi-dose containers after being opened is improved. This information should always be kept available and updated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez Peiró, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tudela Orteils, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavião Prado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaspar Carreño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Ferrer, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrico Martín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es establecer un procedimiento normalizado de utilización y conservación de fármacos, dietoterápicos y productos cosméticos en envases multidosis. Método: Se procede a elaborar una tabla resumen de los fármacos, dietoterápicos y productos cosméticos incluidos en la guía farmacoterapéutica del hospital disponibles en envases multidosis y se recopilan informaciones de conservación y período de validez de los ítems seleccionados mediante consulta a las fichas técnicas de los productos, consulta a laboratorios o revisión bibliográfica. Resultados: Se ha revisado un total de 205 envases multidosis incluídos en la Guía Farmacoterapéutica (GFT) del Hospital. Se ha elaborado un procedimiento normalizado de trabajo con instrucciones generales y tabla de recomendaciones para los casos de no disponer de información. Conclusiones: En conclusión, con el presente estudio se facilita información sobre el período de validez y conservación de los envases multidosis tras su apertura. Esta información deberá mantenerse siempre disponible y actualizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(6): 450-468, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de conservación y período de validez de los envases multidosis tras su apertura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16719</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
