<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139396</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical consequences of alpha-thalassemia in the basque country, Spain. Impact of neonatal screening</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Alpha-thalassemia is the most common hemoglobinopathy with a variable clinical manifestation depending on the number of allele mutations (asymptomatic/mild anemia if 1-2 allele mutations, severe disease if 3-4 allele mutations). A study was conducted from May 2011 on hemoglobinopathies found in the neonatal screening in the autonomous community of the Basque Country (CAPV). Objectives: To analyze the impact of alpha-thalassemia in this area and the effectiveness of its neonatal screening. Methods: A review was made of patients with a positive gene study for alpha-thalassemia over a 2-year period (2012-2013) and an analysis was made of the age at diagnosis, ethnic group, analytical result, and treatment. Results: The genetic study was performed on 107 patients, of which 61 had some mutation, with 62% having one allele mutations and 38% with two alleles. The mean age at diagnosis was 31 years, with 28% being younger than eighteen years old. Most of the patients were European with a significant number of Africans (26%) and Arabs (13%). All patients were asymptomatic, and 28% had mild anemia. Two patients were diagnosed by neonatal screening. Most of them did not need any treatment or only required iron therapy. Conclusions: The detection of one or two alpha gene mutations has no clinical impact, but allows genetic counseling. No patient was found with 3-4 mutations or severe symptoms in our region. Contrarily to the diagnosis of other diseases, our results does not support that routine neonatal screening for alpha-thalassemia has any clinical impact in our community (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragües, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sasieta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catediano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navajas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aristizabal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La alfa-talasemia es la hemoglobinopatía más frecuente de expresión clínica variable en función del número de alelos mutados (1-2 alelos mutados: asintomático/anemia leve, 3-4 alelos mutados: enfermedad grave). Desde mayo de 2011 se ha añadido el estudio de hemoglobinopatías al screening neonatal en la Comunidad Autónoma del País Vasco (CAPV). Objetivos: Valorar el impacto de la alfa-talasemia en nuestro medio y la utilidad del screening neonatal en su detección. Método: Revisión de pacientes con estudio genético positivo para alfa-talasemia durante 2 años (2012-2013) y estudio de la edad al diagnóstico, etnia, resultados analíticos y tratamiento. Resultados: Se realizó un estudio genético de alfa-talasemia a 107 pacientes, de los cuales 61 presentaron alguna mutación. El 62% tenía un alelo mutado y el 38%, 2 alelos. La edad media al diagnóstico fue de 31 años, con un 28% menores de 18 años. La mayoría eran de procedencia europea con un porcentaje no desdeñable de africanos (26%) y árabes (13%) Todos los pacientes estudiados estaban asintomáticos con anemia leve en el 28%. Dos pacientes fueron diagnosticados por screening neonatal. La mayoría de pacientes no requirió tratamiento o precisó ferroterapia. Conclusiones: La presencia de una o 2 mutaciones en los genes alfa carece de repercusión clínica, y el único interés de su estudio es que permite el consejo genético. En nuestro entorno no hemos encontrado pacientes con 3-4 mutaciones ni con sintomatología grave. A diferencia de lo que ocurre con otras enfermedades, nuestros resultados no apoyan que el screening neonatal de alfa-talasemia tenga un impacto significativo en nuestro entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);83(2): 85-88, ago. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Repercusión clínica de la alfa-talasemia en nuestro medio. Impacto del screeningneonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14168^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14168^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15204^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
