<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94652</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Involuntary outpatient treatment in civil law. A review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, the Involuntary Outpatient Treatment (IOT) in Spain is analized. Also we briefly summarize the international law about it. In Spain there is not explicit legislation about OIT, but in 2004 the Parliamentary Group of CIU (Convergencia i Unió) proposed a modification of the article 763 of the Law of Civil Judgement to explicitly authorising the OIT. This arose one of the most controversial issues in mental health in the last years and nowadays it is not yet solved. There are three positions about de OIT: Those who argument for OIT, those who argument against, and those others who consider unnecessary new legislation. Many professionals hope that Assertive Community Treatment minimize the so-called "revolving door syndrome". This treatment was recommended in 2006 by The National Health System in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analiza el tratamiento ambulatorio involuntario (TAI) en España. También hacemos un breve repaso de él en el derecho internacional. En España no hay una legislación explícita del TAI, pero en el año 2004 el grupo parlamentario CIU (Convergencia i Unió) propuso una modificación del articulo 763 de la Ley de Enjuiciamiento Civil para autorizar el TAI. Surgió así uno de los temas más controvertidos sobre la salud mental de los últimos años estando aún sin resolver. Hay tres posiciones sobre el TAI: aquellos que argumentan a favor, los que argumentan en contra y los que consideran que no es necesaria una nueva legislación. Muchos profesionales esperan que el Tratamiento Asertivo Comunitario (TAC) minimice el denominado "síndrome de puerta giratoria". En España, el Sistema Nacional de Salud recomendó en el año 2006 este tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;16(1/2): 87-97, ene.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento ambulatorio involuntario de carácter civil: Una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
