<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048414</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approach to the socio-sanitary characteristics of sub-Saharan immigrant women in 2 immigrants programs in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the following health and social characteristics of sub-Saharan immigrant women attending 2 immigrant programs: main health problems and utilization of general and gynecological health services. Method. A cross-sectional descriptive study was carried out in sub-Saharan immigrant women over 18 years of age living in Madrid and attending two health and social centers for immigrants in Madrid between August 2003 and February 2004. Results. A total of 270 sub-Saharan immigrant women participated in the survey. Eighty-eight percent had irregular administrative status. Ninety-one percent were working without a work contract. The main health problems were breathing difficulties (23%; 95% CI: 18-28) and gynecologic problems (17%; 95% CI: 13-22). Thirty-two percent (95% CI: 27-38) had used NGO health services and 19% (CI 95%, 15-24) had used emergency services. Sixteen percent (95% CI: 12-21) had used a gynecologic service for check-ups since living in Spain. Conclusions. The immigrant women studied were young. Most were working without contracts and had irregular administrative status. Health services utilization was low, especially that of gynecologic services. These findings reveal the need for health programs to improve information and knowledge about health and health services utilization</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Engel Gómez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Moreno, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo Polo, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer algunas características sociosanitarias de las mujeres subsaharianas que acuden a 2 programas de atención a inmigrantes: principales problemas de salud, utilización de servicios sanitarios generales y ginecológicos. Método. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal realizado a mujeres inmigrantes subsaharianas mayores de 18 años, en 2 programas de atención a inmigrantes que residían en Madrid, durante el período comprendido entre agosto de 2003 y febrero de 2004. Resultados. Contestaron 270 mujeres inmigrantes subsaharianas. Un 88% estaba en situación administrativa irregular. Un 91% trabajaba sin contrato. Los principales problemas de salud fueron problemas respiratorios (23%; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 18-28) y problemas ginecológicos (17%; IC del 95%, 13-22). Respecto a la utilización de servicios sanitarios, el 32% (IC del 95%, 27-38) acudió a organizaciones no gubernamentales (ONG) y un 19% (IC del 95%, 15-24) a centros de urgencias. Un 16% (IC del 95%, 12-21) se realizó revisión ginecológica desde que residía en España. Conclusiones. Se trata de una población joven, una gran mayoría trabaja sin contrato y se encuentra en situación de irregularidad administrativa. Hay una mala utilización de los servicios sanitarios, con poca utilización de servicios ginecológicos. Todos estos datos nos indican la necesidad de programas de salud para mejorar la información y conocimientos acerca de la salud y la utilización de servicios sanitarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(5): 264-267, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acercamiento a las características sociosanitarias de las mujeres subsaharianas de 2 programas de atención a inmigrantes de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31671</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
