<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79213</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesiodens: three case reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mesiodens is the supernumerary tooth that most frequently appears in the permanentdentition. In most cases this is an accidental finding. Early detection allows the early extraction.It also favors the spontaneous eruption of the permanent incisors and helps avoid morecomplex surgical or orthodontic treatments. We present three cases of paediatric patientswith mesiodens, all of them have been radiological findings. In the first case, the patienthad a double mesiodens which blocked the eruption of the upper permanent central and lateralincisors. In the second case, mesiodens has produced the rotation of maxillary centralincisors. Early removal has been practiced in order to favor the spontaneous eruption of theincisors. In the third case, mesiodens is in total inclusion, not producing symptoms or complications,and it has allowed normal eruption of the previous sector. It has not required treatment, only periodic controls. This patient also presents agenesis of a lower premolar. It isreasonable to suspect the presence of a mesiodens in the patient who goes to pediatric orodontology consultation when there is some kind of disorder in the eruption of the upperpermanent incisors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Ortiz, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mesiodens es el diente supernumerario que aparece con mayor frecuencia en la denticióndefinitiva. En la mayoría de ocasiones se trata de un hallazgo casual. El diagnóstico precozpermite realizar la extracción de forma temprana, favoreciendo la erupción espontáneade los incisivos permanentes, y evita tener que efectuar otros tratamientos más complejos,quirúrgicos u ortodóncicos. Presentamos tres casos de pacientes pediátricos con mesiodens.Todos ellos fueron hallazgos radiológicos. En el primer caso, el paciente presentaba un mesiodensdoble que impedía la erupción de los incisivos centrales y laterales superiores definitivos.En el segundo caso, el mesiodens provocó la rotación de los incisivos centrales superiores.Se le realizó una extracción temprana para favorecer la erupción espontánea de losincisivos. En el tercer caso, el mesiodens se hallaba en inclusión total, sin producir sintomatologíani complicaciones. Este hecho permitió la erupción normal del sector anterior. No ha requeridotratamiento y sólo se le realizan controles periódicos. Este paciente presentaba, además,agenesia de un premolar inferior. Es importante sospechar la presencia de un mesiodensen el paciente que acude a la consulta de pediatría u odontología cuando exista algún trastornoen la erupción de los incisivos superiores permanentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;12(45): 79-87, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mesiodens: presentación de tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14470^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14487^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
