<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72921</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care professionals and pain: a crosssectional study on information, assessment and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aimsOne of the proposals made by institutional programs toimprove pain control is setting up of interdisciplinary committees.There is a lack of studies which evaluate howhealth care professionals cope with pain management. Inorder to discover the opinions and attitudes of hospitalstaff a study was conducted which focused on: informationprovided to the patient, assessment of pain and treatmentmethods used.MethodsA random sample of 25% was chosen from 1060 hospitalbased personnel. The 264 subjects chosen were: 116 doctorsor senior health technicians (TS), and 148 nurses ormedium grade health technicians (TM), employed in medicaland surgical areas. The questionnaire consisted of 12 questionsgrouped into three blocks: patient-personnel information-communication, assessment of the diagnostic protocol,and therapeutic measures applied.ResultsThe response rate was 58,7% (doctors 52,6%, nurses63,5%). Written information is given to patients in 29,6% ofcases, and verbal information is given to only 71,6%. Healthprofessionals are aware of their responsibility (87,1%) but only52,2% have received any training in pain management.While 81,3% ask the patient if they are in pain, only 35,5%use categorical scales, and 45,8% use visual analog scales. Insurgical areas, 92,6% of TM and 86,4% of TS mention theexistence of protocols, whereas in medical areas the correspondingfigures were 28,3% of TM and 35,9% of TS.ConclusionsThe results suggest that measures should be taken to improvepain management(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arbonés, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casamitjana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoLa creación de comités interdisciplinarios es una de laspropuestas establecidas en programas institucionales para lamejoría del control del dolor en los centros hospitalarios. Faltanestudios que evalúen como afronta el personal sanitarioel manejo del dolor. Para conocer la opinión y la actitud de los profesionales hospitalarios se elaboró un estudio centradoen: información al paciente, evaluación del dolor y métodosde tratamiento utilizados.Material y métodosSobre un total de 1060 profesionales, médicos y enfermeras,se eligió aleatoriamente una muestra que seleccionó a264 profesionales (25 %): 116 médicos o técnicos superiores(TS) y 148 enfermeras o técnicos medios (TM), distribuidosen área médica (AM) y área quirúrgica (AQ). El cuestionarioconstaba de 12 preguntas agrupadas en tres bloques: información-comunicación personal-paciente, evaluación del protocolodiagnóstico y medidas terapéuticas aplicadas.ResultadosLa tasa de respuesta fue de un 58,7% (52,6% médicos y63,5% enfermeras). Solo un 29,6% de los profesionales declararontransmitir información escrita, y verbal un 71,6%.Un 87,1% de los profesionales conocen su responsabilidad,pero únicamente un 52,2% han recibido formación en elmanejo del dolor. Un 81,3% pregunta al paciente si presentadolor, pero solamente un 35,5% utiliza escalas categóricas yun 45,8% la escala visual analógica. En el AQ un 92,6% delos TM y un 86,4% de los TS manifiestan la existencia de protocolosfrente a un 28,3% de los TM y 35,9 de los TS delAM.ConclusionesEstos resultados han permitido tener información sobre laactitud de los médicos y enfermeras frente al dolor y establecermedidas de mejora en la gestión del dolor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(2): 75-82, mar.2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los profesionales sanitarios ante el dolor: estudio transversal sobre la información, la evaluación y el tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
