<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166810</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess breakthrough pain management in patients at radiation oncology and its impact on pain control in these patients, as well as the tolerability of the analgesic treatments used and the satisfaction and impact on the quality of life of patients. Material and methods: An epidemiological, observational, prospective, multicentre study carried out in patients diagnosed with cancer and with cancer pain treated with a 3rd step analgesic therapy who had begun radiotherapy treatment (RT) susceptible to modification by an oncologist, for pain control. Patients were recruited from 15 Radiation Oncology Services centres from the regions of Valencia and Murcia between May 2013 and December 2014. Patient data collected included: demographic data, basal cancer process characterization and baseline pain, and information on basal analgesic treatment and RT employed. Pain level was recorded at 1 and 3 months by assessing: the change in the dimension of Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) pain and the amount of pain caused by episodes of breakthrough pain, the level of satisfaction, the quality of life (EQ-5D), and the tolerability to analgesic treatment. Results: Patients included in the analysis (n = 49) were mainly males (72.3 %) and the mean age (± Standard Deviation) was 63.7 ± 11.5 years. In 26.5 % of patients the tumours were located in lungs and 28.6 % in head and neck. All but one of the patients reported pain during the baseline visit (20.8 % due to the primary tumour, 54.2 % to metastases, and 22.9 % to RT treatment). The median (Q1-Q3) number of breakthrough crises/day was 3.0 (2-4.5). Overall, 60.4 % were receiving treatment for breakthrough pain and Fentanyl was the most commonly used drug (70.4 %). Pain management strategies were: reinforcement/modification of long-term analgesics (30.4%), reinforcement/modification of short-term analgesics (21.7%), reinforcement/modification of long-term and short-term analgesics (21.7 %), and decrease/suppression of any fast- or long-term analgesics (26.1 %). Independently from the strategy, a decrease in the maximum pain and the total amount of pain were observed over time, and an improvement during the follow-up visits was observed in the quality of life, health gain, and overall treatment satisfaction. Only two adverse reactions were reported. Conclusions: Breakthrough pain in cancer patients, who underwent radiotherapy treatment, is a symptom of high prevalence. There is no predominant analgesic strategy in the management of these patients, but Fentanyl is the drug most  frequently used. Patients are very satisfied with the pharmacologic treatment and the reduction in the breakthrough pain obtained has a favourable effect on the global health status and quality of life of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monroy, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fondevilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menguall, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gónzalez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estudiar el manejo del dolor irruptivo en pacientes de oncología radioterápica que lo experimentan, y su impacto en el control analgésico del mismo, la tolerabilidad de los tratamientos analgésicos utilizados, así como la satisfacción y el impacto en la calidad de vida del paciente. Material y métodos: Estudio epidemiológico, observacional, prospectivo, multicéntrico, en pacientes con diagnóstico de cáncer y dolor de origen oncológico tratado con una pauta analgésica de 3er escalón, que iniciaron un tratamiento con radioterapia (RT) susceptible de que el oncólogo modificara su control analgésico. Los pacientes se reclutaron de 15 servicios de Oncología Radioterápica procedentes de centros de las regiones de Valencia y Murcia entre mayo de 2013 y diciembre de 2014. Basalmente se recogieron: datos sociodemográficos, caracterización del proceso oncológico y del dolor, tratamiento analgésico y tipo, y dosis/intensidad de la RT empleada. Al mes y a los tres meses se caracterizó el dolor mediante la valoración del cambio en la dimensión del dolor del cuestionario breve de dolor (CBD) y de la cantidad de dolor producido por episodios de dolor irruptivo, el nivel de satisfacción, la calidad de vida (EuroQol-5D) y la tolerabilidad al tratamiento analgésico. Resultados: Los pacientes incluidos en el análisis (n = 49) fueron mayoritariamente hombres (72,3 %) y la edad media (± desviación estándar) 63,7 ± 11,5 años. En el 26,5 % de los pacientes el tumor se encontraba en pulmón y en el 28,6 % en cabeza y cuello. Todos, excepto uno, refirieron dolor en el momento de la visita basal (20,8 % debido al tumor primario, 54,2 % metástasis y en 22,9 % tratamiento con RT). La mediana (Q1-Q3) del número de crisis al día fue 3,0 (2-4,5). El 60,4 % estaban recibiendo tratamiento para el dolor irruptivo, siendo fentanilo el principio activo más frecuentemente utilizado (70,4 %). Las estrategias para manejar el dolor fueron: refuerzo/modificación de analgésicos de larga duración (30,4 %), corta duración (21,7 %), ambos (21,7 %) o disminución/supresión en analgésicos de acción rápida o de larga (26,1 %). Independientemente de la estrategia, se observa una disminución en cuanto al "máximo dolor", y la cantidad total de dolor entre las 3 visitas, y una mejoría en cuanto a la "calidad de vida", "ganancia de salud" y la "satisfacción global del tratamiento". Solo se reportaron dos reacciones adversas. Conclusiones: El dolor irruptivo en los pacientes oncológicos en tratamiento de radioterapia, constituye un síntoma de elevada prevalencia. No hay una estrategia analgésica predominante para el manejo de estos pacientes, pero el fentanilo es el fármaco más frecuentemente utilizado. Los pacientes están satisfechos con el tratamiento y la reducción del dolor irruptivo repercute favorablemente en el estado general y calidad de vida de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;24(5): 241-255, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166810</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio epidemiológico observacional prospectivo del manejo del dolor en pacientes oncológicos en tratamiento radioterápico: estudio GORVAMUR</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
