<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137499</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polycystic Ovary Syndrome: Where we are and where to go</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze and discuss the latest in the literature about PCOS diagnostic criteria and to review today prevalence. Material and method: Review of the literature. A search  in MEDLINE was performed with the following keywords: PCOS AND diagnostic  criteria, PCOS and prevalence. Results: There was over 3000 articles as a result and we selected 27 based on the relevance, authors, journal impact factor and date of publication. Conclusions: PCOS can be classified into four phenotypes according to the presence or not of three diagnostic criteria: Classic PCOS: (oligo/anovulation + hyperandrogenism + polycystic ovaries (PO)), Classic PCOS w/out PO (oligo/anovulation + hyperandrogenism), Ovulatory PCOS (hyperandrogenism + PO), PCOS w/out hyperandrogenism (oligo/anovulation + PO). We think that the most important step will be to establish each phenotype morbidity (in terms of reproductive problems, metabolic syndrome,  ardiovascular disease risk, cancer risk) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romeu Sarrió, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraga Sánchez, María Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saucedo de la Llata, Eric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fertilidad, Imar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obed Carmona Ruiz, Israel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Sintetizar la información con mayor relevancia sobre los criterios diagnósticos del SOP y revisar los principales estudios de prevalencia. Material Y método: Estudio de revisión de la literatura. Se realiza una búsqueda avanzada en MEDLINE con las siguientes palabras clave: PCOS AND diagnostico criteria, PCOS AND prevalence. Resultados: Se obtienen más de 3000 artículos seleccionando 27 de ellos en base a su relevancia, autores, factor impacto de la revista y fecha de publicación. Conclusiones: El SOP puede clasificarse en 4 fenotipos según la presencia de tres criterios diagnósticos: SOP clásico (oligo/anovulación + hiperandrogenismo + ovarios poliquísticos (OP)), SOP clásico sin OP (oligo/anovulación + hiperandrogenismo), SOP ovulatorio  hiperandrogenismo + OP), SOP sin hiperandrogenismo (oligo/anovulación + OP). Consideramos que lo más importante  y determinante será el establecer La morbilidad (problemas reproductivos, síndrome metabólico, enfermedad cardiovascular, riesgo de cáncer) para cada fenotipo o presentación del síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;32(1): 27-33, ene.-mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Ovario Poliquístico: Donde estamos y hacia donde dirigirnos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53181^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53181^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53181^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53181</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
