<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165441</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between body composition and overweight/obesity. A study in children living in different geographic areas from Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the recent decades a rapid increase of excess weight has been observed. Difficulties in having access to adequate food predispose children to being overweight or obese and many of them are also anemic or have a deficit in the muscle tissue. Objective: To analyze the body composition of overweight or obese children living in two Argentinean cities with different geographical locations: General Alvear (Mendoza) and Puerto Madryn (Chubut). Methods: A cross-sectional study was carried out on 5828 schoolchildren (3048 males and 2780 females) aged from 5,0 to 14,9 living in the cities of General Alvear (GA) and Puerto Madryn (PM). Weight, height, upper arm circumference and tricipital and subscapular skinfolds were measured. Also, muscle and adipose areas of the arm and Subscapular/Tricipital Index (STI) were calculated. The prevalence of overweight (O) and obesity (Ob) were estimated using NHANES III (O&gt; P85 and &amp;#8804;P95 and Ob&gt; P95). The analysis of body composition was performed in the arm estimating deficit and excess of adipose (DAT, EAT) and muscular tissues (DMT, EMT). Results: The O and Ob prevalence was higher in PM than in GA (O= 13.1% vs 7.0%) and (Ob= 9.0% vs 4.8%). The highest percentages of children with DMT and EAT were recorded in GA, whereas those with EMT were recorded in PM. The STI values &gt;1 were found in boys and girls from both cities. Nevertheless, they appear at early ages mainly in obese girls. Discussion and Conclusions: The urban environment of PM and its lifestyle result in a child-juvenile population whit greater excess of weight, as a consequence of the increase in adipose and muscular tissues. The centralization of adipose tissue in girls could lead to the development of non-communicable diseases. On the other hand, even when excess of weight is lower in GA the condition of these children is as worrying, since excess of adipose tissue is accompanied by muscle tissue deficit, possibly as a consequence of highly caloric but poorly protein intakes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navazo, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oyhenart, Evelia Edith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forte, Luis María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dahinten, Silvia Lucrecia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En las últimas décadas se ha observado un rápido incremento del exceso de peso. Las dificultades para acceder a una alimentación adecuada, predisponen a los niños a presentar sobrepeso u obesidad y muchos de ellos resultan además anémicos o con déficit de tejido muscular. Objetivo: Analizar la composición corporal de niños con sobrepeso u obesidad, residentes en dos ciudades argentinas con diferente localización geográfica: General Alvear (Mendoza) y Puerto Madryn (Chubut). Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal en 5828 escolares (3048 varones y 2780 mujeres) desde los 5,0 a los 14,9 años de edad residentes en las ciudades de General Alvear (GA) y Puerto Madryn (PM). Se relevaron: peso, talla, perí- metro braquial y pliegues tricipital y subescapular y se calcularon las áreas muscular y adiposa del brazo y el Índice Subescapular/Tricipital (IST). Las prevalencias de sobrepeso (S) y obesidad (O) se estimaron utilizando NHANES III (S&gt;P85 y &amp;#8804;P95 y O&gt;P95). El análisis de la composición corporal mesobraquial se realizó estimando déficit y exceso de tejidos adiposo (DTA, ETA) y muscular (DTM, ETM). Resultados: Las prevalencias de S y O fueron mayores en PM respecto a GA (S=13,1% vs 7,0%) y (O= 9,0% vs 4,8%). En GA se registraron los mayores porcentajes de niños con DTM y ETA mientras que en PM aquellos con ETM. En niños y niñas de ambas ciudades se encontraron valores de IST&gt;1. No obstante, estos se manifestaron a edades más tempranas principalmente en niñas obesas. Discusión y Conclusiones: El ambiente urbano de PM y su estilo de vida, conducen a que la población infanto-juvenil presente mayor exceso de peso, como consecuencia del aumento en los tejidos adiposo y muscular. La mayor centralización adiposa en niñas puede conducir al desarrollo de enfermedades no trasmisibles. Por otra parte, aun cuando el exceso de peso es menor en GA, la condición de estos niños es también preocupante, puesto que el exceso de tejido adiposo se acompaña de déficit de tejido muscular, posiblemente como consecuencia de ingestas altamente calóricas pero proteicamente deficientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(2): 114-124, 2017. mapas, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición corporal en relación al sobrepeso y a la obesidad. Un estudio en niños residentes en diferentes áreas geográficas de Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
