<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166777</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antithrombotic treatment in diabetics with acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetic patients with acute coronary syndrome exhibit increased platelet reactivity and are at a greater risk of experiencing a cardiovascular event over both the short and long term than nondiabetics with the syndrome. Whereas aspirin appears to function similarly in diabetics with acute coronary syndrome as in nondiabetics, clopidogrel has less of an inhibitory effect on platelets in diabetic patients. The use of powerful antiplatelet agents, such as glycoprotein IIb/IIIa inhibitors, during the acute phase has been shown to be particularly effective in diabetics with the syndrome. In addition, dual antiplatelet therapy with aspirin and prasugrel has demonstrated greater benefits in diabetics than aspirin plus clopidogrel. Meanwhile, the development of alternative antiplatelet agents with novel platelet targets will help to counteract some of the numerous factors responsible for the platelet hyperreactivity seen in diabetic patients with acute coronary síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Rubira, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ortiz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes diabéticos con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA) tienen mayor reactividad plaquetaria y mayor riesgo de sufrir eventos clínicos a corto y largo plazo en comparación con los no diabéticos. Mientras que la aspirina en diabéticos con SCA parece funcionar igual que en los no diabéticos, el clopidogrel tiene menor efecto inhibitorio en las plaquetas de los pacientes diabéticos. La utilización en fase aguda de potentes antiagregantes como los inhibidores de la glucoproteína IIb/IIIa se ha mostrado especialmente eficaz en los diabéticos con SCA, y también con la doble antiagregación con aspirina más prasugrel se ha demostrado mayor beneficio comparado con aspirina más clopidogrel en los diabéticos. Entre tanto, el desarrollo de otros agentes antiplaquetarios dirigidos contra nuevas dianas en la plaqueta servirá para contrarrestar parte de los múltiples factores de la hiperactividad plaquetaria presente en los diabéticos con SCA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.D): 42d-48d, 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento antitrombótico en diabéticos con síndrome coronario agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32647^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
