<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70622</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular diseases (CVD), of which coronary heart disease is the most common, are the major causes of death in middle-aged and older patients in most developed countries and in many developing countries. The comprehensive action for CVD prevention has to include: a) «population» strategy -for altering the lifestyle and environmental factors in the entire population, and b) «high-risk» strategy -identification of people at high cardiovascular risk. The principles for CVD prevention were described by several International Heart Health Conferences: Victoria Declaration (1992), Catalonia Declaration (1996), Singapore Declaration (1998), Osaka Declaration (2001), International Principles for National and Regional Guidelines on CVD Prevention (2004), Luxemburg Declaration (2005), and European Heart Health Charter (2006). There is an international consensus among guidelines regarding the priorities and goals for CVD prevention, lifestyles and risk factor management, and use of cardioprotective medication. Patients with established CVD are considered to be a top priority for prevention. For healthy individuals, the decision to treat blood pressure or lipids depends on the level of absolute multifactorial risk for developing CVD. The risk charts and tables can be used to decide the likelihood of cardiovascular events and the intensity of risk factor management. The guidelines provide guidance to policy-makers and health care workers on how to target high risk people in different resource settings, using evidence-based and cost-effective preventive approaches (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kotseva, Kornelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV), la más frecuente de las cuales es la enfermedad coronaria, son las principales causas de muerte en los pacientes de mediana edad y de edad avanzada en la mayoría de los países desarrollados y en muchos países en desarrollo. La actuación global para la prevención de la ECV debe incluir: a) una estrategia «poblacional» para modificar los factores de estilo de vida y ambientales en toda la población, y b) una estrategia de «alto riesgo» (identificar a las personas en riesgo cardiovascular elevado). Los principios de la prevención de las ECV han sido descritos en varias conferencias internacionales sobre la salud cardiaca: Victoria Declaration (1992), Catalonia Declaration (1996), Singapore Declaration (1998), Osaka Declaration (2001), International Principles for National and Regional Guidelines on ECV Prevention (2004), Luxemburg Declaration (2005) y European Heart Health Charter (2006). Hay consenso internacional entre las diversas directrices respecto a las prioridades y los objetivos de la prevención de las ECV, el control de los factores de riesgo y los estilos de vida y el uso de medicación cardioprotectora. Se considera que los pacientes con una ECV establecida son la principal prioridad para la prevención. En los individuos sanos, la decisión de tratar la presión arterial o los lípidos depende del nivel absoluto de riesgo multifactorial de la aparición de una ECV. Se puede usar gráficos y tablas de riesgo para decidir la probabilidad de que se produzcan episodios cardiovasculares y la intensidad del tratamiento de los factores de riesgo. Las directrices proporcionan orientación a los encargados de la toma de decisiones y a los profesionales de la asistencia sanitaria sobre cómo atender a las personas de alto riesgo en contextos con diferente disponibilidad de recursos, utilizando enfoques preventivos basados en la evidencia y con una relación coste-efectividad favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;61(9): 960-970, sept. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70622</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11482</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
