<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10798</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Insomnia prevalence and environmental conditions in patients older than 65 years at Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the prevalence of insomnia and environmental conditions served as risk factors in its onset in patients equal to or older than 65 years assigned to two nursing consultation centers from Madrid: Ciudad Jardín and Los Ángeles. Methods: Cross-sectional descriptive study. It was expected a proportion of 25% of old patients with insomnia, 95% confidence interval (CI) and a precision of ±7% getting a result of 168 patients randomly selected. Results: Prevalence of insomnia about 46%. The maintenance insomnia is the most prominent. Prevalence of insomnia in women, diabetes, use of antihypertensive drugs and daytime sleepiness. Conclusions: It is advisable to increase activities Health Education regarding this problem and promote courses for updating the knowledge of professionals to facilitate correct case detection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo Crego, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Peña, Carmen María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la prevalencia de insomnio y los condicionantes ambientales que se presentan como factores de riesgo en su aparición en los pacientes de edad igual o superior a 65 años adscritos a dos consultas de enfermería de los centros de salud Ciudad Jardín y Los Ángeles de la Comunidad de Madrid. Método: Estudio descriptivo observacional transversal. Se consideró una proporción esperada de ancianos con insomnio del 25%, un intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95% y una precisión de ±7%, resultando un tamaño muestral aleatorizado de 168 pacientes. Resultados: Prevalencia de insomnio del 46%, destacando entre ellos el de mantenimiento. Predominio en el sexo femenino, la diabetes, el consumo de fármacos antihipertensivos y la somnolencia diurna. Conclusión: Resulta recomendable el incremento de las actividades de educación para la salud en relación con este problema y la promoción de cursos para la actualización de los conocimientos de los profesionales para facilitar la correcta detección de los casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(3): 121-126, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de insomnio y condicionantes ambientales en mayores de 65 años en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
