<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163820</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alagille syndrome. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Alagille syndrome is an autosomal dominant disorder characterised by chronic cholestasis due to intrahepatic biliary hypoplasia, cardiac and skeletal abnormalities and specific facial dysmorphias. Case report and discussion: We report the case of a 25-year-old primigravida referred to the high-risk pregnancy unit at 28 weeks of gestation due to intrauterine growth restriction, foetal ascites and polyhydramnios. Ultrasound examination showed marked thoracolumbar kyphosis at T11/L2 and cardiac anomalies. Necropsy demonstrated the presence of tetralogy of Fallot, fusion of the thoracic and lumbar vertebral bodies (butterfly vertebrae) and agenesis of the gallbladder. The pattern of foetal anomalies was consistent with those associated with Alagille syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Torres, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Cepeda, Duly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas-González, Anny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el síndrome de Alagille es un desorden autosómico dominante caracterizado por colestasis crónica debido a hipoplasia biliar intrahepática, anomalías cardiacas y esqueléticas y alteraciones faciales específicas. Caso clínico y discusión: se presenta un caso de primigesta de 25 años de edad que fue remitida a la Consulta Prenatal de Alto Riesgo a las 28 semanas por presentar restricción del crecimiento intrauterino del feto, ascitis fetal y polihidramnios. La evaluación ecográfica demostró marcada cifosis de la columna toracolumbar en T11/L2 y anomalías cardiacas. La necropsia demostró la presencia de tetralogía de Fallot, fusión de los cuerpos vertebrales toracolumbares (vértebras en mariposa) y agenesia de la vesícula biliar. El patrón de anomalías fetales fue coherente con aquellas asociadas con el síndrome de Alagille (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(1): 39-42, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Alagille. Reporte de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30271^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30271^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
