<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053391</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Langerhans cell histiocytosis in the maxillofacial area in adults. Report of three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Langerhans cell histiocytosis (LCH) is a disease of unknown etiology, characterized by proliferation of pathological Langerhans cells within different organs. It mainly affects children, but adult cases also occur, with an incidence rate of one to two per million. The head and neck are affected in almost 90% of cases. Diagnosis is made by means of histopathologicalanalysis, and imaging studies are necessary in order to determine extent of the disease. There are no controlled trials proposing an optimal treatment protocol for LCH. Prognosis in adults is generally good due to the slow evolution of the disease and its favourable response to treatment. In our report, we present three cases of LCH in patients aged 16, 24, and 28 years respectively, with primary manifestation in the maxillofacial area. A literature review was also conducted</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dean Ferrer, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Ortiz, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela Salas, Borja</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Masera, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Sánchez, Gracia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Marcos, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Bohórquez, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alamillos Granados, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Histiocitosis de Células de Langerhans (HCL), es una enfermedad de etiología desconocida, que se caracteriza por la proliferación e infiltración anormal, de órganos, por células de Langerhans patológicas. Afecta predominantementea pacientes en edad pediátrica, siendo en adultos la incidencia de la enfermedad de uno a dos casos por millón de habitantes. Las manifestaciones en cabeza y cuello aparecen en casi un 90% de los casos. El diagnóstico se obtiene por medios anatomopatológicos, siendo necesarias una serie de pruebas, determinantes de extensión, en todos los pacientes diagnosticados de HCL. No existen estudios, controlados, que determinen un tratamiento óptimo para la HCL. El pronósticode esta enfermedad en adultos es generalmente bueno debido a la lenta evolución de la enfermedad y a su buena respuesta al tratamiento. Presentamos una revisión de tres casos de HCL, de 16, 24 y 28 años de edad, con manifestación primaria en el área Maxilofacial. Así mismo, realizamos una revisión de la literatura</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(2): E145-E150, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitosis de Células de Langerhans en el área maxilofacial en adultos. Informe de tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22589^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22589^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
