<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14202</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability and validity of the EASYCare-2010 Standard to assess elderly people in Portuguese Primary Health Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The EASYCare is a multidimensional assessment tool for older people, which corresponds to the concerns and priorities of older people in relation to their needs, health, and quality of life. The EASYCare instrument has been used in many countries worldwide. Lack of reliability evidence has recently been raised by researchers. This study aimed to test the validity and reliability of the EASYCare-2010 instrument in community-dwelling Portuguese older people attended in Primary Health Care centres. Methods: The sample for this transversal study (N = 244) was collected from Portuguese Primary Health Care Centers. Categorical Principal Component Analysis was used to assess the underlying dimensions of EASYCare-2010. Construct validity was evaluated through correlation with the World Health Organization Quality of Life Assessment Instrument-Short Form. Results: A two-factor model (labelled "mobility and activities of daily life", and "general well-being and safety") was found. The EASYCare-2010 instrument showed acceptable levels for internal consistency (&amp;#8805;0.70). The EASYCare-2010 factors were correlated with measures of quality of life. Results showed that in most polytomous items, some of the more extreme categories were not considered at all or only by a residual number of participants. Conclusion: EASY Care -2010 version is a valid and reliable instrument for holistic assessment of the older people attended in Primary Health Care centres in Portugal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brandão, Maria Piedade</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Philp, Ian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Cardoso, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El EASYCare es una herramienta de evaluación multidimensional para las personas mayores, que corresponde a las preocupaciones y prioridades de las personas mayores en relación con sus necesidades, salud y calidad de vida. El instrumento EASYCare se ha utilizado en muchos países del mundo. La falta de pruebas de fiabilidad ha sido planteada recientemente por los investigadores. Este estudio tuvo como objetivo probar la validez y fiabilidad del instrumento EASYCare-2010 en personas mayores portuguesas residentes en la comunidad, atendidos en centros de Atención Primaria de la Salud. Métodos: La muestra para este estudio transversal (N = 244) se recogió en Centros de Atención Primaria de Portugal. Se utilizó el Análisis de Componentes Principales Categórico para evaluar las dimensiones subyacentes de EASYCare-2010. La validez del constructo se evaluó mediante la correlación con el instrumento de evaluación de la calidad de vida de la Organización Mundial de la Salud, instrumento en su forma corta. Resultados: Se encontró un modelo de dos factores (denominado «movilidad y actividades de la vida diaria» y «bienestar general y seguridad»). El instrumento EASYCare-2010 mostró niveles aceptables de consistencia interna (&amp;#8805; 0.70). Los factores EASYCare-2010 se correlacionaron con medidas de calidad de vida. Los resultados mostraron que en la mayoría de ítems politómicos en algunas categorías extremas no se consideraron o solo por un número residual de participantes. Conclusión: La versión EASY Care-2010 es un instrumento válido y fiable para la evaluación holística de las personas mayores atendidas en centros de Atención Primaria de Salud en Portugal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(10): 576-585, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad y validez del EASYCare-2010 Standard para evaluar a las personas mayores en Atención Primaria de Salud en Portugal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
