<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19263</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Qualitative research in Spain: from political life to maltreatment of the sense</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A current of sociological thought came into being in Spain in the sixties consisting of what is known by the ill-defined term of qualitative methodology in our country. A blatant paradox, as the freedom with which this theoretical and methodological building would be erected was born precisely out of a lack of political freedom and freedom of thought of those dreadful years. Countering the official body of knowledge and also removed from all "protest" orthodoxy, a vivid, problematical reflection of the society's true situation conceived as critical theory took shape. It is in no way owing, as regards its assumptions, its findings or its formulations, to either English-U.S. sociology, which was predominant at the time, or to that which would later progressively makes it way to us. Taking exception to data and the imaginary all-powerful importance thereof, this methodology propounded a radical turnabout of the perspective of this research to focus on language, understood as the social discourse, in the powerful sense of the word, and not as a mere set of statements, also moving away from the more or less subjectivist conceptions of the meaning. Opposing the body of knowledge of this discipline, it construed research as a crossroads, undertaking an endless task, as it is impossible to complete from a logical point of view. It then propounded listening to the sense, which is never the same as the meaning, and includes the analysis of the wording used for a full understanding thereof.... This is a totally autochthonous current perfectly well-founded at its epistemological, methodological and technical levels, the continuing survival today of which is more than uncertain, as it dissolves into the body of university knowledge, into the ongoing flow of the quotes of authors, currents and disciplines. It is corrupted in its commercial use, where its discontinuance now seems assured in benefit of the marketing discourse, and it is running the risk of becoming completely useless in social areas of study (such as Health), where poorer English-U.S. perspectives are coming into play without apparently meeting with the least critical opposition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los años sesenta surge en España una corriente de reflexión sociológica que constituye la (mal llamada) metodología cualitativa en nuestro país. Paradoja viva, pues la libertad con la que se erigió ese edificio teórico y metodológico nacía precisamente de la falta de libertad política y de pensamiento de aquellos años terribles. Contra el saber oficial, y alejada también de toda ortodoxia de la 'contestación', fue articulando una reflexión viva y problemática de la realidad social, concebida como teoría crítica. Nada debe en sus presupuestos, en sus hallazgos, en su formulación..., a la sociología anglosajona que predominaba en aquellos años, o a la que nos ha ido llegando posteriormente. Contra el dato y su reificación imaginaria, esta metodología propuso de modo radical un giro de la perspectiva de la investigación hacia el lenguaje, entendido como discurso social, en el sentido fuerte del concepto, y no como mera colección de enunciados, alejándose también de las concepciones más o menos subjetivistas del sentido. Contra el saber disciplinar entendió la investigación como un cruce de caminos que aborda una tarea inacabable porque su cierre es imposible desde un punto de vista lógico. Propuso entonces la escucha del sentido, que nunca coincide con la significación, e incluyó el análisis de la enunciación para comprenderlo... Hablamos de una corriente completamente autóctona y perfectamente fundamentada en sus niveles epistemológico, metodológico, y técnico, cuya pervivencia hoy día es más que dudosa: se disuelve en el saber universitario, en el interior del magma de las citas de autores, corrientes y disciplinas. Se pervierte en su aplicación comercial, donde la discontinuidad parece ya asegurada, en beneficio del discurso del márketing; y corre el riesgo de perder toda vigencia en áreas sociales de estudio (como la Salud), donde entran perspectivas anglosajonas más pobres, sin encontrar --al parecer-- la menor resistencia crítica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(5): 381-393, sept. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La investigación cualitativa en España: de la vida política al maltrato del sentido</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Peinado, Anselmo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19263</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d11490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
