<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158306</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dementia drug consumption in the Basque Country between 2006 and 2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. We evaluated the consumption of specific medications for treating cognitive symptoms associated with AD and other types of dementia in individuals over 60 years of age between 2006 and 2011 in the Basque Country. Methods. A retrospective descriptive study was conducted. The pharmacy division of the Basque Government Department of Health provided the prescribing data for the following drugs: donepezil, rivastigmine, galantamine, and memantine. The number of defined daily doses (DDDs) and the number of DDDs per 1000 inhabitants/day (DHD) were calculated. Results. Consumption increased by 49.72% between 2006 and 2011. There were marked differences between drugs (13.02% donepezil; 93.18% rivastigmine; 37.79% galantamine; 70.40% memantine) and Basque provinces (16.34% in Áraba; 50.49% in Bizkaia; 57.37% in Gipuzkoa). Likewise, expenditure increased from &#128;11.5 million in 2006 to &#128; 18.1 million in 2011. Conclusions. This study shows increased consumption of these drugs, although there are also marked differences by province which may be due to differences in prescribing habits. Spending for these drugs rose parallel to this increase in consumption; drug prices remained stable throughout the study period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Argumedo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizondo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Este estudio evalúa el consumo de medicamentos para el tratamiento cognitivo de la EA y otras demencias en personas mayores de 60 años entre los años 2006 y 2011 en el País Vasco. Métodos. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo. La Dirección de Farmacia del Departamento de Salud del Gobierno Vasco facilitó los datos de prescripción de donepezilo, rivastigmina, galantamina y memantina. Se obtuvieron el número de dosis diarias definidas (DDD) y el número de DDD por 1.000 habitantes/día (DHD). Resultados. El consumo se incrementó un 49,72% durante el periodo 2006-2011, aumento que varió en función del medicamento (donepezilo 13,02%; rivastigmina 93,18%; galantamina 37,79%; memantina 70,40%) y del TTHH (Álava 16,34%; Bizkaia 50,49%; Gipuzkoa 57,37%). El gasto aumentó de 11,5 millones de euros en 2006 a 18,1 millones en 2011. Conclusiones. Se observó un aumento en el consumo aunque existen diferencias entre TTHH que pueden deberse a hábitos de prescripción diferentes. El gasto farmacéutico se incrementó paralelamente al aumento en el consumo, ya que el precio de los medicamentos permaneció estable en ese periodo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;31(9): 613-619, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de medicamentos para el tratamiento de la demencia en la Comunidad Autónoma Vasca durante el periodo 2006-2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55888^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
