<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74103</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">School harassment related behaviors in a secondary education school</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Bullying in the school is an aggressive,intentional and persistent behavior among students. Thisstudy has aimed to discover the frequency and characteristicsof these aggressive behaviors in the school and the experienceof teenagers regarding the mentioned behaviors.MATERIALS AND METHODS. This is an observationaldescriptive study performed among pupils from first gradeto fourth grade of Compulsory Secondary Education in aschool in Toledo with an anonymous and self-completed survey,elaborated ad hoc.RESULTS. One hundred twenty four youths between 13and 17 years of age, 51.6% males, were included. Of these,16.9% admitted they had felt bullied, rejected or abusedby their schoolmates at one time or another (CI 95%: 11.0-24.9). This percentage was higher among girls (22.0 vs 11.5;p = 0.121). A total of 49.2% stated they know about some casesof harassment.Although the most common place where bullying takesplace is in the street, 40.7% located it in their own classroomsand 36.6% in the playground. The most frequently observedbullying behaviors were physical (87.4%), followedby verbal (75.8%) and isolation (63.7%). Globally, 78.2% admittedthey had done some bullying-related activity at one timeor another, without differences between the genders.&#147;In case of suffering from harassment&#148;, 22.6% stated thatthey would not comment on it with anybody.CONCLUSIONS. Bullying, to a lesser or greater degree, isa frequent phenomenon among teenagers. The high percentageof students who admit that the classroom is the placewhere this type of action occurs is surprising. Both educationand health professionals must act to anticipate, detectand come up with solutions to this problem (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bartolomé Marsá, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, Vélez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Álvarez Vijante, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Parada, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Castro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Aranda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. El acoso escolar (bullying) es una conducta agresiva, intencional y persistente entre escolares. El objetivo de este estudio fue explorar la frecuencia y las características de los comportamientos agresivos en el ámbito escolar y la vivencia de los propios adolescentes de dichas conductas. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Estudio observacional descriptivo, realizado entre alumnos de primero a cuarto de Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria en un instituto de Toledo, mediante encuesta anónima y autocumplimentada, elaborada ad hoc. RESULTADOS. Se incluyeron en el estudio 124 jóvenes entre 13 y 17 años, de los que el 51,6% correspondía a varones. El 16,9% reconoce haberse sentido acosado, rechazado o perseguido alguna vez por sus compañeros (intervalo de confianza del 95%: 11,0-24,9). Este porcentaje es mayor en chicas (22,0 frente a 11,5; p = 0,121). El 49,2% afirmó conocer algún caso de acoso. Aunque el lugar más habitual donde tiene lugar el acoso es la calle, un 40,7% lo situó en las propias aulas y un 36,6% en el patio. Las conductas de acoso más frecuentemente observadas fueron las físicas (87,4%), seguidas de las verbales (75,8%) y el aislamiento (63,7%). Globalmente, el 78,2% reconoció haber realizado algún comportamiento relacionado con el bullying alguna vez, sin diferencias entre sexos. Un 22,6% refiere que ¿en caso de sufrir acoso¿ no lo comentaría con nadie. CONCLUSIONES. El acoso escolar, en mayor o menor grado, es un fenómeno frecuente entre adolescentes. Sorprende el alto porcentaje que reconoce la propia clase como emplazamiento en el que tienen lugar acciones de este tipo. Tanto los profesionales de la enseñanza como los sanitarios debemos actuar para prevenir, detectar y poner soluciones a este problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(10): 489-492, dic. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conductas relacionadas con el acoso escolar en un instituto de educación secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
