<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72993</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The complex regional pain syndrome with no apparent cause. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Complex Regional Pain Syndrome(CRPS) is a nosological entity characterized by the presenceof pain, vasomotor instability and limitation of the normalfunction, whose etiology has still not been demonstrated, althoughit usually occurs after a traumatic injury. It is definedby the presence of pain and its picture may become worsewith inflammation, swelling, skin abnormalities, changes incolor and limp. The 99TC-scintigraphy is a sensitive diagnostictest. However, there is no specific test for its diagnosis. Nowadays,several scales have been described whose criteriamake it possible to reach a probable diagnosis. Treatment ofCRPS must be begun as soon as possible. Several steps areproposed: pharmacological treatment, neural blockade, sympathectomy,spinal cord stimulation, intrathecal drug deliveryaccompanied by rehabilitation and in some cases psychotherapy.We describe the case of a 38-year-old woman with noprevious factors who develops CRPS. We present a bibliographicreview on this disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-Socorro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de dolor regional complejo(SDRC) es una entidad nosológica que cursa con dolor, inestabilidadvasomotora y limitación funcional, cuya etiología noestá aún demostrada; con frecuencia se produce después deun traumatismo. Se caracteriza por dolor, y el cuadro se puedeagravar con inflamación, tumefacción, alteraciones cutáneas,cambios de color y claudicación. La gammagrafía contecnecio-99 es una prueba sensible, sin embargo no existeuna prueba específica para el diagnóstico certero; hoy en díase han descrito numerosas escalas cuyos criterios permitenllegar a un diagnóstico probable. El tratamiento del SDRCdebe ser introducido lo antes posible; se plantea en variosescalones: farmacológico, bloqueos nerviosos, simpatectomía,estimulación medular, infusión intratecal, acompañados de rehabilitacióny en algunos casos de psicoterapia.Se describe el caso de una mujer de 38 años que sin causaprevia desarrolla un SDRC. Asimismo se hace una revisiónbibliográfica de esta enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(4): 187-190, jul.-ago.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de dolor regional complejo sin causa aparente. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13942^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
