<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77368</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between the consumption of tobacco and alcohol and physical exercise while at university</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo find out the influence that going to University has on changing smoking and alcohol habits, and on physical exercise in students in the EU.DesignCross-sectional descriptive study.SettingUniversity of Murcia.ParticipantsA sample of 1179 students was selected.InterventionsA self-filled and anonymous questionnaire was used. It consisted of 36 questions using 4 measurement scales: level of health information on cardiovascular risks (CVR), smoking, alcohol consumption and doing physical exercise.ResultsA total of 39.2% of university students in their last academic year said they were smokers, compared to 36.4% in the first year (NS). A total of 81.6% of first year students had consumed alcohol at weekends, compared to 81.1% of those in their last year (NS). In the overall assessment of alcohol consumption, 13% «stopped drinking or drank less» and 10% «drank more», although the majority (55%), did not change their drinking habits. As regards physical exercise, the number of students who did more physical exercise was 21.2% in the first academic year, compared to 20% of students in their last year (NS).ConclusionsGoing to University does not seem to exercise a positive influence on the habits and lifestyles of young people. Measures should be taken to encourage healthy lifestyles in Universities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leal Hernández, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abellán Alemán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balanza Galindo, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conesa Bernal, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pastor, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosAveriguar la influencia que tiene el paso por la universidad en la modificación de los hábitos de consumo de tabaco y alcohol y el ejercicio físico en los estudiantes universitarios.DiseñoEstudio descriptivo, transversal.EmplazamientoÁmbito universitario de Murcia.ParticipantesSe selecciona una muestra de 1.179 alumnos.IntervencionesSe utiliza un cuestionario autocumplimentado y anónimo. Consta de 36 preguntas con 4 escalas de medida: grado de información sanitaria sobre RCV, consumo de tabaco, consumo de alcohol y realización de ejercicio físico.ResultadosLos estudiantes universitarios (EU) del último curso se declaran fumadores: el 39,2 frente al 36,4% de los de primer curso (NS). El 81,6% de los de primer curso consumen alcohol durante los fines de semana, frente al 81,1% de los del último curso (NS). En la valoración general del consumo de alcohol el 13% deja de consumir o consume menos y el 10% consume más, aunque la mayoría (55,2%) no modifica su hábito de consumo. Respecto al ejercicio físico, la frecuencia de EU que refieren practicar más ejercicio es de un 21,2% en los del primer curso frente al 20% en los del último curso (NS).ConclusionesEl paso por la universidad no parece tener influencia positiva en los hábitos y estilos de vida de los jóvenes. Es necesario aplicar medidas para potenciar estilos de vida saludables entre los universitarios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;41(10): 558-563, oct. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el consumo de tabaco y alcohol y el ejercicio físico con el paso por la universidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
