<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91145</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A study on surgical dressings and the uses associated to them</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the variability in the surgical dressing practices and to assess the factors of their use. Method: A prospective study on surgical dressings was carried out. Data was collected on some post surgery patients who, once outside the operating room in a general hospital, they were still wearing a surgical dressing. A non-random sample was included. Socio demographic data, pre operative and intra operative data inside the operating room were collected as well as post surgical tests in the surgical inpatient wards. Tests alpha2 were carried out for the category variables, ? Student for the continuous ones and the variant analysis.  Results: 315 patients were put into groups of 5 according to the surgical proceedings. All dressings were realized with non-woven gauze dressings (more absorbent) and mostly removed every 24 to 48 hours. Two groups showed more exuded dressings. The highest percentage of lesions appeared when dressings were removed between 24 and 48 hours. 50% of the removed ones before the first 24 hours had been over dressed and the chance of having skin lesion was increased 7 times with the reinforcement. Patients showed a medium average of comfort of 6,09 (EVA 0-10) to the dressings.  Conclusions: The use of the traditional dry dressings to cover surgical wounds and the technique to apply a dressing over the existing one are here confirmed. A direct relation is observed between the reapplication of dressings to the same wound and the skin lesions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosell-Cinca, Fina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clotet-Argemí, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pons, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantillo-Vila, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca-Closa, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirveches-Pérez, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dot-Suárez, Imma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar la variabilidad en la práctica de los apósitos quirúrgicos y los factores asociados con su uso. Método: se realizó un estudio transversal sobre los apósitos quirúrgicos. Se estudió una población de pacientes quirúrgicos de un hospital general que al salir del quirófano eran portadores de dicho apósito. Se incluyó una muestra no aleatoria. Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos y clínicos preoperatorios e intraoperatorios en el quirófano y postoperatorios en las plantas de hospitalización quirúrgica. Se efectuaron pruebas de alpha2 para las variables categóricas y para las continuas la ? de Student y el análisis de la varianza. Resultados: 315 pacientes se agruparon en cinco grupos, según el procedimiento quirúrgico. Todos los apósitos se realizaron con gasas hidrófilas de algodón, fijados con apósito de tejido sin tejer y la mayoría cambiados entre las 24-48 horas. Dos grupos presentaron más apósitos manchados. El mayor porcentaje de lesiones aparecía cuando se cambiaban entre las 24 y las 48 horas. El 50% de los cambiados antes de las 24 horas había sido reforzado y la probabilidad de que se lesionara la piel se multiplicaba por siete con el refuerzo. Los pacientes manifestaron un confort medio de 6,09 (EVA 0- 10) respecto al apósito. Conclusiones: se constata el uso del apósito tradicional de gasa seca para cubrir las heridas operatorias y la técnica de refuerzo de los apósitos. Se observa una relación directa entre el refuerzo y las lesiones en la piel(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(10): 694-699, oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apósitos quirúrgicos. Factores asociados con su uso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
