<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140728</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cause of death in hospitalized patients with laboratory-confirmed influenza</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. We analyzed the underlying cause of death recorded in hospitalized patients with laboratory-confirmed influenza. Methods. The present study included all patients with a laboratory-confirmed diagnosis of influenza during the influenza seasons 2009-2010 to 2013-2014 who were attended to in hospital and died. Their underlying cause of death according to the International Classification of Diseases 10th Revision was obtained from the Navarre Mortality Registry. Results. Among 49 patients studied, the underlying causes of death were 35% influenza, 4% pneumonia, 14% other respiratory diseases, 10% circulatory disease and 37% other causes. Conclusions. Non-cardiorespiratory causes accounted for a third of deaths in patients with confirmed influenza, thus all-cause mortality should be considered in estimating the full burden of influenza mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chamorro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Baz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Floristán, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezpeleta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La mortalidad por gripe no se conoce bien porque la mayoría de las personas que mueren por gripe no se confirman por laboratorio. Analizamos la causa básica de muerte registrada en los pacientes hospitalizados con gripe confirmada por laboratorio. Métodos. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes con diagnóstico de gripe por laboratorio que habían sido atendidos en el hospital y murieron durante las temporadas 2009-2010 a 2013-2014 en Navarra. La causa básica demuerte se obtuvo del Registro de Mortalidad. Resultados. Entre los 49 pacientes estudiados, la causa básica de muerte fue en el 35% gripe, en el 4% neumonía, en el 14% otras enfermedades respiratorias, en el 10% enfermedades cardiovasculares y en el 37% otras causas. Conclusiones. Un tercio de las muertes en pacientes con gripe confirmada se asignaron a causas no cardiorrespiratorias. Deberían tenerse en cuenta todas las causas para estimar la carga total de la mortalidad por gripe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;38(2): 263-268, mayo-ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140728</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causa de muerte en pacientes hospitalizados con gripe confirmada por laboratorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51711^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51711^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55554^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28029^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55554^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55554^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
