<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129058</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interventions that improve the prognosis in neurofibromatosis type 2: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurofibromatosis type 2 (NF2) is an autosomal dominant (AD) disease that predisposes to multiple neoplasms; the bilateral acoustic neuroma is pathognomonic. The presence of several types of tumors having different pathological lineage and localization is frequent in the same patient. This hinds treatment decisions, especially in children and adolescents. The disorder is located on chromosome 22q12. The different types of surgery and radiotherapy are essential tools for the treatment of NF2. Therefore, individualized rehabilitation treatment influences the final functional prognosis. The purpose of the clinical and neuroimaging follow-up should be that of controlling the progression of tumors and therapeutic decision(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Palero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amosa Delgado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iodrovo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Dolado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurofibromatosis tipo 2 (NF2) es una enfermedad autosómica dominante (AD) que predispone a múltiples lesiones neoplásicas; el neurinoma del acústico bilateral es patognomónico. Es frecuente la presencia en el mismo paciente de varios tipos de tumores con estirpe patológica y localización diferentes, lo que hace más difícil las decisiones terapéuticas, especialmente en niños y adolescentes. El trastorno se localiza en el cromosoma 22q12. Las distintas modalidades de cirugía y radioterapia son armas fundamentales en el tratamiento de la NF2. El tratamiento rehabilitador individualizado influye en el pronóstico funcional final. El seguimiento clínico y de neuroimagen debe tener como objetivo el control evolutivo de los tumores y la decisión terapéutica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);45(2): 173-176, abr.-jun.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones que mejoran el pronóstico en la neurofibromatosis tipo 2: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9635^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9635^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29932^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9635^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
