<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136169</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infliximab use as a therapeutic option in bilateral breast refractory postoperative pyoderma gangrenosum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pyoderma gangrenosum is a rare, non-infection, ulcerating skin disease, included into neutrophilic dermatosis. The pathogenesis of pyoderma gangrenosum has not been determined yet, but it might be related to the immunologic mechanism. The breast localization is unusual, appearing after surgery in most of cases due to the phatergy phenomenon but it can also appear unexpectedly. We report a case of bilateral postsurgical pyoderma gangrenosum of the breast in a patient with breast cancer subjected to mastectomy with reconstruction. The case is wrongly diagnosed as surgical wound dehiscence leading to several debridements that exacerbate the problem and delay the diagnosis by more than one year. After several treatments, it was decided to start with infliximab therapy due to the refractoriness of the process, evolving satisfactorily. The aim of investigating this case is to be able to detect the disease early, to prevent physical and psychological harm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castaño González, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Palacios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero Hernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilar Alejo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pioderma gangrenoso es una rara enfermedad cutánea ulcerada no infecciosa, perteneciente a las dermatosis neutrofílicas. Su etiopatogenia no está bien definida hasta el momento, barajándose un mecanismo inmunológico. La localización mamaria de la afectación es inusual, apareciendo tras cirugía en la mayoría de casos en relación con el fenómeno de patergia, pero también puede ser de aparición espontánea. Presentamos un caso de paciente con carcinoma de mama izquierda sometida a mastectomía radical con reconstrucción que desarrolla un pioderma gangrenoso bilateral postquirúrgico. Se diagnosticó erróneamente como dehiscencia de herida quirúrgica, procediéndose a múltiples desbridamientos que exacerbaron el problema y retrasaron el diagnóstico más de un año. Tras múltiples tratamientos, se decide inicio de terapia con infliximab debido a la refractariedad del proceso, evolucionando satisfactoriamente. La presentación de este caso tiene como objetivo el reconocimiento y abordaje precoz de esta entidad para aprender a prevenir su morbilidad física y psicológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;41(1): 97-103, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infliximab como opción terapéutica en pioderma gangrenoso mamario bilateral postquirúrgico refractario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23752^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30584^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
