<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042634</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteonecrosis of the jaws and bisphosphonates. Report of three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bisphosphonates are recently acquiring increasing relevance in the treatment of several diseases.In line with the increased use of these compounds, cases of mandibular osteonecrosis, and to a lesser extent, maxillary osteonecrosis,are being reported. This necrosis is difficult to treat in patients who usually have a previously limited quality of life.A surgical performance carried out by oral and maxillofacial surgeons, stomatologists and odontologists might lead to bone exposure.A treatment based on conservation and as harmless as possible seems to be the most advisable way of acting with these patients in order to minimize the incidence and treat the complications, once the lesions have been ascertained.We report three cases treated in our service of osteonecrosis of the jaws after exodontics.This side effect should be remembered before starting any surgical treatment in these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sebastián López, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etayo Pérez, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garatea Crelgo, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Zuazaga, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino Gorbea, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los bisfosfonatos están adquiriendo una relevancia terapéutica cada vez mayor, dada su utilidad en el manejo de diversas patologías.Con el incremento de su uso, se están documentando casos de necrosis ósea mandibular, y en menor medida maxilar, de difícil solución y con una importante afectación de la calidad de vida de los pacientes en tratamiento con estos fármacos.El factor que con mayor frecuencia desencadena el proceso es la actuación de los profesionales: odontólogos, estomatólogos y cirujanos orales y maxilofaciales. La previsión, las intervenciones atraumáticas y el tratamiento conservador, parecen ser los medios más adecuados para minimizarla incidencia o resolver las complicaciones.Este artículo presenta tres casos, seguidos por nuestro servicio, de pacientes con necrosis ósea maxilar tras procedimientos dentales, fundamentalmente exodoncias.El conocimiento de este posible efecto secundario de los bisfosfonatos debería ser tenido en cuenta antes de cualquier intervenciónen este tipo de pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(1): 76-79, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteonecrosis maxilar y bisfosfonatos. Presentación de tres nuevos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24221^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7274^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
