<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043428</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 76 year old male sent to thegeriatric out patient clinic from his health care center dueto weight loss accompanied by anorexia, asthenia andlumbar pain in the last month. Based on all of the testscarried out, the diagnostic conclusion reached was ainfective endocarditis caused by Enterococus faecalislocated on the prosthetic valve with insidious clinical signsand serious embolic events.We describe the clinical evolution. We compare the clinicalcharacteristics of infective endocarditis with some previousstudies in elderly patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canovas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un varón de 76 años, ingresado enel Servicio de Geriatría remitido desde su Centro de Saludpor presentar pérdida de peso acompañado de anorexia,astenia y dolor lumbar de un mes de evolución. Con laspruebas realizadas se llegó al diagnóstico de endocarditisbacteriana por Enterococcus faecalis subaguda sobreválvula protésica biológica con comienzo clínico insidioso,inespecífico y complicaciones embolígenas graves. Secomenta su evolución clínica. Se compara con las característicasclínicas y evolutivas de la endocarditis bacterianaen ancianos en la literatura</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;15(2): 92-96, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043428</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endocarditis: un diagnóstico difícil en el anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1255^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
