<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052276</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Confidentiality and privacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Secrecy has always been a part of patient care.    Already at the dawn of western medicine, not telling    others what the doctor might know about his patient    was considered a requirement of good practice. A    substantial change that has occurred in recent    decades is the transformation of secrecy into a    citizen&#146;s right. Recognition of the personal autonomy    of the patient forms the basis of his right to consent    to, or reject, the proposals of the health    professionals, and also to decide who can have    access to his personal data and what limits he    imposes on the handling of his body. Nonetheless,    the intimacy of patients frequently continues to be    violated, perhaps because we live in a society that    trivialises these questions, and the health milieu is    not immune to this way of thinking. Besides, the new    information technologies have added a new danger    by enormously facilitating access to personal data.    This article reviews the ethical and legal aspects of    this issue, the results of research carried out on the    way the professionals of eight Spanish hospitals deal    with confidentiality, and some recommendations are    outlined in an attempt to encourage reflection by the    professionals who interact in a scenario where the    patient is obliged to lay himself bare in body and    soul</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iraburu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El secreto siempre ha formado parte de la atención    al enfermo. Ya en los albores de la medicina occidental,    no decir a otros lo que el médico conociera de su    paciente era considerado una exigencia del buen hacer.    El cambio sustancial acaecido en las últimas décadas    es la transformación del secreto en un derecho ciudadano.    El reconocimiento a la autonomía personal del    paciente sustenta su derecho a consentir o rechazar    las propuestas de los profesionales de la salud y también    a decidir quién puede acceder a sus datos personales    y qué límites impone al manejo de su cuerpo. Sin    embargo, la intimidad de los pacientes sigue siendo    vulnerada con frecuencia quizás porque vivimos en    una sociedad que trivializa estas cuestiones y el ámbito    sanitario no es impermeable a esta manera de pensar.    Las nuevas tecnologías de la información han añadido,    además, un nuevo peligro facilitando enormemente    el acceso a los datos personales. En este artículo    se revisan los aspectos éticos y legales sobre este    tema, los resultados de una investigación llevada a    cabo sobre el modo en que los profesionales de ocho    hospitales españoles tratan la confidencialidad y se    esbozan algunas recomendaciones en un intento de    promover la reflexión de los profesionales que interactúan    en un escenario donde el paciente se ve obligado    a desnudarse en cuerpo y alma</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(supl.3): 49-59, sept.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Confidencialidad e intimidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32286^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
