<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99517</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morbo Cholera in Granada by documentation of the Royal Academy of Medicine and Surgery of Cadiz</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since its founding the Royal Academy of Medicine and Surgery of Cadiz has been managing as cientific relationship with Partners National Correspondents y foreign, arguably the greatest Spanish medical institution maintained exchanges with service providers in Europe and over seas during the nineteenth century. Study is presented in Granada cholera in different patients and different forms and signs, symptoms, and treatment regimen of life care, and followed; indicating the influence of weather on the Indian cholera. The author makes a statement as a comment on the various forms of cholera that have occurred in Granada, and provides a number of cases, when he was serving as attending physician and in turn was Corresponding Member of the Royal Academy of Medicine and Surgery of Cadiz. In this report we review the various drugs applied under all forms of anger that have been presented, among which includes birth hidrargirio vermifuge and sweet rhubarb(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Vega, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su fundación la Real Academia de Medicina y Cirugía de Cádiz estuvo manteniendo una relación científica con sus Socios Corresponsales nacionales y extranjeros, posiblemente sea la institución médica española que mayor intercambio mantuvo con los centros sanitarios de Europa y Ultramar durante el siglo XIX. Es el estudio de cólera morbo presentado en Granada en diferentes enfermos y bajo diferentes formas así como los signos, los síntomas y el tratamiento seguido terapéutico y régimen de vida seguido; indicando la influencia de la meteorología en el Cólera Morbo Indiano. El autor hace una exposición según una observación sobre las distintas formas del cólera morbo que se han presentado en Granada, y aporta una serie de casos, cuando él ocupaba el cargo de médico titular ya su vez era Académico Correspondiente de la Real Academia de Medicina y Cirugía de Cádiz. En esta memoria se hace una revisión de los diferentes medicamentos aplicados bajo de todas las formas de cólera que se han presentado, entre los que incluye píldoras vermífugas de ruibarbo e hidrargirio dulce(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 575-586, jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Cólera morbo en Granada según documentación de la Real Academia de Medicina y Cirugía de Cádiz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2821^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2821^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31567^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31567^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26607^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2821^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31567^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31567^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26607^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26607^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31567^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12659^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
