<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89015</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of early detection of breast cancer program (EDBCP) implanted at south cordoba health district</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Early Detection of Breast Cancer Program (EDBCP) was implanted at South Cordoba Health District by the end of 1999. The objective of this study is to evaluate the EDBCP in our health district over the last 4 rounds of the program. We calculated the participation rate (examined women/ target population), the inclusion rate (attended women/ target population)  and the hospital derivation rate in percentage, together with the detection rate (number of women diagnosed with malignant tumors x 10?/ number of women examined with mammograms) in our health district. The target population was 17058, 16421, 18.098 and 20478 for the 4 rounds respectively. The participation rates in our district were 73.9% (1st round), 77% (2nd round), 76.3% (3rd round) and 76.2% (4th round). The inclusion rates of the district were 82% (1st round), 78.8% (2nd  round), 78.2% (3rd round) and 77.9% (4th round). The hospital derivation rates of the district were 7.8% (1st round), 4.4% (2nd round), 6.3% (3rd round) and 6.57% (4th round). The detection rates of the district were 4.68 (1st round), 2.21 (2nd round), 2.97 (3rd round) and 2 (4th round). Since the EDBCP was implanted we have detected 162 malignant tumours, with global detection rate of 7.13 per 103 examined women. In conclusion, the EDBCP at South Cordoba Health District have obtained higher participation and inclusion rates than the target objective of the Andalusian Health Services. This has permitted the early diagnosis of 162 women with malignant tumours, which would improve the prognosis and the quality of life  of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero Lanzas, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Oteros, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Lana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farouk Allan, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Programa de Detección Precoz del Cáncer de Mama (PDPCM) se implantó en el Distrito Sanitario Córdoba Sur finales del año 1999. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar el PDPCM en nuestro distrito sanitario a lo largo de las primaras 4 ediciones del programa. Se calcularon las tasas de participación (mujeres exploradas/ población elegible), las tasas de captación (mujer que acuden/ población elegible) y las tasas de derivación hospitalaria en porcentaje, además de las tasas de detección  (numero de mujeres diagnosticados de tumor maligno x 10?/ numero de mujeres mamografiadas) en el nuestro distrito sanitario. La población elegible fue de 17.058, 16.421, 18.098 y 20.478 para las 4 ediciones, respectivamente. Las tasas de participación del Distrito fueron de 73,9% (1ª edición), 77% (2ª edición), 76,3% (3ª edición) y 76,2% (4ª edición). Las tasas de captación del Distrito fueron de 82% (1ª edición), 78,8% (2ª edición), 78,2% (3ª edición) y 77,9% (4ª edición). Las tasas  de derivación hospitalaria del Distrito fueron de 7,8% (1ª edición), 4,4% (2ª edición), 6,3% (3ª edición) y 6,57% (4ª edición). Las tasas de detección del Distrito fueron de 4,68 (1ª edición), 2,21 (2ª edición), 2,97 (3º edición) y 2 (4ª edición). Desde que comenzó el PDPCM se han detectado 162 tumores malignos con una tasa de detección global del 7,13 por 103 mujeres mamografiadas. En conclusión, el PDPCM en el Distrito Sanitario Córdoba Sur ha obtenido unas tasas de participación y  de captación más altas de las marcadas por la Conserjería de Salud de Andalucía. Esto ha permitido el diagnóstico temprano de 162 mujeres con tumores malignos, lo que su pone una mejora en el pronostico y la calidad de vida de las pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;12(4): 153-156, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del programa de detección precoz del cáncer de mama en el distrito sanitario córdoba sur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
