<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83347</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of renin in chromophobe renal cell carcinomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate frequency of renin detection in chromophobe renal cell carcinoma, and if this expression was associated to systemic high blood pressure. Material and methods: A descriptive retrospective study. All the cases with confirmed diagnosis of chromophobe carcinoma and resected between 1990 and 2004 were included in our study: 31 cases from 31 patients. Immunohistochemistry was carried out on sections from the paraffin-embedded tissue using a monoclonal antiserum. Patient blood pressure before and after neoplasm resection was registered from clinical histories. We compared frequencies of hypertension in cases with and without expression of renin (Fisher´s text or &amp;#967;2 as appropriate) and evolution of HTA after tumour resection. Results: We found that 10 of 31 tumors (32.3%) contained immunoreactivity for renin; this staining was diffuse in 6 cases and focal in the other 4. Systemic hypertension was detected in 6 of 10 (60.0%) patients with renin expression and in 6 of 21 (28.6%) patients without renin immunolabeling (p=0.13). After tumor resection none patient with renin expression and high blood pressure showed remission of the hypertension. Conclusion: Renin is frequently expressed in chromophobe renal cell carcinoma, but this renin appears clinically inactive. More studies will be necessary to know implications of this feature on clinical presentation, diagnosis or pathogenesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruneval, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la expresión de renina en carcinomas cromófobos de células renales y la posible asociación de esta expresión con hipertensión arterial (HTA) sistémica. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo. Se incluyeron todos los casos con diagnóstico confirmado de carcinoma cromófobo entre 1990-2004: 31 casos provenientes de 31 pacientes. De los bloques de tejido tumoral incluidos en parafina se hizo inmunohistoquímica para detectar renina usando un anticuerpo monoclonal. De los archivos de historias clínicas obtuvimos información completa con respecto a la presión arterial sistémica antes y después de la resección tumoral. Comparamos frecuencias de HTA en casos con y sin expresión de renina (prueba de Fisher o &amp;#967;2, según lo adecuado) y evolución de la HTA posresección. Resultados: En 10 de los 31 tumores (32,3%) hubo inmunotinción para renina; esta tinción fue difusa en 6 casos y focal en los 4 restantes. Se detectó HTA en 6 de los 10 pacientes con expresión de renina (60,0%) y en 6 de los 21 pacientes sin expresión de renina (28,6%) (p=0,13). Después de la resección tumoral, ningún paciente con expresión de renina e HTA mostró remisión de la hipertensión. Conclusión: En el carcinoma cromófobo de células renales es frecuente la expresión de renina, pero esta renina parece clínicamente inactiva. Serán necesarios más estudios para conocer las implicaciones en el diagnóstico, la patogénesis y la presentación clínica de esta expresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(8): 694-698, sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de renina en carcinomas cromófobos de células renales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29553^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
