<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85741</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Female sexuality during menopause. Representations, symbols and stereotypes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to offer women in today&#146;s society health educationthat is in tune with their needs it is necessary to understandthe meaning of sexuality during menopause. With this objectivein mind, a bibliographic review was performed thataimed specifically to identify the physiological and socialcharacteristics of menopause and sexuality and to analyse theinfluence of cultural representations on the female experienceof sexuality during that life phase.Methodology: Cuiden, SciELO-España and Enfispo wereselected as the primary databases, and a historic review ofstudies published within the last fifteen years (1994 to 2009)was conducted. The most recent international studies onthe topic (2007 to 2009), extracted from the Cochrane Plus,Doaj, Cinahl and Medline databases, were also reviewed.Results: vasomotor symptoms, bone and joint pain, depression,anxiety and dyspareunia are the most frequentsymptoms. The presence, intensity and subjective experienceof these symptoms are culturally influenced. The anatomical-physiological changes that take place during menopauseproduce a change in the sexuality pattern that isinfluenced by each woman&#146;s cultural schemes, sometimesleading to important health problems.Health care demand on the part of the female population duringmenopause has increased significantly in the past fewyears, as a result of the lack of information they have onthis stage of life and the physical changes it entails. Sexualitystereotypes that lead to unhealthy practices, anxiety andfear are very frequent. Health education decreases the perceptionof the problems perceived by women undergoing menopause (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Casado, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Comprender el significado que tiene la sexualidad en el climateriopara las mujeres de la sociedad actual es necesariopara ofertar una educación sanitaria acorde a sus necesidades.Con ese propósito se realizó una revisión bibliográfica cuyosobjetivos concretos fueron identificar las características fisiológicasy sociales del climaterio y de la sexualidad y analizarla influencia de las representaciones culturales en la vivenciade la sexualidad femenina en esa etapa del desarrollo.Metodología: se eligieron Cuiden, SciELO-España y Enfispocomo principales bases de datos, realizando una revisiónhistórica de los estudios publicados en los últimos quinceaños (1994 hasta 2009). Del ámbito internacional se revisaronlos estudios más recientes del tema en cuestión de lasbases de datos Cochrane Plus, Doaj, Cinahl y Medline (2007hasta 2009).Resultados: son frecuentes los síntomas vasomotores, eldolor osteoarticular, la depresión, la ansiedad y la dispareunia.La presencia, intensidad y vivencia de los mismos tieneinfluencia cultural. Las modificaciones anatomofisiológicas delclimaterio producen un cambio en el patrón sexual que estáinfluenciado por los esquemas culturales de cada mujer, desembocandoen algunos casos en problemas de salud importantes.La demanda sanitaria de la población femenina durante elclimaterio ha sufrido un importante incremento en los últimosaños, relacionado con el desconocimiento que refierenlas mujeres sobre este período. Son muy habituales los estereotiposacerca de la sexualidad que conducen a prácticaspoco saludables, ansiedad y miedo. La educación sanitariadisminuye la percepción de los problemas percibidospor la mujer durante el climaterio.Conclusiones: una buena autoestima y una correcta educaciónsanitaria en esta etapa permitirán a la mujer cuidar suentorno afectivo y disfrutar de su sexualidad de una maneraglobal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(3): 50-55, abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85741</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sexualidad femenina durante el climaterio. Representaciones, símbolos y estereotipos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22129^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
