<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94791</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The beginnigs of neurosciencie in spain "Neural Circulation" in the work of the illustrious novator Martín Martínez (1684-1734)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. During the &#145;scientific revolution&#146; that took place in the 18th century, a complex and poorly completed theory on the functioning of the nervous system, neural circulation, was to draw the attention of the European vanguards and, although it came up against a number of important obstacles, it also attempted to renew the traditional gallenic knowledge that had prevailed until then. In Spain, the field of medical knowledge was to flourish and the neurosciences presented their credentials with the introduction and development of the concept of neural circulation by the novator Martín Martínez. Development. This work attempts to evoke that historic time and to summarise the elements that go to make up the neural or &#145;spirituous&#146; circulation, as well as reviewing the figure of Martín Martínez. Conclusions. Neural circulation was a speculative theoretical deviation that tried, unsuccessfully, to offer a better explanation for empirical facts. In Spain, led by Martín Martínez, it was at least an attempt to modernise thinking by introducing the new ideas about neurological anatomy that were going round Europe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Albea Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Albea Riston, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. Durante la &#145;revolución científica&#146; del siglo XVIII, una teoría compleja y mal clausurada sobre el funcionamiento del sistema nervioso, la circulación neural, ocupará a las vanguardias europeas y tratará de renovar, no sin dificultades, los tradicionales conocimientos galénicos vigentes hasta entonces. En España se producirá un importante florecimiento de los conocimientos médicos y las neurociencias recibirán su bautizo con la introducción y el desarrollo del concepto  de circulación neural por el novator Martín Martínez. Desarrollo. Este trabajo trata de evocar ese momento histórico y sumariar los elementos que constituyen la circulación neural o &#145;espirituosa&#146;, así como la figura de Martín Martínez. Conclusiones. La circulación neural supuso una desviación teórica especulativa que intentó &#150;sin lograrlo&#150; explicar mejor los hechos empíricos. En España, en manos de Martín Martínez, supuso al menos un intento de modernización con las nuevas ideas anatómicas neurológicas que circulaban por Europa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(2): 95-99, jul. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los albores de la neurociencia en España. La &#145;circulación neural&#146; en la obra del novator ilustrado Martín Martínez (1684-1734)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
