<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99536</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of body parameters of an obese population under a nutritional intervetion with hipocaloric diet and nutritional</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Factors such as physical activity, beyond calories diet and lack of nutrition education can be modified in order to improve the prognosis of obesity and associated comorbidities. Material and method: 20 subjects with over weight or obesity (BMI &gt; 25kg/m2), aged between 28 and 62. The intervention lasted 8 weeks, following an intervention healthy nutrition intervention and physicalactivity. To evaluate the changes, weight, BMI, waste and hip sizes and percentages of fat and muscle mass were measured. Statistical analysis was performed through SPSS 15.0 statistical package. After verifying the normality of variables, paired samples T-test was made for comparison between pre-test and post-test.                                                          Results: The results showed statistically significant declines for the parameters weight (90.99 ± 17.27 to 82.69 ± 9.16), fat percentage (37.28 ± 5.97 to 33.73 ± 6.69), BMI (from 30.81 ± 5.92 to 27.98 ± 5.6), waist diameters (101.8 ± 16.5 to 95.23 ± 14.12) and hip(98.83 ± 14.11 to 95.7 ± 1358). The percentage of muscle mass parameter shows a statistically significant rise after intervention.                                     Conclusion: we can say that physical and nutrition interventions can help prevent diseases such as obesity and disorders arising therefrom(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliveras López, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo Aponte, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalón Mir, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muros Molina, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-García de la Serrana, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Factores como la actividad física, el exceso de calorías de la dieta y la falta de educación nutricional pueden modificarse con el objeto de mejorar el pronóstico de la obesidad y comorbilidades asociadas.                        Material y método: Participaron 20 sujetos con sobrepeso u obesidad (IMC &gt; 25kg/m2) con edades comprendidas entre los 28 y 62 años. La intervención tuvo una duración de 8 semanas, y consistió en una intervención nutricional y física saludable. Para evaluar los cambios producidos tras la intervención se realizaron mediciones de peso, IMC, diámetros de cintura y cadera y porcentajes de grasa y masa muscular. Los análisis estadísticos se realizaron a través del paquete estadístico SPSS 15.0. Se realizó la prueba T de muestras apareadas para la comparación entre pre-test y post-test.                                  Resultados y conclusiones: Los resultados muestran descensos estadísticamente significativos para los parámetros peso (de 90,99 ± 17,27 a 82,69 ± 16,09), porcentaje graso (de 37,28 ± 5,97 a 33,73 ± 6,69), IMC (de 30,81 ± 5,92 a 27.98 ± 5,6), diámetros de cintura de (101,8 ± 16,5 a 95,23 ± 14,12) y cadera de (98,83 ± 14,11 a 95,7 ± 13,58). El parámetro porcentaje de masa muscular muestra un ascenso estadísticamente significativo tras la intervención.                                           Conclusión: Podemos afirmar que intervenciones nutricionales y físicas pueden ayudar a prevenir enfermedades como la obesidad y patologías derivadas de la misma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 823-827, jul. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99536</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de los parámetros corporales de una población de obesos sometidos a una intervención con dieta hipocalórica y educación nutricional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
