<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105502</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish consensus on the use of natalizumab (Tysabri ®) - 2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Natalizumab is very effective at reducing relapses and delaying disease progression in patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (RRMS). However, treatment has also been associated with a risk of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML). The aim of this article is to provide a consensus view on the assessment and stratification of these risks, and to improve the management of natalizumab-treated patients.Development: At an initial meeting of experts on multiple sclerosis (the authors of this consensus), the relevant topics of the consensus were determined and assigned for further elaboration. Topics included how to establish benefit and risk in general, stratification for risk of PML, informing patients of benefits/risks, and how to monitor patients during treatment and after discontinuing treatment. During the drafting phase, all available information published or presented at international meetings was reviewed. After a series of review sessions and meetings, the final draft was produced. Conclusions: Although natalizumab is a very effective drug, its use needs to be considered carefully in view of possible adverse effects and the risk of PML in particular. The neurologist should carefully explain the risks and benefits of treatment in terms the patient can best understand. Before starting treatment, baseline laboratory tests and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) should be available for future comparisons in the event of suspected PML. The risk of PML should be stratified into high, medium and low risk groups according to presence or absence of anti-JC virus antibodies, prior immunosuppressive therapy, and treatment duration. The follow-up, and frequency of MRI scans in particular, should depend on the risk group to which patient belongs. As our understanding of the risk factors for PML develops, it should be possible to offer patients increasingly individualised therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja-Guevara, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalbán, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Antigüedad, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Cermeño, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbizu, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Merino, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olascoaga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Natalizumab es un tratamiento que ha demostrado ser muy eficaz en los pacientes con esclerosis múltiple recurrente-remitente (EMRR) en cuanto a la reducción del número de brotes y al enlentecimiento de la progresión de la enfermedad. Sin embargo, el fármaco se ha asociado con el riesgo de desarrollar leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva (LMP). El objetivo de este artículo es proporcionar una posición consensuada sobre la valoración y estratificación de este riesgo y mejorar el manejo de los pacientes tratados con natalizumab.Desarrollo: En una reunión inicial de expertos en EM (los autores de este consenso), se perfilaron los temas de interés que fueron asignados a los asistentes para su desarrollo ulterior. Los temas incluían cómo establecer el beneficio y el riesgo en general, la estratificación para el riesgo de LMP, cómo informar a los pacientes de los beneficios y riesgos, cómo realizar el seguimiento del paciente en tratamiento y tras la suspensión del fármaco. Durante la fase de redacción, se revisó toda la información disponible, publicada o presentada en reuniones internacionales. Después de varios ciclos de revisión y de reuniones, se produjo el borrador final.Conclusiones: A pesar de ser un fármaco muy eficaz, la decisión de prescribir natalizumab debe ser tomada con cuidado por los posibles efectos adversos y en particular, el riesgo de LMP. El neurólogo debe explicar al paciente en detalle los riesgos y beneficios del tratamiento, en términos comprensibles para el paciente. Antes de empezar el tratamiento, deben estar disponibles las pruebas de laboratorio y las imágenes de resonancia magnética (RM) que permitan comparaciones en el futuro, en caso de sospecha de LMP. El riesgo de LMP debe estratificarse en alto, medio y bajo de acuerdo con la presencia o ausencia de anticuerpos frente al virus JC, antecedente de tratamiento inmunosupresor y duración del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(7): 432-441, sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105502</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso español sobre la utilización de natalizumab (Tysabri ®) - 2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
