<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87509</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Compare surface microhardness of different commercial silver amalgams with different powder morphology and to determine the influence of the powder metal elements and the percentage of residual mercury on the said parameter. Methods: 28 encapsulated commercial lathe cut, spherical, admixed and hybrid alloys for silver amalgam were subjected to microhardnesstests. Samples for each material were prepared according to the ISO1559:1995 specification, 9 Vickers indentations were made on the surface of a 600 x 600 &amp;#956;m matrix at 1h, 3h, 24h, 7 days, 15 days and 30 days. Ray fluorescence X (RFX) were used to determine the weight percentage of Ag, Sn, Cu, Zn. Results: Anova and Tukey test were used. Up to 24 h., spherical and hybrid alloys showed a significantly greater micro hardness (p&gt;0.000)than the other morphologies. Nevertheless, lathe cut, spherical and hybrid showed a similar behaviour at 30 days. Lathe cut showed a significantly lower silver content but higher Cu and Hg than the other alloys (p&gt;0.001), whilst the admixed showed a significantly lower Sncontent (p&gt;0.001). The results showed that Cu and Sn exercised apositive influence on micro hardness, Ag a negative influence whilst the residual Hg almost nothing. Significance: In recent years, there has been a tendency towards short-term hardening as mechanical protection because this prevents premature fracturing of the restoration facilitating fast removal of the matrix band, but reduces the manipulation time therefore difficultiesin condensation, porosity and lamination might arise. At this moment in time, the influence of microhardness on restoration survival is unknown, however, it might prove valuable if a significant correlation can be found between this property and clinical performance (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler, José I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ruiz, Inma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lartitegi, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Baciero, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ellacuría, Joseba</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El artículo pretende comparar la microdureza superficial de diferentes amalgamas comerciales con polvo metálico de morfología diferente al objeto de determinar la influencia que el contenido de los diferentes elementos metálicos del polvo y el contenido en mercurio residual presente en la aleación fraguada ejercen sobre el citado parámetro. Material y métodos: Un total de 28 aleaciones comerciales para amalgama de plata dispensadas en forma de cápsulas fueron sometidas a ensayos de microdureza superficial. Probetas de cada material fueron preparadas de acuerdo a la Especificación ISO 1559:1995y sobre la superficie de las mismas se realizaron 9 indentaciones Vickers abarcando una matriz de 600 x 600 &amp;#956;m a 1 hora, 3 horas,24 horas, 7, 15 y 30 días. Muestras del polvo fueron sometidas a Fluorescencia de Rayos X (RFX) para determinar el porcentaje en peso de Ag, Sn, Cu y Zn. A su vez probetas de material preparadas según especificación ISO fueron pesadas previamente y posteriormente sometidas a 600º C en un horno durante 3 horas, de acuerdo con las indicaciones obtenidas en un ensayo termo gravimétrico previo, para determinar el porcentaje en peso de Hg residual. Resultados: Se usó contraste estadístico mediante Anova y test de Tukey. Hasta las 24 h. las aleaciones esféricas e híbridas mostraron una microdureza significativamente mayor (p&gt;0.000) que el resto de las morfologías. No obstante, las limallas esféricas e híbridas mostraron una microdureza similar a los 30 días. A su vez, las limallas mostraron un contenido significativamente menor en plata y mayor en cobre y en mercurio residual que el resto de las aleaciones (p&lt;0.001), (..)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);5(4): 127-135, oct.-dic. 2005. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la microdureza superficial de 28 aleaciones comerciales para amalgama de plata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3735^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
