<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89568</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Kingella kingae infections in the pediatric age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Kingella kingae infections have aroused great interest in the last few years because of the increasing number of identified cases. Although considered an emerging pathogen, the increase in diagnosis of these infections can probably be explained by better knowledge of the bacteria, improved microbiological diagnostic techniques and greater awareness among clinicians. K. kingae is an aerobic cocobacillus with high tropism for osteoarticular tissue, endocardium, and vascular space. This pathogen mainly produces osteomyelitis, endocarditis, septic arthritis and bacteriemias. First choice antibiotics are penicillins and cephalosporins. This article reviews the literature on this microorganism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silveira, Laura Fernández</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Ana Ortí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tamarit, M. Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Policarpo, Sergio Negre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durántez, María Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Reigada, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones por Kingella kingae han despertado recientemente un importante interés debido al mayor número de casos identificados. Aunque se considera un patógeno emergente, probablemente el mejor conocimiento de la bacteria, las mejores técnicas para el diagnóstico microbiológico y una mayor concienciación de los clínicos frente a este microorganismo justifican este aumento de casos descritos. K. kingae es un cocobacilo aerobio gramnegativo que presenta especial tropismo por el tejido osteoarticular, endocardio y espacio vascular. Las infecciones descritas con mayor frecuencia son osteomielitis, artritis séptica, endocarditis y bacteriemia. Los antimicrobianos de elección son penicilinas y cefalosporinas. Se revisa en este artículo la bibliografía relacionada con este microorganismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(supl.3): 29-32, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones por Kingella kingae en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31372^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29937^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7760^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
