<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95010</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial functioning and psychological interventions in pediatric cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this article is to offer a global and updated view of the results obtained from the two main investigation paths concerning pediatric psycho-oncology for the last years: child´s psychological adjustment to the disease and its treatment and the effectiveness of psychological interventions. Regarding the first subject, the results clearly show that children adapt especially well to cancer-related circumstances. Regarding the second subject, it can be said that the psychological methods used to reduce procedural related pain and distress are widely supported by evidence; however, it is distraction and breathing techniques that offer the best cost-effectiveness ratio and are easier to implement in health services. Lastly, evidence shows that psychological strategies used in other areas (psychological support for the family when facing the diagnosis or black to school programmes for children) are not as conclusive as there are less controlled studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bragado, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se ofrece una visión general y actualizada sobre los resultados obtenidos en dos líneas de investigación que concitan el interés de la psico-oncología pediátrica de los últimos años: el ajuste psicológico de los niños a la enfermedad y sus tratamientos y la eficacia de las intervenciones psicológicas. Respecto al primer punto, los datos revelan de forma concluyente que globalmente considerados los niños se adaptan especialmente bien a las circunstancias que rodean al cáncer. En cuanto al segundo, se puede afirmar en que los métodos psicológicos empleados para minimizar el dolor y el malestar asociado a los procedimientos médicos invasivos gozan de buen refrendo empírico, aunque la distracción y los ejercicios de respiración muestran la mejor relación coste-beneficio y son fáciles de implementar en el contexto hospitalario. La evidencia disponible para las estrategias psicológicas utilizadas en otras áreas de intervención (apoyo psicológico a la familia para afrontar el estrés del diagnostico, programas dirigidos a facilitar la reincorporación al colegio) son menos concluyentes porque existen pocos estudios controlados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);6(2/3): 327-341, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funcionamiento psicosocial e intervenciones psicológicas en niños con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
