<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156905</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Increased lipoprotein(a) in a paediatric patient associated with nephrotic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A common complication in paediatric patients with nephrotic syndrome (NS) is hyperlipidaemia. About 20% of children do not respond to treatment with corticosteroids, presenting with a cortico-resistant NS (CRNS), which can progress to kidney failure. It has been observed that paediatric patients with CRNS have an elevated low density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-c), very low density lipoprotein cholesterol (VLDL-c), and triglycerides levels, as well as elevated Lipoprotein-a [Lp (a)] levels. The case is presented of a 5 year old boy, diagnosed with CRNS, presenting with dyslipidaemia with increased LDL-c, Apo-B100, and Lp(a) levels. After the poor prognosis of the renal function, immunosuppressant treatment was started with tacrolimus and atorvastatin to control dyslipidaemia. Although tacrolimus causes an elevation of total cholesterol and LDL-c, the significant alterations of the children lipid profile suggest the existence of a high cardiovascular risk. In these cases, it would be interesting to have reference values in children in our health area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fabiani Romero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Pérez, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Valladares, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez de la Vega, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrobas Velilla, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una complicación común en los pacientes pediátricos con síndrome nefrótico (SN) es la hiperlipidemia. Alrededor del 20% de los niños no responden al tratamiento con corticoides, presentando un SN corticorresistente (SNCR), que puede evolucionar a insuficiencia renal. Se ha observado que los pacientes pediátricos con SNCR cursan con incremento de c-LDL, c-VLDL y triglicéridos, y presentan niveles elevados de lipoproteína (a) [Lp(a)]. Presentamos el caso de un niño de 5 años con diagnóstico de SNCR y dislipemia, con niveles incrementados de c-LDL, apo B100 y Lp(a). Tras el mal pronóstico de la función renal, se inicia tratamiento inmunosupresor con tacrolimus y con atorvastatina para controlar la dislipemia. A pesar de que el tacrolimus produce una elevación del colesterol total y c-LDL, las notables alteraciones del perfil lipídico del niño sugieren la existencia de un riesgo cardiovascular elevado. En estos casos sería interesante disponer de valores de referencia en edades pediátricas para nuestra área sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(5): 227-229, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156905</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incremento de lipoproteína(a) en paciente pediátrico asociado a síndrome nefrótico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8249^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52261^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9596^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52274^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
