<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134607</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disseminated bone metastases from occult thyroid cancer effectively treated with debulking surgery and a single dosimetry-guided administration of radioiodine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper we report on a successful management of multiple bone metastases from differentiated thyroid cancer. In 2007, a 75-year-old female patient, previously referred for thyroidectomy for multinodular goiter, underwent surgical removal of a lumbar mass with histological findings of metastasis from well differentiated thyroid cancer. After surgery, serum thyroglobulin (sTg) was 204.4 ng/mL. A diagnostic/dosimetric 123 I WBS was performed, following stimulation by rTSH. Serial WBSs were acquired, along with SPECT/CT and bone scan for localization of lesions. sTg raised to 3.810 ng/mL, and 123 I WBS showed thyroid remnants and numerous areas with high iodine-uptake corresponding to skeletal sites, the two largest loading on the skull, with osteolytic pattern. Calculated radiation absorbed dose for skull lesions, determined by mean of MIRD methodology, was 63.5 mGy/MBq. The patient underwent surgical removal of the two major skull lesions. Successively, 100mCi 131I was administered after stimulation by rTSH, with stimulated sTg 297 ng/mL. After 8 months, diagnostic WBS was negative both for remnants and metastases and rTSH-stimulated Tg was 0.6 ng/mL. To date, the patient has maintained sTg values &lt;1 ng/mL during L-T4 suppressive therapy and after rTSH stimulations. In this unusual case of extensive bone cancerous involvement with high iodine avidity, a multidisci-plinary approach based on surgery and dosimetry-guided radiometabolic therapy allowed to accurately assess the patient, execute a small number of treatments and achieve a complete remission of the disease in a very short time, with no additive morbidity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Scatena, Cristian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boni, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzola, Maria Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borsò, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grosso, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Traino, Antonio C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazzarri, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubello, Domenico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortenzi, Valerio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cocciaro, Ardico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manca, Giampiero</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gambacciani, Carlo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariani, Giuliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vannozzi, Riccardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo presentamos el abordaje adecuado de múltiples metástasis óseas de un cáncer diferenciado de tiroides. En 2007, una mujer de 75 años previamente remitida para tiroidectomía por bocio multinodular, se sometió a la extirpación quirúrgica de una masa lumbar con resultado histológico de metástasis de cáncer bien diferenciado de tiroides. Tras la cirugía, los niveles séricos de tiroglobulina (Tgs) fueron 204,4 ng/ml. Se realizó un rastreo de cuerpo completo diagnóstico/dosimétrico con 123 I después de la estimulación con rTSH. Se adquirieron rastreos seriados junto con SPECT/TC y gammagrafía ósea para la localización de las lesiones. Los niveles de Tgs se elevaron a 3810 ng/ml, y el rastreo de cuerpo completo con 123 I demostró captación en restos tiroideos y en numerosas localizaciones esqueléticas, las dos de mayor tamaño en la calota con un patrón osteolítico. La dosis absorbida calculada para las lesiones de calota, determinada mediante metodología MIRD, fue 63,5 mGy/MBq. Se extirparon mediante cirugía las 2 lesiones de la calota. Posteriormente, se administraron 100 mCi 131 I tras la estimulación con rTSH y unos niveles de Tgs 297 ng/ml. Después de 8 meses, el rastreo diagnóstico de cuerpo completo fue negativo tanto para los restos tiroideos como para las metástasis y la Tgs estimulada con rTSH fue 0,6 ng/ml. En la actualidad, la paciente ha mantenido valores de Tgs &lt;1 ng/ml durante la terapia supresora con T4L y después de la estimulación con rTSH. En este caso poco habitual de extensa afectación metastásica ósea con elevada captación de radioiodo, una estrategia multidisciplinaria basada en cirugía y radioterapia metabólica según dosimetría permitió evaluar con precisión a la paciente, administrar un número pequen &amp;#771;o de tratamientos y alcanzar una remisión completa de la enfermedad en muy breve tiempo, sin originar morbilidad adicional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);34(2): 111-115, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134607</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis óseas diseminadas de un carcinoma de tiroides oculto tratado efectivamente con cirugía citorreductora y administración simple de radioyodo rastreado con dosimetría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54697^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13269^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
