<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048187</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of hypertension in elderly patients intaked of internal medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To investigate hypertension control in elderly patients. To identify the cardiovascular risk factors and cardiovascular diseases associated with poor control of hypertension. To evaluate the pharmacologic treatment needed for the good control of hypertension. To analyse the existence of date in the medical history to evaluate the cardiovascular risk.                 Methods: A coss-sectional study of elderly hypertensive patients intaked between 1 to January 2002 to 31 December 2002 in a Internal Medicine Service. Blood pressure was measured in the standard manner. Blood pressure control was regarded as optimum if pressure averaged less than 140/90 mmHg or, in diabetics, less than 130/80 mmHg.                 Results: The study included 484 hipertensive patients. In the hypertensive patients, both systolic and diastolic blood pressures were well controlled in 53.9% of patients, systolic blood pressure alone in 2,1% and diastolic blood pressure alone in 30.8%. The isolated systolic arterial hypertension prevalence is bigger in the group with poor control, p &lt; 0.001. The 77% of hypertensive patients associated other cardiovascular risk factor, and the 69% associated any cardiovascular disease. The 64% of hypertensive patients needed pharmacologic treatment.                 Conclusions: Arterial blood pressure control was optimum in only one out of two hypertensive patients. Diabetes is the most influential variable in poor control. The diuretics are the active ingredients more used in the hypertension therapeutic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cinza Sanjurjo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Pol, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Zúñiga, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabarcos Ortiz de Barrón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer el grado de control de la presión arterial (PA) en los pacientes hipertensos mayores de 65 años que ingresaron en un servicio de Medicina Interna a lo largo del año 2002. Identificar los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y las patologías cardiovasculares asociadas al mal control de la presión arterial. Valorar el tratamiento farmacológico necesario para un adecuado control de la hipertensión arterial. Analizar la existencia de datos suficientes en la historia clínica que permitan una adecuada valoración del riesgo cardiovascular.                 Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal, en el que se incluyeron los pacientes mayores de 65 años que fueron ingresados, a lo largo del año 2002, en el Servicio de Medicina Interna del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Santiago de Compostela. La PA se midió siguiendo normas estandarizadas y se consideró que había un buen control si eran los valores &lt;140/90 mmHg (en pacientes diabéticos &lt; 130/80).                 Resultados: Se incluyeron 484 pacientes hipertensos, de los que el 53,9% presentaban buen control de presión arterial sistólica (PAS) y diastólica (PAD), el 2,1% sólo de PAS y el 30,8% sólo de PAD. El 77% de los hipertensos presentan asociado otro factor de riesgo cardiovascular, y el 69% asocian alguna patología cardiovascular. La probabilidad de presentar mal control de HTA en pacientes diabéticos es 1,45 veces mayor que en los no diabéticos. En el momento del alta, el 64% de los pacientes hipertensos precisaron tratamiento farmacológico para el control de la HTA.                 Conclusiones: Sólo la mitad de los pacientes hipertensos mayores de 65 años están correctamente controlados. La diabetes es la variable que más influye en el mal control de la PA. Los diuréticos son los fármacos más empleados para el control farmacológico de la HTA</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(8): 369-373, ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grado de control de hipertensión arterial en población mayor de 65 años ingresada en un servicio de Medicina Interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4294^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
