<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168009</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Appendicitis versus nonspecific acute abdominal pain: diagnostic accuracy of ultrasound</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. The aim of this study is to assess the diagnostic accuracy of ultrasound to differentiate appendicitis from nonspecific acute abdominal pain, that is the most common process requiring differential diagnosis in clinical practice. Material and methods. Patients admitted for suspicion of appendicitis were prospectively evaluated in our hospital during two years (2013-2014). Cases of nonspecific acute abdominal pain and appendicitis assessed by ultrasound were enrolled in the study. The different variables collected were statistically analyzed by descriptive, univariate and diagnostic accuracy studies. Results. A total of 275 patients were studied, 143 cases of nonspecific acute abdominal pain and 132 cases of appendicitis. Ultrasound sensitivity and specificity to differentiate appendicitis were 94.7% and 87.4% respectively, with a 12.6% rate of false positives and a 5.3% rate of false negatives. The rate of false negatives in perforated group was 17.4% and analysis according to Pediatric Appendicitis Score risk groups showed a 12.2% rate of false positives in low-risk group and a 6.3% rate of false negatives in high-risk group. Conclusions. The use of ultrasound in low clinical probability cases of appendicitis could rise unnecessary surgery rate, due to the significant number of false positives in this group of patients. In high probability clinical cases, ultrasound does not contribute too much to diagnosis and it could be a confusion factor by the significant number of false negative associated to perforated appendicitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Veiras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lorenzo, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Saavedra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Eire, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada Arias, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Barreira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo del estudio es evaluar el rendimiento diagnóstico de la ecografía para diferenciar la apendicitis del dolor abdominal agudo inespecífico, principal proceso con el que requiere diagnóstico diferencial en la práctica clínica. Material y métodos. Se evaluaron los pacientes atendidos por sospecha de apendicitis en nuestro centro durante 2 años (2013-2014), incorporando al estudio los casos de dolor abdominal agudo inespecífico y apendicitis en los que se realizó ecografía. Las diferentes variables recogidas se analizaron estadísticamente de manera descriptiva, univariante y con estudios de rendimiento diagnóstico.    Resultados. Se estudiaron 275 casos; 143 casos de dolor abdominal agudo inespecífico y 132 casos de apendicitis. La sensibilidad y especificidad de la ecografía para diferenciar apendicitis fue del 94,7% y 87,4%, respectivamente, con un porcentaje de falsos positivos del 12,6% y de falsos negativos del 5,3%. El porcentaje de falsos negativos en el grupo de apendicitis perforada alcanzó el 17,4% y el análisis según los grupos de riesgo establecidos por el Pediatric Appendicitis Score mostró un porcentaje de falsos positivos del 12,2% en el grupo de bajo riesgo y de falsos negativos del 6,3% en el grupo de alto riesgo. Conclusiones. El uso de la ecografía en casos de baja probabilidad clínica de apendicitis podría incrementar la tasa de cirugía innecesaria, debido al significativo número de falsos positivos en este grupo de pacientes. En casos de alta probabilidad clínica de apendicitis, la ecografía aporta poco al diagnóstico, e incluso podría ser un factor de confusión por el significativo número de falsos negativos asociados a la apendicitis perforada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(3): 146-151, jul. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apendicitis versus dolor abdominal agudo inespecífico: rendimiento diagnóstico de la ecografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10666^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10361^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
