<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97786</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive reserve and planning deficit in patients with multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiple sclerosis affects the nervous system causing cognitive impairment. Memory is one of the most affected, notwithstanding the nature or primary factor of disturbance is not yet clarified. Objective: To study the differences in verbal information processing in a group of this neurological pathology patients compared to healthy control group. To do this we examined the neuropsychological performance of 16 patients with multiple sclerosis relapsing-remitting type and a control group. The two groups were administered the Verbal Learning Test Spain-Complutense and a comparison between various test indices in both groups, and an analysis of correlation between socio-demographic variables in the experimental group to identify a protective factor. Results: Multiple sclerosis group obtained lower scores on indices analyzed with respect to control, as well as positive correlation between years of schooling and the onset of the disease and between the onset of the disease and occupation. The data found suggest that multiple sclerosis patients have little ability to plan, which directly affects their performance in learning and memory tasks(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Judith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mestas, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esclerosis múltiple afecta el sistema nervioso produciendo alteraciones cognitivas. La memoria es uno de los más afectados, no obstante la naturaleza ó factor primario de alteración aún no se clarifica. Objetivo: Estudiar las diferencias en el procesamiento de la información verbal en un grupo de pacientes con esta patología neurológica respecto a un grupo de control sano. Para ello se analizó el desempeño neuropsicológico de 16 pacientes con esclerosis múltiple de tipo remitente-recurrente y un grupo de control equiparado en las variables sociodemográficas. A los dos grupos se les aplicó el Test de Aprendizaje Verbal España-Complutense, y se realizó una comparación entre diversos índices de la prueba, además de un análisis de correlaciones entre las variables socio-demográficas del grupo experimental para identificar algún factor protector. Resultados: el grupo de esclerosis múltiple obtuvo rendimientos inferiores en los índices analizados respecto al de control, además de una correlación positiva entre años de escolaridad y el inicio de la enfermedad y entre el inicio de la enfermedad y la ocupación. Los datos encontrados parecen indicar que los pacientes con esclerosis múltiple tienen poca capacidad de planificación, que incide de manera directa en su desempeño en tareas de memoria y aprendizaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;32(113): 55-65, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reserva cognitiva y déficit en la planificación en pacientes con esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
