<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148232</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aplicability of Zenith p-branch(R) standard fenestrated endograft</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the endovascular treatment of abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAA) with short or absent infrarenal neck, the delay in the availability of a fenestrated device and its high cost, has led to the manufacture of standardised models. Although there are no regulated criteria for their use and long-term studies are lacking, another option is the endograft with stents in parallel. Objective: The AAA treated with fenestrated device or stents in parallel in our department were assessed to see whether they complied with the characteristics for the placement of the new p-branch® endograft, and to analyse the differences between the p-branch® and the implanted prosthesis. Material and methods: A descriptive study was performed on 31 aneurysms treated consecutively from 2008-2013. The anatomical characteristics analysed were: relative distances between the visceral arteries, &#147;o&#146;clock&#148; position, diameter in the sealing area and number of fenestrations, and its compatibility with the p-branch®. Results: The anatomical compatibility rate with the p-branch® options was 74.2% (23 cases). Of the 8 incompatible cases, 5 were due to misalignment of the visceral branches, one to the aortic neck diameter being greater, another because the femoral access was inappropriate, and one more due to the fenestration configuration. Of the 23 cases where there was compatibility, in 7 (30%), the configuration used coincided with the p-branch®. In 13 cases the number of fenestrations was higher than those currently used, with 23 fenestrations carried out and 39 hypothetical fenestrations with the new endograft. In the 3 remaining cases a fenestration for the coeliac artery was necessary to achieve an adequate seal. Conclusion: The p-branch® could meet the needs of three quarters of the aortic anatomies of our series, with favourable expectations on cost and waiting time. However, in most cases either a higher number of fenestrations are needed for visceral vessels or the proximal seal was shorter than would be ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bargay Juan, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza Martínez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Gisbert, SM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Monzón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Palonés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragozá García, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el tratamiento endovascular de los AAA con cuello infrarrenal corto o ausente, el retraso en la disponibilidad de endoprótesis fenestradas y su elevado coste han llevado a fabricar modelos estandarizados con el objetivo de un uso protocolizado y sin demora. Otra opción de recurso empleada son las endoprótesis con stents en paralelo, que aún carecen de un criterio de uso regularizado y de estudios a largo plazo. Objetivo: Analizar los AAA tratados en nuestro servicio con endoprótesis fenestradas o stents en paralelo, para valorar si cumplían las características de la nueva endoprótesis p-branch® y sus diferencias. Material y métodos: Estudio unicéntrico, descriptivo de 31 aneurismas tratados consecutivamente entre 2008-2013 en el que se analizaron características anatómicas: distancias relativas entre arterias viscerales, su posición horaria, el diámetro en la zona de sellado y el número de fenestraciones requeridas y su compatibilidad con la p-branch®. Resultados: La tasa de anatomías compatibles con una de las 2 opciones de p-branch® fue del 74,2% (23 casos). De los 8 casos incompatibles 5 fueron por inadecuada alineación de las ramas viscerales, uno por diámetro de cuello aórtico mayor al máximo disponible, otro por inadecuado acceso femoral y otro por la configuración de las fenestraciones. De los 23 casos compatibles, en 7 (30%) la configuración coincide con las 3 fenestraciones de la p-branch®. En 13 el número de fenestraciones sería mayor con respecto al utilizado, con 23 fenestraciones realizadas y 39 hipotéticas con la nueva endoprótesis. En los 3 restantes ha sido necesaria la fenestración del TC para un sellado adecuado. Conclusión: La endoprótesis p-branch® podría abarcar 3/4 partes de las anatomías aórticas de nuestra serie, con unas expectativas favorables en coste y tiempo de espera, aunque en la mayoría requiriendo mayor número de fenestraciones o un sellado proximal más corto al ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;68(1): 12-19, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148232</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicabilidad de la nueva endoprótesis fenestrada Zenith p-branch(R)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2480^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12498^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30658^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30658^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2480^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12498^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
