<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90471</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychotherapy in Primary care: presentation of a case of somatomorphic disorder treated with interpersonal therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Problems of medically unexplained somatic symptoms are common in Primary care. They often involve a psychiatric comorbidity that requires some form of psychotherapy that addresses, among other problems, the frequent use of the service.The purpose of this paper is to present the rationale and the generalities of a brief psychotherapeutic intervention, interpersonal therapy (IPT), in its adaptation to primary care. Its applicability is shown through a case of undifferentiated somatoform disorder, a condition so prevalent and difficult to approach in the field of primary care.IPT assumes that stressful life events and interpersonal difficulties act as triggers or maintainers of the psychic symptoms. The intervention is structured around four possible sources: grief, role transitions, interpersonal disputes and interpersonal deficits(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra Cabrera, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diéguez Porres, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En Atención Primaria las demandas de síntomas somáticos sin explicación médica son habituales. Es frecuente que conlleven comorbilidad psiquiátrica y que sea preciso utilizar algún tipo de tratamiento psicoterapéutico que aborde, entre otros problemas, la hiperfrecuentación.El objeto de este trabajo es exponer el fundamento y las generalidades de una intervención psicoterapéutica breve, la terapia interpersonal (TIP), en su adaptación a Atención Primaria. Se muestra su aplicabilidad a través de un caso clínico de trastorno somatomorfo indiferenciado, trastorno tan prevalente como de difícil abordaje en el ámbito de Atención Primaria.La TIP parte de la base de que los acontecimientos vitales estresantes y las dificultades interpersonales actúan como factores desencadenantes o mantenedores de los síntomas psíquicos. La intervención se estructura en torno a cuatro posibles focos: duelo, transición de rol, disputas interpersonales y déficit interpersonales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(8): 440-446, ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoterapia en Atención Primaria: a propósito de un caso de trastorno somatomorfo tratado con terapia interpersonal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
