<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83933</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Public health research: are there differences among northern, southern and eastern European countries? A perspective from national associations of public health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionResearch provides the important evidence base for public health practice. We sought to compare the current support for public health research within European countries.MethodsWithin a collaborative study SPHERE (Strengthening Public Health Research in Europe), we developed an e-mail questionnaire and sent it to 93 representatives of national member associations of the European Public Health Association. We compared the answers with reference to tree macro-areas: Northern, Southern and Eastern Europe.ResultsWe gained responses for 22 of 39 European countries (56% country response rate). Current priorities at national level were: health service and patient safety for Northern Europe; infectious disease, health service and cardiovascular disease for Southern Europe; and food safety and nutrition, environmental and occupational health for Eastern Europe. Respondents gave fewer priorities for international research. In the North Europe the priorities empathized were health promotion, prevention and education (26.3%) together the injuries and alcohol habits (26.3%).ConclusionSupport for public-health research differs across Europe, and barriers to undertaking better research include structures and sufficient personnel. National public health associations and public authorities should cooperate in order to find effective answers to common problems(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ricciardi,  Walter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bes-Rastrollo, Maira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>La Torre, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mannocci,  Alice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>McCarthy,  Mark</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónLa investigación aporta la salud pública la importante base de la evidencia científica. Nuestro objetivo fue comparar el actual apoyo de investigación en salud pública en los países europeos.MétodosEn el marco del estudio colaborativo SPHERE (Strengthening Public Health Research in Europe) se desarrolló un cuestionario vía correo electrónico que fue enviado a 93 representantes de las asociaciones nacionales miembros de la Asociación Europea de Salud Pública. Se compararon las respuestas en tres macroáreas: norte, sur y este de Europa.ResultadosSe obtuvo respuesta de 23 de los 39 países europeos (tasa de respuesta por países: 56%). Las prioridades nacionales actuales fueron: servicios de salud y seguridad del paciente en el norte de Europa; enfermedades infecciosas, servicios de salud y enfermedad cardiovascular en el sur de Europa; y seguridad alimentaria y nutrición, salud medioambiental y ocupacional en los países del este de Europa. Los encuestados dieron menos prioridad a la investigación internacional. En el norte, las prioridades enfatizadas fueron la promoción de la salud, la prevención y la educación (26,3%), junto con los accidentes y los hábitos alcohólicos (26,3%).ConclusiónEl apoyo para la investigación en salud pública difiere en los países europeos, y el no disponer de unas buenas infraestructuras y de personal suficiente fueron barreras para llevar a cabo mejor investigación. Las asociaciones de salud pública nacionales y las autoridades sanitarias deberían cooperar para encontrar respuestas efectivas a problemas comunes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(3): 253e1-253e5, May. - Jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación en salud pública: ¿hay diferencias entre los países del norte, el sur y el este de Europa? Una perspectiva desde las asociaciones nacionales de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
