<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77026</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims: Team sports require players thatcan carry out a high number of short sprints, interspersedwith periods of recovery or periods of low to moderateintensity. This type of exercise, is called Repeated SprintAbility (RSA). Although the importance of these exercises isconstant in team sports, the difference in the test of RSAamong athletes of different sports or disciplines should bestudied due the variety of physical efforts required in differentteam sports. In line with this thinking, present investigation&#146;saim is to determine the differences and analogiesof RSA tests between amateur and professional athletes ofdifferent team sports such as basketball and handball.Method: Four teams were evaluated, 2 basketball and 2handball that were divided into amateurs and professionals.The RSA test was carried out by running 8 times 30 m with25 s of recovery, on tracks with photoelectric cells.Results: The results obtained do not show significant differencesin the kinetic variables among the different groups.Differences between professional basketball and professionalhandball were found of (p &lt; 0,05) in the best sprint andacceleration 0-10 m. A decline in power was observed (between20,51% and 23,37%) between the 1st and 8th sprintin the 4 groups, but there was not difference among them.Conclusion: The type of efforts carried out by athletes incooperation sports and similar disciplines (such as basketballand handball) are similar in the RSA test, due to theefforts carried out in competition resemble a lot betweendifferent sports and in the exercise carried out in the protocolutilized. Thus it is appropriate to emphasize that nodifferences between amateur and professional levels werefound(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heredia Jiménez, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirosa Ríos, Luis Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán Casas, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirosa Ríos, Ignacio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los deportes de equipo requierenjugadores que puedan realizar un número elevadode sprints cortos, intercalados con períodos de recuperacióno de intensidad, y a este tipo de esfuerzos se le hadenominado capacidad de realizar sprints repetidos (RSA).Aunque la importancia de estos esfuerzos está constatadaen deportes de equipo, la diferencia entre deportistas dedistintas disciplinas debe ser estudiada debido a la variabilidadde esfuerzos en los numerosos deportes colectivos. Lapresente investigación va encaminada a determinar las diferenciasy analogías en test RSA entre deportistas amateursy profesionales de deportes colectivos distintos como sonel baloncesto y balonmano.Método: Se evaluaron 4 equipos, 2 de baloncesto y 2 debalonmano (divididos en amateurs y profesionales). El testRSA realizado fue 8 × 30 m con 25 s de recuperación, enpista con células fotoeléctricas.Resultados: Los resultados obtenidos no muestran diferenciassignificativas en las variables cinéticas entre los diferentesgrupos. Sí se encontraron diferencias entre baloncestoprofesional y balonmano profesional (p &lt; 0,05) en lasvariables mejor sprint y aceleración 0-10 m. Se observó undescenso en la potencia (entre el 20,51 y el 23,37%) entreel sprint 1 y 8 en los 4 grupos, pero no hubo diferenciasentre ellos.Conclusiones: El tipo de esfuerzos realizados por deportistasde deportes de cooperación y oposición de disciplinassemejantes (como baloncesto y balonmano) es similaren el test RSA, debido a que los esfuerzos realizados encompetición se asemejan mucho entre deportes y con losesfuerzos realizados en el protocolo utilizado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);44(164): 163-173, oct.-dic. 2009. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la capacidad de realizar sprints repetidos entre jugadores de balonmano y baloncesto amateurs y profesionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14532</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7758</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
