<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95590</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From competence to compart-tence in the transcultural care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this XXI century it is necessary to confront the different logics that cross the glob-local thinking and the what-to-do in the cultural care in health, in the communitarian surroundings and in the nursery's professionals. This confrontation is carried out by the theoretical methodological's reflection about the sense and the meaning of two categories: Competence and compart-tence, that express the hegemonic and the resistance, respectively, which helps to explain and to comprehend the actions in healthcare within occidental cultural sphere and in the people's traditional culture. The compart-tence concept is taken from the northern mountainous part of the State of Oaxaca, Mexico, and from the Colombian guambian peoples' traditional cosmogonist thought. This reflection does not disregard the varieties that are present in the conceptual and practices' appropriations that are made in every cultural territory, in which the health care exercises are realized from the cultural competence or the compart-tence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nubia Romero, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este siglo XXI es necesario confrontar las lógicas diferenciales que atraviesan el pensar y el quehacer glocal de los cuidados culturales de la salud en los entornos comunitarios y de los profesionales de la enfermería. Esta confrontación se hace mediante la reflexión teórico-metodológica del sentido y significado de dos categorías: competencia y compartencia, que expresan hegemonía y resistencia, respectivamente, y sirven para explicar y comprender las acciones en los cuidados de la salud en ámbitos de la cultura occidental y la cultura tradicional de los pueblos. El concepto de compartencia se aborda desde la cosmogonía tradicional de los pueblos de la sierra norte del estado de Oaxaca, México, y de los indígenas guambianos de Colombia. Esta reflexión no desconoce los matices que se presentan por las apropiaciones conceptuales y prácticas que se hacen en cada espacio del territorio cultural en los que se ejercen los cuidados de la salud desde la competencia cultural o la compartencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(2/3): 157-161, sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">De la Competencia a la Compartencia en los cuidados transculturales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8686^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52938</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
