<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044851</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recent changes in the incidence and mortality of cancer in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To study the different rates of cancer incidence and mortality risk observed in theSpanish national estimates.Methods: The authors make an observational-analytical cohort study of cancer mortality usingdeath records and incidence rates published in Globocan 2000, and in the 1985 Saragossa mortalityrecords. The 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) were calculated.Results: Cancer localization has changed in Spain as time passes. The overall cancer mortalityand incidence risk is lower in women than in men.Conclusions: Regional data should guide cancer prevention and control activities in the differentparts of Spain. The disparity of regional risk of mortality, incidence and localization makes urgent toimprove regional cancer control measures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraj, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, G. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las estimaciones nacionales del riesgo de enfermedad por cáncer pueden permitirestimar variaciones del riesgo de esta enfermedad.Métodos: Realizamos un estudio epidemiológico observacional analítico de cohortes estratificadasrealizado a partir de datos previos publicados en Globocan 2000 y en otras ediciones de tasas deincidencia. Los datos para la Mortalidad fueron tomados de las estadísticas de mortalidad publicadasen Zaragoza.Resultados: Ha variado el riesgo de padecer cáncer en España respecto a las diferentes localizaciones,siendo menor en mujeres que en hombres.Conclusión: Los datos de cáncer podrían ser una guía para prevención de las actividades en España.La diferencia temporal del riesgo en cáncer manifiesta una urgencia en medidas de control decáncer</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;29(3): 107-113, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios recientes en la incidencia y mortalidad del cáncer en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
