<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036543</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PREVENCAT study: control of cardiovascular risk in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Most studies of cardiovascular risk factors (CVRF) conducted in our environment concentrate in a single CVRF. The PREVENCAT study was designed to estimate the control of CVRF in the population attended in primary care presenting arterial hypertension (HT), type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM2) and/or hypercholesterolemia (HC) as well as to assess the prevalence of Metabolic Syndrome in these patients. Patients and method: Multicenter, cross-sectional study, in patients with HT, DM2 and/or HC, consecutively recruited by primary care physicians in Spain. The blood pressure, cholesterol, basal glycaemia, obesity, smoking and physical activity were assessed. The degree of control of these CVRF and the prevalence of MS were estimated. Results: 2,649 patients were recruited, aged 64 (11.3) years, with a 51.6% of women. The most frequent diagnosis was HT (78.9%), followed by HC (58.4%) and DM2 (37.4%). In the whole sample, the percentages of patients who had a control or had initially normal values of blood pressure, cholesterol and basal glycemia were 40.0% (confidence interval [CI], 95% 38.2-41.9), 42.6% (95% CI, 40.5-44.7) and 62.7% (95% CI, 60.8-64.5), respectively. 15.6% of cases (95% CI, 14.3-17.0) had body mass index 25 kg/m2; 87.5% were non-current smokers (95% CI, 86.2-88.8); and 46.2% practiced regular physical activity (95% CI, 44.3-48.1). 40% of patients had 2 CVRF in good control. The prevalence of metabolic syndrome was 50.6% (95% CI, 48.7-52.5). Conclusions: The control of the CVRF considered in primary care attended population is insufficient. Hardly one of each 2 patients with HT, DM2 and HC is under control. The overweight and sedentarism control is still poorer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sala, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, Vivencio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franch, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mantilla, Teresa </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruilope, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Muchos estudios de factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV) realizados en nuestro medio se centran en sólo uno. El estudio PREVENCAT se diseñó para estimar el control de los principales FRCV en población asistida en atención primaria que presenta hipertensión arterial (HTA), diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM-2) y/o hipercolesterolemia (HC) y para conocer la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en estos pacientes. Pacientes y método: Estudio multicéntrico, transversal, en pacientes con HTA, DM-2 y/o HC, reclutados de forma consecutiva por médicos de atención primaria en España. Se evaluaron la presión arterial, el colesterol, la glucemia basal, la obesidad, el tabaquismo y el ejercicio físico, y se estimaron el grado de control de estos FRCV y la prevalencia del síndrome metabólico. Resultados: Se incluyó en el estudio a 2.649 pacientes (un 51,6% mujeres) con una media (desviación estándar) de edad de 64 (11,3) años de edad. El diagnóstico más frecuente fue la HTA (78,9%), seguido de HC (58,4%) y de DM-2 (37,4%). En toda la muestra, el porcentaje de pacientes que tenía bien controlada o basalmente normal la presión arterial, el colesterol y la glucemia basal fue del 40,0% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 38,2-41,9), del 42,6% (IC del 95%, 40,5-44,7) y del 62,7% (IC del 95%, 60,8-64,5), respectivamente. El 15,6% de los casos (IC del 95%, 14,3-17,0) tenía un índice de masa corporal menor o igual a 25 kg/m2, el 87,5% no fumaba en la actualidad (IC del 95%, 86,2-88,8) y el 46,2% practicaba ejercicio físico regular (IC del 95%, 44,3-48,1). El 40% de los pacientes presentaba 2 o menos FRCV bien controlados. La prevalencia del síndrome metabólico fue del 50,6% (IC del 95%, 48,7-52,5). Conclusiones: El control de los FRCV considerados en población atendida en atención primaria es insuficiente. Apenas uno de cada 2 pacientes con HTA, DM-2 o HC está controlado. El control del sobrepeso y el sedentarismo es aún peor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(11): 406-410, mar. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio PREVENCAT: control del riesgo cardiovascular en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
