<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142924</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A program of effective psychology referral between the Center of Pediatric and Adolescent Mental Health of Lleida and the division of pediatrics of the Hospital Universitari Arnau de Vilanova of Lleida (1996-2002)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To avoid unnecessary prolongation of hospital admissions, decrease the parental anxiety that may interfere with the appropriate medical management or delay discharges, and to expedite the referral to the network of pediatric mental health once a psychiatric disturbance is detected. Methods. Consultation with the primary pediatrician, diagnostic interview with the child and the family, diagnostic tests, and discussion of diagnostic possibilities and proposed intervention with the primary pediatrician. Results. Between May 1996 and December 2003, 1,104 children (45% boys, 55% girls) were evaluated. The most common age group was 11 to 14 years (34% of the boys, 50% of the girls). The most common reasons for consultation were insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus (IDDM) (30.4%), nonspecific pain (28.4%), eating disorders (11.3% of girls), and accidents (7.4% of boys). The most common diagnosis was neurosis (44.1% total; anxiety, 24.6% boys; hysteria, 17.3% girls, and depression, 11.3% girls), and reactive disorders (27.2% of the total). 55% of the boys, and 45% of the girls were referred to the CSMIJ of Lleida. Conclusions. The families and the patients have been very cooperative during the diagnostic process, which has facilitated the rapid triage and detection of psychosomatic and psychiatric disorders. This has resulted in the avoidance of unnecessary prolongations of hospital admissions, and facilitated the multidisciplinary work within our network (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tello, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallmanya, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goma, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galíndez, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evitar la prolongación innecesaria de los ingresos, disminuir las ansiedades de los padres que pueden prolongar innecesariamente los ingresos y/o la correcta aplicación del tratamiento médico y agilizar la derivación a los recursos de la red infantil de salud mental en el caso de detectar un trastorno psiquiátrico. Método. Interconsulta con el pediatra responsable del paciente, entrevista diagnostica con la familia y con el niño, pruebas gráficas e interconsulta con el pediatra para comentar la cribación diagnóstica y la propuesta de intervención. Resultados. Se hicieron un total de 1.104 consultas (44.85% chicos y 55.15% chicas). La edad mayoritaria fue de 11-14 años (34.4% chicos, 49.7% chicas). Las interconsultas más frecuentes fueron por diabetes mellitus I (DMID) (30.4% total), algias (28.4% total), trastornos del comportamiento alimentario (11.3% chicas) y accidentes (7.4% chicos). El diagnóstico más frecuente fue de trastornos neuróticos (44.1% total: ansiedad, 24.6% chicos; histeria, 17.3% chicas, y depresión, 11.3% chicas) y de trastornos reactivos (27.2% total). Se derivaron al CSMIJ de Lleida 54.9% chicos y 44.6% chicas. Conclusiones. Mayoritariamente las familias y pacientes han colaborado en la cribación diagnóstica, esto ha facilitado la discriminación rápida e interdisciplinar de los aspectos psicosomáticos y la detección de trastornos psiquiátricos. Se han evitado prolongaciones innecesarias de ingresos. Ha facilitado el trabajo en red de los distintos dispositivos relacionados con la infancia y la adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;64(3): 119-124, mayo-jun. 2004. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de interconsulta entre el Centro de Salut Mental de Lleida y el Servicio de Pediatría del Hospital Universitario Arnau de Vilanova (1996-2002)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
