<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054676</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9626</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From immune surveillance to tumor-immune escape: the story of an enemy with multiple strategies of resistance and counterattack</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tumors must circumvent the immune response of the host to    become clinically detectable. For this purpose, malignant cells    have devised multiple strategies to thwart immune attack. These    mechanisms are suggested to conspire in advanced stages of cancer    to limit the ability of the immune system to restrain the tumor    and the effectiveness of immunotherapy strategies to successfully    eradicate malignant cells. From tumor biology to cancer immunotherapy    and back again, we will summarize here some of the    most important mechanisms used by tumors to evade the immune    response and their potential impact in the design of cancer    immunotherapy strategies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rico, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabinovich, GA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fluck, MZ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scharovsky, OG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matar, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores deben evadir la respuesta inmunológica para ser    clínicamente detectables en el paciente. A estos fines, las células    cancerosas han desarrollado múltiples estrategias para eludir el    ataque inmunológico. Estos mecanismos conspiran en estadíos    avanzados de un tumor limitando la habilidad del sistema inmune    para inhibir el crecimiento tumoral y la efectividad de estrategias    de inmunoterapia en cáncer. Desde la biología tumoral a    la clínica, en el presente artículo expondremos los más importantes    mecanismos utilizados por tumores para evadir la respuesta    inmunológica y su potencial impacto en el diseño de estrategias    de inmunoterapia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inmunología (1987);25(2): 101-114, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">De la inmunovigilancia al escape tumoral: Historia de un enemigo con múltiples estrategias de resistencia y contra-ataque</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23827^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32587^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32837^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37465^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32587^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32587^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32587^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14768^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
