<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129779</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Observational study of the safety and effectiveness of nifedipine in pre-term labor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the effectiveness and safety of nifedipine as a tocolytic agent in pregnant women with preterm labor (PL). Subjects and methods. We performed a prospective observational study (April 2003 - December 2004) and a retrospective study (January- December 2008). A total of 106 pregnant women were included and the hospital PL protocol was applied. Thirty-three patients were excluded for different reasons, mainly because of a false PL diagnosis. Results. Pregnancy was prolonged by more than 48 hours in 56.2% [95% CI: 44.8-67.5] and 2 doses of betametasone were administered in 69.9% [95% CI: 59.3-80.4]. The incidence of maternal adverse reactions was 29.4% (95% CI: 7.8-51.2), mainly mild hypotension. Of the 99 newborns, 10 died, mainly because of infectious complications and low birthweight and there was one case of hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy. Conclusions. Tocolysis with nifedipine is safe and effective if precautions for use are strictly respected. In this study, there was a low incidence of maternal and fetal adverse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramis Barceló, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González González, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán Ramos, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Usandizaga Calparsoro, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigventós Latorre, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Guivernau, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar la efectividad y seguridad del nifedipino en gestantes con amenaza de parto prematuro (APP). Sujetos y métodos. Estudio observacional prospectivo de abril de 2003 a diciembre de 2004 y retrospectivo de enero a diciembre de 2008. Se incluyeron 106 gestantes a las que se aplicó el protocolo de APP del hospital. Se excluyeron 33 por diferentes motivos, principalmente falsos diagnósticos de APP. Resultados. La prolongación del parto fue superior a 48 h en el 56,2% (IC 95%: 44,8-67,5) y se administraron 2 dosis de betametasona en el 69,9% (IC 95%: 59,3-80,4). La incidencia de reacciones adversas maternas fue del 29,4% (IC 95%:7,8-51,2), principalmente hipotensión leve. De los 99 recién nacidos hubo 10 fallecimientos, principalmente por complicaciones infecciosas y bajo peso, y hubo un caso de encefalopatía hipóxico-isquémica. Conclusiones. La tocólisis con nifedipino es efectiva y segura si se respetan las precauciones de uso de forma estricta, registrando una baja incidencia de efectos adversos maternos y fetales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(10): 451-457, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio observacional de la efectividad y seguridad de nifedipino en la amenaza de parto prematuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3276^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22355^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23402^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23402^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
