<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84936</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Limitations of biomarkers serum levels during pulmonary vein isolation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Several biomarkers have been used for evaluation and quantification of myocardial injury after effective ablation. Westudied possible different thermal stability and usability of the proteins released by cardiac cells injured by different energy sources. Methods: Firstly, we tested in vitro thermal stability of creatinine kinase (CK), myocardial bound creatinine kinase (CKMB), cardiac troponins I (cTnI) and cardiac troponins T (cTnT) in collected blood samples from 15 patients (pts) with confirmed ST-segment elevated myocardial infarction (STEMI). Secondly, the biomarkers were collected and analyzed in 82 pts treated with radiofrequency ablation (RFA) and in 79 pts treated with cryo-balloon ablation (CBA). Results: In vitro experiment showed that all biomarkers were stable in low temperature of -30oC. Troponins were stable in the high temperatures analyzed. A substantial drop in CK and CKMB levels were measured at 50 8C and 408 C, respectively. In vivo study showed that the increase in CKMB levels was highly significant in CBA pts only. Pathological CKMB values were observed in 24% of RFA pts and 98% of CBA pts. Pathological cTnI values were observed in all pts and the rise in cTnI levels was highly significant in both groups after ablation.  onclusions: Both in vitro and in vivo results show that CKMB cannot be used for quantitative determination of myocardial injury produced by radiofrequency energy. Only cardiac troponins reflect myocardial injury, regardless of energy source, and may be considered in future studies for comparison of biomarkers effects of cryo versus radiofrequency ablation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wysokinski, Andrej</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Janin, Sebastien</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pitschnera, Heinz F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kuniss, Malte</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neumann, Thomas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berkowitsch, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erkapic, Damir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wojcik, Maciej</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hamm, Christian W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaltsberg, Sergey</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madlener, Katherina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Se han usado varios biomarcadores para la evaluación y la cuantificación de la lesión miocárdica tras ablación. Estudiamos las posibles diferencias en la estabilidad térmica y las posibilidades de uso de las proteínas liberadas por las células cardiacas lesionadas mediante diferentes fuentes de energía. Métodos. En primer lugar, estudiamos la estabilidad térmica in vitro de la creatincinasa (CK), la isoenzima miocárdica de la creatincinasa (CK-MB), las troponinas I (cTnI) y las troponinas T (cTnT) en muestras de sangre obtenidas de 15 pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST (IAMCEST) confirmado. En segundo lugar, se obtuvieron y se analizaron los biomarcadores en 82 pacientes tratados mediante ablación con radiofrecuencia (ARF) y en 79 pacientes tratados mediante crioablación con balón (CAB). Resultados. Los experimentos in vitro mostraron que todos los biomarcadores eran estables a temperaturas bajas (&#150;30°C). Las troponinas se mostraron estables al analizarlas a altas temperaturas. En cambio, se observó un descenso importante en los valores de CK y CK-MB a 50 y 40°C, respectivamente. El estudio in vivo mostró que el aumento de las cifras de CK-MB fue significativamente elevado en pacientes sometidos a CAB exclusivamente. Se observaron valores patológicos de CK-MB en el 24% de los pacientes con ARF y en el 98% de los pacientes sometidos a CAB. Se observaron valores patológicos de cTnI en todos los pacientes y el aumento de la concentración de cTnI fue muy significativo en ambos grupos tras la ablación. Conclusiones. Tanto los resultados in vitro como los obtenidos in vivo muestran que la CK-MB no puede usarse para la determinación cuantitativa de las lesiones miocárdicas producidas por la energía de radiofrecuencia. Sólo las troponinas reflejan las lesiones miocárdicas independientemente de la fuente de energía, y se debería utilizarlas para comparar los efectos en los biomarcadores de la crioablación frente a la ablación con radiofrecuencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(2): 127-132, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Limitaciones de la determinación de los niveles de los biomarcadores séricos durante el aislamiento de venas pulmonares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12104^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52841^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12104^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52841^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50743^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50743^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50743^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6488^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3469^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12104^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
