<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147128</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current status of time-lapse systems in the laboratory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of time-lapse systems is increasingly widespread in laboratories, it has proved useful in the selection of the best embryos when combined with their morphology, the traditional method used until now. Although there are some authors that disagree with this statement, a large majority agrees that the continuous monitorization of the embryos offers relevant information at the time of choosing the best embryos within a culture. In recent years there have been studies that support the use of this technique, and have proven that higher pregnancy rates can be achieved with its use, placing more emphasis on single embryo transfer. Everything published in the literature describes the results of with division patterns and the various studies that validate those models, but none provide an in-depth description of their specifications, thus the aim of this study was to highlight the differences between each of the platforms found on the market and indicate the predicted future of each of them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez Calonge, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Peregrín, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaya, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna Cañas, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega López, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Gallego, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de los sistemas time lapse está cada vez más extendido en los laboratorios, se ha demostrado su utilidad a la hora de seleccionar mejor los embriones en combinación con la morfología, que hasta hoy era el método utilizado para realizar esta selección. Aunque existen autores que no están muy de acuerdo con esta afirmación, hay una gran mayoría que coincide en que la monitorización continua de los embriones ofrece una información relevante a la hora de elegir los mejores embriones de un cultivo. Durante los últimos años han surgido estudios avalando el uso de esta técnica, así se ha descrito que se puede conseguir elevar las tasas de embarazo y apostar con más fuerza por la transferencia de embrión único. Todo lo descrito en la literatura habla de resultados con patrones de división y los distintos estudios que validan esos modelos, pero ninguno nombra en profundidad las especificaciones propias de cada sistema, por tanto, el objetivo de este estudio ha sido el intentar resaltar las diferencias existentes entre las plataformas que se pueden encontrar en el mercado e indicar el futuro de cada una de ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;32(4): 8-14, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147128</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual de la técnica time lapse en el laboratorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53237^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53237^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53237^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53237^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
