<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99827</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Allergies in occupational health. Prevention aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The concern in all countries of occupational health has led to the study of occupational risk factors and their impact on health. But maintaining the health of workers is increasingly complex, especially in occupational allergic diseases, which have increased in parallel with the increased use in industries of potentially irritating chemicals or allergens, leading to skin or respiratory sensitization. Diseases arising from these immunological substances are classified by Spanish Legislation as occupational diseases, as set out in Royal Decree 1299/2006, of November 10, 2006 (Group 1, Group 4 and Group 5). The most important ones in occupational medicine are allergic respiratory diseases and dermatological allergic diseases, although there are other allergies of interest, such as those involving mucous membranes (allergic eye diseases). A joint collaboration between the different medical disciplines involved to improve prevention at work is highly desirable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Herrero, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terradillos García, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capdevila García, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Iñiguez de la Torre, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-González, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La preocupación en todos los países por la salud laboral ha favorecido el estudio de los factores de riesgo laboral y su repercusión sobre la salud. Pero mantener esta salud en los trabajadores es cada vez más complejo, especialmente en las enfermedades alérgicas de origen laboral, que se han incrementado de forma paralela al mayor uso de sustancias potencialmente irritantes o alergénicas y sensibilizantes por vía dérmica o respiratoria utilizadas en las industrias. Las enfermedades de tipo inmunológico generadas por estas sustancias son catalogadas por la legislación española como enfermedades profesionales según se recoge en el Real Decreto 1299/2006, de 10 de noviembre de 2006 (grupo 1, grupo 4 y grupo 5). Las de mayor importancia en el ámbito laboral son las enfermedades alérgicas respiratorias y las enfermedades alérgicas dermatológicas, si bien existen otras alergias de interés, como las que afectan a mucosas (enfermedades alérgicas oculares). Interesa una colaboración conjunta entre todas las especialidades implicadas para una mejor labor preventiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(3): 192-196, abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las alergias en salud laboral. Aspectos preventivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29208^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27801^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
