<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89711</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carotid intima-media thickness in diabetics and hypertensive patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this study are to describe the mean values of carotid intima-media thickness and how it increases with age, and to compare carotid injury in diabetics and hypertensive patients with that of controls. We included 562 subjects (121 diabetics, 352 hypertensive patients, 89 controls). The mean intima-media thickness was 0.781mm in diabetics, 0.738mm in hypertensive patients and 0.686mm in controls. The difference in intima-media thickness between diabetics and controls and between hypertensive patients and controls, adjusted for age, was 0.040 and 0.026mm, respectively. We observed an increase in intima-media thickness of 0.005 mm in diabetics and of 0.005 mm in controls with every additional year of age. We found carotid damage in 23% of the diabetics, 12% of the hypertensive patients and 3.4% of the controls. In conclusion, the intima-media thickness is greater in diabetics, but the annual increase in the thickness is greater in hypertensive patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sánchez, Emiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sánchez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ortiz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Patino-Alonso, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Vizcaino, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recio-Rodríguez, José I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Marcos, Manuel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magallón-Botaya, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es describir los valores medios del grosor íntima-media carotídeo (GIMc), la evolución con la edad y la presencia de lesión carotídea en diabéticos e hipertensos comparados con controles. Estudiamos a 562 sujetos (121 diabéticos, 352 hipertensos y 89 controles). El valor medio del GIMc fue 0,781±0,119 mm en diabéticos, 0,738±0,108mm en hipertensos y 0,686±0,093mm en controles. La diferencia del GIMc entre diabéticos y controles e hipertensos y controles ajustado por edad fue 0,040 y 0,026 mm respectivamente. Por cada año que aumenta la edad, cabe esperar un incremento del GIMc de 0,005 mm en diabéticos, 0,006 mm en hipertensos y 0,005 mm en controles. Presentaron lesión carotídea el 23% de los diabéticos, el 12% de los hipertensos y el 3,4% de los controles. En conclusión, el GIMc es mayor en diabéticos, pero el incremento anual del grosor es superior en hipertensos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(7): 622-625, jul. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89711</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grosor íntima-media carotídeo en diabéticos e hipertensos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2387^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2387^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
