<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86940</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute care and one-year outcome of Mexican patients with first-ever acute ischemic stroke: the PREMIER study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Information on acute care and outcome of Mexican patients with ischaemic stroke is lacking. The aim of this report is to provide results of a first step stroke surveillance system and outcome at one year of follow-up. Patients and methods. In the PREMIER study 1,376 patients from 59 Mexican hospitals were included from January 2005 to June 2006. Of these, 1,040 (52% women, mean age 67.5 years) with first-ever cerebral infarction are here analyzed. Five visits were completed during the one year follow-up. Results. Main risk factors were hypertension (64%), obesity (51%) and diabetes (35%). Total anterior circulation stroke  syndrome occurred in 19% of patients, partial anterior in 38%, lacunar in 26% and posterior stroke syndrome in 17% cases. In 8% the stroke mechanism was large-artery atherosclerosis, in 18% cardioembolism, in 20% lacunar, in 6% miscellaneous mechanisms and in 42% the mechanism was undetermined, mainly due to a low use of diagnostic resources. Although 17% of patients arrived in &lt; 3 h from stroke onset, only 0.5% had IV thrombolysis. Only 1% received endarterectomy or stenting. The 30-day case fatality rate was 15%. At one-year of follow-up, 47% had a modified Rankin score 0-2 (independent), 23% had 2-5 (dependent) and 29% died. One-year acute ischaemic stroke recurrence rate was 8%.  Conclusion. In Mexico a significant proportion of patients arrive on time for thrombolysis, but very few receive this therapy. There is a low use of diagnostic resources to assign aetiology. Thirty-day case fatality rate doubles at 1-year after acute ischaemic stroke (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sandoval, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Bonilla, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rangel Guerra, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arauz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiquete, Enwin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Moreno, Alma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantú Brito, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal lCareaga, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barinagarrementería, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Jiménez, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se carece de información sobre el cuidado agudo y pronóstico de mexicanos con infarto cerebral. El objetivo de este informe es proveer los resultados de un sistema multicéntrico de vigilancia hospitalaria en ictus isquémico agudo. Pacientes y métodos. En el estudio PREMIER se incluyeron 1.376 pacientes de 59 hospitales entre enero de 2005 y junio de 2006. De éstos, se analizaron 1.040 (52% mujeres; edad promedio: 67,5 años) con un primer infarto cerebral. Cinco  visitas se completaron durante un año de seguimiento. Resultados. Los principales factores de riesgo fueron hipertensión (64%), obesidad (51%) y diabetes (35%). Un 19% de los pacientes se presentó con un síndrome de circulación anterior total, un 38% de circulación anterior parcial, un 26% lacunar y un 17% de circulación posterior. En el 8%, el mecanismo del ictus fue aterotrombosis de grandes arterias, el 18% fue cardioembólico, el 20% lacunar, el 6% misceláneo y el 42% indeterminado. Aunque un 17% de los pacientes llegó en  menos de tres horas de ocurrido el ictus, sólo al 0,5% se le realizó trombólisis intravenosa. Se practicó endarterectomía o colocación de endoprótesis arterial en el 1%. La mortalidad a 30 días fue del 15%. Al año de seguimiento, un 47% tuvo una puntuación en la escala de Rankin modificada de 0-2 puntos (independiente), un 23% tuvo 2-5 puntos (dependiente) y un 29% falleció. La tasa anual de recurrencia fue del 8%. Conclusión. En México, una proporción significativa de pacientes llega a tiempo para trombólisis, pero muy pocos la reciben.  Existe un bajo uso de recursos de diagnóstico para asignar la etiología del infarto cerebral. La tasa de fatalidad a 30 días se duplica un año después del ictus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(11): 641-649, dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86940</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo agudo y pronóstico a un año en pacientes mexicanos con un primer infarto cerebral: resultados del estudio multicéntrico PREMIER</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
