<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040674</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical characteristics of spinal cord injury caused by infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Infections account for 3% of all non-traumatic spinal cord injuries. The demographic distribution andclinical course are still not fully understood in these patients. Aims. The aim of this study was to determine the clinicalepidemiologicalcharacteristics and clinical course in patients with infectious spinal cord injury referred to our centre. Patientsand methods. A retrospective study (over the period 1997-2003) was carried out. Variables examined included age, sex, type ofinjury, aetiology, causing agent, ASIA classification on admission and discharge. Results. N = 27 (8% of the total number of nontraumaticspinal cord injuries). Mean age: 37.3 years (range: 14-75). Higher prevalence was found between the ages of 20 and39 years (48.1%) and in males (70.4%). A prevalence of dorsal injuries (59.3%) was also observed. On hospital admission mostof the injuries were incomplete (70.4%) and this figure increased to 77.8% on discharge. Spondylodiscitis was the most frequentcause (51.9%) and Staphylococcus aureus was found to be the most common microbiological causing agent. The greatestprevalence of complete injuries was observed in cases of dorsal injuries (43.75%). All cases of tuberculosis were situated in thedorsal region (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions. In our care centre, non-traumatic spinal cord injuries of an infectious origin seem to bemost often caused by spondylodiscitis due to S. aureus, with a higher incidence in the dorsal region. They predominantly affectmales in their thirties and forties, and usually give rise to incomplete injuries</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artime, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo-Leco, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Borrego, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz-Ramírez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz-Rousselet,  M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labarta-Bertol, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La etiología infecciosa representa el 3%de la lesión medular no traumática. La distribución demográfica yevolución clínica no son completamente conocidas en estos pacientes.Objetivos. Conocer las características clinicoepidemiológicasy la evolución en pacientes con lesión medular infecciosa remitidosa nuestro centro. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo (período1997-2003). Variables: edad, sexo, tipo de lesión, etiología,agente causal, clasificación ASIA al ingreso y al alta. Resultados.N = 27 (8% del total de lesiones medulares no traumáticas). Edadmedia: 37,3 años (rango: 14-75). Mayor prevalencia en edadescomprendidas entre 20 y 39 años (48,1%) y en varones (70,4%). Seobserva una mayor prevalencia de lesiones dorsales (59,3%). Alingreso la mayoría de lesiones fueron incompletas (70,4%), y aumentaronhasta un 77,8% al alta. La espondilodiscitis fue la causamás frecuente (51,9%), y el Staphylococcus aureus, el agente microbiológicoetiológico más frecuente. La mayor prevalencia de lesionescompletas se observa en lesiones dorsales (43,75%). El100% de los casos de tuberculosis asentaron en la región dorsal(p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. En nuestro centro, la lesión medular decausa no traumática de etiología infecciosa parece estar producidaen mayor frecuencia por espondilodiscitis por S. aureus, con unamayor incidencia en la región dorsal. Afecta predominantemente avarones en la tercera y cuarta décadas de la vida y suele producirlesiones incompletas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(4): 205-208, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características clínicas de la lesión medular de causa infecciosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2034^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1103^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9379^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
