<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80098</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in socioeconomic inequalities in mortality over a twenty-two-year period in the city of Barcelona (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To analyze the trend in socioeconomic inequalities in all-cause mortality in Barcelona from 1983 to 2004.MethodsWe performed an ecological study of trends over 4 cross-sections (1983&#150;1988, 1989&#150;1994, 1995&#150;1999 and 2000&#150;2004), with the basic health area (BHA) as the unit of analysis. The study population consisted of men and women aged 20 years or more living in Barcelona. The information sources were the mortality registry, the municipal census and the census of inhabitants and dwellings. The age- and sex-specific mortality rate (ASMR) for all causes was used as the dependent variable. As the independent variable, a composite index of socioeconomic deprivation of the BHA was calculated; BHAs were grouped in quartiles according to the values on the index. Poisson models were adjusted to estimate the relative risk of mortality from all causes in the 4 groups of BHA, stratified by age groups and sex.ResultsIn all the study periods, inequalities in mortality were found, depending on the BHA of residence, both for men and for women: the ASMR of the most deprived BHAs were greater than those of less deprived BHA, and were greater among men than among women. Likewise, relative risks in the youngest age groups were higher than in the oldest age groups. However, from the second to fourth study periods, inequalities decreased in absolute and relative terms, especially among men.ConclusionsInequalities in mortality persist in BHA in Barcelona but have decreased over the last 2 decades. Public policies should take this information into account when tackling inequalities among BHA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Altés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Katherine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marí-Dell&#146;Olmo, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalmau-Bueno, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kunst, Anton E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Analizar la evolución de las desigualdades socioeconómicas en la mortalidad por todas las causas en Barcelona durante los años 1983&#150;2004.MétodosEstudio ecológico de tendencias con 4 cortes transversales (1983&#150;1988, 1989&#150;1994, 1995&#150;1999 y 2000&#150;2004), con el área básica de salud (ABS) como unidad de análisis. La población de estudio fueron los varones y mujeres residentes en Barcelona, de 20 o más años de edad. Las fuentes de información fueron el registro de mortalidad, el padrón municipal y el censo de habitantes y viviendas. Como variable dependiente se utilizó la tasa de mortalidad específica (TME) por todas las causas. Como variable independiente se calculó un índice compuesto de privación socioeconómica de las ABS; las ABS se agruparon en cuartiles según los valores del índice. Se ajustaron modelos de Poisson para estimar el riesgo relativo (RR) de mortalidad por todas las causas en las 4 agrupaciones de ABS, estratificado por grupos de edad y sexo.ResultadosEn todos los períodos de estudio se observan desigualdades en la mortalidad según el ABS de residencia, tanto en varones como en mujeres. Las TME de las ABS con mayor privación socioeconómica fueron mayores que las de aquellas con menor privación, y también fueron mayores en los varones que en las mujeres. Asimismo, los grupos de edad más jóvenes presentan mayor RR de mortalidad que los de edad avanzada. No obstante, las desigualdades disminuyeron tanto en términos absolutos como en términos relativos a partir del segundo período de estudio, especialmente en los varones.ConclusionesEste estudio ha demostrado que, a pesar de haber desigualdades en mortalidad en las ABS de Barcelona, éstas han disminuido a lo largo de 2 décadas. Las políticas públicas deberían tener en cuenta esta información en el abordaje de las desigualdades entre ABS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(1): 20-27, ener. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Veintidós años de evolución de las desigualdades socioeconómicas en la mortalidad en la ciudad de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28459^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
