<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162796</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When the healthcare does not follow the evidence: the case of the lack of early intervention programs for psychosis in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is now sufficient evidence to support the importance of interventions in the early stages of psychosis. The delay in the detection and treatment of the first-episode psychosis is related to a lower and slower recovery, as well as a higher risk of relapse. Despite this fact, early intervention units or teams are still not regularly implemented in mental health service settings in Spain. In this opinion article, a review is presented of the main arguments for defending the need to implement these programs and strategies in order to achieve this aim. There are a number of programs for early intervention for psychosis currently working in other countries, with a therapeutic program that includes pharmacological and psychosocial interventions, together with public awareness, information dissemination, and family-professional collaboration activities. Published literature on the experience of these programs indicates that early intervention is not only effective in terms of the improvement of health status, but is also economically efficient. The main steps and recommendations needed to implement such early intervention programs in our country are described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lennox, Belinda R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrabera, Sílvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Nel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Facorro, Benedicto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melau, Marianne</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta, Manuel J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente existe evidencia suficiente que avala la importancia de las intervenciones en fases tempranas de la psicosis. El retraso en la detección y el tratamiento del primer episodio psicótico se asocia con una recuperación menor y más lenta, así como con un riesgo mayor de recaídas. A pesar de ello, todavía no se han implementado de forma regular programas de intervención temprana en los servicios de salud mental en España. En este artículo de opinión se revisarán los principales argumentos que nos permitan defender la necesidad de la implementación de estos programas y las estrategias a seguir para cumplir con este objetivo. Existen actualmente programas de intervención temprana para la psicosis bien establecidos en otros países que incluyen intervenciones farmacológicas y psicosociales, junto con actividades de sensibilización al público, de colaboración entre familias y profesionales y de difusión de información. Los datos publicados acerca de la experiencia de estos programas ya instaurados indican que esta atención es eficiente no solo en términos de salud, sino también desde el punto de vista económico. Se resumen en este artículo las principales acciones y estrategias para la implementación de servicios de atención temprana en nuestro país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);10(2): 78-86, abr.-jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuando la asistencia no sigue a la evidencia: el caso de la falta de programas de intervención temprana en psicosis en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54849^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53394^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
