<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052341</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">National survey on vitreo-retinal surgery and the management of rhegmatogenous retinal detachments in Spain. Project Retina 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To obtain information throughout Spain        on the current management of vitreo-retinal surgical        diseases, the number of ophthalmologists involved        in retinal surgical diseases care, and the urgent        management of retinal detachments.        Methods: A 30 item questionnaire was sent by mail,        on two separate occasions, to the heads of Ophthalmology        Departments of 276 centers in Spain.        Results: A total response rate of 48.2% was achieved,        however the answers from private centers        represented only 9.4% of the total so these were        excluded from the analysis. The centers most likely        to respond were those in Teaching Hospitals (TH)        (52.3%). Of these, 64% of hospitals responded that,        in the last year, they performed pars plana vitrectomies        (PPV) and 70% performed more than 100        PPVs in the year. In all, 77% of the centers that performed        PPVs had also performed them urgently. A total of 75% of hospitals indicated that they had        ophthalmologists mainly dedicated to retinal diseases        care, with a median of 2 specialists per center,        with this representing 23% of their total staff. Retinal        surgery was performed by general ophthalmologists        in 11.5% of centres. Only 40.3% of hospitals        audit their results (37.5% TH).        Conclusions: Despite the existence of a relatively        low response rate, as well as some biases and methodological        problems, data on the management of        retinal surgical disease has been obtained for the        first time at a national level. This data will facilitate        later studies and must be taken into consideration        in improving the planning and adequate management        of these diseases in Spain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ulla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Obtener información de ámbito nacional        sobre el manejo habitual de la patología quirúrgica        de la retina, del número de especialistas dedicados        a esta actividad y del manejo urgente de los desprendimientos        de retina.        Métodos: Se realizaron 2 envíos postales de un        cuestionario de 30 preguntas a los jefes de servicio        de 276 centros oftalmológicos de toda España.        Resultados: Se obtuvo una tasa de respuesta global        del 48,2%. Las respuestas de los centros de carácter        privado fueron solo el 9,4% por lo que se eliminaron        del estudio. Los centros que más respondieron        fueron los docentes (HD) (52,3%) existiendo un        sesgo por sobre-representación de este grupo. El        64% de los centros respondieron que, en el último        año, realizaron vitrectomías por pars plana (VPP) y        de ellos, el 70% practicaron más de 100 programadas.        El 77% de los centros que realizan VPP las hacen también de urgencia. El 75% dispone de        especialistas en vítreo retina, con una mediana de 2        retinólogos por centro, lo que representa el 23% de        la plantilla. El 11,5% responden que sus oftalmólogos        generales realizan cirugía de retina. Y solo el        40,3% de los centros auditan sus resultados (37,5%        HD).        Conclusiones: A pesar de la relativa baja tasa de        respuesta, la existencia de algunos sesgos y algunos        problemas metodológicos, se han obtenido por primera        vez datos sobre el manejo de la patología        vítreo-retiniana quirúrgica a nivel nacional, que        pueden facilitar estudios posteriores y que pueden        ser aprovechados para mejorar la planificación de la        atención oftalmológica en España</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(11): 635-640, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta nacional sobre la cirugía vítreo-retiniana y la atención de los desprendimientos de retina regmatógenos en España. Proyecto Retina 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31976^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33767^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
