<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123041</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preventive cardiology and cardiac rehabilitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Preventive Cardiology and Rehabilitation Section of the Spanish Society of Cardiology provides the principal national reference point for scientific knowledge about cardiovascular risk factors in the Spanish population, about the incidence and prevalence of cardiovascular disease in Spain, and about disease prevention and the use of cardiac rehabilitation to improve the quality of life and prolong the survival of individuals already affected by the disease. By necessity, research into cardiovascular prevention involves sponsoring the implementation of studies into cardiovascular risk factors and disease occurrence. The MESYAS study is a good example. It is the fruit of the combined efforts of members of the metabolic syndrome working group belonging to our Section of the Spanish Society of Cardiology and its aim was to answer a number of unresolved questions that had arisen about the incidence, prevalence and consequences of cardiovascular disease in the Spanish population. Today, after this cohort has been followed up for more than 5 years, the first analysis of the cardiovascular events that occurred in the cohort and their relationship with individual risk factors observed many years previously has become available. Here, the metabolic syndrome working group reports some interesting findings. With the aim of communicating up-to-date information that has undergone expert review, the coordinator of the cardiac rehabilitation working group has the responsibility of summarizing, evaluating and updating the scientific data available on the important subject of the secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grima-Serrano, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo-Fernández, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Porrero, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Latre, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Sección de Cardiología Preventiva y Rehabilitación de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología ha de ser una importante referencia científica nacional en el conocimiento de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular de los españoles, la incidencia y la prevalencia de la enfermedad cardiovascular en España y la forma de prevenir su aparición y, mediante la rehabilitación cardiaca, mejorar la calidad de vida y la supervivencia de todos los que ya la han padecido. La investigación en prevención cardiovascular debe potenciarse auspiciando la elaboración de registros sobre los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y la presencia de la enfermedad. El estudio MESYAS es un buen ejemplo de ello. Es el fruto del esfuerzo de los miembros del grupo de trabajo sobre síndrome metabólico de nuestra sección, que intenta responder a varias incógnitas que se planteaban sobre su incidencia, su prevalencia y sus consecuencias en nuestra población. Ahora, con más de 5 años de seguimiento de esa cohorte, disponemos ya de los primeros análisis sobre los episodios cardiovasculares que han acontecido en ella y su relación con los factores de riesgo individuales detectados años atrás. El grupo de trabajo de síndrome metabólico nos presenta esos interesantes resultados. En el interés de trasladar el conocimiento actualizado y asimilado por expertos, el coordinador del grupo de trabajo de rehabilitación cardiaca se encarga de sintetizar, ponderar y poner al día la información científica disponible en esa importante área de la prevención secundaria cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(supl.1): 66-72, 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123041</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiología preventiva y rehabilitación cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
