<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104860</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of the dipeptide N(2)-L-Alanyl-L-glutamine in traumatic patients admitted to the ICU; a prospective, randomized, double-blind, multicentre study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypothesis: the endovenous administration of glutamine, independently of the type of nurtrition received, can reduce the ICU length of stay, the incidence of infections and the mortality in the traumatic patients admitted to the ICU. Objectives: The main objective is to assess the efficacy of glutamine suplementation, given intravenously, to reduce the incidence of infectious complications, mortality and ICU length of stay in the traumatic patients admitted to the ICU. Other objectives are: 1) to assess the efficacy of glutamine in different groups of patients according to the severity and the plasma levels of glutamine. 2) Record all the adverse events due to the intravenous administration of glutamine. Methods: prospective, randomized, doble-blind and multicenter study with two parallel groups: placebo and treatment group. The patients who fulfill the inclusion criteria will receive either glutamine or placebo, independently of the type on nutrition. Glutamine will be administered as a pharmaco nutrient at 0.5 g/kg/day during 5days as a continous perfusion.  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cervera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raurich, JMª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Lorenzo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frontera, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llompart-Pou, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marsé, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Bárcena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hipótesis: La suplementación endovenosa con el dipéptido N(2)-L-alanil-L-glutamina, en pacientes traumáticos ingresado en la UCI puede ejercer un efecto beneficioso en cuanto a reducción de la incidencia de infecciones, de la estancia en UCI y de la mortalidad, independientemente del tipo de nutrición (enteral o parenteral) administrada. Objetivos: El objetivo principal es medir la eficacia de la suplementación con el dipéptido, administrado deforma endovenosa, en reducir la incidencia de las complicaciones infecciosas, la mortalidad y la estancia en UCI de los pacientes traumáticos ingresados en la UCI. Otros objetivos secundarios son: 1) Evaluar la eficacia de L-alanil-L-glutamina en diferentes grupos de gravedad y en relación con los niveles plasmáticos de glutamina. 2) Recoger los posibles efectos adversos del dipéptido administrado de forma endovenosa. Metodología: Ensayo clínico prospectivo, multicéntrico, aleatorizado y doble ciego, con dos grupos paralelos de tratamiento, para evaluar eficacia frente a placebo. Los pacientes traumáticos ingresados en la UCI que cumplan los criterios de inclusión/no exclusión, serán aleatorizados para recibir L-alanil-L-glutamina o placebo, independientemente del tipo de nutrición que reciba el paciente (enteral o parenteral) El dipéptido será administrado como un fármaco nutriente en forma de perfusión continua durante 24 horas y durante 5 días a 0,5 g/kg/día(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(1): 116-122, ene.-feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104860</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del dipéptido N(2)-L-Alanil-L-glutamina en los pacientes traumáticos ingresados en la UCI; estudio prospectivo, multicéntrico, aleatorizado y doble ciego; hipótesis y protocolo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6117^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4207^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
