<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139214</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuing medical education: How to write multiple choice questions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evaluating professional competence in medicine is a difficult but indispensable task because it makes it possible to evaluate, at different times and from different perspectives, the extent to which the knowledge, skills, and values required for exercising the profession have been acquired. Tests based on multiple choice questions have been and continue to be among the most useful tools for objectively evaluating learning in medicine. When these tests are well designed and correctly used, they can stimulate learning and even measure higher cognitive skills. Designing a multiple choice test is a difficult task that requires knowledge of the material to be tested and of the methodology of test preparation as well as time to prepare the test. The aim of this article is to review what can be evaluated through multiple choice tests, the rules and guidelines that should be taken into account when writing multiple choice questions, the different formats that can be used, the most common errors in elaborating multiple choice tests, and how to analyze the results of the test to verify its quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Méndez Díaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la competencia profesional en medicina es una tarea difícil pero indispensable porque permite, en diferentes momentos y desde distintas perspectivas, valorar en qué medida se han adquirido los conocimientos, habilidades, actitudes y valores necesarios para el ejercicio profesional. Las pruebas basadas en preguntas de opciones múltiples han sido y son, una de las herramientas más útiles y utilizadas para evaluar de forma objetiva el aprendizaje en medicina. Cuando están bien diseñadas y se aplican de forma correcta, además de estimular el aprendizaje, pueden incluso medir habilidades cognitivas superiores. Redactar un cuestionario de preguntas con opciones de respuesta múltiple es una tarea difícil que requiere conocimientos sobre la materia que se ha de valorar, aprendizaje de una metodología y tiempo para su elaboración. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar lo que las preguntas de opciones múltiples pueden evaluar, las reglas y normas que deben tenerse en cuenta para su redacción, los distintos formatos que pueden utilizarse, los errores más frecuentes que suelen cometerse en su elaboración y como analizar los resultados de los exámenes para poder verificar su calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);55(supl.1): s28-s36, jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación continuada. Cómo redactar preguntas con opciones de respuesta múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15354^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
