<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120717</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety sensitivity and choking under pressure: Effects on sport performance in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to examine dispositional anxiety sensitivity and positive and negative affectivity as moderators of choking in sport. One hundred high school students (66% were females) completed the Childhood Anxiety Sensitivity Index (CASI) and the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule for Children and Adolescents (PANASN) prior to completing a badminton set in low-pressure and high-pressure conditions. A series of ANOVAs supported the hypothesis that anxiety sensitivity, but not positive or negative affectivity, acts as a moderator of the choking effect under psychological pressure; participants with high anxiety sensitivity showed a dramatic drop on sport performance during the high-pressured condition. The present study extends the choking literature including the anxiety sensitivity as a new relevant variable in this field of sport and physical activity psychology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sandín, Bonifacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorot, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio consistió en examinar la sensibiidad a la ansiedad y la afectividad positiva y negativa como posibles factores moduladores del choking (caída del rendimiento deportivo asociado a la presión psicológica). Participaron 100 estudiantes de secundaria (el 66% eran mujeres), los cuales cumplimentaron el Childhood Anxiety Sensitivity Index (CASI) y el Positive and Negative Affect Schedule para Niños y Adolescentes (PANASN) antes de participar en un set de bádminton en condiciones de baja y alta presión. Los datos basados en ANOVAs apoyan la hipótesis de que la sensibilidad a la ansiedad, pero no la afectividad positiva o negativa, actúa como modulador del deterioro del rendimiento deportivo inducido por la condición de alta presión; los participantes con elevado nivel de sensibilidad a la ansiedad experimentaron una caída dramática en el rendimiento deportivo durante la condición de alta presión. El presente estudio amplía la literatura sobre el fenómeno del choking incluyendo la sensibilidad a la ansiedad como nueva variable relevante en el campo de la psicología de la actividad física y el deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(1): 45-54, ene.-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad a la ansiedad y presión psicológica: Efectos sobre el rendimiento deportivo en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
