<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90079</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Möbius syndrome: misoprostol as a teratogenic?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Möbius syndrome (Moebius syndrome) is an infrequent congenital disorder characterized by facial and abducens nerve palsy as well as the external ocular motor palsy. It is associated with other craniofacial and orthopedic anomalies. Its etiology is still unclear, although in its appearance teratogenics agents such as misoprostol have been related. Misoprostol&#146;s etiopathogenic mechanism would be explained due to a secondary vascular disruption due to the vasoconstrictor effect of the medication, in the level of the area of the brain stem. Here we report a newborn with the Möbius syndrome whose mother had used misoprostol as an abortive during the first trimester of pregnancy. There has been a large number of Möbius syndrome associated with the use of misoprostol due to abortion attempt during the last years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Liarte, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moliner Calderón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Borau, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginovart Galiana, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Moebius (SM) es una alteración congénita poco frecuente, caracterizada por la parálisis del nervio facial y del motor ocular externo, asociada a otras malformaciones craneofaciales y musculoesqueléticas. Su etiología no está clara, aunque en su aparición se asocian algunos agentes teratógenos, como el misoprostol. El mecanismo etiopatogénico se explicaría por la disrupción vascular secundaria al efecto vasoconstrictor del fármaco, en el territorio troncoencefálico. A continuación se describe el caso de un recién nacido afectado de SM, cuya madre usó misoprostol con fines abortivos durante el primer trimestre de la gestación. En los últimos años se ha documentado un número cada vez mayor de casos de SM asociados a esta práctica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(4): 189-192, abr. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Moebius: ¿misoprostol como teratógeno?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37657^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34300^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34300^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34300^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34294^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29962^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11475^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34300^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29962^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34300^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33348^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34294^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
