<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048994</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of anthropological forensic study to the juridical qualification of a violent death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Identification of a corpse in a bad condition can be    complicated due to taphonomical processes and active    decomposition on human remains. The combination of    classical autopsy techniques, characteristic of the study of a    recent corpse, and legal anthropology analysis, is    fundamental in order to determine the type of lesions, the    mechanism, its evolution and, as in this case, to allow a    juridical qualification.    In this paper we describe the case of an unidentified    corpse, partially burned that appeared in the open air in a    waste area. External examination showed the coexistence of    carbonization, mummification, skeletal reduction and active    decomposition zones. Autopsy showed the existence of    stitches at abdominal level as an individual trait and, as signs    of violence, a multiple craneal traumatism. A skeleton has    been made with the human remains and an anthropological    and odontological study was carried out. Starting from these    analysis we obtained information about the age, sex, height    and also peculiar morphological and odontological traits.    These researches, in the light of the autopsy's results, have    been compared with the information about missing people    supplied by police. Finally, the identification was possible.    The pattern of the skull's fracture allowed to arrange in    sequence the lesions and to consider them to the repeated    action of a blunt instrument such as a hammer. The    chronology of the lesions, based on the pattern of    interruption of irradiated fractures, permit to assure that the    first hammer's blow was made on the cráneoum's rear. This    has been qualified as a treacherous act and increased the    murderer's penalty requested by the public attorney</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Subirana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordana, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galtés, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malgosa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La identificación de un cadáver en "mal estado"    puede ser complicada a causa de los procesos tafonómicos    y putrefactivos que ha sufrido. La combinación de las técnicas    de autopsia clásicas, específicas de un cadáver    reciente, además de los análisis en antropología forense    son fundamentales para determinar el tipo de lesiones,    mecanismo de producción, evolución y, como en este caso,    para la calificación jurídica.    Presentamos el caso de un cadáver no identificado y    parcialmente incinerado aparecido en un descampado. El    examen externo evidenció la coexistencia de zonas de carbonización,    momificación, reducción esquelética y descomposición    activa. La autopsia reveló la existencia de puntos    de sutura a nivel abdominal como signos individualizadores    y como signos de violencia un traumatismo craneoencefálico    múltiple. Los restos fueron esqueletizados y se    efectuó un estudio antropológico y odontológico. A partir    de estos análisis se obtuvo información sobre la edad,    sexo, talla además de rasgos morfológicos y odontológicos    particulares. Estos hallazgos, además de los proporcionados    por la autopsia, se contrastaron con la información de    la policía sobre individuos desaparecidos y finalmente    pudo identificarse. El patrón de fractura craneal permitió    secuenciar el orden de las lesiones que fueron atribuidos a    la acción repetitiva de un objeto contundente como un    martillo. La cronología lesional, basada en el patrón de    interrupción de las fracturas craneales irradiadas, permitió    asegurar que el primer impacto del martillo fue en la    zona posterior del cráneo y sirvió de base para la calificación    de traición como agravante de la pena solicitada por    el Ministerio Fiscal para el homicida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;11(42): 293-305, oct. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia del estudio antropológico forense para la calificación jurídica de una muerte violenta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23151^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
