<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153929</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Persistent psychotic symptoms after long-term heavy use of mephedrone: A two-case series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mephedrone (4-methylmethcathinone) is a synthetic stimulant drug of the cathinone class. Similar effects to those of cocaine and ecstasy are reported by users, with a high addictive potential. Given its increasing rate of consumption in Europe, it is getting more and more attention from the addiction field. In spite of that, little is known about the long-term consequences of prolonged heavy use. The two following cases might depict some of them. Case 1 was a middle-age man who reported three years of intravenous use of mephedrone. He used to binge for several days in a row. Psychotic symptoms appeared after a few months, especially paranoid delusions. Sent to aftercare in a therapeutic community, delusions kept reappearing after prolonged abstinence. A good response to risperidone was observed. Case 2 was a young man who used mephedrone heavily for two years, always snorted. Upon admission to the therapeutic community, the patient reported auditory hallucinations that partially remitted with olanzapine. Both cases showed a good insight and no personality deterioration. Given its similarities to other substances that are known to induce psychotic symptoms, and the increasing consumption of mephedrone around Europe, similar cases are expected in the near future. Conventional antipsychotic treatment seems a reasonable pharmacological approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fábregas, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaskell, Matthew</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilardell, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goti, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mefedrona (4-methylmethcathinone) es un estimulante sintético del grupo de las catinonas. Los usuarios refieren efectos similares a los de la cocaína y el éxtasis, con un potencial adictivo elevado. Dada la creciente tasa de consumo en Europa, cada vez recibe más atención desde el campo de las adicciones. No obstante, poco se sabe sobre las consecuencias a largo plazo de su consumo abusivo. Los dos siguientes casos pueden servir para mostrar alguna de ellas. El caso 1 es un hombre de mediana edad, quien refería un consumo intravenoso de mefedrona de 3 años de duración. Su patrón de uso consistía en atracones que duraban varios días. Tras varios meses de consumo, aparecieron síntomas psicóticos, especialmente delirios paranoides. Tras ser enviado a una comunidad terapéutica, los síntomas psicóticos se continuaron produciendo pese a mantener una abstinencia prolongada. Se observó una buena respuesta a la risperidona. El caso 2 es un hombre joven, con un consume abusivo de 2 años de duración, vía nasal. A su llegada a la comunidad terapéutica, el paciente refirió alucinaciones auditivas que remitieron parcialmente con olanzapina. Ambos casos mostraron una buena conciencia de enfermedad, así como ausencia de deterioro en su personalidad.  Dadas las similitudes bioquímicas con otras sustancias con potencial para inducir síntomas psicóticos, y el creciente consumo de mefedrona en Europa, casos similares son esperables en un futuro cercano. El uso de antipsicóticos convencionales parece una estrategia razonable de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(3): 154-157, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153929</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas psicóticos persistentes después del uso abusivo prolongado de mefedrona: una serie de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12041^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12041^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8869^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
