<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73948</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The tendency during the last meetings of the American Heart Association (AHA) and European Resuscitation Council(ERC) has been to minimize both maneuvers in advanced cardiac life support (ACLS) as well as the use of drugs. Thus, the number or type of drugs used in cardiopulmonary resuscitation(CPR) is being increasingly reduced. In spite of it, the urgency of their use makes it necessary for us to know the exact doses to administer, method and moment. Therefore, a rapid guide to the use of these drugs in CPR has been elaborated, that is adapted to its use in the Primary Care Emergency Service. This guide demonstrates the possible administration routes, dose for an adult individual as well as some precautions to bear in mind during its use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Esteban, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente-Rodrígueza, A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyos-Valencia, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora-Sáez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevillano-Marcos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante las últimas reuniones de la American Heart Association (AHA) y el European Resuscitation Council(ERC), la tendencia es la de minimizar tanto las maniobrasen soporte vital avanzado (SVA), como el uso de fármacos. Por ello, cada vez más, se van simplificando el número o tipo de fármacos que se usan en reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP). A pesar de ello, la premura de su utilización hace necesario que conozcamos las dosis exactas, el modo y el momento en que deben administrarse. Por todo esto, se elaboró una guía rápida de uso de estos fármacos usados en RCP adecuada para la utilización que se podría hacer en el Servicio de Urgencias de Atención Primaria (SUAP),en la que se muestran las posibles vías de administración, la dosis para un individuo adulto, así como algunas precauciones que deben tenerse en cuenta en su utilización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(8): 376-379, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía rápida de fármacos en soporte vital avanzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
