<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142500</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teen mother and newborn nutritional status in a group of teenagers of the city of Medellin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: in developing countries, including Colombia, teen pregnancy is a public health problem. It brings social, health and nutritional consequences for the mother/son binomial. Objective: to assess demographic, socioeconomic, food security, health and nutritional status characteristics in a group of pregnant teenagers and their newborns. Methodology: a cross sectional analytical study was performed in 294 pregnant teenagers in their third trimester of pregnancy enrolled in the prenatal care programs of the public network of hospitals in Medellin-Colombia between 2011 and 2012. Association between the mother´s body mass index, iron nutritional status and newborn´s weight at birth using explicative variables was assessed. Results: monthly incomes under a minimum salary were associated with low mother´s weight and newborns small for gestational age. Low gestational weight was higher in pregnant women under 15 years of age and with a gynecological age under five years. The prevalence of anemia was low in the first trimester and increased at the end of pregnancy; 5.6% had adequate iron reserves. Low weight at birth was associated with infections and mother´s low weight in the third trimester of pregnancy. Conclusion: teenage pregnancy is a complex problem associated with negative effects in the nutritional, health and social status of the girl and their newborn (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra Sosa, Beatriz Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancur Arrovaye, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Vásquez, Luz Estela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo-Mesa, Sandra Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapata López, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en los países en vía de desarrollo, entre ellos Colombia, el embarazo adolescente es un problema de salud pública por sus consecuencias sociales, de salud y nutrición para el binomio madre-hijo. Objetivo: evaluar las características demográficas, socioeconómicas, de seguridad alimentaria, de salud y el estado nutricional en un grupo de gestantes adolescentes y sus recién nacidos. Métodos: se realizó un estudio analítico de corte transversal con 294 embarazadas adolescentes en el tercer trimestre de gestación del programa de control prenatal de la Red Pública Hospitalaria de Medellín-Colombia, durante 2011-2012. Se buscó la asociación del índice de masa corporal materno, estado nutritivo del hierro y peso al nacer del neonato con variables explicativas. Resultados: los ingresos económicos mensuales inferiores a un salario mínimo se asociaron con bajo peso materno y con recién nacidos pequeños para la edad gestacional. El bajo peso gestacional se presentó en mayor proporción en las gestantes de 15 años o menos y con una edad ginecológica inferior a cinco años. La prevalencia de anemia fue baja en el primer trimestre y aumentó significativamente al final del embarazo; 90% presentaron reservas inadecuadas de hierro. El bajo peso al nacer se asoció con la presencia de infecciones y el bajo peso materno en el tercer trimestre de gestación. Conclusión: la gestación adolescente es un problema complejo que se asocia con efectos negativos en el estado nutricional, de salud y social de la mujer y su recién nacido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1300-1307, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142500</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional materno y neonatal en un grupo de adolescentes de la ciudad de Medellín</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
