<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159322</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of families: environmental and cultural factors associated with overweight and obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Determine whether overweight and obesity in family members are related to environmental and cultural factors regarding the functioning of families. Method: Descriptive Correlational Study. The sample consisted of 198 family members. A General Data Card, a Scale to Evaluate Intra-family Relations, the Food Selection Questionnaire, and the Physical Activity Questionnaire were used. Results: 8.6% of the participants 18 years old or older were overweight, and 46.5% had some degree of obesity. The Body Mass Index of adults was related to total kilocalories as a product of physical activity (rs=.594; p&lt;.01) and with the subscales, eating ecology (rs=.160; p&lt;.05) and nutritional value (rs=.242; p&lt;.01). Cultural values were not associated with the Body Mass Index (rs=.242; p&gt;.01). Conclusions: In this sample, Overweight/Obesity was associated with environmental factor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Landeros Olvera, Erick Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Valverde, Juana Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guevara Valtier, Milton Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez Reyna, María Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Morales, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández del Ángel, Martha Arely</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si el sobrepeso y la obesidad en los integrantes de la familia están relacionados con los factores ambientales y culturales relativos al funcionamiento de la familia. Método: Estudio descriptivo correlacional. La muestra fue constituida por 198 integrantes de familias. Se aplicaron una Cédula de Datos Generales, una Escala para Evaluar las Relaciones Intrafamiliares, el Cuestionario de Elección de Alimentos y el Cuestionario de Actividad Física. Resultados: El 8.6% de los participantes mayores de 18 años presentó sobrepeso y el 46.5% algún grado de obesidad. El índice de masa corporal de los adultos se relacionó con las kilocalorías totales producto de la actividad física (rs=.594; p&lt;.01) y con las subescalas ecología de la alimentación (rs=.160; p&lt;.05) y valor nutritivo (rs=.242; p&lt;.01). Los factores culturales no se asociaron con el índice de masa corporal (rs=.242; p&gt;.01). Conclusiones: En esta muestra el Sobrepeso/Obesidad se asoció con los factores ambientales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(45): 1-10, ene. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159322</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio en familias: factores ambientales y culturales asociados al sobrepeso y obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
