<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124987</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional abnormalities in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nutritional abnormalities are associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease with a frequency ranging from 2 to 50%, depending on the geographical area and the study design. Diagnostic tools include anthropometry, bioelectrical impedance, dual energy radioabsortiometry and deuterium dilution, being the body mass and the lean mass indices the most frequently used parameters. While the most important consequences of nutritional abnormalities are muscle dysfunction and exercise limitation, factors implicated include an imbalance between caloric intake and consumption, and between anabolic and catabolic hormones, inflammation, tobacco smoking, poor physical activity, hypoxemia, some drugs and aging/comorbidities. The most important molecular mechanism for malnutrition associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease appears to be the mismatching between protein synthesis and breakdown. Among the therapeutic measures proposed for these nutritional abnormalities are improvements in lifestyle and nutritional support, although the use of anabolic drugs (such as secretagogues of the growth hormone) offers a new therapeutic strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barreiro, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez LLorens, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica asocia alteraciones del estado nutricional, con prevalencia variable (2-50%) dependiendo de la zona geográfica y el diseño del estudio. Entre los instrumentos diagnósticos destacan la antropometría, la impedancia bioeléctrica, la radioabsorciometría de doble energía y la dilución de deuterio, siendo los índices de masa corporal y de masa magra las variables más utilizadas. Las consecuencias más importantes de las alteraciones nutricionales son la disfunción muscular y la limitación al ejercicio, y los factores que se han implicado en su aparición incluyen el desequilibrio entre ingesta y consumo calo´ rico, así como entre hormonas anabólicas y catabólicas, la inflamación, el tabaco, la escasa actividad física, la hipoxemia, algunos fármacos y el envejecimiento comorbilidades. El mecanismo molecular más importante parece ser la pérdida del equilibrio entre síntesis y destrucción proteicas. Entre las medidas terapéuticas destacan la mejora en los hábitos de vida y el soporte nutricional, aunque el uso de fármacos anabolizantes, como las secretagogas de la hormona de crecimiento, está abriendo prometedoras opciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(2): 78-84, jul. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones nutricionales en la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
