<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049976</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of childhood bronchial asthma, 2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors present an update of the most widely accepted preventiva and therapeutic measures in the management of children with bronchial asthma. After pointing out the alarming and increasing morbidity and the need for a broad but individualized approach, they review the available resources for the acute phase, regression period and base therapy. The measures for modifying the predisposing factors, the management of the symptoms (antileukotrienes, corticosteroids) and the possible defensas against environmental factors and treatment of the underlying causes (reduction or elimination of allergens, immunotherapy) are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Hernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se resume la actualización de las medidas preventivas y terapéuticas más consolidadas en el cuidado del asma bronquial infantil. Se parte de la creciente y alarmante morbilidad y de la necesidad de un enfoque terapéutico amplio pero individualizado, revisando sucesivamente los recursos en la fase aguda, el período de regresión y la terapéutica básica. Se distinguen las medidas para modificar los factores predisponentes, el tratamiento sintomático (broncodilatadores) y patogénico (antileucotrienos, corticoides), los recursos frente a los factores ambientales y el tratamiento etiológico (reducción o eliminación de alérgenos, inmunoterapia)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(7): 323-327, jul. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del asma bronquial infantil, 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
