<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166726</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Active search contributes to the identification of adverse events and incidents in intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Analyze adverse events and incidentes in the intensive care unit of a university hospital and check which portion of the active search contribuition in identifying occurrences. Methods: Retrospective study, documentary of nature quantitative. Results: It was recorded 253 events/incidents, of which 239 (94%) were recorded by active search. Injury pressure was the incident more frequently (n=88; 34.78%) and affected more patients (n= 54; 48.9%). It was found that 136 (53.8%) events/incidents were mild. Conclusion: The active search has proved to be a management strategy that corroborated so substantially to the identification of risk situations in the intensive care unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvalho, Ariana Rodrigues Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges, Fabieli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Reginaldo Passoni dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luz, Mayara Aparecida Passaura da</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar los eventos adversos e incidentes en la unidad de cuidados intensivos de un hospital universitario y comprobar cuál es la parte de contribuición de la búsqueda activa en la identificación de las ocurrencias. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo, documental cuantitativo. Resultados: Se registraron 253 eventos/incidentes, de los cuales 239 (94%) fueron registrados por búsqueda activa. Lesión por presión fue el incidente con más frecuencia (n=88; 34,78%) y afectó a más pacientes (n=54; 48,9%). Se observó que 136 (53,8%) eventos/incidentes fueron leves. Conclusión: La búsqueda activa ha demostrado ser una estrategia de gestión que corrobora sustancialmente a la identificación de situaciones de riesgo en la unidad de cuidados intensivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(48): 465-475, oct. 2017. tab, ^graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Búsqueda activa contribuye a la identificación de eventos adversos e incidentes en unidad de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12720^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
