<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041163</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caspase-1 as a radio and chemosensitizer regardless of JNK and p38 pathways</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The cytotoxic effect of anticancer drugs has been shown to involve induction of apoptosis. This observationraises the possibility that factors affecting caspase activation might be important determinants as anticancerdrug sensitivity. Ectopic expression of caspase-1 has been shown to trigger apoptosis. Here, we examine theeffect of caspase-1 over-expression on the response to chemotherapy and radiotherapy. Caspase-1 expressionmediated by an adenoviral vector was able to kill directly cells and to sensitize the remaining cells to cisplatinor ã-radiation in vitro. In HeLa cells stably transfected with caspase-1, sensitisation to cisplatin was due to anamplification of the cisplatin-induced mitochondrial apoptotic pathway activation but this effect is independentof p53, JNK or p38 status</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vassaux, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Losa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancheño-Corvo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintanilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Duque, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco-Álvarez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Barahona, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El efecto citotóxico de las drogas antitumorales es producido mediante la inducción de apoptosis. Esta observaciónimplica la posibilidad de que los factores que afecten la activación de caspasas pueden ser determinantesimportantes como sensibilizantes a los tratamientos antitumorales. Aquí, examinamos el efecto de la sobreexpresiónde caspasa-1 en la respuesta a la quimio y radioterapia. La expresión de la caspasa-1 mediada porun vector adenoviral fue capaz de matar directamente a las células y de sensibilizar las restantes a cisplatino oradiación gamma in vitro. En células HeLa transfectadas establemente con caspasa-1, la sensibilización a cisplatinofue debida a una amplificación en la vía mitocondrial de apoptosis inducida por cisplatino pero esteefecto es independiente del estado de p53, JNK o p38 en la célula</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;28(8): 394-406, ago. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041163</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La actividad de la Caspasa-1 como gen sensibilizador a radio y quimioterapia es independiente de las vías de JNK y p38</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2971^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12279^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33827^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
