<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137967</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin E nutritional status assessment in a group of elder in Havana</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Scientific evidence supports there is an association between inadequate vitamin E intake and development of chronic diseases such as coronary heart disease and several types of cancer. The objective of this paper is to analyse vitamin E nutritional status in a random population sample of elder in Havana. Methods: A cross-sectional study was designed for this purpose. Three municipalities in Habana according to economical and health status were selected. The sample was randomized by age and gender and cosisted of 442 adults older than 60 years. Vitamin E as well as lipid fractions were assessed for adjustment of vitamin E levels. By means of epidemiological survey, general background data and environmental exposure information was collected. Dietary intake was assessed in a subgroup of elder. Results: Mean vitamin E levels were 1,12 mgldl, 2,5% 01 individuals showed a high risk of deficiency. There was a significant difference among municipalities (p=O.OOOJ, with poorest results in the municipality with the worst economical situation. Risk of deficiency levels were more common in men (p=O,OOOL Vitamin E intake was significantly low and above 80% of the sample showed intake levels below 90% of daily recommended dietary intake. Analysis of the median stratified by gender showed no significant difference between smokers and non smokers. Conclusion: Main factors influencing vitamin E status are socioeconomic condition, which can be modified, and gender, which can not be modified but should be considered when designing nutrition education interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martin González, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Triana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita, Gisela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, Alejandrina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Existen evidencias científicas de la relación entre una dieta inadecuada de vitamina E y la aparición de enfermedades crónicas y degenerativas; en particular la cardiopatía coronaría y diversos tipos de cáncer. El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar el estado de la vitamina E de un grupo de ancianos representativos de la población de Ciudad de la Habana. Métodos: Se diseñó un estudio transversal donde se seleccionaron tres municipios de Ciudad de la Habana de acuerdo a la situación socioeconómica y de salud. La muestra se aleatorizó por grupos de edad y sexo, estando constituida por 442 adultos mayores de 60 años. Se determinó vitamina E y fracciones lipídicas para el ajuste de los valores de vitamina E; se tomaron datos generales y de exposición ambiental mediante encuesta epidemiológica y se realizó evaluación dietética de un subgrupo de los ancianos.  Resultados: los resultados muestran una media de vitamina E de 1,12 mgldl, con alto riesgo de deficiencia en el 2,5% de los individuos. Existió diferencia significativa entre los municipios (p=O.OOO), con valores más bajos en el municipio de peor situación socioeconómica. Se encontró diferencia significativa entre sexos (p=O,OOO), con predominio de valores deficientes en el sexo masculino. La ingestión de la vitamina E mostró niveles significativamente bajos y más del 80% de la población estudiada mostró niveles de ingestión inferiores al 90% de la recomendación diaria. Al realizar el análisis de mediana estratificado por sexo no se encontraron diferencias entre fumadores y no fumadores. Conclusión: los principales factores que afectan el estado nutricional en vitamina E son la situación socioeconómica, modificable, y el sexo, factor no modificable a tener en cuenta en los programas de educación nutricional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;10(3): 114-120, sept. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación nutricional de la vitamin E de un grupo de adultos mayors de Ciudad de la Habana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15212^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15211^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
