<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117342</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The human being and the genesis of community nursing work</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It describes the origin of nursing work and its relationship with human beings according to cultural context where it is performed. It exams terms that are socially interpreted and accepted and that are full of meanings according to Western hegemonic medical model. It also discusses the concept of man and the apparent contradiction between universality and particular diversity . Concepts, from the point of care, beyond the purely biological that allow to build a network of meanings with a psychological and social origin and continually reinvent themselves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Riera, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez Arias, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el origen del trabajo enfermero y su relación con el ser humano de acuerdo al contexto cultural donde se realiza. Se examinan términos que son interpretados y aceptados socialmente y que están repletos de significados de acuerdo al modelo médico hegemónico occidental. Así mismo se analiza el concepto de ser humano y la aparente contradicción entre universalidad y diversidad particular. Conceptos que, desde la óptica del cuidado, trascienden lo puramente biológico y  permiten construir toda una red de significados de orden psicológico y social y que se reinventan continuamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(36): 59-65, mayo-ago. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117342</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ser humano y la génesis del trabajo enfermero comunitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
