<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111804</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The snapping scapula as a sympton of a tumor in the scapulothoracic region</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The snapping scapula syndrome is a grating sensation located in the scapulothoracic region that appears with movement.This sign is occasionally related to tumors. Objective. To show the high incidence of this relationship (clinical sign-tumor), and to be aware of it when performing a differential diagnosis. Material and method. Retrospective study of the elastofibromas dorsi (ED) and scapular osteochondromas (SO), which may have presented with the sign under study in our center over the last 17 years (1993-2009). Thirty-seven ED and 6 SO were identified. The series was divided into group A (ED) and group B (SO). Mean follow-up was 7 years. The cohorts are made up of 23 women and 4 men with a mean age of 57 years (42-78) in group A, there were 2 women and 4 men with a mean age of 20 years (11-28) in group B. Action was taken to identify the initial medical sign at diagnosis, the treatment carried out, and the outcome. Results. Around 21% of these tumors are reported to be associated with physical activity. The initial symptom was a painful mass in 81% of the patients, followed by a scapular snapping or clicking in 30 out of the 43 patients (70%). The treatment of choice was resection in both groups. A noticeable improvement in terms of pain was seen (VAS 7.5 preoperatively, 2.8 postoperatively). Conclusion. The presence of snapping scapula has a strong relationship to tumors of the scapulothoracic region. Therefore it is important to be aware of this (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abat, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivera, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trullols, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grácia, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El chasquido escapular es un crujido localizado en la región escapulotorácica que aparece con los movimientos. Este signo clínico está relacionado en ocasiones con los tumores escapulares. Objetivo. Mostrar la alta incidencia de esta relación (tumor escapular-chasquido) para recordar la misma al realizar el diagnóstico diferencial. Material y método. Estudio retrospectivo de elastofibromas dorsi (ED) y osteocondromas escapulares (OE), que puedan presentar el signo clínico a estudio, en nuestro centro en los últimos 17 años (1993-2009). Se han identificado 37 ED y 6 OE. El tiempo medio de seguimiento ha sido de 7 años. Se ha divido la serie en grupo A (ED) y grupo B (OE). Las cohortes las forman, en el grupo A: 23 mujeres y 4 varones, media de 57 años (42-78), y en el grupo B: 2 mujeres y 4 varones, media de 20 años (11-28). Se ha procedido a identificar el signo clínico inicial al diagnóstico, el tratamiento realizado y la evolución. Resultados. Se reporta una asociación entre la actividad física y la presencia de estas tumoraciones del 21%. La clínica inicial fue una masa dolorosa en el 81% de los pacientes, y un chasquido escapular en el 70% (30 de 43). El tratamiento de elección fue la exéresis en ambos grupos, obteniendo una notable mejoría en el dolor (VAS: 7,5 preoperatorio; 2,8 postoperatorio). Conclusión. La presencia de chasquido escapular tiene una fuerte relación con los tumores de la región escapulotorácica, por lo que debemos conocer esta asociación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(2): 123-128, mar.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111804</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El chasquido escapular como síntoma de un tumor de la región escapulotorácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
