<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119473</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening and early care programmes in children with autism spectrum disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The need for effective methods of detection and treatment in the early stages of autism spectrum disorders is something that is currently accepted both by professional societies and by the healthcare authorities alike. Up-to-date comprehensive information about the screening procedures and early care techniques for children with autism spectrum disorders would make it easier to implement better detection devices as well as easing the job of counselling families and professionals about care and intervention at early ages in children. Development. This study offers an updated review of the procedures for early detection and early care in autism, while reflecting the most relevant aspects that can be deduced from the experiments and studies conducted to date. Conclusions. The review carried out on trials involving the early detection of autism yields a group of important considerations to be taken into account in carry out critical analyses of screening programmes that are already under way, as well as a set of recommendations for future experiments. The review of the early care programmes provides a promising view because studies on the effectiveness of early care programmes are becoming increasingly more frequent, systematic and methodologically more appropriate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Primo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canal Bedia, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Borbujo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Carrera, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Posada De la Paz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La necesidad de la detección y de tratamientos eficaces de forma temprana para los trastornos del espectro autista es algo actualmente aceptado tanto por las sociedades profesionales como por la administración sanitaria. Una información actualizada y sintetizada sobre los procedimientos de cribado y las técnicas de atención temprana para niños con trastornos del espectro autista facilitará la puesta en marcha de mejores dispositivos de detección  la labor de asesoramiento a familias y profesionales sobre la atención e intervención a edades tempranas de los niños. Desarrollo. Se proporciona una revisión actualizada de los procedimientos de detección precoz y de atención temprana en el autismo, reflejando los aspectos más relevantes que se deducen de las experiencias y estudios llevados a cabo hasta el momento. Conclusiones. Tras la revisión realizada sobre las experiencias de detección precoz de autismo, se obtiene un grupo de consideraciones importantes para realizar análisis críticos de programas de cribado en marcha, así como recomendaciones para experiencias futuras. La revisión sobre los programas de atención temprana proporciona una visión esperanzadora porque cada vez son más frecuentes, sistemáticos y metodológicamente más apropiados los estudios sobre la eficacia de los programas de atención temprana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(supl.1): 123-127, feb. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119473</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programas de cribado y atención temprana en niños con trastornos del espectro autista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
