<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132595</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consumption of sweetened, energy and alcoholic beverages among college students in the México-Us Border</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The consumption of sugary, energy and alcoholic drinks among college students might be a health risk factor. Objective: To assess the consumption of sugary, energy and alcoholic drinks and to determine their associations with body mass index (BMI) status among college students. Methods: Second and third year college students enrolled in five different majors at the Universidad Autónoma de Baja California were evaluated. Weight, height and waist circumference were measured and BMI was calculated. A frequency questionnaire of 19 drinks was administered. Results: A total of 1138 students participated in the study. The prevalence of obesity and abdominal obesity was 12 and 33% with 14 and 17% in women and men  respectively. Fifty-five per cent of women and 68% of men consumed more than 25g of sugar drinks per day; 12% consumed more than 100g of sugar daily. The daily caloric intake from beverages was greater than 450kcal with 350kcal in men and women respectively. Ten per cent of women and 15% of men consumed more than 30g of alcohol daily. The sugary drinks more frequently consumed were fruit juices (90%), whole milk (69%), regular soft drinks (83%), beer (37%), liquor (27%) and energy drinks (12%). Conclusions: Consumption of sugary, energy, and alcoholic drinks is very high, which may be a health risk in this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Miranda, Luis Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caravalí Meza, Nuris Yohana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacardí Gascón, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El consumo de bebidas azucaradas, energéticas y alcohólicas en universitarios puede ser un riesgo para la salud. Objetivo: Determinar el consumo de bebidas azucaradas, energéticas, y alcohólicas y compararlo con el estado del IMC en universitarios. Metodología: Se evaluaron estudiantes de segundo y tercer año de la UABC. Se midieron el peso, la talla y la circunferencia de cintura, y se calculó el IMC. Se aplicó un cuestionario sobre consumo de 19 bebidas. Resultados: Participaron 1138 estudiantes. La prevalencia de obesidad y obesidad abdominal fue de 12 y 33% y de 14 y 17% en mujeres y hombres respectivamente. El 55% de las mujeres y el 68% de los hombres consumían más de 25g de azúcar de bebidas al día; 12% consumían más de 100g de azúcar al día. El consumo calórico diario proveniente de bebidas fue mayor de 450 kcal en hombres y de 350kcal en mujeres. Diez por ciento de mujeres y 15% de hombres consumen más de 30g de alcohol diarios. Las bebidas que contienen carbohidratos y que se consumen con mayor frecuencia son los zumos de frutas (90%), la leche entera (69%), los refrescos regulares (83%), las cervezas (37%), los licores (27%) y las bebidas energéticas (12%). Conclusiones: El consumo de bebidas azucaradas, alcohólicas y energéticas es muy alto, lo que podría ser un riesgo para la salud en esta población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(1): 191-195, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de bebidas energéticas, alcohólicas y azucaradas en jóvenes universitarios de la frontera México-USA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54831^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2292^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
