<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95946</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The reason for this exercise was to stress the family&#146;s importance during the patient&#146;s pre &amp; postsurgical period, as well as any anxiety and possible difficulties that could arise when assisting patients during this period. Material and methods: Inquiries from patients and family members received immediately after surgery regarding understanding the information for postsurgical treatment provided by nurses qualified in Ambulatory Surgery. These inquiries were analyzed on a quantitive and quality basis: sex, age, stress, predisposition or healthcare knowledge. Result: The results obtained through these inquiries show the difficulties that relatives are confronted with and the new situation when looking after a patient who has recently undergone ambulatory surgery. The fear of uncontrolled pain or sudden bleeding are two of the many anxieties that relatives who are obliged to look after these patients are faced with. Conclusion: Adequate information is the basic key that nurses have when confronting the caregiver&#146;s anxiety. Care-giving protocols explained by the nursing staff and the capacity of transmitting the necessary information, as well as an optimistic predisposition and enthusiasm on the part of the patient and his relatives, ensures that surgery, undertaken in outpatient surgical surroundings, will be successful, comfortable and secure for patients and caregivers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Carrasco, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de este trabajo es evaluar la importancia de la familia en el circuito pre- y postoperatorio del paciente, así como las inquietudes y dificultades que a estos nuevos cuidadores se les pueden plantear. Material y métodos: Encuestas presentadas en el postoperatorio inmediato al paciente y a la persona que va a responsabilizarse de sus cuidados tras recibir y comprender toda la información dada por el personal de enfermería de CMA. En dichas encuestas se analizan variables tanto cuantitativas como cualitativas: sexo, edad, estrés, predisposición, conocimientos sanitarios, etc. Resultado: Los resultados obtenidos en las encuestas demuestran las dificultades con las que se enfrentan los familiares ante una situación nueva para ellos, que es la de cuidar a una persona recién operada. El miedo a un dolor incontrolable y a un sangrado inesperado son dos de las muchas inquietudes que tienen las personas que asumen cuidar a su familiar. Conclusión: La formación es la herramienta fundamental con la que cuenta la enfermería para enfrentarse a la ansiedad del cuidador.La protocolización de cuidados de enfermería y la capacidad de transmitir la información necesaria para llevarlos a cabo junto a una buena predisposición basada en el optimismo y entusiasmo de la familia y del paciente, hace que la cirugía practicada en régimen ambulatorio sea un éxito en cuanto a seguridad y confort para el paciente y su cuidador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;15(2): 49-52, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95946</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cuidador: elemento fundamental en la atención al paciente en cirugía mayor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
