<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93910</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation of task and ego orientation in sport questionnaire (TEOSQ) to the Mexican population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the study was to analyse the psychometric properties (factor structure and reliability) of the TEOSQ (Task and Ego Orientation in Sport Questionnaire; Duda, 1989) when adapted to the Mexican context and to ascertain whether there were any gender-contingent differences. The questionnaire was distributed to 239 athletes from 14 different kinds of sport competing in the 2008 National Children&#146;s and Youth Olympiad with an age range of 12 to 18 years (M = 14.56, SD = 1.67). The confirmatory factor analysis supported the structure of the instrument obtained in previous studies (Task Orientation and Ego Orientation). The instrument also showed an acceptable internal consistency (a = .85 and a = .85 respectively). Gender differences indicated that girls showed greater task orientation than boys (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meliá, Josep Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tristán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Walle, Jeanette</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue analizar las propiedades psicométricas (estructura factorial y fiabilidad) del TEOSQ (Task and Ego Orientation in Sport Questionnaire, Duda, 1989) adaptado al contexto mexicano, así como conocer si había diferencias en función del género. El cuestionario fue administrado a 239 deportistas con un rango de edad de 12 a 18 años (M = 14.56, DT = 1.67), participantes en la Olimpiada Nacional Infantil y Juvenil 2008, pertenecientes a 14 diferentes disciplinas deportivas. El análisis factorial confirmatorio apoyó la estructura del instrumento obtenida en otros estudios (Orientación a la Tarea y Orientación al Ego). También se obtuvo una adecuada consistencia interna (a = .85 y a = .85 respectivamente). Respecto al género, las chicas mostraron una mayor orientación a la tarea que los chicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;20(2): 523-536, jul.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93910</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación a la población mexicana del Cuestionario de Orientación al Ego y a la Tarea en el Deporte (TEOSQ)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
