<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107186</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pancreatic pseudocyst: less is more</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pancreatic pseudocysts (PQP) are rare in childhood and management tends to be individualized and controversial, and it is a challenge for the pediatric surgeon. The aim of this study is to determinate the best management strategies in each patient. Material and methods: Retrospective review of children admitted to our institution with the diagnosis of PQP and review of literature between 1990 and 2007Results: We report two children with postraumatic PQP that respond to non-operative management and 284 cases that were reported in literature ( 76% after blunt abdominal trauma). 26% of these patients had complete resolution of PQP with conservative management and the others patients required surgical intervention: external percutaneous drainage(18.6%), non-percutanueous external drainage drenaje (3.87%), cystogastrostomy (28.87%), cystojejunostomy o pancreaticojejunostomy(9.5%), endoscopic drainage (9.5%) or distal pancreatectomy (3.5%).Conclusion: The choice of treatment depends on the surgeon&#146;s experience and management of the endoscopic techniques, as well as the availability of interventionist radiology. Asymptomatic PQP in children does no require any specific intervention other than expectant management, especially in patients with trauma-induced PQP. Children with persistent clinical symptoms or those who developed complications may require further intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calleja Aguayo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Ibarz, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martínez-Pardo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Alvira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pseudoquistes pancreáticos (PQP) son poco frecuentes en la infancia, por lo que su manejo es controvertido y supone un reto para el cirujano pediátrico. Nuestro objetivo es establecer unas pautas de actuación y determinar el tipo de tratamiento más indicado en cada paciente. Material y métodos: Revisión retrospectiva de los paciente con PQP atendidos en nuestro Servicio de Cirugía Pediátrica así como los casos publicados en la literatura mundial entre 1990 y 2007.Resultados: Presentamos dos niños con PQP tras un traumatismo abdominal que se resolvieron con tratamiento conservador. En la literatura hemos encontrado 284 casos descritos de niños con PQP, cuyo origen fue traumático en el 76% de los casos. En el 26% de los pacientes el PQP se resolvió con tratamiento conservador y el resto precisó algún tipo de intervención: drenaje percutáneo (18,6%), drenaje externo no percutáneo (3,87%), cistogastrostomía (28,87%), cistoyeyunostomía o pancreático yeyunostomía (9,5%), drenaje endoscópico (transpapilar, transduodenal o transgástrico) (9,.5%) o pancreatectomía distal (3,5%).Conclusión: Pensamos que los PQP asintomáticos, sobre todo de origen traumático, no requiren ninguna intervención y deben ser manejados de manera conservadora. Si aparecen síntomas persistentes o complicaciones, requieren cirugía. La elección del tratamiento dependerá de la experiencia del cirujano y de su manejo de las técnicas endoscópicas, así como de la disponibilidad de radiología intervensionista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;22(2): 55-60, abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107186</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudoquiste pancreático: cuando menos es más</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10380^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
