<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140821</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Up-date in Family Medicine: Use and abuse of drugs. Myths, realities and practical aspects in the primary care consultation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The term pharmacon means remedy and poison. Whether it is considered a remedy or poison depends on the level of purity, the dose and how it is used, accessibility conditions and how its consumption is accepted culturally along with the consumer's physical, mental, emotional and spiritual condition. Every culture has its own permitted and prohibited drugs, that are controlled or only for the use of a few. The terms illegal, prohibited and restricted use are not new to this era. What is currently being seen is that there are some changes taking place in the consumption patterns, basically because of the wide variety of substances available all around us, easier access and younger age of initiation. Tobacco and alcohol continue to be the principal cause of health problems in our environment. Cannabis is the most prevalent illegal drug and cocaine is the drug that generates the most need for medical attention. This article does not discuss illegal drugs, nor is it a comprehensive study of illegal drugs. We will not go into definitions and treatments, it is our attempt to broach the subject from a rational standpoint allowing doctors to have a practical perspective as to how we have reached this point, what are the current street terms and why it is currently so popular amongst our youth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Mateo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustos-Fonseca, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Miñarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El término pharmacon significa remedio y veneno. Que apliquemos un sentido u otro al término depende del grado de pureza, de la dosis y las modalidades de empleo, de las condiciones de acceso y las pautas culturales de consumo, junto al estado físico, emocional, mental y espiritual de quien lo consume. Cada cultura tiene sus drogas permitidas y sus drogas prohibidas, controladas o para el uso de unos pocos. Los términos ilegal, prohibido y de consumo restringido no son exclusivos de nuestra época. En la actualidad, lo que sí se evidencia es una edad de inicio más temprana y cambios en los patrones de consumo, básicamente por la mayor variedad de sustancias en nuestro entorno y más accesibilidad. El tabaco y el alcohol siguen siendo las que más problemas de salud generan en nuestro medio, el cannabis es la droga ilegal más prevalente y la cocaína la que más demandas de atención médica requiere. Este artículo no abordará las drogas legales, no es tampoco un estudio exhaustivo de las ilegales, ni pretende entrar en definiciones o tratamientos. Se trata de abordar el tema desde un punto de vista racional, poniendo al alcance del médico una perspectiva práctica del porqué se llega al consumo, qué términos se usan en la calle y por qué están en auge estas sustancias entre los jóvenes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(2): 91-100, feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en Medicina de Familia: Drogas de uso y abuso. Mitos, realidades y aspectos prácticos en la consulta de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
