<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153995</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of mortality in severe chest trauma in the elderly patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Persons older than 65 years represent about 30% of all cases requiring care for traumatic injury, and is the fifth leading cause of death. Thus, it is considered important to search for epidemiological parameters that can identify this population group. Patients and method. A retrospective, observational, and comparative study was conducted on patients aged 65 years and over admitted to the Intensive Care Unit of tertiary hospital with a primary diagnosis of severe chest trauma between January 1992 and January 2012. A logistic regression was performed to determine the probability of hospital death in relation to the year of hospitalisation. Results. The cohort included 235 patients. Univariate logistic regression analysis showed a gradual decrease in the probability of death over the years, with an OR of 0.95 [95% CI; 0.90 to 0.99] for each year of admission after 1992 (P = .029). The multivariate model showed an association of mortality with patient age (OR: 1.08 for year over 65), the score on the scale APACHE II (OR: 1.1 for each point obtained), and need for mechanical ventilation (OR: 5.36). Conclusions. This study shows a decrease in mortality over the years, with an association that remained after adjustment for different confounding parameters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez-Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñasco, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Borregan, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorca, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las personas con edad igual o mayor a 65 años representan alrededor del 30% de todas las atenciones por enfermedad traumática, constituyendo la quinta causa de muerte en esta población. En este contexto resulta importante el conocimiento de parámetros epidemiológicos en este grupo poblacional. Pacientes y método. Estudio observacional y comparativo con análisis retrospectivo, en la unidad de cuidados intensivos de un hospital terciario. Se incluyó a los pacientes con edad igual o superior a 65 años ingresados entre enero de 1992 y enero de 2012, con diagnóstico principal de traumatismo torácico grave. Se realizó una regresión logística para determinar la probabilidad de muerte intrahospitalaria en relación con el año de ingreso. Resultados. La muestra seleccionada fue de 235 pacientes. El análisis univariante mediante regresión logística mostró una disminución de la probabilidad de muerte de forma progresiva a lo largo de los años, con una OR de 0,95 (IC 95%: 0,90-0,99) por cada año de ingreso posterior a 1992 (p = 0,029). El modelo multivariante mostró asociación de la mortalidad con la edad de los pacientes (OR: 1,08 por cada año por encima de 65), la puntuación en la escala APACHE II (OR: 1,1 por cada punto obtenido) y la necesidad de ventilación mecánica (OR: 5,36). Conclusiones. Nuestro estudio muestra una disminución de la mortalidad a lo largo de los años, cuya relación se mantuvo tras ajustar por diferentes parámetros de confusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(4): 204-211, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153995</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la mortalidad en el traumatismo torácico grave del paciente anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14285^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
