<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165141</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determinants of nutritional status in children under five living in a rural area of Mozambique: a population survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Malnutrition in sub-Saharan Africa contributes to high rates of childhood morbidity and mortality. Little information is available regarding moderate malnutrition prevalence in children under five in rural areas. Methods: To assess nutritional status and the prevalence of malnutrition in children from Ibo Island, Mozambique, a nutritional population survey in children under 5 years was carried out. A structured questionnaire was administered from April 2009 to February 2010. Anthropometric measurements were recorded as z-scores and child nutritional status derived from the World Health Organization Child Growth Standards (WHO) reference population. Results: 3313 people on Ibo were identified and interviewed and nutritional assessment was carried out in the 526 children under five. Most children had been fully vaccinated (90.5%), breastfed (100%), and some were also bottle fed (22.0%). The mean duration of the different feeding regimes were 20.3±4.47 months for breastfeeding, 2.5±0.8 months for exclusive breastfeeding and 3.2±4.0 months for bottle feeding. The mean number of daily meals across the child age range was 2.3±0.5. More stunted children had been exclusively breastfed than mixed fed (p=0.058). Severe stunting was more likely in children in the &amp;#8804;11 (26.3%) and 12-23 (21.2%) month age groups (p=0.007). 13.5% of severely stunted children had not been fully vaccinated (p=0.014), 72.7% ate unassisted (p=0.013) and 64.8% had their own dish to eat from (p=0.001) compared to the non-stunted group. More children from the 46-60 month age group (27.7%) were underweight compared to the other groups (p=0.047). Conclusions: moderate and severe malnutrition, especially stunting, in children under five in a rural setting in Mozambique are still prevalent. Strategies to tackle this problem are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Olivé, F Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilella-Nebot, Maria Eugènia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murphy, Michelle M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abacassamo, Fatima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clark, Benjamin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ismael, Carina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez-Ballart, Joan D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La desnutrición en el África subsahariana contribuye a las elevadas tasas de morbilidad y mortalidad infantil, disponiéndose de poca información sobre la prevalencia moderada de la malnutrición en niños menores de cinco años de las zonas rurales. Métodos: se realizó una encuesta nutricional de población en niños menores de 5 años, para evaluar el estado nutricional y la prevalencia de malnutrición en los niños de Ibo Island, Mozambique. Se administró un cuestionario estructurado de abril de 2009 a febrero de 2010. Las medidas antropométricas se registraron como puntuaciones z y el estado nutricional de los niños se obtuvo de acuerdo a las referencias de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) para el Crecimiento Infantil. Resultados: 3313 personas en Ibo fueron identificadas y entrevistadas. Se realizó una evaluación nutricional en los 526 niños menores de cinco años. La mayoría de los niños habían sido totalmente vacunados (90,5%), amamantados (100,0%) y algunos también alimentados con biberón (22,0%). La duración media de los diferentes regímenes de alimentación fue de 20,3±4,47 meses para la lactancia materna, 2,5±0,8 meses para la lactancia materna exclusiva y 3,2±4,0 meses para la alimentación con biberón. El número medio de comidas diarias en el rango de edad de los niños fue de 2,3±0,5. Los niños más atrofiados habían sido alimentados exclusivamente con leche materna que los alimentados con leche materna (p = 0,058). El retraso en el crecimiento fue más probable en los niños en los grupos &amp;#8804; 11 (26,3%) y 12-23 (21,2%) meses (p = 0,007). El 13,5% de los niños gravemente atrofiados no habían sido vacunados totalmente (p=0,014), el 72,7% no asistió (p=0,013) y el 64,8% tenía su propio plato para comer (p=0,001) en comparación con el grupo no atrofiado. Más niños del grupo de edad de 46-60 meses (27,7%) tenían peso inferior al de los otros grupos (p = 0,047). Conclusiones: la malnutrición moderada y severa, especialmente el retraso en el crecimiento, en niños menores de cinco años en un entorno rural en Mozambique siguen siendo frecuentes. Se requieren estrategias para abordar este problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;22(4): 0-0, oct.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinantes del estado nutricional en niños menores de cinco años que viven en una zona rural de Mozambique: una encuesta de población</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32961^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32961^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
