<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054455</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retroperitoneal laparoscopic lymphadenectomy for stage I non seminomatous testicular cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We report a series of patients with stage I non seminomatous testicular cancer in whom laparoscopic retroperitoneal lymphadenectomy was carried out. METHODS: Between March 1993 and January 2004 100 and patients with the diagnosis of stage I non seminomatous testicular cancer underwent laparoscopic retroperitoneal lymphadenectomy (LRPL). All operations were performed by the same surgeon (O.A.C). Clinical data were collected prospectively in a database. Patients' demographic data, operative time, estimated blood loss, hospital stay, operative and post operative complications, convention rate and follow-up were all analyzed. RESULTS: 111 LRPL were performed in 111 patients with a mean age of 29.3 years (range 15-44 years). 61 procedures were right-LRPL and 50 left-LRPL. Mean operative time was 138 minutes (range 60-300 minutes). Introoperative complications appeared in 10 cases (9%), 9 vascular complications (8.1%) and 1 duodenal lesion (0.9%). Conversion to open surgery was necessary in three patients (2.7%). Mean hospital stay was 43.3 hours (range 24-120). 5 patients (4.5%) had tumor recurrence, with a mean follow-up of 30 months (range 24-94 months). Recurrences were localized in the retroperitoneum, mediastinum and lungs. Recurrence time varied between four and 64 months. CONCLUSIONS: LRPL offers oncological results equivalent to open surgery, with the advantage of being minimally invasive and its consequent decrease in morbidity. The laparoscopic retroperitoneal lymphadenectomy is a good option for the management of patients with stage 1 testicular cancer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Octavio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitagliano, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Salas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS        Se presenta una serie de pacientes con cáncer de testículo no seminoma estadio I sometidos a linfadenectomía retroperitoneal por vía laparoscópica.                 METODOS        Entre marzo de 1993 y enero de 2004, 111 pacientes con diagnóstico de cáncer de testículo no seminomatoso estadio I fueron intervenidos quirúrgicamente por linfadenectomía retroperitoneal laparoscópica (LRP-L). Todos los procedimientos fueron realizados por el mismo cirujano (O.A.C). Los datos clínicos fueron recolectados de forma prospectiva en una base de datos creada para tal fin. Se analizaron la características del grupo de pacientes, tiempo operatorio, sangrado, tiempo de hospitalización, complicaciones operatorias y perioperatorias, tasa de conversión a cirugía abierta y seguimiento.                 RESULTADOS        Se realizaron 111 LRP-L en 111 pacientes con edad promedio de 29.3 años (rango 15-44 años). 61 procedimientos correspondieron a LRP-L derecha y 50 a LRP-L izquierda. El tiempo operatorio promedio fue de 138 minutos (rango 60-300 minutos). Se presentaron complicaciones intraoperatorias en 10 pacientes (9%), de las cuales, 9 correspondieron a lesiones vasculares (8.1%) y 1 a lesión duodenal (0.9%). Se realizo conversión a cirugía abierta en 3 pacientes (2.7%). El tiempo promedio de hospitalización fue de 43.3 horas (rango 24-120). 5 pacientes (4.5%) presentaron recurrencia del tumor, con un seguimiento promedio de 30 meses (rango 24-94 meses). Las recurrencias se ubicaron a nivel retroperitoneal, en mediastino y a nivel pulmonar. El tiempo de recurrencia oscilo entre 4 y 64 meses.                 CONCLUSIONES        La LRP-L ofrece resultados oncológicos equivalentes a los obtenidos con cirugía abierta, con la ventaja de ser mínimamente invasiva y consecuentemente disminuir la morbilidad. La linfadenectomía retroperitoneal laparoscópica es una buena alternativa para el manejo de los pacientes con cáncer de testículo en estadío I</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(1): 59-66, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfadenectomía retroperitoneal laparoscopica en cáncer de testículo no seminoma estadio I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
