<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101992</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care in dementia: satisfaction and needs of the caregiver</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Primary care (PC) and general neurology clinics (NC) assume the leading role in the health care of patients with dementia. There are hardly any studies on the satisfaction of the caregiver at these settings of health care. Methods: A questionnaire was designed and distributed to 75 caregivers of patients with dementia who were reviewed in an NC and who had been referred from PC. The questionnaire included questions associated with the care, the use of services, and satisfaction. Sociodemographic and clinical variables were also collected. The results of the questionnaire are described and a simple correlation analysis (Spearman r) was performed to determine the factors associated with satisfaction.Results: The majority of carers were sons or daughters (60%) or spouses (31%), of which 73% were women. The service most used was home help (36%), but 41% of patients had no services available. Satisfaction was high (84% quite or very satisfied with PC, 97% quite or very satisfied with the NC, P &lt; .01). A greater number of years giving care was associated with a lower satisfaction with PC ((r=&amp;#8722;0.37, P&lt;.005), while institutionalisation was associated with a lower satisfaction with the NC (r=&amp;#8722;0.30, P&lt;.01).Conclusions: In a context of a scarcity of resources, the satisfaction of the caregivers of patients with dementia, as regards health care, was high, possibly due to the motivation of the health professionals and the positive attitude of the caregivers themselves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sastre Paz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olazarán Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La atención primaria (AP) y las consultas de neurología general (CN) asumen la principal carga en la asistencia sanitaria de los pacientes con demencia. Apenas se dispone de estudios acerca de la satisfacción del cuidador con estos ámbitos asistenciales. Métodos: Se diseñó y administró una encuesta a 75 cuidadores de pacientes con demencia que acudieron a revisión a una CN y que habían sido remitidos desde la AP. La encuesta incluía cuestiones relacionadas con los cuidados, la utilización de servicios y la satisfacción. Se recogieron, además, variables sociodemográficas y clínicas, se describieron los resultados de la encuesta y se realizó un análisis de correlaciones simples (r de Spearman) para explorar los factores asociados a la satisfacción. Resultados: Los cuidadores fueron mayoritariamente hijas/os (60%) o cónyuges (31%). El 73% eran mujeres. El servicio más utilizado fue la ayuda en el domicilio (36%), pero el 41% de los pacientes no disponía de ningún servicio. La satisfacción fue alta (84% bastante o muy satisfechos con la AP, 97% bastante o muy satisfechos con la CN, p&lt;0,01). Un mayor número de años cuidando se asoció a una menor satisfacción con la AP (r=&amp;#8722;0,37, p&lt;0,005), mientras que la institucionalización se asoció a una menor satisfacción con la CN (r=&#150;0,30, p&lt;0,01). Conclusiones: En un contexto de escasez de recursos, la satisfacción de los cuidadores de pacientes con demencia respecto de la asistencia sanitaria fue alta, posiblemente debido a la motivación de los profesionales y a la actitud positiva de los cuidadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(4): 189-196, mayo 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asistencia sanitaria en las demencias: satisfacción y necesidades del cuidador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
