<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049021</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fatherhood: a road under construction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, due to the social changes of men and women, the role of the father has    suffered diverse modifications; it has gone from a rigid and dominant model to a more    flexible and equivalent structure. The father has gone from merely an economic provider    to a provider of care, affection, teachings, formation, and economic provision. Given that    to be a father is one of the experiences that is most valued by men in this study analyzes    the different paternal aspects in Spanish males along with their formation as fathers, their    responsibilities, their fears, their limitations; their concept of fatherly authority, their    satisfactions, and the differences and similarities with the paternity of their fathers. This    study come upon males are in transition from a traditional model to a new unfinished    model, they do not have a model to adhere to, and they have changed with respect to the    paternity of their fathers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Velázquez, Laura Evelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, ante los cambios sociales de hombres y mujeres, el papel de la paternidad    ha sufrido diversas modificaciones, ha pasado de un modelo rígido y dominante    a una estructura más flexible e igualitaria; de sólo proveedor económico a proveedor de    cuidados, afectos, enseñanza, formación y, también, económico. Dado que el ser padre    constituye una de las experiencias más valoradas por los varones, en este estudio se analizan    las vivencias de diversos aspectos de la paternidad en varones españoles. Aquí se    examina: su formación para la paternidad, sus responsabilidades, temores, limitaciones,    su concepto de autoridad paterna, sus satisfacciones y las diferencias y semejanzas con la    paternidad de sus padres. Se encuentra que los varones están en transición de un modelo    tradicional a un nuevo modelo inacabado, que los varones no tienen un modelo al cual    adherirse y que han cambiado con respecto a la paternidad de sus padres</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;23(2): 161-174, 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La paternidad: un camino en construcción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
