<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100508</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plasmid-mediated AMPc producing Proteus mirabilis in the Health Care Area of Santiago de Compostela: molecular and epidemiological analysis by rep-PCR and MALDI-TOF</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Proteus mirabilis is an important pathogen isolated from both community-acquired and health-care associated infections. Acquired AmpC-type beta-lactamases represent an important mechanism of resistance to extended-spectrum cephalosporins and are emerging in several European countries. The objective of this work was to know the prevalence of acquired AmpC beta-lactamase producing P. mirabilis over the last three years and eight months and their clonal relationships comparing MALDI-TOF and automated rep-PCR results. Methods: P. mirabilis isolates (n= 1,396) were obtained from routine cultures at the University Hospital Complex of Santiago de Compostela from January 2006 to August 2009. Identification to the species level and antimicrobial susceptibility testing were achieved with Vitek 2. The isolates showing intermediate or total resistance to amoxicillin-clavulanic and cefoxitin, cefotaxime or ceftazidime were selected for AmpC phenotypic detection by double-disk synergy test, and molecular confirmation by multiplex PCR. Molecular typing of the isolates was performed by automated rep-PCR and MALDI-TOF. Results: For the last three years and eight months, the prevalence of AmpC-producing P. mirabilis increased from 0.17% to 4.5%, mainly associated with urinary tract infection in elderly outpatients. In all cases, plasmidic AmpC belonging to LAT/CMY lineage were detected. A high genetic variability was seen with both, rep-PCR and MALDI-TOF MS. Conclusions: AmpC-producing P. mirabilis is an emergent pathogen. The high genetic variability detected suggests that the spread of the resistance mechanism is more probable than a clone dispersion. Automated rep-PCR and MALDI-TOF MS show as fast and decisive methods for bacterial strain typing in clinical microbiology laboratories(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Areses, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueiro, Benito J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbeito, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Treviño, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Riestra, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Proteus mirabilis es un patógeno de importancia creciente tanto en las infecciones nosocomiales como en las comunitarias. La producción de AmpC plasmídica es un mecanismo de resistencia frente a cefalosporinas de espectro extendido emergente en esta bacteria por lo que se consideró de gran interés estudiar su prevalencia en nuestro Área Sanitaria así como su variabilidad genética, comparando dos métodos recientemente incorporados al mercado: MALDI-TOF y rep-PCR automatizada. Métodos: Entre enero de 2006 y agosto de 2009 se recuperaron 1.396 aislamientos de P. mirabilis a partir de los cultivos de rutina realizados en Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Santiago de Compostela. La identificación y el antibiograma se hicieron por Vitek 2. Aquellos aislamientos con sensibilidad reducida a amoxicilina-clavulánico y a cefoxitina, cefotaxima o ceftazidima fueron seleccionados para la detección fenotípica y genotípica de AmpC plasmídica mediante sinergia con doble disco y PCR múltiple, respectivamente. La tipificación molecular se llevó a cabo, comparativamente, mediante rep-PCR automatizada y MALDI-TOF. Resultados: A lo largo de tres años y ocho meses, la prevalencia de P. mirabilis productor de AmpC pasó del 0,17% al 4,5%, mayoritariamente asociado a infección urinaria en pacientes ancianos no hospitalizados. En todos los casos, AmpC plasmídica perteneció a la familia LAT/CMY. Se observó una gran variabilidad genética entre los aislamientos tanto por rep-PCR (DiversiLab) como por MALDI-TOF MS. Conclusión: P. mirabilis productor de AmpC adquirida es un patógeno emergente. La variabilidad genética de las cepas estudiadas apunta a una dispersión de este mecanismo de resistencia más que a una diseminación clonal. Rep-PCR automatizada y MALDI-TOF se muestran como métodos rápidos y resolutivos para la tipificación molecular en los laboratorios de microbiología clínica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;25(2): 122-128, jun.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proteus mirabilis productor de AmpC plasmídica en el Área Sanitaria de Santiago de Compostela: prevalencia y caracterización molecular por rep-PCR y MALDI-TOF MS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11953^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32315^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11953^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
