<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108765</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pickering Syndrome &#150; renal artery stenosis and flash pulmonary edema. A new name for an old concept</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Flash pulmonary edema is a type of recurrent pulmonary edema that usually develops in patients with critical bilateral renal artery stenosis or renal artery stenosis to a solitary kidney. A recent recommendation from the 20thEuropean Meeting on Hypertension proposes naming this clinical entity Pickering Syndrome. Currently, it is one of the few clear indications for endovascular procedures in atherosclerotic renovascular disease. We present a case of a61-year old man with Pickering syndrome and good outcome after revascularization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallès, Martí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faur, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torguet, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calabia, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Nàdia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remollo, Sebastià</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch, Bernat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El «&amp;#64258;ash» edema pulmonar es un tipo de edema pulmonar recurrente que normalmente se presenta en pacientes con estenosis crítica de arteria renal bilateral o unilateral enmonorrenos. Una recomendación reciente de la 20.aReunión Europea de Hipertensión propone denominar a esta entidad clínica síndrome de Pickering. En la actualidad representa una de las pocas indicaciones claras de tratamiento endovascular en la enfermedad renovascular ateroesclerótica. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 61 años con síndrome de Pickering y buena evolución tras revascularización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;28(4): 154-156, Jul. -Ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Pickering &#150; estenosis de arteria renal y flash edema pulmonar. Nueva denominación de un concepto antiguo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7157^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12499^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
