<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153059</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposal of a model of schizophrenic delusions&#146; response to antipsychotics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite recent advances in psychopharmacology, some obvious questions regarding the day-to-day practice do not use to draw attention of researchers. Our model tries to explain the variable response of schizophrenic delusions to antipsychotic drugs. It is a model composed of two poles. In one of them the principle of conditioned avoidance response applies, which refers to the ataraxic or neuroleptic effect of antipsychotic drugs. At the other end of the model Husserl&#146;s phenomenology is applied to psychopathology in order to organize diverse and distinctive phenomena of schizophrenia. Results of this research are then related to the dopaminergic aberrant salience occurring in the schizophrenic outbreak. Finally, constraints of this work are pointed out, which are the same for the very foundations of psychiatry, a medical specialty compelled to move between fields of knowledge mutually irreducible such as neuroscience and human experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Real Román, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Pastor, Carlos J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Pese al gran avance experimentado por la psicofarmacología, hay preguntas obvias en la práctica cotidiana que no suelen centrar la atención de los investigadores. Se propone un modelo que explique la respuesta variable que se observa en los delirios esquizofrénicos al tratamiento antipsicótico. Se trata de un modelo compuesto por dos polos. En uno de ellos rige el paradigma de la inhibición de la respuesta de evitación condicionada, que remite al efecto ataráxico o neuroléptico de estos fármacos. El otro polo se basa en una aplicación de la fenomenología de Husserl a la psicopatología, que permite la organización de diferentes fenómenos característicos de la esquizofrenia. Las ganancias en este ámbito se ponen en relación con la hipersaliencia dopaminérgica característica del brote esquizofrénico. Por último, se reconocen las limitaciones del modelo propuesto, que no dejan de ser las mismas que las de la psiquiatría, obligada a moverse entre la neurociencia y la persona, ámbitos de conocimiento mutuamente irreductibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;36(129): 15-28, ene.-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153059</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de un modelo de respuesta de los delirios esquizofrénicos a los antipsicóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23620^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
