<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041300</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clustering of cardiovascular risk factors in obese offspring of parents with essential hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The prevalence of obesity in industrialized countries is increasing and is closely related to essential hypertension (EHT) in adolescents.                 Objective. To analyze the prevalence of obesity and its association with other known cardiovascular risk factors in a sample of children and young adults with at least one parent with EHT.                 Methods. The EHT group consisted 51 children and young adults (28 males [aged 5.4-25.6 years]) with at least one parent with EHT. The control group comprised 73 healthy normotensive children and young adults (43 males [aged 7.2-25.2 years]) who completed the follow-up visits of the RICARDIN study. Blood pressure (BP) was measured with a standardized technique using a mercury sphygmomanometer. A 12-hour fasting blood sample was taken for lipid profile and high sensitivity C-reactive protein (CRP) determinations. Financial support: FIS 03/0350, ESV Foundation Grant, 2003.                 Results. The prevalence of obesity was five times higher in the EHT group than in controls (19.6 % vs. 4.1 %, p 5 0.007). In this group, obese subjects showed higher systolic BP (122.0 vs. 110.4 mmHg p 5 0.004) and lower high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels (47.6 vs. 58.0 mg/dl, p &lt; 0.05). After adjustment for age and systolic BP, obese subjects in the EHT group showed significantly higher CRP values than non-obese subjects in this group (p 5 0.024).                 Conclusions. The prevalence of obesity is higher in the offspring of parents with EHT than in non HT-prone subjects. Clustering of other additional risk factors indicates the need for high-risk preventive interventions in this group of children and young adults</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Málaga Diéguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vijande Vázquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Luis, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Málaga Guerrero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Martín, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diéguez Junquera, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La prevalencia de obesidad está aumentando alarmantemente en países industrializados y se relaciona con el desarrollo de hipertensión arterial esencial (HTE) en adolescentes.                 Objetivo. Analizar la prevalencia de obesidad y su relación con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular, en una muestra de niños y jóvenes en los que al menos uno de sus padres padecía HTE.                 Métodos. Grupo HTE: 51 niños y jóvenes, 28 varones (5,4-25,6 años) en los que al menos uno de sus padres padecía HTE. Grupo control: 73 niños y jóvenes sanos y normotensos, 43 varones (7,2-25,2 años) que completaron el seguimiento longitudinal del estudio RICARDIN. La presión arterial (PA) se midió mediante una técnica estandarizada con un esfigmomanómetro de mercurio. Determinación tras ayuno de 12 h de perfil lipídico y proteína C reactiva (PCR) ultrasensible.                 Resultados. La prevalencia de obesidad fue 5 veces mayor en hijos de HTE que en controles (19,6 % frente a 4,1 %, p 5 0,007). Los hijos obesos de padres HTE presentaron cifras mayores de PA sistólica (122,0 mmHg frente a 110,4 mmHg; p 5 0,004), y menores de colesterol HDL (47,6 mg/dl frente a 58,0 mg/dl; p &lt; 0,05) que los no obesos. Ajustado por edad y PA sistólica, los descendientes obesos de padres HTE presentaron valores de PCR más altos que los no obesos (p 5 0,024).                 Conclusiones. En hijos de padres HTE se observa una alta prevalencia de obesidad. La coexistencia de éste con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular hace patente la necesidad de aplicar medidas preventivas intensivas en este tipo de pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(3): 238-243, sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agrupamiento de factores de risgo cardiovascular en hijos obesos de padres con hipertensión esencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
