<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057686</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morphine maintenance treatment in opiate dependent patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Morphine is an opiate drug widely used as an analgesic in multiple medical diseases. Currently, its management in the maintenance treatment of opiate dependent patients is being studied. The most significant studies are described. In these, its usefulness has been assessed in comparison with other treatments, such as methadone, buprenorphine. Morphine has shown efficacy and tolerability. Its management is easy both in patients who consume heroin as well as those who have received other opiate drugs. Thus, it is a drug that may extend the therapeutic armamentarium in patients who begin with treatment with other opiates for the first time or who have previously received them. However, new studies must be conducted to adequately characterize its clinical use</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roncero Alonso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Francàs, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Brugué, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells Cervelló, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La morfina es un fármaco opiáceo ampliamente utilizado como analgésico en múltiples patologías médicas. En la actualidad se está estudiando su manejo en el tratamiento de mantenimiento en pacientes dependientes de opiáceos. Se describen los estudios más significativos en los que se ha valorado su utilidad en comparación con otros tratamientos, como la metadona o la buprenorfina. La morfina ha demostrado eficacia y tolerabilidad, su manejo es sencillo tanto en pacientes que consumen heroína como en los que han recibido otros fármacos opiáceos, por lo que es un medicamento que puede ampliar el arsenal terapéutico en pacientes que se incorporen por primera vez o que hayan recibido previamente tratamiento con otros opiáceos. Sin embargo es necesario realizar nuevos estudios para caracterizar adecuadamente su uso clínico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(4): 194-196, abr.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con morfina en la dependencia de opiáceos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
