<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158070</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biological relevance of a mysterious hydroxyl group</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evolution is linked to gene loss, being of biological relevance the inactivation of CMAH gene which made humans genetically unable to produce the sialic acid N-glycolylneuraminic (Neu5Gc). This acid acts as a foreign antigen after incorporation into tissues from dietary components, interacting with human antiNeu5Gc antibodies thus promoting inflammation and cancer progression. Xenotransplants, stem cells and drugs of biological origin may be contaminated by Neu5Gc. The binding chemistry of the monoclonal antibody 14F17, which is able to discriminate the tumorspecific antigen N-glycolyl GM3 from the closely related N-acetyl GM3 on the basis of the presence of a single additional hydroxyl group in the former, reveals some clues of this phenomenon that could be of interest in new cancer immunotherapy approaches (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avendaño López, M del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evolución lleva consigo la pérdida de diversos genes ancestrales, siendo relevante la inactivación en los seres humanos del gen GMAH que nos hace genéticamente incapaces para producir el ácido siálico N-glicolilneuramínico (Neu5Gc). Este ácido se comporta como un antígeno extraño si se incorpora a los tejidos a partir de componentes alimentarios, pudiendo interaccionar con anticuerpos humanos anti-Neu5Gc y promover inflamación y cáncer. Xenotrasplantes, células madre y medicamentos de origen biológico pueden estar contaminados con Neu5Gc. El conocimiento de las interacciones de enlace en el anticuerpo monoclonal 14F17, capaz de discriminar el antígeno tumoral Nglicolil GM3 de su análogo N-acetilado debido a la presencia de un grupo hidroxilo adicional, está dando algunas claves de este fenómeno, cuya aplicación podría ser de interés en la inmunoterapia del cáncer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;82(3): 274-282, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relevancia biológica de un misterioso grupo hidroxilo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54578^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31398^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d955^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32226^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32977^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
