<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32849</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blood-brain barrier: development of a structure which supports the functional heterogeneity of the central nervous system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To analyze the functional reasons justifying the existence of the blood-brain barrier with an emphasis on its fundamental role supporting neuroglial coupling. Development. We review in an integrated manner the contributions of different research areas in physiology and metabolism of the central nervous system which allow to understand the functional need for the existence of the blood-brain barrier. In particular, we describe the physiological basis of the metabolic-functional coupling and the metabolic interactions between neurons and glial cells, two properties directly derived from the presence of the blood-brain barrier. Likewise the blood-brain barrier is presented as an important determinant of the heterogeneous activation of cerebral tissue as detected by neuroimaging technologies as positron emission tomography and functional magnetic resonance imaging. Conclusions. The main function of the blood-brain barrier is to maintain a stable composition of the extracellular milieu in nervous tissue. This allows the changes in ionic composition and neurotransmitter concentration in the extracellular milieu, to reflect indirectly the generation of action potentials and the state of neurotransmission of neuronal circuits. Glial cells induce the development of the blood-brain barrier and are the main sensors of neuronal function, due to their important take up capacity for extracellular potassium and neurotransmitters. Glial homeostasis of the extracellular milieu is circuit-specific, limiting the functional-metabolic coupling to discrete regions of the brain and generating the classical pattern of heterogeneous activity in the different modules of the nervous tissue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las razones funcionales que justifican la existencia de la barrera hematoencefálica (BHE), con énfasis en su papel crucial como soporte de la unidad funcional neurona-glía.Desarrollo. Se revisan en detalle y de manera integrada las aportaciones de diversas áreas de investigación en fisiología y metabolismo del sistema nervioso central que permiten comprender la necesidad funcional de la existencia de la BHE. En especial, se describen las bases fisiológicas del acoplamiento metabólico-funcional en el tejido nervioso y las interacciones metabólicas entre las neuronas y las células gliales, dos propiedades derivadas directamente de la presencia de la BHE. Se presenta la barrera como un importante determinante de la activación heterogénea del tejido cerebral, detectable mediante tecnologías de neuroimagen funcional, como la tomografía de emisión de positrones y la imagen de resonancia magnética funcional. Conclusiones. La función principal de la BHE es mantener una composición estable del medio extracelular en el tejido nervioso. Esto permite que los cambios de composición iónica y de concentración de neurotransmisores del medio extracelular sean el reflejo indirecto de la generación de potenciales de acción y del estado de neurotransmisión de los circuitos neuronales. Las células gliales inducen el desarrollo de la barrera y son los principales sensores de la función neuronal, debido a su capacidad de recaptación del exceso extracelular de potasio y de neurotransmisores. La homeostasis glial del medio extracelular es específica de circuito, limita el acoplamiento metabólico-funcional a regiones discretas del cerebro y genera el patrón de actividad heterogénea en los diversos módulos del tejido nervioso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(6): 565-581, mar. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La barrera hematoencefálica: desarrollo de una estructura que permite la heterogeneidad funcional del sistema nervioso central</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Roda, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Arribas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Garvi, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gónzalez Llanos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerdán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32849</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6117</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28186</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5819</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
