<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118459</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Down syndrome due to rare inherited 15/21 Robertsonian translocation: genetics and reproductive counseling</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The carriers of a rearrangement involving with chromosome 21 have a potential risk of genetically unbalanced conceptions, which may result in liveborn children with Down syndrome. Reproductive risks for couples carriers of a balanced Robertsonian translocation depends on the rearranged chromosomes and the sex of the carrier. This article aims to analyze the segregation and reproductive trend of a rare 15/21 translocation in five generations of a family. It was considered the current advances in reproductive technology as a possibility to prevent fetal aneuploidia. Given the genetic risk, the preimplantation diagnosis appears also as an alternative to avoid the option of an unwanted later abortion and to obtain a healthy progeny (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandes Lacerda Carvalho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azevedo Moreira, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Damasceno Espirito Santo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los portadores de un reordenamiento que afecta al cromosoma 21 tienen un riesgo potencial de concepciones genéticamente desequilibradas que pueden dar origen a niños con síndrome de Down (SD). Los riesgos reproductivos de las parejas portadoras de una translocación robertsoniana equilibrada dependen de los cromosomas reordenados y del sexo del portador. Este artículo tiene como objetivo analizar la tendencia de segregación y reproductiva de una rara translocación 15/21 en cinco generaciones de una familia. Se consideraron los avances actuales en tecnología reproductiva como una posibilidad para evitar la aneuploidía fetal. Dado el riesgo genético, el diagnóstico de preimplantación aparece también como una alternativa para evitar la posibilidad de un aborto posterior no deseado y para obtener una descendencia saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);17(3): 36-38, sept.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Down hereditario poco común debido a la translocación robertsoniana 15/21: asesoramiento genético y reproductivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19123^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19123^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19123^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23644^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23644^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
