<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68128</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Imported childhood malaria has become an emerging disease in Spain. The two main reasons are international travel to endemic countries and the increase in immigrant and adopted children coming from those geographical regions. We describe the case of an adopted Ethiopian girl who was infected with Plasmodium falciparum, although with the exception of splenomegaly, she was asymptomatic at the time of her arrival. Early diagnosis and treatment of malaria is essential to decrease the associated morbidity and mortality. Therefore, steps should be taken to rule out this disease in patients coming from endemic areas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blázquez Gamero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ortega, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado Peña, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ascaso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hortelano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Fontelos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La malaria importada en la edad pediátrica es una enfermedad emergente en nuestro medio gracias al aumento de los viajes internacionales a países endémicos y a la llegada de niños inmigrantes o adoptados desde estas zonas. Describimos el caso de una niña adoptada procedente de Etiopía con parasitación por P. falciparum, que se encontraba asintomática a su llegada y sólo presentaba esplenomegalia como único hallazgo clínico. El diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz de esta enfermedad resulta fundamental para disminuir la morbimortalidad asociada, por lo que siempre debe descartarse en aquellos pacientes procedentes de área endémica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(7): 362-364, jul. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68128</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11394^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2774^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11394^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35308^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
