<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043831</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Progression following the embolisation of 100 intracranial arteriovenous malformations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We analysed the characteristics, progression and outcomes observed following the embolisation of 100intracranial arteriovenous malformations (AVM) that were performed in order to achieve complete obliteration of the AVM, theelimination of associated vascular risk factors and also to reduce their size with a view to increasing the effectiveness of latertreatments. Patients and methods. The demographic and anatomical characteristics of 110 patients with AVM were analysedover a period of 13 years, and embolisation was performed in 100 of them. In all, 203 embolisation sessions were carried outwith an average of 3 embolisations per patient. Of the 100 AVM that were embolised, 36 were AVM which were treated byembolisation with no later therapy, 48 required radiosurgery after the embolisation and the other 16 were submitted to surgeryfollowing the embolisation. The type of materials used included liquid adhesive embolic agents (Hystoacryl, Glubran ®), nonadhesiveembolic agents (Onyx) and polyvinyl alcohol particles. Patients were examined clinically and arteriographically.Results. Of the 100 AVM that were embolised, complete eradication was accomplished with just embolisation in 27 cases ofAVM (27%). Of the 48 AVM in which radiosurgery was carried out at a later date, the average rate of obliteration was 78% andof the 16 AVM in which surgery was carried out some time later, the average rate of obliteration was 70%. Of the 100 AVM thatwere embolised, some residue remained in 16 cases. Embolisation eliminated most of the associated vascular risk factors, ascan be seen by the fact that associated risk factors disappeared in 28 (65%) out of the 43 AVM with such factors. The morbidityand mortality rates with embolisation were 8% and 2%, respectively. Conclusions. Embolisation eliminated most of the vascularrisk factors, with complete obliteration in 27 cases and size was satisfactorily reduced for later treatment; at the same time,morbidity and mortality rates were acceptable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Subirán, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guelbenzu, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo-Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo-Hervías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrena, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Rodríguez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Analizamos las características, evolucióny resultados tras la embolización de 100 malformaciones arteriovenosas(MAV) intracraneales con el objetivo de conseguir la obliteracióncompleta de la MAV, la eliminación de los factores de riesgovascular asociados y disminuir su tamaño para la efectividad deposteriores tratamientos. Pacientes y métodos. Analizamos las característicasdemográficas y anatómicas de 110 pacientes portadoresde MAV durante 13 años, y se realizó una embolización a 100de éstos. Se practicaron 203 sesiones de embolización con una mediade 3 embolizaciones/paciente. De las 100 MAV embolizadas,hubo 36 MAV a las que sólo se realizó embolización sin otro tratamientoposterior, a 48 se les realizó radiocirugía postembolizacióny a los 16 restantes cirugía postembolización. El tipo del materialusado fueron agentes embólicos líquidos adhesivos (Hystoacril, Glubran®), agentes embólicos no adhesivos (Onyx) y partículas de polivinilalcohol. Se revisó a los pacientes clínica y arteriográficamente.Resultados. De las 100 MAV embolizadas, hubo una erradicacióncompleta con sólo embolización en 27 MAV (27%). De las48 MAV a las que se les realizó radiocirugía posterior, hubo unaobliteración media del 78%. De las 16 MAV a las que se realizócirugía posterior, hubo una obliteración media del 70%. De las 100MAV embolizadas, hubo 16 en las que quedaron restos. La embolizacióneliminó la mayoría de los factores de riesgo vascular asociados:de 43 MAV con factores de riesgo asociados, desaparecieronen 28 MAV (65%). Con la embolización se produjo una morbilidaddel 8% y mortalidad del 2%. Conclusión. La embolización eliminóla mayoría de los factores de riesgo vascular, con una obliteracióncompleta en 27 casos y se redujo el tamaño para posteriores tratamientosde manera satisfactoria, y todo ello con una morbimortalidadaceptable</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(1): 8-16, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043831</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución tras la embolización de 100 malformaciones arteriovenosas intracraneales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
