<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79060</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Childbirth via the vagina birth canal. Breech presentation through the cervix uteri</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At the present time in our country, when faced with a breech presentation through the cervix uteri, the majority of hospitals carry out an elective Cesarean section. The Spanish Association of Gynecology and Obstetrics does not indicate a strict operating protocol for these cases. The authors carry out a transversal study to test a mother&#146;s and her child&#146;s state of health after having undergone birth through the vagina birth canal when a breech presentation through the cervix uteri occurred, using various parameters for their analysis. Our results indicate that with the mother&#146;s consent and in the situations indicated, to have birth via the vagina birth canal when there is a breech presentation through the cervix uteri can be traed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Adamuz, María Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Galiano, Juan Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Gómez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, en nuestro país, ante una presentación de nalgas la mayoría de los hospitales realiza una cesárea electiva. La SEGO (Sociedad Española de Ginecología y Obstetricia) no indica un protocolo de actuación estricto de cesárea en estos casos. Se realiza un estudio transversal para comprobar el estado de salud de la madre y el recién nacido en partos vaginales con presentación de nalgas, midiendo diferentes parámetros. Nuestros resultados indican que, en consenso con la madre y en los casos que se indiquen, se podría intentar parto vía vaginal de presentación de nalgas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(6): 409-412, jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parto por vía vaginal en presentación de nalgas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
