<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147602</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-3655</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The prevalence of major potential drug-drug interactions at a University health centre pharmacy in Jamaica</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify major potential drug-drug interactions (DDIs) on prescriptions filled at the University Health Centre Pharmacy, Mona Campus, Jamaica. Methods: This investigation utilised a cross-sectional analysis on all prescriptions with more than one drug that were filled at the Health Centre Pharmacy between November 2012 and February 2013. Potential DDIs were identified using the online Drug Interactions Checker database of Drugs.com. Results: During the period of the study, a total of 2814 prescriptions were analysed for potential DDIs. The prevalence of potential DDIs found during the study period was 49.82%. Major potential DDIs accounted for 4.7 % of the total number of interactions detected, while moderate potential DDIs and minor potential DDIs were 80.8 % and 14.5 % respectively. The three most frequently occurring major potential DDIs were amlodipine and simvastatin (n=46), amiloride and losartan (n=27) and amiloride and lisinopril (n=16). Conclusion: This study has highlighted the need for educational initiatives to ensure that physicians and pharmacists collaborate in an effort to minimise the risks to the patients. These interactions are avoidable for the most part, as the use of online tools can facilitate the selection of therapeutic alternatives or guide decisions for closer patient monitoring and thus reduce the risks of adverse events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kennedy-Dixon, Tracia-Gay</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blossom, Anglin-Brown</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gossell- Williams, Maxine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hall, Jannel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar interacciones potenciales medicamento-medicamento (DDI) en las prescripciones atendidas en la farmacia del centro de salud de Universitario del campus de Mona, Jamaica. Métodos: Esta investigación utilizó un análisis transversal de todas las prescripciones con más de un medicamento que fueron atendidas en el centro de salud universitario entre noviembre de 2012 y febrero de 2013. Las DDI potenciales se identificaban en el Drug Interactions Checker de la base de datos Drugs.com. Resultados: Durante el periodo de estudio, se analizaron a la busca de DDI un total de 2.814 prescripciones. La prevalencia de DDI potenciales encontrada durante el estudio fue del 49,82%. Las DDI major potenciales totalizaron el 4,7% del total de interaciones detectadas, mientras que las moderadas y minor fueron el 80,8% y el 14,5%, respectivamente. Las tres DDI potenciales major que aparecieron más frecuentemente fueron amlodipina y simvastatina (n=46), amilorida y losartan (n=27), y amilorida y lisinopril (n=16). Conclusión: Este estudio ha remarcado la necesidad de iniciativas educativas para asegurar que los médicos y los farmacéuticos colaboren en el esfuerzo de minimizar los riesgos de los pacientes. Estas interacciones eran evitables en su mayor parte, ya que el uso de herramientas online puede facilitar la selección de tratamientos alternativos o guiar decisiones para monitorizar más de cerca a los pacientes, y así reducir el riesgo de eventos adversos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. pract. (Granada, Internet);13(4): 0-0, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147602</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de interacciones potenciales medicamento-medicamento en una farmacia de centro de salud universitario en Jamaica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4583^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4583^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4583^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4583^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55138^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55138^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7732^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55138^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55138^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
