<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050908</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Leptospirosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leptospirosis is the most common zoonosis worldwide, although mostcases occur in tropical countries. Leptospira interrogans, a spirochete,is the causative agent. Rats are the main reservoir. Most patients presenta mild clinical form of the disease, which consists of a self-limited febrileprocess, without jaundice. Nevertheless, about 10 % of patients suffersevere infections, with intense jaundice. Typically the disease manifestsin two phases: acute or leptospiremic and immune or leptospiuric,although in many patients the two phases are indistinguishable, and inmild cases the second one is frequently absent. Diagnosis is carried outby serology or culture of the microorganism. Treatment consists ofantibiotics such as penicillin G, ceftriaxone, doxycycline or amoxicillin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roca, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La leptospirosis es la zoonosis más ampliamente distribuida en el mundo,aunque la mayoría de casos ocurre en países tropicales. Está producidapor la espiroqueta Leptospira interrogans. Las ratas constituyen elprincipal reservorio. La mayoría de pacientes presenta una forma levede la infección, consistente en un cuadro febril autolimitado y sin ictericia.Sin embargo alrededor del 10 % sufre cuadros graves, con ictericiaintensa. Típicamente presenta dos fases: la aguda o leptospirémica y lainmune o leptospiúrica, sin embargo en muchos casos las dos fases sonindistinguibles, y en los casos leves no siempre se presenta la segundafase. El diagnóstico se realiza mediante la serología o mediante el cultivodel microorganismo. El tratamiento consiste en la administración deantibióticos, como penicilina G, ceftriaxona, doxiciclina o amoxicilina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;50(2): 3-6, abr.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leptospirosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8100^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
