<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77753</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Orally Disintegrating Tablets are defined as non-coated tablets that are placed in the mouth, where they are rapidly disintegrated before being swallowed. These formulations are known by the acronym FDDT's (Fast Dissolving Disintegrating Tablets). They are useful for administration to patients with difficulties in swallowing, present high acceptance by the patient, improve the bioavailability of the active pharmaceutical ingredient and represent a new alternative for the pharmaceutical industry. Among their disadvantages are the lack of knowledge by the patient, the low hardness and friability, their major degradation susceptibility by temperature and moisture environment, the non bioequivalence with the conventional formulations that sometimes happens and finally the difficulty to obtain prolonged or delayed drug release. From a pharmaceutical technological point of view, there are several processes that can be applied in their preparation. With the conventional tableting technology, choosing a proper role of excipients and variables in the compression stage, tablets with a good balance between hardness and disgregation must be obtained. A series of innovative technologies have been arisen: Flashtab, Wowtab, Orasolv and Durasolv. Another option is the use of freeze drying technique, although it high cost represents a significantly disadvantage. There are some special patented technologies such as Lyoc, QuickSolv and Zydis. Finally, these tablets can be produced by the method of interlocking polymers, also known as FlashDose base on the formation of a matrix of interwoven threads of sugar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espada García, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Alegre, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Suárez, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sabroso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes Tavares, D. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los comprimidos bucodispersables se definen como comprimidos no recubiertos destinados a ser colocados en la boca, donde se dispersan rápidamente antes de ser tragados. Estas formulaciones son conocidas por las siglas FDDT´s (Fast Dissolving Disintegrating Tablets). Son útiles para la administración a pacientes con dificultades en la deglución, presentan una elevada aceptación por parte del paciente, mejoran de la biodisponibilidad del principio activo y suponen una nueva alternativa para la industria farmacéutica. Dentro de sus inconvenientes destacan el poco conocimiento por parte del paciente, la baja resistencia mecánica, su mayor susceptibilidad a la degradación por temperatura y humedad; la falta, a veces, de bioequivalencia con las formulaciones convencionales, y la dificultad de obtener liberaciones prolongadas o retardadas del principio activo. A nivel tecnológico, existen varios procesos que se pueden aplicar en su elaboración. Con los métodos clásicos de elaboración de comprimidos, mediante la correcta selección de los excipientes y de las variables de la etapa de compresión se obtienen unos comprimidos en los que existe un equilibrio entre dureza y disgregación. Han surgido una serie de tecnologías novedosas: Flashtab, Wowtab, Orasolv y Durasolv. Otra opción es el empleo de técnicas de liofilización, aunque presenta como desventaja su alto coste. Algunas tecnologías especiales patentadas como son Lyoc, QuickSolv y Zydis. Por último, estos comprimidos se pueden elaborar por el método de los polímeros entrecruzados, también conocido como FlashDose y se basa en la formación de una matriz de hilos de azúcares entrelazados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;50(3): 153-167, jul.-sep. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comprimidos bucodispersables: ventajas terapéuticas y tecnológicas de elaboración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13990^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5748^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13990^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13990^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
