<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039847</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Th1-Th2 immune paradigm: a link among obesity, atherosclerosis and diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An association between elevated C-reactive protein related to low-intensity chronic inflammation and chronic disease (obesity, atherosclerosis and diabetes mellitus) has been the focus of recent attention.   A growing body of knowledge indicates that this association is due to disregulation of the Th1-Th2 immune response, with increased production of proinflammatory cytokines TNF-*, IL1-ß, IFN-* and IL-6. Such an abnormality plays a key physiopathologic role in the development of obesity, atherosclerosis and diabetes mellitus. Moreover, this proinflammatory disregulation of the immune response can lead to the insulin resistance, hyperglycemia and dyslipidemia that characterize the metabolic syndrome due to the metabolic effects of the cytokines involved.   The study of these mechanisms will promote better understanding of the physiopathology of chronic diseases and could be useful for the development of new preventive and therapeutic strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peralta-Zaragoza, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Aldana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barquera-Cervera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente ha llamado la atención la asociación entre inflamación crónica de baja intensidad --evidenciada como elevación de la proteína C reactiva (PCR)-- y obesidad, aterosclerosis y diabetes mellitus.   Hay evidencia de que esta asociación se debe a una desregulación de la respuesta inmune de linfocitos T cooperadores tipos 1 y 2, orientada hacia un perfil proinflamatorio, con aumento en la producción de interleucina (IL) 6 y de otras citocinas, como el factor de necrosis tumoral alfa, la IL-1-ß y el interferón-gamma. Esta desregulación de la respuesta inmune tiene un papel fisiopatológico crucial en la obesidad, la enfermedad aterosclerótica y la diabetes mellitus. Asimismo, podría ser el origen de las anomalías observadas en el síndrome metabólico, como la resistencia a la insulina, la hiperglucemia y la dislipidemia, debido a los efectos de las citocinas involucradas sobre el metabolismo.   El conocimiento de estos mecanismos proporcionará un mejor entendimiento de la fisiopatología de las enfermedades crónicas degenerativas y puede ser la base para el planteamiento de nuevas estrategias preventivas y terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);17(5): 232-248, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paradigma inmune Th1-Th2: un vínculo entre obesidad, aterosclerosis y diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32004^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32005^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
