<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89517</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Celiac disease in 3 patients with Takayasu's arteritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Takayasu's arteritis (TA) is a chronic vasculitis of unknown etiology. Celiac disease (CD) is an autoimmune disease caused by the ingestion of gluten. TA and CD have been associated with many other autoimmune conditions. However, only five cases with this association have been reported. In this series, three patients with TA and CD were included; all were female, 21, 30 and 54 years old. TA clinical manifestations preceded CD diagnosis in all patients. Aortic arch branches were affected in all of them. Serologic markers were positive and a small intestine biopsy showed typical findings of CD in the three patients. Special attention should be given to this possible association because these entities may be asymptomatic; the recognition of new disease variants modifies treatment, and sometimes CD constitutes a differential diagnosis of mesenteric ischemia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tumminello, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escasany, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albertón, Valeria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedetto, Nicolás Di</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Allievi, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Muñoz, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La arteritis de Takayasu (AT) es una vasculitis de causa incierta. La enfermedad celíaca (EC) es una enfermedad autoinmunitaria provocada por la exposición al gluten. Ambas entidades se relacionan con distintas enfermedades autoinmunitarias, pero hasta la fecha sólo hay 5 casos descritos de asociación entre ellas. Se presentan tres casos clínicos con EC y AT. Los tres son mujeres de 21, 30 y 54 años. En todas ellas las manifestaciones de la AT precedieron a las de la EC y en todos los casos había compromiso de los vasos supraaórticos al diagnóstico. La EC fue diagnosticada por marcadores serológicos y biopsia duodenal en los tres casos. Reconocer esta asociación tiene importancia porque ambas entidades pueden cursar largo tiempo sin ser diagnosticadas, el diagnóstico de una nueva entidad modifica la terapéutica y la EC en un paciente con AT puede simular a la isquemia mesentérica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);7(4): 255-257, jul.-ago.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad celíaca en 3 pacientes con arteritis de Takayasu</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6127^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
