<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038642</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lingual ulcer as the only sign of recurrent mycobacterial infection in an HIV/AIDS-infected patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The report describes an HIV/AIDS patient seen at a referral center in Mexico City, in whom a mycobacterial infection in the oral mucosa, probably tuberculosis (TB) was identified. The purpose is to describe the clinical and histological findings in an HIV-infected patient, who after being treated successfully for tuberculous lymphangitis 4 years ago, presented with a lingual ulcer as the only suggestive sign of recurrence of mycobacterial infection, probably M. tuberculosis. A 39-year-old man seen inthe HIV clinic of the Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Médicas y Nutrición &#147;Salvador Zubirán&#148; in Mexico City since 1991 for HIV infection. In 1999 the patient developed tuberculous lymphangitis; he was managed with a 4-drug regimen for 12 months, with improvement of local and systemic symptoms. In May of 2003, the patient presented a painful superficial lingual ulcer, 0.7 cm in diameter, well circumscribed, crateriform with slightly elevated, irregular and indurated borders, of 4 months duration. The histopathological examination showed chronic granulomatous inflammation with giant multinucleated cells, suggestive of mycobacterial infection, and recurrence of TB was considered. Rifampin, isoniazide, pyrazinamide, ethambutol and streptomycin were administered. The lingual lesion improved with partial healing at the first week and total remission at 45 days after the beginning of the antituberculous treatment. In June, 2003, the patient began highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) that included two NRTIs and one NNRTI. At 7 months of follow-up, the patient remains free of lingual lesions. The particularity of the present case is that the lingual ulcer was the only sign of infection by mycobacteria, suggestive of TB, in an HIV/AIDS patient that probably represented a recurrence of a previous episode</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosqueda Gómez, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Madero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Amador, Velia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquivel Pedraza, Lilly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anaya Saavedra, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ramírez, Imelda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes Gutiérrez, Edgardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe un paciente con VIH/SIDA en el que se identificó una infección por micobacteria en la mucosa bucal, probablemente tuberculosis, en un centro de referencia para VIH/SIDA de la Ciudad de México. El propósito del presente informe es describir los hallazgos clínicos e histológicos en un paciente con VIH/SIDA, quien después de haber sido tratado exitosamente para tuberculosis ganglionar 4 años antes, presentó una úlcera lingual como único signo que sugirió recurrencia de infección por micobacteria, probablemente tuberculosis. Hombre de 39 años de edad, atendido desde 1991 en el Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Médicas y Nutrición &#147;Salvador Zubirán&#148;, por el diagnóstico de infección con VIH. En 1999, el paciente presentó tuberculosis ganglionar, recibiendo tratamiento antifímico con involución de las adenopatías y desaparición de los síntomas sistémicos. En mayo del 2003 acudió a consulta por presentar una úlcera superficial en lengua, dolorosa, de 4 meses de evolución, de 0.7 cm. de diámetro, bien circunscrita, crateriforme, con bordes ligeramente elevados, irregulares e indurados. El estudio histopatológico mostró inflamación granulomatosa crónica con células gigantes multinucleadas sugestivas de infección por micobacteria, lo cual hizo pensar en recurrencia de tuberculosis, por lo que se indicó rifampicina, pirazinamida, etambutol y estreptomicina. En junio del 2003 el paciente inició TARAA, que incluyó dos ITRAN y un ITRNN. La lesión lingual evolucionó favorablemente, con cicatrización parcial a la primera semana y remisión total a los 45 días del inicio del tratamiento antifímico; a los 7 meses de seguimiento permanece sin lesión. El presente caso tiene la particularidad de que la úlcera lingual fue la única manifestación de infección por micobacteria, sugestiva de tuberculosis, en un paciente con VIH/SIDA, que pudo ocurrir como resultado de la recurrencia del episodio previo de TB ganglionar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(2): 109-114, mar.-abr. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ulcera lingual como signo único de infección recurrente por micobacteria en un paciente con VIH/SIDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9358^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14450^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
