<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118942</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients&#146; selfmanagement of type 2 diabetes: a narrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to the World Health Organization in2030 the number of people with diabetes mellitus will reach 366 millions in the whole world, having the diabetes mellitus type 2 the highest prevalence. The current National Chronicity and Diabetes Strategies advocate patients&#146; self management programmes and /or interventions. Nevertheless, the lack of knowledge and inadequate attitudes hinder the associative relationship between patients and professionals that is required in these programmes. This literature review aims to show the outstanding needs that type 2 diabetes mellitus patients have when it comes to managing the illness. Thus, results from this literature review could set the bases for the development of future effective programmes, helping professionals approach patients&#146; needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portillo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Guinea, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según la Organización Mundial de la Salud para el año 2030 la cifra de personas con diabetes mellitus alcanzará valores cercanos a 366 millones en el mundo, ocupando su mayor proporción la diabetes mellitus tipo2. Las estrategias actuales de Cronicidad y de la Diabetes presentes en España abogan por un adecuado automanejo del paciente por medio de programas y/o intervenciones apropiadas para ello. Sin embargo, existen unos conocimientos y actitudes inadecuadas que limitan la asociación paciente-profesional que las estrategias de automanejo implican. A través de esta revisión bibliográfica se pretende mostrar las necesidades reales no cubiertas que los pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 tienen a la hora de automanejar la enfermedad. Así, se asentarán las bases para el desarrollo de futuros programas efectivos que se implementen ayudando al profesional sanitario a dirigir su trabajo diario hacía su principal objetivo, la persona con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 y sus necesidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(3): 489-504, sept.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El automanejo de los pacientes con diabetes tipo 2: una revisión narrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
