<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108404</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Agomelatine in Elderly &#150; Finally a Patient Friendly Antidepressant In Psychogeriatry?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Geriatric depression is a serious psychiatric conditions with prevalence from 10&#150;40% in community living seniors. Polymorbidity and potential vulnerability of seniors towards medication is a challenge for seeking newer, well tolerated antidepressant with good clinical efficiency and safety. Agomelatine is new promising antidepressant which could fulfill these criteria. Objective: Evaluation of effectiveness, safety and side effects of agomelatine used for treatment senior patients with major depression hospitalized in inpatient psychogeriatric ward in Mental hospital in Kromeriz (2010-2011).Methods: Psychiatric scales Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale (MADRS) and Clinical Global Impression (CGI) were used initially before starting with agomelatine treatment, then after 4 and 8 weeks and finally after 12weeks of using agomelatine. Potential side effects caused by agomelatine (side effects according AISL data basis&#150;Automatized Information system of Registered Drugs in theCzech republic) were monitored after 12 weeks of treatment with agomelatine. Results: While treating major depression in seniors with agomelatine, decrease in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale (MADRS), Clinical Global Impression scale (CGI) was evident after 4 weeks of treatment and continued constantly after 8 and 12 weeks of treatment. Clinical remission was achieved in all studied patients. Conclusion: Agomelatine proved excellent efficiency in treating severe major depression in seniors with no serious averse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lu&#158;ný, Jan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La depresión geriátrica es una condición psiquiátrica grave con una prevalencia de 10&#150;40% en mayores que viven en comunidad. La multiple comorbilidad y la vulnerabilidad potencial de los mayores a la medicaciónes un desafío para la búsqueda de antidepresivos novedosos bien tolerados con una seguridad y eficacia clínica apropiadas. La agomelatina es un antidepresivo nuevo que podría cumplir estos criterios. Objetivos. Evaluar la efectividad, seguridad y efectos secundarios de la agomelatina usada en el tratamiento de pacientes ancianos con depresión mayor hospitalizados en una unidad de psicogeriatría en el hospital mental de Kromeriz (2010-2011).Método. Se usaron las escalas psiquiátricas Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale (MADRS) y Clinical Global Impression (CGI) antes de comenzar con el tratamiento de agomelatina, a las 4 semanas, a las 8 y finalmente a las 12 semanas de uso de la agomelatina. Los posibles efectos secundarios causados por la agomelatina (efectos secundarios según la base de datos AISL&#150;Automatized Information system of Registered Drugs, sistema de información automatizada de fármacos registrados en la República Checa)se monitorizaron tras 12 semanas de tratamiento conagomelatina. Resultados. Al tratar con agomelatina la depresión mayor de los ancianos, se evidenció un descenso en la puntuación de las escalas Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale(MADRS) y Clinical Global Impression (CGI) a las 4 semanas de tratamiento y continuó descendiendo a las 8 y las 12 semanas. La remisión clínica se obtuvo en todos los pacientes del estudio. La agomelatina ha demostrado una eficiencia excelente en el tratamiento de la depresión mayor graveen ancianos sin efectos adversos graves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;40(6): 304-307, nov.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agomelatina en el anciano &#150; ¿Un antidepresivo apropiado para el paciente de psicogeriatría?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
