<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115418</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Childhood adversities increase the risk of psychosis: A meta-analysis of patient-control, prospective and cross-sectional cohort studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To examine the association between childhood adversity and trauma (sexual abuse, physical abuse, emotional/psychological abuse, neglect, parental death, and bullying) and psychosis outcome, MEDLINE, EMBASE, PsychINFO, and Web of Science were searched from January 1980 through November 2011. The analysis included 18 case-control studies (n=2048 psychotic patients and 1856 nonpsychiatric controls), 10 prospective and quasi-prospective studies (n=41803) and 8 population-based cross-sectional studies (n=35.546). There were significant associations between adversity and psychosis across all research designs, with an overall effect  of OR = 2.78 (95% CI = 2.34-3.31). The integration of the case-control studies indicated that patients with psychosis were 2.72 times more likely to have been exposed to childhood adversity than controls (95% CI= 1.90-3.88). The association between childhood adversity and psychosis was also significant in population based cross-sectional studies as well as in prospective and quasi prospective and psychosis was also significant in population based cross-sectional studies as well as in prospective and quasiprospective studies. The estimated population attributable risk was 33% (16%-47%). These findings indicate that childhood adversity is strongly associated with increased risk for psychosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lieverse, Ritsaert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Van Os, Jim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Drukker, Marjan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viechtbauer, Wolfgang</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bentall, Richard P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Read, John</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varese, Filippo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Smeets, Feikje</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lataster, Tineke</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evidencia sugiere que las experiencias adversas en la infancia están asociadas con psicosis. Para examinar la asociación entre adversidad infantil y trauma (abuso sexual, maltrato físico, maltrato psicológico/emocional, negligencia, muerte parental y bullying) y pronóstico de psicosis, se realizó una búsqueda entre enero de 1980 y noviembre de 2011 en MEDLINE, EMBASE, PSychINFO, y Web of Science. El análisis incluyó 18 estudios de caso-control (n=2.048 pacientes psicóticos y 1.856 no psicóticos), 10 estudios prospectivos y cuasi prospectivos (n=41.803) y 8 estudios poblacionales de corte transversal (n=35.546). Hubo asociaciones significativas entre adversidad y psicosis en todas las investigaciones. Los estudios de caso control indicaron que los pacientes con psicosis tuvieron 2,72 veces más probabilidad de que hayan estado expuestos a la adversidad en la infancia que los controles. La asociación entre adversidad en la infancia y psicosis también fue significativa en los estudios poblacionales de corte transversal, así como en estudios prospectivos y cuasi prospectivos. Estos hallazgos indican que la adversidad en la infancia está fuertemente asociada con un riesgo elevado de psicosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(21): 51-64, abr. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las adversidades en la infancia aumentan el riesgo de psicosis: metaanálisis con pacientes control y estudios de cohortes prospectivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
