<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053981</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical evacuation in biosecurity conditions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The possibility of airborne or vector/fomite transmission of infectious diseases renders necessary the institution of cleaning/decontamination and desinfection protocols for medicalised transport vehicles. This causes health care resources and implements to be inoperative for variable periods of time depending on the procedures used. The possibility of transmission increases in the case of emergent or re-emergent diseases, and becomes critical when transport of presumably or confirmedly NBC (Nuclear - Biological - Chemical) agent-affected individuals is contemplated. Hence the necessity to use more or less complex isolation systems and means which may even allow performing a number of medical procedures. The advantages of such protocols or systems range from the reduction and shortening of the in situ health care / medical assistance times where the ABC incident has occurred, through the optimisation of resources through the reduction of the non-operative periods of medicalised transport means, down to reducing the stress levels of the health-care personnel by not having to use personal protection devices and equipment in order to feel personally safe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cique Moya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La posibilidad de transmisión de enfermedades infecciosas por vía  aerógena o por fomites, hace necesario la instauración de protocolos  de limpieza y desinfección en los vehículos de transporte  sanitario, y provoca que los recursos sanitarios estén inoperativos  durante más o menos tiempo de acuerdo a los procedimientos empleados.  Esta posibilidad de transmisión es mayor si cabe cuando nos referimos  a enfermedades emergentes o reemergentes, y se hace crítica  cuando debamos realizar transporte sanitario de personas que hayan  resultado afectadas por agentes NBQ. Y de aquí surge la necesidad  de utilizar sistemas de aislamiento más o menos complejos, que permitan  incluso realizar ciertos actos médicos. Las ventajas de su uso  irán desde reducirse los tiempos de asistencia sanitaria en la zona  donde se haya producido un incidente NBQ, pasando por una optimización  de recursos al disminuir los tiempos de inoperatividad de los  transportes sanitarios, hasta reducir los niveles de estrés del personal  sanitario al no tener que utilizar equipos de protección individual para  sentirse seguros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);19(3): 144-150, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evacuación sanitaria en condiciones de bioseguridad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10550^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28837^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25093</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28479^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22766^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
