<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107376</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cherubism: diagnosis and treatment in the pediatric age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cherubism is a benign bone dysplasia of childhood, exclusively involving maxillary bones and spontaneous resolving after puberty indifferent grades. Approximately, 280 cases have been reviewed in the literature. It is an autosomal dominant disorder in which the normal bone is replaced by cellular fibrous and immature bone, resulting in painless symmetrical enlargement of the jaws. Diagnosis is based inclinical and radiological findings, confirmed by histology. Treatment is a controversial issue, and it is recommended surgical management as conservative as possible during the rapid growth phases. An aggressive case of cherubism is reported, diagnosed and followed since early childhood until puberty, with progressive involvement of facial bones developing in a disruption of facial contours and occlusion. The patient is treated by several surgical interventions oriented to minimize the aesthetic impact of the disease being as conservative as possible. The highlights of this case are the great proportion of the lesions, the functional and emotional disturbances brought out by these lesions and the difficulty to choose the most appropriate age and form of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Burgos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Piqueras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgueño García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El querubismo es una displasia ósea benigna de la infancia, que afecta exclusivamente a los huesos maxilares y se resuelve en gradovariable de forma espontánea durante la pubertad. Se han descrito aproximadamente 280 casos en la literatura, la mayoría en varones. Es una enfermedad hereditaria autosómica dominante en la que el hueso normal es sustituido por hueso fibroso e inmaduro, dando lugar a una expansión indolora simétrica de los maxilares. El diagnóstico es clínico y radiológico, confirmado por la histología. El manejo es controvertido, recomendándose una actitud quirúrgica lo más conservadora posible durante la fases de crecimiento rápido. Se presenta un caso agresivo de querubismo diagnosticado y seguido desde la infancia precoz hasta la pubertad, con afectación progresiva amplia de los huesos faciales, provocando una disrupción de los contornos de la cara y la oclusión. El paciente es tratado mediante una serie de intervenciones encaminadas aminimizar el impacto estético de la enfermedad de la forma más conservadora posible. El interés del caso se centra en la amplia extensión dela enfermedad, los trastornos funcionales y emocionales que provoca y la dificultad para elegir el momento adecuado y el tipo de intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;25(1): 56-59, ene. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Querubismo: diagnóstico y tratamiento en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23965^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
