<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146764</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Septic arthritis due to methylcyllin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Septic arthritis due to methylcyllin resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) is a serious infection that has increased in incidence in the past 10years. Methods. We conducted a retrospective study (1984-2011) in which a description of the clinical and epidemiological characteristics of MRSA arthritis in adults was performed and then compared to native joint infections caused by MRSA vs. methylcyllin sensitive Staphylococcus aureus (MSSA). Results. Fourteen MRSA infections were included (7 native joint, 5 prosthetic and 2 bursae). No case was polyarticular. There was significant comorbidity, although none was associated to rheumatoid arthritis. Seven patients had bacteremia. Four required surgical treatment. Six died. When comparing the 7 patients with native joint MRSA infection with the 17 cases caused by MSSA, no significant differences in risk factors were seen, except more malignancies in the MRSA group. The infection was polyarticular in 7 cases (41%) of the MSSA group. Bacteremia was more frequent in the MRSA group (71.4 vs 58.8%). Empirical antibiotic was useful in 28.6% of MRSA cases versus 100% of MSSA cases. There was a greater tendency to associated mortality in MRSA arthritis (57.1% vs 17.6%, P=.07). Conclusions. MRSA septic arthritis is a serious condition that occurs in the elderly and patients with high comorbidity. It is usually monoarticular, with positive blood cultures and higher mortality than MSSA arthritis. In patients at risk, vancomycin empiric antibiotic therapy is indicated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gimenez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinos, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivé, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La artritis séptica por Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina (SARM) es una infección grave que ha aumentado su incidencia en los últimos 10años. Métodos. Estudio retrospectivo (1984-2011) en el que se realiza una descripción de las características clínicas y epidemiológicas de las artritis por SARM en adultos y se comparan después las infecciones en articulación nativa causadas por SARM vs Staphylococcus aureus sensible a la meticilina (SASM). Resultados. Se incluyeron 14 infecciones por SARM (7 sobre articulación nativa, 5 protésicas y 2 bursas). Ningún caso fue poliarticular. Tenían importante comorbilidad, aunque ninguno con artritis reumatoide. Siete pacientes presentaron bacteriemia. Cuatro requirieron tratamiento quirúrgico. Seis fallecieron. Se compararon los 7 pacientes con infección de articulación nativa por SARM con los 17 casos causados por SASM. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en los factores de riesgo, excepto más neoplasias en el grupo SARM. La infección fue poliarticular en 7 casos (41%) del grupo SASM. La bacteriemia fue más frecuente en el grupo SARM (71,4 vs 58,8%). El antibiótico empírico resultó apropiado en el 28,6% de los casos SARM, frente al 100% de los casos SASM. Existió mayor tendencia a la mortalidad en las artritis por SARM (57,1% vs 17,6%, p=0,07). Conclusión. La artritis séptica por SARM es una entidad grave que acontece en pacientes ancianos y con gran comorbilidad. Es generalmente monoarticular, con hemocultivos positivos y mayor mortalidad que la artritis por SASM. En los pacientes de riesgo el tratamiento antibiótico empírico indicado es la vancomicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(6): 381-386, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis séptica por Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina en adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
