<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142191</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary affection mimicking a tumor as initial manifestation of polymyositis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Polymyositis is characterized by proximal muscle weakness, in most cases with arthralgias, Raynaud phenomenon and systemic symptoms. This is a multisystemic disorder that frequently affects other organs, pulmonary affection being one of the most frequent. We present the case of a 62-year old man who came to the consulting room with a respiratory infection that progressively worsened in spite of treatment. He was diagnosed of pulmonary affection with high suspicion of non-small cell lung cancer, so that a lower right lobectomy was performed. The histology of the extirpated lobe showed a lesion without any tumoral transformation. A few months later, the dyspnea had disappeared but he manifested important asthenia, polyarthalgias, myalgias and proximal muscle weakness in the four limbs. The subsequent study was consistent with polymyositis. Based on the above, we can conclude that the pulmonary affection that initially mimicked a cancer had been the first manifestation of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Vadillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado Prieto, L. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triano Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La polimiositis se manifiesta por debilidad muscular proximal acompañada en muchos casos de artralgias, Raynaud y síntomas constitucionales. Es una enfermedad multisistémica que con frecuencia afecta a otros órganos. La afección pulmonar es de las más frecuentes. Se presenta el caso de un varón de 62 años que acudió a consulta por un cuadro de infección respiratoria que empeoró progresivamente a pesar del tratamiento. Se le diagnosticó lesión pulmonar con alta sospecha de carcinoma no microcítico, por lo que se realizó lobectomía inferior derecha. El resultado histológico del lóbulo extirpado fue una lesión sin signos de transformación tumoral. Unos meses después la disnea había desaparecido, pero persistía importante astenia; además aparecieron poliartralgias, mialgias y debilidad muscular proximal de las cuatro extremidades. En el estudio ulterior se le diagnosticó polimiositis. Con todo esto, podemos concluir que la afección pulmonar, que inicialmente parecía un tumor, había sido la primera manifestación de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(1): 49-52, ene. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afectación pulmonar que simula un tumor como manifestación inicial de polimiositis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
