<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120673</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity and sedentarism in children and adolescents: What should be bone?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paediatric overweight continues to be a public health problem, and the etiology of obesity is multifactorial and complex. Dietary patterns, physical activity (PA) and sedentary behaviors are acknowledged as major behavioural determinants of obesity. New technologies and electronic based activities have produced a decrease in PA levels, and an increase in sedentary activities in children and adolescents. Potential mechanisms that explain the association between TV viewing and childhood obesity are: displacement of PA, unhealthy food preferences produced by food advertisements, a higher energy intake by automatic eating and overconsumption caused by distraction. Interventions aimed to reduce time in sedentary behaviours are in children generally positive. However, their benefits on adiposity markers are small. Thus, if global and macro-level obesogenic factors are not changed substantially, the interventions oriented to prevent obesity will produce small benefits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Aznar, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaliestra-Pasías, Alba M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey-López, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sobrepeso en población en edad pediátrica continúa siendo uno de los problemas de salud pública. La alimentación, actividad física y las conductas sedentarias son los mayores determinantes de la obesidad. Las nuevas tecnologías y las actividades basadas en la electrónica han producido un descenso en los niveles de actividad física y un aumento delas actividades sedentarias en niños y adolescentes. Diversos mecanismos se han sugerido para explicar la asociación entrever la televisión y la obesidad: desplazamiento de actividad física, los efectos de la publicidad de alimentos, el aumento de la ingesta energética en ausencia de hambre (automáticamente),y el aumento de la ingesta producida por la distracción. Intervenciones orientadas a reducir el comportamiento sedentario en niños y adolescentes han mostrado ser exitosas. Sin embargo, su impacto sobre marcadores de adiposidad es pequeño. Por lo tanto, si los factores obeso génicos que dependen de escalas a nivel global y macro no son cambiados substancialmente, los beneficios de las intervenciones para prevenirla obesidad serán muy modestos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(supl.5): 99-104, sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad y sedentarismo en niños y adolescentes: ¿qué debería hacerse?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
