<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120926</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fungal keratitis caused by Colletotrichum spp. A presentation of case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 23 years old male with an unremarkable past medical history suffered an injury with a branch of a lemon tree in the right eye two days prior to presentation. The slit-lamp examination showed a central corneal erosion with a white tree-shaped stromal infiltrate and Tyndall +/++ in anterior chamber. Cultivation of corneal scraping was positive for Colletotrichum spp. The patient responded favourably to topical amphotericin. Discussion: Colletotrichum spp. is an uncommon cause of keratitis, usually secondary to corneal erosion caused by plant material and should be included in the differential diagnosis of fungal keratitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Morales, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado Montalbán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles de Imperal Mora Figueroa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morcillo Guardiola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villegas Pérez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Paciente varón de 23 años sin antecedentes personales de interés que acude por traumatismo con rama de limonero en ojo derecho hacía dos días. En la biomicroscopia se observaba una erosión corneal central, un infiltrado estromal arboriforme blanquecino y un Tyndall +/++. El cultivo de raspado corneal fue positivo para Colletotrichum spp. El paciente respondió favorablemente a la anfotericina tópica. Discusión: Colletotrichum spp. constituye una causa infrecuente de queratitis, secundaria generalmente a erosiones ocasionadas por productos de origen vegetal, y debe ser incluido en el diagnóstico diferencial de las queratitis fúngicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(3): 110-112, mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120926</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queratitis fúngica por Colletotrichum spp. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24641^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33739^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24638^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
