<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82688</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of nutritional status in esophageal atresia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of the study was to find out whether patients who underwent esophageal atresia (EA) surgery suffered from nutritional problems, to compare the nutritional status of these patients with a control group, and to determine if there is a relationship between the type of atresia and the nutritional condition. Material and methods: We selected 25 patients out of a total of 32 who underwent EA surgery in our hospital from 2000 to 2006. A retrospective was conducted study based on the information obtained from the medical histories. A case-control study was also carried out by selecting a control group from a randomized population. Results: The analyses performed showed that the mean weight and height Z-score was always negative, but not below &amp;#8722;2 SD. There was a significant decrease in the weight Z-score between 3 and 9 months and in the weight/size Z-score between 3 and 24 months. Significant differences in weight and size Z-score were found between cases and controls, but not in skin-fold thickness. Independently of the type of atresia and the presence or not of congenital heart defects, no significant differences were found. Conclusions: There are significant differences in the weight and height Z-score between cases and controls. We stress the need to be aware of the nutritional status in order to prevent changes that could lead to a further deterioration of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clavero Montañés, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez López, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Bernal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zandueta Pascual, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares López, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar si aparecen alteraciones nutricionales en el desarrollo de los pacientes intervenidos de atresia de esófago, comparar el estado nutricional de estos pacientes con un grupo control y valorar si existe relación entre el tipo de atresia y el estado nutricional. Material y métodos: Se selecciona a 25 pacientes del total de 32 intervenidos por atresia de esófago en el período comprendido entre los años 2000&#150;2006 en nuestro hospital. Se realiza un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo basado en la recopilación de datos de las historias clínicas. Se realiza también un estudio analítico tipo casos-control para lo cual se selecciona de manera aleatoria una población control de niños sanos. Resultados: En los controles realizados, la media de la Z-score de peso y talla es siempre negativa, sin estar por debajo de &amp;#8722;2 desviación estándar. Se observa que se produce una disminución significativa en la Z-score del peso entre los 3&#150;9 meses y de la Z-score del peso/talla entre los 3&#150;24 meses. Resultados: Entre el grupo de casos y de controles se han encontrado diferencias significativas en la Z-score de peso y talla actual sin encontrarse diferencias en los pliegues cutáneos. No se han demostrado diferencias significativas en función del tipo de atresia y la existencia o no de cardiopatía asociada. Conclusiones: Existen diferencias significativas en la Z-score de peso y talla entre casos y controles. Destacamos la necesidad de prestar atención al estado nutricional de estos niños para que en el caso de que aparezcan alteraciones se detecten precozmente y se lleven a cabo las intervenciones nutricionales para evitar el deterioro del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(2): 74-77, ago. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82688</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del estado nutricional en los pacientes afectos de atresia de esófago</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29567^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5023^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
