<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111455</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experimental study about the effects of quercetin on the organic and cognitive dysfunction induced by ionizing radiation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the effect of oral quercetin supplementation on the behavioral, biochemical, and histological alterations by a sublethal X-ray dose in rats. Materials and method: Male Wistar rats, supplemented with 50 mg/kg quercetin or solvent, were whole-body irradiated with 6 Gy X-rays. MRI was obtained at 2, 7, 15, and 30 days post-irradiation. Open field exploratory behavior was observed before and after irradiation. Rats were sacrificed at 7 and 30 days post-irradiation, and blood, brain, spinal cord, and bone marrow samples were obtained. Results: Red cell, white cell, and platelet counts strongly decreased at 7 days post-irradiation. White cell and platelet counts recovered at 30 days post-irradiation, with no effect by quercetin. MRI shows focal microbleeds consistent with the histological findings of cell infiltration by neurovascular alterations, more evident in non-supplemented rats. Quercetin improved these changes and reverted the decrease in exploratory activity due to Xirradiation. Conclusions: Preventive use of quercetin could improve early behavioral symptoms and decrease tissue damage appearing shortly after radiotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreras, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, C. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costilla, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marina, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comprobar el efecto de la incorporación de quercetina por vía oral sobre las alteraciones comportamentales, bioquímicas e histológicas de una dosis subletal de rayos X en la rata. Material y método: Se irradiaron a cuerpo entero con 6 Gy de rayos X ratas Wistar macho suplementadas o no con 50 mg/kg de quercetina. Se obtuvieron imágenes por RM a los dos, siete, 15 y 30 días tras la irradiación, y se observó el comportamiento exploratorio mediante open field antes y después de la irradiación. Los animales se sacrificaron a los siete y 30 días, obteniéndose muestras de sangre, cerebro, médula espinal y médula ósea. Resultados: Se observó un fuerte descenso en el recuento eritrocitario, leucocitario y plaquetario a los siete días, recuperándose a los 30 días los recuentos leucocitario y plaquetario, sin efecto de la quercetina. La RM mostraba focos de microsangrado consistentes con los hallazgos histológicos de infiltración celular por alteraciones neurovasculares, más evidentes en animales no suplementados. La quercetina atenuó estas alteraciones y revertió la disminución de la actividad exploratoria ocasionada por la irradiación. Conclusiones: El uso preventivo de quercetina podría mejorar los síntomas comportamentales y disminuir el daño tisular a corto plazo tras sesiones de radioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(1): 24-32, ene.-mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio experimental sobre los efectos de la quercetina en la disfunción orgánica y cognitiva originada por radiación ionizante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23437^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12230^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23437^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12230^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12273</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
