<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156195</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metrics in academic profiles: a new addictive game for researchers?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims to promote reflection and bring attention to the potential adverse effects of academic social networks on science. These academic social networks, where authors can display their publications, have become new scientific communication channels, accelerating the dissemination of research results, facilitating data sharing, and strongly promoting scientific collaboration, all at no cost to the user. One of the features that make them extremely attractive to researchers is the possibility to browse through a wide variety of bibliometric indicators. Going beyond publication and citation counts, they also measure usage, participation in the platform, social connectivity, and scientific, academic and professional impact. Using these indicators they effectively create a digital image of researchers and their reputations. However, although academic social platforms are useful applications that can help improve scientific communication, they also hide a less positive side: they are highly addictive tools that might be abused. By gamifying scientific impact using techniques originally developed for videogames, these platforms may get users hooked on them, like addicted academics, transforming what should only be a means into an end in itself (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado López-Cózar, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Martín, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orduna-Malea, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Pretende este trabajo provocar la reflexión y alertar de los posibles peligros para la ciencia que encierran las nuevas redes sociales académicas que tanto éxito están teniendo en nuestros días. Las redes sociales académicas donde los autores pueden mostrar sus publicaciones se han convertido en nuevos canales de comunicación científica, pues agilizan la diseminación de los resultados de investigación, facilitan la compartición de datos y fomentan la colaboración científica de forma extensa sin coste alguno. Una de las novedades principales de estas plataformas, que es lo que las hace enormemente atractivas para los investigadores, consiste en la disponibilidad de una amplia batería de indicadores bibliométricos que van más allá del conteo de publicaciones y citas pues permiten medir el uso, la participación, la conectividad social y el impacto científico, académico y profesional. Sobre estos indicadores se está construyendo la propia imagen y reputación digital de los científicos. Pues bien, todos estos beneficios de las redes sociales académicas en la mejora de la comunicación científica esconden un lado no tan positivo para la ciencia. Se trata de herramientas muy peligrosas, que pueden convertirse en auténticas adicciones. Mediante la gamificación del impacto científico a través de persuasivas técnicas procedentes de los videojuegos, estas plataformas pueden hacer que los usuarios queden enganchados, como académicos adictos, convirtiendo lo que es un medio en un fin en sí mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;90: 0-0, 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métricas en perfiles académicos: ¿un nuevo juego adictivo para los investigadores?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d49^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54836^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12529^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
