<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21169</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inverted papilloma: treatment and evolution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inverted Papilloma is a frequent benign nasosinusal tumour. The high frequency of recurrences and the malignant potential are its clinical characteristics. We present our experience in a retrospective study done in the last 10 years. 10 patients with Inverted Papilloma have been treated during that period. According to the Classification made by krouse who divides the Inverted Papilloma in four stages, we found 3 in stage I, 6 in stage II and 1 in stage IV. The treatment in almost all of the patients in Stage I and II was endonasal surgery. External approach was performed for stage IV. The recurrence rate was 30% and malignization occurred in 10% of the cases. Finally, we have compared other publications, and revised the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El papiloma invertido es una tumoración que afecta principalmente a las cavidades nasosinusales. Clínicamente se caracteriza por su elevado porcentaje de recidivas y la posibilidad de malignización. Presentamos nuestra experiencia de 10 años, a través de un estudio retrospectivo en el cual encontramos 10 pacientes portadores de esta patología. De acuerdo a la clasificación de Krouse, quien divide los Papilomas Invertidos en cuatro estadios, encontramos a tres en Estadio I, seis en Estadio II y uno en Estadio IV. El tratamiento efectuado fue principalmente cirugía endonasal en Estadio I y II y abordaje externo en Estadio IV. La recidiva fue del 30 por ciento y la malignización del 10 por ciento. Finalmente realizamos una comparación con la experiencia acumulada en la literatura revisada. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;54(4): 242-248, mar. 2003. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papiloma invertido: tratamiento y evolución</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Gorostiaga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altuna, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zulueta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henríquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algaba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21169</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31219^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22601^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
