<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053393</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of odontogenic infection of pulpal and periodontal origin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The dental biofilm is a complex bacterial ecosystem that undergoes evolution, maturing and development, and thus leads to odontogenic infection. The infection is normally located in the tissues of the dental organ itself, and follows a chronic course of evolution. However, bacterial pathogens express virulence factors in the biofilm, and this together with changesin host immunity, may cause clinical exacerbations and spread of infection to other areas of the body. Odontogenic infection management should take into consideration the fact that therapeutic success lies in the control of the infectious aetiologic agent, using mechanical-surgical debridement and/or antimicrobial therapy. Debridement techniques have a fundamentally quantitative effect (by reducing the size of the inoculum) and therefore if these techniques are used alone to control infection, despite an initial clinical improvement that is sometimes prematurely considered as therapeutic success, odontopathogens may persist and the process may recur or become chronic. Microbiological examination may be helpful in defining therapeutic success in a more reliable way, it could define the prognosis of recurrence more precisely, and could enable the most appropriate antibiotic to be selected, thus increasing therapeutic efficacy. Antimicrobial therapy brings about a quantitative and qualitative change in the bacterial composition of the biofilm, in addition to being able to act on sites that are inaccessible through mechanical debridement. However, incorrect antimicrobial use can lead to a selection of resistant bacterial species in the biofilm, in addition to side effects and ecological alterations in the host. In order to minimise this risk, and obtain maximum antimicrobial effect, we need to know in which clinical situations their use is indicated, and the efficacy of different antibiotics with regard to bacteria isolated in odontogenic infection</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Píriz, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La biopelícula dental es un ecosistema bacteriano complejo cuya evolución, maduración y desarrollo ocasiona la infecciónodontogénica. Habitualmente la infección se encuentra localizada en los tejidos del propio órgano dentario y sigue un curso evolutivo crónico, aunque la expresión de factores de virulencia bacterianos en la biopelícula o cambios en la situación inmune del huésped pueden ocasionar exacerbaciones clínicas y la extensión de la infección a otras zonas del organismo. En el abordaje de la infección odontogénica debemos tener presente que el éxito terapéutico radica en el control del agente etiológico infeccioso, mediante desbridamiento con técnicas mecánico-quirúrgicas y/o administraciónde antimicrobianos. El efecto de las técnicas de desbridamiento sobre la biopelícula es fundamentalmente de tipo cuantitativo (disminuye el tamaño del inóculo) de modo que su empleo como único medio de control de la infección puede suponer la persistencia de odontopatógenos y la recurrencia o cronificación del proceso, aunque obtengamos una mejoría clínica inicial que en ocasiones consideramos éxito terapéutico de modo precipitado. Realizar un estudio micro-biológico podría ayudar a definir el éxito terapéutico con mayor fiabilidad, dar más exactitud a nuestros pronósticos de recurrencia, y seleccionar el antibiótico más apropiado aumentando la eficacia terapéutica. El tratamiento antimicrobiano ocasiona un cambio cuantitativo y cualitativo en la composición bacteriana de la biopelícula, además de poder actuar en lugares no accesibles al desbridamiento mecánico. Sin embargo, un mal uso de los antimicrobianos puede ocasionar selección de especies bacterianas resistentes en la biopelícula además de efectos secundarios y alteraciones ecológicas en el huésped. Para minimizar este riesgo y obtener el máximo rendimiento del empleo de antimicrobianos es preciso conocer las situaciones clínicas que indican su uso y la eficacia de los distintos antibióticos frente a los aislados en la infección odontogénica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(2): E154-E159, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053393</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de infección odontogénica de origen pulpar y periodontal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10699^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10699^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10699^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
