<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154024</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Haemodynamic changes in duplex ultrasound after native renal artery stenting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To describe the haemodynamic changes in duplex ultrasound after angioplasty and stenting of the native renal artery (RA). Patients and methods: All native RA angioplasties performed between 2000 and 2013 were retrospectively analysed, selecting those cases: 1) Duplex ultrasound within 6 months before and after the procedure, 2) unilateral renal artery angioplasty and stenting with patency of the contralateral RA. The flow velocities at the origin of the treated and untreated RA, and the renal aortic ratio (RAR), were compared using the Wilcoxon test before and after the procedure. Results: Seventy-one cases (40%) satisfied the inclusion criteria, all of them without significant residual stenosis after the procedure. In the treated arteries, the mean velocity decreased significantly by 56% after the procedure (341  vs. 164 cm/s; P&lt;.00). The post-angioplasty flow velocity in 73% of these RAs decreased to within the normal range (&lt;200 cm/s). The mean velocity in contralateral RAs (untreated) also significantly decreased by 13% (199 vs. 175 cm/s; P&lt;.029). After angioplasty, the percentage of contralateral RAs with velocity above normal (&gt;200 cm/s) fell from 41 to 33%. The RAR also showed a statistically significant decrease in the treated RA (413 vs. 1.87; P&lt;.000) and untreated RA (2.71 vs. 2.28; P&lt;.026). Conclusions: Duplex ultrasound after renal angioplasty and stenting produced a significant decrease in the flow velocity at the origin of both the treated and untreated RAs. The latter finding suggests the existence of a vicarious acceleration in the untreated renal artery, which decreases when correcting the lesion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibañez Pallares, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa Aranguren, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacambra Peñart, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clará Velasco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos Torres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir los cambios hemodinámicos que se producen en el ecodoppler tras una angioplastia con stent de arteria renal (AR) nativa. Pacientes y métodos: Se analizaron retrospectivamente todas las angioplastias sobre AR nativa realizadas entre los años 2000 y 2013, seleccionando aquellos casos con: 1) ecodoppler durante los 6 meses previos y posteriores al procedimiento, 2) angioplastia con stent de una AR con permeabilidad de la contralateral. Se compararon mediante el test de Wilcoxon las velocidades en el origen de ambas AR y la ratio renoaórtica (RAR), antes y después del procedimiento. Resultados: Setenta y un casos (40%) cumplieron los criterios de inclusión. En las arterias tratadas, la velocidad media disminuyó significativamente un 56% tras el procedimiento (341 vs. 164 cm/s; p &lt; 0,00). En un 73% de estas AR, las velocidades postangioplastia disminuyeron al rango de la normalidad (&lt;200 cm/s). En las AR contralaterales (no tratadas), la velocidad media también disminuyó significativamente un 13% (199 vs. 175 cm/s; p = 0,029). Tras la angioplastia disminuyó de 41 a 33% el porcentaje de AR contralaterales con velocidad por encima del valor normal (&gt;200 cm/s). La RAR también mostró una disminución estadísticamente significativa en la AR tratada (4,13 vs. 1,87; p &lt; 0,000) como en la no tratada (2,71 vs. 2,28; p &lt; 0,026). Conclusiones: En la exploración ecodoppler tras una angioplastia con stent renal se produce una disminución significativa de las velocidades en el origen de ambas AR, la tratada y la no tratada. Este último hallazgo indica la existencia de una aceleración vicariante en la arteria no tratada, que disminuye cuando se corrige la lesión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;68(4): 272-275, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154024</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios hemodinámicos en la exploración mediante eco-doppler tras angioplastia con stent de arteria renal nativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2346^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2346^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12498^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12498^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
