<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145575</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">V Consensus Meeting of the Spanish Society for Liver Transplant on high-risk recipients, immunosupression scenarios and management of hepatocarcinoma on the transplant waiting list</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the aim to promote the elaboration of consensus documents on state of the art topics in liver transplantation with multidisciplinary management, the Spanish Society for Liver Transplantation (SETH) organized the V Consensus Meeting with the participation of experts from all the Spanish liver transplant programs. In this edition, the following topics were revised, and we present the summary: 1. High-risk receptors; 2. Immunosuppression scenarios; and 3. Management of the patient with hepatocarcinoma in the waiting list (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briceño, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con objeto de promover la elaboración de documentos de consenso sobre temas de actualidad en trasplante hepático de abordaje multidisciplinario, la Sociedad Española de Trasplante Hepático (SETH) ha realizado la V Reunión de Consenso con participación de expertos de todos los programas de trasplante hepático españoles. En esta edición se han abordado los siguientes temas, cuyo resumen ofrecemos a continuación: 1. Receptores de riesgo elevado; 2. Escenarios de inmunosupresión, y 3. Manejo del paciente con hepatocarcinoma en lista de espera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(10): 619-637, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145575</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">V Reunión de Consenso de la Sociedad Española de Trasplante Hepático sobre receptores de riesgo elevado, escenarios actuales de inmunosupresión y manejo del hepatocarcinoma en espera de trasplante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33103^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
