<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052514</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beneficial effects of adding ezetimibe to maximum- dose statins on serum lipid control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Clinical trials have shown that the addition of ezetimibe, a selective inhibitor of cholesterol absorption, to statins reduces low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (cLDL) by an additional 20% over statin monotherapy. However, the question of whether the same is true in clinical practice remains to be determined. Objective: To assess the effect of the addition of ezetimibe on cLDL and its action on other serum lipids (SL) in clinical practice in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in whom maximum-dose of statins failed to achieve the recommended goals. Patients and methods: Sixty-six patients with T2DM (27 men and 39 women) with dyslipidemia treated with maximum-dose atorvastatin, fluvastatin, pravastatin or simvastatin and with cLDL &gt; 100 mg/dl, were included in this study. Disease duration was 13.4 ± 9.8 years and age was 64.8 ± 10.3 years. In all patients, we measured total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (HDL-C) and triglyceride (TG) levels and calculated cLDL before and 9 months after adding an evening dose of 10 mg of ezetimibe to a maximum-dose statin. The percentage of patients who reached the SL targets according to the American Diabetes Association recommendations before and 9 months after adding ezetimibe treatment was compared. Results: After 9 months of adding ezetimibe, 58% of patients achieved the cLDL target of &lt; 100 mg/dl (P=.000). There was also a significant decrease in mean TC (P=.000), cLDL (P=.000) and TG (P=.01) and an increase in HDL-C (P=.025). Conclusions: In clinical practice, the addition of ezetimibe achieved the cLDL target in almost 60% of the patients with T2DM and dyslipidemia in the population studied, in whom maximum-dose statin monotherapy failed to achieve the recommended goals. In addition to this effect, the increase in HDL-C and the decrease in TC and TG observed reveal the importance of the addition of ezetimibe to statins in the treatment of T2DM patients with dyslipidemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bohigas Roldan, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira Andrés, María N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Puebla, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañizo Gomez, Francisco J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La coadministración de ezetimiba, un inhibidor de la absorción de colesterol, y estatinas ha demostrado en ensayos clínicos reducir el colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) un 20% con respecto a estatinas en monoterapia. Pero, ¿ocurre lo mismo en la práctica clínica? Objetivo: Valorar en la clínica diaria, los efectos de la adición de ezetimiba en el cLDL y en el grado de control de los lípidos séricos (LS), en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) en los que dosis máximas de estatinas no consigan los objetivos de buen control. Pacientes y métodos: A 66 pacientes con DM2 de 13,4 ± 9,8 años de evolución (27 hombres y 39 mujeres) de 64,8 ± 10,3 años de edad, con dislipidemia tratada con dosis máximas de atorvastatina, fluvastatina, pravastatina o simvastatina, y un cLDL &gt; 100 mg/dl, se les administró, conjuntamente con la dosis máxima de estatina, una dosis diaria de 10 mg de ezetimiba en la cena. A todos se les determinó el colesterol total (CT), el colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad (cHDL) y los triglicéridos (TG), y se calculó el cLDL antes y a los 9 meses de añadir ezetimiba a la estatina. Además, se comparó el porcentaje de pacientes que cumplían los objetivos de buen control para los LS según la American Diabetes Association (ADA), antes y a los 9 meses de añadir ezetimiba. Resultados: A los 9 meses de añadir ezetimiba, el 58 % de los pacientes alcanzaron un cLDL &lt; 100 mg/dl (p = 0,000). Asimismo, se observó una disminución significativa del CT (p = 0,000), cLD (p = 0,000) y TG (p = 0,01), y un incremento del cHDL (p = 0,025). Conclusiones: En la práctica clínica habitual, la adición de ezetimiba consiguió los objetivos de buen control para el cLDL en casi el 60% de los pacientes con DM2 y dislipidemia de la población estudiada, que no lo habían conseguido con dosis máximas de estatinas en monoterapia. Este efecto, unido al incremento del cHDL y a la disminución del CT y de los TG observado, ponen de manifiesto la importancia de ezetimiba coadministrada con estatinas en el tratamiento de pacientes con DM2 y dislipidemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(3): 139-144, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos beneficiosos de la adición de ezetimiba a dosis máximas de estatinas en el control de los lípidos séricos en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
