<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151512</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect on an antibacterial adhesive (Clearfil Protect Bond) in the adhesive force of composite&#146;s resins orthodontics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To determine if the bonding capacity of the orthodontic bonding system Transbond XT used in combination with Clearfil Protect Bond (CPB) is equal to that obtained using either Transbond XT with Adper Prompt L-Pop (Adper PLP)or traditional acid etch technique. Brackets were bonded to extracted human premolars using Transbond XT. Bonding was carried out following one of three procedures for enamel preparation: (1) Phosphoroc acid etch at 37%; (2) CPB; (3) Adper PLP. Shear bond strength was measured with a universal test machine, the cross-head set at a speed of I mm/min. Bond material remaining on teeth after debonding was quantified using image analysis equipment. CPB showed significantly less bond strength than either Adper PLP or conventional acid etch technique (P&lt; 0.05). With both the acid etch technique and CPB significantly more bond material remained on the tooth after debonding than with Adper PLP (P&lt;0.05). Although the antibacterial self-etching primer CPB's bond strength was significantly less than that achieved by either the self-etching Adper PLP or acid etch technique, the values obtained remain above the minimum required for orthodontic practice. Further research into the use of bonding agents with anti-bacterial properties for bracket bonding is necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jacobo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Determinar si la capacidad adhesiva del sistema adhesivo ortodóncico Transbond XT junto con Clearfil Protect Bond (CPB) es equiparable a la obtenida cuando Transbond XT se utiliza con Adper Prompt L-Pop (Adper PLP) o a la técnica de grabado ácido tradicional. Los brackets fueron adheridos a premolares humanos extraídos usando Transbond XT. Este procedimiento fue llevado a cabo de acuerdo con uno de los siguientes3 protocolos de acondicionamiento del esmalte:(1) grabado con ácido fosfórico al 37%, (2) CPB, y (3) Adper PLP. La resistencia a las fuerzas de cizalla se midió con una máquina universal de test, con una velocidad de la cabeza de la máquina de I mm/min. El adhesivo remanente en el diente después del descementado fue cuantificado usando un equipo de análisis de imagen. CPB proporciona una fuerza adhesiva significativamente menor que Adper PLP y con la técnica de grabado ácido convencional (p&lt; 0.05). Con la técnica de grabado ácido convencional y con CPB quedaba tras el descementado significativamente más adhesivo en el diente que con Adper PLP (P&lt;O.05).Aunque la fuerza adhesiva del autograbante antibacteriano CPB fue significativamente menor que la obtenida con el autograbante Adper PLP y con la técnica de grabado ácido, los valores se encuentran por encima de los mínimos requeridos en Ortodoncia. Son necesarios más estudios sobre la incorporación de productos adhesivos con propiedades antibacterianas en la adhesión de brackets (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);47(3): 177-182, jul.-sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de un adhesivo antibacteriano (Clearfil Protect Bond) en la fuerza adhesiva de las resinas de composite ortodóncicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29217^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3219^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3752^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
