<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112858</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of visual attentional biases in a sample of university smokers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The tobacco consumption continues being a worrying problem due to the negative consequences in the health. At presents, strategies of prevention based on the persuasion across clue pictures are used, which need to attract the attention of the smoker in order that they are effective. Nevertheless, the number of experimental studies in Spain on attentional biases in smokers is very limited. For it, in this study the aim was to verify the presence of visual attentional biases using the dot probe task in university smokers, stage where the smoking habit is consolidated. The sample was constituted by 337 students of the University of Huelva, with ages between 17 and 30 years. The participation was voluntary and the participants signed an informed assent. 135 subjects presented consumption history, which were distributed, according to classification of the WHO, in daily smokers, occasional smokers and former smokers. A experimental Ex post facto prospective design was used. The results showed that the smokers group was significantly later time to respond to the clue located in the same place that the tobacco picture than the group of not smokers. This shows that the smokers presented more difficulty to disconnect the attention towards smoking cues than not smokers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Orts, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Muñoz de Arenillas, Rocio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Domínguez, Zaira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de tabaco sigue siendo un problema preocupante debido a las consecuencias negativas que provoca en la salud. Actualmente, están empleándose estrategias de prevención basadas en la persuasión a través de imágenes, las cuales necesitan atraer la atención del fumador para que sean efectivas. Sin embargo, el número de estudios experimentales en España sobre sesgos atencionales en fumadores es muy reducido. Por ello, el objetivo planteado en este estudio fue comprobar la presencia de sesgos atencionales visuales a través de la tarea de detección del punto en fumadores universitarios, etapa donde se consolida el hábito tabáquico. La muestra estuvo formada por 337 estudiantes de la Universidad de Huelva, con edades comprendidas entre los 17 y 30 años. La participación fue voluntaria y efectuada tras firmar un consentimiento informado. Hubo 135 sujetos con historia de consumo, los cuales se distribuyeron, según clasificación de la OMS, en fumadores diarios, fumadores ocasionales y exfumadores. Se utilizó un diseño de tipo Ex post facto prospectivo. Los resultados mostraron que el grupo de fumadores tardaba significativamente más tiempo en responder a las claves estimulares cuando aparecían situadas en el mismo lugar que la imagen relacionada con el tabaco que el grupo de no fumadores. Esto refleja una mayor dificultad a la hora de dejar de prestar atención hacia los estímulos relacionados con el tabaco por parte del grupo fumador con respecto al grupo no fumador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);25(2): 163-169, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de sesgos atencionales visuales en una muestra de fumadores universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
