<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150513</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anatomical, pathophysiological and neurochemical bases of rigid-akinetic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The rigid-akinetic syndromes include a heterogeneous collection of pathologies grouped by a series of common symptoms that appear in the motor, cognitive and emotional spheres. Development. The basal ganglia are made up of a group of anatomically dispersed structures that are nonetheless connected to each other and with several other structures to form a cluster of functional networks. Lesions in these circuits produce symptoms in the motor, cognitive and emotional spheres. Of all the syndromes that occur in Parkinson's disease, which is the best-known and most widely studied rigid-akinetic syndrome, only tremor and bradykinesia can presently be explained. Rigid-akinetic syndromes are nowadays considered to be neurodegenerative diseases that affect a number of structures and systems within the central and peripheral nervous system. Many of these can be included within the groups of synucleinopathies and tauopathies, although on occasions the pathological findings overlap between the two. Conclusions. Further knowledge of the functioning of the nervous system and the processes involved in neuronal degeneration is needed to be able to produce new, more effective therapeutic strategies (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobrido, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Antelo, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dias Silva, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puy Núñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sancho, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Real, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los síndromes rígido-acinéticos incluyen un grupo heterogéneo de patologías agrupados por una serie de síntomas comunes en las esferas motora, cognitiva y emocional. Desarrollo. Los ganglios basales están constituidos por un grupo de estructuras anatómicamente dispersas que se conectan entre sí y con diversas estructuras formando un entramado de redes funcionales. Las lesiones en estos circuitos producen síntomas en las esferas motora, cognitiva y emocional. En la enfermedad de Parkinson, el síndrome rígido-acinético más conocido y estudiado, actualmente sólo pueden explicarse del conjunto de sus síntomas el temblor y la bradicinesia. Los síndromes rígido-acinéticos se consideran hoy enfermedades neurodegenerativas que afectan a múltiples estructuras y sistemas del sistema nervioso central y periférico. Una gran parte de estos pueden agruparse dentro de las sinucleinopatías y las taupatías, aunque en ocasiones los hallazgos anatomopatológicos entre ambas se solapan. Conclusiones. Es preciso un mayor conocimiento del funcionamiento del sistema nervioso y los procesos de degeneración neuronal para poder obtener nuevas estrategias terapéuticas más eficaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(supl.4): s1-s12, 3 oct., 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases anatómicas, fisiopatológicas y neuroquímicas de los síndromes rígido-acinéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32181^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9318^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9318^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
