<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156863</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Why, and how, undertake mixed methods design in health research: a concrete experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of mixed methods to address health problems generates more knowledge of reality to get a more complete analysis of the problem under investigation. This is based on the fact that the answers to the questions posed are as subjective as the individuals themselves. In that way, it is necessary quantitative and qualitative data for comprehensiveness (a more realistic and comprehensive approach to the object of the study). Objective.Reflect on this methodology through a practical example. SyntheSiS. We explain, through Participatory Education Program Focused on Colorectal Cancer Surgery Patient (mixed methods research project: multistrand, sequential and mixed in each of its three phases), what is this methodology and its advantages. The second phase of the study emerges from the results of the first one, and so on. At the end of the study a metaresult, that gives meaning and response to the study in its entirety, arises. cOncluSiOn. Despite the challenges, mixed methods gives us a more accurate perspective of the phenomenon of study; It helps us to formulate the problem statement and the most appropriate way to study it; and finally, the scientific inferences obtained are more solidly supported (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias Rodríguez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llabres Sole, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa Álvarez, María Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perdomo Hernández, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Peraza, María Elisa de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Rocha, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de mezcla de métodos para abordar problemas de salud genera un mayor conocimiento de la realidad al obtener un análisis más completo del problema que se investiga. Este hecho se basa en que las respuestas a las preguntas que se formulan son tan subjetivas como los propios individuos, siendo necesario, por lo tanto, datos cuantitativos y cualitativos para una aproximación más real y completa al objeto del estudio. ObjetivO: Reflexionar sobre esta metodología mediante un ejemplo práctico. SínteSiS. Explicamos, a través del Programa Educativo Participativo Centrado en el Paciente de Cirugía Oncológica Colorrectal (mezcla de métodos multistrand, secuencial y mezclado en cada una de sus tres fases), en qué consiste esta metodología y sus ventajas. La segunda fase del estudio emerge de los resultados de la primera, y así sucesivamente. Al final del estudio surge un metarresultado que da sentido y respuesta al estudio en su totalidad. COnCluSión. A pesar de los retos que supone, la mezcla de métodos nos ofrece una perspectiva más precisa del fenómeno de estudio; nos ayuda a formular el planteamiento del problema y la forma más apropiada para estudiarlo; y, por último, se apoyan con mayor solidez las inferencias científicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(10): 650-656, oct. 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156863</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Por qué y cómo realizer diseños multimétodo en investigación en salud. Una experiencia concreta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10042^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10042^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
