<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122135</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Auditory and extra-auditory effects of noise in the fishing sector: two sides of the same coin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fishing sector has certain peculiarities which make it special, and that is why Royal Decree 286/2006 of 10 March, on the protection of health and safety of workers from risks related to noise exposure did not enter into force for this group until 16 February 2011. All the aforementioned RD, the RD 1299/2006 on occupational diseases and the protocol approved by the Ministry of Health for specific health surveillance for workers exposed to noise, only refer to the impact of exposure on hearing. However, multiple studies show the involvement of other organs and systems, as the negative impact of exposure to noise on psychophysical health including levels below 80 dB(A). This study conducted in the fishing sector (deep-sea and coastal fishing) aims to analyze the perception of workers about their health and the impact of noise exposure on hearing and other health in-dicators, such as accidents, psychosomatic disorders, cardiovascular disease, digestive disorders, sleep disorders or fatigue. The study reveals a high prevalence of extra-auditory disturbances due to noise exposure, so this evaluation should be included in specific medical checks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vilchez Medina, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Caro de la Rosa, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarín Guillermo, Soriano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dieguez Rodríguez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rubiales, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sector de la pesca tiene unas peculiaridades que lo hacen especial, y es por ello que el Real Decreto 286/2006, de 10 de Marzo, sobre la protección de la salud y la seguridad de los trabajadores contra los riesgos relacionados con la  exposición al ruido no entró en vigor para este colectivo hasta el 16 de febrero de 2011. Tanto el mencionado RD, como  l RD 1299/2006 de enfermedades profesionales y el propio protocolo aprobado por el Ministerio de Sanidad para la  vigilancia específica de la salud para trabajadores expuestos a ruido, sólo hacen referencia al impacto de la exposición sobre la audición. Sin embargo, son múltiples los estudios que demuestran tanto la afectación de otros órganos y  sistemas, como el impacto negativo de la exposición a ruido sobre la salud psicofísica incluso por debajo de niveles de  0dB(A). El presente estudio realizado entre trabajadores del sector de la pesca (gran altura, altura y bajura), tiene como  objetivo analizar la percepción de los trabajadores sobre su estado de salud y el impacto de la exposición a ruido sobre la audición y otros indicadores de salud exclusivamentales como la siniestralidad, alteraciones psicosomáticas, patología cardiovascular, trastornos digestivos, trastornos del sueño o la fatiga. El estudio pone de manifiesto una prevalencia elevada de alteraciones extra-auditivas por exposición a ruido, por lo que se debe incluir su evaluación en los controles médicos específicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;21(4): 8-17, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos auditivos y extra-auditivos del ruido en el sector de la pesca: dos caras de una misma moneda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6462^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9809^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9808^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
