<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111123</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical blogs as a source of training and information: the example of the blog "Pediatría basada en pruebas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Blogs have become a potential source of information and training in medicine in general and in pediatrics in particular, especially in the present health care environment in the social web. The authors&#146; personal experience relating to the blog Pediatría basada en pruebas has made possible to analyze the readers&#146; interests, as well as the communication movements around the Spanish pediatric blogosphere. The 1311 public entries from May 2008 to September 2012 are analyzed, with a detailed study of the 105 posts with more than 1000 visits. The subjects that interest the most to the readers of Pediatría basada en pruebas blog gather around six groups: 1) infectious diseases (flu, meningitis, septicemia, measles, chickenpox, vaccinations, etc.); 2) peri-neonatology (pregnancy and newborn subjects, some of them issued in two established sections named Propositus and Neo-Dividencias; 3) social subjects (smoking, injuries, immigration, bulling, etc.); 4) guidelines and reports of scientific societies; 5) established sections in the blog (five of them consolidated: Propositus, Neo-Dividencias, Training and Information in Pediatrics, Pediatric blogosphere summary and Cinema and Pediatrics; 6) controversies (subjects of special social and/or healthcare debate, that are the more commented ones and include subjects such as abortion, newborn circumcision, anti-vaccination groups, medical malpractice, etc.). Taking into account that blogs are already considered by the Spanish Pediatrics Association itself as a source of information, our compromise with the blog is to build this information in the best possible way. And the initial best possible way is to know our readers&#146; dynamics, and therefore staying rigorous and ethical, we can (and should) consider valid this way of transmitting training and information to our colleagues, patients and families, and to society in general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buñuel Álvarez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza Olcina, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los blogs se han convertido en una potencial fuente de información y formación en Medicina, en general, y en Pediatría, en particular, máxime en el actual entorno sanitario de la &#147;web social&#148;. La experiencia personal de los autores en relación con el blog Pediatría basada en pruebas ha permitido analizar el interés temático de los lectores del blog, así como los flujos de comunicación en el entorno de la &#147;blogosfera&#148; pediátrica española. Se analizan las 1311 entradas publicadas en el blog Pediatría basada en pruebas durante el periodo de revisión (de mayo de 2008 a septiembre de 2012), con un estudio pormenorizado de las 105 entradas que han recibido más de 1000 visitas. Los temas que más interesan a los lectores del blog Pediatría basada en pruebas se concentran en seis grupos: 1) enfermedades infecciosas (gripe, meningitis, sepsis, sarampión, varicela, vacunas, etc.); 2) Perineonatología (temas de la gestación y del recién nacido, algunos volcados en dos secciones ya consolidadas como Propositus y Neo-Dividencias); 3) temas sociales (tabaquismo, accidentes, inmigración, acoso escolar, etc.); 4) guías e informes de sociedades científicas; 5) secciones ya establecidas del blog (con cinco consolidadas: Propositus, Neo-Dividencias, Formación e Información en Pediatría, Resumen de la blogosfera pediátrica y Cine y Pediatría), y 6) polémicas (temas de especial debate social y/o médico y que corresponden con los más comentados, y donde se incluyen temas como el aborto, la circuncisión neonatal, grupos antivacunas, mala praxis sanitaria, etc.). Teniendo en cuenta que el entorno de los blogs ya es considerado por la propia Asociación Española de Pediatría como una fuente de información fiable, nuestro compromiso en el blog es construir esta información de la mejor forma posible. Y la mejor forma posible inicial es conocer la dinámica de nuestros lectores y, con ello, y sin dejar de ser rigurosos y éticos, podemos (y debemos) plantear como válida esta forma de transmitir formación e información a nuestros colegas de profesión, a pacientes y familias, y a la sociedad en general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;15(57): 27-35, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Blogs médicos como fuente de formación e información. El ejemplo del blog Pediatría basada en pruebas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54394^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
