<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92424</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical Management of Patient With Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify clinical management of benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) in Spain and its associated health care resources. Material and methods: A qualitative cross-sectional study was conducted through telephone interviews to general practitioners (GP) and urologists. Information about diagnosis, pharmacologic treatment and follow-up was collected. Results were clustered according to the key variables considered as drivers of clinical practice patterns: BPH diagnosis, severity classification, treatment initiation and follow up of patients. Results: 153 GP and 154 urologists participated in the study. 7 different clinical patterns were identified in primary care (PC). Resource use during diagnosis is relatively homogeneous, reporting a range of 2.0 to 2.6 visits employed and being the most frequent test performed PSA and urine test. Follow-up is heterogeneous; frequency of follow-up visits oscillates from 3.2 to 7.0 visits/patient/year and type of tests performed is different among patterns and within the same pattern. In Urology, 3 clinical patterns were identified. Resource use is homogeneous in the diagnosis and in the follow-up; urologists employed 2 visits in diagnosis and a range of 2.1 to 3.2 visits/patient/year in the follow-up. The most frequent tests both in diagnosis and follow-up are PSA and digital test. Conclusions: BPH management shows variability in PC, identifying 7 different clinical practice patterns with different resource use during the follow-up among patterns and within the same pattern. The implementation of clinical guidelines could be justified to reduce heterogeneity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brenes, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huerta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cozar, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Escolano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Pro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solsona, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer el manejo asistencial de la hiperplasia benigna de próstata (HBP) en España y el uso de recursos sanitarios asociado. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal mediante entrevistas telefónicas a médicos de atención primaria (MAP) y urólogos. Se recogió información acerca del diagnóstico, tratamiento y seguimiento. Los resultados se agruparon por patrones asistenciales, definidos a partir de las variables: diagnóstico, clasificación según sintomatología, inicio de tratamiento farmacológico y seguimiento. Resultados: Participaron 153 MAP y 154 urólogos. Se identificaron 7 patrones asistenciales en atención primaria (AP). El uso de recursos sanitarios en el diagnóstico presenta cierta homogeneidad, empleando de 2,0 a 2,6 visitas, siendo las pruebas diagnósticas más habituales el análisis de PSA y de orina. En el seguimiento se observa heterogeneidad en el uso de recursos. Las visitas de seguimiento oscilan entre 3,2 y 7,0 visitas/ paciente/ año y el tipo de pruebas realizadas varía entre patrones y dentro del mismo patrón. En Urología se identificaron tres patrones asistenciales. Existe homogeneidad en el uso de recursos en el diagnóstico y en el seguimiento. La frecuencia de visitas es de 2 para el diagnóstico y entre 2,1 y 3,2 visitas/paciente/año en el seguimiento. Las pruebas más comúnmente realizadas en el diagnóstico y en el seguimiento son el análisis de PSA y el tacto rectal. Conclusiones: En AP la asistencia prestada al paciente con HBP está sujeta a variabilidad, encontrándose 7 patrones asistenciales diferentes con un seguimiento heterogéneo entre patrones y dentro del mismo patrón. Esta situación podría justificar la necesidad de difusión e implantación de protocolos asistenciales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;35(10): 580-588, nov.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92424</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo asistencial del paciente con hiperplasia benigna de próstata en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
