<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036123</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro activity of amphotericin B, itraconazole and voriconazole against 20 species of Aspergillus using the Sensititre® microdilution method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND. The in vitro activity of antifungal agents against Aspergillus has been recently investigated. We studied the susceptibility to amphotericin B, itraconazole and voriconazole of 68 strains belonging to 20 different Aspergillus species. METHODS. The minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs)for 10 strains of A. fumigatus, 9 A. flavus, 8 A. niger,5 A. tamarii, 5 A. versicolor, 4 A. terreus, 3 A. glaucus,3 A. ochraceus, 3 A. oryzae, 2 A. candidus, 2 A. chevalieri,2 A. rubrobrunneus, 2 A. sclerotiorum, 2 A. sydowii,2 A. unguis, 2 A. ustus, 1 A. clavatus, 1 A. nidulans,1 A. pseudofischeri y 1 A. reptans, were determined using the Sensititre® Yeast One microdilution method. RESULTS. Voriconazole was more active in vitro thanamphotericin B and itraconazole, with 95.6% (65/68) ofstrains exhibiting MICs of = 2 mg/l); A. niger, A. versicolor,A. sclerotiorum and A. ustus showed in vitro resistance to itraconazole (MIC &gt;= 1 mg/l); and A. sclerotiorum and A. ustus displayed poor susceptibility to voriconazole(MIC &gt;= 2 mg/l).CONCLUSIONS. The susceptibility of Aspergillus species to itraconazole and voriconazole was generally good; never the less, susceptibility to amphotericin B was low. These results suggest that Aspergillus susceptibility testing to this antifungal agent would be advisable to guide treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Martos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Calzada, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saldarreaga, Abel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Aragón, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Agudo, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ANTECEDENTES. La actividad in vitro de los antifúngicos frente a Aspergillus se ha investigado recientemente. Estudiamos la sensibilidad frente a la anfotericina B, itraconazol y voriconazol de 68 cepas pertenecientes a 20 especies diferentes de Aspergillus. MÉTODOS. Se determinaron las concentraciones inhibitorias mínimas (CIM) para: 10, A. fumigatus; 9, A. flavus;8, A. niger; 5, A. tamarii; 5, A. versicolor; 4, A. terreus;3, A. glaucus; 3, A. ochraceus; 3, A. oryzae; 2, A. candidus;2, A. chevalieri; 2, A. rubrobrunneus; 2, A. sclerotiorum;2, A. sydowii; 2, A. unguis; 2, A. ustus; 1, A. clavatus;1, A. nidulans; 1, A. pseudofischeri, y 1, A. reptans,utilizando el método de microdilución Sensititre Yeast One®. RESULTADOS. El voriconazol fue más activo in vitro que la anfotericina B y el itraconazol, exhibiendo el 95,6% (65/68)de las cepas una CIM igual o inferior a 2 mg/l. Las especies A. flavus, A. versicolor, A. terreus, A. ochraceus,A. sclerotiorum, A. ustus y A. reptans presentaron una sensibilidad reducida frente a la anfotericina B(CIM &gt;= 2 mg/l); A. niger, A. versicolor, A. sclerotiorumy A. ustus mostraron cierta resistencia in vitro frente al itraconazol (CIM &gt;= 1 mg/l); A. sclerotiorum y A. ustus fueron poco sensibles frente al voriconazol (CIM &gt;= 2 mg/l).CONCLUSIONES. La sensibilidad de las especies de Aspergillus frente a itraconazol y voriconazol es buena, pero es significativa la sensibilidad reducida frente a la anfotericina B. Estos resultados sugieren que las pruebas de sensibilidad de Aspergillus a los antifúngicos están recomendadas para orientar un tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(1): 15-18, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad in vitro de anfotericina B, itraconazol y voriconazol frente a 20 especies de Aspergillus empleando el método de microdilución Sensititre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3574^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5017^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36060^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14956^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15176</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
