<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122928</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in cesarean sections between spontaneous and induced labour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The induction of labour (IOL) may be associated with complications for pregnant women. The aim was to assess the differences in the number of caesarean sections between spontaneous or induced labour. Methods: Historical groups from 841 women with induced labour and 2,534 women with an spontaneous onset of labour over a three- year period (from 2009 to 2011). They were carried out in &#147;Mancha Centro&#148; Hospital (Alcázar de San Juan). It was used a multivariate analysis through binary logistic regression to control confounding variables. Results: The prevalence of IOL was 22,9%. The most frequent indi- cations were: Premature Rupture of Membranes (22,7%), bad- controlled Diabetes (22,5%). It was reported a relation between induced labour and cesarean section risk due to parity (nulliparous OR= 2.68, IC 95%: 2.15- 3.34 and multiparous OR= 2.10, IC 95%: 1.72- 2.57). Postterm pregnancy (37,1%), pathological monitor (35.3%) and hypertensive diseases of preg- nancy (34%) reported the highest risks of cesarean section. The IOL was related to other factors: a long- time length first -stage of labour (OR= 6.00; IC 95%: 4.02- 8.95), use of epidural analgesia (OR= 3.10; IC 95%: 2.24- 4.29) and blood transfusion needs (OR= 3.33; IC 95%: 1.70- 9.67). Conclusion: Independently of parity, The IOL increases the risk to: have a longer duration first- stage, use epidural analgesia, need a blood transfusion and have a cesarean section. This relation is stronger when induction is due to postterm pregnancy, pathological monitor or hyperten- sive diseases. No relation was found among induced labour and second- duration, episiotomy, perineal tears, excessive blood loss or uterine rupture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Pedreño, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño Garnés, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melero Jiménez, María del Rocio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martínez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Alarcón, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La inducción del parto (IDP) puede estar asociada a mayores complicaciones para la mujer gestante. El objetivo de este trabajo fue determinar las diferencias en el número de cesáreas entre partos espontáneos y partos inducidos. Métodos: Cohortes históricas sobre un total de 841 inducciones y 2.534 partos espontáneos realizados entre 2009 y 2011 en el Hospital &#147;Mancha-Centro&#148; de Alcázar de San Juan. Se empleó análisis multivariante por medio de regresión logística binaria para control de la confusión. Resultados: La prevalencia de IDP fue del 22,9%, presentándose como indicaciones más frecuentes la rotura prematura de membranas (RPM) de más de 12 horas (22,7%) y diabetes mellitus mal controlada con un 22,5%. Se observó relación entre inducción y riesgo de cesárea tanto en mujeres nulíparas (OR= 2,68; Intervalo de confianza [IC] 95%: 2,15-3,34) como en multíparas (OR=2,10; [IC] 95%:1,72-2,57). La indicación con mayor riesgo de cesárea fue la gestación cronológicamente prolongada (GCP) (37,1%) seguida del registro cardiotográfico (RCTG) patológico (35,3%) y estados hipertensivos del embarazo (EHE) (4,0%). La IDP también se relacionó con la mayor duración de la dilatación (OR=6,00; IC 95%:4,02-8,95), empleo de epidural (OR=3,10;IC95%: 2,24-4,29) y necesidades de transfusión sanguínea (OR=3,33; IC %:1,70-5,67). Conclusiones: La IDP es un factor de riesgo para una mayor duración de la dilatación, empleo de analgesia epidural, necesidad de transfusión sanguínea y de cesárea tanto en mujeres nulíparas como en multíparas, especialmente en las indicaciones de gestación cronológicamente prolongada, registro cardiotocográfico patológico y estados hipertensivos del embarazo. No se encontró relación con la duración del período expulsivo, la práctica de episiotomía, desgarros, sangrado excesivo y rotura uterina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(3): 383-393, mayo-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en el número de cesáreas en los partos que comienzan espontáneamente y en los inducidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22235</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7923^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
