<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057298</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of mycophenolate mofetil in renal failure acute ischemia in rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) is a purine synthesis inhibitor commonly used as        immunosupresive agent in transplantation. Kidney grafts undergo more or less prolonged cold ischemia after harvesting which results in variable degrees of ischemia        reperfusion injury. To determine whether the inhibition of early events of cellular        infiltration may influence the severity of damage induced by ischemic acute        renal failure, 45 Sprague Dawley rats were given MMF at a dose of 20 mg/kg/day        (MMF-rats) by gavage 2 days before (pre-MMF group, n = 15) or after (post-MMF        group, n = 15) clamping the left renal artery for 40 minutes followed by rigt-sided        nephrectomy (control group, n = 15) received vehicle. Serum Creatinine (Screat)        was measured daily in all groups. On the 2nd post-ischemic day Screat was significantly        lower (p = 0.001) in pre-MMF group compared with post-MMF group and        control group (4 +/- 2 mg/dl post-MMF group vs 1.7 +/- 1.2 mg/dl pre-MMF        group, control group 5 +/-2, p &lt; 0.05). Kidney biopsies shown that the histologic        damage was 54 +/- 28% in post-MMF group vs 34 +/- 22% in pre-MMF group        and 61 +/- 25% in control group (pre-MMF vs post-MMF, p NS). On the 5th day        post-ischemic, MMF-rats showed more severe tubulointerstitial necrosis (pre-MMF        group: 17 +/- 20%, post-MMF group: 33 +/- 27%) than controls (4 +/- 5%). The        severity of ATN was significantly higher in post-MMF group compared with controls        (p = 0.01). Tubulointersticial T-lymphocyte (T CD 5) and monocyte (ED 1)        infiltration evaluated on the 2nd post-ischemic day was less intense in group I (T        CD5: 3 +/- 3, ED 1: 10 +/- 9, cel/mm2) compared to post-MMF group (T CD 5:        10 +/- 4, ED 1: 55 +/- 40) and to control group (T CD 5: 10 +/- 4, ED 1: 64        +/- 46). However, on the 5th post-ischemia day, ED 1 infiltration was significantly        higher in post-MMF group (24 +/- 18%) compared to pre-MMF group (5 +/- 5,        p NS) and also in pre-MMF group vs control group (31 +/- 33, p &lt; 0.05). Our        results suggest that MMF given before a renal ischemic insult may reduce the severity        of histologic damage resulting from ischemia reperfusion injury</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chávez-Velásquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiroz, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El micofenolato mofetil (MMF) es un inhibidor de la síntesis de las purinas comúnmente        usado como inmunosupresor. Previo al trasplante, el riñón es sometido        a períodos variables de isquemia, resultando en daño tisular por isquemia-reperfusión.        Para determinar si la inhibición de infiltración celular temprana están implicados        en la evolución de la IRA isquémica, esta se indujo en ratas Sprague Dawley        por oclusión del pedículo renal izquierdo durante 40 minutos con nefrectomía derecha,        se le administró MMF (20 mg/kg/día por gavage) 2 días previos a la isquemia        (MMF-pre, n = 15), post-isquemia (MMF-post, n = 15) o vehículo (control, n = 15).        La creatinina sérica (CS) fue medida diariamente en todos los grupos. Al segundo        día postisquemia la CS fue significativamente más baja en el grupo MMF-pre con        respecto al grupo MMF-post y control. El análisis histológico reveló que el daño histológico        fue (34 ± 22 en el MMF-pre vs 54 ± 28% MMF-post, p NS). Al quinto día        las ratas pre-tratadas y post-tratadas con MMF presentaron mayor necrosis tubulointersticial        que en el control (17 ± 20 vs 33 ± 27, en el control 4 ± 5%). La infiltración        de linfocitos T y monocitos (CD5 y ED 1 respectivamente) fue menor en        animales pre-tratados con MMF, mientras en el grupo post-tratado y control fue        mayor al segundo y quinto día. Así, en el intersticio a los 2 días, las células T CD5        fueron 10 ± 4 cel/ mm2 en el MMF-post vs 3 ± 3 en el MMF-pre (p &lt; 0,01), en el        control 10 ± 4. A los 5 días no hubo diferencias significativas entre los grupos. Las        células ED1 fueron 55 ± 40 cel/ mm2 en el MMF-post vs 10 ± 9 en e MMF-pre, en        el grupo control 64 ± 46 (p &lt; 0,05). A los 5 días se mantuvo menor infiltración en        el MMF-pre (5 ± 5 cel/ mm2 vs 24 ± 18 en el MMF-post, grupo control 31 ± 33).        Estos resultados sugieren que el tratamiento con MMF previo a la inducción de isquemia-        reperfusión puede mejorar el daño renal temprano (2 días)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;27(4): 448-458, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del micofenolato mofetil en la insuficiencia renal aguda isquémica en ratas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
