<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81356</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Penetrating aortic ulcer and saccular aneurysm of the abdominal aorta</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Saccular aortic aneurysms are an unusual and uncommon condition (1%). Although they can be secondary to an infection, they are usually associated with an emerging aortic disease: the penetrating aortic ulcer (PAU). Clinical case. A case is presented of a patient with a previous history of peripheral artery embolisms, due to a small fusiform aneurysm, who over the years was re-admitted due to unbearable and continuous pain. The angio-CT showed a thrombosed saccular aortic aneurysm associated with the previous fusiform. Due to suspicion of a contained ruptured aneurysm the patient was operated on by resection and an end to end silver impregnated Dacron endograft, with the contained rupture of the aortic wall being checked during the surgery. Conclusion. Saccular aortic aneurysms secondary to a PAU have an uncertain evolution. However, due to the potential risk of an aortic rupture, surgical treatment is recommended(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Morillo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros-Pomar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Morán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Martín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas aórticos saculares constituyen una entidad peculiar e infrecuente (1%). Aunque pueden ser secundarios a una infección, en la actualidad con frecuencia están asociados a una afección aórtica emergente: la úlcera penetrantre aórtica. Caso clínico. Se describe el caso de un paciente con historia previa de ateroembolismo periférico, por aneurisma fusiforme de pequeño tamaño que en el transcurso de los años reingresó por dolor abdominal incoercible y continuo; la angiotomografía computarizada mostró existencia de un aneurisma aórtico sacular trombosado, asociado al fusiforme previo. Ante la sospecha de un aneurisma roto contenido, el paciente fue intervenido mediante resección e injerto protésico terminoterminal de Dacron impregnado en plata, y se comprobó durante la cirugía la perforación contenida de la pared aórtica. Conclusión. Los aneurismas aórticos saculares secundarios a una úlcera penetrantre aórtica tienen una evolución incierta. Sin embargo, por el potencial riesgo de rotura aórtica, se recomienda su tratamiento quirúrgico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;61(6): 349-354, nov.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81356</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlcera penetrante aórtica y aneurisma sacular de la aorta abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31490^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14854^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
