<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050238</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of moxifloxacin in the emergency setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Moxifloxacin is a 4th-generation fluoroquinolone with recognised efficacy in airway infections in the emergency setting. At present, its wide spectrum that encompasses Gram-positive, Gram-negative and atypical bacteria, its greater activity against key pathogens, its almost nonexistent resistances and its excellent pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic features render it into the &#147;reference fluoroquinolone&#148;, with guaranteed success in the empirical and directed management in the emergency setting. The present review shall address the differences to other antimicrobials, mainly quinolones, in order to update the true role of moxifloxacin in airway infections. In vitro evidence and in vivo practical experience demonstrate its efficacy in achieving clinical cure and bacterial eradication, in increasing the period between COPD exacerbations, its &#147;lack of resistances&#148; and but slight ability to induce them, and its excellent dosage regime and tolerance, which have led a number of scientific societies to recommend moxifloxacin as the reference drug in the management of airway conditions, both in at-home and in admission therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Julián Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Moxifloxacino es una fluoroquinolona de 4ª generación con reconocida eficacia en la patología infecciosa de las vías respiratorias en urgencias. En la actualidad y gracias a su amplio espectro que incluye gérmenes grampositivos, gramnegativos y atípicos, su mayor actividad frente a patógenos clave, sus casi inexistentes resistencias y sus excelentes características farmacodinámicas y farmacocinéticas, la convierten en la fluoroquinolona de referencia, siendo un antimicrobiano con garantía de éxito en el tratamiento empírico y dirigido en los servicios de urgencias. Se analizan las diferencias con otros antimicrobianos, fundamentalmente quinolonas, para actualizar el verdadero papel de moxifloxacino en las infecciones respiratorias. La evidencia &#147;in vitro&#148; y la práctica &#147;in vivo&#148; nos demuestran su eficacia en la curación clínica, erradicación bacteriana, aumento del tiempo entre agudizaciones en la EPOC, &#147;inexistencia de resistencias&#148; y poca capacidad de originarlas, excelente posología y tolerancia, lo que determina que numerosas sociedades científicas recomienden moxifloxacino como referencia en el tratamiento de los procesos respiratorios; tanto domiciliario como en los casos de hospitalización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);18(6): 355-362, dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050238</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de moxifloxacino en Urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36060^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
