<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042429</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Traumatic Spigelian hernia. Elective extraperitoneal laparoscopic repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traumatic Spigelian hernia is rare. These hernias are usually treated in the same admission through open surgery. We present a case of Spigelian hernia in a high anatomical location following injury, with a cutaneous lesion and preperitoneal hematoma. Delayed parietal repair was performed through extraperitoneal laparoscopy. Elective laparoscopic repair in this case avoided surgery in an injured area, providing clear cosmetic advantages to the patient. We describe a modification to the classical approach to facilitate access to high-lying Spigelian defects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Girela-Baena, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralba-Martínez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillo-Soto, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral de la Calle, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Egea, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo-Albasini, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hernia traumática de Spiegel es infrecuente. Habitualmente suele tratarse durante el mismo ingreso mediante cirugía abierta. Presentamos un caso de hernia de Spiegel alta tras un traumatismo, con lesión cutánea y hematoma preperitoneal, cuya reparación parietal se realizó de forma diferida mediante laparoscopia extraperitoneal. La reparación laparoscópica electiva de este caso evitó la cirugía sobre el área traumatizada ofreciendo claras ventajas estéticas al paciente. Se describe una modificación del abordaje clásico para facilitar el acceso a los defectos altos del área de Spiegel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(1): 61-63, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hernia traumática de Spiegel: reparación laparoscópica extraperitoneal electiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
