<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045970</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Choice of ceramic for use in treatments with porcelain laminate veneers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Porcelain laminate veneers (PLVs) have been used for over two decades to treat esthetic and/or functional problems, particularly in the anterior sector (1-3). A range of dental ceramic materials are presently available on the market for these treatments, though with very different characteristics in terms of the composition, optic properties and manufacturing processes involved. As a result, selection of the material best suited for the management of each individual patient may prove complicated.    The present study proposes a simple system for selecting the most appropriate ceramic material, based on the two variables that most influence the esthetic outcome: the intrinsic characteristics of the substrate tooth, and the characteristics of the ceramic material in terms of resistance and optic properties</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Labaig Rueda, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fons Font, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá Ruíz, M. Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granell Ruíz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento mediante Frentes Laminados de Porcelana (FLP) se utiliza desde hace más de dos décadas para el tratamiento de problemas estéticos y/o funcionales, particularmente en el grupo anterior de las arcadas dentarias (1,2,3). La actual oferta en el mercado de cerámicas dentales aptas para este tipo de tratamiento, pero muy distintas en cuanto a composición, características ópticas y sistema de elaboración, hace complicada la selección del material más adecuado a cada paciente en particular.    Proponemos un sistema sencillo de elección de la cerámica teniendo en cuenta las dos variables que más influirán en el resultado estético final: de un lado las características propias del diente (sustrato en el que nos apoyamos), y de otro las características propias del material cerámico en cuanto a resistencia y propiedades ópticas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(3): E297-E302, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección de la ceramica a utilizar en tratamientos mediante frentes laminados de porcelana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3816^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3791^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
