<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109576</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Levodopa in the treatment of Parkinson&#146;s disease: myths and realties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years we have witnessed a growing tendency to opt for the use of dopamine agonists (DA) as treatment for Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD), with the aim of delaying as far as possible the development of fluctuations and dyskinesias. Yet, levodopa continues to be the most effective antiparkinson drug and is probably the one that improves the greatest number of symptoms of the disease. This article reports on the results of a comprehensive review of the literature dealing with the benefits and risks of levodopa treatment in patients with PD which was conducted by a group of expert neurologists and members of the Spanish Neurology Society&#146;s Movement Disorder Group. The main conclusion reached in this article is that levodopa continues to be the most effective treatment for PD. Although the risk and incidence of developing dyskinesias remains at a lower level in the group initially treated with DA, the number of patients who develop disabling dyskinesias is very low in all the studies and is similar for DA and for levodopa. Scores on the quality of life scales are also similar in the two groups, which casts some doubt on the impact that these motor complications have on the quality of life of patients with PD. In view of these findings, we should consider whether there is any real justification for depriving patients of the good control of their symptoms offered by levodopa owing to the fear of developing dyskinesias or mild motor fluctuations that are not really going to have any negative effect on their quality of life. There is also the  possibility of their developing severe side effects, which are more frequent with the use of DA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, Lydia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribacoba Montero, Renée</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castrillo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Esteban, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos García, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz, Pedro J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luquin, María Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Arillo, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Utrera, Marino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Herrera, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguera, Juan Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chacón, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Merino, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grandas, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juni, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ramos, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los últimos años hemos sido testigos de una utilización preferente de agonistas dopaminérgicos (AD) como tratamiento de la enfermedad de Parkinson (EP), con la intención de retrasar en lo posible el desarrollo de fluctuaciones y discinesias. Sin embargo, la levodopa continúa siendo el fármaco antiparkinsoniano más eficaz y, probablemente, el que mejora un mayor número de síntomas de la enfermedad. En este artículo se ha realizado una revisión exhaustiva  de la literatura por parte de un grupo de neurólogos expertos y miembros del Grupo de Trastornos del Movimiento de la Sociedad Española de Neurología sobre los beneficios y riesgos del tratamiento con levodopa en pacientes con EP. La principal conclusión de este artículo es que la levodopa continúa siendo el tratamiento más eficaz para la EP. Aunque el riesgo y la incidencia de desarrollar discinesias se mantiene en un nivel menor en el grupo tratado inicialmente con AD, el número de pacientes que desarrollan discinesias incapacitantes es muy bajo en todos los estudios y similar para los AD y la levodopa, y las escalas de calidad de vida son también similares en ambos grupos, lo que cuestiona el impacto que estas complicaciones motoras tienen sobre la calidad de vida de los pacientes con EP. A la vista de estos resultados, deberíamos plantearnos si está justificado privar a los pacientes del buen control de los síntomas que proporciona la levodopa  por el temor a que desarrollen discinesias o fluctuaciones motoras leves que no van a mermar su calidad de vida. A ello hay que añadir la posibilidad de que desarrollen efectos secundarios graves, que son más frecuentes con el uso de AD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(11): 669-688, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Levodopa en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Parkinson: mitos y realidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
