<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89273</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Harmonic hypogrowth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypogrowth is considered to be harmonic when normal proportions are maintained between the different body segments. During this paper, this concept and the difficulties that exist to establish normality or abnormality regarding these proportions and the multiple causes that may determine harmonic hypogrowth are analyzed. Based on the anamnesis data (prenatal or postnatal onset of hypogrowth) and examination (body harmony/disharmony), a proposal is made on how to make a diagnostic orientation and what how to rationally request complementary tests. Finally, the therapeutic options available in regards to short stature and what their specific treatment would be according to the etiopathogeny are analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo Román, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un hipocrecimiento es considerado armónico, cuando se mantienen las proporciones normales entre los distintos segmentos corporales. A lo largo del trabajo, se analiza dicho concepto y las dificultades que existen en establecer la normalidad o anormalidad entre dichas proporciones, así como las múltiples causas que pueden determinar un hipocrecimiento armónico. A partir de los datos de la anamnesis (inicio prenatal o postnatal del hipocrecimiento) y exploración (armonía/disarmonía dorporal), se propone cómo realizar  una orientación diagnóstica y qué pruebas complementarias solicitar de forma racional. Por último, se analizan las opciones terapéuticas disponibles ante un hipocrecimiento y cuál sería el tratamiento específico según su etiopatogenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(5): 370-385, sept.-oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipocrecimiento armónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33003^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1849</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
