<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81246</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a revision program on the control of type 2 diabetics followed at the primary care level. Diabetes First program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To analyze the evolution of the glycosylated hemoglobin and other parameters after performing a control program and follow-up by nurses to improve the control of the patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (Diabetes First). Patients and method: Intervention study in type 2 diabetes mellitus patients from Murcia. The inclusion criterium was to be a type 2 diabetes mellitus patient badly controlled on diabetes parameters (glycosylated haemoglobin ¡Ý 7%). We included 831 patients from 8 primary care centers. The program consisted of three visits (first one, after three months and after six months), where the patients received diabetic education. Results: The mean initial glycosylated haemoglobin value was 8.1% ¡À 1.3%, after 3 months it decreased to 7.5% ¡À 1.1%, and after 6 months from the first visit its value was 7.5% ¡À 2.6%. There was a statistically significant (p &lt; 0.001) difference between the initial glycosylated haemoglobin and the values three months later. There was not such a difference between the second and third visit. Total and low-density liporpotein cholesterol decreased significantly after 3 months (p &lt; 0.05). High-density lipoprotein cholesterol and triglycerides showed no difference. Systolic and diastolic blood pressure significantly decreased after three months (p &lt; 0.0001 and p &lt; 0.005). Conclusions: A simple nursing intervention program performed in primary care centers has a very positive impact on the control and treatment of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leal Hernández, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Oliver, Ana Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ruiz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lifante Pedrola, Zoila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pastor, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo: Analizar la evolución de la glucohemoglobina y otros parámetros tras aplicar un programa de revisión y seguimiento de enfermería (Diabetes First) para mejorar el control de sujetos con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Pacientes y método: Estudio de intervención, realizado con pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 de la Región de Murcia. El criterio de inclusión era ser diabético tipo 2 no controlado (glucohemoglobina ¡Ý 7%). Se obtuvo una muestra final de 831 pacientes pertenecientes a ocho centros de salud. El programa constaba de tres visitas (inicial, a los 3 y a los 6 meses) en las que se daba educación diabetológica. Resultados: La glucohemoglobina inicial fue una media del 8,1% ¡À 1,3%; a los 3 meses descendió al 7,5% ¡À 1,1%, y a los 6 meses de la visita inicial era del 7,5% ¡À 2,6%. La comparación de los valores de la visita inicial y a los 3 meses mostró significación estadística (p &lt; 0,001). Entre la segunda visita (3 meses) y la tercera (6 meses) no hubo diferencias significativas. Las cifras de colesterol total y colesterol de las lipoproteínas de baja densidad disminuyeron significativamente entre el inicio y los 3 meses (p &lt; 0,05). El colesterol de las lipoproteínas de alta densidad y los triglicéridos no mostraron diferencias. Respecto a la presión arterial sistólica y diastólica, disminuyeron significativamente las cifras entre el inicio y los 3 meses (p &lt; 0,0001 y p &lt; 0,005 respectivamente). Conclusiones: Un programa de intervención enfermera sencillo realizado en las consultas de atención primaria tiene un impacto muy favorable en el control y el tratamiento de los pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;57(1): 16-21, ene. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de revisión en el control de los diabéticos tipo 2 seguidos en atención primaria. Programa Diabetes First</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
