<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149459</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human resources and their mitigating unbalances</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper, the policy-sensitive imbalances in the health professional markets are discussed. In Spain, the current staffing levels are still the result of unforeseen demographic and socio-economic developments. In some specialties and areas, there are selective shortages which in all likelihood will become more serious in the coming years due to the objective causes analyzed in this text. We propose a gradual increase in the medical schools&#146;numerus clausus and in the number of resident's positions, the use of a variety of incentives to attract professionals to specific positions and, particularly, to increase the standing and quality of primary care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González López-Valcárcel, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barber-Pérez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se discuten los desequilibrios de los mercados de profesionales sanitarios que son sensibles a las políticas. En España, las dotaciones actuales siguen siendo el resultado de fenómenos demográficos y socioeconómicos no previstos. Hay déficits selectivos en algunas especialidades y zonas, que muy probablemente se agravarán en los próximos años, por las causas objetivas que se analizan en el texto. Se propone aumentar progresivamente el numerus clausus de medicina y la oferta de plazas MIR, y utilizar incentivos de distintos tipos e intensidades para atraer y mantener a los profesionales en determinados puestos, y particularmente para aumentar el prestigio y la calidad de la atención primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;20(supl.1): 103-109, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los recursos humanos y sus desequilibrios mitigables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8674</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33543^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37681</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5681^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
