<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121773</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of mesoflow in asthmatic patients with different bronchial hyperactivity intesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The so-called small airways account for 99,9% of the bronchial tree. Thus, their affectation in asthma patients is significant, which is why it is necessary to know their functional status by evaluating the forced mean flow (FMF25-75) of the spirometry curve. Material and methods. Evaluation of the spirometry curve prior to the methacholine test that was permormed to know the grade of bronchial hyperreactivity in a total of 82 children diagnosed of asthma. The children were distributed into three groups according to the response to this test: Group 1: PD20 with &lt; 1000 µg, Group 2: PD20 between 1000 and 2000 µg, Group 3: PD20 with &gt;2000 µg. Results. The percentage difference was estimated between the total expiratory flow (FEV1) and the mesoflow (FMF25-75) in each one of the groups. This was significant for groups 1 and 2 (p&lt;0,0001) and not significant for Group 4 (p&lt;0,07). This manifests the greater participation of the small airways in the asthmatic reaction and their relation with bronchial hyperreactivity. Conclusions. Knowing the real status of the airways during the course of asthma requires knowledge about the sate of the small airways by means of measuring periodically versus other usual procedures (e.g., peak flow), which only show the totality of the flow (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Alcolea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Las llamadas pequeñas vías aéreas representan el 99.9% del árbol bronquial, de ahí que sea notable su afectación en los pacientes asmáticos, por lo que es necesario conocer su estado funcional valorando el flujo medio forzado (FMF25-75) de la curva espirométrica. Material y métodos. Valoración de la curva espirométrica previa a la prueba de metacolina que se efectuó para conocer el grado de hiperreactividad bronquial en un total de 82 niños diagnosticados de asma, que se distribuyeron en tres grupos de acuerdo con la respuesta a esta prueba: Grupo 1: PD20 con &lt;1.000 µg, Grupo 2: PD20 entre 1.000 y 2.000 µg, Grupo 3: PD20 con &gt; 2.000 µg. Resultados. Se estimó la diferencia porcentual entre el total de flujo espiratorio (FEV1) y el mesoflujo (FMF25-75) en cada uno de los grupos, siendo significativo para los grupos 1 y 2 (p&lt;0,0001) y poco significativo para el Grupo 3: (p&lt;0,07), lo que evidencia la mayor participación de las pequeñas vías en la reacción asmática y su relación con la hiperreactividad bronquial. Conclusiones. La noción del estado real de las vías aéreas a lo largo de la evolución del asma, precisa conocer el estado de las pequeñas vías por la medición del mesoflujo, de ahí la necesidad de efectuar la espirometría periódicamente en contra de otros procedimientos usuales (pico flujo: peak flow), que sólo informan de la totalidad del flujo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;70(1): 28-32, ene.-feb. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del mesoflujo en pacientes asmáticos con distinta intensidad de hiperreactividad bronquial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30224^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
