<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138727</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carotid endarterectomy: description, results and clinic evolution in 100 consecutive symptomatic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The efficacy of endarterectomy in symptomatic carotid stenosis greater than 70% in secondary stroke prevention has been demonstrated although the benefit is dependent upon the perioperative morbidity and mortality risk. Despite the recommendation that the results of centres regularly practicing endarterectomies be analysed and reported, few studies have in fact been published. The aim of our study was to analyze the incidence of surgical complications from carotid endarterectomy at our hospital and to describe the stroke profile of the operated patients. Material and methods. 100 consecutive patients submitted to carotid endarterectomy between 2002 and 2006 were included. We recorded stroke risk factors, clinical presentation, ultrasonography findings including transcranial and carotid eco-Doppler, neuroimaging, intra and perioperative complications including mortality- stroke rate, and clinical outcome at three months. We compare our results with the NASCET, ECST and Spanish published series. Results. Males predominated (74 % vs 26 %). The mean age was 70±8.5 years with 36 % of patients older than 75 years. Arterial hypertension was the most common vascular risk factor (74%), 14% had a critical contralateral carotid stenosis or occlusion. Stroke was the most frequent clinical presentation (67 %). The most commonly detected intraoperatory and postoperatory complication was subclinical haemodynamic changes (67% and 45% respectively). Cranial nerve lesions were the most usual local complication. Four patients suffered stroke recurrence, leading to death in one. A further patient died due to a reperfusion syndrome. The rate of stroke-mortality at three months was 5%. Conclusions. Morbidity and mortality related to carotid endarterectomy for symptomatic stenosis greater than 70 % was within guideline ranges. Surgical risk at every centre should be periodically evaluated in order to guarantee that acceptable standards are maintained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La endarterectomía carotídea (EC) ha demostrado ser eficaz en la prevención secundaria de ictus isquémico en pacientes con estenosis sintomática de arteria carótida interna (ACI) mayor del 70%. Este beneficio está condicionado por la morbimortalidad perioperatoria del centro. Pese a la recomendación de analizar y comunicar los resultados de la EC en centros que la realizan de forma habitual, son muy escasas las publicaciones al respecto. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue analizar el perfil de pacientes intervenidos y riesgo quirúrgico asociado a la EC en nuestro hospital. Material y métodos. Se incluyeron 100 pacientes consecutivos intervenidos entre 2002 y 2006. Se recogieron datos sobre antecedentes patológicos, clínica de inicio, hallazgos ultrasonográficos (incluido Doppler transcraneal y carotídeo), neuroimagen, complicaciones intra y postoperatorias y evolución clínica a los 3 meses. Se compararon con resultados de los estudios previos, incluidos los ensayos clínicos NASCET, ECST y series publicadas en nuestro país. Resultados. En nuestra serie destaca el elevado perfil de riesgo de los pacientes. Hubo predominio masculino (74% frente a 26 %), con una edad media de 70 (8,5) años, un 36% de pacientes mayores de 75 años. En un 42% la estenosis de ACI fue &gt;90% y en un 14% existía una estenosis crítica u oclusión de ACI contralateral. La clínica de presentación más frecuente fue el infarto cerebral establecido (67%). La complicación intra y postoperatoria más frecuente fue la alteración hemodinámica subclínica (67 y 45%, respectivamente). Un 4% de los pacientes presentaron recidiva del ictus y uno un síndrome de reperfusión. Dos pacientes fallecieron. La tasa de ictus-mortalidad a 3 meses se situó en el 5%. Conclusión. Nuestros pacientes presentan un perfil de alto riesgo con una morbimortalidad asociada a la EC dentro de los rangos de seguridad recomendados. Pese a las recomendaciones vigentes, son escasas las auditorías internas evaluando el riesgo quirúrgico en cada centro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(6): 391-398, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endarterectomía carotídea: descripción, resultados y evolución clínica en 100 pacientes sintomáticos consecutivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30132^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30211^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30132^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
