<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048317</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The diabetes mellitus metabolic check-up objectives met in the rural area of Ourense, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To evaluate the degree to which the metaboliccheck-up objectives among Type II diabetes patients were met inrural primary care by comparing them to the values recommendedby the American Diabetes Association (ADA) and the Diabetes inPrimary Care Study Group (GEDAPS).Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study. A sample size wascalculated based on the glycosolated hemoglobin (HbA1c) test in119 individuals. A total of 253 patients with Type II diabetes followedup for at least two years at their healthcare facility took part. Thepatients in question were selected at random from among 17 medicallists at 11 rural healthcare facilities in the province of Ourense(Spain). Demographic variables, cardiovascular risk factors, pharmacologicaltreatment, self-analyses, eye fundus, tactile sensitivity,HbA1c, lipid profile, blood pressure and body mass index data weretaken from the patients´ clinical records.Results: A total of 44.3% of those in the sample had undergonean HbA1c test within the immediately prior six-month period, showinga value of under seven percent (7%). A total of 21.2% had ablood pressure of under 130/80, and 19.8% a LDL cholesterol levelof under 100 mg/dl. A total of 40.7% of those patients with a LDLcholesterol level over 100 were not undergoing any hypolipemianttreatment. A total of 20.4% of the patients showing high blood pressurereadings were not undergoing any blood pressure lowering treatment.On the basis of these three factors, a total of 2.5% met thecheck-up objectives. Thirty-six percent (36%) were antiaggregatedwith AAS.Conclusions: A major deficit is revealed both in the frequencyof the check-ups conducted by the healthcare professionals as well asthe number of interventions performed for achieving the proposedobjectives, showing results far below what is recommended in theclinical practice guidelines</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palmeiro Fernández, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Grávalos, Gabriel J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arandia García, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Górriz, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portuburu Izaguirre, M. Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Fernández, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Valorar el cumplimiento de los objetivos de controlmetabólico en el paciente diabético tipo 2 en la atención primariade ámbito rural, comparándolo con los valores recomendados porla American Diabetes Association (ADA) y el Grupo de estudio de ladiabetes en atención primaria de salud (GEDAPS).Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Se calculó un tamañomuestral, basándose en la determinación de la hemoglobina glicosilada(HbA1c), de 119 individuos. Participaron 253 personas diabéticastipo 2 con al menos 2 años de seguimiento en su centro de salud.Fueron seleccionados de forma aleatoria de 17 cupos médicos de 11centros de salud rurales de la provincia de Ourense. A partir de la historiaclínica se recogieron variables demográficas, factores de riesgocardiovascular, tratamiento farmacológico, realización de autoanálisis,fondo de ojo, sensibilidad táctil, HbA1c, perfil lipídico, presiónarterial e índice de masa corporal.Resultados: En el 44,3% de las personas de la muestra se habíadeterminado HbA1c en los últimos 6 meses y presentaba un valorinferior a 7%. Un 21,2% tenía la presión arterial por debajo de130/80, y el 19,8% un colesterol LDL menor de 100 mg/dl. Entre lospacientes con colesterol LDL mayor de 100 el 40,7% no recibía tratamientohipolipemiante. El 20,4% de los que tenían cifras elevadasde presión arterial no recibía tratamiento hipotensor. Considerandoestos tres factores el 2,5% alcanzaba los 3 objetivos de control. Un36% realizaba tratamiento antiagregante con ácido acetil salicilico.Conclusiones: Se constata un importante déficit tanto en la frecuenciade los controles realizados por los profesionales sanitarioscomo en el número de intervenciones realizadas para conseguir losobjetivos propuestos, con resultados muy inferiores a lo recomendadoen las guías de práctica clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(1): 67-75, ene.-feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de los objetivos de control metabólico en diabetes mellitus en el medio rural de Ourense</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
