<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159929</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience of a reflection space in a palliative care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the experience, after a year of running monthly sessions of reflection and learning in the palliative care unit of a geriatric hospital in Barcelona. Material and methods: Through a qualitative-phenomenological methodological approach, three individual interviews and a focus group involving 11 professionals from the unit were assessed. Interviews and focus group session was audio recorded. Data were analyzed with the support of Atlas.ti software version 5.0. A triangulation was performed on the techniques used, as well as on the interviews and focus group. Results: Through the process of analysis of the contributions collected in this study, two qualitative vectors emerged: positive aspects and unfavourable aspects of the experience. The following categories were positive aspects: necessary and essential space; useful for sharing experiences, and helps to express emotions. As for the unfavourable aspects, the resulting categories were: lack of maturity of group and poor working methodology. Conclusions: The professional of the palliative care units interviewed and participated in the focus group considered the space for reflection as an achievement that must be maintained in the operation of the unit, but new methodology should be incorporated in order to increase the maturity of the team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Inzitari, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera, Sabrina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clèries, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la experiencia, después de un año de funcionamiento, de las sesiones mensuales de reflexión y aprendizaje realizadas en la unidad de cuidados paliativos de un hospital sociosanitario de Barcelona. Material y métodos: Mediante un enfoque metodológico cualitativo-fenomenológico se realizaron tres entrevistas individuales y un grupo focal en el que participaron 11 profesionales de la unidad. Se registraron magnetofónicamente las entrevistas y la sesión del grupo focal. Los datos se analizaron con el apoyo del programa Atlas.ti versión 5.0. Posteriormente se procedió a la triangulación de las técnicas empleadas, entrevistas y grupo focal. Resultados: A través del proceso de análisis de las aportaciones recogidas en la presente investigación emergieron dos vectores cualitativos: aspectos favorables y desfavorables de la experiencia. Las categorías correspondientes a los aspectos favorables fueron: espacio necesario e imprescindible; útil para compartir experiencias y ayuda a expresar emociones. En cuanto a los aspectos desfavorables, las categorías resultantes fueron: falta de madurez del grupo y metodología de trabajo inadecuada. Conclusiones: Los profesionales de la unidad de cuidados paliativos que fueron entrevistados y participaron en el grupo focal consideran el espacio de reflexión como un logro que se debe mantener en el funcionamiento de la unidad aunque deben incorporarse cambios más dirigidos a incrementar la madurez del equipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;24(1): 26-30, ene.-mar. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159929</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de un espacio de reflexión en una unidad de cuidados paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29873</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
