<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056476</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of malnutrition in intestinal anastomosis collagenization: an analysis of procollagen (PINP) andcarboxyterminal telopeptide (ICTP) by radioimmunoassay</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: some clinical, anatomo-pathological, and technical    factors influence the correct healing of intestinal suture following    an intestinal resection. One of the most influential factors    is patient nutritional status.    Objectives: to evaluate the influence of malnutrition on the    viability of primary intestinal anastomosis by the analysis of collagen    I deposition.    Methods: 40 Wistar rats, radioimmunoassay material. We    used 2 groups of rats, 20 animals in each group: a control group    (A) and a &#147;malnutrition&#148; group (B).    Results: there was a decrease in PINP (procollagen) deposition    in the colon of group B rats as compared to the colon of group A    (0.3620 and 0.4340 &amp;#956;g/g respectively) (p = 0.032). There is an increase    in ICTP (carboxyterminal telopeptide) in the colon of group B    (0.9545 as against 0.8460 &amp;#956;g/g in group A) (p = 0.875). In anastomoses    of group B there was a decrease in PINP synthesis as compared    to group A (0.376 and 0.468 mg/g respectively, p = 0.002).    As regards ICTP, there was an increase in group B (p = 0.330). In    relation to the control group no differences were observed in ICTP    increases in group B (p = 1).    Conclusions: colonic anastomosis increases the levels of    PINP and ICTP in healed tissue (p = 0.000); malnutrition reduces    collagenization in anastomoses (p = 0.000)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Socas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pareja, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Moreno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Artacho, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Grau, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daza, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álamo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: diversos factores influyen en la cicatrización    correcta de las suturas intestinales tras la práctica de una resección    intestinal. Uno de los factores más implicados es el estado    nutricional del paciente.    Objetivos: evaluar la influencia de la desnutrición inducida sobre    la viabilidad de una anastomosis intestinal primaria mediante    el análisis del procolágeno (PINP) como marcador de la síntesis de    colágeno I, y del telopéptido carboxiterminal del colágeno I (ICTP)    como marcador de la destrucción del mismo.    Métodos: 40 ratas Wistar y material de radioinmunoensayo.    Métodos: diseñamos 2 grupos de ratas, 20 animales por cada grupo:    grupo control (A) y grupo &#147;desnutrición&#148; (B). Se analiza PINP    e ICTP mediante RIA sobre tejido colónico homogeneizado, preanastomótico    y anastomótico.    Resultados: existen unos niveles menores de PINP en el colon    de las ratas del grupo B comparado con el colon del grupo A    (0,3620 y 0,4340 &amp;#956;g/g respectivamente) (p = 0,032). Hay un    mayor nivel de ICTP analizado en el colon del grupo B (0,9545    en contraposición a 0,8460 &amp;#956;g/g en el grupo A) (p = 0,875). En    las anastomosis del grupo B existe una menor síntesis de PINP en    comparación con el grupo A (0,376 y 0,468 &amp;#956;g/g respectivamente,    p = 0,002).    Conclusiones: la anastomosis colónica incrementa los niveles    de PINP e ICTP en el tejido cicatricial (p = 0,000); la malnutrición    reduce la colagenización de las anastomosis (p = 0,000)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(2): 76-83, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la desnutrición sobre la colagenización de anastomosis intestinales: análisis de procolágeno y telopéptido carboxiterminal mediante radioinmunoanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29521^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2309^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30578^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
