<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72913</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">To annul or to shorten the first steps of the WHO Analgesic Leader</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveThis study was designed to evaluate the possibility of eithershorten or annul the first and second level of the WHOanalgesicladder; in order to achieve pain control in patientessuffering from OA within the shortest period of time.Material and Methods- First group pain was not adequately controlled by nonopioidanalgesic and afterwards treated with TD-Fentanyl.- The second group was treated with TDF after not beingadequately controlled by weak opoids, with a dose thatranged between 1 mg up to 3 mg/kg.- The third group was treated with TDF after a dose of weakopioids (tramadol) which ranged between 3,5 mg upto 6 mg/kg.ResultsResults related to pain control, adverse effects and therapydiscontinuing, were statistically and clinically similaramong the three groups.ConclusionIt is possible to shorten the period of time necessary toachieve pain control in patients who suffer from chronic painrelated to OA by shorting or avoiding the second or first levelof the WHO-anlgesic ladder(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoConsideramos la posibilidad de anular o acortar el segundopeldaño de la escalera analgésica de la OMS, con el propósitode controlar el dolor crónico de nuestros pacientes enel menor tiempo posible.Material y métodosPresentamos un estudio sobre 74 pacientes, divididos entres grupos, para valorar si existen diferencias entre ellos. Unprimer grupo pasó a tratarse con fentanilo TTS sin tratamientoprevio con opioides débiles, los otros dos se trataronanteriormente con tramadol a dosis distintas. Un grupo a dosisprevias de tramadol comprendidas entre 1 y 3 mg/Kg yotro grupo con dosis comprendidas entre 3.5 y 6 mg/Kg.ResultadosLos resultados han sido similares, clínica y estadísticamente,en cuanto a efectos secundarios, control del dolor yabandonos. ConclusionesConcluimos que es posible acortar el tiempo necesario paracontrolar el dolor crónico en pacientes con patologías severasy que se presuponga necesitarán la prescripción deopioides mayores y que se puede anular el primer escalón dela OMS y también acortar el segundo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(1): 13-20, ene.-feb. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anular o acortar los primeros peldaños de la Escalera Analgésica de la OMS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14538^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
