<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94464</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of post-catheterization phlebitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the prevalence of phlebitis associated to peripherally inserted catheters at the Virgen del Rocío de Sevilla University Hospitals and to analyse associated risk factors, as well as differences in prevalence at different times of the year.Method: descriptive study with three cross-sections in patients who are carriers of peripherally inserted catheters admitted to hospitalization units in which the catheter is in place over 48 hours. Study variables: type of catheter; type of infusion; Maddox Scale to determine phlebitis; patientage and sex. Results: 470 patients were studied. According to the Maddox scale, a phlebitis prevalence of 8,5% (first cross section), 17,1% (second cross section)and 11% (third cross section) was found. The risk of phlebitis onset was greater if there was intermittent infusion (OR = 3,236), if there was no three-step key (OR = 3,647), if there was a connection via a bioconnector(OR = 2,98) or if the patient was a woman (OR = 2,421).Conclusions: the prevalence of catheter-related phlebitis in this study mirrors that of other published data. The results of the study have enabledus to discover that the applied processes are found within desirable variability margins, detecting areas of improvement which should be worked on (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco Sánchez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paneque Sánchez Toscazo, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estepa Osuna, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión Camacho, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro García, Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso Vázquez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limpo de la Iglesia, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peinado Barraso, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rodríguez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez González, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la prevalencia de flebitis asociada a catéteres de inserción periférica en los centros de Hospitales Universitarios (HU) Virgendel Rocío de Sevilla y analizar los factores de riesgo asociados, así como las diferencias en la prevalencia en función de distintos momentos del año. Método: estudio descriptivo con tres cortes transversales en pacientes portadores de catéteres de inserción periférica ingresados en unidades de hospitalización en los que la permanencia del catéter es superior a 48 horas.Variables de estudio: tipo de catéter; tipo de conexiones; localización del catéter; tipo de infusión; Escala de Maddox para determinar la flebitis;edad y sexo del paciente.Resultados: se estudiaron 470 pacientes. Según la escala de Maddox, se encontró una prevalencia de flebitis del 8,5% (primer corte), del 17,1%(segundo corte) y del 11% (tercer corte). El riego de aparición de flebitisera mayor si había infusión intermitente (OR = 3,236), si no había llave de tres pasos (OR = 3,647), si existía conexión por bioconector(OR = 2,98) y si se era mujer (OR = 2,421).Conclusiones: la prevalencia de flebitis asociadas a catéter en los distintos cortes del presente estudio está consonancia con otros publicados.Los resultados del estudio han permitido conocer que los procesos aplicados se encuentran dentro de los márgenes de variabilidad deseables,detectando áreas de mejora sobre las que se deberá incidir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(8): 28-32, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94464</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de flebitis postcateterización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
