<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144633</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">First Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) cases detected in hospitalised patients in a tertiary care university hospital in Spain, October 2014</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several outbreaks of Enterovirus 68 (EV-D68) have recently been reported in the USA and Canada, causing substantial hospitalisation of children with severe respiratory disease. The acute flaccid paralysis detected in the USA and Canada among children with EV-D68 infection has raised concerns about the aetiological role of this EV serotype in severe neurological disease. The circulation of EV-D68 in the general European population seems to be low, but European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) recommends being vigilant to new cases, particularly in severely ill hospitalised patients. In October 2014, enteroviruses were detected in respiratory samples collected from five hospitalised patients, children and adults. Phylogenetic analysis of partial VP1 sequences confirmed that the detected enteroviruses belonged to the D68 serotype, which were also similar to strains reported in USA (2014). However, all five patients developed respiratory symptoms, but only one required ICU admission. None of the patients described had symptoms of neurological disease. Other considerations related to the detection methods used for the diagnosis of respiratory enteroviruses are also discussed. In conclusion, additional evidence has been provided that supports the role of EV-D68 in respiratory infections in hospitalised patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esperalba, Juliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco Fuentes, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campins, Magda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin, Maria del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codina, Maria Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomas Pumarola, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andres Anton, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimferrer, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En EEUU y Canadá, desde el pasado verano, se han descrito varios brotes causados por EV-D68 afectando a pacientes, principalmente niños, con enfermedad respiratoria grave. En algunos de estos casos la infección por EV-D68 se ha asociado a enfermedad neurológica grave. Aunque en población europea la circulación de este serotipo parece ser baja, el ECDC recuerda la necesidad de reforzar la vigilancia, especialmente en pacientes hospitalizados. En octubre de 2014, en las muestras respiratorias de 5 pacientes ingresados en el Hospital Universitario Vall d&#146;Hebron de Barcelona, se pudieron detectar enterovirus. Estos fueron caracterizados como EV-D68 mediante análisis filogenético de las secuencias parciales codificantes para la proteína viral VP1. Estas secuencias eran además similares a las de las cepas aisladas en los últimos meses en EEUU. Estos 5 pacientes presentaron síntomas respiratorios, pero sólo uno requirió ingreso en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos. Sin embargo, ninguno de los pacientes presentó síntomas de enfermedad neurológica. En este trabajo se comentan también consideraciones relacionadas con los métodos de diagnóstico para enterovirus, especialmente para este serotipo. En conclusión, en este trabajo se confirma el posible papel etiológico del EV-D68 en la infección respiratoria del paciente ingresado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;33(9): 585-589, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primeras detecciones de Enterovirus D68 (EV-D68) en población hospitalizada en España, Octubre 2014</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35630^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
