<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047409</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of Magnetic Resonance in assessing prognosis after moderate and severe head injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cranial MR is more sensitive in defining the anatomicsubstrate of traumatic brain injury than cranial CT, which has been, for themoment, the most extended test in the evaluation of these patients. Thereforecranial MR could be a determinant test in order to establish the prognosis ofpatients after head injury.Objective: To establish the role of MR findings in determining prognosisof patients who have suffered moderate or severe head injury.Materials and methods: 98 patients suffering moderate or severe headinjury to whom a MR had been performed in the first 30 days after traumawere included. All clinical variables related to prognosis were registered, aswell as the data from the initial CT following Marshall et al. classification.The MR was blindly evaluated by two neuroradiologists that were not awareof the initial CT results or the clinical situation of the patient. All lesions wereregistered as well as the classification following Gentry et al. and Fishing etal. scales. Outcome was determined six months after head injury by meansof the extended version of the Glasgow outcome scale administered by astructured interview and applying the Barthel index and the Mini-MentalState examination described by Folstein. The relation between the differentfactors recorded during admission and outcome six months after head injurymeasured by different scales was evaluated by means of uni and multivariateanalysis (logistic regression). The prognostic capacity of the different factorsrelated to outcome was compared by the analysis of ROC curves and the areaunder the curve for each factor.Results:The information obtained by cranial MR is most useful indetermining prognosis after moderate and severe head injury, and itscontribution to the prognostic models is superior to the information offeredby cranial CT. There exists a clear relation between the depth of the traumaticlesions shown in MR, and their classification by the two proposed scales, andthe outcome of patients suffering traumatic brain injury determined sixmonths after the injury by different scales. The classification of MR findingsby the scale of Gentry/Adams establishes groups of patients with differentoutcome. The deeper the lesion the worse the prognosis and patients withbrainstem lesions have poor outcome. However, not all patients withbrainstem lesions have a poor outcome. Motor GCS and lesion localizationin MR are the most important predictors of outcome in patients withmoderate and severe head injury</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lagares, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballenilla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrese, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alday, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobato, R. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La RM craneal ha demostrado ser una prueba más sensible ala hora de definir anatómicamente el daño cerebral traumático que la TC craneal,prueba que hasta el momento ha sido la más extendida en la evaluaciónde estos enfermos. Por ello, la RM craneal podría ser una prueba determinantea la hora de establecer el pronóstico tras TCE.Objetivos: Establecer la capacidad pronóstica de los hallazgos en RM enenfermos que han sufrido un TCE grave o moderado.Material y métodos: Se incluyen en el estudio 98 enfermos con TCEmoderado y grave a los que se ha realizado RM craneal dentro de los primeros30 días tras el trauma craneal. Se recogieron todas las variables clínicaspotencialmente relacionadas con el pronóstico de los enfermos, así como losdatos del TC inicial según la clasificación de Marshall y cols. La RM fue evaluadade manera ciega por dos neurorradiólogos que ignoraban el resultado de la TCinicial y la situación clínica inicial del paciente. Se recogieron todas las lesionesque presentaban así como su clasificación según Gentry y cols. y Firshing y cols.La evolución fue determinada a los seis meses del TCE mediante la aplicación dela escala de evolución de Glasgow extendida mediante cuestionario normalizadoy aplicando el índice de Barthel y el Mini-Mental State Examination de Folstein.Se estudiaron las relaciones entre los diferentes variables recogidas durante elingreso y la evolución a los seis meses medida mediante las diferentes escalasmediante la aplicación de análisis uni y multivariable (regresión logística). Secomparó asimismo la capacidad pronóstica de los diferentes factoresrelacionados con el pronóstico mediante el análisis de las curvas ROC y el áreadebajo de la curva para cada factor.Resultados: La información obtenida a través de la RM es útil en elestablecimiento del pronóstico de los enfermos con TCE moderado y grave,siendo mayor su contribución en los modelos pronósticos que la informacióndada por la TC. Existe una clara relación entre la profundidad de las lesionestraumáticas demostradas con RM, y su clasificación según las dos escalaspropuestas, y el pronóstico de los enfermos con TCE moderado y grave a los seismeses tras el traumatismo medido mediante diferentes escalas. La clasificaciónde los hallazgos en RM según el modelo de Gentry/Adams establece grupos deenfermos con diferente pronóstico. A mayor profundidad de la lesión peorpronóstico, siendo peor el pronóstico de los enfermos con lesiones en troncocerebral. Sin embargo, no todos los enfermos con lesiones en tronco tienen malaevolución. El GCS motor y la localización de las lesiones son los predictores másimportantes de la evolución de los enfermos con TCE moderado y grave</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;3(1): 41-54, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de la RM craneal en el traumatismo craneoencefálico moderado y grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
