<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162433</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between vitamin D levels and cardiovascular risk factors in obese children and adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aim: Childhood obesity is associated with an increased risk of chronic disease. We aimed to determine the association between vitamin D deficiency and cardiovascular risks in obese children. Method: The studied children were selected from obese children who were followed up at obesity clinic, aged 6-17 years. Basic demographic information and laboratory data were collected retrospectively from hospital records. Results: A total of 310 students (178 [57.4%] girls) were evaluated for 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25[OH] D) levels in late winter/spring. The prevalence rates of vitamin D deficiency, insufficiency, and sufficiency were 62.3%, 34.5%, and 3.2%, respectively. Insulin resistance was observed in 146 (47.1%) children; the frequencies of dyslipidemia and hypertension were 31% and 19.4%, respectively. The mean atherogenic dyslipidemia ratio was higher in the defi cient group (p = 0.049). Inverse correlations of 25(OH) D levels were observed with homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance values (r = -0.146, p = 0.010). The mean values of 25(OH) D (ng/mL) were lower in girls (12.15 ± 6.60) than in boys (16.48 ± 8.69) (p &lt; 0.05) and in children with hypertension (11.92 ± 5.48) than in those without (14.50 ± 8.24) (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: Vitamin D deficiency is observed more frequently than expected in obese children and adolescents. Our findings indicate that low 25(OH) D levels are associated with insulin resistance. Vitamin D deficiency could contribute to the morbidities associated with childhood obesity, such as insulin resistance or diabetes mellitus, increased cardiovascular/cardiometabolic risks, atherogenic dyslipidemia, and hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yilmaz, Resul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sonmezgoz, Ergun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozer, Samet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Takçi, &amp;#350;ahin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kasap, Tuba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demir, Osman</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gul, Ali</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: la obesidad infantil se asocia a un riesgo aumentado de enfermedades crónicas. El objetivo de este estudio es determinar la relación entre la deficiencia en vitamina D y el riesgo cardiovascular en niños obesos. Método: se seleccionaron niños tratados en la clínica de obesidad, con edades entre 6 y 17 años. Los datos de laboratorio y la información demográfica básica se recogieron de forma retrospectiva a partir de las historias clínicas. Resultados: se evaluaron 310 estudiantes (178, 57,4% mujeres) midiendo los niveles de vitamina D a finales de invierno y en primavera. La prevalencia de deficiencia en vitamina D, insuficiencia y suficiencia fueron 62,3%, 34,5% y 3,2% respectivamente. Se encontró resistencia insulínica en 146 niños (47,1%); mientras que la frecuencia de dislipemia e hipertensión fue de 31% y 19,4%, respectivamente. La razón de aterogenicidad debida a dislipemia fue mayor en el grupo deficiente (p = 0,049). Se encontró una correlación inversa entre los niveles de 25-OH-D y los valores de HOMA (r = -0,146; p = 0,01). Los valores medios de vitamina D (ng/Ml) fueron inferiores en niñas (12,15 ± 6,60) que en niños (16,48 ± 8,69) (p &lt; 0,05) y en niños con hipertensión (11,92 ± 5,48 vs. 14,50 ± 8,24 en normotensos) (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: se encontró una prevalencia de deficiencia en vitamina D en niños y adolescentes obesos superior a lo esperado. Nuestros hallazgos indican que los niveles bajos de vitamina D se asocian con resistencia insulínica. La deficiencia en vitamina D podría contribuir a las morbilidades que se asocian a la obesidad infantil, como la resistencia insulínica o la diabetes mellitus, el aumento del riesgo cardiovascular, la dislipemia y la hipertensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(2): 323-329, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162433</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre los niveles de vitamina D y factores de riesgo cardiovascular en niños y adolescentes obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
