<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62896</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strategies to improve treatment with efalizumab</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is essential to improve the clinical results of efalizumab and to assure that it is used under safety criteria in order to obtain a systemic management of the treatment. Prior to proposing and prescribing the treatment, the dermatologist should make sure that the patient fulfills pills the requirements to be able to initiate it and that, on the other hand, there is no serious contraindication that may affect its short-to-long term safety. During the course of the treatment, some follow-up guidelines should be established that will make it possible to compare the evolution of the patient with the general perspectives of efalizumab as well as to monitor and manage the most common adverse effects associated to its use. Finally, it would be convenient to become familiar with the natural course of the disease once the treatment is discontinued in those cases in which this action is decided or should be carried out (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de optimizar los resultados clínicos de efalizumab y garantizar su empleo bajo criterios de seguridad resulta fundamental adquirir una cierta sistemática en su manejo. De forma previa a proponer y prescribir el tratamiento, el dermatólogo deberá cerciorarse de que el paciente cumple los requisitos para poder iniciarlo y de que, por otro lado, no presenta ninguna contraindicación grave que pueda comprometer su seguridad a corto o largo plazo. Durante el curso del tratamiento deberán establecerse unas pautas de seguimiento que permitan tanto contrastarla evolución del paciente con respecto a las perspectivas generales de efalizumab como monitorizar y manejarlos efectos adversos más habituales asociados a su empleo. Finalmente, será adecuado familiarizarse con la evolución natural de la enfermedad una vez suspendido el tratamiento en aquellos casos en los que esta actuación decida o deba tomarse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(supl.1): 37-50, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias para optimizar el tratamiento con efalizumab</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3544^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7295^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7295^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
