<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10804</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fixed drug eruption with acetaminophen. Clinical case with bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fixed drug eruption is a toxicodermia characterized by the appearance of a well-circumscribed reddish or violet, circular or oval, edematous skin lesion which can present recurrences after taking the causal agent, usually a drug. It can be produced by a wide variety of drugs, including acetaminophen. Acetaminophen is a drug with analgesic and antipyretic properties widely known and used for its wide range of safety and high bio-availability. However, different types and intensity of adverse skin reactions have been reported following administration, mainly urticaria and angioedema, and less frequently erythema multiforme, toxic epidermal necrolysis, fixed exanthema and Henoch-Schönlein purpura. We present the case of a role model user with fixed drug exanthema after acetaminophen consumption. A bibliographic review has been made on the various clinical findings and the differential diagnosis between different toxicodermias, as well as the management and approach of the lesions based on the TIME concept (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rueda López, Justo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Palmero, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruces Baca, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa García, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Moreno,  Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El exantema fijo medicamentoso es una toxicodermia caracterizada por la aparición de una lesión cutánea en forma de mácula de color rojizo o violáceo, redonda u oval, edematosa, bien delimitada, y que presenta recurrencias tras la administración del agente causal, generalmente un fármaco. Puede ser producido por una gran variedad de fármacos, entre ellos el paracetamol. El paracetamol es un medicamento con propiedades analgésicas y antipiréticas ampliamente conocido y utilizado por su amplio margen de seguridad y elevada biodisponibilidad. Sin embargo, se han descrito reacciones cutáneas adversas de diferentes tipos e intensidad tras su administración, fundamentalmente urticaria y angioedema, y con menor frecuencia eritema multiforme, necrólisis epidérmica tóxica, exantema fijo y púrpura de Henoch-Schönlein. Se presenta el caso de un usuario tipo con exantema fijo medicamentoso relacionado con el consumo de paracetamol. Se ha realizado una revisión bibliográfica sobre los diversos hallazgos clínicos y el diagnóstico diferencial entre las diferentes toxicodermias, así como el manejo y abordaje de las lesiones basado en el concepto TIME (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(3): 158-162, sept. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10804</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exantema fijo medicamentoso por paracetamol. Caso clínico con revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
