<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123136</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of specific biological markers in the global survival rate and response to treatment of breast cancer with pleural metastasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: 1. To study what type of biological markers have prognostic value in the global survival rate and response to treatment of breast cancer, regarding discovery of pleural metastases. 2. To examine the influence of the application of intrapleural talc. 3. To establish a therapeutic approach outline based on the different prognosticfactors. Patients and methods: we studied a series of 126 patients with breast cancer and pleural metastasis. The classic factors of breast cancer were thoroughly examined. Also, we calculated the disease-free interval(DFI), the interval between the appearance of the pleural effusion and its thoracoscopic approach, the interval between pleurodesis with talc and death and the interval between the diagnosis of the first tumour and death. The biological factors (polymorphisms) were studied starting with the DNA of peripheral blood samples or cryopreservation of pleural liquid samples. Results: the pleural effusion was the first manifestation of a relapse of the disease in 77% of the cases. The disease-free interval (DFI) was57.9 months (13.6-83.3). The survival rate (expressed as median)from the diagnosis of the first tumour was 77.5 months (0.83-384).The average follow-up after the application of talc was 14.6 months. We found a correlation between the appearance of breast cancer(p=0.003) at a young age and the presence of the A2/A2 allele(homozygote of the CYP-17).Conclusions: the ideal profile for candidates for pleurodesis is those patients with an age &gt;50 years, long DFI, short interval of time between the appearance of the pleural effusion and the application oftalc, absence of other metastasis at the time of thoracoscopy, positive ER (estrogen receptors) and PR (progesterone receptors) and a percentage of lymph nodes infiltrated/extracted less than 50%. The presence of mutated GSTM1 will be related with a more effective (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas Fernández de Tejerina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Panadero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Worboys, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Juan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Falcón, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arellano Orden, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: 1. Estudiar qué tipo de marcadores biológicos tienen valor pronóstico en la supervivencia global y la respuesta al tratamiento en el cáncer de mama, a partir del descubrimiento de metástasis pleurales. 2. Examinar la influencia de la aplicación de talco intrapleural. 3. Establecer un esquema de abordaje terapéutico en base a los diferentes factores pronósticos. Pacientes y métodos: estudiamos una serie de 126 pacientes con cáncer de mama y afectación pleural metastásica. Se examinaron exhaustivamente los factores clásicos del cáncer de mama. Así mismo se calcularon el intervalo libre de enfermedad (ILE), el intervalo entre la aparición del derrame pleural y el abordaje toracoscópico del mismo, el intervalo entre la realización de la pleurodesis con talco y el exitus y el intervalo desde el diagnóstico del tumor primario hasta el exitus. Los factores biológicos (polimorfismos)fueron estudiados a partir del ADN de muestras de sangre periférica o líquido pleural crio conservado. Resultados: el derrame pleural era en el 77% de los casos la primera manifestación de recidiva de la enfermedad. El intervalo libre de enfermedad (ILE) fue de 57,9 meses (13,6-83,3). La supervivencia(expresada como mediana) desde el momento del diagnóstico del tumor primario fue de 77,5 meses (0,83-384). La media de seguimiento tras el talcaje fue de 14,6 meses. Encontramos correlación entre la edad temprana de presentación del cáncer de mama (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;21(4): 179-186, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123136</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de determinados marcadores biológicos en la supervivencia global y la respuesta al tratamiento del cáncer de mama con metástasis pleurales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29084^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32076^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14293^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
