<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103878</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Triamcinolone acetonide without solvents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purification of commercially prepared triamcinolone acetonide is important in order to avoid the potential toxic side-effects of the solvent benzyl alcohol. We present a new technique for preparation of pure triamcinolone acetonide by dissolving the powder in sterile distilled water with no additional solvents. As the triamcinolone powder is relatively insoluble in water, we describe the sterile method used for the preparation and control of this suspension. Materials and methods: The triamcinolone acetonide is prepared in our hospital pharmacy, under optimum sterile conditions, and then packaged in a primary vial, sealed and sterilized in an autoclave at 121 ºC. This vial contains an individual dose of 4 mg/0.1 ml. Results: A final dose for an intravitreal administration of 3.77 mg/0.1 ml triamcinolone acetonide was obtained using high pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC). The chemical,physical and microbiological stability allows the solution to be kept at a temperature of 2-8 &amp;#9702;C for 6 months. Conclusions: A rapid method is presented for preparing triamcinolone acetonide in pure state without preservatives in a concentration near the standard dose and under optimum sterile conditions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rubio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belmonte Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Moya, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lazcano, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selva Otaola-Urruchi, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La purificación del preparado comercial de triamcinolona acetónido disponible es importante para evitar el efecto potencialmente tóxico del disolvente alcohol bencílico. Presentamos una nueva técnica de preparación de triamcinolona en polvo, a partir de su forma pura, sin disolventes y diluida con agua destilada estéril. Dada su escasa solubilidad en aguase describe cómo preparar y controlar dicha suspensión. Material y método: El acetónido de triamcinolona es preparado por el Servicio de Farmacia del Hospital, en condiciones de máxima esterilidad, bajo campana de flujo laminar. La suspensión de triamcinolona es envasada en un vial primario, capsulado y posteriormente esterilizado en autoclave a 121 &amp;#9702;C. Del vial primario se obtienen dosis individualizadas de 4 mg/0,1 ml. Resultados: Se obtiene la dosis real administrada (3,77 mg/0,1 ml) mediante cuantificación de triamcinolona por cromatografía líquida de alta resolución (HPLC). La estabilidad física, química y microbiológica conservando el vial entre 2-8&amp;#9702; se mantiene a los 6 meses. Conclusión: Se presenta un método de preparación de triamcinolona en estado puro, obteniendo una concentración muy próxima a la dosis óptima, evitando el uso de disolventes y con máxima garantía de esterilidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(10): 320-323, oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103878</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acetónido de triamcinolona sin conservantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33374^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22707^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51672</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
