<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108377</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Difficulties and chances for nursing: a narrative review about the economic evaluation in health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is a narrativre review about the economic evaluation in health which had as an objective to identify the developed studies about the topic in the last ten years. The expenses and cost analysis descriptors were used at the data bases: LILACS, MEDLINE, IBECS AND CAPES. 88 publications were found and 65 were selected, from which the 44&#146;62% belonged to the database LILACS, the 44&#146;62% to MEDLINE, 4&#146;6% to IBECS and to CAPES. The 75&#146;38% were about the partial assessment of expenses and the 24&#146;62% about the economic assessment. The medicine was the sub-area that published (41&#146;54%), considering the two types of methodologies; followed by the nursing, which only published about partial evaluation of expenses (15&#146;38%). The nurse as an administrative tool in the Health Institution, needs to look for the knowledge about this segment of the economy, recognizying his role as a transformator agent and looking for the balance betewwen quality, quantity and expenses when deciding how to distribute the available financial resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Schutz, Vivian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata, Verónica Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas Peregrino, Antonio Augusto de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Revisión narrativa sobre evaluación económica en salud que tuvo como objetivo identificar los estudios desarrollados sobre el tema en los últimos diez años. Fue utilizado el descriptor costo y análisis de costos en las bases de datos: LILACS, MEDLINE, IBECS y CAPES. Fueron encontradas 88 publicaciones y seleccionadas 65, de las cuales 44,62% pertenecían a la base LILACS, 44,62% a MEDLINE, 4,60% a IBECS y 6,16% a CAPES. 75,38% eran sobre evaluación parcial de costos y 24,62% sobre evaluación económica. La medicina fue la sub-área que más publicó (41,54%), considerando los dos tipos de metodologías; seguida por la enfermería, que solo publicó sobre evaluación parcial de costos (15,38%). El enfermero como herramienta administrativa dentro de la Institución de Salud, necesita buscar conocimientos sobre este segmento de la economía, reconociendo su papel como agente transformador y buscar el equilibrio entre calidad, cantidad y costos en el momento de decidir cómo distribuir los recursos financieros disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(29): 392-403, ene. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dificultades y oportunidades para la enfermería: una revisión narrativa sobre evaluación económica en salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23782^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4539^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4539^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4539^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23782^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23782^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4539^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4539^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
