<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043374</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activity registry of the Spanish Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery, year 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. The main objective is to describe the assistance activity in the Angiology and Vascular Surgery services/units in Spain, corresponding to the year 2004. PATIENTS AND METHODS. A transversal study. The tested population was constituted by the endovascular and surgical procedures which were performed, on the year 2004, in 50 services of Angiology and Vascular Surgery, that voluntarily accepted the participation in this record. The instrument to collect information was the Vascular Registry (VR) of The Spanish Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery. We realised a descriptive analysis of the collected data. RESULTS. The VR was complemented by 50 services, from which 29 had official accreditation for teaching. There was a total of 33,210 admissions in hospital, 13,024 from which there were urgent (39.21%) and 20,186 (60.78%) were programmed and a global media stay of 9,4 days. In the waiting list, dated to the 31/12/04, there was a predominant of patients with venous pathology,5,420, the total of patients in waiting list for arterial pathology was 2,411 in the same date. The surgical activity detailed was composed by open arterial surgery, corresponding 1,525, carried out on supra-aortic trunks, 549 in upper limbs, 68 in thoracic aorta, 2,712 in aorto-iliac anatomic sector (including 1,273 AAA), 882 in aorto-iliac extra-anatomic sector, 48 in mesenteric arteries, 35 to renal arteries, 2,057 (femoro-popliteal) and 1,080 (femoro-distal) to lower limbs arteries. The venous surgery had a whole predominant of varicose vein surgery with 13,611 procedures. The endovascular procedures were performed in arterial level, corresponding 196 to SAT, 111 to vascular access, 434 endografts were implanted by aneurysm of abdominal aorta, 81 by thoracic aortic aneurysm, 10 in mesenteric arteries, 102 in renal arteries and 2,001 in lower limbs arteries. The total of venous endovascular procedures was 77. CONCLUSIONS. Participation was not increased this year. Arterial pathology has conditioned the majority of the registered procedures, such us surgical or even endovascular. Again, significant differences were found between teaching and no teaching centres in quantitative parameters relatives to open arterial surgery, in endovascular treatment of aneurysms and in assistential parameters</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Carriles, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir la actividad asistencial, correspondiente al año 2004, de los Servicios de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular en España. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio transversal. La población muestreada se constituyó, por los procedimientos quirúrgicos y endovasculares que se realizaron, en el año 2004, en 50 servicios de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular que voluntariamente aceptaron la participación en el registro. El instrumento de recogida de la información fue un formulario específico, Registro Vascular (RV) de la Sociedad Española de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular (SEACV). Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de los datos recogidos. Resultados. El RV fue cumplimentado por 50 servicios, 29 de los cuales poseen acreditación para la docencia. Hubo un total de 33.210 ingresos hospitalarios, 13.024 urgentes (39,21%), 20.186 (60,78%) programados y una estancia media global de 9,4 días. En la lista de espera, a fecha 31/12/04, existía un predominio de pacientes con patología venosa (n = 5.420), y el total de pacientes en lista de espera por patología arterial era de 2.411 en la misma fecha. El detalle de la actividad quirúrgica comprende en cirugía arterial directa 1.525 procedimientos practicados en los troncos supraaórticos, 549 en miembros superiores, 68 en la aorta torácica, 2.712 vía anatómica (de los cuales 1.273 por AAA) y 882 vía extraanatómica en sector aortoilíaco por oclusión, 48 a los troncos viscerales digestivos, 35 a arterias renales, 2.057 en sector femoropoplíteo y 1.080 en sector femorodistal de los miembros inferiores. La cirugía venosa, tuvo un alto predominio de cirugía de varices con 13.611 procedimientos realizados por esta entidad. Se realizaron procedimientos endovasculares correspondiendo 196 a TSA, 111 a accesos vasculares, 68 a sector aórtico, implantándose además 81 endoprótesis por aneurisma en aorta torácica y 434 por aneurisma de aorta abdominal, 10 en troncos viscerales digestivos, 102 renales y 2.001 en arterias de miembros inferiores. Los procedimientos endovasculares venosos fueron 77. Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre los centros docentes y no docentes en los parámetros relativos a cirugía arterial directa, el tratamiento endovascular de los aneurismas de aorta abdominal y parámetros asistenciales. Conclusiones. No se ha producido incremento en la participación. De nuevo este año, la mayoría de los procedimientos registrados son arteriales, tanto quirúrgicos como endovasculares. También se han demostrado diferencias cuantitativas entre centros docentes y no docentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(1): 69-83, ene.-feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro de actividad de la Sociedad Española de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular, año 2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
