<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81444</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wounds with different aetiology treated using larval debridement therapy: Presentation of two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AbstractThis paper describes two cases of wounds with different aetiology and dissimilar size which were treated with Larval Debridement Therapy. Two different techniques of Larval Debridement were used for each case: Free Range and BioFoam® larvae. Observations and treatment were carried out in a Primary Health Centre in Barcelona, Spain. The application and observations were performed by two nurses with the collaboration of two family physicians.AbstractThe Larval Therapy efficacy outcome was checked with an Ulcer Reverse Stage Scale (PUSH v2), by taking photographs and a Visual Analogue Pain Scale (VAPS) was completed by both subjects before and after the treatment.AbstractIt was observed in both cases that the larval therapy caused debridement of all fibrin and collagen tissue, and the slough dropped to a normal level. As a consequence of this change the PUSH scale punctuations were improved. On the negative side, the therapy was associated with an increase in pain. The beneficial effect of applying Larval Therapy enables following a basic wound healing care plan. The larval debridement therapy did not pose any threat for the patients; they could go about their Activities of the Daily Life (ADL) without any change. These wound cases treated with larval debridement therapy are the first ones reported in the Primary Health Care field in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-de Paz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortes-Bordas, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro-Elvira, Belén de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ResumenSe describen 2 casos de herida con diferente etiología y dimensiones en 2 pacientes que fueron tratadas mediante tratamiento desbridante larval. Se empleó una técnica en cada caso: Free Range y BioFoam®. Las observaciones y el tratamiento se llevaron a cabo en un centro de salud de Barcelona, España (ámbito de atención primaria). Los profesionales que realizaron la aplicación y observaron la evolución fueron 2 enfermeros con la colaboración de dos médicos de familia.ResumenLa eficacia de la terapia larval se comprobó mediante la aplicación de una escala de reversión del estadio de la herida (PUSH v2), la realización de tomas fotográficas y una escala visual del dolor.ResumenEn los 2 casos se observó que la aplicación del tratamiento larval originó el desbridamiento de todo el tejido fibrinoso y el colágeno desnaturalizado y el exudado de la herida también decreció hasta niveles normales en ambas heridas. Como consecuencia de este cambio las puntuaciones de la escala PUSH mejoraron. Como elemento negativo se observó el incremento del dolor. El efecto beneficioso de la aplicación de esta terapia permitió continuar con un plan de curas basado en la cura húmeda. La aplicación de la terapia larval desbridante no supuso amenaza alguna para la seguridad de los pacientes y pudieron realizar las actividades de la vida diaria con normalidad. Estos dos casos son los primeros que han sido tratados mediante terapia larval desbridante en el ámbito de la atención primaria de salud en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 47-53, ene.-feb. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de dos casos de herida, con diferente etiología, tratadas mediante terapia larval desbridante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7992</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
