<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77865</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spinal granuloma in a patient receiving a spinal infusion of morphine and clonidine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients treated with long-term spinal infusion of highdoses of morphine develop a granuloma at the locationof the catheter tip. Diagnosis is based on a steadyincrease in intrathecal morphine dosage after arelatively prolonged period of stability, on the gradualdevelopment of neurologic signs and symptomssuggesting radicular or spinal cord compression, and onmagnetic resonance images. We describe a man withcentral neuropathic pain after removal of a tumor. Thepresence of all 3 of the aforementioned diagnosticcriteria led to suspicion of a spinal granuloma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abejón, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Pozo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Saz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ley, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes en tratamiento con infusión espinal demorfina a dosis elevadas presentan como efecto adversoa largo plazo la formación de un granuloma en la puntadel catéter intradural. La subida ininterrumpida de lasdosis de morfina intratecales tras un periodo relativamenteprolongada de estabilidad, la aparición progresivade una sintomatología neurológica característica decompresión radicular o medular, y las imágenes de resonanciamagnética llevan al diagnóstico de este fenómeno.Se presenta un caso clínico de un paciente con dolor neuropáticocentral tras exéresis tumoral, que reúne los tresprincipios mencionados que llevan al diagnóstico de sospechade granuloma intradural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(6): 380-384, jun.-jul. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Granuloma intradural en un paciente con infusión espinalde morfina y clonidina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3025^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24741^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24701^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24701^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
