<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147218</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training effects in repeated sprint ability (RSA) in basketball referees</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most studies in basketball have focused on the study of the players and just a few have focused on the study of basketball referees. The ability to repeat sprints (RSA) is one of the key components in physical performance in basketball. Therefore, the aim of this study is to analyze the RSA and the anthropometric values in basketball referees after a period of 5 weeks of specific training. 24 referees were evaluated divided into Group Control (GC) and Experimental Group (GE). An anthropometric determination (Size, Weight, Body fat%, and BMI) and a 7x20m RSA test were performed twice, before and after of 5 specific training weeks (PRE and POST). Small differences in the weight of the referees in PRE and POST in both groups were found but also there are some differences in body fat%, decreasing in 2.5% the GC and in 5.29% the GE. The improvements in RSA are 0.67% for GC and 5.10% for the GE. In conclusion, the basketball referees improvements in RSA after a specific training clearly improves their physical condition and their anthropometric value (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bayón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dehesa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Tormo, JV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayor parte de los estudios en baloncesto se han centrado en el estudio de los jugadores existiendo pocos que se hayan centrado en el estudio de los árbitros de baloncesto. La habilidad para repetir sprints (RSA) es uno de los componentes claves en el rendimiento físico en baloncesto. Por ello, el objetivo de este estudio es analizar la RSA y los valores cineantropométricos en árbitros de baloncesto después de un periodo de entrenamiento de 5 semanas. 24 árbitros fueron analizados, divididos en Grupo Control (GC) y Grupo Experimental (GE). Se les realizó una determinación cineantropométrica (Talla, Peso, % Graso y IMC) y un test de RSA de 7x20 m. en dos ocasiones, antes y después de estas semanas de entrenamiento (PRE y POST). Encontramos pequeñas diferencias en el peso en ambos grupos entre el PRE y POST así como diferencias en el % graso, donde ambos disminuyeron, 2.5% el GC y 5.29% el GE. Las mejoras en el RSA fueron evidentes, siendo 0.67% para el GC y 5.10% para el GE. En conclusión, después de un entrenamiento específico, las mejoras en RSA en árbitros de baloncesto claramente mejorarán su condición física así como sus valores cineantropométricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 163-168, oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del entrenamiento en la habilidad para repetir sprints (RSA) en arbitros de baloncesto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
