<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122477</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with residents&#146; satisfaction with their training as specialists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: We do not know what factors influence residents&#146; perceived satisfaction during their training. The aim of this study was to analyze the satisfaction of specialists with their training and its associated factors. Material and methods: This was a cross-sectional study using self-completion surveys of residents in training at the Clinic Hospital San Carlos for the courses conducted in 2006, 2009, 2010 and 2012. The study's dependent variable was overall satisfaction with the training; the independent factors were demographic and occupational characteristics, variables related to healthcare, teaching and research activity. Results: The total participation percentage was 83.7% (1,424/1,701), and the mean age was 28.4 years (SD, 3.2 years). The overall satisfaction percentage was 75.2%. The factors statistically associated with overall satisfaction in the multivariate analysis were the involvement of the teaching staff (tutors and assistants) in the training, greater satisfaction in medical versus surgical specialties, the year of residence, the facilities for completing the thesis, working less than 40h a week, adequate time to perform daily tasks, appropriate number of department meetings and not having a previous specialty. Conclusions: the activities related to research and teaching are associated with the overall satisfaction of residents. The routine activity factors most closely associated with satisfaction were the time available and the work hours. More studies are necessary to understand the impact of resident satisfaction on care quality and in their activity as future specialists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Ferrer, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Díaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumayor Zarzuelo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala Morillas, L. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: No se conoce qué factores influyen en la percepción de la satisfacción de los residentes durante su formación. El objetivo del estudio fue analizar la satisfacción del especialista en formación y sus factores asociados. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal mediante encuestas autocumplimentadas a los residentes en formación del Hospital Clínico San Carlos en los cortes realizados en los años 2006, 2009, 2010 y 2012. La variable dependiente del estudio fue la satisfacción global con la formación, y como factores independientes se estudiaron características sociodemográficas y laborales, variables relacionadas con la actividad asistencial, docente e investigadora. Resultados: Porcentaje de participación total de un 83,7% (1.424/1.701). La edad media fue 28,4 (DE 3,2) años. El porcentaje de satisfacción global fue de un 75,2%. En el análisis multivariado, los factores asociados de manera estadísticamente significativa a la satisfacción global fueron: la implicación del personal docente (tutores y adjuntos) en la formación, mayor satisfacción en especialidades médicas frente a las quirúrgicas, el año de residencia, las facilidades para realizar la tesis, trabajar menos de 40h a la semana, el tiempo adecuado para la realización de las tareas diarias, la adecuación en el número de sesiones en el servicio y el no disponer de otra especialidad previa. Conclusiones: Las actividades relacionadas con la investigación y docencia están asociadas con la satisfacción global del residente. Los factores de la actividad rutinaria que más se asocian con la satisfacción fueron el tiempo disponible y las horas de trabajo. Son necesarios más estudios para conocer el impacto de la satisfacción del residente en la calidad asistencial y en su actividad como futuro especialista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(4): 175-183, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122477</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a la satisfacción del residente con su formación como especialista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17571^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
