<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152905</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and factors associated with frequent attendence in family medicine clinic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The use of health services has seen a steep rise. The frequent users are responsible for significant economic, human and social impact. The objective is to analyze the characteristics of frequent attenders in our Health Center, in order to evaluate the possibility of taking corrective measures to improve the quality of care and efficiency in the use of resources. Materials and methods. Descriptive observational study of a sample of 379 patients over 18 years old. The dependent variables were attendance (number of visits to their family doctor during the previous year), frequent attendance (10 or more visits to the family doctor in the last year), and persistent frequent attenders (10 or more visits to the family doctor in each of the last two years). Data were collected from medical records and by telephone interview. Results. The mean attendance was 6.83 (95% CI: 6.13-7.53), frequent attendance reached 25.4% (95% CI: 21.4-29.6), and persistent frequent attenders, 1.6% (95% CI: 0.5-2.9). Frequent attendance was associated with sex, age, marital status, educational level, family structure, existence of chronic disease, use of anxiolytic and antidepressants, request for additional tests, and referrals to other specialists, proximity to the health center, and level of satisfaction with their family doctor. Conclusions. The low persistent frequent attenders found suggests that frequent attendance could be largely due to factors related to professional and organization. Studies are required to address the high level of consumption of psychotropic drugs, and improving professional skills in dealing with mental problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parejo Maestre, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez-Torres, FM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gónzalez-Contero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espejo-Almazán María, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez-Espinosa de los Monteros, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lendínez-de la Cruz, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La utilización de servicios sanitarios ha experimentado un fuerte incremento. Los hiperfrecuentadores son responsables de un importante impacto económico, humano y social. El objetivo es analizar las características de la hiperfrecuentación en nuestro Centro de Salud con el propósito de evaluar la posibilidad de adoptar medidas correctoras que mejoren la calidad asistencial y la eficiencia en el uso de los recursos. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional descriptivo realizado a una muestra de 379 personas mayores de 18 años. Las variables dependientes fueron frecuentación (número de consultas a su médico de familia durante el año anterior), hiperfrecuentación (10 o más visitas al médico de familia en el último año) e hiperfrecuentación persistente (10 o más visitas al médico de familia en cada uno de los 2 últimos años). Los datos fueron recogidos de la historia clínica y mediante entrevista telefónica. Resultados. La media de frecuentación fue de 6,83 (IC 95%: 6,13-7,53), la hiperfrecuentación alcanzó el 25,4% (IC 95%: 21,4-29,6) y la hiperfrecuentación persistente el 1,6% (IC 95%: 0,5-2,9). La hiperfrecuentación se relacionó con el sexo, la edad, el estado civil, el nivel académico, la estructura familiar, la existencia de enfermedad crónica, el consumo de ansiolíticos y antidepresivos, la solicitud de exámenes complementarios y derivaciones a otros especialistas, la proximidad al centro de salud y el grado de satisfacción con su médico de familia. Conclusiones. La escasa hiperfrecuentación persistente sugiere que la hiperfrecuentación pudiera deberse en gran parte de factores relacionados con el profesional y la organización. Sería aconsejable promover investigaciones que aborden el alto nivel de consumo de psicofármacos y la mejora de las competencias profesionales en el abordaje de los problemas mentales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(4): 216-224, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152905</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y factores asociados a la hiperfrecuentación en la consulta de medicina de familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10004^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10004^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6452^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6452^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
