<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130022</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tattoo pigment in limphatics in patient with melonma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case that shows the complexity in the treatment of malignant melanoma specially in young patients and the great importance of sentynel node biopsy in the prognostic and treatment of these patients. Our patient was a 26 years old scandinavian female with a pigmented lesion in lumbar central region. After the excision it results a malignat melanoma. Patient delayed for 6 months to come back to us. Following our protocol and accord to Breslow index 1,1 mm., Clark IV, we decide to perform a marginal wide excision of the lesion and a lymphoscintigraphy, previous to sentinel node biopsy. Lymphoscintigraphy showed 3 different routes of drainage: to left pubis, to left axial and to the right inframmary region. Complementary analysis lead to final diagnostic: lymphatic pigmentation by tattoo ink coming from an anatomical area next to melanoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros-Cantó, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesta-Alcaraz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso clínico que ilustra la complejidad del tratamiento del melanoma maligno en pacientes jóvenes así como la importancia que tiene en la actualidad la biopsia selectiva del ganglio centinela, imprescindible para su pronóstico y su tratamiento. Se trata de una paciente de 26 años de edad y de origen escandinavo con lesión pigmentada en región lumbar central, que tras la extirpación, resultó ser un melanoma maligno. La paciente no se presentó a recoger el resultado hasta 6 meses después de la extirpación. Siguiendo el protocolo habitual y teniendo en cuenta el grado de profundidad de la lesión, Breslow 1,1mm., Clark IV, planteamos ampliación de márgenes quirúrgicos de la lesión y gammagrafía isotópica previa a la biopsia selectiva del ganglio centinela. La gammagrafía detectó 3 territorios de drenaje desde la localización del tumor primario en espalda: región inguinal izquierda, región axilar izquierda y región inframamaria derecha. El resto de pruebas realizadas, llevó al diganóstico final de pigmentación ganglionar por tinta de tatuaje corporal en área adyacente al melanoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;40(3): 337-341, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pigmento de tatuaje en linfáticos en paciente con melanoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
