<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112734</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Pain is one of the most feared outcomes of surgery by patients, yet current practices of pain management are suboptimal. Failure to address acute postoperative pain can have a variety of consequences that affect physical and psychological aspects of the patient. Current perioperative pain management normally consists of opioid therapy, which has been a mainstay for many years. However, use of opioids can have moderate risks, including nausea/vomiting, dizziness, and constipation, or more severe risks, including respiratory depression and immunosupression. Aim: In order to address some of the issues surrounding perioperative pain management, a group of key opinion leaders gathered at an international summit to analyze the current practices of perioperative pain management. One of the topics focused on buprenorphine&#146;s role in perioperative pain and the information discussed is presented throughout this article. Conclusion: Buprenorphine has been demonstrated to be effective and safe in many postoperative pain models. Its administration versatility, its manageable side effects, and its use in combination with other analgesics allow buprenorphine therapy to be successful in perioperative pain management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pergolizzi Jr, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muniz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plancarte, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taylor Jr, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bashkansky, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El dolor es uno de los eventos más temidos por los pacientes después de una cirugía, y en la actualidad el manejo del dolor es subóptimo. La falta de control del dolor agudo postoperatorio puede tener una serie de consecuencias que afectan a los aspectos físicos y emocionales de los pacientes. El manejo habitual del dolor postoperatorio se basa en la utilización de opioides, pilar de tratamiento desde hace muchos años. Sin embargo, el uso de opioides puede tener riesgos moderados, como son las náuseas y vómitos, mareos y constipación, o riesgos más severos que incluyen a la inmunosupresión y depresión respiratoria. Objetivo: Para poder determinar algunos de los factores circundantes del dolor postoperatorio, se realizó una reunión cumbre internacional en la que un grupo de líderes de opinión analizó las prácticas habituales de manejo de dolor postoperatorio. Uno de los temas abordados fue el rol de la buprenorfina en el manejo del dolor perioperatorio, y la información discutida se presenta a lo largo de este artículo. Conclusión: La buprenorfina ha demostrado ser eficaz y segura en muchos modelos de dolor postoperatorio. Su versatilidad de administración, sus efectos secundarios manejables y su posibilidad de ser combinada con otros analgésicos hacen que la buprenorfina sea exitosa en el manejo del dolor perioperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;19(6): 281-292, nov.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112734</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es la Buprenorfina una buena opción en el manejo de dolor postoperatorio?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2079^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2079^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2079^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7109^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
