<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124323</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">cycEVA study: case control study Measuring influenza vaccine effectiveness in Spain, 2008-2013</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In Spain, influenza vaccine effectiveness (EV) is estimated since 2008-09 season through the cycEVAcase-control study, the Spanish component of the European I-MOVE (Monitoring Influenza Vaccine Effectiveness in the EU/EEA) network.We aimed at describing cycEVAperformance in its five consolidated editions 2008/09 &#150; 2012/13. Methods: During the study period the following indicators were analysed: 1) the participation of sentinel general practitioners and pediatricians (MP), 2) the population studied and the study period, 3) the data quality and 4) the dissemination of the cycEVA results. Trend analysis of the indicators was done using the Cochran-Armitage test to compute theAnnual Percentage Change (PCA). Results: The number of participatingMP increased from 164 in 2008-09 to 246 in the following editions. The percentage of MP recruiting at least one patient increased significantly annually (PCA = 15.33%). The percentage of recruited patients included into the analysis increased (PCA=5.91%) from 77% in 2008-09 to more than 95% in the following editions. The percentage of cycEVA patients contributing to the I-MOVE study ranged between 23% and 30% in the pilot and 2011-12 editions respectively.. Final results were disseminated in quartile 2 peer-reviewed journals and 2010-11 and 2011-12 preliminary EV estimates were published in quartile 1 journals. cycEVA publications received 97 citations. Conclusion: cycEVA study achieved more quality information, timely EV estimates and a higher impact of the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Sanz, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Sánchez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Durán, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo García, Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiñones Rubio, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanrell Berga, Juana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Savulescu, Camelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gay, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altzíbar Arotzena, Jone Miren</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Alonso, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Jorge, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Martin, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cenoz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo Ontañón, Salvador de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ochoa, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Aceitero, Julián Mauro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castrillejo Pérez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez i Mateo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla Catalán, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrauri Cámara, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Morilla, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Carril, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torner Gràcia, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Desde 2008-09 la efectividad de la vacuna (EV) antigripal en España se estima con el estudio de casos y controles para la evaluación de la EV antigripal (cycEVA), componente español de la red europea (Influenza- Monitoring Vaccine Effectiveness (I-MOVE). El objetivo es describir la evolución del estudio cycEVAdurante las cinco temporadas del período 2008/09&#150; 2012/13. Métodos: Se analizaron los siguientes indicadores: 1) participación de los médicos/pediatras centinela (MP); 2) población y periodo de estudio, 3) calidad de los datos y 4) difusión de los resultados mediantes publicaciones. Se calculó el porcentaje anual de cambio constante de los indicadores analizándose su tendencia mediante el test de Cochran-Armitage. Resultados: El número de MP participantes aumentó de 164 en 2008-09 hasta 246 en ediciones posteriores. El porcentaje de médicos que reclutaron al menos un paciente experimentó un cambio anual significativo (PCA) del 15,33%. El porcentaje de pacientes reclutados incluidos en el análisis aumentó del 77% en 2008-09 a más del 95% en las siguientes ediciones (PCA=5,91%). El porcentaje de casos y controles participantes en cycEVA sobre el total de pacientes que contribuyeron al estudio europeo I-MOVE osciló entre el 23% en la edición piloto y 30% en la temporada 2011-12. Los resultados finales se difundieron en revistas científicas con un factor de impacto situado en el cuartil 2 y en 2010-11 y 2011-12 se publicaron resultados preliminares en revistas con un factor de impacto situado en el cuartil 1 (97 citas). Conclusiones: La experiencia del estudio cycEVA se reflejó en una mejora en la oportunidad e impacto de sus resultados, cruciales para orientar las recomendaciones anuales de vacunación antigripal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(5): 601-611, sept.-oct. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio cycEVA: caos y controles para la estimación de la efectividad de la vacuna antigripal en España, 2008-2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
