<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115355</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asssessment and treatment of school phobia in children and adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">School anxiety is defined as a maladapted pattern of anxiety behaviours related to school situations, being considered one of the most disabling anxiety disorders during childhood and adolescence. This article reviews the common characteristics of youths with school anxiety, distinguishing between other anxiety disorders such as separation anxiety disorder and truancy. Moreover, methods of evaluation commonly employed are reviewed, in particular the Fear School Inventory (FSI) and the School Refusal Assessment Scale (SRAS). Furthermore, the literature about the treatment of school anxiety is reviewed, concluding that the cognitive-behavioural approach is the most widespread and effective therapy. Finally, the advances in research on school anxiety are described</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inglés, Cándido J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Monteagudo, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ansiedad escolar se define como un patrón desadaptativo de respuestas de ansiedad ante situaciones escolares, siendo considerado como uno de los trastornos infanto-juveniles más incapacitantes. Este artículo revisa las características comunes de los jóvenes que presentan ansiedad escolar, distinguiéndose de otros trastornos de ansiedad, tales como ansiedad por separación y hacer novillos. Además, se revisan los métodos de evaluación generalmente utilizados, subrayando el Inventario de Miedos Escolares (IME) y la &#147;Escala de evaluación del rechazo a la escuela&#148; (School Refusal Assessment Scale; SRAS). Del mismo modo, se revisa la literatura sobre el tratamiento de la ansiedad escolar, encontrándose que la orientación cognitivo-conductual es la terapia más ampliamente utilizada y eficaz. Finalmente, se describen los avances en la investigación sobre ansiedad escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;16(3): 413-437, sept.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y tratamiento de la ansiedad escolar en la infancia y adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
