<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116748</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tolerance and respect for differences: The effects of an educational activity at school</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study of an experimental intervention that evaluated the impact of an educational activity in schools to promote tolerance and respect for differences is reported. A total of 300 children participated, divided into three groups: one control (without intervention), and two experimental groups (drama and audiovisual presentation of a children&#146;s story, focusing on the topic of preferences for soccer teams). The intervention was assessed before and after, with a semantic differential scale range in which children attributed positive and negative adjectives to their own team as well as the opposing team. The results showed: (1) a more favorable evaluation of one&#146;s own team maintained during the two specific moments, (2) the initially more unfavorable evaluation, towards the opposing team, improved significantly after the intervention. The implications of the results are discussed in relation to the school social function of improving students&#146; social-emotional development, as well as the importance of evaluating pedagogical alternatives addressing this objective. Some limitations regarding this study and also research referrals are presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prette, Zilda Aparecida Pereira del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amaro, Livia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laurenti, Aline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prette, Almir del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domeniconi, Camila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benitez, Priscila</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se trata de una investigación de intervención experimental que evaluó el impacto de una actividad educativa en la escuela cuyo propósito era promover la tolerancia y el respeto a las diferencias. Participaron 300 niños, divididos en tres grupos: uno de control (sin intervención) y dos experimentales (dramatización y presentación audiovisual de una historia infantil, ambos procedimientos con la temática de la preferencia por equipos de fútbol). La intervención se evaluó, antes y después, por medio de una escala de diferencial semántico en que los niños atribuían adjetivos positivos y negativos al propio equipo y al equipo adversario. Los resultados mostraron (1) que la evaluación más favorable al proprio equipo se mantuvo en los dos momentos y (2) la evaluación inicial más desfavorable al equipo adversario mejoró después de la intervención de forma significativa. Se discuten las implicaciones de los resultados para la función social de la escuela en la formación socioemocional de los alumnos, así como la importancia de la evaluación de alternativas pedagógicas orientadas a este objetivo. Por último, se señalan las limitaciones del estudio y se hacen sugerencias respecto a la investigación futura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(1): 59-66, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La tolerancia y el respeto a las diferencias: efectos de una actividad educativa en la escuela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55088^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
