<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167776</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">"Explora": Assisting students with more curiosity, motivation, or ability without excluding anyone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the academic year 2014/2015, the Education Department of the Government of La Rioja launched in eight schools in this region, on an experimental basis, the program "Explora" for the attention to students with high intellectual capacity. Both face-to-face and online workshops were planned. The implementation of face-to-face workshops (goals, contents, activities, student selection, sessions, etc.) was designed by the own educational centers in a traditional way. However, the four online workshops (maths, language, computing, and emotional intelligence) were developed following the Sports Approach by Joan Freeman. This paper shows the foundation, development, and evaluation of these online workshops. A qualitative and quantitative evaluation was carried out, with very encouraging results: big acceptance of the program by participants was confirmed along with the program appropriateness for the selection of students with high intellectual capacity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Díez, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Fernández, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Sáenz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hierro-Berceo, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Fernández, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cencerrado-de-Aller, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante el curso 2014/2015, la Consejería de Educación del Gobierno de La Rioja puso en marcha en ocho colegios de esta Comunidad Autónoma, de manera experimental, el programa "Explora" para la atención al alumnado de capacidad intelectual elevada. Se planearon tanto talleres presenciales como online. La implementación de los presenciales (objetivos, contenidos, actividades, selección de alumnado, sesiones, etc.) fue diseñada por los propios centros docentes, estructurándose su funcionamiento de manera tradicional. Sin embargo, los cuatro talleres online (matemáticas, lenguaje, informática e inteligencia emocional) se desarrollaron siguiendo el enfoque deportivo (Sports Approach) de Joan Freeman. En el presente artículo se muestra la fundamentación, desarrollo y evaluación de estos talleres online. Se realizó una evaluación cualitativa y cuantitativa cuyos resultados son muy alentadores: se confirmó la buena aceptación del programa por parte de los participantes y se comprobó su adecuación para la selección del alumnado de elevada capacidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);23(2): 95-103, jul.-dic. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167776</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">"Explora": atender a los alumnos con más curiosidad, motivación o capacidad sin excluir a nadie</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2706^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
