<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127581</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Demographic, clinical, and genetic characteristics of patients with medullary thyroid cancer in the past 16 years in Castilla-La Mancha</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Medullary thyroid cancer is a rare tumor that is more aggressive and has a worse prognosis than differentiated thyroid cancer. The purpose of this study was to report the demographic, clinical, and genetic characteristics of patients seen in the health care system of the community of Castilla-La Mancha over a 16-year period. Patients and methods Data were collected through a review of patients&#146; medical records. Results The medical records of 58 patients (mean age at diagnosis, 51 years; range, 6-82 years; 63.8% women) were reviewed. Prevalence rate was 2.84 cases per 100,000 inhabitants, with a high variability between areas (range, 0-5.4 cases per 100,000 inhabitants). Familial cases accounted for 34.5% of all medullary thyroid cancers, and the most common mutation was C634Y. The condition was most commonly diagnosed following palpation of a cervical lump (70.6%). At diagnosis, 56 of 58 patients underwent ultrasound and 8 of 58 patients were tested for serum calcitonin. Tumor multicentricity was reported in 59 and 50% of patients with multiple endocrine neoplasia syndrome type 2A and 2B, respectively, and in no sporadic cases. Fifty-two percent of patients had an advanced stage (III or IV) at diagnosis. Median follow-up was 36 months (interquartile range, 14-210); 11 patients were lost to follow-up. ConclusionsIn Castilla-La Mancha, medullary thyroid cancer is diagnosed by cervical ultrasound, rather than calcitonin assay. There is a high prevalence of both familial and sporadic medullary thyroid cancer, and a significant variability in the type of proto-oncogen rearranged during transfection mutation as compared to the rest of the Spanish population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pinés, Pedro J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Louhibi, Lynda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padillo, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alramadán, Mubarak</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo El carcinoma medular de tiroides es un tumor de baja prevalencia cuyo pronóstico es peor que el del cáncer diferenciado de tiroides debido su mayor agresividad. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir las características demográficas, clínicas y genéticas de los pacientes atendidos en el área sanitaria de la Comunidad de Castilla-La Mancha durante 16 años. Pacientes y métodos Los datos se recogieron mediante revisión de historias clínicas. Resultados Se revisaron las historias clínicas de 58 pacientes con una edad media al diagnóstico de 51 años (intervalo de 6 a 82 años) y un 63,8% de mujeres. La prevalencia fue de 2,84 casos por 100.000 habitantes, con una gran variabilidad entre áreas (de 0 a 5,4 casos por 100.000 habitantes). Los casos familiares representaron el 34,5% del total, siendo la mutación más frecuente la C634Y. El motivo más frecuente de diagnóstico fue la palpación de un bultoma cervical (70,6%); se solicitó ecografía al diagnóstico en 56 de 58 casos, y la calcitonina en 8 de 58 casos. La multicentricidad del tumor fue descrita en el 59 y 50% de los casos de síndrome de neoplasia endocrina múltiple tipo 2A y 2B, respectivamente, y en ningún caso esporádico. El 52% de los pacientes presentaba un estadio avanzado al diagnóstico (III o IV). La mediana de seguimiento fue de 36 meses (rango intercuartílico 14-210), con la pérdida de 11 pacientes durante el seguimiento. Conclusiones El diagnóstico de carcinoma medular de tiroides en Castilla-La Mancha se basa en la ecografía cervical, pero no en la calcitonina. Existe una alta prevalencia de este carcinoma, tanto familiar como esporádico, y una importante variabilidad en el tipo de mutación del protooncogén rearranged during transfection comparadas con las del resto de la población española(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(8): 398-403, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demografía, características clínicas y genéticas de pacientes con carcinoma medular de tiroides en los últimos 16 años en Castilla-La Mancha</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19632^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29779^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31589^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32133^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
