<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042491</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnetic resonance imaging evidence of the effectiveness of combination chelation therapy in iron overload cardiomyopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heart failure secondary to iron overload is the main cause of death in patients with â-thalassemia major. Combination therapy with deferoxamine and deferiprone has been shown to be more effective than either drug used alone in patients with â-thalassemia major and symptomatic cardiomyopathy. Although monitoring the response to chelation therapy is usually carried out by indirect measurement of the serum ferritin level or by direct determination of tissue iron content in biopsy specimens, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) seems to be useful for noninvasive qualitative and quantitative assessment of iron deposition. We present a case in which the efficacy of double chelation therapy in a patient with â-thalassemia major and heart failure was demonstrated by MRI</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martíneze, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estornell, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María Martín, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orero, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ridoccid, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia cardíaca secundaria a la miocardiopatía por sobrecarga de hierro es la principal causa de muerte en los pacientes con â-talasemia mayor. Estudios recientemente publicados demuestran que el tratamiento combinado con deferoxamina y deferiprona es más eficaz que la monoterapia en pacientes con â-talasemia mayor y miocardiopatía sintomática. Aunque el control de la respuesta al tratamiento quelante se realiza habitualmente mediante la determinación de ferritina sérica o de hierro tisular en las muestras de biopsia, la resonancia magnética (RM) parece ser capaz de identificar de forma no invasiva el depósito de hierro en diferentes órganos y, además, hacer una estimación cuantitativa de éste. Presentamos un caso que demuestra la eficacia del tratamiento quelante combinado en un paciente con â-talasemia mayor e insuficiencia cardíaca objetivada por RM</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(1): 75-77, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia por resonancia magnética de la eficacia del tratamiento quelante combinado en la miocardiopatía por depósito férrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30812^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30812^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3689^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28113^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23180^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
