<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137132</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sanitary waste in the hospital setting: Knowledge level and overall rating</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sanitary waste represents a potential hazard for health workers. Given the high risk of infection in labor accidents, the correct management of sanitary waste minimizes this risk and improves labor and environment conditions. Objective. The current study was aimed at identifying the knowledge that health workers have about classification and management of sanitary waste. Methodology. The current study is a descriptive, cross-sectional study of 178 health workers (physicians, nurses, nurse assistants, lab technicians) of 3 hospitals in Barcelona. Results. Using a score from 1 (minimum) to 15 (maximum) to assess the knowledge, the average value for nurse assistants, nurses, physicians and lab technicians was 10.59, 10.61, 8.92 and 8.39, respectively. The global assessment of sanitary waste management (using a score from 1 to 5) was 2.89, 2.93, 2.88 and 2.94, respectively. Conclusions. These results suggest that nurses and nurse assistants have a good level of knowledge about the management of sanitary waste. By contrast, physicians and laboratory technicians have a lower level of knowledge compared to nurses and nurse asistants in relation to segregation and disposal of sanitary waste. Concerning the global assessment, the level is good, without differences between the different categories of health workers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galimany Masclans, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Egea, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Estaella, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girbau García, Mª Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Agredano, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrens García, M. Llum</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los residuos sanitarios representan un peligro potencial para los trabajadores sanitarios. Dado el alto riesgo de infección en los accidentes laborales, la gestión correcta de los residuos sanitarios minimiza el riesgo y mejora las condiciones laborales y ambientales. Objetivos. Identificar el nivel de conocimiento que tienen los profesionales sanitarios, en relación con la clasificación y gestión avanzada de los residuos sanitarios (RS) y valorar de forma global la gestión de los mismos. Metodología. Estudio descriptivo transversal con 178 participantes (auxiliares, enfermeras, médicos y técnicos de laboratorio), de 3 hospitales de la provincia de Barcelona.  Se utilizó un cuestionario de elaboración propia, que analizabalas variables laborales, el conocimiento y la valoración  global de la gestión de los RS. Resultados. El nivel medio de conocimiento sobre los RS delos auxiliares, las enfermeras, los médicos y los técnicos de laboratorio, en una escala de 1 (valor mínimo) a 15 (valor  máximo), es de 10.59, 10.61, 8.92 y 8.39, respectivamente. La valoración global que hacen los auxiliares, las enfermeras, los médicos y los técnicos de laboratorio de la gestión de los RS en una escala de 1 (valor mínimo) y 5 (valor máximo), es de 2.89, 2.93, 2.88, 2.94, respectivamente. Conclusiones. Los resultados sugieren que las enfermeras y los auxiliares tienen un nivel de conocimiento aceptable con respecto a la gestión correcta de los RS. En cambio, los médicos y técnicos de laboratorio tienen un nivel de conocimiento inferiorsobre la segregación y eliminación adecuada de los RS. En cuanto a la valoración global, se obtienen valores aceptables, y muy similares, entre las diferentes categorías de profesionales estudiadas, en relación con la gestión correcta de los RS en los centros asistenciales donde realizan su actividad laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(4): 48-52, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de los residuos sanitarios en el ámbito hospitalario. Nivel de conocimiento y valoración Global</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8673^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8673^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8673^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8673^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31974^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31974^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31974^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31974^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
