<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052799</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of children with ADHD: psychopedagogical program at school versus psychostimulant medication</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examined the impact of medication management compared to a psycho-educational program on parent and teacher ratings of children with combined type ADHD. The study lasted 14 weeks and included 50 children. 17 children took medication, 17 received psycho-educational intervention, and 16 children were assigned to the control group. The measures used were the IOWA Conners Scale, the School Problem Inventory, the Abbreviated Conners, and the DSM-IV Inattention-Disorganization and Hyperactivity-Impulsivity rating scales. Regarding teacher ratings, improvements were observed on: a) inattention and school problems in the medication group versus the control group; and b) hyperactivity symptoms in the psycho-pedagogical group versus the control and medication groups. Regarding to parent ratings, improvements were observed on: a)inattention in the psycho-pedagogical group versus the control and medication groups; and b) hyperactivity symptoms in the psycho-pedagogical group versus the control and the medication groups</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miranda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarque, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosel, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio comparó el impacto de la medicación versus un programa psicopedagógico en las estimaciones de los padres y profesores de niños con TDAH, subtipo combinado. El estudio duró 14 semanas y participaron 50 niños. 17 niños tomaron medicación, 17 recibieron una intervención psicopedagógica y los otros 16 conformaron el grupo de control. Se emplearon las siguientes medidas: IOWA Conners, Inventario de Problemas en la Escuela (IPE), versión abreviada del Conners y escalas de Inatención-Desorganización e Hiperactividad-Impulsividad del DSM-IV. Según las estimaciones de los profesores, se observaron mejoras en: a) inatención y problemas escolares en el grupo de medicación versus el grupo control; y b)hiperactividad en el grupo de intervención psicopedagógica versus el grupo control y el de medicación. Según las estimaciones de los padres, se observaron mejoras en: a) inatención en el grupo de intervención psicopedagógica versus el grupo control y el grupo de medicación; y b) hiperactividad en el grupo de intervención psicopedagógica versus el grupo control y el grupo de medicación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 335-341, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento para niños con TDAH: programa psicopedagógico en la escuela frente medicación psicoestimulante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7129^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
