<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142693</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and use of IT in medical lifelong learning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Information technologies (IT) have contributed to scientific and social development and play an essential role in teaching and in continuing medical education (CME). Although IT have been used, they have a number of limitations that should be known and corrected to improve implementation. The aim of this study was to know the degree of knowledge and application of IT in CME, and the advantages and disadvantages that doctors see on them. Subjects and methods. A questionnaire hosted on the Internet website of the Signo Foundation was used and an email was sent to request information from doctors about IT in CME. Statistical analysis of the results was performed. Results. Information was obtained from 661 individuals, 56.7% of whom were male. The average age was 48.9 years, 30.6% was living in the province of Toledo and 60% were on clinical work. Most (76%) have experience in CME, both as students (54%) and as teachers (19%). The inclusion of multimedia materials (86.1%), good organization of the course (76.1%) and usability (74%) are the most valued aspects of IT. The need of student effort and consistency (59%), language other than Spanish (39.6%), the difficulty in assessing learning (35.5%) and limited interaction between students and teachers (23.6%) were the greatest difficulties reported. Twitter and Facebook were not frequently used. Conclusions. This experienced group in the use of IT in CME acknowledges clear advantages of these techniques, but also pointed out some disadvantages which should be solved to improve implementation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cacheiro-González, María Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Padial, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina-Rivilla, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las tecnologías de la información y de la comunicación (TIC) han contribuido al desarrollo científico y social y deben desempeñar un papel esencial en la docencia y en la formación médica continuada (FMC). Aunque se han utilizado las TIC, presentan una serie de limitaciones que deben conocerse y corregirse para conseguir una mayor implantación de éstas. Por ello, se pretende conocer la experiencia y opinión que los médicos tienen sobre el uso de las TIC en la FMC. Sujetos y métodos. Se ha utilizado un cuestionario por Internet alojado en la web de la Fundación Signo y se ha remitido un correo electrónico para recabar información de los médicos sobre las TIC. Se realiza análisis estadístico de los resultados. Resultados. Se ha obtenido información de 661 profesionales del área de la salud, el 56,7% de los cuales son varones. La edad media es de 48,9 años. El 30,6% es de la provincia de Toledo y el 60% realiza labor asistencial. La mayoría (76%) tiene experiencia en la FMC, como alumnos (54%) y como de docentes (19%). La inclusión de materiales multimedia (86,1%), la buena organización de las actividades (76,1%) y la facilidad de uso (74%) son los aspectos mejor valorados. La necesidad de constancia por parte del alumno (59%), el idioma (39,6%), la dificultad para evaluar el aprovechamiento (35,5%) y para la interacción adecuada entre alumno y profesor (23,6%) son las mayores dificultades. Se observa un escaso conocimiento de herramientas que podrían ser útiles, como Twitter y Facebook. Conclusiones. Este colectivo tiene experiencia en el uso de las TIC en la FMC y valora claras ventajas, aunque señala inconvenientes que deben mejorarse para alcanzar un mayor uso de dichas tecnologías en la FMC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(4): 283-291, jul.-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142693</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento y uso de las tecnologías de la información y de la comunicación en la formación médica continuada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
