<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134641</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Visual screening (part 2)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper the recommendations of PrevInfad on visual screening in children are reviewed. The health benefits of early detection, and the validity and safety of the screening tests are analysed as well as treatment effectivity and the potential risks of early diagnosis and treatment of the detected problems. PrevInfad recommends including eye inspection and red reflex test in the health visits of the first 6 month of life, as well as the detection of visual impairments (amblyopia, strabismus and refraction errors) at 3-5 years of age. Evidence to assess the balance between risks and benefits of reduced visual acuity screening in children 6 to 14 years old is insufficient. Due to its extent, the text has been divided into two parts. We present in this paper the second part (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colomer Revuelta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano Faura, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ruiz-Cabello, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Rico, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Aguado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual Gil, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galbe Sánchez-Ventura, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza Olcina, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Moína, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallás Alonso, C. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se revisan y actualizan las recomendaciones de PrevInfad sobre el cribado de alteraciones visuales en la infancia. Se analizan los beneficios en salud de la detección precoz, la validez y seguridad de las pruebas de cribado, la efectividad del tratamiento y los posibles riesgos de la detección precoz y el tratamiento de los problemas detectados. PrevInfad recomienda incluir la inspección ocular y la prueba del reflejo rojo en las visitas de salud de los primeros seis meses de vida, así como la detección de alteraciones visuales (ambliopía, estrabismo y errores de refracción) a la edad de 3-5 años. La evidencia para evaluar el balance entre los beneficios y los riesgos del cribado de la disminución de la agudeza visual por errores de refracción en niños de 6 a 14 años es insuficiente. Debido a su extensión, el texto se ha divido en dos partes, siendo esta la segunda de ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;17(65): e57-e67, ene.-mar. 2015. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134641</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado de alteraciones visuales (parte 2)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12452^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12453^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
