<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051977</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Should hydration and artificial nutrition be accepted as a palliative care?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Ethical considerations are becoming more and more common in clinical practice. There is no unanimous agreement on which measures should be deemed as basic care, specially regarding hydration and artificial nutrition. Aim: To know the opinion of lay people and health professionals, stratified according to their university degree, about which palliative measures, including hydration and artificial nutrition, should be judged as palliative care. Methods: A descriptive transversal study has been designed to know the opinion of 256 subjects: 91 users of the National Health System (NHS), 80 nurses, 47 pharmacists and 38 physicians. A questionnaire examined which of the following measures should be considered as palliative care: hygiene, analgesia, pressure ulcer care, position change, sedation, oxygen administration, urinary catheter, hydration, enteral and parenteral nutrition. Results: More than 50% of the participants think that all the proposed measures can be considered as a palliative care, except parenteral nutrition. There is unanimous agreement to accept analgesia, pressure ulcer care, position change and enteraL nutrition as basic care, but there is disagreement in relation to hygiene (p = 0.000),sedation (p = 0.005), oxygen administration (p = 0.007), urinary catheter (p = 0.011) and parenteral nutrition (p = 0.000). There were not differences of opinion after adjusting for age, sex, religious beliefs, and length of professional experience among the individuals that answered the questionnaire. Conclusion: There is no agreement on which measures should be considered as palliative care. Opinions differ regarding hygiene, sedation, oxygen administration, urinary catheterisation and parenteral nutrition. In comparison to enteral nutrition, many responders believe that parenteral nutrition is a therapeutic option. The opinions shown in this questionnaire were independent from the demographic characteristics of the subjects that answered it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Nido, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Villares, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Zanuy, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Cada vez son más frecuentes los dilemas éticos en la práctica clínica. No existe acuerdo unánime, en especial en lo relativo a la hidratación y nutrición artificial, sobre que medida debe ser considerada como un cuidado básico. Objetivo: Conocer la opinión del personal sanitario, diferenciando la titulación universitaria, sobre que medidas de cuidado paliativo, incluyendo la hidratación y la nutrición artificial, deben ser consideradas como cuidado paliativo. Material y metodos: Se ha diseñado un estudio de campo descriptivo transversal, en el que se analiza la opinión de 256 individuos mediante las respuestas a un cuestionario: 91 usuarios del Sistema Nacional de Salud, 80 enfermeras, 38 médicos y 47 farmacéuticos sobre qué medida de las siguientes debe ser considerada como cuidado paliativo: higiene, analgesia, cuidado de las escaras, cambios posturales, sedación, oxigenoterapia, sondaje urinario, hidratación intravenosa, nutrición enteral y nutrición parenteral. Resultados: Más del 50% de los encuestados valora todas las medidas interrogadas como paliativas, a excepción de la nutrición parenteral. Entre los diversos grupos no existen diferencias en considerar a la analgesia, cuidado de escaras, cambios posturales, sueroterapia y administración de nutrición enteral como un cuidado básico, pero sí existen diferencias de opinión sobre la higiene (p = 0,000), sedación (p = 0,005), oxigenoterapia (p = 0,007), sondaje urinario (p = 0,011) y nutrición parenteral (p = 0,000). La edad, sexo, creencia religiosa y años de experiencia profesional en el ámbito sanitario del encuestado no influyen los resultados obtenidos. Conclusiones: No existe unanimidad entre los individuos, en qué medida debe ser considerada como cuidado paliativo. Se discrepa en relación a la higiene, la sedación, la oxigenoterapia, el sondaje urinario y la nutrición parenteral. Esta última medida se considera más como una opción terapéutica que la nutrición enteral. La opinión no depende de las características sociodemográficas de la población estudiada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(6): 680-685, nov.-dic. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se considera la hidratación y la nutrición artificial como un cuidado paliativo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32108</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
