<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139872</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of factors influencing outcome in 500 homologous intrauterine insemination cycles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the results and analyse different factors influencing pregnancy rate using homologous intrauterine insemination. Subjects and methods: Retrospective analysis of 500 homologous intrauterine insemination cycles in 183 infertile couples. Only one insemination per stimulated ovarian cycle was performed in patients with: mild endometriosis, ovulatory factor, male subfertility or unexplained infertility. We studied female age, duration of infertility, stimulation protocol, number of cycle, number of preovulatory follicles, motile sperm count and endometrial thickness related to pregnancy rate. Results: Pregnancy rate per couple was 24% and per intrauterine insemination 9%, 11% was multiple pregnancies. Best outcome has been got in women younger than 37 years (P=.048) and in cycles with more than one preovulatory follicle. Other studied factors did not have influence in homologous intrauterine insemination outcome. Conclusions: Female age is a prognostic factor for homologous intrauterine insemination with poor outcome in women older than 38 years. Cycles with more than one preovolatory follicle have better outcome. No differences in pregnancy rate have been achieved with motile sperm count over 1.5 millions/0.3 ml (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martos Cano, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Goy, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tasende Areosa, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Benjumea, Reyes de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluación de nuestros resultados y análisis de diferentes variables como determinantes de éxito en la inseminación intrauterina homóloga. Sujetos y método: Análisis retrospectivo de 500 ciclos de inseminación intrauterina realizados a 183 parejas. Se ha realizado una sola inseminación por ciclo de estimulación ovárica controlada a pacientes con endometriosis, anovulación, subfertilidad masculina o esterilidad idiopática. Las variables estudiadas incluyen edad de la mujer, tiempo de esterilidad, etiología, protocolo de estimulación, número de ciclo, número de folículos preovulatorios, recuento de espermatozoides móviles poscapacitación y grosor endometrial. Resultados: La tasa acumulada de embarazo por pareja fue del 24%, la tasa media por ciclo del 9%, con un 11% de embarazos múltiples. Se han obtenido mejores resultados en mujeres menores de 37 años (p = 0,048) y en ciclos con más de un folículo preovulatorio. No ha habido diferencias en la tasa de embarazo según el número de ciclo, el protocolo de estimulación o el recuento de espermatozoides móviles inseminados. Conclusión: La edad mayor de 38 años empeora el pronóstico de la inseminación intrauterina; los ciclos con más de un folículo preovulatorio son de mejor pronóstico. Con recuento de espermatozoides móviles inseminados superior a 1,5 millones los resultados son similares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);51(2): 68-77, feb. 2008. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los factores de influencia sobre el resultado de 500 ciclos de inseminación intrauterina homóloga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32643</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6210^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7491</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7423^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7423^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
