<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61233</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the effectiveness of cognitive interventions in preventing cognitive deterioration in healthy elderly individuals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In the last few years, several non-pharmacologicalinterventions have been developed to prevent age-associatedcognitive deterioration, specifically memory deterioration.The effectiveness of these interventions has not beensufficiently evaluated.Objective: To determine the effectiveness of cognitive interventionsin preventing age-associated memory impairment bymeans of a literature review.Methods: An exhaustive search was carried out in PubMed.Studies published from 1990 onwards that assessed the effectivenessof cognitive interventions on memory outcomesin older adults without mild cognitive impairment or dementiawere included. The studies were classified according to theirquality. The short- and long-term effects of the interventionson objective and subjective memory tasks and transfer of gainsto other cognitive domains were assessed.Results: Twenty-five studies met the inclusion criteria. Eleven(44%) were considered high-quality, of which all exceptone reported improved memory outcomes. The most commontype of memory assessed was recent verbal objective memory,which improved in eight out of nine high-quality studies. Recentnon-verbal and association objective memory, mainly assessedin medium-quality studies, improved in four out of sevenand in 10 out of 11 studies, respectively. The results concerningsubjective memory were heterogeneous. Transfer of gainswas only observed in one out of seven high-quality studies.Conclusions: The results of this study suggest that certaincognitive interventions performed in healthy older adults areeffective in preventing cognitive deterioration, especially recentverbal memory(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Novoa, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nebot, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: En los últimos años han aparecido diversasintervenciones no farmacológicas destinadas a prevenir el deteriorocognitivo asociado a la edad, concretamente los problemasde memoria, cuya efectividad no ha sido suficientementeevaluada.Objetivo: Establecer la efectividad de las intervenciones cognitivasen la prevención del deterioro de la memoria asociadoa la edad mediante una revisión de la literatura científica.Métodos: Se realizó una búsqueda exhaustiva en PubMed.Se incluyeron los estudios publicados desde 1990 que evaluaranla efectividad de una intervención cognitiva sobre la memoriaen personas mayores sin deterioro cognitivo leve ni demencia,y se clasificaron según su calidad. Se evaluaron losefectos, a corto y a largo plazo, sobre el rendimiento en tareasde memoria objetiva y subjetiva y la transferencia a otrosdominios cognitivos.Resultados: Veinticinco estudios cumplieron los criterios deinclusión. Once (44%) fueron considerados de elevada calidad,de los cuales todos excepto uno mejoraron algún indicadorde memoria. El tipo de memoria más evaluada fue lamemoria objetiva reciente verbal, que mejoró en 8 de 9 de losestudios de elevada calidad. La memoria objetiva reciente noverbal y de asociación, evaluadas principalmente por los estudiosde calidad media, mejoraron en 4 de 7, y en 10 de 11estudios, respectivamente. Los resultados referentes a memoriasubjetiva fueron muy heterogéneos. La transferencia únicamentese observó en uno de 7 estudios de elevada calidad.Conclusiones: Los resultados sugieren que determinadas intervencionescognitivas desarrolladas en personas mayoressanas son efectivas en la prevención del deterioro de la memoria,especialmente sobre la memoria reciente verbal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(5): 474-482, oct. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61233</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de las intervenciones cognitivas en la prevención del deterioro de la memoria en las personas mayores sanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14559</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
