<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96546</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial activity of [2-(methacryloyloxy)ethyl]trimethylammonium chloride against Candida spp</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Candida-associated denture stomatitis is the most common manifestation of oral candidal infection, caused mainly by Candida albicans. Several authors have attempted to add antifungal agents or antiseptics to denture temporary soft lining materials or to denture acrylic resins, without relevant results. Therefore, the investigation of a quaternary ammonium functionalized compound [2-(methacryloyloxy)ethyl]trimethylammonium chloride (MADQUAT), which copolymerizes with methacrylates and which could act as a fungal inhibitor, is of paramount importance. Aims. To evaluate the in vitro activity of MADQUAT against Candida species. Methods. Thirty-one Candida strains were used to determine the in vitro antifungal activity of this compound. The minimum inhibitory concentrations and minimum fungicidal concentrations of MADQUAT and nystatin were determined. Results. MADQUAT showed antifungal properties at concentrations of 6.25 to &gt; 100mg/ml, and fungicidal activity between 25 and &gt; 100mg/ml. The quantitative determinations of the fungistatic and fungicidal activity of MADQUAT showed fungistatic activity against all Candida albicans, Candida krusei and Candida parapsilosis strains, revealing fungicidal activity against some strains of the other species. Conclusions. MADQUAT has antifungal activity against Candida spp. Moreover, the sensitivity to this substance varies across the different species in terms of MIC values and fungicidal or fungistatic activity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piva, Evandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scroferneker, Maria Lúcia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Werner Samuel, Susana Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ottonelli Stopiglia, Cheila Denise</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aulo Ogliari, Fabrício</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges Fortes, Carmen Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mezzomo Collares, Fabrício</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La estomatitis protética es la forma más común de infección bucal producida por especies de Candida, siendo Candida albicans el agente etiológico más común. Diversos autores han intentado asociar agentes antifúngicos o antisépticos a los materiales de revestimiento blando o a las resinas acrílicas de las prótesis dentales, pero sin éxito. Por ello, se ha investigado un compuesto de amonio cuaternario (2-metacriloil oxietil trimetilamonio [MADQUAT]), que copolimeriza con los metacrilatos y que podría actuar como inhibidor de levaduras. Objetivos. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la actividad in vitro del MADQUAT contra especies de Candida. Métodos. Se utilizaron 31 cepas de Candida para determinar la actividad antifúngica in vitro. Se determinó la concentración mínima inhibitoria (CMI) y la concentración mínima fungicida del MADQUAT, así como de la nistatina. Resultados. El MADQUAT presentó propiedades antifúngicas en las concentraciones entre 6,25 y &gt; 100mg/ml y actividad fungicida entre 25 y &gt; 100mg/ml. Los estudios cuantitativos de la actividad fungistática y fungicida del MADQUAT demostraron actividad fungistática contra todas las cepas de Candida albicans, Candida krusei y Candida parapsilosis, revelando actividad fungicida contra algunas cepas de otras especies. Conclusiones. El MADQUAT presenta actividad antifúngica contra Candida spp. Además, la sensibilidad a dicho compuesto es distinta entre las diferentes especies considerando los valores de la CMI y la actividad fungicida o fungistática(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;29(1): 20-23, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antimicrobiana del cloruro de 2-metacriloil oxietil trimetilamonio contra Candida sp</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2634^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28213^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28213^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50533^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
