<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91141</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morbid obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Morbid obesity (MO) is a serious disease caused by genetic and environmental factors, which is associated with multiple comorbid factors that impact very significantly on the amount and life quality.  Obesity surgery is a complex surgery, but not without complications, which objective is to achieve an ideal weight or cure obesity, reducing comorbidities and improving the welfare of patients. The Spanish Society for the Study of Obesity (SEED) and the Spanish Society of Obesity Surgery (SECO) have developed a consensus document that allows the various professionals involved in the treatment of OM practical guidance in developing their own protocols in their work environment. In this context, the general and digestive service of the HUB team developed the clinical course of this surgical procedure because it is a tool that facilitates systematic care and multidisciplinary group of patients with a predictable clinical course, such as whether morbidly obese patients operated by laparotomy or laparoscopy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio Martín, M. J. Del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>La Puerta Alcalde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo Chamizo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cartañá Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masó Serra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad mórbida (OM) es una enfermedad grave, causada por diversos factores genéticos y ambientales, que se asocia a múltiples elementos de comorbilidad que repercuten de forma muy importante en la cantidad y calidad de vida. La cirugía de la obesidad es compleja, no exenta de complicaciones, cuyo objetivo no es alcanzar un peso ideal ni curar la obesidad, sino reducir significativamente las comorbilidades asociadas y mejorar el bienestar de los pacientes. En este contexto, La Sociedad Española para el Estudio de la Obesidad (SEEDO) y la Sociedad Española de Cirugía de la Obesidad (SECO) han elaborado un documento de consenso que proporciona a los distintos profesionales implicados en el tratamiento de la OM una orientación práctica a la hora de desarrollar sus propios protocolo en su ámbito de trabajo. Siguiendo las recomendaciones de la SECO, el equipo de Cirugía General del Servicio del Aparato Digestivo del Hospital Universitario de Bellvitge (HUB) elaboró la trayectoria clínica de este proceso quirúrgico, ya que constituye una herramienta que facilita la atención sistemática y multidisciplinar de grupos de pacientes que presentan un curso clínico predecible, como son los pacientes obesos mórbidos ya sean intervenidos por laparotomía o bien mediante laparoscopia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(10): 664-668, oct. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad mórbida. Guía para elaborar una trayectoria clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
