<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121274</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric Neurology and rare diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last three decades, The Pediatric Neurology Sevice at Vall d´Hebron University Hospital in Barcelona has been a pioneer in the country in developing a modern approach to the care of the severe neurological disorders of the developing nervous system. In the setting of a tertiary care enter, a multidisciplinar attentionto the patient, the fostering of clinical and applied research and the excellence in postgraduate training have been prioritized. This is reflected in the foudation of a laboratory research group and a Master programme in Pediatric Neurology. In the present review the Service achievements are illustrated through a brief accout of the contributions made in the field of rare disorders. Among a large number of publications, we emphasize the description and characterization of at least three novel syndromes, a progressive vacuolating glycine leukoencephalopathy with pulmonary hypertension, congenital brainstem dysgenesis and a distinct epileptic encephalopathy phenotype, as well as a rather productive research in genetics of migraine and other paroxysmal disorders and in the pathophysiology of muscle necrosis and regeneration associated to dystrophin deficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roig Quils, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall Chaure, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munell Casadesús, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro Riera, M del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boronat Guerrero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Servicio de Neurología Pediátrica del Hospital Universitario Vall d´Hebrond e Barcelona, en sus 30 años de historia, ha sido pionero en el desarrollo de asitencia e investigación en enfermedades neurológicas graves que afectan als istema nervioso en desarrollo. Sobre la base de un enfoque propio del hospital terciario, ha dadoprioridad a la interdisciplinariedad en la asistencia y a la potenciación de investigación y docencia a través de la creción de un grupo propio de investigación y un progrma de máster en Neurología Pediátrica. La presente revisión ilustra la trayectoria del servicio a tráves de sus contribuciones en el campo de las enfermedades minoritarias. Entre la extensa bibliografía del grupo, destaca la descripción o caracterización de al menos tres nuevos síndromes neurológicos pediátricos, la leuconcefalopatía maligna con hiperglicinemia e hipertensión pulmonar, el síndorme de disgenesia congénita trocoencefálica y una nueva variante de encefalopatía epiléptica, así como la productiva investigación en neurogenética de la migraña y otros trastornos paroxísticos y en la fisiopatología de la necrosis-regeneración muscular asociada al déficit de distrofina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;69(6): 345-352, nov.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Neurología Pediátrica y las enfermedades minoritarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28916^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2869^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53513^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
