<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138780</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update in statins. New clinical recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In November 2013, the American College of Cardiology and the American Heart Association (ACC/AHA) released a new clinical practice guideline for the treatment of blood cholesterol in people at high risk for cardiovascular disease. The guideline identifies: 1) 4 major groups of patients for whom statins should be prescribed to reduce the chance of stroke and heart attacks, 2) elimination of routine assessments of LDL cholesterol levels in patients receiving statin therapy, because target levels are no longer emphasized, and 3) avoidance of non-statin LDL cholesterol-lowering agents in statin-tolerant patients. This update represents the first major guideline revision since the released of the Adult Treatment Panel III report in 2002, which has been a subject of controversy. The main concerns focused on problems with the risk calculation, ethics (conflicts of interest), and inferences (too many people offered treatment). The guideline also emphasizes the importance of adopting a heart-healthy lifestyle to control high blood cholesterol, and create an opportunity to advance patient-centered care and share decision making. The new guideline gives the clinicians the tool to engage in discussing with individual patients about the potential benefits and potential harms of statin use to prevent future cardiovascular events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Alonso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Espada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Palomino, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">The American College of Cardiology y la American Heart Association (ACC/AHA) publicaron hace unos meses (noviembre 2013) una nueva guía de práctica clínica para el tratamiento de la hipercolesterolemia en pacientes del alto riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular. En ella se propone: 1) 4 nuevos grupos de pacientes a los que se les debe prescribir tratamiento con estatinas para reducir la tasa de eventos vasculares, 2) abandonar el objetivo de medir los niveles de LDLc y 3) recetar estatinas a dosis moderadas y altas, excluyendo otros tratamientos hipolipidemiantes (niacinas, fibratos, etc.). Esta actualización representa un cambio sustancial en la práctica clínica habitual de los últimos 30 años y ello ha generado una importante controversia por varios aspectos: 1) por la utilización de una nueva calculadora del riesgo cardiovascular no suficientemente validada, 2) porque esto puede hacer que aumente sustancialmente la población mundial potencialmente tratable y 3) porque ello se deba a un oculto conflicto de intereses económicos. En esta guía se sigue prestando un especial interés a la modificación de los hábitos de vida de los pacientes como medida de tratamiento junto con la prescripción de estatinas. Y como novedad se le otorga al paciente un papel relevante a la hora de decidir, junto con el médico, los beneficios y los riesgos de asumir el tratamiento para la prevención de futuros eventos cardiovasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;67(4): 304-311, jul.-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138780</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Puesta al día en estatinas. Nuevas recomendaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53818</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
