<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155653</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of stein´s anthropology to personalistic bioethics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dr. Juan Manuel Burgos proposes 'a challenge' to whom aims to consolidate the dignity of the human person as the center of a thought structure. Burgos presents a well-founded trilogy, citing Wojtyla, Sgreccia and he himself, as a perfect combination to support personalist bioethics. However, the possibility of giving a solid anthropological support to this bioethics remains open provided that a substantial list of personalistic authors is revised. This research seeks to collate Stein&#146;s anthropological proposal to personalist bioethics needs expressed by Burgos. The study aims to prove how Stein&#146;s anthropology can be assembled to the characteristics of personalism, and thus infer that more specific levels of the personalist bioethics can be based on this anthropology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles Morejon, Jeannette Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hemos denominado 'un reto' al que el Dr. Juan Manuel Burgos propone a quienes aspiramos a consolidar la dignidad de la persona humana como el centro de una estructura de pensamiento. Si bien es cierto que este autor plantea una trilogía de pensamiento bien fundamentada: Wojtyla, Sgreccia y el mismo Burgos como una conjunción perfecta que dote de sustento fundante a la bioética personalista, sin embargo, deja abierta la opción para que, a partir de una lista sustanciosa de autores personalistas, se pueda dar a esta bioética una fundamentación antropológica consistente. Se pretende cotejar la propuesta antropológica steiniana con las necesidades de fundamentación de la bioética personalista expresadas por Burgos. Comprobar cómo ésta ensambla con las características planteadas del personalismo y, colegir que la antropología de E. Stein puede fundamentar desde la metabioética a la bioética personalista en niveles más específicos del ejercicio práctico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(90): 195-205, mayo-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones de la antropología steiniana a la bioética personalista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36364</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
