<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166090</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequent episodic migraine and calcitonin gene-related peptide. Influence of treatment with topiramate and zonisamide on levels of the peptide</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The pathophysiology of pain in migraine is related to the activation of the trigeminovascular system by releasing vasoactive neuropeptides, the most important of which is calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP), which causes a neurogenic inflammation in the leptomeningeal vessels. Aim. To study whether CGRP is increased in frequent episodic migraine and whether preventive treatment with topiramate or zonisamide modifies its levels. Subjects and methods. We studied 28 patients with episodic migraine with or without aura, in accordance with the International Headache Society criteria, with a frequency of 4-14 days/month. Plasma levels of CGRP were determined in all the patients during an interictal period (&gt; 72 hours without pain). Patients were divided at random into two treatment groups, one with 50 mg/day of topiramate and the other with 50 mg/day of zonisamide, for three months. At the end of the active period the CGRP level was analysed again. The control group consisted of nine healthy subjects. Results. CGRP was significantly higher in the episodic migraine group than in the control group (50.61 ± 22.5 pg/mL versus 34.96 ± 17.03 pg/mL; p = 0.037). After treatment with neuromodulators no significant differences were found in the level of CGRP (46.11 ± 24.2 pg/mL basal versus 47.5 ± 24.88 pg/mL post-treatment). Neither were any differences found on analysing the topiramate and zonisamide groups individually. Conclusions. The plasma level of CGRP is increased in episodic migraine, and its levels are not modified by treatment with low doses of topiramate or zonisamide (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Parrado, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Estévez, Daniel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silvarrey-Rodríguez, Saúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La fisiopatología del dolor en la migraña se relaciona con la activación del sistema trigeminovascular por medio de la liberación de neuropéptidos vasoactivos, y el más importante es el péptido relacionado con el gen de la calcitonina (CGRP), que causa una inflamación neurógena en los vasos leptomeníngeos. Objetivo. Investigar si el CGRP está incrementado en la migraña episódica frecuente y si el tratamiento preventivo con topiramato o zonisamida modifica sus niveles. Sujetos y métodos. Se estudiaron 28 pacientes con migraña episódica con o sin aura, cumpliendo los criterios de la Sociedad Internacional de Cefaleas, con una frecuencia de 4-14 días/mes. En todos los pacientes se determinaron los niveles plasmáticos del CGRP durante un período intercrítico (&gt; 72 h sin dolor). Los pacientes se aleatorizaron en dos grupos de tratamiento, uno con 50 mg/día de topiramato y otro con 50 mg/día de zonisamida, durante tres meses. Al finalizar el período activo se analizó nuevamente el nivel del CGRP. El grupo control lo constituyeron nueve sujetos sanos. Resultados. El CGRP fue significativamente superior en el grupo de migraña episódica comparado con el grupo control (50,61 ± 22,5 pg/mL frente a 34,96 ± 17,03 pg/mL; p = 0,037). Después del tratamiento con neuromoduladores no se hallaron diferencias significativas en el nivel de CGRP (46,11 ± 24,2 pg/mL basal frente a 47,5 ± 24,88 pg/mL postratamiento). Tampoco se hallaron diferencias al analizar los grupos de topiramato y zonisamida de forma individualizada. Conclusiones. El nivel plasmático del CGRP está incrementado en la migraña episódica y sus niveles no son modificados por el tratamiento con dosis bajas de topiramato o zonisamida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(4): 153-156, 16 ago., 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Migraña episódica frecuente y péptido relacionado con el gen de la calcitonina. Influencia del tratamiento con topiramato y zonisamida en los niveles del péptido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24549^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
