<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041148</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aftermath of dietary educational intervention in patients with obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Foundations: In the present work there areexposed the conclusions obtained of a longitudinalstudy with intervention, analyzing the resultsin the treatment of the obesity, by meansof education and follow-up every 1-2 weeks inconsultation of private external nutrition of thehospitable area.Methods: For three years they have treateda whole of 249 patients, all of them older than16. These patients were receiving food educationand they an individualized follow-up was realizedevery 1-2 weeks.Results and conclusion: In the moment ofcut they were still under study 18.07% of the patients, had finished the treatment obtainingthe goals marked (reduction of the weight at leastof 10%) 72.28%, 19.67% had left the followup.Also has wanted to see the possible relationbetween the beginning of the treatment and thetrimester of the year that begins the above mentionedprogram, being the second trimester(36.54%) more demanding to begin the abovementioned program.Besides we have stated that the majority ofthe patients are women (80.33%) of which86.70% already previously had tried to loseweight. We think that the program to treat theobesity must be based on the reeducation onthe way of eating of the patient, providing a foodeducation that contains the knowledges necessaryto be able to realize a balanced and healthynourishment more that imposing diets.The follow-up must be periodic, individualizedand frequent, reinforcing this way the adherenceto the program and the obtaining of the royal(real) marked and agreed results</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cerrillo, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Moraleda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caracuel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En el presente trabajo se exponenlas conclusiones obtenidas de un estudiolongitudinal con intervención, analizando los resultadosen el tratamiento de la obesidad, medianteeducación y seguimiento cada 1-2 semanasen consulta de nutrición privada externa delámbito hospitalario.Métodos: Durante tres años se han tratado aun total de 249 pacientes, todos ellos mayoresde 16 años. Estos pacientes recibían educaciónalimentaria y se les realizaba un seguimientoindividualizado cada 1-2 semanas.Resultados y conclusión: En el momentode corte continuaban en consulta el 18.07% delos pacientes, habían finalizado el tratamientoconsiguiendo el objetivo marcado (reduccióndel peso al menos del 10%) el 72.28%, el19.67% había abandonado el seguimiento.También se ha querido ver la posible relaciónentre el inicio del tratamiento y el trimestre delaño que se comienza dicho programa, siendo elsegundo trimestre (36.54%) el más demandandopara comenzar dicho programa.Además hemos constatado que la mayoríade los pacientes son mujeres (80.33%) de lascuáles el 86.70% ya con anterioridad había intentadoperder peso. Pensamos que el programapara tratar la obesidad debe basarse en lareeducación en la forma de comer del paciente,proporcionando una educación alimentaria quecontenga los conocimientos necesarios parapoder realizar una alimentación equilibrada ysaludable más que imponiendo dietas. El seguimientodebe ser periódico, individualizado y frecuente,reforzando así la adherencia al programay la obtención de los resultados reales marcadosy pactados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;25(4): 143-149, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la intervención dietético-educativa en pacientes con obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
