<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153993</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Modeling a clinical process for differentiated thyroid cancer health care in Hospital Base Valdivia, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To design a clinical process model in the management of differentiated thyroid cancer in order to improve accessibility to this treatment. Material and methods. Based on modified Participatory Action Research, a model design process was conducted using a literature review and meetings with organisations committed to the redesigning process, and to agree an improved and feasible process. Results. The process map was constructed by participatory action including, characterisation of the value chain, fault detection in the flow of the process, relevant documents and process for proposing modifications and approvals necessary for this purpose. Links were established between the main process and the support and strategic processes. The participatory model helped to cut the waiting times for diagnosis and treatment of this disease from 12 to 4 months. Conclusions. For each unit to be able to fully visualise the map of the process and understand their contribution as a set of integrated contributions and not fragmented, helps in the comprehensive management of patients and operation processes based on the hierarchical and dominant organisational model in Chilean hospitals. To analyse and remodel clinical processes by participatory action helps to limit failures in the fluidity of care of the patients, by presenting each participating unit with a general view of the process, the problems, and the possible solutions. Furthermore, this approach helps to clarify the process in order to make it more efficient, to harmonise relationships, and to improve coordination in order to optimise patient care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Andrade, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Manzano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila-Schwerter, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Modelizar el proceso clínico para la asistencia a pacientes con cáncer tiroideo diferenciado, con el fin de mejorar la accesibilidad a este tratamiento. Material y métodos. En función de la metodología de investigación acción participativa modificada se realizó la modelización del proceso a partir de revisión bibliográfica y de reuniones con las entidades comprometidas para el rediseño de proceso, hasta consensuar un proceso mejorado y factible. Resultados. Se modelizó participativamente el mapa del proceso, la caracterización de la cadena de valor, los fallos en la fluidez del proceso, los documentos relevantes, la propuesta de modificaciones del proceso y las autorizaciones correspondientes para mejorar el proceso. Se establecieron las vinculaciones del proceso principal con los procesos de soporte y estratégicos. La modelización participativa contribuyó a acortar los tiempos de espera entre el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de esta enfermedad de 12 a 4 meses. Conclusión. Que cada unidad pueda visibilizar completamente el mapa del proceso y entender su aporte como un conjunto de aportes integrados, y no fragmentados, ayudó al manejo integral de los pacientes y al funcionamiento institucional basado en los procesos, en un modelo organizativo jerarquizado y preponderante en los hospitales chilenos. Analizar y remodelar los procesos clínicos de manera participativa puede evitar fallos en la fluidez en la atención a los pacientes, al presentar a cada unidad participante la visión general del proceso, los problemas y las posibles soluciones. Asimismo, este enfoque puede contribuir a clarificar el proceso para hacerlo más eficiente, a armonizar las relaciones interpersonales y a mejorar la coordinación para optimizar la atención de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(4): 190-195, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelamiento del proceso clínico para manejo de usuarios con cáncer tiroideo diferenciado en el Hospital Base Valdivia, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d732^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
