<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73798</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interactions between herbal medicines and drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years there has been a significant increase on theinterest for herbal products, which are generally associatedwith safe and harmless use. However, some adverseeffects and/or drug interactions have been reported whenherbal medicines and drugs are administrated concomitantly.Clinically relevant interactions between drugs and someof the most commonly used medicinal plants in Europe(St John´s wort, ginkgo, ginseng, garlic, milk thistle, echinaceaand valerian) have been identified. Books and articleson herb-drug interactions of the selected plants weresearched on several databases from 1987-2007. Studies inhumans, including case reports, case series, clinical trialsor other types of studies were selected, as well as nonclinicalstudies with information usefull for understandingthe interactions mechanisms.The results show that these interactions are common andcan trigger serious complications, which could sometimesbe prevented by its description on labels and / or by sharingthis information with health professionals and consumers(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Geraldes Dias, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgueiro, Lígia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se ha producido un aumento significativodel interés por las plantas medicinales, que suelenser consideradas por la población como parte de una terapianatural y tradicionalmente segura, la fitoterapia. Sinembargo, se han descrito efectos adversos e interaccionesasociadas con la administración concomitante de preparadosa base de plantas medicinales con medicamentos.En el presente artículo se identifican las interacciones clínicamenterelevantes entre medicamentos y algunas delas plantas medicinales más utilizadas en Europa (hipérico,gingko, ginseng, ajo, cardo mariano, equinácea y valeriana).Para ello se ha buscado en diversas bases de datosy evaluado la información sobre interacciones publicadaen libros y artículos entre 1987 y 2007. Se seleccionaronlas notificaciones de casos, series de casos, ensayos clínicosy otros artículos con información clínica relevante,así como estudios no clínicos con la información necesariapara la comprensión de los mecanismos de interacción. Losresultados muestran que estas interacciones son comunesy pueden desencadenar graves complicaciones, que, aveces, podrían evitarse mediante un adecuado etiquetajey compartiendo esta información con profesionales de lasalud y consumidores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;9(1): 5-22, 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones entre preparados a base de plantas medicinales y medicamentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
