<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85001</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malacoplakia of the testis: a new case report and a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malakoplakia is a uncommon chronic granulomatous condition of a benign nature preferentially occurring in the genitourinary tract. Testes are affected in 12% of cases, and the first case of testicular malakoplakia was reported in 1958. Forty cases have been reported worldwide since that date. We report a new case of testicular and epididymal malakoplakia in a 68-year-old male patient diagnosed of complicated orchiepididymitis who underwent orchidectomy to rule out a malignant tumor. The histopathological study demonstrated achronic inflammatory infiltrate with histiocytes with an eosinophilic cytoplasm containing the characteristic Michaelis-Gutmann bodies diagnostic of malakoplakia. In connection with this new case and because of its unusual presentation, the literature on testicular malakoplakia is reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guarch Troyas, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián Lostal, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Parra, José D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Bandrés, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo Cárdenas, Álvaro de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ripa Saldías, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La malacoplaquia es un proceso granulomatoso crónico de naturaleza benigna, poco frecuente, que afecta de forma preferente al tracto genitourinario. El compromiso testicular representa el 12%; se ha descrito el primer caso de malacoplaquia a este nivel en 1958. Desde entonces, 40 casos se han publicado en todo el mundo. Presentamos un nuevo caso de malacoplaquia testicular y epididimaria en un varón de 68 años diagnosticado de orquiepididimitis complicada, al que se le practicó orquiectomía con el fin de descartar proceso neoformativo maligno. El estudio histológico objetivó la presencia de un infiltrado inflamatorio crónico con histiocitos de citoplasma eosinófilo, en el interior de los cuales se visualizaron los característicos cuerpos de Michaelis-Gutmann, que dieron el diagnóstico de malacoplaquia. A propósito de este nuevo caso, y por lo inusual de su presentación, realizamos una revisión de la literatura científica de la entidad que nos ocupa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(9): 1028-1031, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malacoplaquia testicular: aportación de un nuevo caso y revisión de la literatura científica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12213^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14116^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10099^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14116^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14116^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8461^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36060^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
