<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111082</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training for home care service staff and its benefits to users/patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Home care service is essential for the care and maintenance of many people in their homes. Aware of the need for qualified home care assistance to dependent persons, we have considered some important points as to check the level of training of home care aides in the province of Almería in terms of daily household support, on the one hand and on the other, to determine how these dependent people are benefited by home care service. This study aims to describe, observe and present a cross-section of a randomly selected sample of a total of 66 professionals working as home care aides (HCAs) throughout the province of Almeria. Results show that the HCAs in our sample do not meet the minimum training requirement published in the BOE. More than 84% of the sample either have not completed any course related to the job or if they have done so, they have only done below the 600 hours required. Thus, we believe that in order for the HCA to be able to provide quality home care and give real benefit to users, personnel qualification and supervision are necessary for them to adequately do their job and comply with the existing legislation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solano García, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillo Cano, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simonelli Muñoz, Agustín Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El servicio de ayuda a domicilio es básico para el mantenimiento de muchas personas en su domicilio. Debido a la existencia de unas necesidades de atención cualificada a las personas dependientes nos planteamos: por un lado, comprobar el nivel de formación de los auxiliares de ayuda a domicilio de la provincia de Almería, saber las actividades que realizan diariamente en los domicilios y, por último, determinar el beneficio en el usuario que aportan con su cuidado. Se trata de un estudio descriptivo, observacional, transversal en el que se seleccionaron a través de un muestreo aleatorio simple a un total de 66 personas que trabajaban como auxiliares de ayuda a domicilio (AAD) por toda la provincia de Almería. Los resultados muestran las AAD de nuestra muestra no cumplen los mínimos de formación que vienen reflejados en el BOE, pues más del 84% o no tienen cursos relacionados o los tienen por debajo de las 600 horas. Así, creemos que para que los AAD puedan proporcionar unos cuidados de calidad que reporten un beneficio real en los usuarios, es necesario cualificar y supervisar a dicho personal para que puedan cumplir adecuadamente su trabajo conforme a lo dispuesto en la legislación vigente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(30): 244-255, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación del personal de ayuda a domicilio y el beneficio generado en el usuario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9914^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9914^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9914^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9914^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
