<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058480</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antialdosteronic agents: Their role in heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antialdosteronic treatment is used again in heart failure. It pursues the neurohormonal blockage of the final effector of the renin-angiotensin axis. Employed agents include espironolactone and, more recently, eplerenone (which lacks the adverse effects of the former such as gynecomastia).They have beneficial effects both in advanced heart failure (NYHA class III or IV) and heart insufficiency appearing after myocardial infarction. It remains to be demonstrated if they are also effective in less advanced chronic heart insufficiency (NYHA class II) and diastolic cardiac failure, though several ongoing studies are testing this benefit. Trials with antialdosteronics have shown improvements in overall mortality, even when patients were already receiving full therapy including ACEIs and, lastly, beta-blockers. The limitation of antialdosteronics is hyperkaliemia, which occurs more frequently in the general population than in patients enrolled in clinical trials, since the former is an elderly population with greater comorbility and submitted to less controls. Therefore, antialdosteronic treatment cannot be administered in some cases (especially if there is a renal function impairment) and a careful monitoring of the serum ionnograme is mandatory</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galve, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento antialdosterónico vuelve a emplearse intensamente en la insuficiencia cardíaca (IC). Con él se quiere conseguir el bloqueo neurohormonal en el efector final del eje renina-angiotensina. Los fármacos empleados son la espironolactona y, más recientemente, la eplerenona (que carece de los efectos secundarios de la primera, como la ginecomastia). Se ha demostrado el beneficio tanto en la IC crónica avanzada (clase III o IV de la New York Heart Association [NYHA]) como en la IC que ocurre tras un infarto de miocardio. Aún hay que demostrar si también son eficaces en la IC crónica menos avanzada (clase II de la NYHA) y en la IC diastólica, pero ya hay estudios en marcha en estos escenarios. Los ensayos con antialdosterónicos han obtenido mejorías en el parámetro más exigente ­la mortalidad global­, a pesar de que los pacientes ya estaban recibiendo tratamiento máximo, incluso inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina (IECA), y últimamente también bloqueadores beta. Los antialdosterónicos tienen el inconveniente de que inducen hiperpotasemia, lo que ocurre mucho más frecuentemente en la población general que en la de los ensayos clínicos, ya que aquélla es una población de edad más avanzada, con mayor comorbilidad y en la que hay menos controles. Por tanto, el tratamiento antialdosterónico no puede administrarse en ciertas circunstancias (especialmente si hay deterioro de la función renal) y requiere de un seguimiento atento del ionograma</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);130(1): 30-34, ene. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fármacos antialdosterónicos: su papel en la insuficiencia cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7128^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13531^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
