<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83491</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current clinical practice guidelines in type 2 diabetes: how should they be applied in primary care?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical practice guidelines should be drawn up with systematic methodology based on the best available evidence. Recommendations should be based on evaluation of the overall quality of the evidence and grading of the strength of recommendations. Consensus documents combine a review of the evidence with expert opinion in an attempt to reach some agreement in areas of uncertainty due to the lack of conclusive proof. The debate aroused by new treatments stimulates the production of documents advocating their use even when there are few long-term studies on their safety and efficacy.There are several methodologically rigorous international guidelines on diabetes (NGC, NICE, SIGN, CAD, ADA). The most recent debate has centered on the ADA-EASD treatment algorithm. In Spain, the production of clinical practice guidelines with analysis of the evidence and grading of recommendations remains scarce, although the most recent published guidelines show greater rigor. More common is the drafting of consensus documents by scientific societies with the aim of combining external evidence with experience and reflection. In Spain there are also organisms (such as GuíaSalud or Fisterra) that facilitate free access to guidelines drawn up by Spanish groups(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Adam, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá Munuera, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Pérez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Beltrán, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las guías de práctica clínica deben elaborarse con una metodología sistemática basada en la mejor evidencia disponible. La elaboración de las recomendaciones debe comprender la evaluación de la calidad global de la evidencia y la graduación de la fuerza de las recomendaciones. Asimismo, hay documentos de consenso que combinan la revisión de evidencias con la opinión de expertos buscando obtener algún acuerdo en áreas de incertidumbre por ausencia de pruebas concluyentes. El debate que suscitan los nuevos tratamientos propicia la aparición de documentos en los que se recomienden sus usos, aun cuando haya pocos estudios a largo plazo acerca de su eficacia y seguridad.En el ámbito internacional hay guías sobre diabetes metodológicamente muy bien elaboradas (NGC, NICE, SIGN, CAD, ADA), centrándose el debate más reciente en el algoritmo terapéutico, tras la propuesta conjunta de la ADA-EASD. En España, la elaboración de guías de práctica clínica con análisis de la evidencia y graduación de las recomendaciones aún es escasa, si bien se aprecia un esfuerzo en el rigor de las publicadas más recientemente. Más común es la elaboración por sociedades científicas de documentos de consenso, que pretenden combinar la evidencia externa con la experiencia y la reflexión. Asimismo, en nuestro país hay organismos recopiladores (como GuíaSalud o Fisterra) que facilitan el acceso gratuito a guías elaboradas por grupos nacionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(supl.1): 9-15, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías actuales de práctica clínica en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2: ¿cómo aplicarlas en atención primaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
