<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055702</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cocygeal transdiscal approach of ganglion impar for the treatment of coccygodynia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive To test the efficacy and safety of the Walter ganglion blockade trough coccygeal disc, in patients who suffered from coccygodynia. Patients and Methods We evaluated six patients, 4 women (66,6%) and two men (33,4%), with chronic coccyx pain (&gt;6 months), and more than 6 points in Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). We described the trans-coccygeal disc approach to Walter ganglion blockade technique. The improvement of pain score, degree of satisfaction and complications of the patients were evaluated. Results Five patients improved VAS score 6 to 1. All the patients were satisfied with the treatment. We had no complications. Conclusions The trans-discal approach of the Walter ganglion is easy, safe (with less risk of rectal perforation and bone traumatism than the classical ano-coccygeal ligament via), and effective for chronic coccygodynia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meseguer, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Navarro, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Valorar la eficacia y seguridad del abordaje transdiscal coccígeo para el bloqueo con anestésicos locales y corticoides del ganglio de Walter en la coccigodinia. Pacientes y Método Estudiamos prospectivamente 6 pacientes, 4 mujeres (66´6%) y 2 hombres ( 33,4%) , con coccigodinia de más de 6 meses de duración, de origen benigno y puntuación media 6 en la escala analógica visual (EVA). Se llevó a cabo el abordaje del ganglio de Walter para su bloqueo (con anestésicos locales y corticoides) por vía transdiscal coccígea en quirófano. Se evaluó la eficacia analgésica, el grado de satisfacción y las complicaciones. Resultados Cinco de los seis pacientes, fueron dados de alta sin dolor (EVA&lt;1). El total de la muestra manifestó estar satisfecho con el tratamiento. Tras cuatro meses de seguimiento, no registramos complicaciones. Conclusiones El abordaje transdiscal del ganglio de Walter es sencillo,  seguro (con menos riesgo de perforación del recto y de inyección peri-ósea de la solución, que la vía clásica utilizada  para su bloqueo) y eficaz en el tratamiento de la coccigodinia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;14(2): 113-116, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje del ganglio de Walter por vía transdiscal coccígea en coccigodina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12821^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5871^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d790^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7179^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
