<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84270</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Applications of the heart rate maximum on the evaluation and prescription of exercise</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to show the possible applications of the heart rate maximum (HRmax) on training and clinical environment, as well as to identify the use of different equations to estimate the HRmax. The training provides information for the prescription of exercise, state of over-training and to calculate the daily energy expenditure. Moreover, when performed in the clinical environment they can help interpret sub-maximal tests as maximal ones. In some situations mathematical equations are used for calculating the HRmax. Thus, of more than fifty (50) equations were available in the specialised literature, some only have age as a factor, while others include, age, state of health and anthropometric parameters. However, to obtain more accuracy when choosing any equation to estimate the HRmax, one must have all the data and choose the one that best suits the objectives of evaluation or exercise prescription(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ottoline Marins, Nádia Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Fernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouzas Marins, João C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es presentar posibles aplicaciones de la frecuencia cardiaca máxima (FCM) en el entrenamiento y ambiente clínico así como identificar las ecuaciones que estiman la FCM. En el entrenamiento proporciona informaciones para la prescripción del ejercicio, el estado de sobreentrenamiento y el cálculo del gasto diario energético. En el ambiente clínico ayuda en la realización e interpretación de pruebas submaximales y maximales. En determinadas situaciones se utilizan ecuaciones matemáticas para el cálculo de la FCM. En la literatura médica especializada existen más de cincuenta ecuaciones disponibles, en las cuales solo se tiene en cuenta el factor edad o se incluyen otros factores tales como sexo, condición de salud o parámetros antropométricos. Por todo ello, para tener mayor exactitud a la hora de elegir una ecuación estimativa de la FCM es necesario conocer las existentes y optar por aquella que se adapta mejor a los objetivos de evaluación o prescripción de ejercicio(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);45(168): 251-258, oct.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicaciones de la frecuencia cardiaca máxima en la evaluación y prescripción de ejercicio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
