<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136152</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cold preservation and chronic rejection, development of a rat hind limb transplantation model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Composite tissue allotransplantation has become a clinical reality nowadays, with more than 150 transplants performed in the last 15 years. Chronic allograft vasculopathy has been detected in 3 cases of composite tissue allotransplantation, being responsible of late graft failure. Decreased vascular lumina caused by intimal hyperplasia and constrictive remodeling of the adventitia, are the main histological features of this entity. Immune and not immune factors are related with the development of the vasculopathy, being cold damage between the later. We present the development of an experimental model of chronic allograft vasculopathy in a model of rat hind limb allotransplantation after 7 hours of cold ischemia at 4ºC, between Lewis Brown-Norway rats as donors and Wistar-Lewis rats as receptors. All animals were under low dose immunosuppression with cyclosporine A and were sacrificed 2 months post transplantation. The characteristic changes of chronic vasculopathy were found in the middle muscular and distal thirds at the histological analysis. Statistically differences were found when comparing the number of pathological small and medium size vessels of the middle and distal muscular thirds (P = 0,007 and 0,004 respectively). The present study establishes a reproducible experimental model of chronic allograft vasculopathy in composite tissue allotransplantation. We have verified the association of cold ischemia preservation and chronic vasculopathy at different vascular segments of the rat hind limb (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonastre Juliá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landín Jarillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trasplantes de tejidos compuestos son una realidad clínica con más de 150 casos realizados con éxito en los últimos 15 años. La vasculopatía crónica del aloinjerto es una causa de pérdida tardía del órgano observada en 3 trasplantes de tejidos compuestos. Histológicamente se caracteriza por estenosis de la luz vascular causada por hiperplasia de la íntima y fibrosis cicatricial de la adventicia. La vasculopatía está causada por factores inmunitarios y no inmunes, entre los que se encuentra el daño por frío. Presentamos el desarrollo de un modelo experimental de vasculopatía crónica del aloinjerto en el contexto del trasplante de pata posterior entre ratas tipo Lewis Brown-Norway como donantes y ratas tipo Wistar-Lewis como receptoras, tras 7 horas de isquemia fría a 4ºC. Todos los animales recibieron dosis infraterapéuticas de ciclosporina A y fueron sacrificados trascurridos 2 meses desde el trasplante. El análisis histológico permitió identificar los hallazgos característicos de la vasculopatía crónica del aloinjerto en los tercios musculares medio y distal de cada aloinjerto. Encontramos diferencias estadísticamente significativas al comparar el número de vasos patológicos de pequeño y mediano calibre observados por campo de aumento en el tercio medio y el tercio muscular distal (P = 0,007 y 0,004 respectivamente). El presente estudio establece un modelo experimental reproducible de vasculopatía crónica del aloinjerto en trasplante de tejidos compuestos. Pone en evidencia también la asociación entre la preservación en isquemia fría y la vasculopatía en diferentes segmentos vasculares de aloinjertos de pata posterior en ratas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;41(1): 1-10, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Preservación en frío y rechazo crónico, desarrollo de un modelo de trasplante de extremidad posterior en ratas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6772^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55174^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8458^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51226^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14410^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24593^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
