<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159931</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study on the efficacy of Counselling and Dignity Therapy in palliative care patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Many works contemplate patient needs at the end of life, with many integral models for palliative care interventions. The most commonly used methodology for meeting these needs is Counselling therapy, although recently there has been an increase in the international use of the Dignity therapy. This study aims to identify and quantify differences in emotional distress, quality of life, and preservation of dignity after both of these types of interventions. Method: A study of quasi-experimental design was developed in the Home Hospitalization Service (HHS) of University General Hospital of Valencia. After applying inclusion and exclusion criteria, 30 patients with an advanced oncology diagnosis were randomly assigned to the two intervention groups. Data were collected on sociodemographic, clinical, emotional distress (EVA), anxiety (HADS), depression (HADS), dignity (PDI) and quality of life (EORT-QLQ-30). Following intervention guides, patients received psychological treatment of 2-3 sessions per week at home. The statistics tests t and &amp;#967;2 were used to compare the baseline characteristics of both groups, t tests for repeated measures to assess treatments efficacy, and t tests for independent groups to compare differences between interventions. Results: There were no differences between the groups at baseline, except for gender. The Counselling group improved in suffering, quality of life, and in two of the dignity dimensions (existential and dependence anguish). The Dignity group results were similar, except for anxiety, which did not improve after the intervention. The comparison of efficacy showed no differences between the interventions. Conclusions: Both interventions were beneficial for patients, to the same extent, improving their quality of life, emotional well-being, and distress. Future research should study this situation taking into account one of the limitations of this study, the small sample size, and studying the repeatability of the results found in this ground-breaking work on Dignity Therapy in the Spanish context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galiana, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rudilla, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreto, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Existen múltiples trabajos que contemplan el conjunto de las necesidades de los pacientes al final de la vida, contando con propuestas de modelos integrales para una intervención terapéutica paliativa. La metodología más común que aborda estas necesidades es la intervención de counselling, aunque recientemente también ha crecido el uso internacional de la «terapia de la dignidad». Este estudio tiene como objetivo identificar y cuantificar diferencias en términos de distrés emocional, calidad de vida y preservación de la dignidad tras el tratamiento con estos 2 tipos de intervenciones. Método: Diseño cuasi-experimental en la Unidad de Hospitalización a Domicilio (UHD) del Hospital General Universitario de Valencia. Tras aplicar criterios de inclusión y exclusión, 30 pacientes con diagnóstico oncológico avanzado fueron asignados aleatoriamente a los 2 grupos de intervención. Se registraron datos sociodemográficos, clínicos, sobre malestar emocional (EVA sufrimiento), ansiedad (HADS), depresión (HADS), dignidad (IPD) y calidad de vida (EORT-QLQ-30). Siguiéndose las guías de intervención, los pacientes recibieron tratamiento psicológico de 2-3 sesiones semanales en sus domicilios. Se llevaron a cabo pruebas t y &amp;#967;2para comparar las características de los grupos en la línea base, pruebas t de medidas repetidas para evaluar la eficacia de los tratamientos y pruebas t para muestras independientes para comparar las diferencias entre intervenciones. Resultados: Los grupos no fueron diferentes en la línea base en ninguna de las variables, a excepción del género. El grupo counselling mejoró las variables sufrimiento, calidad de vida y 2 de las dimensiones de dignidad (angustia existencial y angustia dependencia). El grupo Dignidad obtuvo los mismos resultados, a excepción de la variable ansiedad, en la que no se encontró mejoría tras la intervención. La comparación de la eficacia de las intervenciones no mostró diferencias entre estas. Conclusiones: Ambas intervenciones fueron beneficiosas para los pacientes, en la misma medida, mejorando su calidad de vida, bienestar emocional y distrés. Futuras investigaciones deberían abordar esta problemática haciendo frente a una de las limitaciones del estudio, el reducido tamaño muestral, y estudiar la posible replicabilidad de los resultados encontrados en este trabajo, pionero en terapia de la dignidad en el contexto español (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;24(1): 39-46, ene.-mar. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la eficacia del counselling y de la terapia de la dignidad en pacientes paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3391^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
