<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87258</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between Asperger&#146;s Syndrome and autistic disorder. A reflection regarding  nature of mental illnes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asperger´s Syndrome was described over sixty years ago, making reference to a group of patients who showed social and communication abnormalities, as well as restricted and narrow interests. Similar features had been  described by Leo Kanner one year before under the name of Child Autism. In this work we will analyze the similarities and differences between both disorders, paying special attention to those features which would allow us  to establish an independent nosological entity for Asperger´s Syndrome through its external validity. We will highlight a few methodological difficulties which might have played an important role in the unsuccessful result achieved by this research to the present date.  Finally, we shall analyze the inherent features pertaining the nature of psychiatric disorders, considered as mere constructs, and the difficulties derived from their nature when applied to the field of empirical research, paying  special attention to the concept of &#147;reification&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Adán Manes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espliego Felipe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Asperger fue descrito hace más de sesenta años haciendo referencia a un grupo de pacientes que presentaban determinadas características en común, destacando una serie de dificultades a nivel de la interacción social y de la comunicación, así como por la presencia  de intereses restringidos y repetitivos. Similares rasgos habían sido descritos por Leo Kanner un año antes bajo el nombre de Autismo Infantil. Este trabajo analiza las semejanzas y diferencias entre ambos trastornos,  haciendo hincapié en los rasgos que permitirían establecer el Síndrome de Asperger como entidad nosológica independiente en base a su validez externa. Por  otra parte, se resaltan una serie de dificultades metodológicas que parecen haber jugado un papel decisivo en el infructuoso desenlace al que ha llegado dicha investigación  hasta la fecha. Finalmente analizaremos los rasgos inherentes a la naturaleza de los trastornos psiquiátricos, entendidos como meros constructos, y las trabas que de su naturaleza se derivan al proceder a su aplicación en el  terreno de la investigación empírica, para lo que prestaremos un especial énfasis al concepto de &#147;reificación&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;24(2/4): 213-223, abr.-dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el Síndrome de Asperger y el autismo infantil. Una reflexión sobre la naturaleza de la enfermedad mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12942^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
