<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92273</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psycopathology and spatial crewed missions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The papier reviews and summarizes the major diagnostic categories in psycopathology in the literature on psychological aspects on the special work environment of human space missions. It details the most common syndromes, as well as the charazteristics of some controversial syndromes in the literature such as asthemia. This is a pioneering work in this area in Spanish offers a general vision of this new and important field of investigation in psychology clíni to i expreimental for the advance of the spatial career. Finally one refers to the implications that for the mental health can have the near spatial missions of long duration, for example to Mars (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramallo Luna, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Benitez, Gabriel G. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo revisa y resume las principales categorías diagnósticas en psicopatología presentes en la literatura sobre aspectos psicológicos en el especial ambiente del trabajo quew suponen las misiones espaciales tripuladas. Se detallan los síndromes más comunes, así como las carazterísticas de algunos síndromes controvertidos en la literatura especializada como la astenia. El trabajo pionero en la materia en español ofrece una visión general de este novedoso e importante campo de investigación en psicología clíni a i expreimental para el avance de la carrera espacial. Finalmente se hace referencia a las implicaciones que para la salud mental pueden tener las próximas misiones espaciales de larga duración, por ejemplo a Marte(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;28(3): 377-389, sept.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicopatología y misiones espaciales tripuladas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33886</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32349^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
