<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043708</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypotension in unstable patients: predictive factors and preventive measures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypotension continues to be the most frequent complication occurring during haemodialysis. Of the 81 patients at risk in the chronic haemodialysis programme in the Satellite Unite of the HUC (Hospital Universitario de Canarias) in 2003, 25% showed particular fragility with more than 30% hypotensive events. Accordingly, we have set as our objectives the definition of the traits shown by labile patients, hypotension predictive events, and the proven preventive measures possible. A prospective, interventionist, randomised and controlled study was designed. Hypotension preventive intervention protocols were applied based on maximum hourly ultrafiltration (UF) control, axillar temperature of 36º, and different UF and conductivity profiles. Age, together with the associated comorbility, and sex were predictors. In fact, 79% of the unstable patients included in the hypotension protocol were over75 years of age, and 81.9 % were women. All the protocols reduced the incidence of hypotension, but a spectacularly reduction down to 17.2%, when the basal period had a result of 41.1%, was found in the period in which the protocol with lineal profiles was used. We think that Nursing staff can apply simple, proven measures that can significantly improve comfort during haemodialysis sessions in the more unstable patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de la Cruz Maestro, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Marrero, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Morejón, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello González, Oliver</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledesma Galindo, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Villar, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipotensión arterial continúa siendo la complicación más frecuente durante la sesión de hemodiálisis. De los 81 pacientes en riesgo en programa de hemodiálisis crónica en la Unidad Satélite del HUC (Hospital Universitario de Canarias) durante el año 2003, el 25% presentaba una especial fragilidad, con más de 30% de eventos hipotensivos. Por esto, nos planteamos como objetivos definir los matices que posee el paciente lábil, los eventos predictivos de hipotensión y las medidas preventivas contrastadas que se pueden plantear. Se diseñó un estudio prospectivo, intervencionista, aleatorizado y controlado. Se aplicaron protocolos de intervención preventivos de hipotensión basados en el control de la ultrafiltración (UF) máxima horaria, temperatura de 36º C, y distintos perfiles de UF y conductividad. La edad, junto con la comorbilidad asociada, y el sexo fueron predictores. De hecho, el 79% de los pacientes inestables incluidos en protocolo de hipotensión eran mayores de 75 años y el 81,9 % mujeres. Todos los protocolos disminuyeron la incidencia de hipotensiones, pero fue en el período en el que se utilizó el protocolo con perfiles lineales cuando disminuyen espectacularmente hasta el17,2%, cuando en el período basal eran el 41,1%. Pensamos que enfermería puede aplicar medidas sencillas y contrastadas que pueden mejorar de forma importante el confort durante la sesión de hemodiálisis de los pacientes más inestables</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;8(3): 193-197, jul.-sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La hipotensión en pacientes inestables: factores predictores y medidas preventivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
