<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68037</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Our aim was to evaluate the efficacy of treatment with multiple daily injections (MDI) using insulin glargine as basal insulin and insulin lispro as prandial insulin. Forty-five patients with type 1 diabetes and inadequate metabolic control with intensive therapy based on NPH insulin and rapid-acting insulin were treated with insulin glargine once daily associated with 3 or more doses of preprandial lispro insulin during 5 months. Clinical and analytical variables and satisfaction with treatment were analyzed before and after treatment, and a continuous glucose monitoring was performed during 48 hours at the end of the study. An increase in body mass index (24.01 ± 3.55 versus 24.42 ± 3.38 kg/m2, p &lt;0.05), a reduction in insulin requirements (0.86 ± 0.28 versus 0.72 ± 0.20 IU/kg/day, p &lt;0.001) and diminution of severe hypoglycemia episodes were observed with the basal-bolus therapy. At the same time, a significant decrease of fasting plasma glucose levels (189 ± 78 versus 145 ± 58 mg/dl, p= 0.005) and HbA1c levels (8.5 ± 1.1 versus 7.8 ± 0.8%, p= 0001), as well as an improvement in the degree of satisfaction with treatment were observed. In conclusion, treatment with MDI in basalbolus regimen with insulin glargine as basal insulin reduces fasting plasma glucose and HbA1c levels, with lower insulin requirements and a slight weight increase. Furthermore, this therapy achieves a significant reduction of episodes of severe hypoglycemia with an important improvement in the degree of treatment patient satisfaction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Diosdado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo era evaluar la eficacia del tratamiento con múltiples dosis de insulina (MDI) utilizando insulina glargina como insulina basal y lispro como insulina prandial. Cuarenta y cinco pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 (DM1) y un control metabólico inadecuado con terapia intensiva con insulina protamina neutra de Hagedorn (NPH) e insulina rápida, fueron tratados con una dosis de insulina glargina asociada a 3 o más dosis de insulina lispro preprandial durante 5 meses. Antes y después del tratamiento, se analizaron variables clínicas, analíticas y grado de satisfacción con el tratamiento, y se efectuó una monitorización continua de glucosa durante 48 horas al final del estudio. Los resultados fueron los siguientes: con la terapia basal-bolos se observó un aumento del índice de masa corporal (24,0 ± 3,5 frente a 24,4 ± 3,4 kg/m2; p &lt;0,05), una reducción de las necesidades de insulina (0,86 ± 0,28 frente a 0,72 ± 0,20 UI/kg/día; p &lt;0,001) y una disminución de los episodios de hipoglucemia grave. Al mismo tiempo, un descenso significativo tanto de la glucemia basal (189 ± 78 frente a 145 ± 58 mg/dL; p= 0,005) como de los niveles de hemoglobina glucosilada (HbA1c) (8,5 ± 1,1 frente a 7,8 ± 0,8%; p= 0,001), así como una evidente mejora en el grado de satisfacción con el tratamiento. En conclusión, el tratamiento con MDI en régimen bolos-basal con insulina glargina como insulina basal reduce la glucemia basal y el nivel de HbA1c, con menores requerimientos de insulina, e induce un ligero incremento ponderal. Además, esta terapia consigue una reducción significativa de los episodios de hipoglucemia grave, con una mejora importante en el grado de satisfacción del paciente con el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;24(3): 237-243, mayo-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68037</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1503^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30156^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30156^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27231^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
