<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047070</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family socialization and values</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Occupying a fundamental place among the intra-family interaction processes are those objective is to socialize  children in a determined system of values, norms and beliefs; in other words, parents attempt to configure a determined type of person in their children. These socialization processes are some of the most widely known functions in a family; around these, family roles are distributed and the limits of parent-child expectations and behavior patterns are set; perhaps socialization is the fundamental axle in family life. These processes are also one of the main dimensions to articulate intra-family interactions and the socio-cultural context in which the family as an institution is inscribed. For this reason, most literature regarding family interaction -if not the lion´s share- deals with describing the relevant related to the aforementioned socialization processes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Musitu, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de los procesos de interacción intrafamiliar ocupan una parte fundamental aquellos que tienen como objetivo socializar a los hijos en un determinado sistema de valores, normas y creencias; es decir, el intento de los padres por configurar un determinado tipo de persona en sus hijos. Estos procesos de socialización son una de las funciones más ampliamente reconocidas de la familia; en torno a ellos se distribuyen los roles familiares y se delimitan las expectativas y las conductas paternofiliales; la socialización es tal vez el eje fundamental de la vida familiar. También una de las dimensiones principales de articulación de la interacción intrafamiliar y el contexto sociocultural en el que la institución se inscribe. Por este motivo, gran parte de la literatura acerca de la interacción familiar -si no la mayor parte- se refiere a la descripción de las variables relevantes en dichos procesos de socialización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;29(1): 46-50, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Socialización familiar y valores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
