<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111136</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes, functional disorders, and diseases in the gastrointestinal tract of elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes changes in the basic digestive functions (motility, secretion, intraluminal digestion, absorption) that occur during aging. Elderly individuals frequently have oropharyngeal muscle dysmotility and altered swallowing of food. Reductions in esophageal peristalsis and lower esophageal sphincter (LES) pressures are also more common in the aged and may cause gastroesophageal reflux. Gastric motility and emptying and small bowel motility are generally normal in elderly subjects, although delayed motility and gastric emptying have been reported in some cases. The propulsive motility of the colon is also decreased, and this alteration is associated with neurological and endocrine-paracrine changes in the colonic wall. Decreased gastric secretions (acid, pepsin) and impairment of the mucous-bicarbonate barrier are frequently described in the elderly and may lead to gastric ulcer. Exocrine pancreatic secretion is often decreased, as is the bile salt content of bile. These changes represent the underlying mechanisms of symptomatic gastrointestinal dysfunctions in the elderly, such as dysphagia, gastroesophageal reflux disease, primary dyspepsia, irritable bowel syndrome, primary constipation, maldigestion, and reduced absorption of nutrients. Therapeutic management of these conditions is also described. The authors also review the gastrointestinal diseases that are more common in the elderly, such as atrophic gastritis, gastric ulcer, colon diverticulosis, malignant tumors, gallstones, chronic hepatitis, liver cirrhosis, Hepato Cellular Carcinoma (HCC), and chronic pancreatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mennuni, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scarno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabetta, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grassi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontana,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraioli, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Petraccia, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo describe los cambios en las funciones digestivas básicas (motilidad, secreción, digestión intraluminal, absorción) que ocurren en el envejecimiento. Los individuos ancianos a menudo presentan una dismotilidad de la musculatura orofaríngea y una alteración de la deglución de los alimentos. Las reducciones en el peristaltismo esofágico y de las presiones del esfínter esofágico inferior (EEI) también son más frecuentes en las personas mayores y pueden causar un reflujo gastroesofágico. La motilidad y el vaciamiento gástricos así como la motilidad intestinal son, por lo general, normales en los individuos ancianos, si bien se han notificado en algunos casos una motilidad y vaciamiento gástricos retardados. La motilidad propulsora del colon también está disminuida y esta alteración se asocia con cambios neurológicos y endocrinos-paracrinos de la pared colónica. En el anciano se describen frecuentemente disminución de las secreciones gástricas (ácido, pepsina) y alteración de la barrera mucosa-bicarbonato, lo cual puede favorecer la úlcera gástrica. A menudo la secreción pancreática exocrina está disminuida, así como el contenido en sales biliares de la bilis. Estos cambios representan mecanismos subyacentes de las disfunciones gastrointestinales sintomáticas del anciano tales como disfagia, enfermedad por reflujo gastroesofágico, dispepsia primaria, síndrome del intestino irritable, estreñimiento primario, maladigestión y disminución de la absorción de nutrientes. También se describe el manejo terapéutico de estos trastornos. Los autores también revisan las enfermedades gastrointestinales que son más frecuentes en el anciano, tales como las gastritis atrófica, la úlcera gástrica, la diverticulosis colónica, los tumores malignos, los cálculos biliares, la hepatitis crónica, la cirrosis hepática, el carcinoma hepatocelular (CHC) y la pancreatitis crónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(4): 659-668, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111136</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios, dolencias funcionales y enfermedades en el sistema gastrointestinal en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5898^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30319^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37754^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
