<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118236</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of chronic diseases on a pediatric emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Childhood chronic diseases are an increasing problem for the healthcare systems. Advances made in their management have led to a marked increase in the survival of these children and thus there is a need to analyze their impact on the emergency services. Objective. To describe the clinical characteristics of patients with chronic diseases seen in a pediatric emergency department. Method. Case-control study performed in a tertiary pediatric hospital, including emergency room visits one day per week for three consecutive months. Cases were defined as any visit of patients with chronic diseases, and controls were defined as the visits immediately following the case. Results. Of the 2,826 visits, 278 were from patients with chronic diseases (prevalence 9.8%, CI 95% 8.8-10.9), corresponding to 265 children (12 revisits). The most frequent diseases were respiratory (35.2%) and neurological (24.9%) disorders; 28.8% of the visits were related to their chronic condition. The median age was higher in cases than controls (4 years vs. 2.5 years respectively, p&lt;0.001). There were no significant differences in gender distribution (60.8% male vs. 52.7% female, p=0.059). More blood tests and CT scans were performed in cases compared to controls (16.5% vs. 9%, p=0.008, and 3.2% vs. 0.7%, p=0.033, respectively). There was no difference between cases and controls in the number of urinalysis (11.2% vs. 9% respectively, p=0.398), chest X-ray (19.1% vs. 13.3% respectively, p=0.065), or other tests performed. Compared to controls, visits of patients with chronic diseases included more consultations to specialists (7.6% vs. 2.9% respectively, p=0.013) and resulted in more admissions (19.1% vs. 7.6% respectively, p&lt;0.001). Conclusions. Children with chronic diseases represent a large proportion of emergency room visits and require a greater utilization of hospital resources and multidisciplinary management. Pediatricians should be aware of the emergency management and treatment guidelines of these conditions and identify promptly any signs of deterioration in these children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trenchs Sainz de la Maza, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casadevall Llandrich, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basteiro Diego, María G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquivel Ojeda, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo Garau, Araceli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir las características clínicas de pacientes con patología crónica en un servicio de urgencias pediátrico. Método. Estudio de casos y controles realizado en un hospital pediátrico de tercer nivel. Incluye las visitas realizadas en urgencias un día a la semana durante 3 meses consecutivos. Se define como caso toda visita de pacientes con patología crónica, y como control, la visita inmediatamente posterior al caso. Resultados. De las 2.826 visitas realizadas, 278 son pacientes con patología crónica (prevalencia 9,8%; IC 95% 8,8-10,9%), que corresponden a 265 niños (12 reconsultan). Las patologías más frecuentes son respiratorias (35,2%) y neurológicas (24,9%). El 28,8% de las visitas están relacionadas con su patología crónica. La mediana de edad es mayor en casos que en controles (4 años vs 2,5; p&lt;0,001), sin diferencias significativas en la distribución por sexos (60,8% masculino vs 52,7%, p=0,059). En los casos se realizan más análisis de sangre (16,5% vs 9%, p=0,008) y tomografías craneales (3,2% vs 0,7%, p=0,033). No encontramos diferencias en los análisis de orina (11,2% vs 9%, p=0,398), ni en las radiografías torácicas (19,1% vs 13,3%, p=0,065), ni en otras pruebas. En los casos se realizan más interconsultas a especialistas (7,6% vs 2,9%, p=0,013) y más ingresos (19,1% vs 7,6%, p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones. Los niños con patología crónica constituyen un grupo importante de las visitas realizadas en urgencias, requieren mayor utilización de recursos hospitalarios y manejo multidisciplinario. El pediatra de urgencias debe conocer las pautas de manejo y tratamiento de estos pacientes e identificar cualquier descompensación de las enfermedades de base que sufren (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;73(4): 150-153, oct.-dic.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la patología crónica en un servicio de urgencias pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
