<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73090</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The asthma in children is the second cause of infantile chronic morbidity, consuming great part of the sanitary resources</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The asthma in children is the second cause of infantile chronic morbidity, consuming greatpart of the sanitary resources. Methodology: we made of cross-sectional study of 1,509 histories of patients of 6 to 14 years, followed in Primary Care in the Castilian plateau (Spain). Results: the average age was 8.9 years with a slight predominance of males, accumulated prevalence of 11.9% and in the last 3 years of 9%. The age of onset was 3.5 years. Familiar atopic disease was present in 39.4% and personal antecedents in 54.7%. Another respiratory condition was present in 51.4%. Eighty-nine point eight percent of the children were controlled in primary care. Forty-four point one percent of children had sensitization tests performedand 48.8% had undergone tests of pulmonary function. Conclusions: most of the follow up of these patients takes place in Primary Care and thisfact has allowed an improvement in the control of the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arribas Santiago, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos García, J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machín Rodríguez, E. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán Martín, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camina Gutiérrez, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El asma infantil es la segunda causa de morbilidad crónica infantil consumiendo gran parte de los recursos sanitarios. Material y métodos: estudiamos de forma transversal 1.509 historias de pacientes de 6 a14 años, seguidos en un centro de salud de la meseta castellana (España). Resultados: la edad media de los niños con asma fue 8,9 años con un ligero predominio en varones, la prevalencia acumulada de 11,9% y en los últimos 3 años del 9%. La edad de inicio fue de 3,5 años. Presentaban antecedentes familiares de enfermedad atópica el 39,4% y personales en el 54,7%. Otra patología respiratoria se halló en el 51,4%. El 89,8% de los niños erancontrolados en Atención Primaria, las pruebas de estudio de sensibilización alérgica se realizaron en el 44,1% y la función pulmonar en el 48,8%. Conclusiones: el seguimiento mayoritario de estos pacientes se ha realizado en Atención Primaria y ha permitido una mejora en el control de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;10(40): 593-601, oct.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características del asma infantil en Atención Primaria. Mejora del seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
