<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153888</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of acquired brain injury towards the community integration: employment outcome, disability and dependence two years after injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To analyze the impact of acquired brain injury towards the community integration (professional career, disability, and dependence) in a sample of people affected by vascular, traumatic and tumor etiology acquired brain damage, over a two year time period after the original injury, and also to examine what sociodemographic variables, premorbid and injury related clinical data can predict the level of the person&#146;s integration into the community. Patients and methods. 106 adults sample suffering from acquired brain injury who were attended by the Neuropsychology and Neuropsychiatry Department at Hospital of Navarra (Spain) affected by memory deficit as their main sequel. Differences among groups have been analyzed by using t by Student, chi squared and U by Mann-Whitney tests. Results. 19% and 29% of the participants who were actively working before the injury got back their previous status within one and two years time respectively. 45% of the total sample were recognized disabled and 17% dependant. No relationship between sociodemographic and clinical variables and functional parameters observed were found. Conclusions. Acquired brain damage presents a high intensity impact on affected person&#146;s life trajectory. Nevertheless, in Spain, its consequences at sociolaboral adjustment over the the two years following the damage through functional parameters analyzed with official governmental means over a vascular, traumatic and tumor etiology sample had never been studied before (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tirapu Ustárroz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna Lario, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar el impacto del daño cerebral adquirido en la integración comunitaria (trayectoria laboral, discapacidad y dependencia) en una muestra de sujetos con daño cerebral adquirido de etiología vascular, traumática y tumoral, durante un período de dos años tras la lesión original, y examinar qué variables sociodemográficas, datos clínicos premórbidos y relacionados con la lesión predicen la integración en la comunidad. Pacientes y métodos. Muestra de 106 sujetos adultos con daño cerebral adquirido, atendidos en el Área de Neuropsicología y Neuropsiquiatría del Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra, con déficit de memoria como secuela principal. Las diferencias entre grupos se analizan con los tests t de Student, chi al cuadrado y U de Mann-Whitney. Resultados. De los participantes que antes de la lesión se encontraban activos laboralmente, el 19% y 29% recuperaron su estatus previo al año y a los dos años, respectivamente; a un 45% de la muestra total se le reconoció la discapacidad, y a un 17%, la dependencia. No se halló relación entre las variables sociodemográficas y clínicas y los parámetros funcionales contemplados. Conclusiones. La lesión cerebral adquirida impacta con intensidad en la trayectoria vital de los afectados, aunque no se han estudiado antes en España sus consecuencias en el ajuste sociolaboral en los dos años siguientes al daño a través de parámetros funcionales valorados con instrumentos oficiales estatales en una muestra de etiología vascular, traumática y tumoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(12): 539-548, 16 jun., 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del daño cerebral adquirido en la integración comunitaria: reinserción laboral, discapacidad y dependencia dos años después de la lesión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55125^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55780^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55125^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55125^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
