<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124915</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cocaine Use Disorders and Acute Myocardial Infarction, Excess Length of Hospital Stay and Overexpenditure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives To investigate the relationship between the prevalence of cocaine use disorders and acute myocardial infarction in patients aged &amp;#8805; 18 years and to estimate the influence of cocaine use disorders on mortality, excess length of stay, and overexpenditure among hospitalized patients with acute myocardial infarction. Methods Retrospective study of the minimum basic data set of 87 Spanish hospitals from 2008 to 2010.ResultsAmong 5 575 325 admissions reviewed, there were 24 126 patients with cocaine use disorders and 79 076 cases of acute myocardial infarction. The incidence of acute myocardial infarction among patients with cocaine use disorders increased with age and reached a peak at 55 years to 64 years (P &lt; .0001). Multivariate analysis showed that cocaine use disorders were more prevalent among patients with acute myocardial infarction independently of age, sex, other addictive disorders, and 30 other comorbidities (odds ratio = 3.0). Among patients with acute myocardial infarction, those with cocaine use disorders did not show an increase of in-hospital death, but did show excess length of hospital stay (1.5 days) and overexpenditure (382 euros). Conclusions Cocaine use disorders are associated with acute myocardial infarction and increase the length of hospital stay and overexpenditure among acute myocardial infarction patients. Cessation of cocaine use among these patients should be one of the primary therapeutic goals after hospital discharge(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gili, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Béjar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos Analizar la relación entre la prevalencia de trastornos por cocaína y el infarto agudo de miocardio en pacientes &amp;#8805; 18 años y su influencia en la mortalidad, la prolongación de estancias y el exceso de costes de los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio. Métodos Estudio retrospectivo de los datos del conjunto mínimo básico de datos de 87 hospitales españoles durante 2008-2010.ResultadosSe estudiaron 5.575.325 ingresos, entre los cuales hubo 24.126 pacientes con trastornos por cocaína y 79.076 casos de infarto agudo de miocardio. La prevalencia de infarto agudo de miocardio entre los pacientes con trastornos por cocaína aumentó con la edad, y fue máxima entre los de 55-64 años de edad (p &lt; 0,0001). El análisis multivariable indicó que los trastornos por cocaína son más prevalentes entre los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio (odds ratio = 3,0) e independientemente de edad, sexo, otras adicciones y 30 comorbilidades. Entre los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio, aquellos con trastornos por cocaína no presentaron mayor mortalidad, pero sí una prolongación indebida de las estancias hospitalarias (1,5 días) y un exceso de costes (382 euros).Conclusiones Hay una asociación entre los trastornos por cocaína y el infarto agudo de miocardio. Estos trastornos prolongan las estancias hospitalarias y aumentan los costes de los pacientes hospitalizados. La interrupción del uso de la droga debe ser uno de los principales objetivos terapéuticos tras el alta del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(7): 545-551, jul. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124915</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos por cocaína e infarto agudo de miocardio, prolongación de estancias y exceso de costes hospitalarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
