<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147031</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To show updated information about the implementation of Aloe Vera in the treatment of pressure ulcers. Material and methods: Literature search of articles published, between 2004 and 2014, in different biomedical databases. Results: The evidence confirms that Aloe Vera can help in the prevention and treatment of pressure ulcers of grade I and II. However, there are no references that justify its use in pressure ulcers III and IV. Conclusions: The World Health Organization (WHO) recommends that governments put patient safety at the center of Health Policy, emphasizing measures like prevention and treatment of pressure ulcers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Melchor, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón Melchor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Castán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Presentar una información actualizada acerca de la aplicación del Aloe Vera en las úlceras por presión (UPP). Material y métodos: Búsqueda bibliográfica de los artículos publicados, entre 2004 y 2014, en diferentes bases de datos biomédicas. Resultados: La evidencia confirma que puede ayudar en la prevención y en el tratamiento de UPP de grado I y II. Sin embargo no existen referencias que justifiquen su uso en las UPP III y IV. Conclusiones: La Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) recomienda a los gobiernos que sitúen la seguridad del paciente en el centro de las Políticas Sanitarias, destacando medidas cómo la prevención y el tratamiento de las UPP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;17(6): 755-762, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las úlceras por presión con Aloe Vera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
