<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98645</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience of the moving day of a general hospital and effect on clinical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To describe the moving day of a general hospital and to analyze the impact on clinical activity in the first few months after the move. Methods We describe the process of patient transfer and analyze the impact on activity of moving a regional general hospital in Catalonia (Spain) to a new building. Activity was compared in two periods: the first 3 months after the move (period 2) and the same 3 months in the previous year (period 1).Results We moved 37 patients without incidents. A total of 18,786 patients were admitted to the emergency room in period 1 and 21,266 were admitted in period 2 (+13.2%). The number of admissions from the emergency room vs elective admissions was 1,314/803 in period 1 and 1,427/979 in period 2 (+8.59%/ +21.91%). The number of outpatient visits in period 1 was 32,116 and 30,777 in period 2 (-4.16%).Conclusions Proper planning and coordination allowed the hospital to be moved without incidents and without decreasing activity(SU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tor, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enjamio, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramon, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir, Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Terol, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Describir el proceso del día del traslado de un hospital general. Analizar el impacto en la actividad asistencial en los primeros meses después del traslado. Método Hospital general de ámbito comarcal, en Cataluña, que se traslada a un nuevo edifico. Se describe el proceso del traslado de los pacientes y se analiza el impacto en la actividad (se comparan 3 meses a partir del traslado [período 2] con los mismos meses del año anterior [período1]).Resultados Se trasladaron 37 pacientes sin incidencias. Se atendieron 18.786 urgencias en el período 1 y 21.266 en el período 2 (+13,2%). El número de ingresos urgentes/programados fue de 1314/803 en el período 1 y de 1427/979 en el período 2 (+8,59%/+21,91%). Las visitas realizadas en consultas externas fueron 32.116 en el período 1 y 30.777 en el período 2 (-4,16%)Conclusiones Una adecuada planificación y coordinación permitió realizar un traslado de hospital sin incidencias y sin reducir la actividad asistencial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(1): 94-96, ene. -feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia acerca del traslado de un hospital general y su repercusión en la actividad asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6425^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
