<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165908</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">European guidelines on dyslipidemia. Strengths and weaknesses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The joint guidelines of the European Society of Cardiology and the European Atherosclerosis Society on the management of dyslipidemia include a number of interesting clinical features: risk stratification provides the basis for selecting the type and intensity of lipid-lowering treatment; the principal therapeutic target is the low-density lipoprotein cholesterol level; the precise treatment target for this parameter depends on the level of risk (&lt;70 mg/dl for very-high-risk patients and &lt;100 mg/dl for high-risk patients); potent statins, given at a high dose, are the drugs of choice for achieving these goals; and particular recommendations must be followed for a number of common clinical scenarios: e.g. the elderly, women, patients with chronic kidney disease and secondary prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegría Barrero, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría Barrero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría Ezquerra, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La guía conjunta de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología y la European Atherosclerosis Societypara el manejo de la dislipemia incluye varios aspectos de interés clínico: la estratificación del riesgo como base de la decisión del tratamiento hipolipemiante y su intensidad; el colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad como diana terapéutica principal; la delimitación de objetivos terapéuticos de este parámetro según el riesgo (&lt; 70 mg/dl para los pacientes de riesgo muy alto y &lt; 100 mg/dl para los de riesgo alto); el énfasis en las estatinas potentes y a dosis altas como tratamiento básico para alcanzar dichos objetivos, y las recomendaciones específicas en diversos escenarios de interés clínico como ancianos, mujeres, prevención secundaria, disfunción renal y otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);15(supl.A): 14a-17a, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La guía europea de dislipemia. Fortalezas y debilidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d650^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3419^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8252^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
