<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74892</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The regulación of emtions and feelings of students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this reseach we have carried out an empirical analysis of the emotional regualtion of future primary teachers, focused on the emotional dimension of first- and third-year students of different specialities. The aim is to provide clarifying data as regards the level of emotional intelligence of  a sample of students, as well as, their use of some of its dimensions in a problematic situation within the educational context. In the light of the results obtained, the charaeristics of their socioemotional environment throughout their training as future primary teachers will be compared and analysed, making us think about the new challenges that the integration of the emotional dimesnion poses for initial teacher training within the context of the Europena Higher Education Area (EHEA)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Teruel Melero, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta investigación hemos analizado la regulación eocional de los fueron maestros, mediante un esudio empírico, indagando en la dimensión emocional de los estudiantes de vairas especialidades de los cursos primero y tercero de Magisterio. Se pretende aportar datos clarificadores acerca del nivel de inteligencia emocional de una muestra de alumnos, así como del manejo de algunas diensiones d ela misma, en una situación problemática denro del contexto educativo. A la luz de los resultados, se comparan y anlizan las características que constituyen el ámbito socioafectivo a lo largo de su formación como docentes, preguntándonos en torno a los nuevos retos y desafios que la integración de la dimensión emcional suponene dentro de la ormación inicial del profesorado, en el contexto del espacio Europeo de Educación Superior (EEES)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;12(2/3): 379-391, dic. 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La regulación de las emociones y de los sentimientos en alumnos de magisterio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14537^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
