<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90121</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative estimation of the risk of lung resection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article discusses the two most up-to-date clinical practice guidelines containing therecommendations of US and European scientific societies on preoperative assessment of the risk of lungresection. Despite some differences between the two documents, both guidelines agree on the importance ofroutine preoperative measurement of diffusion lung capacity for carbon monoxide (DLCO) in the predictivevalue of exercise tests, especially measurement of maximal oxygen uptake per minute (VO2max). Preciselybecause of its ability to predict the risk of operative death, VO2max should be measured in patients with aforced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) or DLCO below 80% of the theoretical value. The authorsrecommend using one of the two above-mentioned guidelines in clinical practice and periodically auditingthe results to compare them with in-hospital mortality for lung resection in Europe, currently availablethrough the European Association of Thoracic Surgeons. There is currently no validated risk index that couldbe directly applied in clinical decision making in lung resection(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ramos, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Barenys, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paradela de la Morena, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se comentan las 2 guías de práctica clínica más actuales que contienen las recomendacionesde las sociedades científicas europeas y norteamericana acerca de la evaluación preoperatoria del riesgo de laresección pulmonar. A pesar de algunas diferencias entre los 2 documentos, ambas guías coinciden en la importanciade la medición preoperatoria rutinaria de la difusión pulmonar de monóxido de carbono (DLCO) yen el valor predictivo de las pruebas de ejercicio, especialmente la medición del consumo máximo de oxígenopor minuto (VO2max). Precisamente debido a su capacidad predictiva del riesgo de muerte operatoria, se debemedir la VO2max en los casos de pacientes con FEV1 o DLCO por debajo del 80% de su valor teórico. Los autoresrecomiendan utilizar alguna de las 2 guías citadas en la práctica clínica y auditar periódicamente los resultadospropios para compararlos con la mortalidad hospitalaria de la resección pulmonar en Europa que, actualmente,están disponibles a través de la European Association of Thoracic Surgeons. Actualmente, no existeningún índice de riesgo validado y que se pueda aplicar directamente en la toma de decisiones clínicas enresección pulmonar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.3): 2-4, mayo 2011. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación preoperatoria del riesgo de la resección pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
