<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147821</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiple chemical sensitivity: Clinical evaluation of the severity and psychopathological profile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: Multiple chemical sensitivity (MCS) is a multisystem disorder of controversial etiology, affecting some subjects when exposed to chemicals at no harmful concentrations. The objective of this paper is to describe the epidemiological, clinical and psychological features of a sample of patients with MCS for further specific group treatment. Patiens and method: Descriptive study of patients diagnosed with MCS in a toxicology unit. We administered the Quick Environmental Exposure and Sensitivity Inventory, the structured interview SCID-II, the anxiety scale HAS and the type A personality test, PCTA. Results: Seventy-three patients were included. The mean age was 52,6 years (range 33-77; SD 9.29). Sixty-six were females (90.4%). Fifty-three percent were classified as i-ii and ii grade. Sixty-one patients (83%) presented some type of comorbidity, mainly chronic pain, fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue. They exhibited higher levels of anxiety (average score of 19.2), prevalence of phobic-avoidant traits of personality and type A behavior in 31.1%. Conclusions: MCS affects middle-aged women with comorbidities (chronic pain, fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue) and high anxiety and avoidance behaviors. This preliminary analysis should help provide a specific therapeutic approach to these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agüero Gento, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvà Coll, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizà Portell, Maria Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Enríquez, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lago Blanco, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer Ferrando, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: La sensibilidad química múltiple (.SQM) es un trastorno multisistémico de etiología controvertida que afecta a algunos sujetos al exponerse a productos químicos a concentraciones no perjudiciales. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir las características epidemiológicas, clínicas y psicológicas de una muestra de pacientes con SQM, para un posterior tratamiento grupal específico. Pacientes y método: Estudio descriptivo de los pacientes diagnosticados de SQM en una unidad de toxicología, mediante la administración del cuestionario Quick Environmental Exposure and Sensitivity Inventory, junto con la entrevista estructurada SCID-II, la escala de ansiedad HAS y el test de personalidad tipo A, PCTA. Resultados: Se incluyeron 73 pacientes, con una edad media de 52,6 años (rango 33-77; DE 9,29), siendo 66 mujeres (90,4%). El 53% estaban clasificados como grado i-ii y ii. Sesenta y un pacientes (83%) presentaron algún tipo de comorbilidad, fundamentalmente dolor crónico, fibromialgia y fatiga crónica, con niveles de ansiedad mayores (puntuación media 19,2), predominio de rasgos de personalidad fóbico-evitativo y patrón de conducta tipo A (31,1%). Conclusiones: La SQM afecta principalmente a mujeres de mediana edad, con comorbilidades (dolor crónico, fibromialgia y fatiga crónica), elevada ansiedad y conductas de evitación. Este análisis previo debería ayudar a ofrecer un abordaje psicoterapéutico específico a estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(3): 108-111, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad química múltiple: evaluación clínica de la gravedad y perfil psicopatológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32135^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32135^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32135^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
