<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122753</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Could it just be a matter of cold?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The CREST syndrome is a variant of scleroderma characterized by calcinosis, Raynaud`s phenomenon, esophageal dysfunction, sclerodactyly and telangiectasias. Skin affection is usually limited to distal extremities, it progresses more slowly and its prognosis is more favorable than in scleroderma, with the possibility of no visceral involvement. The aim of this paper is to present a clinical case of CREST syndrome, highlighting the relevance of the family physician in the assessment of the patient´s signs and symptoms, thus allowing adequate diagnosis and therapeutic guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neves, Ana Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teles, María Joao</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de CREST es una variante de la esclerodermia y se caracteriza por calcinosis, fenómeno de Raynaud, cambio de la motilidad esofágica, esclerodactilia y telangiectasias. Normalmente, la afectación cutánea se limita a las extremidades distales, la progresión es más lenta y el pronóstico más favorable que en la esclerodermia, pudiendo no existir compromiso visceral. El objetivo de este trabajo es relatar un caso clínico de síndrome de CREST, enfocando la importancia del médico de familia en la valoración de las señales y síntomas presentados por los pacientes, permitiendo un diagnóstico y una orientación terapéutica adecuados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;7(1): 63-65, feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Será sólo una cuestión de frío?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23402^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12976^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10625^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12362^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
