<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73448</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent obesity: Anxiety, cognitive and behavioural symptoms characteristic of eating disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the presence of symptoms of anxiety, cognitive and behavioural symptoms characteristic of eating disorders in overweight adolescents. Material and Methods: The sample consisted of 297 adolescents (55.2% female and 44.8% male) aged from 11 to 17 years, divided into four groups according to their BMI percentile: normal weight, overweight, obesity and severe obesity. The questionnaires used were the Eating Disorders Inventory-2 (EDI-2) and the state-trait anxiety questionnaire (STAI). Results: The results showed that the adolescents with severe obesity were more concerned about their physical appearance (body dissatisfaction and obsession with being thin), by their social environment (interpersonal distrust), and showed more anxiety state and anxiety trait than adolescent overweight or obese. In the clinical sample, the adolescents with normal weight showed specific factors for developing eating disorders in the future. Conclusions: As the BMI increased, symptoms of anxiety and symptoms associated with eating disorders were also increased. The findings of this study are discussed in order to improve therapeutic interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varea, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forns, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la presencia de síntomas de ansiedad y síntomas cognitivos y conductuales característicos de los trastornos de alimentación en adolescentes con exceso de peso. Material y método: Muestra de 297 adolescentes (55,2% de mujeres y 44,8% de hombres) de entre 11 y 17 años, divididos en 4 grupos según su índice de masa corporal (IMC) percentilado: normopeso, sobrepeso, obesidad y obesidad grave. Los cuestionarios utilizados fueron el Eating Disorders Inventory-2 (EDI-2) y el cuestionario de ansiedad estado-rasgo (STAI). Resultados: Los resultados indican que los adolescentes con obesidad grave muestran más preocupación por su aspecto físico, por su entorno social, mayor sensibilidad corporal y más tensión subjetiva que los adolescentes con sobrepeso u obesidad. En nuestra muestra clínica, los adolescentes normopeso presentan factores específicos para desarrollar en un futuro trastornos de alimentación. Conclusiones: A medida que incrementa el IMC aumentan los síntomas de ansiedad y los síntomas asociados a los trastornos de alimentación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(6): 489-494, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad infantil: ansiedad y síntomas cognitivos y conductuales propios de los trastornos de alimentación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
