<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141097</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic targets in Gaucher's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gaucher&#146;s disease (GD) occurs because of deficiency of the enzyme beta-glucocerebrosidase that results in accumulation of this glycolipid compound in the cells of the macrophage-monocyte system. There are 3 types: type 1 is non-neuronopathic with primarily visceral signs and symptoms which range tremendously in severity; infantile-onset type 2 and later-onset type 3 involve the central nervous system. More than 300 mutations have been described in the gene, partially explaining phenotypic heterogeneity. Commercialization in 1991 of the first enzyme replacement therapy, alglucerase, resulted in a revolution in the management of patients with symptomatic GD (i.e., by improving the hematological and visceral signs and symptoms). Within the first 5 years of alglucerase, its safety and efficacy in improving hemoglobin levels and platelet counts, and in reducing splenic and hepatic enlargement were confirmed albeit recognizing its inability to impact neurological symptoms and signs because of its large molecular size. Recombinant imiglucerase soon replaced alglucerase as the standard of care for GD. The therapeutic targets recently defined as treatment goals were: normalization of cell counts; reduction of liver and spleen volume; elimination of the infiltration in the bone marrow to prevent the complications, and improvement in surrogate biomarkers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roca, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giraldo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Gaucher (EG) se produce por el déficit de la enzima beta-glucocerebrosidasa, lo que provoca el acúmulo del compuesto glicolípídico en las células del sistema monocito-macrófago. Hay 3 tipos: el tipo 1 se corresponde con las manifestaciones principalmente viscerales, que son muy variables. En los pacientes que presentan los tipos 2 y tipo 3 se ve afectado el sistema nervioso central. Se han descrito más de 300 mutaciones en el gen que codifica esta enzima, lo que en parte explica su heterogeneidad fenotípica. En 1991 se comercializó el primer tratamiento de sustitución enzimática (TSE): la alglucerasa, obtenida de tejido placentario humano y que supuso una revolución en el tratamiento de los pacientes con EG sintomática. Cinco años más tarde, la alglucerasa había demostrado su seguridad y eficacia en los objetivos terapéuticos de la enfermedad: recuperación de las concentraciones de hemoglobina y plaquetas, reducción del volumen del bazo y del hígado; sin embargo, debido al gran tamaño de la molécula, que no permite atravesar la barrera hematoencefálica, el tratamiento se demostró incapaz para reducir los síntomas y signos neurológicos. Posteriormente se introdujo la enzima recombinante imiglucerasa, que sustituyó rápidamente a la alglucerasa como tratamiento estándar de la EG. En los últimos años se han definido los objetivos del tratamiento como: normalización de recuentos celulares; reducción del volumen hepático y esplénico; eliminación de la infiltración en la médula ósea para evitar la aparición de complicaciones, y mejoría de los biomarcadores subrogados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(supl.1): 46-49, sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Objetivos terapéuticos en la enfermedad de Gaucher</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5916^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11406</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5916^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53690</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6686^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22189^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6107^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
