<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142939</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Specific language impairments and deafness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The possibility that a Specific Language Impairment (SLI) may be observed in children with hearing loss is based on the evidence that a percentage of children with cochlear implant (CI) do not seem to benefit from that device, and only limited linguistic forms persist in them. The possibility of using the diagnosis SLI for children with CI is discussed. Criteria describing SLI accepted by the international scientific community was used for this purpose. The proposals that describe the language and communicative behaviours of children with hearing impairment affected with SLI are reviewed. The resulting picture is blurry and intractable, because of the amount of symptoms proposed with a low level of specificity. The confusion about the attribute of &#145;specific&#146; in these proposals is emphasised. There are no specific linguistic symptoms of SLI, and &#145;specific&#146; refers to the primary nature of impairment, not due to cognitive retardation, malformations of the organs of articulation, perceptual limitations, neurological disease, or qualitative alterations in social interaction. Data from research comparing the language of children with CI and hearing children, children with CI with limited language and without this limitation, etc. are revised. It is concluded from these results that the expression &#145;SLI&#146; referring to limited language of some children with CI is not appropriate. Some clear criteria are tentatively proposed in order to identify children with CI who persist with a very limited language (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguado, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La posibilidad de que el trastorno específico del lenguaje (TEL) se observe en niños con hipoacusia se basa en la evidencia de que un porcentaje de niños con implante coclear (IC) no parecen beneficiarse de ese dispositivo y persisten en unas formas lingüísticas muy limitadas. Se discute el posible encaje del TEL en los niños con IC a partir de los criterios del TEL aceptados por la comunidad científica internacional. Se revisan algunas propuestas que tratan de describir el lenguaje y las conductas comunicativas de los niños sordos afectados de TEL. El panorama resultante es confuso, intratable por la cantidad de síntomas propuestos con un nivel bajo de especificidad. Se pone de relieve la confusión acerca del atributo de «específico» en estas propuestas: no existen síntomas lingüísticos específicos del TEL; «específico» se refiere a que el trastorno es primario, no consecuente a retraso cognitivo, a malformaciones de los órganos de la articulación, a limitaciones perceptivas, a enfermedad neurológica o a alteraciones cualitativas en la interacción social. Se revisan datos obtenidos de investigaciones en las que se compara el lenguaje de niños con IC y niños oyentes, de niños con IC con lenguaje limitado y sin esa limitación, etc. A partir de esos resultados se concluye que no es apropiado utilizar la expresión TEL para referirse al lenguaje limitado de algunos niños con IC y se proponen, simplemente como tentativa, unos criterios claros para la identificación de los niños con IC que persisten en un lenguaje muy limitado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);35(4): 171-176, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142939</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos específicos del lenguaje e hipoacusia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3082^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
