<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160881</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rapidly progressive dementia and parkinsonism associated to multiple dural arteriovenous fistulas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Rapidly progressive dementias are an infrequent group of diseases characterised by cognitive deterioration and other neurological disorders that develop over a period ranging from weeks to months. Their causation is varied and includes a large number of neurodegenerative, toxic, metabolic, autoimmune, infectious and vascular conditions. Case report. We report the case of a 69-year-old male who was admitted to hospital due to a rapidly progressive dementia and parkinsonism caused by multiple dural arteriovenous fistulas, which were successfully treated by means of endovascular therapy. Conclusion. Dural arteriovenous fistulas are anomalous connections between the dural arteries and the venous sinuses or cortical veins that are an unusual cause of rapidly progressive dementia. They must, however, be taken into account, given the availability of a specific treatment with reversal of the symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piedra, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejía, Paúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merchán-Del Hierro, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las demencias rápidamente progresivas son un grupo poco frecuente de enfermedades caracterizadas por un deterioro cognitivo y otras alteraciones neurológicas que evolucionan en el transcurso de semanas a meses. Su etiología es diversa e incluye un gran número de condiciones neurodegenerativas, tóxicas, metabólicas, autoinmunes, infecciosas y vasculares. Caso clínico. Varón de 69 años, que ingresó por demencia rápidamente progresiva y parkinsonismo causado por múltiples fístulas arteriovenosas durales tratadas exitosamente mediante terapia endovascular. Conclusión. Las fístulas arteriovenosas durales son conexiones anómalas entre las arterias durales y los senos venosos o venas corticales que constituyen una causa inusual de demencia rápidamente progresiva, pero que debe considerarse, dada la disponibilidad de un tratamiento específico con reversión de los síntomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(5): 214-218, 1 mar., 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160881</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demencia rápidamente progresiva y parkinsonismo asociados a múltiples fístulas arteriovenosas durales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23184^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2576^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23184^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
