<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111218</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of falls in a University Hospital: factors related</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: falls are a real risk that occurs in hospitals; falls are health a care quality indicator. The World Health Organization (WHO) defines the term falls as the result of any event which precipitate someone to the ground against their will. Aims: to analyze the incidence of falls, the profile of patients who fall in the hospital and to identify causes and effects. Methodology: design: Descriptive study on falls reported in Jaen&#146;s Hospital, which includes any fall(36) that has taken place at some time of hospital stay. Data collection was performed by each unit supervisors developed a data collection sheet. Data were transcribed to a database. Variables collected were: demographic data, date and time of the fall event, unit which produces the fall, Morse scale score, previous falls, fall circumstances, factors such as medication, cognitive, functional factors environment, care after the fall and need for assistive devices. Results: during the period under review there were a total of 36 falls, representing an incidence of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández,  Francisco P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alejo-Esteban, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque-Martínez, Francisco M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrabal-Orpez,  M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra-López, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa-García, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa-Corral,  Raquel R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna-Parras,  Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las caídas son un riesgo real que acontece en el medio hospitalario, y constituyen un indicador de calidad asistencial. La Organización Mundial de la Salud(OMS) define el término caída como &#147;la consecuencia de cualquier acontecimiento que precipita al individuo hacia el suelo en contra de su voluntad&#148;. Objetivo: analizar la incidencia de caídas, el perfil de los pacientes que sufren caídas en el hospital e identificar las posibles causas y efectos de la misma. Metodología: estudio descriptivo sobre las caídas registradas en el Complejo Hospitalario de Jaén durante la estancia hospitalaria. La obtención de datos se hizo directamente por las supervisoras. Se elaboró una hoja de recogida de datos cuyas anotaciones se transmitieron a una base de datos electrónica. Las variables que se recogieron fueron datos de filiación del paciente, fecha y hora de la caída, unidad donde se produce la caída, puntuación escala Morse, caídas previas, circunstancias de la caída, factores relacionados como medicación, trastornos (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);22(4): 167-173, dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de caídas en un hospital de nivel 1: factores relacionados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
