<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048412</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care related to the prevention of ventilator-associated pneumonia. A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the efficacy of eight nursing care interventions in the prevention of ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP). Method. We performed a search of the MEDLINE, CINAHL, Cochrane and Cuiden databases for articles published from 1990 to 2005. We included randomized clinical trials in adults undergoing mechanical ventilation in intensive care units that provided data on the incidence of VAP when the following nursing interventions were applied: oral rinse with chlorhexidine 0.12%; subglottic secretion aspiration; semirecumbent patient positioning; ventilator circuit changes; heat and moisture filter changes; body position changes (rotational therapy); closed aspiration system; and percussion and vibration. Results and conclusions. Twenty articles meeting all the inclusion criteria were analyzed. The VAP-preventive interventions supported by the strongest evidence were: oral rinse with chlorhexidine 0.12%, subglottic secretion aspiration, semirecumbent patient positioning, avoidance of routine circuit ventilation changes, and changing the heat and moisture filter every 48 hours. Body position changes (rotational therapy) may be useful in patients who tolerate it. There is no evidence to support the closed aspiration system, percussion and vibration as preventive measures against VAP. The results show the importance of nursing care in the prevention of VAP</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huertas-Linero, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor-Martínez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel-Roig, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picó-Segura, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la efectividad de 8 intervenciones de enfermería para la prevención de la neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica (NAV). Método. Se realizó una búsqueda electrónica en la que se utilizaron las bases de datos Medline, Cinahl, Cochrane y Cuiden desde el año 1990 a 2005. Se incluyeron ensayos clínicos aleatorios, de pacientes adultos ingresados en unidades de críticos, con ventilación mecánica y que medían la incidencia de NAV al aplicarse las siguientes intervenciones: lavado bucal con clorhexidina 0,12%; aspiración subglótica de secreciones; posición semisentada del paciente; cambio del circuito del respirador; cambio del humidificador; cambios posturales (terapia rotacional); sistema de aspiración cerrado, y percusión y vibración. Resultados y conclusiones. Se analizaron un total de 20 artículos tras ser seleccionados según los criterios de inclusión. Las intervenciones con un mayor grado de evidencia para la prevención de la NAV son: el lavado bucal con clorhexidina 0,12%, la aspiración subglótica de secreciones, la posición semisentada del paciente, evitar el cambio rutinario del circuito del respirador y realizar el cambio del humidificador cada 48 h. El cambio postural (terapia rotacional) se recomienda si el paciente lo tolera. No se encuentra evidencia científica que permita recomendar el sistema de aspiración cerrado y la vibración y percusión como medidas para prevenir la NAV. Los resultados muestran la importancia de los cuidados de enfermería para la prevención de la NAV</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(5): 244-252, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados de enfermería en la prevención de la neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24402^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
