<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115026</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HIV/HBV coinfection: Serological control and therapeutic strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The evolution and prognosis of patients co-infected by human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and hepatitis B (HBV) is not well know. This study describes the treatment and serological, virological and biochemical and elastographic responses of HIV and HBV-coinfected patients. Patients and methods. A descriptive, retrospective study of all the HIV/HBV-coinfected patients seen in a specialized HIV department between 1 January 2007 and 30 November 2008 was performed. Virological and serological determinations of HIV and HBV infections as well as CD4 lymphocytes and transaminases prior to antiretroviral treatment and at the time of analysis were obtained. Results. A total of 54 (5.4%) cases of HIV/HBV coinfection were identified. The median nadir and current CD4 were 179 and 437 cells/L, respectively. There was undetectable RNA-HIV in 70%. There were 52 patients (96.3%) who followed active drugs treatment against HBV. After treatment, 68.8% had HBeAg negative result, with 81.6% virologic response. The HBsAg became negative in 10.4%. ALT was normal in 75.5%. FibroScan® was performed in 30 (55.6%) patients, yielding a median of 7.0kPa. Conclusions. The results obtained suggest a good serological, virological and biochemical control of HIV/HBV-coinfected patients with treatments recommended by clinical guidelines(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Artacho, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cruz-Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez-Molina, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada-Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergas-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altali-Alhames, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. La evolución y pronóstico de los pacientes coinfectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) y el de la hepatitis B (VHB) no es bien conocida. Este estudio describe el tratamiento y el control serológico, virológico, bioquímico y elastográfico de los pacientes coinfectados por VIH/VHB. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo, de la totalidad de pacientes coinfectados por VIH/VHB seguidos en una consulta monográfica de VIH entre el 1 de enero de 2007 y el 30 de noviembre de 2008. A los pacientes se les realizaron determinaciones virológicas y serológicas para el VHB y el VIH, así como linfocitos CD4 y transaminasas, antes de comenzar el tratamiento antirretroviral y en el momento del análisis. Resultados. Se identificaron 54 (5,4%) pacientes coinfectados por VIH/VHB. Las medianas de CD4 nadir y actual fueron de 179 y 437 células/&amp;#956;l, respectivamente. El 70% tenían RNA-VIH indetectable. Cincuenta y dos pacientes (96,3%) seguían terapia con fármacos activos frente al VHB. Un 68,8% presentaron negativización del antígeno «e» del VHB, con un 81,6% de respuesta virológica. El antígeno de superficie del VHB se negativizó en el 10,4%. La alanina aminotransferasa era normal en el75,5%. Se realizó FibroScan® a 30 (55,6%) pacientes, obteniéndose una mediana de 7.0 KPa. Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos sugieren un buen control serológico, virológico, bioquímico y elastográfico de los pacientes coinfectados por VIH/VHB con los tratamientos recomendados por las guías clínicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;213(6): 285-290, ago.-sept.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coinfección por VIH/VHB: estrategias terapéuticas y control serológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23666^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15175^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54468^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54468^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54468^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54468^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
