<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100430</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinions and beliefs of the Spanish population on serious mental illnesses (schizophrenia and bipolar disorder)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:To find out the opinions, beliefs and concerns of the Spanish population on serious mental diseases: schizophrenia and bipolar disorder. Material and methods:An ad-hoc questionnaire was constructed for the survey. A panel of seven experts extracted the contents. The Societies that involved were: ASAENES, ABBA, FEAFES-ANDALUCÍA, AMAFE, and AFAEM-5 advocacy societies were also involved. The questionnaire contained 12 questions about: knowledge of the diseases, diagnostic difficulties, symptoms, triggering factors, interference, treatments and effectiveness, beliefs and concerns. The questionnaire was administered during the IV Campaign of Social Awareness about Serious Mental Illness (Madrid and Seville, September-October 2009). Results:A total of 5,473 questionnaires were collected, 55.8% in Seville. The majority (66.2%) of the sample were women, and the mean age was 35 years (SD=14.5). Both illnesses were known by 82% of the population, but 51% did not known any symptom of schizophrenia. Other notable opinions were; they are difficult to diagnose (59%), they were not diagnosed due to social rejection (27%), interfered quite a lot with daily life (49%) or prevented a normal life (42%), the effective treatments are psychological (72%). Beliefs were: social rejection, family burden, and patient suffering. Concerns included: dangerousness, social rejection, lack of information, and scarcity of resources. Conclusions:There is a lack of knowledge of the symptoms. The majority do not know about specific symptoms and highlight the negative ones. Combined pharmacological-psychological treatment is believed to be most effective. Social stigma and family and personal burden are concerns(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dios Perrino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correas Lauffer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauriño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción:Conocer las opiniones, creencias y preocupaciones de la población general sobre dos enfermedades mentales graves: esquizofrenia y trastorno bipolar. Material y métodos:Se construyó un cuestionario ad-hoc para encuesta. Un panel de siete expertos extrajo los contenidos. También participaron: ASAENES, ABBA, FEAFES-ANDALUCIA, AMAFE, FEMASAM y AFAEM-5. El cuestionario contenía 12 preguntas sobre: conocimiento de las patologías, dificultades diagnósticas, síntomas, desencadenantes, interferencia, tratamientos y efectividad, creencias y preocupaciones. Administrado: IV Campaña de Concienciación Social sobre la Enfermedad Mental Grave (Madrid y Sevilla, septiembre - octubre 2009). Resultados:Se recogieron 5.473 encuestas, 55,8% en Sevilla. El 66,2% de la muestra eran mujeres y la edad media 35 años (DE=14,5). El 82% conocía ambas enfermedades, pero el 51% no conocía ningún síntoma de la esquizofrenia. Otras opiniones destacables: son difíciles de diagnosticar (59%), no se diagnostican por rechazo social (27%), interfieren bastante en la vida cotidiana (49%) o impiden la vida normal (42%), los tratamientos eficaces son psicológicos (82%) y farmacológicos (72%). Las creencias refieren: rechazo social, sobrecarga familiar y sufrimiento del paciente. Las preocupaciones refieren: peligrosidad, rechazo social, falta de información y escasez de recursos. Conclusiones:Existe desconocimiento sobre la sintomatología. La mayoría desconoce síntomas específicos y resalta los negativos. Se atribuye mayor eficacia al tratamiento conjunto psicológico-farmacológico. Preocupan la estigmatización y la sobrecarga familiar y personal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);5(2): 98-106, abr.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opiniones y creencias sobre las enfermedades mentales graves (esquizofrenia y trastorno bipolar) en la sociedad española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
