<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136613</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraoperative floppy iris syndrome after treatment with duloxetine: coincidence, association, or causality?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: The case is presented of a severe Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome (IFIS) in a patient that had been treated with duloxetine. Discussion: Tamsulosin is the main etiological agent involved in IFIS. However several cases of IFIS, supposedly secondary to drugs of different groups have recently been reported in the literature. The authors use this case report as a means to discuss why most of these cases should be considered anecdotal evidence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zarallo-Gallardo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Miguel, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Martín-Moro,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-López,  J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta un caso de síndrome de iris flácido intraoperatorio (IFIS) severo en una paciente que había recibido tratamiento con duloxetina. Discusión: Aunque el agente etiológico principal es la tamsulosina, se han descrito casos de IFIS supuestamente secundarios a fármacos pertenecientes a diversos grupos farmacológicos. Los autores utilizan este caso para realizar un análisis crítico de todas estas asociaciones anecdóticas comunicadas en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(2): 94-96, feb. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de iris flácido intraoperatorio tras tratamiento con duloxetina: ¿casualidad, asociación o causalidad?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28111^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28111^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28111^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28111^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
