<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055477</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metaplastic ossification in nasal polyp</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metaplasia is the production by cells of a kind of tissue other than that corresponding to their lineage, ie it represents the conversion of one tissue into another. Bony metaplasia has frequently been described in polyps of the gastrointestinal tract. In nasal polyposis it is an extremely uncommon finding.         We describe the case of a 42 year-old female presenting nasal obstruction due to a unilateral nasal tumour. She was operated on by means of endoscopic sinonasal surgery and the definitive diagnosis was nasal polyposis with areas of bony metaplasia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poyato Zamorano, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marques Asin, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Iniesta, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cantero, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Moyano, Juan Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La metaplasia es la producción por parte de las células de un tipo de tejido distinto del de su estirpe; es el cambio de un tejido en otro. La metaplasia ósea ha sido descrita en pólipos del tracto gastrointestinal con cierta frecuencia. En la poliposis nasal es un hecho extremadamente infrecuente.         Describimos el caso de una paciente de 42 años con clínica de obstrucción nasal; presentaba una tumoración nasal unilateral y fue intervenida mediante abordaje endoscópico nasosinusal. El diagnóstico definitivo fue poliposis nasal con áreas de metaplasia ósea</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(6): 276-277, jun.-jul. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055477</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metaplasia ósea en pólipo nasal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28183^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30396^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
