<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94226</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of immigration on tuberculosis transmission patterns in Castellón, Spain (2004&#150;2007)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This study aimed to identify tuberculosis transmission patterns in Castellón in a period ofmajor demographic changes. Methods: A prospective study of patients with positive culture in the province of Castellon over a 4-yearperiod (2004&#150;2007) was carried out. Cases were described by year and nationality and were compared with those reported to the Department of Public Health. We studied the population with available molecular patterns, identified through restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) and analyzed the variables from patient clusters, based on data collected in surveys of the Department of Health and the Laboratory Management Program. Results: According to data from the Department of Public Health, the overall rate of tuberculosis per100,000 inhabitants in the province of Castellón was 15.7 in 2004, 19.9 in 2005, 18.2 in 2006 and 17.5 in 2007. In our laboratory, strains were identified from 301 patients, representing 77% (301/390) of reported cases and 94% (301/321) of reported cases with a positive culture. The percentage of tuberculosis amongforeigners increased with age, exceeding 50% in 2007. Molecular studies were available in 95% of patients (286); 58% were Spanish and 42% were foreigners, of whom 54% were Romanians. The cluster percentage was 40%, with 30% of mixed clusters. According to conventional contact studies, 85% of patients in clusters had been considered isolated cases.Conclusions: The increased rate of tuberculosis in Castellón was mainly due to the increasing numberof cases among foreigners, mostly Romanians. The availability of molecular studies in all patients with apositive culture allowed us to analyze how and where tuberculosis is transmitted in our province. Forty percent of the patients were grouped into clusters; of these, mixed clusters accounted for one third,indicating the high integration of immigrants in our area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romeu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomila, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeu, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los patrones de transmisión de la tuberculosis en Castellón en un periodo de importantes cambios demográficos. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo descriptivo de los pacientes con cultivo positivo en la provincia de Castellón entre 2004 y2007. Se describen los pacientes por año y nacionalidad, y se cotejan con los casos declarados a la Dirección General de Salud Pública (DGSP). Se estudia la población con patrón molecular disponible por RFLP (restriction fragment length polymorphism) y se analizan las variables de los pacientes agrupados (clusters) a partir de los datos de la DGSP y del Programa de Gestión del Laboratorio.Resultados: Según la DGSP, la tasa global de tuberculosis por 100.000 habitantes en la provincia de Castellón fue de 15,7 en 2004, 19,9 en 2005, 18,2 en 2006 y 17,5 en 2007. En nuestro laboratorio se identificaron las cepas de 301 pacientes, que suponen el 77% (301/390) de los casos declarados y el94% (301/321) aquellos con cultivo positivo. El porcentaje de tuberculosis en extranjeros aumentó hasta superar el 50% en 2007. Se disponía de estudio molecular en el 95% de los casos (286), con un 58% deespañoles y un 42% de extranjeros. El porcentaje de agregación fue del 40%, con un 30% de clusters mixtos.Según el estudio convencional de contactos, el 85% de los pacientes en cluster habían sido considerados casos aislados. Conclusiones: El aumento de la tasa de tuberculosis en Castellón se debe, principalmente, al creciente número de los casos en extranjeros. Disponer del estudio molecular de todos los pacientes con cultivo positivo nos ha permitido analizar cómo y dónde se transmite la tuberculosis. El 40% de los pacientes se agruparon en clusters, y eran mixtos un tercio de ellos, lo que indica una elevada integración de los inmigrantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(2): 122-126, may. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la inmigración en los patrones de transmisión de la tuberculosis en Castellón (2004&#150;2007)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28897^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
