<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163049</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on the treatment of RASopathies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The term «RASopathies» covers a series of diseases that present mutations in the genes that code for the proteins of the RAS/MAPK pathway. These diseases include neurofibromatosis type 1, Noonan syndrome, Legius syndrome, LEOPARD syndrome, Costello syndrome and cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome. Involvement of the RAS/MAPK pathway not only increases predisposition to develop tumours, but also determines the presence of phenotypic anomalies and alterations in learning processes. Aim. To review the use of therapeutic strategies with mechanisms that have a selective action on RASopathies. Development. The fact that the RAS pathway is involved in a third of all neoplasms has led to the development and study of different drugs at this level. Some of these pharmaceutical agents have been tested in RASopathies, mainly in neurofibromatosis type 1. Here we analyse the use of different antitarget treatments: drugs that act on the membrane receptors, such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors, in the mTOR pathway or MEK inhibitors. These latter have shown potential benefits in recent studies conducted on different RASopathies. Conclusions. Today, thanks to the results from the first studies conducted with MEK inhibitor based mainly on animal models, a number of promising clinical trials are being carried out (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Martín, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duat-Rodríguez, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El término «rasopatías» agrupa una serie de enfermedades que presentan mutaciones en genes que codifican las proteínas de la vía RAS/MAPK. Estas enfermedades incluyen la neurofibromatosis de tipo 1, el síndrome de Noonan, el síndrome de Legius, el síndrome LEOPARD, el síndrome de Costello y el síndrome cardiofaciocutáneo. La afectación de la vía RAS/MAPK no sólo aumenta la predisposición a desarrollar tumores, sino que también determina la presencia de anomalías fenotípicas y alteraciones en los procesos de aprendizaje. Objetivo. Revisar el papel del uso de estrategias terapéuticas con mecanismos de acción selectivo en las rasopatías. Desarrollo. El hecho de que la vía RAS participe en un tercio de las neoplasias ha motivado el desarrollo y el estudio de distintos fármacos a este nivel. Algunos de estos fármacos han sido probados en las rasopatías, principalmente en la neurofibromatosis de tipo 1. Analizamos el uso de distintos tratamientos antidiana: fármacos que actúan en los receptores de membrana, como los inhibidores de la tirosincinasa, en la vía mTOR o los inhibidores de MEK. Existe un potencial beneficio de estos últimos en estudios recientes realizados en distintas rasopatías. Conclusiones. Actualmente, gracias a los resultados de los primeros trabajos desarrollados con inhibidor de MEK basados principalmente en modelos animales, se están realizando múltiples ensayos clínicos prometedores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(supl.3): s13-s17, 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización del tratamiento de las rasopatías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31254^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31254^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9821^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30086^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34448^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54051^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19589^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29058^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
