<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16348</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaccine Storage Cold Chain at Primary Care Centers in one Area of Madrid: Keeping the Chain Intact and Degree of Knowledge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Vaccines are heat-labile medications, and to guarantee their immunogenicity and safeguarding effectiveness as part of immunization programs, it is absolutely essential that the «Cold Chain» go unbroken. Fundamental thereto is the personnel responsible for the vaccines, who must know the stability-related characteristics of each preparation so as to prevent handling errors. The purpose of this study was that of ascertaining how the cold chain is kept intact in primary care systems in one healthcare area of the Autonomous Community of Madrid, as well as determining the degree of information possessed by those responsible for vaccines as far as their heat-stability is concerned. Methods. A cross-sectional study has been made at 46 primary care vaccination points. The data was gathered by means of a personal interview by one single researcher. Results. The participation rate was 93.5% (43/46). In all cases, there was a maximum and minimum thermometer and monthly temperature record. An unsuitable temperature was found in three cases (6.97%). The percentage of professionals who were aware of the effect freezing has on vaccines varied greatly: 53.5%, 51.2%, 44.2% and 53.5% for diphtheria-tetanus-pertussis (DTP), hepatitis B (HBV), oral polio (OPV) and measles-mumps-rubella (MMR) respectively. And only 32% were familiar with the shake test. Conclusion. The professionals were found to be properly trained regarding the effect which high temperatures have on vaccines, but it is necessary for their training with regard to the instability of adsorbed preparations when frozen must be further strengthened (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Las vacunas son medicamentos termolábiles y para garantizar su inmunogenicidad y eficacia protectora, dentro de los programas de inmunización, es imprescindible mantener la cadena de frío. El elemento fundamental en esta cadena es el personal responsable de las vacunas, que debe conocer las características de estabilidad de cada preparado con el fin de evitar errores durante su manipulación. El objetivo de este trabajo fue conocer cómo se realiza el mantenimiento de la cadena del frío en equipos de atención primaria de un área sanitaria de la Comunidad Autónoma de Madrid, así como establecer el grado de información que poseen los responsables de las vacunas con respecto a la termoestabilidad de las mismas.Métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio transversal en 46 puntos de vacunación en atención primaria. La recogida de los datos se realizó mediante entrevista personal por un único investigador.Resultados. La tasa de participación fue del 93,5 per cent (43/46). En todos los casos existía termómetro de máxima y mínima y registro mensual de la temperatura. Se observó una temperatura inadecuada en tres ocasiones (6,97 per cent). El porcentaje de profesionales que conocía el efecto que la congelación producía sobre las vacunas fue muy diverso: 53.5 per cent, 51.2 per cent, 44.2 per cent y 53.5 per cent para difteria-tétanos-pertussis (DTP), hepatitis B (VHB), polio oral (VPO) y rubéola-sarampión-paperas (RSP) respectivamente. Y sólo el 32 per cent conocía el test de agitación.Conclusión. La formación de los profesionales sobre el efecto que las altas temperaturas ocasionan en las vacunas era correcta, pero es necesario reforzar su formación sobre la inestabilidad que presentan los preparados adsorbidos cuando se someten a congelación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(4): 333-346, jul. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cadena del frío para la conservación de las vacunas en los centros de atención primaria de un area de Madrid: mantenimiento y nivel de conocimientos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rábago, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albaladejo Vicente, Romana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Molina, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Rojas, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astasio Arbiza, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanes Pardo, José Ramón de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16348</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12456</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
