<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116548</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of differents training parameters and incidence of injury in aerobic gymnastics sporstmen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present work has been to analyze the characteristics of training and its relation with the appearance of injuries in competition Aerobic Gymnasts. This is a retrospective longitudinal study using a questionnaire-interview given to 42 gymnasts from junior and senior categories with a mean age of 18.78 (± 5.84) years who competed in the 2011 Spanish Champion ship. The variables studied were the time of practice, hours and days of training, planning, safety equipment, regulatory landing surfaces and the injuries suffered by the gymnasts studied. The most numerous injuries were to muscles and joints.65.78% were to the lower limb, 21.06% to the upper limb, and the remaining 13.15% to the trunk. 84.21% of the injuries suffered by the athletes were moderately serious. The greatest number of gymnastics affected did not use protective measures, the injury index being grater during training then in competition. 44.13% had to go to the doctor, and needed rehabilitation and presented sequels. This information shows that the appearance of injuries is related to the scanty use of protection material and training on unsuitable surfaces provoking overload injuries due to impact. For this reason, it is relevant to inform coaches of these results to enable them to implement the necessary measures to prevent the occurrence of injuries or minimize their severity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abalo, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vernetta, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Sánchez, Águeda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo ha sido analizar las características del entrenamiento y su relación con la aparición de lesiones en los deportistas de Gimnasia Aeróbica de Competición. Para ello se desarrolla un estudio descriptivo longitudinal retrospectivo a través de un cuestionario-entrevista a 42 gimnastas de las categorías junior y senior con una edad media de 18,78 años (±5,84) que compitieron en el Campeonato de España del 2011. Las variables objeto de estudio han sido el tiempo de práctica, horas y días de entrenamiento, planificación, material de seguridad, suelo reglamentario y las lesiones sufridas por los gimnastas sometidos al estudio. Las lesiones más numerosas han sido las musculares y las articulares. Los 65,78% producidas en el miembro inferior, 21,06% en el miembro superior, y el 13,15% restante en el tronco. El 84,21% de las lesiones padecidas por los deportistas han sido de gravedad moderada. Se encontró que el mayor número de afectados no utilizan medidas de protección, siendo el índice lesional mayor durante el entrenamiento que en la competición. Se destaca que el 44,13% acuden al médico, necesitan rehabilitación y presentan secuelas. Estos datos muestran que, la aparición de lesiones está relacionada con el escaso uso del material de protección y el entrenamiento en superficies no adecuadas provocando lesiones de sobrecarga debido al impacto. De ahí, la necesidad de poner en conocimiento de los entrenadores estos resultados con el fin de que puedan poner en marcha las medidas necesarias para prevenir la aparición de las lesiones o minimizar la gravedad de las mismas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;29(150): 740-749, jul.-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116548</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de diferentes parámetros de entrenamiento e incidencia lesional en deportistas de gimnasia aeróbica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
