<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33116</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasonography in diagnosis and monitoring of dissection of cervicocerebral arteries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ultrasonography has become part of the arsenal of diagnostic methods available for examining the dissection of cerebral blood vessels (DCV). Aims. To analyse the value of ultrasonography in the diagnosis and monitoring of DCV. Patients and methods. We conducted a consecutive study of 67 patients with a history and clinical manifestations compatible with DCV; all of them were given confirmation of their diagnosis by another reference method (digital angiography or MR angiography) during the 48 hours prior to or following the ultrasound study. The ultrasonography was carried out on the neck and skull as per the usual system using continuous Doppler, neck duplex and transcranial Doppler ultrasonography. Ultrasound diagnosis of the dissection was based on direct and indirect signs, in the absence of an atheroma plaque. The following were considered to be direct signs: haematoma in the wall of the vessel, flap, local increase in flow velocity and echograms with split systole. Indirect signs were: haemodynamic alterations proximal to the dissection, a pattern of slow flow and high resistance. Transcranial Doppler showed the findings lying distal to the dissection to be a lowered mean velocity and pulsatility. Results. The ultrasonography of the series revealed direct signs in 46 patients (69%) and indirect signs in 21 (31%). Ultrasonography was used as the primary diagnostic method in 29 (43%) patients; in the other 38 (57%) it was employed to verify the diagnosis or for the follow-up. All the ultrasound diagnoses were confirmed using digital angiography (21 cases) or magnetic resonance angiography (46 cases). Conclusions. Due to its harmlessness, ultrasonography may be the first examination used to establish a probable diagnosis of DVC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La ecografía se ha incorporado al arsenal de métodos diagnósticos disponibles para el examen de la disección de vasos cerebrales (DVC). Objetivo. Analizar la utilidad de la ecografía en el diagnóstico y el seguimiento de la DVC. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio consecutivo de 67 pacientes con antecedentes y clínica compatibles con DVC, que dentro de las 48 horas previas o posteriores al estudio ecográfico tuvieron confirmación diagnóstica con otro método de referencia -angiografía digital o angiorresonancia magnética-. La ecografía se realizó en el cuello y cráneo según la sistemática habitual, mediante estudio Doppler continuo, dúplex de cuello y estudio Doppler transcraneal. El diagnóstico de disección se basó en signos directos e indirectos, en ausencia de placas de ateroma. Se consideraron signos directos: hematoma de la pared del vaso, flap, aumento localizado de la velocidad del flujo y ecogramas con sístole bífida; como signos indirectos: alteraciones hemodinámicas proximales a la disección y patrón de flujo de baja velocidad y alta resistencia. En el estudio Doppler transcraneal se apreciaron los hallazgos distales a la disección: disminución de la velocidad media y pulsatilidad. Resultados. La ecografía de la serie reveló signos directos en 46 pacientes (69 por ciento) e indirectos en 21 (31 por ciento). La ecografía se empleó como método primario de diagnóstico en 29 (43 por ciento) pacientes; en los 38 (57 por ciento) restantes, para verificar el diagnóstico o para el seguimiento. Todos los diagnósticos ecográficos se confirmaron mediante angiografía digital (21 casos) o angiorresonancia magnética (46 casos). Conclusiones. Por su inocuidad y fiabilidad, la ecografía debería constituir el primer examen para establecer un diagnóstico presuntivo de DVC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(9): 813-817, mayo 2004. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ecografía en el diagnóstico y el control evolutivo de las disecciones de las arterias cervicocerebrales</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Blanco García- Barroso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Cabezas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cejas Archidamo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nobo López, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ameriso Martínez, SF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lagos Grinstein, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cisneros, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33116</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30991</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
