<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115909</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of depressive symptoms in hospitalized elderly medical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Depressive symptoms in hospitalized patients are very common, and they have been related to higher mortality. The aim of the study was to estimate the prevalence of depressive symptoms in hospitalized elderly patients and its relationship to various diseases, as well as their functional and mental status and mortality. Material and methods: A total of 115 patients over 64 years of age were prospectively studied. The validated Spanish version of the Geriatric Depression Scale of Yesavage (15-item version) was used. Patients were considered to have depressive symptoms if &gt;=6 points were obtained. The demographic characteristics, the Charlson comorbidity index, the diagnosis at admission, the functional status assessed by the Barthel and Lawton-Brodie index, the mental capacity assessed by the Pfeiffer questionnaire, the length of the hospital stay, and hospital mortality were recorded. Results: Out of the 115 patients studied, with a mean age of 70.5 years, 71 (61.7%) were female. Depressive symptoms were observed in 46 patients (40%, 95% CI: 34.8-43.9). Patients who died showed a significantly higher score on the Yesavage scale (P=.04). The multivariate analysis showed a significantly independent association between depressive symptoms and functional capacity (P=.026), mental status (P=.021), renal failure (P=.001), liver disease (P=.018), and osteoarthritis (P=.017), but losing the previously seen significant association with diabetes (P=.43). Conclusions: The prevalence of depressive symptoms in hospitalized elderly patients is high, and is associated with the diagnoses of renal failure, liver disease and osteoarthritis, with a higher comorbidity and especially with a poorer functional capacity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conde Martel, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Fuentes, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hemmersbach-Miller, Marion</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anía Lafuente, Basilio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sujanani Afonso, Natacha</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los síntomas depresivos en los pacientes mayores hospitalizados son muy frecuentes, y se han asociado a una mayor mortalidad. Nos planteamos estimar la prevalencia de los síntomas depresivos en los ancianos hospitalizados y su relación con distintas afecciones, así como con su situación funcional, mental y mortalidad. Material y métodos. Se estudiaron prospectivamente 115 pacientes mayores de 64 años. Se utilizó la escala de depresión geriátrica de Yesavage en su versión de 15 ítems validada en español. Se consideró la presencia de los síntomas depresivos si se obtenían de 6 o más puntos. Se recogieron las características demográficas, el índice de comorbilidad de Charlson, los diagnósticos de ingreso, la situación funcional evaluada mediante el índice de Barthel y de Lawton-Brody, la capacidad mental evaluada mediante el cuestionario de Pfeiffer, la estancia y la mortalidad hospitalaria. Resultados. De los 115 pacientes estudiados con una edad media de 70,5 años, 71 (61,7%) eran mujeres. Se observaron síntomas depresivos en 46 pacientes (40%; IC 95%: 34,8-43,9). Los pacientes que fallecieron mostraron una puntuación significativamente superior en la prueba de Yesavage (p = 0,04). En el análisis multivariante se observó la asociación significativa independiente entre los síntomas depresivos y la capacidad funcional (p = 0,026), la capacidad mental (p = 0,021), la insuficiencia renal (p = 0,001), la hepatopatía (p = 0,018) y la artrosis (p = 0.017), perdiéndose la significación obtenida previamente para la diabetes (p = 0,43). Conclusiones. La prevalencia de síntomas depresivos en los ancianos hospitalizados es elevada, y se asocia con los diagnósticos de insuficiencia renal, hepatopatía y artrosis, con una mayor comorbilidad y especialmente con una peor capacidad funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);48(5): 224-227, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones de los síntomas depresivos en los ancianos hospitalizados por afección médica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
