<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122504</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between vitamin D deficiency and metabolic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Vitamin D deficiency and metabolic syndrome are 2 very common health problems in the Spanish population. It has been suggested that patients with metabolic syndrome may be vitamin D deficient more often than subjects without it and that low vitamin D levels may predispose to metabolic syndrome development. However, the results of prospective and intervention studies have been different and such relationship remains unclear. We assessed the relationship between 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels and the prevalence and incidence of metabolic syndrome. Patients and methods: We undertook a population-based cohort study in Spain. At baseline (1996-1998),  1,226 subjects were evaluated. Follow-up visits were performed in 2002-2004 and 2005-2007.At baseline and follow-up, participants underwent an interview and a standardized clinical examination with an oral glucose tolerance test in those subjects without known diabetes. At the second visit, 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels and intact parathyroid hormone levels were measured. Results: The prevalence of metabolic syndrome at the second and third visit was 29.4 and 42.5%, respectively. Mean levels of 25-hydroxyvitamin D were lower in subjects with metabolic syndrome: 21.7 (6.21) vs 23.35 (6.29) ng/ml, P &lt; .001.The prevalence of vitamin D deficiency (25-hydroxyvitamin D &lt; 20 ng/ml) at the second evaluation was 34.7%, with significant differences between subjects with and without metabolic syndrome(34.6 vs 26.5%, P &lt; .01). Men with vitamin D deficiency had more frequently hypertension and metabolic syndrome than men with normal levels. Women with vitamin D deficiency had more frequently hyperglycemia, hypertension, increased waist circumference and hypertriglyceridemia. In a prospective study, 25-hydroxyvitaminD values &lt; 20 ng/ml were not significantly associated with an increased risk of developing metabolic syndrome in the next 5 years (odds ratio 0,99, 95% confidence interval 0.57-1.7, P = .97) after adjusting by sex and age. Conclusions: Vitamin D deficiency is associated with an increased prevalence but not with an increased incidence of metabolic syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Repiso, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriguer, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Martín, Eleazara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morcillo, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Valero, Vidal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Molero, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El déficit de vitamina D y el síndrome metabólico son 2 entidades muy frecuentes en población española. Se ha sugerido que los pacientes con síndrome metabólico pueden tener déficit de vitamina D con mayor frecuencia que los sujetos sin e´ l, y que unos valores bajos de vitamina D pueden predisponer al desarrollo de síndrome metabólico. No obstante, los resultados de estudios prospectivos y de intervención han sido diversos, sin que se haya aclarado por el momento si existe esta relación. El objetivo de este trabajo fue evaluar la relación entre los valores de 25-hidroxivitamina D y la prevalencia e incidencia del síndrome metabólico. Pacientes y método: Se realizó´ un estudio poblacional de cohortes. Al inicio del estudio (1996-1998), 1.226 pacientes fueron evaluados. Las visitas de seguimiento se llevaron a cabo en 2002-2004 y 2005-2007. Basalmente y durante el seguimiento, los participantes se sometieron a una entrevista y un examen clínico estandarizado con una prueba de tolerancia oral a la glucosa. En la segunda visita se midieron la 25-hidroxivitamina D y los valores de parathormona intacta. Resultados: La prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en la segunda y la tercera evaluación fue del 29,4 y del 42,5%, respectivamente. Los valores medios (DE) de 25-hidroxivitamina D fueron menores en los pacientes con síndrome metabólico, 21,7 (6,21) frente a 23,35 (6,29) ng/ml, p &lt; 0,001. La prevalencia de deficiencia de vitamina D (25-hidroxivitamina D &lt; 20 ng/ml) en la segunda evaluación fue del 34,7%, con diferencias significativas entre los sujetos con y sin síndrome metabólico (34,6 frente a 26,5%, p &lt; 0,01). Los varones con deficiencia de vitamina D tuvieron con mayor frecuencia hipertensión y síndrome metabólico que aquellos con valores normales. Las mujeres con deficiencia de vitamina D tuvieron ma´ s frecuentemente hiperglucemia, hipertensión, aumento de la circunferencia de la cintura e  hipertrigliceridemia. En el estudio prospectivo, los valores de 25-hidroxivitamina D &lt; 20 ng/ml no se asociaron significativamente con un mayor riesgo de desarrollar el síndrome metabólico en los siguientes 5 años (odds ratio 0,99, intervalo de confianza del 95% 0,57-1,7, p &lt; 0,97) después de ajustar por sexo y edad. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con síndrome metabólico tienen con mayor frecuencia déficit de vitamina D, pero este no predice el riesgo de desarrollar síndrome metabólico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(11): 473-477, jun. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre déficit de vitamina D y síndrome metabólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6096^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
