<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042354</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The affective dimensional structure of emotions: a comparative study on anger and fear</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study presented in this paper is mainly based on the theoretical framework namely circumplex model of affect put forward by Russell &amp; Feldman Barrett (1999). The aim of the present paper is to study in detail how subjects experience fear and anger in terms of affective dimensions, by presenting two modalities of imaged scenarios: (1) an imagining situation induced by the experimenter, and (2) an imagining situation selected by the subject (free recall) for each emotion. Results showed that subjects scored similar patterns of affective core feelings for both emotions in the modality of free recall. However, there were significant differences between fear and anger for the modality of induced emotions regarding degree of realism and arousal. Anger situation was imaged more realistic than fear one, while anxiety situation scored as more activated than anger one. Our data support the Russell &amp; Feldman Barrett's model with regard to the arousal affective dimension but not in relation to the pleasure affective dimension, due to anger and fear did not reflect significant differences regarding along the pleasant-unpleasant positional dimension</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Nieto, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ordi, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo se fundamenta en el estudio de la estructura de las emociones a partir de las dimensiones afectivas del modelo circunflejo de Russell y Feldman Barrett (1999). El objetivo de este estudio es explorar en detalle cómo los sujetos experimentan ira y miedo en términos de dichas dimensiones afectivas, presentándoles dos modalidades de escenarios a imaginar para cada emoción: (1) situación imaginada inducida por el experimentador y (2) situación imaginada elegida por el sujeto (recuerdo libre). Los resultados muestran que los sujetos valoraron de forma similar ambas emociones en la modalidad de recuerdo libre. Sin embargo, existieron diferencias significativas entre el miedo y la ira en la modalidad de inducción por el experimentador en relación al grado de realismo y el grado de activación producido por cada emoción. La situación de ira fue imaginada con más realismo que la situación de miedo, mientras que la situación de miedo produjo mayor activación auto informada que la ira. Nuestros resultados apoyan la propuesta del modelo circunflejo sobre la ira y el miedo sólo en la dimensión de activación-desactivación pero no en la dimensión placer-displacer, donde el miedo y la ira ocuparían posiciones similares</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;11(2/3): 141-155, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La estructura afectiva de las emociones: un estudio comparativo sobre la ira y el miedo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d797^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
