<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050845</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric acute spinal cord injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction                 Pediatric acute spinal cord injury is rare but is often associated with significant disability and prolonged stay in the intensive care unit (ICU).                 Objectives                 The main objective of this study was to determine the epidemiology, initial clinical abnormalities, diagnostic studies, treatment and outcome of acute spinal cord injuries in a tertiary level pediatric hospital. A second objective was to analyze whether early tracheostomy allows earlier discharge of these patients.                 Patients and methods                 A retrospective analysis of patients with acute spinal cord injuries admitted to our pediatric ICU since 1992 was performed.                 Results                 We included 16 patients in the study, 12 of whom were boys (75 %). The patients were aged from birth to 19 years on admission to the ICU. The length of stay in the ICU was between 12 hours and 6 years. The cause of the lesion was birth trauma in four patients; one died and the remaining three live at home under mechanical ventilation. Traumatic injuries occurred in seven patients, two of whom died; a further two live in a long-term care facility and the remaining three live at home. Vascular spinal malformation occurred in two patients, and the three remaining injuries occurred during the acute postoperative period following spinal surgery. Of the 16 children, 56.2 % were tracheostomized and 83 % of the survivors live at home.                 Conclusions                 Early tracheostomy, the availability of invasive ventilation for home use and parent education permit earlier discharge of these patients and allow more of them to live at home</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trenchs Sáinz de la Maza, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claret Teruel, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomeque Rico, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción                 La lesión medular aguda es una entidad de escasa frecuencia en edad pediátrica pero adquiere especial relevancia debido a las graves secuelas y a las prolongadas estancias que provoca.                 Objetivos                 Conocer la epidemiología, forma de presentación, pruebas diagnósticas, tratamiento y evolución de las lesiones medulares agudas ingresadas en un hospital pediátrico de tercer nivel. Determinar el efecto que puede tener la traqueostomía precoz en el tiempo de estancia en la Unidad.                 Pacientes y métodos                 Se trata de un estudio retrospectivo de cohortes que revisa las lesiones medulares agudas ingresadas en nuestro centro desde el año 1992.                 Resultados                 Se recogieron 16 pacientes, 12 varones (75 %) con edades al ingreso comprendidas entre las pocas horas de vida y los 19 años. Los días de ingreso en la unidad de cuidados intensivos oscilaron entre 12 h y 6 años. En 4 casos la causa fue una lesión obstétrica; uno de ellos falleció y el resto se encuentran en su domicilio con ventilación mecánica. En 7 casos la causa fue traumática; fallecieron 2 pacientes, otros dos residen en un centro sociosanitario y tres en su domicilio. En 2 casos la causa fue una malformación vascular medular y los tres últimos se presentaron en el postoperatorio inmediato de una cirugía de columna. De los 16 pacientes recogidos el 56,2 % fueron traqueostomizados y el 83 % de los supervivientes residen en su domicilio.                 Conclusiones                 La realización precoz de la traqueostomía, la posibilidad de la ventilación mecánica domiciliaria y la instrucción de las familias ha permitido reducir la estancia de estos pacientes en la Unidad y que puedan residir en su casa</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);65(2): 162-165, ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesión medular aguda en edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
