<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92589</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Scale of Behavior Indicators of Pain (ESCID) in critically ill, non-communicative patients under mechanical ventilation: results of the ESCID scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the reliability and validity of the &#147;Scale of Behavior Indicators of Pain&#148; (Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor: ESCID) as a tool to assess pain in the critically ill, non-communicative patients with mechanical ventilation.MethodsAn observational study of development and validation of this scale as an instrument for pain measurement in ICU patients over 18 years of age, who are uncommunicative and under mechanical ventilation. Their pain was assessed with the Behavioral Pain Scale (BPS) and the ESCID simultaneously, by two independent observers, when the painful maneuvers (PM), secretion aspiration and mobilization, were applied. Measurements were obtained before, during and after the PM. A descriptive analysis of the general characteristics of the population was carried out. The reliability of the ESCID was measured through the internal consistency of each item using Cronbach's alpha. Intraobserver and interobserver concordance was measured with the repeated measurements analysis of variance test. The components of the two pain scales were compared to obtain the change between the results obtained based on time, observer and procedure. The correlation between the scales was measured with the Pearson's correlation.ResultsA total of 480 observations were obtained in 42 patients, 62% were males; age 57.33 ± 16.35 years. The most frequent ICU admission was due to infectious disease (36%) and neurological disease (35%). Glasgow Coma Scale 8.45±1.2 and Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale &amp;#8722;2.55±1.5. Arterial blood pressure, heart rate and respiratory rate remained stable. Cronbach's s Alpha Coefficient for ESCID ranged from 0.70-0.80. There is a good correlation between the ESCID and BPS in the three measurement points in time: Pearson's correlation: before 0.97, during 0.94 and after 0.95.ConclusionsESCID is a reliable and valid tool to assess pain in critically ill, non-communicative patients under mechanical ventilation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Larrasquitu Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre Marco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romay Pérez, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán Santos, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falero Ruiz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDeterminar la fiabilidad y la validez de la Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor (ESCID) para valorar el dolor en pacientes críticos, no comunicativos y sometidos a ventilación mecánica (VM).MétodosEstudio observacional de desarrollo y validación de una escala como instrumento de medida en pacientes ingresados en UCI mayores de 18 años, con VM, no comunicativos. Se evaluó el dolor con las escalas Behavioural Pain Scale (BPS) y ESCID, simultáneamente, por dos evaluadores independientes, en aplicación de dos procedimientos dolorosos (PD): movilización y aspiración de secreciones, medidos antes, durante y después del PD. Análisis descriptivo de las características generales de la muestra. La fiabilidad de ESCID se midió a través de la consistencia interna de cada ítem con el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach. Mediante análisis de varianza de medidas repetidas se midió concordancia interobservador e intraobservador; se compararon los componentes de las dos escalas de dolor para medir el cambio entre los resultados obtenidos en función del tiempo, observador y procedimiento. La correlación entre las dos escalas se midió con la correlación de Pearson.ResultadosCuatrocientas ochenta observaciones en 42 pacientes, 62% varones; edad 57,33 ±16,35. Predomina patología infecciosa (36%) y neurológica (35%). Glasgow Coma Scale 8,45 ± 1,2 y Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale &amp;#8722;2,55 ± 1,5. La tensión arterial, frecuencia cardiaca y frecuencia respiratoria se mantuvieron estables. El coeficiente alfa de Cronbach para ESCID osciló entre 0,70-0,80. Existe una buena correlación entre ESCID y BPS, en los tres momentos de medición: correlación de Pearson antes 0,97, durante 0,94 y después 0,95.ConclusionesESCID constituye una herramienta útil y válida para valorar el dolor en pacientes críticos, no comunicativos y sometidos a VM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;22(1): 3-12, ene. -mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor para valorar el dolor en pacientes críticos, no comunicativos y sometidos a ventilación mecánica: resultados del proyecto ESCID</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
