<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61054</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopy-assisted surgery of the sellar region</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the usefulness of endoscopic assisted surgery of pituitary adenomas in transesphenoidal surgery, and in surgery of craneopharyngiomas using either minimally invasive approaches to the cranial base or transventricular approaches. Material and methods:We present our preliminary experience in eleven patients operated of sellar region  umor by endoscopic assisted resection: 6 pituitary adenoma via transesphenoidal approach, 4 craneopharyngiomas 3 throung supraciliar approach and 1 by transcortical transventricular approach, and 1 suprasellar cyst. Results: By using the 30 degrees optic the use of endoscope allowed complete resection, confirmed by postoperative MRI, of all six pituitary macroadenomas providing control of resection of supraselar remnants. Complete resection was achieved in three out of four craneopharyngiomas, 2 of them being recurrences. Three were operated by using a supraciliar approach to the cranial base and in one case transcortical transventricular resection of a recurrent intraventricular craneopharyngioma was performed. In the case with partial resection remnant were let in place due to the close adherence to peritumoral structures. In the three craneopharyngiomas operated via supraciliar approach endoscope allowed better control of inferior aspect of ipsilateral optic nerve and internal carotid artery. In the case of intraventricular craneopharyngioma, the use of 30 degrees endoscope provide control of resection of the anterior part of third ventricle through the foramen of Monro with no additional opening. The suprasellar cyst was fenestrated. Conclusions: No matter which approach is going to be used in the resection of sellar tumors, endoscopy can play a crucial role in achieve complete resection with minimal morbidity by using minimally invasive procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iñiesta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-Garijo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prat, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galeano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El estudio pretende evaluar la utilidad del uso del endoscopio en la cirugía de la región selar a través del abordaje transesfenoidal transnasal en los adenomas hipofisarios y a través de abordajes mínimamente invasivos a la base de cráneo o el sistema ventricular en el caso de craneofaringiomas. Material y métodos: Presentamos la experiencia preliminar en once casos intervenidos mediante cirugía asistida con endoscopia. Seis pacientes presentaban macroadenomas hipofisarios y fueron intervenidos por vía transesfenoidal transnasal. Cuatro pacientes presentaban craneofaringiomas, 2 de ellos recidivantes, que fueron abordados, 3 a través de un acceso supraciliar y uno mediante un abordaje transcortical transventricular, abordaje utilizado en un quiste supraselar intraventricular. Resultados : Se consiguió la exéresis completa confirmada por RM de los adenomas hipofisarios en los que el uso del endoscopio con óptica de 30° fue de utilidad en el control de la exéresis de los tumores con expansión supraselar. En el caso de los craneofaringiomas se alcanzó la exéresis completa en 3 de ellos uno de los cuales era recidivante, 2 por vía supraciliar y otro transcortical transventricular. En el caso restante, un craneofaringioma recidivante, la exéresis fue parcial por la íntima adherencia de la cápsula tumoral a las estructuras circundantes. En los 3 casos de acceso supraciliar, el endoscopio fue útil para el control de la exéresis del tumor localizado inferior al nervio óptico y la carótida interna ipsilaterales. En el acceso intraventricular el craneofaringioma que ocupaba el tercio anterior y medio del tercer ventrículo pudo resecarse a través del foramen de Monro, mediante una óptica de 30° que permitió controlar y resecar el resto tumoral del tercio anterior. El quiste fue fenestrado. Conclusiones: En cualquiera de las posibles vías de abordaje a la región selar, el uso de la cirugía asistida por endoscopia favorece una mayor radicalidad en la resección mediante el uso de abordajes mínimamente invasivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);19(6): 501-506, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de la región selar asistida por endoscopia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13040^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11344^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
