<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79116</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic embolization of uterine leiomyomas: cases requiring surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To retrospectively analyze the clinical, radiolgical, and histological findings in patients with uterine leiomyomas (LU) that required surgical intervention after embolization. Material and methods. Between July 1999 and January 2006, we embolized 182 patients with LU. Eight of these patients subsequently required surgical resection of the tumor. We reviewed clinical data, imaging findings, embolization technique, and reasons for surgery, histological findings in the resected specimens, identification and location of the embolizing material, presence and type of necrosis in the LU, and associated pathology in adjacent organs. Results. The 8 patients that required surgery represented 4.3% of all patients embolized for LU. Surgery was necessary due to technical failure in two patients (1.02%), complications in three (1.64%) and failed treatment in the remaining three 3 (1.64%). The mean maximum diameter of the LU was 9.8 cm (range: 4-17 cm). The mean volume of the LU was 491.88 ml (range: 30-1.365 ml) The mean age of the patients was 37.7 years (range: 28-48 years). Global necrosis was evident in 6 LU; necrosis was hyaline type in 3 and inflammatory in the remaining 3. The embolizing material was detected in the LU in one case, in the uterine myometrium in two cases, and in the ovary in one. Conclusion. Less than 5% of cases of LU required surgery after embolization; the risk of surgery after embolization was greater in large lesions. When the embolization technique was adequate, histological study confirmed global necrosis of the tumors, although this was not accompanied by clinical improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Revillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Seoane, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosculluela, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Análisis retrospectivo clínico, radiológico y patológico de pacientes con leiomiomas uterinos (LU) que requirieron intervención quirúrgica tras el tratamiento con embolización. Material y métodos. Desde julio de 1999 hasta enero de 2006 se embolizaron 182 pacientes con LU. Del total de ellas, 8 precisaron intervención quirúrgica con extirpación del tumor. Revisamos retrospectivamente, en estas 8 pacientes, datos clínicos, hallazgos de pruebas por imagen, técnica de embolización y causas de la cirugía, hallazgos histológicos en las piezas extirpadas, identificación y localización del material embolizante (ME), presencia y tipo de necrosis en los LU y patología asociada en órganos adyacentes. Resultados. Las 8 pacientes intervenidas representan un 4,3% del total de pacientes embolizadas. La causa fue por fallo técnico en dos (1,02%), complicaciones en tres (1,64%) y fallo en el tratamiento en otras tres (1,64%). La media de los diámetros máximos de los LU fue de 9,8 cm (rango: 4-17 cm). El volumen medio de los LU fue de 491,88 ml (rango: 30-1,365 ml). La edad media de las pacientes fue de 37,7 años (rango: 28-48 años). Histológicamente se evidenció necrosis global en 6 de los LU, siendo de tipo hialino en 3 e inflamatorio en los otros 3. El ME se detectó en el LU (un caso), en el miometrio uterino (dos casos) y en un ovario (un caso). Conclusión. Los casos de LU que requieren cirugía posembolización son inferiores al 5%, existiendo mayor riesgo en los de gran tamaño. Cuando la técnica de embolización fue adecuada, el estudio histológico confirmó la necrosis global de los tumores, aunque este hecho no se acompañó de mejoría clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);50(5): 409-415, sept. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolización terapéutica de leiomiomas uterinos; casos que requirieron cirugía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9407^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
