<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79762</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ovarian and inferior vena cava thrombosis with associated puerperal endometritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ovarian vein thrombosis is a rare and severe puerperal complication that usually manifests as fever and abdominal pain in the puerperal period and is more frequent in women who have undergone cesarean section. There is an associated high risk of pulmonary embolism and thus early diagnosis and treatment are required. We report the case of a 30-year-old woman with pelvic pain and fever in the puerperal period. Computed tomography scan revealed ovarian vein thrombosis extending to the inferior vena cava. Endometritis was also diagnosed. The patient received dalteparin and antibiotics. Ovarian vein thrombosis should be included in the differential diagnosis of fever in the postpartum period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palavecino, Tamara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quinteros, Nancy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La trombosis de vena ovárica es una complicación infrecuente y grave del puerperio. Suele presentarse como fiebre y dolor abdominal o pélvico en el puerperio, más frecuentemente en cesáreas. Existe un riesgo alto de tromboembolismo pulmonar y requiere un diagnóstico y tratamiento tempranos. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 30 años, puérpera, con un cuadro de dolor pélvico y fiebre. Se realizó una tomografía computada y se detectó una trombosis de la vena ovárica derecha con extensión a la vena cava inferior. Se diagnosticó además endometritis, se trató con dalteparina y antibióticos. La trombosis de vena ovárica es un diagnóstico diferencial importante de fiebre en el puerperio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(5): 206-208, mayo 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de vena ovárica y vena cava inferior asociada a endometritis en el puerperio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4795^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15084^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
