<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102200</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biological markers for malignant pleural effusions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnostic process of patients with pleural effusion and high suspicion of malignancy often leads us to question the utility of some serum or pleural fluid tumor markers. Up to date, the tumor markers analyzed separately have not demonstrated sufficiently high diagnostic accuracy to obviate the study by cytology and histology of the pleura. This question has encouraged the development of multiple biochemical and immunohistochemical marker panels whose combination has made it possible to improve sensitivity and specificity, discriminate between benign and malignant lesions and between different tumor strains and it behaves as prognostic and survival factors. Currently, it is not possible to recommend specific marker panels for each strain, our objective being to make the existing evidence on this material more available to the clinician in order to have knowledge of the meanings of these markers and the convenience of knowing how to interpret the results obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Melchor Iñiguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Patrón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villena Garrido, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de Miguel Díez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara Chinarroa, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Ramírez, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pun Tam, Y. W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Santamaría, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Steen, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jareño Esteban, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el proceso diagnóstico de los pacientes con derrame pleural y alta sospecha de malignidad, nos preguntamos con cierta frecuencia sobre la utilidad de algunos marcadores tumorales séricos o del líquido pleural. Hasta la fecha, los marcadores tumorales analizados de forma aislada no han mostrado una precisión diagnóstica lo suficientemente elevada como para prescindir del estudio mediante citología e histología de la pleura. Esta cuestión ha estimulado el desarrollo de múltiples paneles de marcadores bioquímicos e inmunohistoquímicos cuya combinación ha permitido mejorar la sensibilidad y la especificidad, discriminar entre lesiones benignas y malignas, y entre diferentes estirpes tumorales. Asimismo, ha permitido que dichos paneles de marcadores sirvan como factores pronósticos y de supervivencia. Hoy por hoy, no es posible recomendar unos paneles de marcadores específicos para cada estirpe. Nuestro objetivo es acercar al clínico la evidencia existente sobre esta materia para que tenga un conocimiento del significado de estos marcadores y de la conveniencia de saber interpretar los resultados obtenidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;13(3): 137-147, jul.-sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores biológicos en el diagnóstico del derrame pleural maligno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23961^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36229^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32327^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32325^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4877^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29084^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
