<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115724</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The street teens and their perception of society</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This research aims to reveal what teenagers think, feel and express on the society around them, the street teens who use drugs. The approach was qualitative, under the methodology of Grounded Theory (Grand theory) supported by symbolic interactionism for understanding the phenomenon. They met seven (7) young women between 13 and 18, which were the key informants, the inclusion criteria were having had the experience of being and living on the street, and using illegal drugs. The technique of data collection was in-depth interviews. After analyzing the data did the category: Visionary Society for street teens with their respective sub categories. It is concluded that adolescents in the street is an This research aims to reveal what teenagers think, feel and express on the society around them, the street teens who use drugs. The approach was qualitative, under the methodology of Grounded Theory (Grand theory) supported by symbolic interactionism for understanding the phenomenon. They met seven (7) young women between 13 and 18, which were the key informants, the inclusion criteria were having had the experience of being and living on the street, and using illegal drugs. The technique of data collection was in-depth interviews. After analyzing the data did the category: Visionary Society for street teens with their respective sub categories. It is concluded that adolescents in the street is an (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alvarado Ch, Roberto E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejías, Marianela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra, Amarilis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación pretende develar lo que piensan, sienten y expresan sobre la sociedad que les rodea, las adolescentes de la calle que consumen drogas. El abordaje fue cualitativo, bajo la metodología de la Teoría Fundamentada en los Datos (Grand theory) sustentada en el interaccionismo simbólico para la comprensión del fenómeno. Se entrevistaron siete (7) jóvenes femeninas con edades entre 13 y 18 años, las cuales fueron las informantes claves, los criterios de inclusión eran haber tenido la experiencia de estar y vivir en la calle, y consumir drogas ilícitas. La técnica de recolección de los datos fue la entrevista en profundidad. Posterior al análisis de los datos surgió la categoría: Visionario de la sociedad para las adolescentes de la calle con sus respectivas sub categorías. Se concluye que las adolescentes en la calle es un fenómeno que cada día se presenta con mayor frecuencia en nuestra sociedad, el cual tiene como factores de riesgo: la familia disfuncional, los grupos de pares y el deseo de vivir la experiencia inicial. Las adolescentes entrevistadas se sienten rechazadas y despreciadas por la comunidad debido a que consumen drogas y viven en la calle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 371-380, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115724</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las adolescentes de la calle y su percepción de la sociedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32192^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
