<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78371</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-cytokine therapeutic targets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The arrival of anti-TNF-&amp;#945; to the clinic has been the most successful example of translational research. However, clinical experience has shown that these compounds do not induce clinical remission in half of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) patients. Recently, new biological drugs against non-cytokine targets have been available for RA patients. These compounds deplete B cells or interfere with the activation of T cells and have also shown effectiveness in controlling signs, symptoms and structural damage progression in RA. Second generation B-cell depletion therapies are progressing in the pipeline of several pharmaceutical companies. These compounds will likely improve the immunogenicity and formulation of rituximab, but it is improbable that they will improve the remission rate achieved by the anti-TNF-&amp;#945;&amp;#948;&amp;#961;&amp;upsi;&amp;#947;&amp;#963;. Currently, regulation of signal transduction has evolved into an important field of drug research, and small molecule inhibitors for a number of pathways are tested as new anti-inflammatory agents. For rheumatic diseases, specific Jak3 and Syk inhibitors are, so far, the most successful compounds representing a significant advance over p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) inhibitors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz González, José Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustabad Reyes, Sagrario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La llegada de los fármacos anti-TNF-&amp;#945; (tumor necrosis factor alpha&#145; factor de necrosis tumoral alfa&#146;) a la clínica ha sido el resultado más exitoso de la investigación traslacional. Sin embargo, la experiencia ha demostrado que estos compuestos no consiguen inducir la remisión clínica en la mitad de los pacientes con artritis reumatoide (AR). Recientemente se han puesto a disposición en el mercado fármacos biológicos no dirigidos contra citocinas que deplecionan las células B o interfieren con la activación de las células T y que también han mostrado eficacia en el control de la actividad de la AR. Una segunda generación de compuestos contra la célula B está en desarrollo de parte de diversas empresas farmacéuticas. Es de esperar que estos productos mejoren la inmunogenicidad y la posología del rituximab, pero es poco probable que incrementen las tasas de remisión alcanzadas por los anti-TNF-&amp;#945;. Actualmente, la regulación de la transducción de señales se ha convertido en un campo muy importante en el desarrollo de los fármacos, y pequeñas moléculas inhibidoras de vías de señalización intracelular se están ensayando como nuevos antiinflamatorios. Para las enfermedades reumáticas, los inhibidores específicos de JAK3 y Syk son, hasta ahora, los compuestos que han mostrado mejores resultados y representan un avance significativo respecto a los inhibidores de la p38 MAPK (mitogen-activated protein kinase ' proteína cinasa activada por mitógeno') (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(extr.1): 13-16, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78371</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Otras dianas terapéuticas distintas a las citocinas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52386^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14549^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24018^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
