<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044046</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-2159</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Espinet effect in conditioned taste aversion: negative results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Two experiments involving conditioned taste aversion with rats are presented, in which an attempt was made to replicate the so-called Espinet effect, where alternating preexposure to two flavour compounds, AX and BX, followed by conditioning to A, appear to endow B with the properties of a conditioned inhibitor. The results found did not succeed in replicating the effect. Alternating preexposure to AX and BX and subsequent conditioning to A failed both to retard the acquisition of the excitatory conditioning of stimulus B and to facilitate its subsequent extinction (Experiment 1; retardation test). Nor was a reduction in the response provoked by a conditioned excitor, Y, found, when accompanied by B(Experiment 2; summation test), relative to a control condition in which stimulus A had not been conditioned. An analysis was made of some aspects of the procedure employed in these experiments that may have obscured the detection of the Espinet effect (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sebastián Lombas, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Gumersinda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan dos experimentos, de aversión condicionada al sabor con ratas, en los que se intentó replicar el conocido como efecto Espinet, consistente en que la preexposición alterna a dos compuestos de sabores, AX y BX, y el posterior condicionamiento de A dotan a B de propiedades de inhibidor condicionado. Los resultados encontrados no consiguieron replicar el efecto. La preexposición alterna a AX y BX y el posterior condicionamiento de A ni retrasaron la adquisición del condicionamiento excitatorio del estímulo B ni facilitaron su posterior extinción (Experimento 1; prueba de retraso), ni tampoco dieron lugar a una reducción de la respuesta condicionada evocada por un excitador, Y, al ir acompañado de B (Experimento 2; pruebas de sumación), cuando se comparó con una condición control en la que el estímulo A no había sido condicionado. Se analizan algunos aspectos relativos al procedimiento empleado en estos experimentos que pudieron obscurecer la detección del efecto Espinet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>PsicolÔogica (Valencia, Ed. impr.);27(1): 97-117, ene.-jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El efecto Espinet en aversión condicionada al sabor: resultados negativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1540</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
