<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158884</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">EPICO 3.0. Antifungal prophylaxis in solid organ transplant recipients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Although over the past decade the management of invasive fungal infection has improved, considerable controversy persists regarding antifungal prophylaxis in solid organ transplant recipients. Aims. To identify the key clinical knowledge and make by consensus the high level recommendations required for antifungal prophylaxis in solid organ transplant recipients. Methods. Spanish prospective questionnaire, which measures consensus through the Delphi technique, was conducted anonymously and by e-mail with 30 national multidisciplinary experts, specialists in invasive fungal infections from six national scientific societies, including intensivists, anesthetists, microbiologists, pharmacologists and specialists in infectious diseases that responded to 12 questions prepared by the coordination group, after an exhaustive review of the literature in the last few years. The level of agreement achieved among experts in each of the categories should be equal to or greater than 70% in order to make a clinical recommendation. In a second term, after extracting the recommendations of the selected topics, a face-to-face meeting was held with more than 60 specialists who were asked to validate the pre-selected recommendations and derived algorithm. Measurements and primary outcomes. Echinocandin antifungal prophylaxis should be considered in liver transplant with major risk factors (retransplantation, renal failure requiring dialysis after transplantation, pretransplant liver failure, not early reoperation, or MELD &gt; 30); heart transplant with hemodialysis, and surgical re-exploration after transplantation; environmental colonization by Aspergillus, or cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection; and pancreas and intestinal transplant in case of acute graft rejection, hemodialysis, initial graft dysfunction, post-perfusion pancreatitis with anastomotic problems or need for laparotomy after transplantation. Antifungal fluconazole prophylaxis should be considered in liver transplant without major risk factors and MELD 20&#150;30, split or living donor, choledochojejunostomy, increased transfusion requirements, renal failure without replacement therapy, early reoperation, or multifocal colonization or infection with Candida; intestinal and pancreas transplant with no risk factors for echinocandin treatment. Liposomal amphotericin B antifungal prophylaxis should be considered in lung transplant (inhalant form) and liver transplant with major risk factors. Antifungal prophylaxis with voriconazole should be considered in lung transplant, and heart transplant with hemodialysis, surgical re-exploration after transplantation, environmental colonization by Aspergillus, or CMV infection. Conclusions. The management of antifungal prophylaxis in solid organ transplant recipients requires the application of knowledge and skills that are detailed in our recommendations and the algorithm developed therein. These recommendations, based on the DELPHI methodology, may help to identify potential patients, standardize their management and improve overall prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortún, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maseda, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Juan Carlos del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouzada, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llinares, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Alejandro H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragoza, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Aunque en la última década se ha observado una mejora en el tratamiento de la infección fúngica invasiva, todavía existen numerosas controversias en la profilaxis antifúngica del paciente trasplantado de órgano sólido. Objetivos. Identificar los principales conocimientos clínicos y elaborar recomendaciones con un alto nivel de consenso, necesarias para la profilaxis antifúngica del paciente trasplantado de órgano sólido. Métodos. Se realizó un cuestionario prospectivo español, que valora el consenso mediante la técnica Delphi. El cuestionario se llevó a cabo de forma anónima y por correo electrónico con 30 expertos multidisciplinarios nacionales, especialistas en infecciones fúngicas invasivas de seis sociedades científicas nacionales, que incluían intensivistas, anestesistas, microbiólogos, farmacólogos y especialistas en enfermedades infecciosas que respondieron a 12 preguntas preparadas por el grupo de coordinación, tras una revisión exhaustiva de la bibliografía de los últimos años. El nivel de acuerdo alcanzado entre los expertos en cada una de las categorías debía ser igual o superior al 70% para elaborar una recomendación. En un segundo término, después de extraer las recomendaciones de los temas seleccionados, se celebró una reunión presencial con más de 60 especialistas y se les solicitó la validación de las recomendaciones preseleccionadas y del algoritmo derivado de estas. Mediciones y resultados principales. Debe considerarse la profilaxis antifúngica con equinocandinas en el trasplante hepático con los principales factores de riesgo (retrasplante, insuficiencia renal postrasplante con necesidad de diálisis, insuficiencia hepática pretrasplante, reintervención quirúrgica no precoz, o MELD &gt; 30); trasplante cardíaco con hemodiálisis, y reexploración quirúrgica postrasplante; colonización ambiental por Aspergillus, o infección por citomegalovirus; trasplante de páncreas e intestino si existe rechazo agudo del injerto, hemodiálisis, disfunción inicial del injerto, problemas en la anastomosis con pancreatitis posperfusión, o necesidad de laparotomía postrasplante. Debe considerarse la profilaxis antifúngica con fluconazol en el trasplante hepático sin los principales factores de riesgo y MELD de 20-30, split o donante vivo, coledocoyeyunostomía, altos requerimientos transfusionales, fracaso renal sin necesidad de terapia sustitutiva, reintervención precoz o colonización multifocal o infección por Candida, y trasplante de páncreas e intestino sin factores de riesgo para el tratamiento con equinocandina. Debe considerarse la profilaxis antifúngica con anfotericina B liposómica en el trasplante pulmonar (vía inhalada) y el trasplante hepático con los principales factores de riesgo. Debe considerarse la profilaxis antifúngica con voriconazol en el trasplante pulmonar y el trasplante cardíaco con hemodiálisis, reexploración quirúrgica postrasplante, colonización ambiental por Aspergillus o enfermedad por citomegalovirus. Conclusiones. El manejo de la profilaxis antifúngica del paciente trasplantado de órgano sólido requiere la aplicación de los conocimientos y destrezas que se detallan en nuestras recomendaciones y en el algoritmo desarrollado. Estas recomendaciones basadas en la metodología Delphi pueden ayudar a identificar a los potenciales pacientes, estandarizar su tratamiento en conjunto y mejorar su pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(4): 187-195, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158884</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">EPICO 3.0. Profilaxis antifúngica en el paciente trasplantado de órgano sólido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24654^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55600^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14577^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14577^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
