<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048482</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laringed mask utility in pediatric patients: Efficacy and complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The laringeal mask airway is a supraglotic devicethat allows airway management. There are severalsizes designed in the adult scale. Anatomy and physiologyof the pediatric airway change with the age.We have performed a study in order to evaluate theefficiency and complications when we use laryngealmask airway in pediatric patients and we intend toput forward our outcomes to emergency situations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gredilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laporta Báez, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mascarilla laríngea (ML) es un dispositivo supraglóticoque permite el control de la vía aérea.Hay distintos tamaños diseñados a escala del adulto.La anatomía y la fisiología de las vías aéreas pediátricascambian con la edad. Hemos realizado unestudio en el que pretendemos evaluar la eficacia ylas complicaciones del uso de la mascarilla laríngeaen quirófano y por personal parcialmente adiestradoen pacientes pediátricos, y aplicar los resultados deeste estudio a la actividad de personal no adiestradoen áreas fuera de quirófano</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);26(6): 200-204, jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048482</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la mascarilla laríngea en Pediatría: eficacia y complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
