<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046672</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion vs multiple daily injections with glargine in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of two different        forms of intensive therapy, continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion        (CSII) and multiple daily injections (MDI) using premeal insulin        rapid analogs and insulin glargine, in children and adolescents        with type 1 diabetes mellitus (1DM).        Patients and methods: Forty-two diabetic patients, previously        treated with MDI using NPH and premeal rapid insulin or shortacting        analogs, were changed to CSII (21 subjects) or MDI using        glargine. There were not significant differences between both        groups, neither in the clinical characteristics nor in the metabolic        data at the beginning. Body mass index (BMI), total daily insulin        dose, severe hypoglycemic episodes incidence, ketoacidosis events,        glycosidase hemoglobin (HbA1c) levels, and quality of life at the        beginning and after one year of treatment were analyzed.        Results: HbA1c has improved in both groups. This improvement        is more significant in the group treated with CSII [7,89 ± 1,46        to 7,51 ± 0,79%] than in the glargine group [7,80 ± 0,53 to 7,65 ±        0,62%]. Insulin dose has declined 17% in CSII patients [0,98 ± 0,24        to 0,81 ± 0,16u/kg/d] (p &lt; 0,05) and 10,6% in glargine patients [0,94        ± 0,27 a 0,84 ± 0,22u/kg/d] (p &lt; 0,05). The number of hypoglycaemic        episodes was lower in the CSII group, although it has decreased        in both groups. BMI did not change in the CSII patients and        was reduced in the glargine patients. There was only one ketoacidosis        episode in one patient treated with CSII. The new treatment        was very well accepted in both groups.        Conclusions: CSII and MDI using insulin glargine are good        alternatives to control children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes        mellitus. They improve metabolic control without increasing        acute complications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Golmayo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Capapé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colino, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y la seguridad de dos tipos de terapia        intensiva: la infusión subcutánea continua de insulina (ISCI) y el        tratamiento con múltiples dosis de insulina (MDI) utilizando análogos        de acción rápida preprandiales e insulina glargina, en niños y        adolescentes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1).        Pacientes y métodos: Cuarenta y dos pacientes con DM1 en tratamiento        intensivo con MDI con NPH y análogos de acción rápida        o insulina regular fueron trasferidos 21 a ISCI y 21 a MDI con insulina        glargina. No había diferencias significativas entre los dos grupos        ni en las características clínicas ni metabólicas al inicio. Se analizan:        índice de masa corporal (IMC), dosis total de insulina al día, incidencia        de hipoglucemias graves, descompensaciones cetoacidóticas,        niveles de hemoglobina glicada (HbA1c) y grado de satisfacción al        inicio y al año de la nueva terapia.        Resultados: La HbA1c mejora en ambos grupos, más en el grupo        tratado con ISCI [7,89 ± 1,46 a 7,51 ± 0,79%] vs glargina [7,80 ± 0,53        a 7,65 ± 0,62%]. El aporte de insulina disminuye un 17% en el grupo        de ISCI [0,98 ± 0,24 a 0,81 ± 0,16u/kg/d] (p &lt; 0,05) y un 10,6% en el        de glargina [0,94 ± 0,27 a 0,84 ± 0,22u/kg/d] (p &lt; 0,05). La frecuencia        de hipoglucemias graves fue más baja en el grupo tratado con        ISCI aunque disminuye en ambos grupos. El IMC no se modifica en        el grupo de ISCI y disminuye en el de glargina. Solo evidenciamos        cetoacidosis en un paciente con ISCI. El grado de aceptación de la        terapia fue bueno en ambos grupos.        Conclusiones: El tratamiento con ISCI o con MDI con glargina        constituye una buena alternativa terapéutica en los pacientes pediátricos        con DM1. Permiten mejorar el control metabólico sin aumentar        la incidencia de complicaciones agudas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(4): 331-337, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con insulina glargina vs infusor continuo de insulina en niños y adolescentes con diabetes tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30156^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
