<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038958</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Balanced score card for clinical management in a nuclear medicine service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine values of management and quality indicators over the previous four 1-year periods and introduce a procedure for the automatic creation of a balanced score card. Material and method: A multidisciplinary working group was created to establish a series of indicators to be determined. Procedures were set up to obtain the values for the selected indicators. Results: The collection of risk-related data was standardized. The data were introduced into the information system. A computer program was created to calculate the indicators for any given period of time. A study of the service over the previous four 1-year periods was carried out and an instrument panel with 63 indicators was created. Discussion: This study demonstrates the advisability of monitoring risk management indicators. The analysis of the results of the instrument panel (2000-2003) defined the characteristics of the service and any changes occurring over this period. In this initial phase, the instrument panel does not include economic or administrative data, but will do so in the near future, with data provided by analytical accounting</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Berrocal, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáinz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar los valores de indicadores de gestión y calidad en los últimos 4 períodos anuales e implantar un procedimiento para la elaboración automática del cuadro de mando. Material y método: Formación de un grupo de trabajo multidisciplinario para fijar una serie de indicadores para determinar. Elaboración de procedimientos para obtener los valores de los indicadores fijados. Resultados: Se ha estandarizado la recogida de la información referida al riesgo que se ha incluido en el sistema de información. Se ha confeccionado un programa informático que calcula los indicadores descritos para cualquier período. Se ha realizado un estudio del servicio en los últimos 4 períodos anuales con la presentación de un cuadro de mando con 63 indicadores. Discusión: El estudio ha puesto de manifiesto la conveniencia de controlar los indicadores de gestión de riesgo. El análisis de resultados del cuadro de mando (2000-2003) define las características del servicio y su evolución en este período. El cuadro de mando no incluye en esta primera fase datos económicos o administrativos, hecho previsto en un futuro próximo con el uso de datos aportados por la contabilidad analítica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(5): 239-245, jul. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038958</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuadro de mando para la gestión clínica en un servicio de medicina nuclear</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34958</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22877</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
