<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97311</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish version of the irrational food beliefs scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of the study was to develop a Spanish adaptation of the Irrational Food Beliefs Scale(IFBS). This is important due not only to the scarcity and limitations of existing instruments in Spanish, butal so to the potential of the IFBS in terms of studying the difficulties some people face in achieving healthy weight control. Methods: Subjects were 323 secondary-level and highschool students (12-20 years; 152 females, 171 males). In addition to the IFBS, we determined the body mass index and analysed the following variables: influence of the aesthetic body shape model, perceived stress, coping strategies, self-esteem and variables from the Eating Disorders Inventory-2.Results: The factor analysis yielded two factors corresponding to irrational and rational beliefs about food. The internal consistency (Cronbach&#146;s alpha coefficient) of the IFBS as a whole and of the irrational and rational subscales was 0.863, 0.881 and 0.779, respectively. The analysis of correlations with the above mentioned variables showed an adequate construct validity. Discussion: The Spanish version of the IFBS fulfils the psychometric requirements for a measure of irrational/rational food beliefs and shows adequate internal consistency and construct validity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui Lobera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolaños, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito del estudio fue adaptar la Irrational Food Beliefs Scale (IFBS) a la población española. La escasez y limitaciones de instrumentos similares en nuestra lengua y las posibilidades de la IFBS para estudiarlas dificultades en el control de peso de manera saludable justifican el trabajo. Métodos: Fueron aceptados 323 estudiantes de educación secundaria y bachillerato (12-20 años; 152 mujeres,171 hombres). Además de la IFBS, se determinó el índice de masa corporal y se analizaron las siguientes variables: influencia del modelo estético corporal, estrés percibido, estrategias de afrontamiento, autoestima y variables del Eating Disorders Inventory-2.Resultados: El análisis factorial sugirió dos factores que representan las creencias irracionales y racionales sobre los alimentos. La consistencia interna del IFBS y de sus subescalas (coeficiente alpha de Cronbach) fue de0.881 y 0.779 para la subescala irracional y racional respectivamente. La IFBS presentó un a=0,863. El análisis de correlaciones con las variables mencionadas demostró una adecuada validez de constructo. Discusión: La IFBS, en su versión española, cubre los requisitos psicométricos para medir las creencias racionales-irracionales acerca de los alimentos, con una adecuada consistencia interna y validez de constructo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(5): 852-859, sept.-oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión Española de la escala de creencias irracionales sobre los alimentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
