<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107930</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the Breast Cancer Survival in a Public Hospital during the Period 1999-2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This report shows the effect of period of diagnosis and treatment in the breast cancer survival in a public hospital between 1999 and 2008. The main aim of this article is the knowledge of the different demographic, clinical and pathological variables among the women collected in our database in order to establish if there have been variations in the evolution of the survival rate in the this decade. Methods: 2132 women were included in the Hospital Cancer Registry between 1999 and 2008. These patients were followed-up by the National Death Index Agency and the last date of medical consultation, up to 31st march 2011. Observed survival was estimated by the actuarial method, and the relative survival was calculated by the Ederer II method. Survival was presented by fixed time point, as such 1, 3 and 5 year, after diagnosis. Confidence Interval 95% was included. Results: The average age at diagnosis was 59,9 ± 14,2 years old. At the time of diagnosis, 12,3% presented in situ carcinoma; 51,8% localized carcinoma; 30% positive lymph nodes and 5% disseminated carcinoma. 72,8% of the cases were ductal carcinomas and 11,8% lobular carcinomas. Surgery resection was applied in the 90,8% of the cases, chemotherapy was administered in 23,4% and radiotherapy in the 56,7%. The overall relative survival was 88% in 5 years; 99, 9% for &#147;in situ&#148; carcinoma, 94,3% for localized carcinoma, 83,7% for regional carcinomas and 25,7% for disseminated carcinoma. In the third year of follow-up, women diagnosed in 2008 presented a relative survival of 94,8% versus 89,5% of those diagnosed in 1999. However, during the follow-up the estimation fluctuated without any significant tendency as a whole or by stages. Conclusions: Evolution of relative survival per year of diagnosis didn&#146;t show any significant increase, even when it was compared across the cohorts of two five-years periods or when it was studied by cohorts of cancer stage at diagnosis. In a 10 year period, relative survival hasn&#146;t changed in the population treated in this hospital(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pilas Pérez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colina Ruizdelgado, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lora Pablos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El estudio de la supervivencia explora la calidad de la atención proporcionada en un hospital. El objetivo del presente trabajo es conocer las variables demográficas y clinicopatológicas así como la supervivencia y evolución a lo largo del decenio 1999-2008 de las mujeres diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama. Métodos: Se recogió la información relativa a las 2.132 mujeres incluidas en el Registro Hospitalario de tumores en esa década. Su seguimiento se realizó hasta el 31 de marzo de 2011 utilizando como fuente de información el Índice Nacional de Defunciones y la fecha del último contacto de la paciente con el hospital. Se calculó la supervivencia observada, estimada mediante el método actuarial, y la supervivencia relativa, calculada por el método Ederer II, para cada uno de los primeros cinco años de seguimiento junto con su intervalo de confianza al 95%. Resultados: La edad media fue 59,9 ± 14,2 años. 12,3% presentaron carcinoma &#147;in situ&#148;, 51,8% localizado, 30% con ganglios positivos y 5% diseminado. Según el tipo histológico, 72,8% fueron ductales y 11,8% lobulillares. Se aplicó cirugía en 90,8%, quimioterapia en 23,4% y radioterapia en 56,7%. La supervivencia global relativa fue 88% a los 5 años; 99,9% en carcinomas &#147;in situ&#148;; 94,3% en localizados; 83,7% en regionales y 25,7% en diseminados. Al tercer año de seguimiento las mujeres diagnosticadas en 2008 mostraron una supervivencia relativa de 94,8% versus 89,5% en las de 1999, pero la estimación a lo largo del seguimiento fluctuó sin existir una tendencia significativa ni de manera global ni por estadios. Conclusiones: La evolución de la supervivencia por año de diagnóstico no mostró incremento estadísticamente significativo, ni comparándola por cohortes de los dos quinquenios ni desglosándola por cohortes de estadio al diagnóstico. No se ha conseguido variar la supervivencia cuando se exploró durante 10 años(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(6): 589-600, nov.-dic.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la supervivencia del cáncer de mama durante el decenio 1999-2008 en un hospital público de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
