<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86681</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical practice guidelines for the treatment of spasticity with botulinum toxin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Spasticity is an important medical and social problem with a high rate of incidence both in childhood, where it is mainly a result of infantile cerebral palsy, and in adults, where it is frequently brought about by a cerebrovascular accident, traumatic brain injury, spinal cord injury or multiple sclerosis, among other pathologies. It gives rise to important problems that have a significant effect on the quality of life of patients and their caregivers. Clinical practice guidelines  (CPG) are instruments that help professionals, administrators and planners to make decisions that can improve clinical outcomes. Development. Due to the complexity of spasticity, its evaluation and treatment should be carried out by specialised units using a multidisciplinary approach. One of the first-line treatment options is botulinum toxin type A (BTA). For this treatment to be successful and to be able to evaluate the patient&#146;s progress, it is advisable to have a work protocol that includes the knowledge and tools necessary to use BTA in the most suitable way and in agreement with the available scientific evidence. All these factors led the Spasticity Unit to consider the need to draw up a set of CPG. Conclusions. These CPG have been in use at the Hospital Universitari Mútua de Terrassa for 15 years, and are updated on a  regular basis. This has enabled us to carry out a standardised selection of spastic patients and to establish a clear-cut set of treatment goals. It has also allowed us to implement a suitable plan regarding follow-up, the adjuvant therapies needed for each of the patients and an evaluation of results that is as objective as possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garreta Figuera, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaler Vilaseca, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrequebrada Giménez, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La espasticidad constituye un problema médico y social de incidencia y trascendencia elevada tanto en la infancia, debido principalmente a la parálisis cerebral infantil, como en el adulto, a consecuencia de un accidente cerebrovascular, traumatismo craneoencefálico, lesión medular o esclerosis múltiple, entre otras patologías. Ocasiona problemas importantes que de forma significativa influyen en la calidad de vida del paciente y de sus cuidadores. Las guías de  práctica clínica (GPC) son instrumentos que ayudan a los profesionales, gestores y planificadores a tomar decisiones que pueden mejorar los resultados clínicos. Desarrollo. Debido a la complejidad de la espasticidad, su valoración y tratamiento deberían hacerse por unidades especializadas, con un enfoque multidisciplinar. Una de las opciones de tratamiento de primera línea es la toxina botulínica  tipo A (TBA). Para que este tratamiento sea un éxito y se pueda evaluar la evolución del paciente, es recomendable disponer de un protocolo de trabajo que recoja el conocimiento y las herramientas necesarias para usar la TBA de forma apropiada y de acuerdo con la evidencia científica disponible. Todos estos factores condujeron a que la Unidad de Espasticidad se plantease la realización de una GPC.  Conclusiones. En el Hospital Universitari Mútua de Terrassa se utiliza esta GPC desde hace 15 años, con actualizaciones periódicas; eso nos ha permitido realizar una selección estandarizada del paciente espástico, el establecimiento claro de unos objetivos del tratamiento y la instauración de un plan apropiado de seguimiento, así como las terapias adyuvantes necesarias para cada uno de los pacientes y una valoración lo más objetiva posible de los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(11): 685-689, jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de práctica clínica del tratamiento de la espasticidad con toxina botulínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9322^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1930^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
