<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143940</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malnutrition epidemiology in Latin America: current situation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: malnutrition is one of the most important public health problems in Latin- America. Objective: to present an analysis based on three anthropometric indicators considering the countries, sex, geographic area and socioeconomic conditions. Methods: The childhood malnutrition (z-score &lt; &#150;2 standard deviation) was made considering anthropometric indicators in children &lt; 5 years; height for age, weight for height and weight for age. Prevalence was estimated based on sex and type of household (urban and rural). Maps with malnutrition distribution were drawn. The World Health Organization database for malnutrition and growth was employed. Statistical analysis included correlation and simple regression. Results: the countries were organized according to quintiles of malnutrition distribution: 0-10%: Argentina, Brazil and Costa Rica; 11-20%: Chile, Colombia, Republican Dominican, Uruguay and Venezuela; 21-30%: Ecuador, El Salvador, Haiti, México and Nicaragua; 31- 40%: Bolivia, Honduras and Peru; &gt; 40% Guatemala. The relation between malnutrition and socioeconomic indicators was always inverse except for infant mortality. Conclusions: Haiti, Guatemala, Honduras and Nicaragua were the countries with the highest malnutrition prevalence. The relation between malnutrition and socioeconomic was inverse for IDH, birth expectancy and schooling. The relation with infant mortality was positive (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kac, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alvear, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la desnutrición infantil es uno de los principales problemas de salud pública de América Latina. Objetivo: presentar un análisis en el ámbito de tres indicadores antropométricos, considerando los países, el sexo, el área geográfica y las condiciones socio-económicas. Método: la descripción de la desnutrición infantil (escore-z &lt; &#150;2 desviaciones estándar) fue hecha sobre la base de indicadores antropométricos en niños &lt; 5 años; estatura para edad, peso para estatura y peso para edad. Las prevalencia fueron analizadas según sexo, y por tipo de domicilio (urbano y rural). Fueron diseñados mapas con la distribución de la malnutrición. La fuente empleada fue el banco de datos de la Organización Mundial de la Salud para crecimiento y desnutrición. Las pruebas se llevaron a cabo mediante correlación simple y regresión. Resultados: los países fueron organizados en cinco quintiles de la distribución de desnutrición: 0-10%: Argentina, Brasil y Costa Rica; 11 y 20%: Chile, Colombia, República Dominicana, Uruguay y Venezuela; 21 y 30%: Ecuador, El Salvador, Haití, México y Nicaragua; 31 y 40%: Bolivia, Honduras y Perú; &gt; 40% Guatemala. La relación entre desnutrición y los indicadores socioeconómicos fue siempre inversa, excepto en el caso de la mortalidad infantil. Conclusiones: Haití, Guatemala, Honduras y Nicaragua son los países que se encuentran con las altas prevalencia de desnutrición. La relación entre desnutrición e indicadores socio económicos fue inversa para IDH, esperanza de vida al nacer y tasa de alfabetización. La relación de mortalidad infantil fue positiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(supl.3): 50-56, oct. 2010. tab, mapas, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143940</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la desnutrición en Latinoamérica: situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8022^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38823^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
