<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116158</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge área of occupational medicine in the grade of spanish universities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To demonstrate the need for a specific knowledge area in Occupational Medicine Degree in Spanish universities. Methods: Review and description of the area of knowledge of Occupational Medicine Degree in Spanish universities. Methods: Review and description of the area of knowledge of Occupational Medicine in the content of curricula and teaching guides for grades of Medicine taught in Spanish universities. Results: We have found differences in the content of the curriculum in relation to the area of knowledge of Occupational Medicine. Conclusions: In most of the teaching guides Medical Grade issues Occupational Medicine either are or are not included in subjects such as Forensic Medicine, Preventive Medicine and Public Health showing the lack of training in this area and the need of a specific area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero Zamora, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saus Carreres, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vico Garcerán, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andani Cervera, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribes Martínez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ligero López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evidenciar la necesidad de un área de conocimiento específica en Medicina del Trabajo en el Grado de Medicina en las universidades españolas. Material y método: Revisión y descripción del área de conocimientos de la Medicina del Trabajo en el contenido de los planes de estudio y guías docentes de los grados de Medicina que se imparte en las universidades españolas. Resultados: Se han encontrado diferencias en el contenido de los planes de estudios en relación al área de conocimiento de Medicina del Trabajo. Conclusiones. En la mayoría de las guías docentes del Grado de Medicina los temas relaciones con la Medicina del trabajo no aparecen como asignatura específica y en general se incluyen en asignaturas como Medicina Legal, Medicina Preventiva o Salud Pública evidenciando las carencias formativas en esa materia y la necesidad de un área específica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;22(3): 135-141, sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El área de conocimiento de Medicina del Trabajo en el grado de Medicina de las Universidades Españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4572^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
