<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132981</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teaching radiology and physical medicine in Dentistry degree through problem-based learning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The current paradigm of high education is based on teaching student-centered skills. The success of this education requires institutional leadership that encourages innovation in teaching and the use of active methodologies for developing these skills. Aim: To evaluate the method of problem-based learning (PBL) for the development of specific and transverse skills in the subject named radiology and physical medicine, in the degree in Dentistry from the University of the Basque Country. Subjects and methods: The scenario-problem was designed for teaching-learning process of the subject of radiology and physical medicine, which was implemented during the last two academic years (2011-2012 and 2012-2013) of the second year of the degree in Dentistry. We conducted a questionnaire of student opinion on the influence of PBL in the acquisition of skills. The influence of this educational innovation in academic outcomes (rates of assessment, performance and success) was analyzed. Results: PBL facilitated situational learning and skills development in a climate of motivation and active participation in group, with a high degree of student satisfaction. In addition, PBL yielded high rates of assessment (0.96 ± 0.01), performance (0.89 ± 0.02) and academic success (0.92 ± 0.01). Conclusion: PBL helps develop the skills of the subject, with a high level of academic performance and high student satisfaction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomares-Casado, Teodoro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El paradigma actual de la formación universitaria se fundamenta en la enseñanza por competencias centrada en el estudiante. El éxito de esta educación superior requiere un liderazgo institucional que estimule la innovación docente y la utilización de metodologías activas para el desarrollo de dichas competencias. Objetivo: Evaluar el método del aprendizaje basado en problemas (ABP) para el desarrollo de las competencias específicas y transversales en la asignatura de radiología y medicina física, en el grado en odontología de la Universidad del País Vasco. Sujetos y métodos: El escenario-problema fue diseñado para su aplicación en el proceso de enseñanza-aprendizaje de la asignatura de radiología y medicina física, de segundo curso del grado en odontología, implementándose en los cursos 2011-2012 y 2012-2013. Se realizó una encuesta de opinión al alumnado sobre la influencia del ABP en la adquisición de las competencias. Se analizó la influencia de la innovación educativa en los resultados académicos (tasas de evaluación, de rendimiento y de éxito). Resultados: Esta innovación educativa facilitó el aprendizaje situacional y el desarrollo de las competencias en un clima de motivación y participación activa grupal, con un alto grado de satisfacción del alumnado. Además, el ABP permitió obtener altas tasas de evaluación (0,96 ± 0,01), de rendimiento (0,89 ± 0,02) y de éxito académico (0,92 ± 0,01). Conclusión: El ABP facilitó el desarrollo de las competencias de la asignatura, con un elevado nivel de rendimiento académico y alto grado de satisfacción de los estudiantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);17(4): 221-228, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enseñanza de la radiología y medicina física en el grado en odontología a través del aprendizaje basado en problemas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4564^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
