<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93166</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness of exenatide versus insulin glargine in Spanish patients with obesity and type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Exenatide, a GLP-1 receptor agonist for adjuvant treatment of type2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), has been shown to be as effective as insulin glargine (IG) for reducingglycated hemoglobin levels combined with metformin or/and sulphonylureas. Exenatide isassociated to weight reduction and a higher incidence of gastrointestinal adverse events. The objective of this study was to assess the cost-effectiveness of exenatide as comparedto IG in obese patients with T2DM not achieving an adequate blood glucose control from the perspective of the Spanish healthcare system. Methods: Pharmacoeconomic model inputs were obtained from an obese subpopulation (BMI &amp;#8805;30 k/m2) of an international, randomized, controlled clinical trial comparing exenatide with IGin poorly controlled T2DM patients, and were supplemented with country-specific data.Results: Exenatide was associated to improvements in life-years gained and quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) by 0.11 and 0.62 respectively versus IG. Direct costs were D 9,306 higher as compared to IG (D 47,010 versus D 37,704, with increased pharmacy costs as the main driver).Exenatideís incremental cost-effectiveness ratio was D 15,068 per QALY gained versus IG. Conclusions: Exenatide was associated to greater clinical benefits and higher costs in obeseT2DM patients as compared to IG. Considering a willingness-to-pay threshold of D 30,000 perQALY gained in the Spanish setting, exenatide represents an efficient option in comparison withIG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goodall, Gordon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dilla, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Smith-Palmer, Jaynea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costi, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reviriego, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timlin, Louise</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos Exenatida es un agonista del receptor de GLP-1 empleado como tratamiento adyuvante en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2), que ha demostrado ser tan eficaz como insulina glargina (IG) reduciendo la concentración de hemoglobina glucosilada, cuando se administra en combinación con metformina o/y sulfonilureas. Exenatida se asocia a una reducción de peso y a una mayor incidencia de acontecimientos adversos de tipo gastrointestinal. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el coste-efectividad de exenatida frente a IG en pacientes obesos con DM2, que no alcanzan un control glucémico adecuado, desde la perspectiva del sistema nacional de salud. Material y métodos Se utilizó un modelo farmacoeconómico que incluyó información procedente de un ensayo clínico internacional, aleatorizado y controlado, que comparaba exenatida con IG, en pacientes con un inadecuado control de la glucosa, en concreto de la subpoblación de pacientes obesos (IMC &amp;#8805; 30 k/m2), y de datos específicos del país. Resultados Exenatida se asocia con un incremento de años de vida ganados y años de vida ajustados por calidad (AVAC) (0,11 y 0,62, respectivamente), frente a IG. Los costes directos se incrementaron 9.306 &#128; en comparación con IG (47.010 frente a 37.704 &#128;) siendo los costes farmacológicos los más importantes. Esto se tradujo en un coste-efectividad incremental de 15.068 &#128;/AVAC de exenatida frente a IG. Conclusiones En pacientes obesos con DM2, exenatida se asocia con mayores beneficios clínicos y mayores costes que IG. Considerando el umbral de disposición a pagar de 30.000 &#128; /AVAC para España, exenatida representa una opción eficiente en comparación con IG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;58(7): 331-340, ago.-sept. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-efectividad de exenatida en comparación con insulina glargina en pacientes con obesidad y diabetes mellitus tipo 2 en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31125^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
