<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135088</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tap water as a dietary source of exposure to fluoride in Tenerife; risk assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Drinking water is the main source of fluoride exposure for the population. According to the Spanish Law RD 140/2003, the fluoride content in drinking water should not exceed the parametric value of 1.5 mg/L. Historically, certain drinking waters in the island of Tenerife have exceeded this value due to the geological/volcanic characteristics of the Canary Islands. Fluoride (F) plays an important role in the prevention of dental caries (tooth decay). However, long exposure to concentrations above 1.5 mg/L in drinking water can cause disorders such as dental fluorosis. Objectives: To determine the amount of fluoride in the tap waters of the 11 municipalities in the north of the island of Tenerife that, at the time of the study, exceeded the parametric value for fluoride set by the Spanish legislation and to toxicologically estimate and evaluate the fluoride daily intakes from water considering the RDI (Recommended Daily Intake) established in Spain for different population groups. Method: 44 samples of tap water collected in the 11 municipalities in the study were analyzed using the fluoride potentiometric determination with an ion selective electrode. Results: 9 of the 11 municipalities presented mean fluoride concentrations in their tap water that exceeded the parametric value set by the Spanish legislation (1.5 mg/L). Considering an average daily water consumption of 2 L, the recommended daily intake (RDI) for women (3mg F/day) is exceeded in 9 of the 11 municipalities and the RDI for men (4 mg F/day) is exceeded in 5 of the 11 municipalities. Considering a daily water consumption of 1.5 L, the RDI for children of 2-3 years (0.7 mg/day) is clearly exceeded in all municipalities. Conclusions: The results show the existing public health problem on the island of Tenerife and justify the tap water consumption restrictions put in force by the Public Health Authorities of the Canary Islands at the time of the study. Children are the most exposed population group to the risks of fluoride because its RDI is lower (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Sacramento, Nazaret</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Gara Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revert Girones, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Armendáriz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hardisson de la Torre, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Fernández, Ángel José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El agua de consumo humano es la principal fuente de exposición al fluoruro para la población. De acuerdo con el Real Decreto 140/2003, el contenido  en fluoruro en el agua de consumo humano no debe superar el valor paramétrico de 1,5 mg/L. Históricamente, ciertas aguas de consumo en Tenerife han superado este valor debido a sus características geológicas/volcánicas. El flúor juega un papel importante en la prevención de la caries dental. Sin embargo, la exposición crónica a concentraciones superiores a 1,5 mg/L en el agua de bebida puede provocar trastornos como la fluorosis dental. Objetivos: Determinar la cantidad de fluoruro en el agua de consumo humano de 11 municipios del norte de la isla de Tenerife que en el momento del estudio superaba el valor paramétrico de fluoruro y estimar y evaluar toxicológicamente las ingestas diarias a partir del consumo de agua considerando las IDR (Ingestas Diarias Recomendadas) establecidas en España para distintos grupos poblacionales. Método: 44 muestras de aguas de abastecimiento público recogidas en los 11 municipios objeto del estudio fueron analizadas usando la determinación potenciométrica de fluoruro mediante el uso de un electrodo de ión selectivo. Resultados: 9 de los 11 municipios las aguas de abasto presentaron concentraciones de fluoruro medias que superaron el valor paramétrico fijado por la legislación española. Considerando un consumo medio diario de agua de 2 L, la ingesta diaria recomendada (IDR) para mujeres (3 mg/día) es superada en 9 de los 11 municipios y la IDR para hombres (4 mg/día) es superada en 5 de los 11 municipios. Considerando un consumo medio diario de agua de 1,5 L, la IDR establecida para los niños de 2 a 3 años (0,7 mg/día) es superada ampliamente en todos los municipios. Conclusiones: Los resultados obtenidos evidencian el problema de salud pública existente en la isla de Tenerife y justifican las restricciones de consumo establecidas por la Dirección General de Salud Pública del Servicio Canario de Salud, vigentes en el momento del estudio. Los niños son el grupo poblacional más expuesto a los riesgos del fluoruro debido a que su IDR es menor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(4): 1787-1794, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El agua de consumo como fuente de exposición crónica a fluoruro en Tenerife; evaluación del riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16183^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9242^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28447^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5593^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24961</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
