<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139140</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Brain death organ donation potential and life support therapy limitation in neurocritical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the profile, incidence of life support therapy limitation (LSTL) and donation potential in neurocritical patients. Study design: A multicenter prospective study was carried out. Setting: Nine hospitals authorized for organ harvesting for transplantation. Patients: All patients consecutively admitted to the hospital with GCS &lt; 8 during a 6-month period were followed-up until discharge or day 30 of hospital stay. Study variables: Demographic data, cause of coma, clinical status upon admission and outcome were analyzed. LSTL, brain death (BD) and organ donation incidence were recorded. Results: A total of 549 patients were included, with a mean age of 59.0 ± 14.5 years. The cause of coma was cerebral hemorrhage in 27.0% of the cases.LSTL was applied in 176 patients (32.1%). In 78 cases LSTL consisted of avoiding ICU admission. Age, the presence of contraindications, and specific causes of coma were associated to LSTL. A total of 58.1% of the patients died (n=319). One-hundred and thirty-three developed BD (24.2%), and 56.4% of these became organ donors (n=75). The presence of edema and mid-line shift on the CT scan, and transplant coordinator evaluation were associated to BD. LSTL was associated to a no-BD outcome. Early LSTL (first 4 days) was applied in 9 patients under 80 years of age, with no medical contraindications for donation and a GCS &amp;#8804; 4 who finally died in asystole. Conclusions: LSTL is a frequent practice in neurocritical patients. In almost one-half of the cases, LSTL consisted of avoiding admission to the ICU, and on several occasions the donation potential was not evaluated by the transplant coordinator (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliver, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llauradó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pont, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mestre, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badía, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodí, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gener, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquirol, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandiumenge, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Twose, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el perfil, la incidencia de limitación de tratamiento de soporte vital (LTSV) y la potencialidad de donación de órganos en pacientes neurocríticos. Diseño: Multicéntrico prospectivo. Ámbito: Nueve centros autorizados para extracción de órganos para trasplante. Pacientes: Todos los pacientes ingresados en el hospital con GCS &lt; 8 durante 6 meses fueron seguidos hasta su alta o hasta 30 días de estancia hospitalaria. Variables de interés: Datos demográficos, causa del coma, situación clínica al ingreso y evolución. Incidencia de LTSV, muerte encefálica (ME) y donación de órganos. Resultados: Se incluyó a 549 pacientes. Edad media 59,0 ± 14,5. El 27,0% de los comas fueron por hemorragias cerebrales. Se aplicó LTSV en 176 pacientes (32,1%). En 78 casos consistió en no ingreso en la UCI. La edad, presencia de contraindicaciones y determinadas causas del coma se asociaron a LTSV. Fallecieron 319 pacientes (58,1%); 133 fueron ME (24,2%) y el 56,4% de ellos fueron donantes de órganos (n=75). Edema y desviación de la línea media en la TAC y la evaluación previa por el coordinador de trasplantes se asociaron a ME. La LTSV se asoció a no evolución a ME. Nueve pacientes de menos de 80 años, sin contraindicaciones para donación y con un GCS &amp;#8804; 4 fueron limitados en los 4 primeros días y fallecieron en asistolia. Conclusiones: La aplicación de LTSV es frecuente en el paciente neurocrítico. Casi la mitad de LTSV consistió en el no ingreso en unidades de críticos y, en ocasiones, sin evaluar su potencialidad como donante por la coordinación de trasplantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(6): 337-344, ago.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potencialidad de donación de órganos en muerte encefálica y limitación del tratamiento de soporte vital en los pacientes neurocríticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8197^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53683^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
