<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146283</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autism spectrum disorder. Clinical implications of a deficit-based conceptualization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the appearance of DSM-5 a vision of autism based on the concepts of spectrum and disability has been consolidated. From this vision emerge a kind of interventions that try to compensate deficits by means of educational adaptations and behaviour therapy, an approach inherited from that applied to intellectual disability In this work we discuss the development of the concept of infantile autism (from his origins tied to schizophrenia and infantile psychoses up to the current consolidation of the idea of autistic spectrum) as a starting point to understand in which way the detachment from classic psychopathology is changing our comprehension of these clinical pictures and, as a consequence, the way we trait them. By means of a small incursion into the clinic with two vignettes, we also intend to take up the idea of autism as something more than a deficit, a positive construction, a harsh defence against some sort of suffering, without thereby having to abandon compensatory interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jordán Cristóbal, Carlos M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la aparición del DSM-5 se consolida una visión del autismo en torno a los conceptos de espectro y discapacidad. De esta visión se derivan intervenciones que tratan de compensar los déficits encontrados mediante la educación adaptada y la modificación de conducta, un enfoque heredado de la discapacidad intelectual. En este trabajo se analiza el devenir del concepto de autismo infantil (desde sus orígenes ligados a la esquizofrenia y las psicosis infantiles hasta la actual consolidación de la idea de espectro autista) como punto de partida para entender de qué forma su desvinculación de la psicopatología clásica está afectando a la comprensión de estos cuadros y, como consecuencia, a las intervenciones que se proponen. Además, mediante una pequeña incursión en la clínica con dos viñetas, intentamos rescatar una visión del autismo como algo más que un déficit, como una construcción positiva, una defensa contra algún tipo de sufrimiento, sin que por ello haya que rechazar las intervenciones compensatorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;35(128): 775-788, oct.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno del espectro del autismo. Implicaciones en la práctica clínica de una conceptualización basada en el déficit</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
