<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047755</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute urinary retention secondary to the obstruction of urinary in dwelling catheters by cellular debris in patients with neoplastic bladder invasion entails serious management difficulties in end-stage malignancies.This situation greatly deteriorates quality of life, and has a significant impact on the suffering of patients, their families, and the multidisciplinary team, becoming a problem when standard palliative care treatment shave failed and more aggressive or invasive measures are not indicated because of the patient's overall status.Theoretically, a treatment that «dissolves» this cellular debris may bea satisfactory palliative solution to this obstructive mechanical problem, and there fore to the acute urinary retention episodes. Hyaluronic acid is an important component of the extracellular matrix. It is hydrolyzed by hyaluronidase, an enzyme that may reduce the viscosity and barrier action of this matrix. Under the hypothesis that, by using hyaluronidase, we may «dissolve» cellular debris, we present in this paper our experience with two cases of previously refractory acute urinary retention that finally achieved excellent symptom control after using intravesical hylauronidase infusions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Val León, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Posada, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta i Sales, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno roldán, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La retención aguda de orina, secundaria a obstrucción de la sondavesical por detritus celulares, en pacientes con invasión vesical tumora lpor patología oncológica avanzada en fase terminal, plantea serias dificultades de manejo, gran deterioro de la calidad de vida y un importante sufrimiento para el paciente, la familia y el equipo asistencial cuando las medidas paliativas convencionales fracasan y otros tratamientos más «agresivos» o «invasivos» no están indicados dentro del contexto global del enfermo. En teoría, un tratamiento que «disolviera» estos detritus celulares, resolvería el problema mecánico obstructivo y por tanto los episodios de retención urinaria. El ácido hialurónico es un componente importante de la matriz intercelulary su hidrolización por la enzima hialuronidasa, produce una disminución de la viscosidad y de la acción de barrera de esta. Bajo la hipótesisde que la hialuronidasa contribuyera a «disolver» estos detritus celulares, presentamos en esta nota clínica nuestra experiencia con dos casos clínicos de retención aguda de orina refractarios, que al ser tratados con hialuronidasa intravesical presentaron una excelente respuesta en el control de los síntomas obstructivos urinarios previos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;13(1): 5-7, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hialuronidasa en el manejo de la obstrucción de las sondas vesicales en pacientes con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6973^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29144^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
