<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14581</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enhanced ultrastructural localization of acid phosphatase using microwave irradiation during enzyme incubation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microwave irradiation in enzyme cytochemistry is not only advantageous for shortening procedures, but will also improve the sensitivity of histochemical detection since short periods and less fixative are required to obtain good preservation. Moreover, shorter incubation procedures will reduce the diffusion and loss of enzyme activity. Here we compared conventional incubations in a shaking waterbath at 37°C, with incubations carried out in a microwave oven. Lysosomal and extralysosomal acid phosphatase were identified using microwave irradiation. Microwave irradiation elicited enhanced reactivity of the chemicals present in the tissue, leading to the detection of minuscule concentrations of enzyme activity, which was most pronounced in the detection of extralysosomal enzyme activity. A major advantage of the microwave is the accelerated formation of reaction product. Furthermore, enzymatic preincubation or chemical treatment of the tissues is no longer necessary. By shortening the incubation time, the danger of artificial precipitations and diffusion of the final reaction product are reduced. The sensitivity and reproducibility of the enzymatic reaction are increased. Consequently, microwave irradiation during enzyme incubation leads to a highly specific localization of acid phosphatase (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la histoquímica enzimática la irradiación con microondas no sólo ofrece ventajas para acortar los procedimientos sino también es capaz de mejorar la sensibilidad de la detección histoquímica puesto que se precisan de periodos cortos y menos fijador para obtener una buena preservación. Además, procedimientos de incubación más cortos reducirán la difusión y pérdida de actividad enzimática. En este trabajo, comparamos las incubaciones convencionales, llevadas a cabo en un baño de agua con agitación a 37º C con las llevadas a cabo en un horno de microondas. Se identificaron la fosfatasa lisosomial y extralisosomial utilizando la irradiación con microondas. La irradiación con microondas suscitó una reactividad intensificada de los reactivos presentes en los tejidos; esto fue muy patente en la detección de concentraciones muy bajas de actividad enzimática. Una ventaja principal de las microondas es la formación acelerada del producto de la reacción. Adicionalmente, la pre-incubación enzimática o el tratamiento químico de los tejidos ya es necesario. Al acortar el tiempo de incubación, se reducen tanto el riesgo de las precipitaciones artificiales como la difusión del producto final de la reacción. La sensibilidad y la reproducibilidad de la reacción enzimática son aumentadas. En consecuencia, la irradiación durante la incubación enzimática conduce a una localización altamente específica de la fosfatasa alcalina  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;6(1): 31-35, mayo 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Localización ultraestructural intensificada de la fosfatasa alcalina utilizando irradiación de microondas durante la incubación enzimática</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Kalicharan, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Want, JLL van der</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Halbhuber, KJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rüdiger, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14581</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8419^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
