<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61644</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transversal competencies for specialists training in the Pediatrics Residency Program, University of Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Teaching guidelines and the pediatrics exercise must adequate to the health requirements of the population needs and country politics, taking in consideration the new tendencies in medical education, with the introduction of competencies in the specialists training programs. Aim. To identify the competencies transversal to all specialties training programs (CT), that are important for the Pediatrics Residency Program (PFEP) at the Chile University. Subjects and methods. Qualitative and interpretive study, performed between November 2006 and January 2007. Key persons were interviewed (6 residents, 6 graduates and 8 opinion leaders)about the relevance and achievement of six CT. Results. The interviewed highlighted the necessity of trained pediatricians in ambulatory settings and continuity clinics, the acquisition of competencies in emergency units and basic skills in hospital training. They considered that the current training is lacking of important CT such as bioethics, physician-patient and family communication, public health, team work and evidence based medicine. Teaching skills and practice management are part of the medical profession; they could be introduced as an elective activity. Conclusion. The acquisition of CT during the PFEP transcend beyond the traditional clinical competencies, it is a challenge to introduce them in the PFEP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Millán-Klusse, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schonhaut-Berman, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hanne-Altermatt, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El Programa de Formación de Especialistas en Pediatría (PFEP) debe responder a las necesidades futuras de la salud, políticas del país y, además, modernizarse acorde con las evidencias de la educación en ciencias de la salud, las que recomiendan la educación basada en competencias. Objetivo. El objetivo del estudio fue identificarlas competencias transversales (CT) que debe lograr el licenciado del PFEP de la Universidad de Chile y evaluar su adquisición. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio cualitativo, descriptivo. Entre noviembre de 2006 y enero de 2007 se seleccionaron informantes clave mediante entrevistas en profundidad: ocho líderes, seis residentes y seis licenciados del PFEP de la Universidad de Chile, y se les preguntó por la relevancia y el logro de seis CT. Resultados. Para enfrentarlos actuales desafíos laborales y epidemiológicos, se consideró fundamental la capacitación como médico de cabecera en pediatría ambulatoria y clínicas de continuidad, la adquisición de competencias de urgencia pediátrica y el manejo básico del niño hospitalizado. Se dio relevancia ala incorporación de CT carentes en el PFEP, como bioética, relación médico-paciente-familia, salud pública, trabajo en equipo y medicina basada en la evidencia (MBE). La docencia fue considerada como una actividad inherente al ejercicio médico, y se pudo ofrecer como un electivo al igual que la gestión. Conclusión. La adquisición de CT, más allá de las tradicionales competencias clínicas, es un desafío para la actual formación del pediatra y su adecuada preparación para el ejercicio profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 33-41, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencias transversales en la formación de especialistas en pediatría, Universidad de Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
