<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116797</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive study of a new diagnostic-therapeutic hysteroscopic morcellation system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypothesis: The new morcellation system is a safe and effective diagnostic-therapeutic technique for the outpatient management of endometrial polyps. Objective: To describe our inicial experience with the new mechanical Truclear System (Smith&amp;Nephew) hysteroscope in a number of polypectomies performed in the outpatient setting without the need for surgical referral. Patients and methods: An observational prospective non-randomized study was performed in 100 patients who underwent hysteroscopy between June 2011 and January 2012 at the Igualada Hospital. There were two patient groups: group 1 included the first 55 patients who met the inclusion criteria for hysteroscopy and group 2 included 45 patients with endometrial polyps suspected on ultrasound. Results: We performed 41 and 40 uneventful hysteroscopies in groups 1 and 2, respectively, 56 and 82.5% were suspected endometrial polyps, respectively. Polypectomy was 100% successful in all patients. None of the patients were referred for surgery. Tolerance was moderate to good in 91.3% of the patients. Conclusion: The new morcellator system allows polypectomies to be conducted in outpatients with an ultrasound diagnosis of polyps, without the need to refer the patient for surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Degollada Bastos, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira Pampalona, Jennifer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu Pruñonosa, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra Garcia, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ratia Garcia, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Montesdeoca, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bresco Torras, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancebo Moreno, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hipótesis. El nuevo sistema de morcelación es una técnica histeroscópica diagnóstica-terapéutica eficaz y segura para el tratamiento ambulatorio de pólipos endometriales. Objetivo. Describir nuestra experiencia inicial con el nuevo sistema de morcelación histeroscópica Truclear System (Smith &amp; Nephew) en término de polipectomías realizadas a nivel ambulatorio sin necesidad de derivación quirúrgica de la paciente. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio observacional prospectivo no aleatorizado que incluye las 100 primeras pacientes en las que se les realizó una histeroscopia con el nuevo sistema morcelador entre junio del 2011 a enero del 2012 en el Hospital de Igualada. Se diferencian 2 grupos de pacientes. Grupo 1: 55 primeras pacientes que cumplen alguno de los criterios de inclusión establecidos para la realización de una histeroscopia; Grupo 2: 45 pacientes con sospecha diagnóstica-ecográfica de pólipo endometrial. Resultados. Se realizó un total de 41 y 40 histeroscopias en el grupo 1 y 2 respectivamente, obteniendo una sospecha histeroscópica de pólipo endometrial en el 56 y 82,5% respectivamente. La tasa de éxito en la polipetomía fue del 100%, sin necesidad de derivación quirúrgica posterior en ningún caso y con una tolerancia buena o regular en el 91,3% de las pacientes. Conclusión. El nuevo sistema morcelador permite la realización de la polipectomía a nivel ambulatorio sin necesidad de derivación quirúrgica en aquellas pacientes con diagnóstico ecográfico de pólipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(9): 482-488, nov. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo del nuevo sistema morcelador de histeroscopia diagnóstica-terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
