<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79167</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethics and the patient&#146;s pharmacotherapeutic record</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study is to consider the ethical aspects ofthe personal and health data fl ooding our computers. Respectfor confi dentiality and the patient&#146;s autonomy when establishingthe pharmacotherapeutic follow-up requires the ethical treatmentof the data contained therein. Concepts like informedconsent, confi dentiality, right of access and right to correctionare terms that go hand in hand with clinical work and which wemust slowly incorporate into our pharmaceutical terminology.The collection and handling of this information may be thecause of one of the main ethical and legal problems arising inpersonalised pharmacotherapeutic follow-up.This study aims to defi ne the concept of personalised pharmacotherapeuticfollow-up and approach different aspects, includingthe purpose of the patient&#146;s pharmacotherapeutic record,its custody, conservation and confi dentiality, as well asinformed consent.Our aim is not to simply extrapolate pharmaceutical ethics frommedical ethics, but rather to approach, on the basis of currentregulations, the treatment of data in patients&#146; pharmacotherapeuticrecords according to certain minimum ethical principles, likerespect for the patient&#146;s confi dentiality, autonomy and freedom(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quijano Rodrigo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es hacer una refl exión ética sobrelos datos personales y de salud que están inundando nuestrosordenadores. El respeto a la confi dencialidad y a la autonomíadel paciente cuando se establece el seguimientofarmacoterapéutico exige un tratamiento ético de los datos queallí se contienen. Conceptos como, por ejemplo, consentimientoinformado, confi dencialidad, derecho de acceso y derecho derectifi cación son términos que acompañan el quehacer clínico yque, poco a poco, hemos de incorporar a nuestra terminologíafarmacéutica.La obtención y el tratamiento de esta información pueden serlas causas de uno de los principales problemas éticos y legalesque se plantean en el seguimiento farmacoterapéutico personalizado.Este trabajo pretende defi nir el concepto de seguimiento farmacoterapéuticopersonalizado y abordar diferentes aspectos, entreellos la fi nalidad de la historia farmacoterapéutica, su custodia,conservación y confi dencialidad, y el consentimiento informado.No se trata simplemente de hacer una extrapolación de la éticamédica a la farmacéutica, sino de, basándonos en la normativalegal, abordar el tratamiento de los datos de la historiafarmacoterapéutica desde unos principios éticos mínimos, comoel respeto a la confi dencialidad, la autonomía y la libertaddel individuo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;12(1): 35-44, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79167</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ética e historia farmacoterapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8064^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8064^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19129^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22412^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8064^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
