<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048553</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inducibility of atrial arrhythmias after adenosine and isoproterenol infusion in patients referred for atrial fibrillation ablation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The identification and ablation of atrial ectopic foci could complement the conventional empirical pulmonary vein approach and may increase the success rate of atrial fibrillation ablation. Although both adenosine and isoproterenol infusion have been reported to induce ectopics, no clear findings on their use during ablation have been published. Our aim was to investigate the utility of these two pharmacologic maneuvers in patients referred for atrial fibrillation ablation. Methods. The effects of adenosine infusion, isoproterenol infusion, or both were evaluated in 53 patients with refractory atrial fibrillation referred for ablation. Patients were in sinus rhythm during evaluation. Results. Administration of adenosine or isoproterenol induced atrial arrhythmias in 46 patients (87%). Arrhythmia inducibility was similar in those with paroxysmal and those with persistent atrial fibrillation (87% and 86%, respectively). Atrial ectopics alone were induced in 31 patients (65%), atrial tachycardia in four (8%), and atrial fibrillation in 13 (27%). In 10 patients (19%), ectopic foci were located outside the pulmonary veins and subsequently underwent ablation. In 32 of the 46 patients with inducible arrhythmias, only the induced ectopic foci were ablated (mean 1.4 [0.6] targets per patient). The long-term success rate of first procedures was 66%. Conclusions. Adenosine and isoproterenol infusion induced atrial ectopics in most patients with drug-refractory atrial fibrillation while they were in sinus rhythm. In almost 20%, the ectopic foci were located outside the pulmonary veins. The effectiveness of induced ectopic-guided ablation observed in our patient series supports the clinical utility of this approach</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doblado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Castellano, Nicasio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacastín, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isa-Param, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La identificación y la ablación de focos ectópicos podría realizarse de forma complementaria al abordaje empírico de las 4 venas pulmonares, con el fin de aumentar la tasa de éxito de la ablación de la fibrilación auricular (FA). Nuestro objetivo fue analizar la inducibilidad farmacológica de ectopia auricular en pacientes con FA, así como la reproducibilidad, la localización y el significado clínico de la arritmia inducida. Métodos. Se analizó el resultado de la infusión de adenosina e isoproterenol en 53 pacientes con FA referidos para ablación que presentaban ectopia abundante en Holter previos y ausencia de ésta en el momento de la ablación (o densidad insuficiente para su cartografía). Resultados. En 46 pacientes (87%) se indujo alguna arritmia auricular tras la administración de adenosina y/o isoproterenol. La tasa de inducibilidad en pacientes con FA paroxística y persistente fue del 87 y el 86%, respectivamente. Se indujo ectopia aislada en 31 pacientes (65%), taquicardia auricular en 4 pacientes (8%) y FA en 13 pacientes (27%). En 10 pacientes (19%), la ectopia inducida tuvo una localización extrapulmonar. En 32 de los 46 pacientes inducibles (70%) se ablacionó exclusivamente la ectopia inducida (1,4 ± 0,6 sustratos por paciente), y se obtuvo un éxito a largo plazo en 21 pacientes (66%). Conclusiones. La infusión de adenosina e isoproterenol en pacientes con FA presenta una alta tasa de inducción de arritmias auriculares, que, en cerca de un 20% de los casos, proceden de focos extrapulmonares. La eficacia de la ablación guiada por la ectopia inducida apoya la relevancia clínica de ésta</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(6): 559-566, jun. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inducibilidad de arritmias auriculares tras la infusión de adenosina e isoproterenol en pacientes con fibrilación auricular remitidos para ablación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7713^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d249^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
