<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118069</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implant-supported mandible rehabilitation over microvascularised fibula graft. Use of computer-guided surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the treatment of the patients with malignant tumours of the oral cavity, the surgery combines the resection and immediate reconstruction with the aim of preserving the functions concentrated in the oral cavity (phonation, deglutition, mastication, aesthetics). The use of microvascularised flaps is a common practice in these patients in order to replace the resected tissues. Dental rehabilitation of these patients is usually very complex, and the use of guided implant surgical systems avoids many of the problems that occur in these patients. Clinical case: A patient who underwent hemimandibulectomy without reconstruction and adjuvant treatment with radiotherapy, who is sent for reconstruction. Initially, a microvascularised fibula flap is performed that provides bone and (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Martín-Moro, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián-Carretero, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobrino del Riego, José Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demaría Martínez, Gastón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro Pons, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introdución: En el tratamiento de los pacientes afectos de tumores malignos de la cavidad oral, la cirugía combina la resección y la reconstrucción inmediata con el fin de preservar las funciones que concentra la cavidad oral (fonación, deglución, masticación, estética). El empleo de colgajos microvascularizados constituye una práctica habitual en estos pacientes para reponer los tejidos resecados. La rehabilitación dental de estos pacientes suele ser muy compleja, y el empleo de sistemas de cirugía implantológica guiada evita muchos de los problemas que se presentan en estos pacientes. Caso clínico: Paciente sometido a (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);10(3): 197-203, sept.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118069</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación mandibular implanto-soportada sobreinjerto microvascularizado de peroné. Empleo de la cirugía guiada por ordenador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9259^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29134^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54867^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
