<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045230</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiple chemical sensitivity under sick-building syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sick building syndrome includes irritation of the eyes and the respiratory tract, neurotoxicity affectation and skin problems, which can occur in individuals under improperly ventilated buildings. Poor air quality, as shown in CO2 atmospheric levels of more than 1,000 ppm, results in a pathological exposure to biological and chemical products. We present a work-related case of multiple chemical hypersensitivity from a dialysis unit that had no air renewal. This person, who was summitted to continuous exposure despite having taken corrective measures in the ventilation, developed chronic fatigue syndrome. An acoustic voice observation alerted of the case which led to the analysis of the environmental conditions which confirmed the relationship between multiple chemical hypersensitivity and chronic fatigue syndrome. This case stresses the neglected fact that all health service centres pose a high risk of chemical exposure and that there exists a lack of rigoroursness in putting in practice scientific medical knowledge</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arnold Llamosas, Pablo A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet Agustí, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente Brull, Xavier de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrizabalaga Clemente, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome del edificio enfermo se refiere a un conjunto de síntomas (irritación de conjuntivas y mucosas respiratorias, afectación neurotóxica y cutánea), que presentan los individuos en edificios mal ventilados. La mala calidad del aire, reflejada por valores atmosféricos de dióxido de carbono superiores a 1.000 ppm, implica la exposición a productos biológicos y químicos patógenos. Presentamos el caso de una paciente con hipersensibilidad química múltiple de origen laboral en un centro de diálisis, con total ausencia de renovación de aire, que bajo exposición repetida al mismo ambiente, pese a la adopción de medidas correctoras de la ventilación, desarrolló un síndrome de fatiga crónica. El análisis acústico de la voz puso de manifiesto el caso, que aconsejó la medición de las condiciones ambientales, que a su vez confirmó la asociación entre la hipersensibilidad química múltiple y el síndrome de fatiga crónica. Se apunta el olvido de que todo centro sanitario comporta un riesgo químico alto y la falta de aplicación del conocimiento científico médico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(20): 774-778, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045230</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipersensibilidad química múltiple en el síndrome del edificio enfermo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32611^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32135^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27918^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
