<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119536</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New Public Management (NPM) makes public hospital and university services in market enterprises. The aim of the paper is to analyze and describe the impact of this metamorphosis in labor subjectivity of staff employed in such services. Empirical studies in Spanish and Latin American hospitals and universities discover a paradoxical experience: relative manifest satisfaction by material and technical conditions allowing work harder and better, but also latent discomfort to the task overload, and professional and ethical dilemmas posed by new organizational demands, facing with these staff develop ways of coping ranging from manifest obedience to latent resistance. This reinforces the reasons for the redesign of those services based on a better balance between commercial and social demands, managerial and professional values, and between business efficiency and quality of working life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanch, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Nueva Gestión Pública convierte servicios hospitalarios y universitarios en empresas de mercado. El objetivo del artículo es analizar y describir el impacto de esta metamorfosis en la subjetividad laboral del personal empleado en tales servicios. Estudios empíricos en hospitales y universidades iberoamericanos descubren una experiencia paradójica: relativa satisfacción manifiesta por condiciones materiales y técnicas que permiten trabajar más y mejor; pero también malestar latente por la sobrecarga de tarea y los dilemas ético-profesionales planteados por las nuevas demandas organizacionales, ante las que el personal desarrolla modos de afrontamiento que van de la obediencia manifiesta a la resistencia latente. Ello refuerza las razones para el rediseño de aquellos servicios en función de un mayor equilibrio entre demandas mercantiles y sociales, entre valores gerenciales y profesionales, entre eficiencia empresarial y calidad de vida laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;35(1): 40-47, ene. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119536</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida laboral en hospitales y universidades mercantilizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
